<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1890-05-06" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1890-05-06">6 May 1890</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
<date when="1890"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="4449" to="4480"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04449.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04451.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04453.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04455.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04457.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04459.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04461.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04463.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04465.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04467.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04469.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04471.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04473.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04475.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04477.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04479.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-03">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-03">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04449"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04449.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04451"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04451.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04453"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04453.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04455"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04455.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04457"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04457.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04459"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04459.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04461"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04461.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04463"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04463.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04465"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04465.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04467"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04467.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04469"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04469.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04471"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04471.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04473"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04473.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04475"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04475.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04477"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04477.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04479"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04479.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="4449" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04449.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4449</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 6, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">4450</fw>

<p>[...]the Crown in Chancery a certificate of the election <lb/>
and return of Charles Herbert Mackintosh, Esq., <lb/>
to represent the electoral district of the city of <lb/>
Ottawa. <lb/></p> 
</div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">THE BREMNER FURS.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:CASG1">Mr. CASGRAIN</persName>. I would ask the Government <lb/>
whether we will soon receive the printed evidence <lb/>
in the Middleton and Bremner case. I understood <lb/>
it was to be printed as soon as possible. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAP4">Mr. CHAPLEAU</persName>. I think it has been printed. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CASG1">Mr. CASGRAIN</persName>. It has not been distributed. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAP4">Mr. CHAPLEAU</persName>. My neighbor here shows <lb/>
me a copy he has received. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. We have none. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. It cannot have been distributed, <lb/>
for I did not get one. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAP4">Mr. CHAPLEAU</persName>. I will see that it is distri<lb break="no"/>buted. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>. I have understood that the hon. <lb/>
gentleman got many things in advance. A state<lb break="no"/>ment was made yesterday, that today we would <lb/>
be informed when the consideration of the report <lb/>
of the Committee on Privileges and Elections <lb/>
would take place. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LANG1">Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN</persName>. The Prime Min<lb break="no"/>ister is not here now, and the hon. gentleman <lb/>
might repeat his question when he is here. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAP4">Mr. CHAPLEAU</persName>. When I receive anything <lb/>
in advance, I do not desire to keep it to myself. <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES ACT.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName> moved second reading of Bill <lb/>
(No. 146) to amend the Acts respecting the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories. He said: The principal provisions <lb/>
in this Act are the following:—It is deemed advis<lb break="no"/>able to define the Territories more particularly <lb/>
than they are at present defined and to change <lb/>
their name to the Western Territories of Canada. <lb/>
This is proposed to be done by section 3 of the <lb/>
Bill. Sections 5, 6, 7, 8 and 9 contain the provi<lb break="no"/>sions which are to govern the composition of the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly, the periods at which sittings <lb/>
thereof are to be held, and the mode of proceedings <lb/>
for electing a new Assembly, or for filling a vacancy. <lb/>
Section 10 defines the classes of subjects respecting <lb/>
which the Legislative Assembly may make ordi<lb break="no"/>nances. By section 13 of the Bill the powers of a <lb/>
single judge are to be extended and defined. By <lb/>
the same section the confirmation reversal, or <lb/>
modification by the Court of Appeal, of the <lb/>
decision of a single judge is to be provided for. By <lb/>
section 14 provision is to be made for the perform <lb/>
ance of the duties of a sheriff or a clerk in <lb/>
the event of a vacancy throu h death or otherwise. <lb/>
By section 18 provision is to be made to empower <lb/>
each judge of the Supreme Court of the Territories <lb/>
    to be <hi rendition="simple:italic">ex-ofiicio</hi> a district magistrate for the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, and also to sit as a criminal court to try and <lb/>
determine charges preferred against any persons <lb/>
for the offences which are specified in that sec<lb break="no"/>tion. By section 22 of the Bill provision is to be <lb/>
made as to the manner of indicting persons so <lb/>
charged. By section 23 provision is to be made <lb/>
for the transmission, by a justice of the peace or <lb/>
magistrate holding a preliminary investigation <lb/>
into any criminal offence, which may not be tried <lb/>

<cb/>

under "The Summary Convictions Act," of the <lb/>
records of such investigation; and for the notifica<lb break="no"/>tion of a judge, with the object of affording the <lb/>
person charged with the crime, a speedy trial. <lb/>
By section 24 those persons convicted of a breach <lb/>
of a municipal by-law and sentenced to imprison<lb break="no"/>ment on account of such breach, are to be excepted <lb/>
from the provisions of section 79 of chapter 50 of <lb/>
the Revised Statutes, unless the municipality shall <lb/>
arrange with the Commissioner of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Mounted Police for the maintenance of <lb/>
the person so convicted during the period of his <lb/>
sentence. By section 30 the wording of section <lb/>
108 of the said chapter 50 is to be slightly changed, <lb/>
and two sub-sections are to be added thereto. <lb/>
The first of these sub-sections fixes the width of <lb/>
public highways, roads or trails which existed in <lb/>
the Territories prior to survey, and also provides <lb/>
for the improvement of the location thereof by the <lb/>
surveyor, if necessary. The second retains the <lb/>
title to the highways in the town for the public <lb/>
uses of the Territories, and provides that such <lb/>
roads cannot be altered and that the land cannot <lb/>
be sold except by consent of the Governor in <lb/>
Council. The amendment proposed by section 31 <lb/>
to section 110 of the said chapter 50 will give the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly which will be elected to <lb/>
succeed the present one the right to regulate and <lb/>
to decide the manner of recording and publishing <lb/>
its proceedings. By section 32 of the Bill it <lb/>
is to be provided that no change shall be made in <lb/>
the existing law of the Territories concerning <lb/>
intoxicating liquor until the dissolution of the <lb/>
present Assembly has afforded the inhabitants an <lb/>
opportunity of expressing their opinion with <lb/>
regard to the nature of such change. The other <lb/>
sections of the Bill contain no material alterations <lb/>
of the present law. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. The hon. gentleman has only <lb/>
given us a synopsis of what the Bill contains, but <lb/>
no explanations as to the reasons of the alterations <lb/>
made in the Act. I think no more important sub<lb break="no"/>ject could be brought before this House at the <lb/>
present time than a Bill legislating in regard to the <lb/>
North-West Territories, and the House, I am <lb/>
sure, will be disappointed at the more than dry <lb/>
manner in which the hon. gentleman has introduced <lb/>
this subject, but I cannot blame him very much <lb/>
for that, because the Bill itself is a very dry one, <lb/>
and the changes made in the present law are mostly <lb/>
technical, with the exception of section 13, which <lb/>
is clothing the Legislature of the North-West <lb/>
Territories With powers similar to those now en<lb break="no"/>joyed by the Provinces. In fact, section 13, as <lb/>
amended by this Bill, is largely borrowed from <lb/>
section 92 of the Confederation Act, which gives <lb/>
the powers now enjoyed by the Provinces. I do <lb/>
not find fault with the Administration for enlarg<lb break="no"/>ing, to that extent, the powers now enjoyed by the <lb/>
Legislature, but it seems to me that while the <lb/>
Government was making that concession, it would <lb/>
have been opportune to supplement it with another <lb/>
concession by giving responsible government to the <lb/>
Territories. The Territories are not progressing <lb/>
very fast, but still the population which goes <lb/>
there is an advanced population, well educated, <lb/>
and already showing great powers of self-govern<lb break="no"/>ment. There are some subjects of a nature which <lb/>
had better be entrusted to them than kept in this <lb/>
House. They are the best judges of what is best <lb/>

<pb n="4451" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04451.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4451</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">4452</fw> 

for them in their present condition. It is felt that <lb/>
the powers which they have already received are <lb/>
inadequate, and I question very much whether <lb/>
this small measure of reform, though it may be <lb/>
accepted for what it is worth, will meet the condi<lb break="no"/>tion of the people of the Territories. If the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment had seen fit to give them a responsible <lb/>
government, or at least a larger measure of self-<lb break="yes"/>government, than they have at the present time, <lb/>
many of the difficulties which may come before <lb/>
this House at some time or another, and many of <lb/>
the difficulties which may arise in the Territories <lb/>
themselves, under the present system, would in all <lb/>
probability be avoided. All the difficulties that <lb/>
have arisen between the Lieutenant Governor and <lb/>
the Legislature—and they have had some difficul<lb break="no"/>ties during the last Session—arose from the fact <lb/>
that the Governor had not a responsible body of <lb/>
advisers who were answerable to the House, and <lb/>
this fact shows the necessity for some larger mea<lb break="no"/>sure of responsible government. Under the cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances, I do not venture at this moment any <lb/>
further criticism of this Bill than to say that, in <lb/>
my judgment, it falls short of what should be the <lb/>
proper remedy for the difficulties which may arise, <lb/>
not only in this House but in the Territories <lb/>
themselves. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I sympathise, to some extent, <lb/>
with the remarks that have fallen from the leader <lb/>
of the Opposition. Those remarks are not couched <lb/>
in a spirit of hostility to the Government or to <lb/>
this Act. In fact, this Act is travelling along the <lb/>
road that the hon. and learned gentleman wishes <lb/>
it to go, but he would have it go further. I think <lb/>
that so long as the Act remained as it was there <lb/>
was a very large section of the people in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West who were well content. I may tell the hon. <lb/>
gentleman that though there was some difficulty in <lb/>
the Assembly last year, I believe as a fact that the <lb/>
weight of opinion in the North-West was with the <lb/>
minority of that Assembly. By the 11th sub-clause <lb/>
of section 10, that is to say, section 13 of the <lb/>
Revised Statutes, which has been put in by the <lb/>
Senate, all the powers that call for responsibility <lb/>
are given, as we find by these words: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The expenditure of such portion of any moneys appro<lb break="no"/>priated by Parliament for the Territories as the Governor <lb/>
in Council may instruct the Lieutenant Governor to <lb/>
expend by and with the advice of the Legislative Assem<lb break="no"/>bly." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>I am afraid that unless some form of responsible <lb/>
government is given, that money will be worse <lb/>
than wasted; that money will be expended— <lb/>
how? It will be expended by the Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor by and with the advice of the Leg<lb break="no"/>islative Assembly. Why, Sir, What will happen? <lb/>
You will have that money log-rolled, as we know <lb/>
has often happened in the history of such Gov<lb break="no"/>ernments. Suppose moneys were voted here in <lb/>
Committee of Supply; if you allowed those <lb/>
moneys to be expended by the advice of this <lb/>
Parliament without any Government to be respon<lb break="no"/>sible therefor to the people, the result would be <lb/>
that vast sums that are now carefully expended, <lb/>
would be worse than wasted. With regard to the <lb/>
local fund which they raise now, amounting, I <lb/>
think, to some $16,000 or $17,000, that sum is log-<lb break="yes"/>rolled. The manner in which that sum is expended is <lb/>
this: It is divided by 22, and the quotient given <lb/>
to each member, and whether he needs it or not, he <lb/>
naturally takes it, although sometimes he may have <lb/>

<cb/>

to fall back upon his inventive faculties for ways <lb/>
of expending it. Yet, of course, he does expend it. <lb/>
One case happened where an hon. gentleman spent <lb/>
the money on purposes that never could have been <lb/>
contemplated when it was voted; and, therefore <lb/>
I think, as we have gone thus far, probably it <lb/>
would be as well to go still further and to give <lb/>
them a little government. I think there are some <lb/>
parts of the Bill that will be found an improve<lb break="no"/>ment; but, when we come to the clause dealing <lb/>
with the appointment of deputy sheriffs, I will ask <lb/>
the Committee to accept an amendment. It seems <lb/>
to me that is indefensible; it is vicious in principle. <lb/>
to have the Assembly provide for the appointment <lb/>
of deputy sheriffs; it would be much better to <lb/>
have the judges provide for the necessity of the <lb/>
appointment of deputy sheriffs, because if you have <lb/>
this work devolving on the Assembly, every mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the Assembly will be troubled with requests <lb/>
from every little town in his district to have a <lb/>
deputy sheriff appointed, because every little place <lb/>
would think it would obtain a certain importance <lb/>
if it had a deputy sheriff. The subject was dis<lb break="no"/>cussed elsewhere, if I may refer to it in passing, <lb/>
and all the North-West opinion was in the direc<lb break="no"/>tion which I now express myself. I will ask the <lb/>
Government to consider that point, because, as I <lb/>
say, you will have such a large number of deputy <lb/>
sherrifs that the receipts will not be enough to give <lb/>
them bread and salt. I think, on the whole, there <lb/>
are very good reforms in the Bill, and the North-<lb break="yes"/>West will welcome it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>. I think it impossible to attach <lb/>
too much importance to the point on which the <lb/>
hon. member for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) has <lb/>
just enlarged. We are proposing to make a <lb/>
departure from the principles of responsible <lb/>
government, as we understand them, in a most <lb/>
important particular. I admit that it is difficulty <lb/>
to deal with the exigency otherwise than it is <lb/>
dealt with by this Bill, without responsible govern <lb/>
ment. The principle, as I understand it, is that, <lb/>
with respect to the expenditure of public moneys, <lb/>
it is the Crown that initiates, not the Assembly. <lb/>
The Assembly is supposed to be a check, a guard, <lb/>
to keep the drag on; that is the function of the <lb/>
popular body. I quite agree that eminent states<lb break="no"/>men, not theorising, but dealing with actual <lb/>
results in late years in the mother country, have <lb/>
pointed out how far the English House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons has departed from the ancient traditions; <lb/>
how far it has ceased to be a bulwark and support <lb/>
to the Administration in matters of prudence and <lb/>
economy in public expenditure. But, none the less, <lb/>
I hold it to be the most important ingredient in se<lb break="no"/>curing economy, and also good direction, in public <lb/>
expenditure, that there shall be an initiative some<lb break="no"/>where else than in the popular assembly, and, deeply <lb/>
as I differ from the hon. member for West Assiniboia <lb/>
(Mr. Davin) as to his characterisation of the ex<lb break="no"/>penditures that have taken place in this House, or <lb/>
rather with the sanction of this House, I say they <lb/>
are, beyond all comparison, better, more prudent, <lb/>
and wiser than they would have been if such a <lb/>
system as we are proposing to give the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories had existed here. We have had <lb/>
a few instances, I am glad to say only a few, of <lb/>
attempted departure from that system. There have <lb/>
been perhaps three cases, three only occur to my <lb/>
mind at this moment, in which select committees <lb/>

<pb n="4453" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04453.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4453</fw> <fw type="dateline">[May 6, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">4454</fw>

have substantially, though not nominally, been <lb/>
allowed to deal with old claims in order, I am <lb/>
afraid, that the Executive might escape the re<lb break="no"/>sponsibility, with the inevitable result that the <lb/>
claims were allowed; but, subject to those trifling <lb/>
exceptions, which only mark the rule, we have <lb/>
observed the rule. We are not without experience <lb/>
in this matter in the old Province. In the early <lb/>
days of the old Legislature of Canada, prior to <lb/>
1840, when, as you know, we had a system which <lb/>
was not a system of responslble government, <lb/>
although there were Ministers representing the <lb/>
Crown, at that time, as Mr. Bourinot says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"All applications for pecuniary assistance were ad<lb break="no"/>dressed directly to the House of Assembly, and every <lb/>
Governor, especially Lord Sydenham, has given his testi<lb break="no"/>mony as to the injurious effect of the system. The Union <lb/>
Act of 1540 laced the initiation of many votes in the <lb/>
Crown, and this wise practice was always strictly followed <lb/>
up to 1867, when the new Constitution came into force." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>And we know the language of the present Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion provides expressly: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"It shall not be lawful for the House of Commons to <lb/>
adopt or pass any vote, resolution, address or Bill for the <lb/>
appropriation of any part of the public revenue, or of any <lb/>
tax or impost, to any purpose that has not been first re<lb break="no"/>commended by a Message of the Governor General, in the <lb/>
the Session in which such vote, resolution, address, or <lb/>
Bill is proposed." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>A similar provision is inserted in the Constitution <lb/>
of each Provincial Legislature. Now, as I have <lb/>
said, I see the difficulty in which hon. gentlemen <lb/>
opposite were plunged when they came to deal <lb/>
with this question, because they have got one or <lb/>
two alternatives to adopt. They have to adopt <lb/>
the language we find here, which says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The expenditure of such portion of any moneys appro<lb break="no"/>priated by Parliament for the Territories, as the Governor <lb/>
in Council may instruct the Lieutenant Governor to ex<lb break="no"/>pend, by and with the advice of the Leglslative Assem<lb break="no"/>bly." <lb/></p> </quote>

<p>That is to say, the advice of the Assembly is to rule. <lb/>
They had that course open to them. Or the course <lb/>
was open to them of providing that the Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor should send down his Message, and with<lb break="no"/>out that Message it should not be competent for the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly to deal with the question at all. <lb/>
There you would at once be face to face with irres<lb break="no"/>ponsible rule. The Legislative Assembly cannot <lb/>
condemn the Lieutenant Governor, or dismiss <lb/>
him, or alter his position in any way, his advisory <lb/>
council is not responsible; and you are brought face <lb/>
to face with a difficulty which must subsist for the <lb/>
want of responsible government. But, on the other <lb/>
hand, what are we doing by the proposed plan? We <lb/>
are deliberately initiating that system which was <lb/>
deliberately abandoned in the early history of the <lb/>
old Province, where it was tried with injurious <lb/>
results, which has been deliberately rendered <lb/>
impossible by the constitutional Act, as to this <lb/>
Assembly and as to the Provincial Legisla<lb break="no"/>tures, and which is decidedly opposed to the <lb/>
spirit of the British Constitution. The hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman from Assiniboia has told us of the method <lb/>
of the expenditure of the scanty funds, which <lb/>
up to this time the Legislative Assembly has <lb/>
been allowed to expend. It is not an entirely <lb/>
new method of expenditure, because, I happen <lb/>
to know, that in the Province of Nova Scotia there <lb/>
are certain moneys called "road moneys," the <lb/>
disposal of which has been placed under the <lb/>
control of members; but, even there, the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of deciding as to how much shall go to each <lb/>

<cb/>

county is decided according to constitutional princi<lb break="no"/>ple, while the detailed application has been left, with <lb/>
very injurious results, to the local members. But <lb/>
the hon. gentleman tells us, that in this case the <lb/>
total fund to be disposed of is divided by the num<lb break="no"/>ber of constituencies, and each member is given his <lb/>
equal share. Of course, it is impossible to sup<lb break="no"/>pose, that in a territory like the North-West, in <lb/>
which, with the best possible desire, you cannot <lb/>
have equal areas with equal wants all over, that <lb/>
an equal division of money all over is a just <lb/>
division. Why, it is beyond all possibility that <lb/>
such an arrangement can be just, and it is im<lb break="no"/>portant that what scanty funds are available should <lb/>
be expended for such objects as may on the advice <lb/>
of responsible Ministers, be submitted to the As<lb break="no"/>sembly and as shall by the Assembly be deemed to <lb/>
be for the general good. It might be that a par<lb break="no"/>ticular district might be infinitely more benefited <lb/>
in reality by the whole fund being expended out<lb break="no"/>side of it, in an adjoining district; its own im<lb break="no"/>mediate local interests might be better served <lb/>
by a large expenditure on a ridge or other means <lb/>
of public communication, than by being frittered <lb/>
away in the district itself. Such a system as <lb/>
this is one which certainly does not encourage <lb/>
us in the scheme of placing more funds in <lb/>
this present fashion under the control of the <lb/>
Assembly. I think, therefore, we are face to <lb/>
face with a very serious question when we are en<lb break="no"/>gaged in the work commenced in 1875, that high <lb/>
and noble work for any Legislative Assembly, the <lb/>
task of improving, as we were engaged then in the <lb/>
task of inaugurating, the institutions under which <lb/>
a large territory, to be inhabited at some future <lb/>
day, we hope, by millions, may grow up and <lb/>
prosper. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName>. In the early part of this <lb/>
Session, a question closely connected with the pre<lb break="no"/>sent legislation which we are now called upon to <lb/>
examine was raised in this House, and it was then <lb/>
stated although the population of the North-West <lb/>
Territories was largely composed of a class of <lb/>
people using the French language, it was astonish<lb break="no"/>ing that in the North-West Council, composed of <lb/>
22 members, not one had been returned who <lb/>
belonged to the French Canadian nationality. This <lb/>
was due to the fact that the electoral divisions <lb/>
were so arranged, that the French population could <lb/>
not muster a sufficient number of electors to elect <lb/>
one of themselves to represent their interests in <lb/>
that Council. I expected that the present Bill <lb/>
would contain such provisions, as would alter the <lb/>
electoral divisions so as to give the French popula<lb break="no"/>tion of the North-West Territories a chance of <lb/>
having representatives upon the floor of their <lb/>
Council. The hon. member for Saskatchewan (Mr. <lb/>
Macdowall) made at the time a suggestion, that <lb/>
when amendments should be framed to the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories Act, they should contain such <lb/>
changes as would help the French population <lb/>
to be properly represented; an if my <lb/>
memory serves me right, the promise was <lb/>
given to him, that when such legislation would be <lb/>
brought before this House, it would contain a pro<lb break="no"/>vision whereby the desired change would be effect<lb break="no"/>ed, and whereby the interests of those which are <lb/>
to-day unrepresented in that body, would be pro<lb break="no"/>tected. I am sorry to see, that when a suggestion <lb/>
was made to the Senate to that effect, it was not <lb/>

<pb n="4455" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04455.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4455</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">4456</fw> 

accepted by those who had the Bill in charge; <lb/>
and the Bill which now comes before this House <lb/>
is, consequently, without such provision. Out of <lb/>
22 members composing the North-West Council, <lb/>
as I have said, not one belonged either to the <lb/>
French nationality, or even to the Catholic religion, <lb/>
although one-fifth of the North-West is French. <lb/>
The population of the North-West Territories, ac<lb break="no"/>cording to the last census, was 22,000 or 27,000 <lb/>
inhabitants, out of which 4,800 were of French <lb/>
origin, and these people, as I repeat, are without <lb/>
representation in the North-West Assembly. <lb/>
Before this Bill is adopted by the House, I hope <lb/>
that such an amendment as will rectify this state <lb/>
of affairs will be incorporated. When a Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion was given to the Province of Quebec, at Confe<lb break="no"/>deration, the framers were very careful to set apart <lb/>
a certain number of counties which were called the <lb/>
English counties; and by the Constitution, the <lb/>
Legislature of the Province of Quebec could not <lb/>
interfere with the limits of these counties, so that <lb/>
the Protestant minority of the Province would <lb/>
have their representatives, and would thus be pro<lb break="no"/>tected against the majority. I say that this was well <lb/>
done. Although there was no danger, still it was <lb/>
right, I believe, that the minority should be pro<lb break="no"/>tected against the majority. If we had this pro<lb break="no"/>tection in the Province of Manitoba, we would not <lb/>
have had to regret the legislation recently adopted <lb/>
in that Province. I maintain that it is within <lb/>
our duty, as representatives of the people here, to <lb/>
see that the minority is protected in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories, as it is in the Province of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba by the Constitution, and as the Protestant and <lb/>
English minority of the Province of Quebec is also <lb/>
protected by the Constitution. I repeat expressing <lb/>
the hope that, before this Bill is put through all its <lb/>
stages in this House, such provision will be incor<lb break="no"/>porated as shall protect the minority of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories, as far as their right to fair repre<lb break="no"/>sentation at least, is concerned. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. I agree with a great deal <lb/>
which has been said by my hon. friend from West <lb/>
Durham (Mr. Blake), but I do not think he has <lb/>
quite stated the law; he has not stated it, at all <lb/>
events, as I understand it. The difficulty with the <lb/>
North-West Territories is, that the Advisory Coun<lb break="no"/>cil is not responsible as a Government would be; <lb/>
although it is stated that the Lieutenant Governor <lb/>
has to consult the Advisory Council with regard to <lb/>
the expenditure of moneys. It is a hybrid system. <lb/>
It is neither a system of responsible government, <lb/>
such as we are accustomed to understand it, nor is <lb/>
it a system by which the Executive—that is, the <lb/>
Lieutenant Governor of the North-West Territories <lb/>
—is responsible, and, I suppose, solely responsible to <lb/>
his official head. But I think the hon. member for <lb/>
West Durham (Mr. Blake) was wrong in this respect. <lb/>
As I understand the effect of the amendment now <lb/>
proposed, it is this: that in addition to the moneys <lb/>
which the people of the North-West vote them<lb break="no"/>selves, and which, according to the present practice, <lb/>
they are supposed to have control over; they are <lb/>
to have control over such further sums of money, <lb/>
under the 11th sub-section: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"As the Governor in Council may instruct the Lieuten<lb break="no"/>ant Governor to expend, by and with the advice of the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>My hon. friend will see that under another clause <lb/>
of the North-West Territories Amending Act of <lb/>

<cb/>

1888, these moneys so expended will have to be <lb/>
recommended by the Lieutenant Governor; so, in <lb/>
point of fact, one of the mischiefs he pointed <lb/>
out, that that would be an expenditure without <lb/>
any responsibility, is, as I conceive, the result of <lb/>
the present scheme; the Lieutenant Governor is <lb/>
not responsible, as the hon. gentleman pointed <lb/>
out, but no money can be expended by the Council <lb/>
without his recommendation. To my mind, that <lb/>
is a most unfortunate condition of things, and I <lb/>
join with the hon. gentlemen of the Opposition in <lb/>
thinking that, if the day has not come, it is fast <lb/>
approaching, when responsible government might <lb/>
well be given to the North-West Territories, in some <lb/>
degree at all events. I do not mean to say that <lb/>
we should give them control of the public lands, <lb/>
but I believe that responsible government might <lb/>
well be given in a very large degree to the people of <lb/>
the North-West Territories. A Bill of a similar <lb/>
nature to this is now before the British <choice><sic>Parliamene</sic><corr>Parliament</corr></choice> <lb/>
with regard to West Australia, and although the <lb/>
population there is 65,000 only—not so much at <lb/>
the population of the North-West Territories, <lb/>
if my memory serves me right—the Imperial <lb/>
Government have introduced a Bill proposing <lb/>
to confer on West Australia responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment, though not giving them absolute control <lb/>
over the great public lands of that country. With <lb/>
that exception, I do not know why our North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories, with 100,000 inhabitants, as, <lb/>
I think, they claim themselves to he, should not <lb/>
be entrusted with responsible government, instead <lb/>
of the extraordinary system which is perpetuated <lb/>
to some extent by this measure. Any one who <lb/>
reads the difficulties of the last session of the <lb/>
North-West Assembly will see how important it <lb/>
is in the interests of that country that this ques<lb break="no"/>tion should be settled, and settled promptly. We <lb/>
find that in the early days of the last meeting of <lb/>
the Legislative Assembly, Mr. Haultain's Admin<lb break="no"/>istration resigned, because the Lieutenant Gover<lb break="no"/>nor declined to account for the expenditure which <lb/>
had been voted by the Assembly the preceding <lb/>
session. Then we find that a new Advisory Board <lb/>
having been selected, the Council promptly voted <lb/>
want of confidence in them, and the Advisory Board <lb/>
having refused to resign on account of that, the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly refused to vote money which <lb/>
had been recommended by the Lieutenant Governor. <lb/>
There is a deadlock; it is a deadlock that this <lb/>
measure is certainly not going to get rid of in any <lb/>
way; the same difficulty will arise next session; <lb/>
and I really think that when the Bill is before us, <lb/>
some more adequate provision should be made for <lb/>
getting rid of a difficulty which is calculated to <lb/>
create uneasiness and disturbance in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, the result of which we must all deplore-<lb break="yes"/>I notice, too—though it is perhaps not intentional— <lb/>
that the effect of the Bill is rather to limit the <lb/>
authority of the Legislative Assembly of the <lb/>
North-West. The 9th sub-section of section 13 <lb/>
simply gives power to the North-West Assembly <lb/>
to constitute courts of civil jurisdiction; but that <lb/>
Assembly has up to this time had power, which it <lb/>
will cease to have if this Bill becomes law, to consti<lb break="no"/>tute courts of criminal jurisdiction as well. I do not <lb/>
know the reason for that change. However, these <lb/>
are provisions which will, perhaps, undergo dis<lb break="no"/>cussion in committee, and I merely refer to them <lb/>
now, Without in any sense opposing the second <lb/>
reading. I regret that this Bill has not been <lb/>

<pb n="4457" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04457.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4457</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 6, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">4458</fw>

brought down earlier in the Session. Dealing as it <lb/>
does with a territory of such vast extent and with <lb/>
such a large population, I think it is not too much <lb/>
to say, that it is one of the most important, <lb/>
if not the most important measure of the whole <lb/>
Session, and I think it is a pity that it has been <lb/>
left to be considered in the dying hours of the <lb/>
Session. But, when the proper time comes, I will <lb/>
move with regard to one or two clauses—one <lb/>
clause which I see in the Bill, and another which <lb/>
I object to not seeing there, if that is not a Hiber<lb break="no"/>nianism. I propose to ask the Committee to recon<lb break="no"/>sider the resolution which is now to be found <lb/>
embodied in the 31st clause of the Bill: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Either the English or the French language may be <lb/>
used by any person in the debates of the Legislative <lb/>
ASSembly of the Territories and in the roceediugs before <lb/>
the courts; and both those languages shall be used in the <lb/>
records and Journals of such Assembly: and all ordinan<lb break="no"/>ces made under this Act shall be printed in both those <lb/>
languages: Provided however. that after the next <lb/>
general election of the Legislative Assembly, such <lb/>
Assembly may, by ordinance or otherwise, regulate its <lb/>
proceedings, and the manner of recordingand publishing <lb/>
the same: and the regulations so made shall be embodied <lb/>
in a proclamation which shall be forthwith made and <lb/>
published by the Lieutenant Governor in conformity with <lb/>
the law, and thereafter shall have full force and effect." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>Now, I submit that this clause does not at all <lb/>
dispose of the question of the dual language. I <lb/>
notice that the hon. gentleman who represents the <lb/>
Government in the other House calls it a compro<lb break="no"/>mise. If it is a compromise, I do not know who <lb/>
were the parties to that compromise. I do not <lb/>
know why the Upper House should have felt bound <lb/>
or precluded by some arrangement or compromise <lb/>
made with regard to this question. Who were the <lb/>
parties to the compromise? Were the people of the <lb/>
North-West consulted? Had they any notice of it, <lb/>
or did they assent to it? <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">MEMBER INTRODUCED.</head>

<p>CHARLES H. MACKINTOSH. Esq., Member for the <lb/>
Electoral District of the City of Ottawa introduced by <lb/>
Sir John A. Macdonald and Mr. Robillard. <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES ACT.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. I was pointing out that it <lb/>
had been urged in the other branch of the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture that this compromise had been agreed to, and <lb/>
that by reason of the compromise it was not in the <lb/>
public interest that this agitation, as it was termed, <lb/>
should be prolonged or renewed. What I want to <lb/>
know is, who were the parties to the compromise, <lb/>
and why should we be bound or precluded by an <lb/>
arrangement when we cannot even tell who were <lb/>
the parties to it. It was not stated on the floor of <lb/>
this House that there had been any arrangement; <lb/>
certainly no arrangement was agreed to on the <lb/>
floor of the House other than that found in the <lb/>
vote that was cast. Then, was the arrangement <lb/>
made outside of the House? If so, who were the <lb/>
parties to it? It was stated, I see, by the hon. <lb/>
gentleman who represents the Government in the <lb/>
fairly. What I feel, and what I think most peo<lb break="no"/>ple feel on this subject, is the mischief resulting <lb/>
other Chamber: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The reason is precisely the one which my hon. friend <lb/>
from Ottawa stated, and it is the one which actuates <lb/>
probably nearly every man in this Chamber who votes <lb/>
or the proviso, namely, that by the introduction of the <lb/>
proviso it is intended not to prolong or increase or re<lb break="no"/>new the agitation on this subject, but, by accepting it, to <lb/>
seek to put an end to the agitation on this subject, because <lb/>
it represents something. in the nature of a compromise <lb/>
which has been impliedly entered into and agreed upon <lb/>
by the leaders of all parties in politics in this country— <lb/>
        
<cb/>

with the exception of this new and small party which has <lb/>
lately sprung lip—as a solution of the difficulty which can <lb/>
reasonsably be accepted." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>Well, I do not understand, and on endeavoring to <lb/>
recall the discussion, I cannot now derive from it, <lb/>
although I paid pretty close attention to it, how <lb/>
this compromise was agreed to. I do remember, that <lb/>
my hon. friend from West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) <lb/>
moved a resolution proposing that the whole subject <lb/>
should be left to the people of the North-West after <lb/>
the general elections; I understood that a large pro<lb break="no"/>portion of the House were in favor of that; I heard <lb/>
the right hon. gentleman who leads the House <lb/>
applaud the sentiment, and I think, if I am not <lb/>
mistaken, that he spoke in favor of it. Shortly <lb/>
afterwards, the hon. member for West Durham <lb/>
(Mr. Blake) made a proposition, he not being <lb/>
satisfied either with the Bill or the amendment of <lb/>
the hon. member for West Assiniboia. Within <lb/>
twenty-four hours afterwards, this other amend<lb break="no"/>ment was suggested, but it was not suggested as <lb/>
the result of a compromise or anything of the <lb/>
kind. Perhaps the leader of the other House <lb/>
knows more about it than I do; all I know of it was <lb/>
what took place on the floor of this House. But <lb/>
what I protest against, is that Parliament should <lb/>
be supposed to be bound by any arrangement come <lb/>
to on that occasion. I ventured to say then, and I <lb/>
repeat now, that that is not going to settle the <lb/>
difficulty. If this dual language discussion is <lb/>
calculated to arouse passions and feelings which <lb/>
had better not be aroused, then the proper thing <lb/>
for Parliament to do is to settle the question once <lb/>
and for all. This is no settlement of it. What <lb/>
does it do? It merely leaves to the Assembly of <lb/>
the Territories the power to say that the Journals <lb/>
shall be printed in the way they think fit; in <lb/>
other words, they shall not be printed in both <lb/>
languages; and further, that but one language. <lb/>
if they please, shall be spoken in the Assembly. <lb/>
have not the slightest doubt that, without any law <lb/>
at all, any reasonable body of men—and I take it <lb/>
that the members of the North-West Assembly <lb/>
are reasonable men—would permit one of its <lb/>
members to speak in any language which suited <lb/>
him, in which they could follow him. I <lb/>
do not think they require any law for that. <lb/>
I do not think that is the grievance which was <lb/>
complained of. What the people of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West complained of, and what they still, if I read <lb/>
their press aright, complain of, is that this is a <lb/>
perpetuation of the system of dual languages, and, <lb/>
therefore, calculated to do a great deal of mis<lb break="no"/>chief, unless put an end to at an early day. <lb/>
That system is still maintained in the courts. <lb/>
I do not object, nor need anybody object, <lb/>
to the printing of the laws in as many lan<lb break="no"/>guages as the Assembly thinks necessary; it is <lb/>
not necessary to impose by this Act imperatively <lb/>
upon the Assembly that the laws shall be printed <lb/>
in French and English, as that is a matter which <lb/>
reasonable men would deal with properly and <lb/>
from the policy of perpetuating the dual system of <lb/>
language. I do not propose to renew the discus<lb break="no"/>sion at any length upon that subject; but ask the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the House to an omission which is per<lb break="no"/>haps still more serious in this Bill, and that is with <lb/>
reference to the question of education. By the <lb/>
law, as it now stands, separate schools have <lb/>

<pb n="4459" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04459.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4459</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">4460</fw> 

been, since 1875, absolutely imposed upon the <lb/>
people of the North-West Territories. The <lb/>
majority constitutes its school and then the <lb/>
minority, whether Protestant or Catholic, has a <lb/>
separate school. This system differs from the <lb/>
system prevailing in Ontario in this way, that in <lb/>
Ontario we have the public schools, which are the <lb/>
general schools, and then we have the separate <lb/>
schools which are the schools of the Roman Catholic <lb/>
minority. But in the North-West Territories the <lb/>
law is the same as in the Province of Quebec, I <lb/>
believe; at all events, it is that the majority <lb/>
having formed their school, the minority, whether <lb/>
Protestant or Catholic, are then entitled to form <lb/>
theirs. So that there are in most of the districts <lb/>
two schools—the school of the majority, whether <lb/>
Roman Catholic or Protestant, and that of the <lb/>
minority. The intention of our Constitution is to <lb/>
give the Local Assemblies absolute and com<lb break="no"/>plete control over education. That is the scheme <lb/>
of our Constitution. In the cases of Quebec <lb/>
and Ontario, special restrictions were imposed <lb/>
on both these Provinces; but in all the other <lb/>
Provinces of the Dominion there is no restriction <lb/>
whatever, and the question is left to be settled by <lb/>
the local authorities, who are the most competent <lb/>
to deal with it. I propose to ask the Committee, <lb/>
when this Bill is in committee, to place the <lb/>
law in the North-West Territories exactly in that <lb/>
position. When this law was passed, it was said <lb/>
there were only five hundred people in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories. It was passed, so far as the <lb/>
Senate was concerned, in opposition to a very <lb/>
large number of Senators. I have here the debate <lb/>
on the subject, and I find that this clause of the <lb/>
Bill was only carried by a majority of two, it hav<lb break="no"/>ing been opposed on a motion made by Senator <lb/>
Aikins and strongly supported by the Hon. <lb/>
George Brown. The late Mr. Brown opposed it <lb/>
on the ground that it was contrary to the spirit of <lb/>
the Constitution, as the British North America <lb/>
Act gave the matter of education absolutely to the <lb/>
Provinces, and that, as at that time, the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories were being endowed with certain <lb/>
powers, the power should be given to them of <lb/>
dealing with this question. Mr. Brown spoke, <lb/>
according to the official reports of the Senate, as <lb/>
follows:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"He held this provision was quite contrary to the <lb/>
British North America Act. Nothing was more clear <lb/>
that each Province should have absolute control over <lb/>
education. He held that was the only principle on which <lb/>
the Union Act could be continued. If the Dominion <lb/>
Government interfered in local matters we would get <lb/>
into inextricable confusion with the Provinces. The <lb/>
safe way for us was to let each Province suit itself in this <lb/>
matter. The country was filled with people of all classes <lb/>
and creeds, and there would be no end to confusion if each <lb/>
class had to have its own peculiar school system. It had <lb/>
been said this clause was ut in for the protection of the <lb/>
Protestants against the Catholics, the latter being the <lb/>
most numerous. But he, speaking for the Protestants, <lb/>
was in a position to say that we did not want that pro<lb break="no"/>tection. In this case, it was proposed that the national <lb/>
machinery should be used for the imposition and collec<lb break="no"/>tion of taxes upon persons of peculiar denominations <lb/>
for the support of schools of their kind. It was an <lb/>
attempt to enforce upon that country peculiar views with <lb/>
regar to education." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>Now, what was the argument against this conten<lb break="no"/>tion? It was that the system of separate schools <lb/>
and public schools was prevailing in Ontario and <lb/>
Quebec, and that it was the subject of very great <lb/>
regret that there was not in New Brunswick—be<lb break="no"/>cause at that time the New Brunswick question <lb/>

<cb/>

was up—a similar law. Well, I have learned from <lb/>
members coming from New Brunswick that the <lb/>
school system there has acted satisfactorily, and <lb/>
that there is no substantial grievance complained <lb/>
of by the minority, who do not find that, in attend<lb break="no"/>ing the ordinary public schools, they are suffering <lb/>
any great wrong. We know that in the Province <lb/>
of Ontario, in many places, all classes of religion <lb/>
attend the public schools. I know of one place in <lb/>
my own riding where the Roman Catholics have <lb/>
always refused to have separate schools, although <lb/>
they are a very large body in that particular town<lb break="no"/>ship. They are quite content, rather more <lb/>
than content, to send their children to the <lb/>
public schools, confident that by joining <lb/>
with the others they would get a much better <lb/>
education than by dividing the schools into two <lb/>
smaller bodies. The suggestions, therefore, which <lb/>
were made in the Senate in support of this clause <lb/>
of the Bill, experience has shown to be not war<lb break="no"/>ranted by the results. It is urged that this <lb/>
and kindred questions should not be dealt with <lb/>
until after the next elections, and I propose to <lb/>
move an amendment in that sense. The Legislative <lb/>
Assembly has unanimously petitioned that the <lb/>
clause to which I refer should be amended in the <lb/>
direction I speak of. I find upon the 29th of <lb/>
October, on motion of Mr. Richardson, seconded <lb/>
by Mr. Brett, it was resolved: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"That an humble Address be presented to His Excell<lb break="no"/>ency, the Governor General in Council, the Senate and the <lb/>
House of Commons, praying that an Act he passed to <lb/>
amend the North-West Territories Act by repealing sub<lb break="no"/>section 1, of section 14, after the word 'education' in <lb/>
the second line." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>In other words, simply giving the North-West <lb/>
Assembly power to deal with the subject of educa<lb break="no"/>tion. A special committee was thereupon ap<lb break="no"/>pointed to draft a petition, and both these motions <lb/>
were carried unanimously; and I find on page 65 <lb/>
of the Journals of the North-West Assembly, that a <lb/>
petition to the same effect was presented and <lb/>
again unanimously adopted. However, if there is <lb/>
any doubt about the propriety of asking the <lb/>
North-West Assembly to deal with this questlon at <lb/>
present, I am quite willing to yield to that doubt, <lb/>
because a year or two cannot make any great <lb/>
difference. Therefore, I propose to move in Com<lb break="no"/>mittee that after the next election they shall have <lb/>
power to deal with this subject of education in an <lb/>
unrestricted manner. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. I regret I was <lb/>
not able to be present during the previous part of <lb/>
this debate, and that I had not the advantage of <lb/>
hearing all the argument of the hon. member for <lb/>
North Simcoe. This Bill, however, does not pretend <lb/>
in any way to be either a consolidation of the laws <lb/>
respecting the North-West Territories or to make <lb/>
any substantial amendments, except to remove the <lb/>
clause dealing with education and leaving to a <lb/>
future Parliament the discussion of the whole <lb/>
system of governing the North-West. I presume <lb/>
that, in a very few years, the population there <lb/>
will be such as to call for the division of the <lb/>
Territories into Provinces. Then I have no doubt <lb/>
a constitution will be adopted similar in substance <lb/>
to the constitutions that prevail in the the various <lb/>
existing Provinces of the Dominion. The Legis<lb break="no"/>lature of Canada has proceeded, with reference to <lb/>
the organisation of the North-West, With great <lb/>
care and caution. It will be remembered that at <lb/>

<pb n="4461" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04461.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4461</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 6, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">4462</fw>

first that country was governed by a Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor with a council appointed, I think, alto<lb break="no"/>gether by the Crown, and afterwards with a council <lb/>
composed of a certain number of Crown nominees <lb/>
and a certain number of elected councillors. The <lb/>
governor was practically without responsibility to <lb/>
the Legislature, and I have no doubt that was <lb/>
designedly so, the Governor being responsible to the <lb/>
central Government, and that central Government <lb/>
or Cabinet being responsible to the Dominion <lb/>
Parliament. The amended measure which was <lb/>
introduced, I think, by my hon. friend from <lb/>
Bothwell (Mr. Mills) made a further advance and <lb/>
provided that when the population amounted to a <lb/>
certain number <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>. That was introduced by the hon. <lb/>
member for East York (Mr. Mackenzie). <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName> I beg the hon. <lb/>
gentleman's pardon for the error. That provided <lb/>
that, when the number of the elected members <lb/>
amounted to 21, the nominated council should <lb/>
disappear, and it should be changed from a council <lb/>
to an assembly, and the Governor would then sever <lb/>
himself—if I recollect aright—from the council of <lb/>
which before he was merely a member, and would <lb/>
assume a more distinct political existence, in fact, <lb/>
would assume by degrees the position of the <lb/>
representative of the Crown in a Province. Still, <lb/>
there was no responsible government provided for <lb/>
in so many words in that Act. In 1888, the last <lb/>
Act was passed, by which without the Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor having a responsible government as we <lb/>
understand it, without having advisers selected <lb/>
from the assembly and obliged to go back to their <lb/>
constituents for re-election upon being appointed <lb/>
advisers of the Crown, it was provided that <lb/>
further steps should be taken towards the assimil<lb break="no"/>ation of the system there to that which prevails in <lb/>
the Provinces, so that the Lieutenant Governor <lb/>
should have an advisory board taken from the <lb/>
Assembly, and so on. The difficulty—if difficulty <lb/>
it may be called—the difference of opinion in the <lb/>
North-West arose from the fact that the Assembly at <lb/>
once assumed that they had a constitution similar <lb/>
to a Provincial constitution. As to the danger <lb/>
that was alluded to by the hon. member for <lb/>
West Durham (Mr. Blake), or rather the practice <lb/>
in the olden days—I am old enough to remember <lb/>
them—the Lieutenant Governor of Upper Canada <lb/>
did not look after the finances at all except those <lb/>
which were derived from Imperial revenues, such <lb/>
as Customs, for instance. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>. And the post office <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. Also the post <lb/>
office and the Indian revenue quoad the Indians. <lb/>
The Lieutenant Governor managed those revenues <lb/>
autpcratieally, but, I believe, with a praiseworthy <lb/>
desire to meet the views of the people, though he <lb/>
was not obliged to do so. As to the revenues <lb/>
which came within the governance of the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture, I am afraid there was a great deal of what <lb/>
the hon. member for Western Assiniboia (Mr. <lb/>
Davin) calls log-rolling. At all events, there were <lb/>
Acts passed appropriating the revenue at the in<lb break="no"/>stance of any member who moved a Bill—some<lb break="no"/>thing like the system which now prevails in the <lb/>
American Congress. There were ludicrous instances <lb/>
of Bills being passed for certain purposes when <lb/>
there was no money in the treasury to carry out <lb/>
the purposes for which they were adopted. Year <lb/>

<cb/>

after year statutes were adopted enabling the <lb/>
Province to borrow money when there was really <lb/>
no power to borrow, and when, if there had been <lb/>
the power, they had not sufficient credit to raise <lb/>
the money required by the Bill. You will find a <lb/>
semi-indignant, but somewhat cynical account of <lb/>
these proceedings in the report of Lord Sydenham. <lb/>
This state of affairs was cured in 1863. In this <lb/>
case no such action can be taken except on the <lb/>
initiative of the Governor, who is responsible to <lb/>
the Parliament of Canada as a Dominion ofiicer, <lb/>
but he had always the power in that country to <lb/>
act at first on his own discretion. In <lb/>
1878, there was an attempt made to provide <lb/>
an embryotic Ministry or Council, to allow the <lb/>
Lieutenant Governor to select four advisers, from <lb/>
those he thought, from their commercial and <lb/>
financial experience, were best fitted to discharge <lb/>
that duty. That was all that was then done in <lb/>
the direction of establishing responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Whether the time has come, or not, when <lb/>
responsible government in its fullest extent should <lb/>
be established in those Territories, I am unable to <lb/>
say, but I can say this, that almost every gentle<lb break="no"/>man from the North-West with whom I have <lb/>
communicated, either personally or by letter, on <lb/>
the subject, has objected very much to the pre<lb break="no"/>mature introduction of the system which now <lb/>
prevails in the Province of Manitoba. They say <lb/>
that they are warned by the results of Provincial <lb/>
Government in Manitoba; that, there not being <lb/>
included in the population of that Province men <lb/>
of political experience, men acquainted with con<lb break="no"/>stitutional principles; they say—I am not ex<lb break="no"/>pressing my opinion on the subject—that the <lb/>
experience of Manitoba, and the enormous ex<lb break="no"/>penditure in that Province, has warned them <lb/>
against having that system prematurely extended <lb/>
to the North-West. I shall not enter into the <lb/>
discussion as to the dual language or the separate <lb/>
schools. The hon. member for North Simcoe <lb/>
(Mr. McCarthy) has promised to express his views <lb/>
by resolution when we are going into Committee <lb/>
of the Whole I hope, therefore, that the Bill <lb/>
will pass the second reading, and will be set down <lb/>
for an early day, when we can discuss those ques<lb break="no"/>tions. I regret that my absence from the House <lb/>
at the time prevented my hearing the speech of <lb/>
the hon. gentleman, and, therefore, no doubt, my <lb/>
remarks are very much short of being an answer <lb/>
to that speech. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). I agree with the hon. <lb/>
member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy), in <lb/>
saying that the measure now under our considera<lb break="no"/>tion is one of the most important, perhaps the <lb/>
most important, that has been before the House <lb/>
this Session, and I feel in my own mind that it is <lb/>
quite impossible at this period of the Session to <lb/>
give to a measure of this importance that full and <lb/>
exhaustive consideration which it ought to receive <lb/>
from this House. The principles involved in the <lb/>
measure are of very great importance, and ought <lb/>
to receive very full consideration, and ought to be <lb/>
discussed from every possible standpoint by the <lb/>
members of this House, before any final action is <lb/>
taken. Now, the hon. gentleman has stated that <lb/>
it is not proper at the present time that responsible <lb/>
overnment should be introduced in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories. Well, it does seem to me an <lb/>
extremely unsatisfactmy condition of things that <lb/>

<pb n="4463" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04463.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4463</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">4464</fw> 

you have given to the people of that country a <lb/>
representative Assembly, but that you should <lb/>
withhold from them executive responsibility. The <lb/>
hon. the First Minister has referred to the Lieute<lb break="no"/>nant Governor as a party who is responsible for <lb/>
the executive government in those Territories. <lb/>
Well, he is only responsible in the same way that <lb/>
the Governor appointed by the Imperial Ministry <lb/>
for this country was responsible to Downing <lb/>
Street before responsible government was con<lb break="no"/>ceded. The Lieutenant Governor of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories is responsible to the Adminis<lb break="no"/>tration here; he is not responsible at all in the <lb/>
sense in which we understand the expression. It is <lb/>
an Administration, or an Executive, that is respon<lb break="no"/>sible to the representatives of the people within <lb/>
the Territories for the purposes for which that repre<lb break="no"/>sentative Assembly is constituted. Now, there has <lb/>
been a good deal of discussion in the House, not on <lb/>
this question but on another question that pre<lb break="no"/>ceded it this Session, which shows that to some <lb/>
extent there is confusion in the minds, I think, of <lb/>
the members of this House, and also perhaps, in <lb/>
public estimation, with regard to the differences <lb/>
that exist between a Territorial Government and a <lb/>
Provincial Government. We recognise this differ<lb break="no"/>ence in every Bill that we introduce to this House, <lb/>
and we have recognised it in the measure that is <lb/>
now before us. But whether we give to the Terri<lb break="no"/>torial Legislature large power, or whether we give <lb/>
to it little power, whatever power is conferred <lb/>
upon it should be exercised, it seems to me, under <lb/>
the control of a responsible Administration. I do <lb/>
not see how it is possible that you can have any<lb break="no"/>thing like permanency in public policy in regard to <lb/>
measures which may be brought before that Legis<lb break="no"/>lature for consideration, unless you have an Admi<lb break="no"/>nistration controlling the legislation and respon<lb break="no"/>sible for its due execution. You may have measures <lb/>
carried through the Territorial Legislature to-day, <lb/>
which will be repealed next Session, because there <lb/>
is no Administration existing which will, in any <lb/>
proper sense, be responsible for the conduct of <lb/>
public affairs. Now, I admit that in a new country <lb/>
people must be content with narrower powers than <lb/>
we have in an older country, which is more densely <lb/>
settled, where the population has grown more <lb/>
wealthy, where their wants are more varied. We <lb/>
recognise this difference in the growth of Provincial <lb/>
establishments under responsible governments. <lb/>
We are not content to-day with the amount of <lb/>
power that was possessed by the old Legislature of <lb/>
the Provinces after responsible government was <lb/>
first introduced. Our population has become more <lb/>
dense, their interests have become more varied, <lb/>
they have external as well as domestic relations, <lb/>
and so they require and ask for a voice in con<lb break="no"/>trolling their external as well as their domestic <lb/>
affairs. This may make a difference between the <lb/>
extent of power which we confer upon a Local <lb/>
Legislature under a territorial system, and upon a <lb/>
Local Legislature that is constituted under a Provin<lb break="no"/>cial organisation. But all these matters are matters <lb/>
that require very careful consideration. I was <lb/>
astonished at the change of sentiment indicated by <lb/>
the speech of the hon. member for North Simcoe <lb/>
here to-day, in discussing the subject of the dual <lb/>
language. The hon. gentleman expressed sentiments <lb/>
to-day with which I, in a great measure, cordially <lb/>
agree; they were those which I enunciated in dis<lb break="no"/>cussing this Bill at an earlier period of the Session. <lb/>

<cb/>

The hon. gentleman has had new light, and I am <lb/>
glad to see that the views which he expressed to<lb break="no"/>day are more nearly in consonance with those <lb/>
entertained by the majority of this House. Now, <lb/>
I am sure that some of the parties outside of the <lb/>
House will be disappointed. Let me tell the hon, <lb/>
gentleman this: A Frenchman and a countryman <lb/>
of his, in this city, were discussing this question of <lb/>
the dual language yesterday, and his countryman <lb/>
said to his French friend: "Ah, ye may use your <lb/>
French lingo to-day, but wait till the Great <lb/>
McCarthy has done wid ye, and ye will only be <lb/>
able to make signs then." I am sure if the hon. <lb/>
gentleman's countryman had heard his speech here <lb/>
to-day, he would be satisfied that the Frenchman, <lb/>
after all, might be able to do something more than <lb/>
make signs after the hon. gentleman had done with <lb/>
him. The hon. gentleman has recognised to-day <lb/>
the principle that language used for public purposes, <lb/>
like language used for private purposes, is a <lb/>
matter of convenience. The hon. gentleman said <lb/>
that we ought not to force two languages upon a <lb/>
population. Well, I do not think we are doing <lb/>
that. I was opposed to that in the first instance, <lb/>
but I never supposed for one moment that if <lb/>
the members of the Council were Frenchmen and <lb/>
could not speak English, they would be debarred <lb/>
from speaking French. That was their privilege. <lb/>
When that Council was first created the Crown <lb/>
appointed to the Council, upon our advice, a <lb/>
half-breed who could not speak a word of English, <lb/>
and we appointed him because he was a man of <lb/>
immense influence over the hall-breed population <lb/>
and one in whom they had the utmost confidence; <lb/>
and I am perfectly sure that we carried on the <lb/>
government of that country during the remaining <lb/>
period of our administration, with very much <lb/>
smaller police force to maintain peace in that <lb/>
country, than if we had appointed a member to <lb/>
the Council in whom the people of the Territories <lb/>
had not the utmost confidence I observe that <lb/>
the hon. gentleman has by this Bill, in section 3, <lb/>
provided that the "territories formerly known as <lb/>
Rupert's Land and the North-West Territories <lb/>
shall be" so and so. Well, the hon. gentleman <lb/>
will see, from looking at any old work on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject of Hudson's Bay, or any old map representing <lb/>
that territory, that Rupert's Land embraced the <lb/>
territory east of Hudson's Bay as well as the <lb/>
territories on the west, and that the designation <lb/>
of the North-West Territories applied rather to the <lb/>
territories extending eastward from the Bay, and <lb/>
that Rupert's Land was, on most old maps, marked <lb/>
as the territory laying on the east and south-east <lb/>
of that Bay. The hon. gentleman will remember <lb/>
that the territory is not embraced in any Province <lb/>
at the present time; it is not embraced in the <lb/>
Territory of Keewatin, and so there ought to be <lb/>
some phraseology used to show what precise terri<lb break="no"/>tories are intended to be embraced under the <lb/>
provisions of this Bill. I notice there are some <lb/>
provisions providing for the appointment of <lb/>
legal experts, for the appointment of a fixed <lb/>
number of members of the Territories, which is, <lb/>
no doubt, right and proper in the first instance; <lb/>
but the limits of the territorial districts and <lb/>
the number of members to be elected, ought to <lb/>
be left to the people of the Territories through the <lb/>
Legislature which they have constituted. I would <lb/>
just say one thing more with regard to the general <lb/>
principles embodied in this Bill, and that is with <lb/>

<pb n="4465" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04465.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4465</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 6, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">4466</fw>

reference to any appropriation that may be made <lb/>
by this Parliament and placed at the disposal of <lb/>
the Legislature of that Territory. I think that an <lb/>
amount of money ought to be appropriated upon <lb/>
some principle such as was recognised in making <lb/>
an appropriation out of the revenue for the use of <lb/>
a Province, and it ought to be as absolutely under <lb/>
the control of the Legislature and its responsible <lb/>
executive as an appropriation that is made by this <lb/>
Parliament under the constitution is under the <lb/>
control of the Legislature of the Province to which <lb/>
it is made. It is impossible that the government <lb/>
of that country can be fairly carried on with the <lb/>
very small appropriation that is made, nor is it at <lb/>
all adequate when we compare the number of the <lb/>
population with the number of the people in any <lb/>
one of the Provinces. It does seem to me, when <lb/>
we look at the fact that the Territories have no <lb/>
resources whatever except those received by direct <lb/>
taxation or those derived from grants made by this <lb/>
House, that an appropriation ought to be placed at <lb/>
the disposal of the Legislature of the Territories <lb/>
for territorial purposes, and it should be as com<lb break="no"/>pletely under their control and as free from inter<lb break="no"/>ference as if it were made to a Province regularly <lb/>
constituted. <lb/></p> 

<p>Motion agreed to, and House resolved itself into <lb/>
Committee. <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">(In the Committee.)</head> 

<p>On section 3, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAWS1">Mr. DAWSON</persName>. Perhaps the hon. Minister will <lb/>
allow me to direct his attention to a technical <lb/>
matter; it is that, I think, the description might <lb/>
be somewhat improved. It at present reads: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"All that portion of the Dominion of Canada which is <lb/>
bounded as follows that is to say: Beginning at the point <lb/>
of intersection of the western boundary of the Province <lb/>
of Manitoba and the international boundary line dividing <lb/>
Canada from the United States; thence westerly along <lb/>
the said international boundary line to the line of the <lb/>
watershed dividing the waters flowing into the Pacific <lb/>
Ocean from those flowing into the Arctic Sea or Hudson's <lb/>
Bay." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>The international boundary line does not touch <lb/>
the watershed of the Arctic Sea at all, but it <lb/>
crosses the watershed separating the waters flow<lb break="no"/>ing into Hudson's Bay from the waters running to <lb/>
the Pacific Ocean. The description would be bet<lb break="no"/>ter in this way: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Dividing the waters flowing into the Pacific Ocean <lb/>
from those flowing into the Gulf of Mexico and Hudson's <lb/>
Bay." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>I believe that in the Rocky Mountains the inter<lb break="no"/>national boundary line actually touches on the <lb/>
sources of the Mississippi, but certainly it does <lb/>
not touch on any river flowing into the Arctic <lb/>
Ocean. It also touches the head waters of the <lb/>
south branch of the Saskatchewan. The hon. <lb/>
Mister has officers in his Department who could <lb/>
draw up a very good description. As it stands <lb/>
now, it is not a great deal better than the descrip<lb break="no"/>tion drawn by the Imperial Privy Council of the <lb/>
boundaries between Manitoba and Ontario, where <lb/>
a very large portion of the United States is given <lb/>
to one of the Provinces. I merely throw out the <lb/>
suggestion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. The officers of the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment have taken much trouble in preparing this <lb/>
description; but if the hon. gentleman will send to <lb/>

<cb/>

me in writing any suggestion he has to officer, it <lb/>
will be considered. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. I doubt very much whether <lb/>
it is advisable to change the name of the country <lb/>
from the North-West Territories to the Western <lb/>
Territories of Canada. The new name is not as <lb/>
convenient as the old one, because there are more <lb/>
words in it. The country has been for many <lb/>
years known as the North-West Territories, and it <lb/>
will very likely continue to be so known despite <lb/>
this legislation changing its name. I question very <lb/>
much the propriety of making any change, and I <lb/>
move that we retain the old name, North-West <lb/>
Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>. It occurred to me that it is a <lb/>
very awkward name that is proposed. If you do <lb/>
not use a name that is easily spoken, it will not be <lb/>
used at all. I felt some difficulty about making a <lb/>
change, but it occurs to me that if a change is to <lb/>
be made it would be a much easier mouthful to say, <lb/>
Western Canadian Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. The name might <lb/>
be changed to Western Territories. Objection has <lb/>
been taken to the word "North" as conveying to <lb/>
the general public the idea of an arctic condition, <lb/>
that the country was not very like the American <lb/>
North-West, but was further north, and possessed <lb/>
a more severe climate, a shorter summer and a <lb/>
longer winter, and for these reasons it was suggested <lb/>
to drop the word "North." <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>. It seems to me that the old name, <lb/>
after all, was not devoid of truth, and the change <lb/>
proposed will not alter the thermometer in winter <lb/>
or in summer in any way whatever. My impres<lb break="no"/>sion is that any announcement made to the world <lb/>
at large, and particularly to the immigrating public, <lb/>
with the view of persuading them that they are <lb/>
not going to cold winters in the North-West, will <lb/>
not have any effect on any sensible man. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). These Territories have <lb/>
been designated by the present name for half a cen<lb break="no"/>tury, and are known to the geographical world by <lb/>
that name, which we should retain. The name <lb/>
merely expresses its relation to the other portions <lb/>
of Canada. In 1787, the territories between the <lb/>
Ohio, Lake Erie and Mississippi, were called the <lb/>
North-West Territories of the United States, and <lb/>
they were so-called because of the geographical po<lb break="no"/>sition of the territory to that embraced within the <lb/>
thirteen States of the Union. So I think those <lb/>
territories may very well retain the name of <lb/>
North-West Territories, considering their relation <lb/>
to the rest of Canada. This section would re<lb break="no"/>quire to be somewhat altered so as to describe <lb/>
the Territory of Keewatin, and the north and west <lb/>
of the Province of Manitoba; otherwise you have <lb/>
not a proper description. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. As to the name, <lb/>
I do not suppose there will be any serious quarrel <lb/>
about it. My hon. friend from Bothwell (Mr. <lb/>
Mills), as did my hon. friend from Algoma (Mr. <lb/>
Dawson), suggested that the description was in<lb break="no"/>accurate. My hon. friend said that Rupert's <lb/>
Land was understood to be the land that lay to <lb/>
the south and south-east of Hudson Bay. If that <lb/>
is the case, the North-West Territories, which <lb/>
was one time held under license, would be sup<lb break="no"/>posed to lie to the south-west of Rupert's Land. I <lb/>
would suggest that the clause should be allowed to <lb/>

<pb n="4467" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04467.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4467</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">4468</fw> 

stand until the Minister of the Interior has time <lb/>
to consider the matter. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Rupert's Land lies east <lb/>
of the Territory of Keewatin. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man does not propose to embrace all that territory <lb/>
under this jurisdiction. All the territories this <lb/>
Bill deals with lie west of the Territory of Keewa<lb break="no"/>tin, and, therefore, it should not refer to Rupert's <lb/>
Land at all. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. The simplest way would <lb/>
be to leave out "Rupert's Land" altogether. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. O'BRIEN</persName>. I think it is a great mistake to <lb/>
change the name. There is a sort of historical <lb/>
interest attached to the name of the "North-<lb break="yes"/>West," and when you speak of the North-West in <lb/>
Dakota or the Western States, the people know at <lb/>
once that you refer to the North-West Territories <lb/>
of Canada. It is a more euphonious name than <lb/>
the one you now propose, and in all respects a <lb/>
better one in my opinion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI9">Mr. DAVIS</persName> (Alberta). I think we should <lb/>
call it the South-West Territories instead of the <lb/>
North-West, for there are plenty of lands which <lb/>
remain there which you can call the North-West <lb/>
if you so wish. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). In that case the hon. <lb/>
gentleman ought to propose to exclude from this Bill <lb/>
all the territories lying north of the Saskatchewan, <lb/>
but this Bill embraces all the territories to the <lb/>
mouth of the Mackenzie River, and the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman will hardly call the territories lying around <lb/>
the Mackenzie and Copper Mine Rivers the "South-<lb break="yes"/>West." <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. The change proposed by the <lb/>
hon. gentleman would lead to the supposition that <lb/>
we had been acquiring territories in Central Ame<lb break="no"/>rica. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName> There are a number of peo<lb break="no"/>ple throughout Canada who have a very strong <lb/>
feeling on this matter. The name of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West often leads to a confusion between our coun<lb break="no"/>try and the United States. I saw, no later than <lb/>
a few days ago, in our local paper here, a statement <lb/>
as to a snowstorm in the North-West Territory, <lb/>
and people looking at the item though it referred <lb/>
to the North-West of Canada, and congratulated <lb/>
themselves that the snow would do good to the <lb/>
fields. I have frequently had letters from the old <lb/>
country, sympathising with us on account of storms <lb/>
and cyclones, which were experienced in the West<lb break="no"/>ern States of the Union, but the people thought <lb/>
they had occurred in our North-West. That is one <lb/>
of the principal reasons that we proposed to change <lb/>
the name. I do not think the name should be <lb/>
struck out of the Bill without consideration, and <lb/>
I think it is better to allow the clause to stand for <lb/>
the present. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. I did not raise an objection that <lb/>
this Bill was not translated into French as I did <lb/>
not wish to delay the House at this late period of <lb/>
the Session, but I should like to know from the <lb/>
Minister of the Interior before I vote for this, what <lb/>
is the translation into French of the name he has <lb/>
suggested. If the hon. Minister cannot answer me, <lb/>
perhaps the hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. <lb/>
McCarthy) can. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. I decline. <lb/></p> 

<cb/>

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAP4">Mr. CHAPLEAU</persName>. Nobody knows that better <lb/>
than my hon. friend from Bellechasse (Mr. Amyot). <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. I am sorry I cannot give <lb/>
the hon. gentleman the name in French. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LANG1">Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN</persName>. The hon. member <lb/>
for Bellechasse (Mr. Amyot) is too good a French <lb/>
scholar not to be able to translate that himself, <lb/>
but no doubt he wanted to have a little joke on <lb/>
my hon. friend the Minister of the Interior, who is <lb/>
not, perhaps, so fluent in French as he is in English. <lb/>
I suppose the translation Would be: "Territoires <lb/>
Occidentaux du Canada." That will be rather a <lb/>
long name, but I believe it will be a good transla<lb break="no"/>tion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. I am glad this has drawn <lb/>
some compliments to my humble self from the <lb/>
Minister of Public Works. I am not used to them. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. We will let the <lb/>
section stand. <lb/></p> 

<p>On section 5, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). I think this section is <lb/>
objectionable in this, that it ought to provide for <lb/>
a fixed number of members until the Legislature <lb/>
otherwise determines. The Legislature ought to <lb/>
have an opportunity of altering the boundaries of <lb/>
constituencies, or increasing the number of mem<lb break="no"/>bers. It may be convenient, on account of settle<lb break="no"/>ment going on more rapidly in one division than in <lb/>
another, to divide it and give it two representa<lb break="no"/>tives. Then, I can see no object in having three <lb/>
legal experts. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. With regard to the twenty-<lb break="yes"/>two electoral districts, I may state, that that <lb/>
number was agreed to during my term as Lieu<lb break="no"/>tenant Governor, and a great deal of trouble was <lb/>
taken in the division of the electoral districts. The <lb/>
members were naturally jealous for their districts, <lb/>
desiring to get as many members for them as <lb/>
possible; but after a good deal of negotiation, the <lb/>
number of twenty-two was agreed to as a com<lb break="no"/>promise. I am not aware whether there will be <lb/>
any objection to giving to the Legislative Assembly <lb/>
power to increase their number; I think they <lb/>
would probably know the position of affairs better <lb/>
than any one else. With regard to the legal <lb/>
experts, during my time they were of very great <lb/>
service in the Council, and I believe they are still <lb/>
felt to be of great service, and I think it would be <lb/>
a pity at present to make any change with regard <lb/>
to them. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). If it is found necessary <lb/>
that parties with legal knowledge should be in the <lb/>
Assembly to advise, the constituencies ought to do <lb/>
just as is done in regard to this House—they ought <lb/>
to return a certain number of legal gentlemen to <lb/>
the Legislature, who would give them the legal <lb/>
advice they require. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I do not think there is any sub<lb break="no"/>stantial reason for changing this clause. It is <lb/>
only a temporary arrangement, and at present it <lb/>
works very well. I may say that the members of <lb/>
the North-West Council pretty well fixed on the <lb/>
number of the constituencies before we fixed on it <lb/>
here. I do not think there is any sense of griev<lb break="no"/>ance with regard to this clause at all. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. The Bill of my <lb/>
hon. friend opposite (Mr. Mills, Bothwell) made <lb/>

<pb n="4469" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04469.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4469</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 6, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">4470</fw>

provision for twenty-one elected members when<lb break="no"/>ever the population arrived at a certain point; <lb/>
and there was frequent request from the North-<lb break="yes"/>West to alter the constitution to allow of twenty-<lb break="yes"/>one elected members. When the Council met to<lb break="no"/>gether, they found that it would be more conveni<lb break="no"/>ent, that it would make a better readjustment—a <lb/>
better gerrymander, as the hon. gentleman would <lb/>
call it—if there were twenty-two elected members <lb/>
instead of twenty-one. That was their own de<lb break="no"/>liberate recommendation, and I think we ought to <lb/>
leave the provision as it is until they ask for an <lb/>
alteration; because the House must remember <lb/>
that the expenses of the Legislature are defrayed <lb/>
out of the Dominion treasury. By-and-bye, when <lb/>
the North-West Territories become Provinces, they <lb/>
will, of course, have all the powers which Provinces <lb/>
have. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. There are at present nineteen <lb/>
territorial divisions, two of which, Edmonton and <lb/>
Calgary, I think, elect two members each. I think <lb/>
it would be wise to adopt the suggestion made by <lb/>
my hon. friend from Bothwell (Mr. Mills), that as <lb/>
the population increases in any division, the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature should have power to increase the number <lb/>
of representatives for that division. Not later <lb/>
than yesterday, the hon. gentleman introduced a <lb/>
Bill which he hoped would very much increase the <lb/>
population in a certain section of the country, that <lb/>
is to say, the section which already returns two <lb/>
members, Calgary and Edmonton. Under such <lb/>
circumstances, it seems to me that the suggestion <lb/>
made by the hon. member for Bothwell has a good <lb/>
deal to commend it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. The difficulty I see about it <lb/>
would be this: that if one district proposed to <lb/>
increase its number, every other district would <lb/>
also insist on an increase. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Why should you un<lb break="no"/>dertake, once you have created a representative <lb/>
body, to tie it up in this way. There is none of <lb/>
the Provinces tied up by the Constitution in that <lb/>
way. The hon. gentleman is just creating a diffi<lb break="no"/>culty similar to the one which was raised here <lb/>
during this Session over the clause relating to the <lb/>
dual language, a clause which was wholly unneces<lb break="no"/>sary to secure the use of both languages. Now, <lb/>
you propose by this restriction to force these peo<lb break="no"/>ple to come here and occupy the time of this <lb/>
House in making a change which they could, if <lb/>
you gave them the power, better make for them<lb break="no"/>selves, as they are better judges in that matter <lb/>
than we can be. Suppose one of these districts in <lb/>
the next few years increases in population while <lb/>
the others scarcely increase at all, that district <lb/>
will require additional representation; and that is <lb/>
a point which the Legislative Assembly is best <lb/>
fitted to pronounce upon. All that it is necessary <lb/>
is to say that the Legislative Assembly shall be <lb/>
composed, until the Assembly otherwise deter<lb break="no"/>mines, of twenty-two members. There is no dan<lb break="no"/>ger of the Assembly wasting its resources lightly <lb/>
by undertaking to increase the number of repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives beyond the actual requirements. If <lb/>
any such a thing were attempted, the people would <lb/>
send other men to represent them. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. The money does <lb/>
not come out of the local revenues, but out of the <lb/>
Dominion treasury. <lb/></p>

<cb/>

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). These people are con<lb break="no"/>tributors to the Dominion treasury. You give to <lb/>
every Province a certain revenue per head <lb/>
according to the population. Are you prepared to <lb/>
give them the same revenue to be at their own dis<lb break="no"/>posal? I think we should. I think, that as soon <lb/>
as they increase in numbers sufficiently to be enti<lb break="no"/>tled to have a competent representative Assembly, <lb/>
they ought to have control of the revenues required <lb/>
to carry on the Government, and those revenues <lb/>
should be voted by this Legislature on some intel<lb break="no"/>ligible principles recognised by the British North <lb/>
America Act as applicable to the Provinces. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I have always contended that we <lb/>
should have a revenue granted on the same prin<lb break="no"/>ciples as those on which revenues are given to the <lb/>
Provinces. But the reason I do not think it neces<lb break="no"/>sary that this clause should be changed, is that I <lb/>
have heard no desire expressed on the part of the <lb/>
members for a change, and have seen no evidence of <lb/>
grievance whatever in that connection. The only <lb/>
thing I have noticed in connection with this clause, <lb/>
is that there is a kind of defiance on the part of the <lb/>
members of three judges who are there. I do not <lb/>
know why they should dislike to have them there, <lb/>
since they cannot vote, and only one of them <lb/>
speaks. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. He speaks very long. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. No; he does not. He has only <lb/>
spoken once or twice. The experience, patience <lb/>
and labor of Judge Richardson, as the hon. the <lb/>
Minister of the Interior well knows, are invaluable <lb/>
to that Assembly; and Judge McLeod is a man <lb/>
of considerable experience and ability; and I <lb/>
cannot understand why there should be, among <lb/>
quite a number of the members, a certain im<lb break="no"/>patience at havihg these gentlemen there. So far <lb/>
as I can see, they do nothing but good. They do not <lb/>
vote, and take no part in the discussions. There is <lb/>
only one subject on which the learned judge ever <lb/>
took a prominent part, and that is the subject of <lb/>
the dual language clause. I do not see much ne<lb break="no"/>cessity of changing this clause; but if, later on, <lb/>
when you come to the clause giving the Assembly <lb/>
power in great part over the revenue, you should <lb/>
make a change so as to give it a little executive, <lb/>
then, on the third reading, you could recom<lb break="no"/>mit this Bill, and alter, as you logically should, <lb/>
this clause. The hon. member for Bothwell (Mr. <lb/>
Mills) says that three or four years hence it may <lb/>
be found necessary to add to the number of the <lb/>
Assembly. Why, Sir, before three or four years <lb/>
pass, we shall require to have another North-West <lb/>
Territories Bill in this House. We shall have a <lb/>
census taken; and I venture to say that we shall <lb/>
find a far larger number in the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories than hon. gentlemen, who always speak dis<lb break="no"/>paragingly of that country, give it credit for; and <lb/>
that being the case, something will have to be done <lb/>
then in order to readjust the representation. If <lb/>
the hon. gentleman had proposed a practical plan, <lb/>
I should see no insuperablc difficulty in altering <lb/>
this clause; but, as a matter of fact, there is no <lb/>
grievance. I have never heard a single complaint <lb/>
about the number; I have never heard any of the <lb/>
members declare that they ought to be able to con<lb break="no"/>trol it; and the only murmur I have heard— <lb/>
in fact they have petitioned was that they <lb/>
objected, for some inscrutable reason, to having <lb/>
the three legal experts, there. At present I think <lb/>

<pb n="4471" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04471.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4471</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">4472</fw> 

it is an advantage to have them there. Our ex<lb break="no"/>perience has shown that the members of the <lb/>
Assembly found it convenient to make use of these <lb/>
gentlemen's experience and legal knowledge. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>. As long as we have not decided <lb/>
to alter fundamentally the system which exists, and <lb/>
which it is proposed by this Bill to continue, I do <lb/>
not see, in the absence of any complaint from the <lb/>
Assembly, why we should interfere with the three <lb/>
legal experts who do not vote. The only com<lb break="no"/>plaint that can be made is that which the hon. <lb/>
member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) suggest<lb break="no"/>ed, that their speeches are rather long. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. There is a petition against <lb/>
them. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>. I was not aware of that; I did not <lb/>
find, on looking at the petitions, that there was <lb/>
any complaint against them. My own impression <lb/>
strongly is, that if a small executive council were <lb/>
granted to the Territories, which, I think, ought <lb/>
to be granted, the experts should disappear; and <lb/>
my opinion is that the people of the country them<lb break="no"/>selves would find it necessary to elect to the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly a certain limited number of gentlemen experi<lb break="no"/>enced in the law, so that their Assembly might not <lb/>
    be a <hi rendition="simple:italic">parliamentum indoctum</hi>, as a well-known Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment was, from which, I believe, the lawyers were <lb/>
altogether excluded. They would thus obtain as <lb/>
much trained assistance as they thought necessary; <lb/>
and if they chose to do without it, nobody but <lb/>
themselves would be the sufferers. With refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the number of members, I was not in a <lb/>
position, of course, to hear the whispers of the <lb/>
North-West; but I heard what were not whispers <lb/>
here. I heard the hon. member for Saskatchewan, <lb/>
at an early period of the Session, declare that <lb/>
complaints were made with reference to the dis<lb break="no"/>tribution of districts in the North—West, and <lb/>
particularly with reference to those in the region he <lb/>
represents; and, if necessary, some remedy ought to <lb/>
be applied to that. If there be a subject with which <lb/>
the Territorial Assembly might be supposed to be <lb/>
better competent to deal than any other, it is in <lb/>
what way the country should be divided for local <lb/>
representation. How is it possible for us to form <lb/>
an intelligent appreciation of that subject? We <lb/>
have to take upon trust the statement of the <lb/>
Minister who studies the subject, with his know<lb break="no"/>ledge of the country from the maps, and the state<lb break="no"/>ments of the four members from the North-West <lb/>
Territories. We cannot judge how things are. <lb/>
We cannot give an intelligent vote upon the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of the arrangement of districts. They are, <lb/>
in a country of that description, arrangements <lb/>
which require an intelligent acquaintance, not <lb/>
merely with the census, but with the prospects of <lb/>
growth and with the particular regions in which <lb/>
those prospects are brightest. It is an evil to <lb/>
change frequently, and in this country we know <lb/>
that, in older days, when changes were made, we <lb/>
recognised the view that newer sections—as, for <lb/>
example, the County of Bruce and the County of <lb/>
Renfrew—should be, as regarded population, over<lb break="no"/>represented for a while, because we expected that an <lb/>
influx of population would redress the difference. <lb/>
That is all a matter to be best considered by the <lb/>
Assembly itself, and, therefore, I think that the <lb/>
readjustment of the electoral districts might be <lb/>
well left to the Assembly. The only question is <lb/>
whether we should give them the power to increase <lb/>

<cb/>

the number of districts, and the only difficulty in <lb/>
regard to that is what the First Minister has sug<lb break="no"/>gested, that they may unduly increase the number <lb/>
of districts because it is a popular thing to do, be<lb break="no"/>cause there are many who in small districts might <lb/>
thus obtain positions of prominence, and possibly of <lb/>
emolument, which they otherwise could not. If <lb/>
we think it necessary so far to hamper and restrain <lb/>
the action of the Assembly, that difficulty might <lb/>
be remedied by providing a maximum number which <lb/>
would cover all demands for increased representa<lb break="no"/>tion for the next few years. We might say the <lb/>
number should be thirty. We might give the new <lb/>
Assembly, elected after the people have had that <lb/>
question before them, the power to readjust the <lb/>
districts, while not giving them the power to <lb/>
increase the number of districts beyond a certain <lb/>
maximum. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). The advantage of not <lb/>
confining the number of the Assembly to twenty-<lb break="yes"/>two is that, if you have a large increase in popu<lb break="no"/>lation you have it met by a division of the districts, <lb/>
but, if you fix the number at twenty-two, it may <lb/>
entail a readjustment of the entire territory. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I am entirely in favor of <lb/>
the view expressed by the hon. member for <lb/>
Bothwell (Mr. Mills). It seems to me that we <lb/>
are treating the people of the North-West as if <lb/>
they were unfitted for responsible institutions. <lb/>
Most of these people come from the older Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, and they are generally well trained in <lb/>
regard to political institutions. From the short <lb/>
visit which I paid to the North—West, it appeared <lb/>
to me that they were particularly well fitted in <lb/>
that respect, though the hon. member for West <lb/>
Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) seems to think that they <lb/>
do not occupy the same plane as members of this <lb/>
House. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. No. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. That seemed to be the tone <lb/>
of the hon. gentleman's remarks. We ought not <lb/>
always to be tinkering with this question of the <lb/>
North-West. We cannot here be competent to <lb/>
reassign and readjust the boundaries of the dis<lb break="no"/>tricts in the North-West. If the Legislative <lb/>
Assembly there are to have the power to readjust <lb/>
the boundaries, we should give them the power to <lb/>
increase the districts when, in their judgment, it is <lb/>
necessary. It may be said that these 22 men have <lb/>
not the ability to do anything until after the next <lb/>
election. That, at all events, is the theory which <lb/>
has been already adopted by this Parliament. At <lb/>
all events, they might be given the power to do it <lb/>
after the next election. I dare say that, if you take <lb/>
many of the districts since the Act was passed <lb/>
two years ago, you will find the changes in popula<lb break="no"/>tion so great that the present representation is not <lb/>
a fair one. I press upon the Committee that a <lb/>
change should be made in the direction suggested <lb/>
by the hon. member for Bothwell (Mr. Mills). <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I wish to repudiate in the strong<lb break="no"/>est manner the language of the hon. member for <lb/>
North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy). He said that I <lb/>
put the representatives in the Assembly on a lower <lb/>
plane than the members composing this Parliament. <lb/>
On the contrary, I have again and again asserted <lb/>
in this House that we have a representation in that <lb/>
Assembly which would do credit to any Assembly <lb/>
in the world. I congratulate the North-West on <lb/>

<pb n="4473" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04473.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4473</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 6, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">4474</fw>

the sudden accession of popularity which it has <lb/>
obtained, because in 1887, 1888 and 1889, when I <lb/>
brought forward the question and moved for a rep<lb break="no"/>resentative government there, I found there was <lb/>
very little interest taken in the subject either by <lb/>
hon. gentlemen on the Reform side, or by hon. <lb/>
gentlemen on the Ministerial side of the House. <lb/>
My hon. friend from Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) must <lb/>
remember that he should not taunt me, who have <lb/>
been a veteran in the service of the North-West, <lb/>
because he is now animated by the warm zeal of a <lb/>
convert. I am glad to welcome him as a <lb/>
convert, but confessedly it is a recent interest on <lb/>
his part, confessedly it is a new love, and it has all <lb/>
the warmth and perhaps some of the imprudence <lb/>
of a new attachment. So he must not taunt me, <lb/>
who have been fighting the battles of this people, <lb/>
and have contended in this House for responsi<lb break="no"/>ble government for them. If you give them <lb/>
representative government now, I want to be <lb/>
logical, and I think that clause should be changed. <lb/>
I think now, when you are going to give them con<lb break="no"/>trol over the funds, you should do what the hon. <lb/>
member for Bothwell (Mr. Mills) contends, <lb/>
namely, strike an average as to the population— <lb/>
you can easily find out what the population is, you <lb/>
can go far below what the actual population is, and <lb/>
still give us far more than we get now; you can <lb/>
give us an adequate income, loose our hands and <lb/>
set us free; give us our majority and let us do the <lb/>
best we can for our country; give us our executive, <lb/>
and then we can go back to this clause and change <lb/>
it, if necessary. But the reason why I desire not <lb/>
to change the clause now is that, after the census <lb/>
which is close at hand, is taken, you cannot deny <lb/>
us responsible government. My hon. friend (Mr. <lb/>
McCarthy) says he has been in that country, and <lb/>
he must know that the people of the North-West <lb/>
are, in intelligence, above the population of any <lb/>
other part of Canada. I mean that there is a <lb/>
greater average intelligence amongst them than <lb/>
there is amongst the people in any other part of <lb/>
    the country. In fact we have had an <hi rendition="simple:italic">immigration <lb/>
d'élite</hi>. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. Dual language. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I do not feel anxious about this <lb/>
clause, but I congratulate the North-West, and I <lb/>
may say, I congratulate myself, on the deep <lb/>
interest which is shown in the North-West this <lb/>
year, because, when I came first in 1887 and in <lb/>
subsequent years to advocate their cause, my <lb/>
words fell on languid ears; but each year this <lb/>
House has taken more interest in the North-West, <lb/>
and I think nothing could be of more happy omen <lb/>
than this fact. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>. The hon. gentleman (Mr. Davin) <lb/>
seems to think that until he came here no one took <lb/>
any interest in the North-West, but the fact is <lb/>
that the North-West owes whatever it possesses <lb/>
of responsible government to the wisdom and <lb/>
prescience of my hon. friend from East York (Mr. <lb/>
Mackenzie), who, in 1875, proposed a measure <lb/>
which contained the germ of all the representative <lb/>
institutions the North-West has to-day. The hon. <lb/>
gentleman may learn, what he evidently does not <lb/>
know, that for many ears gentlemen on this side <lb/>
of the House pressed upon the Government, by <lb/>
speech and by vote, the necessity of extending the <lb/>
representative principle here to the North-West <lb/>
of responsible government: and I am sure that, <lb/>

<cb/>

whatever doubts and fears we may have had before, <lb/>
we may now congratulate ourselves upon the <lb/>
inestimable blessings conferred upon the whole of <lb/>
Canada, upon the North-West, and upon ourselves, <lb/>
in having introduced my hon. friend to this House. <lb/>
He says in the North-West there has been an <lb/>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">immigration d'élite</hi>, and we here have the <hi rendition="simple:italic">élite</hi> <lb/>
    of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">élite</hi>, and we may judge what is <lb/>
left there by the sample which they send us. <lb/>
But the hon. gentleman is quite right. So far as <lb/>
the emigration from Ontario is concerned, and I <lb/>
presume it is the same from the other Provinces, <lb/>
there can be no doubt that by a process of natural <lb/>
selection they have got amongst the best and most <lb/>
energetic men that were to be found among us; and <lb/>
I have no doubt whatever that that immigration, <lb/>
taken on the whole, is of a very superior character
    <lb/>just as, upon the same principles, the upper Pro<lb break="no"/>vince was originally settled. I am old enough to re<lb break="no"/>member the character of those settlers, at least of <lb/>
some of them, living at an extreme old age, and I <lb/>
can bear testimony that a great many of the earlier <lb/>
settlers who came to this country at a period when <lb/>
it was very different from what it is to-day, when <lb/>
there was no assisted emigration, no steamships, <lb/>
no cleared lands, when bears and Indians were <lb/>
supposed to be the attractions of that country, <lb/>
were men of the first rank. Those circumstances <lb/>
indicate of themselves that the early settlers were <lb/>
men of superior force of character, men, I am afraid, <lb/>
we must confess with humility, better, upon the av<lb break="no"/>erage, than many of their sons and grandsons are. So, <lb/>
in degree, though not to the same extent, is the char<lb break="no"/>acter of the immigration to the North-West; and <lb/>
we must not, of course, keep such people as that in <lb/>
leading strings; we must deal with them as men of <lb/>
capacity, as men of will, as men of resolution and <lb/>
ability; and we must trust them with their own <lb/>
fortunes, confident that if they make mistakes, as <lb/>
it is they who will suffer the consequences, so they <lb/>
will be able to repair their errors. Such is the gen<lb break="no"/>eral principle upon which we ought to deal with <lb/>
them, and in that view I am disposed—not forgets <lb/>
ting that we have certain responsibilities towards <lb/>
them and towards Canada until such period as we <lb/>
give them full Provincial rights—I am disposed <lb/>
largely to listen with great respect and attention <lb/>
and deference to the decided and clearly expressed <lb/>
voice of the Territories themselves as to what is <lb/>
for their advantage. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. Perhaps an apology is due <lb/>
by me to the hon. member for West Assiniboia <lb/>
(Mr. Davin) for the insinuation I ventured to make, <lb/>
but really, if I misunderstood him, he is himself <lb/>
to blame. In the observations he made on the <lb/>
second reading of the Bill, he rather intimated that <lb/>
the representatives in the North-West Assembly <lb/>
were in the habit of disposing of public moneys <lb/>
by lot, by some system of log-rolling, to use his <lb/>
own expression, dividing it amongst them and <lb/>
expending the money in some way, being even <lb/>
driven to imagine how they could expend it. Well, I <lb/>
should have not imagined that was the way in which <lb/>
the North-West Legislative Assembly were in the <lb/>
habit of discharging their duties. But if that was <lb/>
a true and correct statement, as no doubt it was <lb/>
according to the hon. gentleman's light, he does <lb/>
not represent them to be a very high class of legis<lb break="no"/>lators. That is what I referred to; therefore, I <lb/>
think the hon. gentleman should see that I was <lb/>

<pb n="4475" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04475.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4475</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">4476</fw> 

not altogether to blame for the statement I made. <lb/>
Now, Sir, as to the new zeal that I am displaying <lb/>
in regard to the North-West. In admitting it is <lb/>
new, I hope it will be permanent, and I hope it <lb/>
will not be imprudent either, as the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man seems to imagine. But I was astonished at <lb/>
the proposition that the people of the North-West <lb/>
were not able to govern themselves; perhaps I <lb/>
    had judged the North-West too much by the <hi rendition="simple:italic">élite</hi> <lb/>
    of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">élite</hi> they had sent to this House, and not <lb/>
enough by what was left behind. When I visited <lb/>
the North-West, from what I saw of the people up <lb/>
there, I am satisfied that this House would be <lb/>
making a very great mistake indeed if they do not <lb/>
realise that they are quite competent to manage <lb/>
their own affairs, and that we ought to give them <lb/>
the power to do it, instead of keeping them in <lb/>
leading strings, and dealing out authority piece by <lb/>
piece, as if they were children. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. My hon. friend refers to the re<lb break="no"/>marks I made on the second reading. Now, Sir, <lb/>
permit me to explain that what I meant by log<lb break="no"/>rolling is a thing that any Assembly, that this <lb/>
Assembly, the hon. gentlemen around me, might <lb/>
fall into it. <lb/></p> 

<p>Some <persName ref="pers:ANON1">hon. MEMBERS</persName>. No, no. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I do not condemn them for doing <lb/>
so; but let me point out my meaning by facts. <lb/>
What did one gentleman do?—and he is not the <lb/>
least intelligent member of that Assembly, not the <lb/>
least energetic, not the man with the least ambi<lb break="no"/>tion. When he got his quotient of the sum <lb/>
divided by twenty-two, he had such difficulty in <lb/>
knowing how to spend that money that he took a <lb/>
legal opinion as to whether he could not spend it <lb/>
on sidewalks for his own town, and he spent it on <lb/>
sidewalks. Another gentleman, a member of that <lb/>
Assembly, told me frankly that as the roads and <lb/>
bridges had all been made in his district, he did not <lb/>
know what to do with the money. As the hon. <lb/>
member for West Durham (Mr. Blake) pointed out, <lb/>
when you have money administered by an Assembly <lb/>
like that, you will have it expended in one quarter <lb/>
where it is not needed, whereas the money of an<lb break="no"/>other man will be expended in another quarter <lb/>
where it is direly needed. As the hon. member <lb/>
pointed out, it would sometime be the proper way <lb/>
to govern the country, and best for the whole of <lb/>
it, that the great portion of the sum should be ex<lb break="no"/>pended in one district. Suppose in one district <lb/>
there is absolute need of a first class bridge, <lb/>
the road of which would serve not merely that dis<lb break="no"/>trict, but half a dozen districts; is it not clear that <lb/>
the half a dozen districts would be better served if <lb/>
all the money that is given to the most of them, or <lb/>
the greater portion of that money, were to be spent <lb/>
in the one district where the work that related to <lb/>
the whole of them belongs? Now, I was not <lb/>
ignorant of the fact that the hon. member for <lb/>
West Durham and his colleagues have taken in the <lb/>
past an interest in the North-West. I have <lb/>
listened, from that gallery, to some of his very <lb/>
brief speeches on that subject; I have listened to <lb/>
that compressed and caustic eloquence of which <lb/>
he is master, when dealing with the North-West, <lb/>
and, of course, I have been proportionately struck. <lb/>
But I have noticed this in the speakers on the <lb/>
Opposition side of the House—although the hon. <lb/>
gentleman from North York (Mr. Mackenzie) did <lb/>
inaugurate a certain policy that is even now <lb/>

<cb/>

bearing fruit—I have noticed that there was not <lb/>
the same evidence of insight as to the needs of <lb/>
the North-West, and as to those things that <lb/>
are necessary to give to the North-West pro<lb break="no"/>gress, that I have seen on the side of the House to <lb/>
which I belong, since the right hon. gentleman and <lb/>
his friends came into power. I do not forget those <lb/>
long and interminable speeches of the hon. member <lb/>
for West Durham, I do not forget all the eloquence <lb/>
that has been lavished upon the North-West; but, <lb/>
Sir, I say this, "nevertheless and notwith<lb break="no"/>standing," to use a locution of which the hon. <lb/>
gentleman is fond, that when I came forward in <lb/>
1887 and proposed a motion to give the North-<lb break="yes"/>West responsible government, the Opposition <lb/>
benches were dumb—I got no support from <lb/>
them whatever. I got no support from the <lb/>
hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy). <lb/>
At that time he was not enlightened, at that time <lb/>
his eyes were not open, at that time he was in the <lb/>
gall of bitterness, in respect to true views regard<lb break="no"/>ing our great western country; but now his eyes <lb/>
are open, and he thoroughly understands the <lb/>
wants of the North-West. I am very glad of <lb/>
it; I do not care whether he assists me or I assist <lb/>
him; I do not care who does the work provided the <lb/>
work is done. For there is much work to be done <lb/>
for the North-West. I am sure that I am express<lb break="no"/>ing the belief of every hon. gentleman who listens <lb/>
to me when I say that there is, to-day, more inte<lb break="no"/>rest in this House in the North-West than there <lb/>
was in 1887. I do not say it is due to the humble <lb/>
voice— <lb/></p> 

<p>Some <persName ref="pers:ANON1">hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Hear, hear. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I do not say it is due to what my <lb/>
    hon. friend from West Durham called the <hi rendition="simple:italic">élite</hi> of <lb/>
    the <hi rendition="simple:italic">élite</hi>, or the <hi rendition="simple:italic">creme de la créme</hi>—I do not suppose <lb/>
that, Sir, as the hon. member for West Durham seems <lb/>
to think. And let me congratulate the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for West Durham, and congratulate the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, on the genial manner in which he has dealt <lb/>
with this question to-day. The North-West, that <lb/>
vast country, with its great capacities, its inspiring <lb/>
possibilities, has acted on his imagination and on <lb/>
his heart, and I never heard him speak more genial<lb break="no"/>ly; because, Sir, I sometimes think that that hon. <lb/>
gentleman, so superior, so learned, is not merely the <lb/>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">créme de la créme</hi>, but he is the cream of tartar as <lb/>
well. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WATS2">Mr. WATSON</persName>. We are all gratified to listen <lb/>
to the hon. gentleman. He says the hon. member <lb/>
for West Durham (Mr. Blake) is cream of tartar; <lb/>
probably it is because he makes a fizz when united <lb/>
with another mixture. The hon. member for West <lb/>
Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) is a kind of mixture, and it <lb/>
is very difficult for the House to understand what <lb/>
he wants and what were the requirements of the <lb/>
North-West from the hon. gentleman's speeches. <lb/>
He delivers himself on every occasion on any <lb/>
matter connected with the North-West that comes <lb/>
up for discussion. Only a short time ago, he told <lb/>
us that he had in 1887 and 1888, advocated a full <lb/>
measure of responsible government for the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, but that, after going home and visiting his <lb/>
constituents, he found out he had made a mistake, <lb/>
and he found only one man in his constituency in <lb/>
favor of such a step. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. That is so. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WATS2">Mr. WATSON</persName>. Still the hon. gentleman calls <lb/>
for responsible government for the North-West, <lb/>

<pb n="4477" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04477.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4477</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 6, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">4478</fw> 

when, on his own admission, the people do not <lb/>
want it. I would not have said anything on this <lb/>
question except for a reflection passed on the <lb/>
Province of Manitoba. The First Minister stated <lb/>
that nearly all the representations he had received <lb/>
from the North-West were to the effect that the <lb/>
people would be in a very much worse position <lb/>
than they occupied to-day if they were governed <lb/>
by the sort of Government they had in Manitoba. <lb/>
I consider that a reflection on the Government of <lb/>
that Province, whoever may be the right hon. <lb/>
gentleman's informants, whether members of this <lb/>
House or persons outside the House; and as a <lb/>
resident of Manitoba, and I know I am speaking <lb/>
the opinion of the great majority of that Province, <lb/>
I say the people are thankful we have a respon<lb break="no"/>sible Local Legislature there, and the right hon. <lb/>
gentleman no doubt would much prefer to have a <lb/>
Council similar to that in the North-West, and one <lb/>
subject to his dictation. But we have a Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture which has protested against the unjust acts <lb/>
of the right hon. gentleman, and we are now <lb/>
reaping the benefits of responsible government. I <lb/>
do not think we should consider the individual <lb/>
acts of any member of the North-West Council <lb/>
to-day, as has been done by the hon. member <lb/>
for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin). It is sufficient <lb/>
for us to know that the Council is Composed <lb/>
of an able body of men, as has been admitted by <lb/>
the hon. member for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin), <lb/>
and I am satisfied although I do not know the in<lb break="no"/>dividual members of that body, that the represen<lb break="no"/>tations of the North-West Council should have <lb/>
more weight in this House than the views of an <lb/>
individual member from the North-West; and if <lb/>
the North-West Council recommend to this House <lb/>
the granting of responsible government to that <lb/>
country, it is in the interest of this House to con<lb break="no"/>sider the advisability of granting it, and if they <lb/>
object to having legal advisers appointed, who <lb/>
must have certain weight in the Assembly, the <lb/>
gentlemen composing that Council are men who <lb/>
are quite competent to elect men who are able to <lb/>
fulfil the positions of the legal advisers. I have <lb/>
no doubt that if the North-West Council and the <lb/>
people, through their representatives in this <lb/>
House, were listened to by this Parliament, and if <lb/>
it would act on their advice, we would do very <lb/>
nearly what is right for the North-West. They <lb/>
are more interested in its welfare than are people <lb/>
2,000 miles away. We should endeavor, as nearly <lb/>
as possible, to carry out the wishes of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Council, and I repeat, if they wish to have <lb/>
the legal experts abolished, this should be done. <lb/>
In the North-West, as in Manitoba, we must have <lb/>
minorities, and the hon. member for Provencher <lb/>
(Mr. LaRivière) represents a class that think <lb/>
they must have all the rights and privileges which <lb/>
the majority possess in the Province and in the <lb/>
Legislature. We must expect these things to oc<lb break="no"/>cur, but the rights of the majority under the <lb/>
British North America Act must prevail, and <lb/>
those constituting the minority must submit to <lb/>
such legislation as is carried by the majority. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man says that no doubt I would prefer to have <lb/>
Manitoba governed as the North-West Territories <lb/>
are governed, because it would bring the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince more under the power of the Government. <lb/>
The hon. gentleman must have forgotten that the <lb/>

<cb/>

Government of which I was a member gave the <lb/>
constitution to the Province of Manitoba. The <lb/>
hon. gentleman might, if he had looked back at <lb/>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">Hansard</hi> of that day, have found that when I pro<lb break="no"/>posed there should be two representatives from <lb/>
that Province in this House, the proposal was op<lb break="no"/>posed by hon. gentlemen opposite, on the ground <lb/>
that the population of the Province did not au<lb break="no"/>thorise the returning of such a number, and I was <lb/>
laughed at when I said that I wanted more than <lb/>
one to come, as one would be lonely coming such a <lb/>
long distance. It is quite true, what the hon. <lb/>
member for West Durham (Mr. Blake) has said, <lb/>
that the credit of giving representative institu<lb break="no"/>tions to that Province is to a certain extent due to <lb/>
the Government of which the hon. member for <lb/>
East York (Mr. Mackenzie) was the head. But <lb/>
the hon. gentleman must not deprive me of my <lb/>
four lambs from the North-West, the four repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives from the North-West, and the fact that <lb/>
representation was given to the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories by the Government of which I was a member. <lb/>
But, speaking in regard to this measure now under <lb/>
consideration, the discussion has gone on as if we were <lb/>
settling a new constitution for the North-West, as if <lb/>
we were applying ourselves to the remodelling of <lb/>
that whole system. If that were so, it would <lb/>
require more consideration than can possibly be <lb/>
given to the subject at this period of the Session, <lb/>
and it must be remembered that this Bill was <lb/>
introduced for the purpose of making such amend<lb break="no"/>ments as were wanted for the present, and not for <lb/>
the purpose of arranging a new constitution for the <lb/>
North-Test, as when we were settling the Quebec <lb/>
resolutions giving a constitution to the Dominion <lb/>
of Canada. It is impossible that we can endeavor <lb/>
in the discussion of this Bill, which is a practical <lb/>
one, to discuss it with any such view. In order to <lb/>
do justice to the measure, we would be kept here <lb/>
for weeks and weeks. And, therefore, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment must either ask the House to take such pro<lb break="no"/>visions as are unobjectionable and adopt them for <lb/>
the nonce, for this Session, or we must ask the <lb/>
House to support the majority, or we must with<lb break="no"/>draw the Bill. We cannot set to work and settle <lb/>
now a new constitution for the North- West. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>. The right hon. gentleman is <lb/>
quite correct in the two statements of fact he has <lb/>
made. It is quite true that the right hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man gave to Manitoba its present popular Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion; it is also true that the right hon. gentleman <lb/>
gave the North-West Territories their representa<lb break="no"/>tion in the House of Commons, and obtained his <lb/>
four lambs, as he called them, but I prefer to call <lb/>
them sheep, and I will not say of what color. <lb/>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">Revenons à nos moutons</hi>. I should like to tell <lb/>
the reason why the right hon. gentleman gave <lb/>
popular institutions to Manitoba, and gave repre<lb break="no"/>sentation in this House to the North-West <lb/>
Territories. That supervened which generally does <lb/>
supervene before a Tory reform. There was a <lb/>
rebellion first. The right hon. gentleman gave the <lb/>
people of Manitoba a paternal Constitution; he sent <lb/>
up there a Lieutenant Governor, who never got into <lb/>
the country; and an alien Council, which could not <lb/>
get in either. The people rose in rebellion against <lb/>
him; and then he came down here and gave them, <lb/>
forsooth, provincial rights. And he now claims <lb/>
credit for having given that which they obtained <lb/>
at the point of the bayonet. So much for Manitoba. <lb/>

<pb n="4479" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-06_Page_04479.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4479</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">4480</fw> 

Then as to the Territories. Year after year we <lb/>
in this House, sitting on this side of the House, <lb/>
inveighed against the absence of representation <lb/>
from the Territories. We pointed out their distance, <lb/>
their remoteness, the murmurs of complaint which <lb/>
came from that country, and we said it was abso<lb break="no"/>lutely essential there should be a safety-valve, at <lb/>
all events, for them, and guidance for ourselves. <lb/>
We did not indeed know then how extensive, or <lb/>
expansive, or expensive,that safety-valve would be; <lb/>
but we called for a safety-valve for them, for light <lb/>
and information for ourselves. We asked for it, <lb/>
we called for it, we pressed for it, we moved for it. <lb/>
Deaf ears were presented to us on those benches. <lb/>
Another rebellion came, and the year after his <lb/>
second rebellion the hon. gentleman gave repre<lb break="no"/>sentation to the North-West Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. I understand the member for <lb/>
North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) to say, that there <lb/>
have been petitions presented from the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories asking for some changes in the <lb/>
system of Government. I think it is material <lb/>
that the Committee should know what were the <lb/>
views submitted to the Government by the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of the North-West Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. The papers were brought <lb/>
down, and are now before the House. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Are they printed? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. They are printed in the <lb/>
proceedings of the North-West Assembly. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. BLAKE</persName>. Are they printed in both lan<lb break="no"/>guages? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. I am afraid not. The Bill <lb/>
of the Minister of the Interior of last Session, <lb/>
which was submitted to the Legislative Assembly, <lb/>
was criticised by them, and they say that section <lb/>
10 of the Bill should be amended, so as to dis<lb break="no"/>pense with the sitting of legal experts in the <lb/>
Assembly. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. How does the Minister pro<lb break="no"/>pose to get over that? I presume it is the ex<lb break="no"/>pression of opinion of the people of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories. I am glad to have the question <lb/>
introduced by my hon. friend from North Simcoe <lb/>
(Mr. McCarthy). I can congratulate him on his <lb/>
increasing light, for I think it is only a year ago <lb/>
since he professed to be a Tory of the Tories. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. I am still. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. At any rate, the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man is repudiating some of the old Tory principles. <lb/>
I think we ought give effect to this expression of <lb/>
opinion of the people of the North-West. <lb/></p> 

<p>Progress reported. <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
<head rendition="simple:centre">MESSAGE FROM HIS EXCELLENCY—SUP<lb break="no"/>PLEMENTARY ESTIMATES.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName> presented a Message from His <lb/>
Excellency the Governor General. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName> read the Message, as follows:— <lb/></p> 

        <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"></quote>

<p>STANLEY OF PRESTON. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Governor General transmits to the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons, Supplementary Estimates of sums required for the <lb/>
service of the Dominion, for the year ending 30th June <lb/>
1891: and, in accordance with the provisions of "The <lb/>
British North America Act 1867," he recommends these <lb/>
Estimates to the House of Commons. <lb/></p> 

<p>GOVERNMENT HOUSE, <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">OTTAWA, 6th May, 1890. <lb/></p>

<cb/>

<p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName> moved that the Message of His <lb/>
Excellency and the Estimates be referred to Com<lb break="no"/>mittee of Supply. <lb/></p> 

<p>Motion agreed to. <lb/></p>
    </div>
        <div type="debate">

<head rendition="simple:centre">FIRST READING.</head>

<p>Bill (No. 151) respecting Railways—(Sir John <lb/>
A. Macdonald.) <lb/></p> 

<p>It being six o'clock, the Speaker left the Chair. <lb/></p> 
        </div>
    <div type="debate">
<head rendition="simple:centre">After Recess.</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">WAYS AND MEANS—THE TARIFF.</head>

<p>House again resolved itself into Committee of <lb/>
Ways and Means. <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
<head rendition="simple:centre">(In the Committee.)</head> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. I have moved the House into <lb/>
Committee of Ways and Means for the purpose of <lb/>
moving an amendment to item 5 in the Tariff Bill, <lb/>
which now reads as follows:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Animals, living, viz.: cattle, sheep and hogs, 30 per <lb/>
    cent. <hi rendition="simple:italic">ad valorem</hi>." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
<p>I desire to take out the word "hogs," and to make <lb/>
another item, as follows:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Live hogs, 2 cents per lb." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
<p>The object of this is to equalise the duty on the <lb/>
live hog with the duty of 3 cents or 1 1/2 cents per lb. <lb/>
on the dead product of the hog, so as to prevent <lb/>
the live animal being imported and made up into <lb/>
meat here in competition with our own live hogs, <lb/>
at a lesser rate of duty than that imposed on <lb/>
the dead meat. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MITC2">Mr. MITCHELL</persName>. I presume that the hon. <lb/>
Minister makes this change with the view of carry<lb break="no"/>ing out the National Policy, and encouraging the <lb/>
Canadian farmer. Now, as there is a certain class <lb/>
of hog that is not raised in this country, I mean <lb/>
the hog that makes the clear and mess pork, does <lb/>
he not think that it would be more in accord with <lb/>
the course decided upon when the duty was reduced <lb/>
from 6 cents to 3 cents per lb. on clear and mess <lb/>
pork, if we were to make a distinction between the <lb/>
hogs that make mess pork and the hogs that make <lb/>
prime and prime mess? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. I imagine 2 <lb/>
cents per pound live weight would be an enormous <lb/>
increase in the heavy duty which the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man originally proposed. The average value of a <lb/>
hog could hardly exceed $6 or $8, so that this <lb/>
would be a duty of at least 50 or 60 per cent. It <lb/>
appears to me that this is practically a prohibitory <lb/>
duty, and a mischievous duty in every sense, inas<lb break="no"/>much as it will probably lead to a suspension of <lb/>
trade, and expose our people to retaliation. Now, as <lb/>
far as the Province of Ontario is concerned, the <lb/>
practical result of this tax would be that, as we im<lb break="no"/>ported two live swine, our farmers would receive <lb/>
a protection to the extent of $4. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. Then we would not get a large <lb/>
increase of duty in that case. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MITC2">Mr. MITCHELL</persName>. No; but you would inflict <lb/>
serious charges on the lumbermen. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. You may pos<lb break="no"/>sibly interfere materially with trade in other <lb/>
quarters. Of all that the hon. gentleman has said[...] <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>