<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1903-07-24"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1903-07-24">24 July 1903</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Ninth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
          <date when="1903"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
          <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="7925" to="7928"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-24_Page_07925.html"/>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-24_Page_07927.xml"/>
               </item>
    
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-26">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-09-26">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-24_Page_07925">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-24_Page_07925.jpg"/>
         
      </surface>
      
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-24_Page_07927">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-24_Page_07927.jpg"/></surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="7925" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-24_Page_07925.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">7295</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">7296</fw>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CORRESPONDENCE WITH THE GOV<lb break="no"/>ERNMENT OF THE NORTH-WEST<lb/>TERRITORIES.<lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName> 
     <lb/>(Hon. Clifford Sifton). Referring to the re<lb break="no"/>quest made by the leader of the opposition<lb/>for a further return in reference to cpies<lb/>of correspondence with the North-west gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and the members thereof, on the<lb/>question of provincial autonomy, I beg now<lb/>to present a supplementary return to the<lb/>Order which was passed, and in complian<lb break="no"/>ce with which a return was presented to<lb/>this House some time ago. I may say to<lb/>my hon. friend (Mr. Borden, Halifax) that<lb/>there are some of the letters which were<lb/>mentioned in the list which he read to the<lb/>House which cannot be found. There<lb/>were letters which passed between A. L.<lb/>
       
       
   
   
            <cb/>
           
           
     
     Sifton and myself, which were upon the 
     <lb/>file that I had in the council chamber and<lb/>which have been mislaid. As soon as that<lb/>was ascertained, I telegraphed to the North<lb break="no"/>west government to send down copies of<lb/>the letters from their files. They will be<lb/>here probably in a day or two.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). I may say 
     <lb/>that I have a print of some correspondence<lb/>from the North-west Territories' legislative<lb/>assembly which contains copies of these<lb/>letters, and I can furnish it to the hon.<lb/>gentleman if it is desired that they should<lb/>be printed at once.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>Then there are the following letters : one<lb/>dated March 15th, 1902, from Mr. Haultain<lb/>to Sir Wilfrid Laurier : one dated March<lb/>18th, 1902, from Sir Wilfrid Laurier to Mr.<lb/>Haultain, which cannot be found at the<lb/>present time. Sir Wilfrid informs me that<lb/>he thinks these can be got, but the result<lb/>of an inquiry from his secretary brought<lb/>the reply that they could not be found.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). I have copies 
     <lb/>of all these that are mentioned on the list<lb/>that I read to the House, and which can<lb/>be furnished for the purpose of being print<lb break="no"/>ed. I think they are probably correct as<lb/>they were printed by command of the ter<lb break="no"/>ritorial legislature.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>I wish to mention the letters that are not<lb/>in the list as presented so that there can<lb/>be no mistake. There was a further letter<lb/>from Mr. Haultain to myself, dated 2nd<lb/>April, 1902, and another letter dated De-<lb break="yes"/>center 17th, from A. L. Sifton to myself.<lb/>There is a letter dated January 31st, 1903,<lb/>from Mr. Haultain to myself : one dated<lb/>February 9th, from Mr. McGee to Mr. Haul-<lb break="yes"/>tain : one dated April 15th, from Mr. Haul-<lb break="yes"/>tain to myself : one dated April 17th, from<lb/>Mr. Haultain to Mr. Fielding, and one dated<lb/>July 25th, from Mr. Pelletier to Mr. Forget.<lb/>These letters have not been found up to the<lb/>present time, although the clerks in charge<lb/>of the files have been busily engaged search<lb break="no"/>ing for them. They appear to have been<lb/>mislaid : possibly they may have been tak<lb break="no"/>en to council. There may be some mistake<lb/>about the dates which were transmitted to<lb/>my hon. friend, and these mistakes may<lb/>result in there being letters which are ac<lb break="no"/>tually on the file, but which are not in<lb break="no"/>dicated by the exact dates. For instance,<lb/>there is one letter which is stated to have<lb/>been by myself from Mr. Haultain,<lb/>by I think there must be some mistake<lb/>about that. It is supposed to have been re<lb break="no"/>ceived while I was away, but neither my<lb/>private secretary nor any one else in the<lb/>department has any record of it being re<lb break="no"/>ceived.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). If the hon. 
     <lb/>gentleman would send his secretary to look<lb/>over the papers I have, I think he could<lb/>
     


            
            <pb n="7927" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-24_Page_07927.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">7297</fw> <fw type="dateline">JULY 24, 1903</fw>
               
               get copies of all these which are referred<lb/>
               to in the list which I read to the House.</p>
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>.<lb/>
               I shall do that, and if there are any that<lb/>
               are not comprised within this return we<lb/>
               will have them presented in the form of a<lb/>
               supplementary return, so that it may be<lb/>
               complete. In the meantime, I will leave<lb/>
               this return on the Table of the House.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>