<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1891-08-14" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1891-08-14">14 August 1891</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, First Session</title>.
<date when="1891"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="3902" to="3948"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03901.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03903.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03905.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03907.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03909.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03911.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03913.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03915.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03917.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03919.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03921.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03923.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03925.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03927.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03929.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03931.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03933.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03935.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03937.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03939.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03941.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03943.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03945.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03947.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-10">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-10">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03901"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03901.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03903"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03903.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03905"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03905.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03907"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03907.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03909"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03909.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03911"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03911.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03913"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03913.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03915"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03915.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03917"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03917.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03919"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03919.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03921"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03921.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03923"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03923.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03925"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03925.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03927"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03927.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03929"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03929.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03931"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03931.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03933"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03933.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03935"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03935.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03937"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03937.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03939"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03939.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03941"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03941.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03943"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03943.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03945"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03945.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03947"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03947.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="3901" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03901.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3901</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 14, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">3902</fw>

<head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES ACT AMEND<lb break="no"/>MENT.</head> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName> moved second reading of Bill <lb/>
(No. 126) to amend the Acts respecting the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. This Bill, as far as it goes, is a <lb/>
good Bill, and will meet certain desires of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of the North-West Territories, but at the same <lb/>
time it leaves a good deal undone that many of us <lb/>
in the North-West would like to see done. When <lb/>
we go into Committee I intend to move the addi<lb break="no"/>tion of a clause to the following effect:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>Section 7 of the amending Act is hereby repealed and <lb/>
the followmg substituted therefor:— <lb/></p> 

<p>The persons qualified to vote at an election for the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Assembly shall be the male British subiects by birth <lb/>
or naturalization (other than unenfranchised Indians and <lb/>
members of the North-West Mounted Police) who have <lb/>
full attained the age of 21 years, and so on. <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>It will be very important to have that clause <lb/>
inserted, which will prevent the members of the <lb/>
North-West Mounted Police voting for candidates <lb/>
for the Assembly. Take the constituency of North <lb/>
Regina, and at the last voting, Jelly had 227 votes <lb/>
and Brown had 135 votes, and there were 80 police <lb/>
votes polled for Jelly, so that Jelly won the election <lb/>
by a very small majority of the civil vote. If Brown <lb/>
had had a few more votes, the police vote would <lb/>
have decided the election, and I think that is very <lb/>
undesirable and creates a great deal of ill-feeling <lb/>
that the constituency should be watered by a vote <lb/>
that is not permanent, because the members of the <lb/>
force are moved from one place to another, have no <lb/>
special interest in the place, and have no reason for <lb/>
devoting their attention to the matters which might <lb/>
affect legislation in that Assembly. I need hardly <lb/>
say that I do not approve of that standpoint in <lb/>
politics which looks to the United States as having <lb/>
everything superior to ourselves, as if we had not <lb/>
as great natural advantages as they have, and as if <lb/>
we could not hope to build up as great a nation as <lb/>
they have built up: but at the same time there is <lb/>
no reason why we should not learn something from <lb/>
what has been done in the United States, and I <lb/>
should have been glad if this Bill had contained <lb/>
some things which it does not contain. However, <lb/>

<pb n="3903" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03903.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3903</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3904</fw> 

this Bill goes a great deal further in the direction <lb/>
of giving the Territorial Assembly the mastery of <lb/>
North-West affairs than any previous Bill. For <lb/>
instance, under this Bill the Assembly will have <lb/>
power to deal with its own elections, and there is <lb/>
a clause that gives the Assembly the power of de<lb break="no"/>ciding other important matters. I consider that <lb/>
the principle we should go upon is to give that <lb/>
Assembly, as far as we can, the power of dealing <lb/>
with all things which the British North America <lb/>
Act places within provincial control, always except<lb break="no"/>ing the power of borrowing money which the people <lb/>
do not desire. I think that a great deal more might <lb/>
with propriety and with great advantage to the <lb/>
North-West be placed in the hands of the Lieute<lb break="no"/>nant Governor and the Assembly. For instance, I <lb/>
have been pressing on the attention of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and of the Hon. Mr. Carling the propriety of <lb/>
placing funds at the disposal of the North-West <lb/>
Government to enable them to deal with immigration. <lb/>
There is no reason why a sum should not be given <lb/>
to the North-West Assembly to enable them to <lb/>
supplement the action of the Dominion Government <lb/>
in bringing immigrants into the North-West. The <lb/>
Dominion Government very properly takes control <lb/>
of the immigration for the whole of this country, but <lb/>
in addition to that the different provinces put forth <lb/>
exertions of their own. British Columbia can put <lb/>
forth exertions of its own, so can Manitoba, so can <lb/>
Ontario, and so can all the provinces, because they <lb/>
get a lump sum paid to them by the Dominion <lb/>
which is based on certain calculations. Probably <lb/>
we may have the census returns in our hands be <lb/>
fore we get through with this Bill, and I believe <lb/>
that, if you take the population of the North-West <lb/>
Territories and the fact that we have no public <lb/>
debt whatever and take all the circumstances into <lb/>
account, you will find that we are entitled to a far <lb/>
larger sum than we receive at present from the <lb/>
Dominion treasury. Therefore, there is nothing <lb/>
unreasonable in asking that a sum shall be placed <lb/>
at our disposal to enable us to put forth our energies <lb/>
for the encouragement of immigration. A few days <lb/>
ago, I was speaking with a gentleman who had <lb/>
been up in the territories looking at the develop<lb break="no"/>ment of the country in the interests of his friends <lb/>
in the old world. He said he was told in Winni<lb break="no"/>peg, that the country near Regina was barren. <lb/>
Now, no matter whether you go to Alberta or to <lb/>
Assiniboia or the Saskatchewan, you will find the <lb/>
country is rich in farming lands, and Mr. Duncan <lb/>
McIntyre and Mr. Angus, who have visited the <lb/>
delta of the Nile, found the same character of de<lb break="no"/>posit in the Regina basin as they found there. <lb/>
Yet this gentleman was told that there was <lb/>
nothing but barrenness around Regina. We, <lb/>
therefore, ask that there should be at the <lb/>
disposal of the Assembly power of action and <lb/>
amounts to enable them to have immigration <lb/>
agents, some from the Saskatchewan, some from <lb/>
Assiniboia and some from Alberta, so that they may <lb/>
go either to Dakota, or to England, Ireland or Scot<lb break="no"/>land, or to German or Scandinavia, and to sup<lb break="no"/>plement the work of the general Dominion agents <lb/>
in pointing out the advantages of the different <lb/>
North-West Territories. Now, I will call the <lb/>
attention of the House to what is done, and has <lb/>
been done in the states, when making territories. <lb/>
When Minnesota was organized into a territory <lb/>
on 3rd March, 1849, it had a population, accord<lb break="no"/>ing to the census of 1850, of only 6,077, con<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

sisting in the main of French Métis in the employ<lb break="no"/>ment of the American Fur Company. When <lb/>
Dakota Territory was organized, which took place <lb/>
on 2nd March, 1861, the population amounted to <lb/>
4,837. Montana, which was lifted to the position <lb/>
of a territory on 20th May, l864, had only a popu<lb break="no"/>lation of 20,595 in 1870. Wyoming. which was <lb/>
organized on 25th July, 1808, had only a popula<lb break="no"/>tion of 9,000 odd in 1870. Now, if you look at the <lb/>
progress they have made you will find it set forth <lb/>
by the following figures:— <lb/></p> 

<table>
    <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1880.</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1890.</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Montana ............... .. .</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">39,159</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">132,139</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Wyoming ......... . .. .. .</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">20,789</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">60,705</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Minnesota ................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">780,773</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,301,826</cell></row>
    <row><cell>North Dakota ........... . . .</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">36, 909</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">182,719</cell></row>
    <row><cell>South Dakota ..... . .......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">98,268</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">328,808</cell></row>
</table>

<p>We know now, as a fact, that the attractions of <lb/>
the North-West of Canada are greater than the <lb/>
attractions of those places. If you take the North-<lb break="yes"/>West of Canada you will find that, compared with <lb/>
any of those territories, some of which have since <lb/>
become states, in farming land, in forest, in mines, <lb/>
in rivers, our North-West, in most all those points, <lb/>
are richer than the states I have mentioned. Now, <lb/>
I will call the attention of the Government to what <lb/>
has been done for a territory in the United States. <lb/>
It is given a governor, judges and executive <lb/>
officers appointed, and salaries paid by the Federal <lb/>
Government at Washington—that we do: a legis<lb break="no"/>lature chosen by the people—that we do; federal <lb/>
appropriations for legislative expenses for a session <lb/>
of 60 days, public buildings, and military and ter<lb break="no"/>ritorial roads—that we practically do: lands <lb/>
for schools and universities, one-eighteenth <lb/>
of the area of the territory—we have lands <lb/>
for schools, but no land has been set apart as <lb/>
yet for a university. Last year I was a member <lb/>
of a body that met together, persons who were <lb/>
supposed to have some fitness for speaking on edu<lb break="no"/>cational subjects, and we passed a resolution which <lb/>
I think was sent. to the Minister of the Interior; <lb/>
we passed a munber of resolutions which, I fancy, <lb/>
the secretary of the school board, Mr. James <lb/>
Brown, sent to the Government, in favour of having <lb/>
land at once set apart for a university in the terri<lb break="no"/>tories. I will say that that cannot too soon be <lb/>
done. Now, that is what we do not do, and I say <lb/>
it is a thing that should be done. The United <lb/>
States make land grants to the territory for 1,800 <lb/>
miles of railway, to be organized and controlled by <lb/>
the Legislature. And what is the advantage of that? <lb/>
At the present moment, in the State of Minnesota, <lb/>
at 3 per cent; on the gross earnings, those rail<lb break="no"/>ways, organized by means of such help as that, <lb/>
now return an income of $600,000 per anmun to <lb/>
the treasury of the state. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TISD1">Mr. TISDALE</persName>. Do I understand the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman to say that in the organization of a terri<lb break="no"/>tory they specially set apart lands, of which the <lb/>
Assembly of the territory have control, for railway <lb/>
purposes? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I do. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TISD1">Mr. TISDALE</persName>. In what territory have they <lb/>
given it? If it is so, I am informed otherwise. I <lb/>
merely want the hon. gentleman to name the terri<lb break="no"/>tory. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I will name the territory—Min<lb break="no"/>nesota. <lb/></p>
    
    <p><persName ref="pers:TISD1">Mr. TISDALE</persName>. When it was a territory?</p>


<pb n="3905" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03905.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3905</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 14, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">3906</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Yes. <lb/></p>
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:TISD1">Mr. TISDALE</persName>. And in the others, Wyoming <lb/>
and Montana? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. When Minnesota was a territory <lb/>
it got 1,800 miles of railway, and after it had been <lb/>
a State for some time it got a large amount of its <lb/>
swamp lands. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TISD1">Mr. TISDALE</persName>. Was not that part of the <lb/>
Northern Pacific, a transcontinental railway? I <lb/>
understood that the only roads built through Min<lb break="no"/>nesota while it was a territory were a part of the <lb/>
United States system of railways. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. My hon. friend says he under<lb break="no"/>stands that; but all I can tell him is that his under<lb break="no"/>standing is not as sound on that matter as it usually <lb/>
is on other subjects, because he will find, if he <lb/>
looks into the history of Minnesota, which he will <lb/>
find in the Library— <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TISD1">Mr. TISDALE</persName>. What was the railway that <lb/>
received this aid? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I state, with the responsibility <lb/>
that belongs to my position here, that that was <lb/>
done, and that they are taking $600,000 a year at <lb/>
this moment, at 3 per cent., from the railways they <lb/>
themselves subsidized. Then there was a repre<lb break="no"/>sentation by delegates in Congress that bettered <lb/>
that. When we got representation we also got a <lb/>
vote. Now, there were subsequent grants, as I <lb/>
have said, to Minnesota that put it in possession of <lb/>
a third of the lands of the State. Now, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, I think that as we are giving the North-<lb break="yes"/>West a new start it would be well for the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to consider whether they should not treat <lb/>
the territories of the North-West just as you treat <lb/>
a young man when you are setting him up in the <lb/>
world, giving him something on which to trade for <lb/>
himself. At present, what we do is to vote certain <lb/>
sums for specific purposes, and we may get, I <lb/>
assume, the power to deal with this; but what we <lb/>
should do is to give them some capital on which <lb/>
they can go on for themselves; we should give <lb/>
them some of the lands in the Territories that they <lb/>
may deal with themselves, and give them a subsidy to <lb/>
be expended on immigration, and on other purposes <lb/>
that may strike them as necessary for the country, <lb/>
give them a sum in addition to what you now give <lb/>
them. I do not want to give up voting specific <lb/>
votes, but to give them a sum in addition to that <lb/>
which will enable them, to use a colloquial expres<lb break="no"/>sion, to go on their own hook in some matters, which <lb/>
will call forth the enterprise of their statesmanship. <lb/>
I think if these suggestions are adopted it will be <lb/>
found that immigration will increase, the population <lb/>
will go ahead at a greater ratio than it has in the <lb/>
past, and the territories will be more prosperous. I <lb/>
may say that the Bill is one that I think will satisfy <lb/>
the people of the North-West, qualified by the <lb/>
criticisms I have made. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. O'BRIEN</persName>. This Bill which proposes to con<lb break="no"/>fer upon the North- West Territories very important <lb/>
rights and very extensive powers, leaves untouched <lb/>
one subject which is, perhaps, if not of the greatest <lb/>
importance, of very great importance, especially in <lb/>
view of what we may hope to see realized, a great <lb/>
extension of population, of wealth, of industry and <lb/>
of enterprise, in those territories—that subject is <lb/>
the subject of education. Now, I find that the 9th <lb/>
clause of the Act which is now being amended, is <lb/>

<cb/>

not referred to at all in this amending Act. <lb/>
that clause it is enacted that: <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The Lieutenant Governor in Council shall pass all or<lb break="no"/>dinary ordinances in respect to education, but it shall <lb/>
therein always be provided that a majority of the rate<lb break="no"/>payers of any district or portion of the Territories, or of <lb/>
any less portion or subdivision thereof, by whatever name <lb/>
the same is known, may establish such schools therein as <lb/>
they think fit and make the necessary assessment and col<lb break="no"/>lection of rates therefor; and, also, that the minority of <lb/>
the ratepayers therein, whether Protestant or Roman <lb/>
Catholic, may establish separate schools therein, and in <lb/>
such case the ratepayers establishing such Protestant or <lb/>
Roman Catholic separate schools shall be liable only to <lb/>
assessments of such rates as they impose upon themselves <lb/>
in respect thereof." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>Judging from the wording of the Act and from <lb/>
there being no reference to this clause one might <lb/>
reasonably assume that it was intended that the <lb/>
power of dealing with the subject should be left in <lb/>
the hands of the Lieutenant Governor in Council. <lb/>
I understand, however, that it is contended that by <lb/>
the interpretation clause this power, herein appar<lb break="no"/>ently given only to the Lieutenant Governor in Coun<lb break="no"/>cil, is also vested in the Assembly, to which new and <lb/>
extensive powers are given. I think, even if that <lb/>
is the case, it would have been better if the Act <lb/>
had been so worded that there should be no doubt <lb/>
as to that point, but that when we are giving this <lb/>
body the power to deal with property and civil <lb/>
rights and a variety of other subjects referred to in <lb/>
the Act, this subject of education, if it were to be <lb/>
dealt with by it, should be specially mentioned. <lb/>
However, that is not the subject to which I wish <lb/>
to direct the attention of the House. This clause <lb/>
which I have read establishes in the North-West <lb/>
Territories, whether the people desire to have it or <lb/>
not, the system of separate schools. The question <lb/>
that I wish to bring before the House to-day is, <lb/>
whether this legislation we are about to pass, <lb/>
giving these territories practically provincial <lb/>
powers, should contain an enactment, which, <lb/>
whether the people like it or not, will compel <lb/>
them to establish separate schools. I use the word <lb/>
"compel" advisedly, because, although the term is <lb/>
permissive, yet we know perfectly well from experi<lb break="no"/>ence in other provinces that although the word <lb/>
"may" is used it is virtually as imperative as <lb/>
if the word "shall" was used, and therefore I <lb/>
am justified in saying that the intention of the <lb/>
clause is that there shall be in these Territories <lb/>
separate schools, and there is no option given to this, <lb/>
I will not say newly constituted body, but this body <lb/>
to which these extensive powers are given, to say <lb/>
whether they will or will not have them. In con<lb break="no"/>sequence of this restriction of the legislative power <lb/>
of this Assembly we shall have again within a very <lb/>
few years the same controversy and agitation which <lb/>
have recently occurred in Manitoba, and, we shall <lb/>
have in the North-West Territories, if I am not <lb/>
much mistaken in the temper of the people living <lb/>
there, and who may be living therewithin a few <lb/>
years, a determined effort made to get rid of this <lb/>
restriction and to assert the right to say whether or <lb/>
not they will have separate schools; and they may <lb/>
go perhaps further than the people of Manitoba <lb/>
have gone, and although in the present case there <lb/>
will not be the doubt as to their power, as in the <lb/>
case in Manitoba, yet certainly we shall have the <lb/>
attempt made to assert a right to which, under all <lb/>
the circumstances, they are entitled, namely, that <lb/>
they shall, at all events, have flower to say whether <lb/>
or not separate schools may be established. I do <lb/>
not propose to enter into the question whether <lb/>

<pb n="3907" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03907.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3907</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3908</fw> 

separate schools are advisable, whether <lb/>
experiences in the various provinces, especi<lb break="no"/>ally in Ontario, where in regard to this matter <lb/>
we have had the largest experience, and where it <lb/>
has been productive of the most important results, <lb/>
would lead us to decide the question as to whether <lb/>
it was advisable or not that separate schools should <lb/>
exist in any of the provinces of the Dominion. We <lb/>
know very well what the result has been. We <lb/>
know very well that in several provinces an <lb/>
agitation in opposition to these schools has taken <lb/>
place and has generally been successful. We <lb/>
know perfectly well that if Ontario had the power <lb/>
today to say whether separate schools should be <lb/>
abolished or not there would be a very strong ex<lb break="no"/>pression on the part of the majority that separate <lb/>
schools should be abolished. I do not speak of the <lb/>
subject as having myself any dislike to religious <lb/>
education. On the contrary, as far as my personal <lb/>
feelings and convictions are concerned, I would very <lb/>
much prefer a system of education which would be <lb/>
essentially a religious system. Unfortunately, under <lb/>
the existing circumstances of the country, no pro<lb break="no"/>vince has been able to devise a plan by which such <lb/>
system could be established; and we find the <lb/>
only result of the adoption of that principle <lb/>
is, that one particular denomination has estab<lb break="no"/>lished schools, by means of which it has sought <lb/>
in various ways to extend its influence politically <lb/>
or otherwise, and has never been content to <lb/>
stand in the position in which it was placed by the <lb/>
British North America Act, but in the various <lb/>
provinces it has extended its power until in Ontario <lb/>
there is a very general determination, which to some <lb/>
extent has been carried out, that that body shall <lb/>
be compelled to revert to the position in which it <lb/>
is placed in the British North America Act. I <lb/>
shall simply content myself on the present occasion <lb/>
with contending that as regards this question of <lb/>
restriction imposed by section 9 of the present Act<lb/> 
    it should be removed, and the Assembly should be <lb/>
given power and control over education, and no <lb/>
restriction should be imposed by this legislation as <lb/>
to whether separate schools shall be established in <lb/>
the North-West Territories or not. I do not pro<lb break="no"/>pose to enter into the question as to whether it is <lb/>
advisable to have a separate school system, but I <lb/>
confine myself to the contention that this Assembly <lb/>
should have power to deal with the question. I <lb/>
go further, and say that as this Act makes no special <lb/>
reference to education, and as before very long <lb/>
there will be another opportunity of dealing with <lb/>
this question, and taking up the whole subject of <lb/>
education, which is virtually not taken up by this <lb/>
Act, and as no particular harm can result from post<lb break="no"/>poning the question for a short time, I will not <lb/>
at the present time go further than to say that <lb/>
I trust the Government will take the subject <lb/>
into its serious consideration, and will decide, <lb/>
in view of all the circumstances of the case, <lb/>
considering the views of all the provinces, con<lb break="no"/>sidering what the future of the country is likely <lb/>
to be, before next session whether or not in con<lb break="no"/>ferring these great owers, which they have con<lb break="no"/>ferred on this Assembly by this Bill, they will not <lb/>
go further, and give them perfect and absolute con<lb break="no"/>trol over education. It maybe said there are no <lb/>
petitions from the North-West Territories asking <lb/>
for this. I think we have had some evidence that <lb/>
there is a strong feeling on the subject, but even <lb/>
were there not one member from the North-West <lb/>

<cb/>

 to rise in this House and endorse the view for which <lb/>
I am contending, it must be remembered that we <lb/>
are not legislating for the comparatively small <lb/>
handful of people in the North-West Territories, <lb/>
but we are legislating for the large number we hope <lb/>
to see there within a very few years, and I think we <lb/>
may fairly assume that the Bill giving these <lb/>
sive powers is intended, although there is no limit <lb/>
stated as to the period of its duration, to remain <lb/>
in force for a very considerable period of time. <lb/>
With the powers that are given to the North-West <lb/>
Territories under this Act there will be no reason <lb/>
for giving more extensive powers or for creating <lb/>
separate provinces for, very probably, a good many <lb/>
years to come. And, Sir, what will be the posi<lb break="no"/>tion of those who may then be prepared to con<lb break="no"/>tend, as I contend now, that this subject should be <lb/>
dealt with by the Provincial Assembly? Why, <lb/>
Sir, we shall have the cry that has been raised so <lb/>
often in reference to this question, as well as to <lb/>
kindred questions in the Dominion of Canada: we <lb/>
shall have the cry that those who were in favour <lb/>
of separate schools have had them established by <lb/>
law, that they have been existing for so many <lb/>
years, that a vested right has been created in them, <lb/>
and that this right ought not to be set aside. The <lb/>
difficulty placed upon those who feel as I do on this <lb/>
question will be very greatly increased if we allow <lb/>
this period of time to elapse without removing the <lb/>
restriction imposed by the 9th section of the Act <lb/>
to which I refer. I say that for this reason this <lb/>
restriction ought to be removed before this system <lb/>
becomes finally established in the North-West Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories I think the proposition is a reasonable one; <lb/>
I think it is a proposition which the Government <lb/>
ought to accede to, and it is a preposition which I <lb/>
hope they will accede to. I hope that now when they <lb/>
are establishing this principle, giving these exten<lb break="no"/>sive powers to this Assembly, they will give them <lb/>
the power of saying whether or not there shall be <lb/>
separate schools in the territories, if they are <lb/>
to have the subject of education in their hands at <lb/>
all. I repeat again that this is a reasonable pro<lb break="no"/>position; it is a proposition which the Government <lb/>
ought to accede to, and it is a proposition which I <lb/>
hope they will accede to. However, under existing <lb/>
circumstances, I do not wish at this period of <lb/>
the session to raise a debate which probably would <lb/>
create a good deal of angry feeling, and which un<lb break="no"/>doubtedly would produce a discussion which, con<lb break="no"/>sidering the many pressing matters now before the <lb/>
House, and in the present condition of the Adminis<lb break="no"/>tration, it is desirable to avoid if possible. And <lb/>
I venture to say, in speaking on this subject, that I <lb/>
am giving expression, not only to my own opinion, <lb/>
but to the opinion of many other members of this <lb/>
House who hold the same opinion as I do in <lb/>
regard to this matter. Under these circum<lb break="no"/>stances, I do not ropose, while the present <lb/>
Act is under consideration, to offer an amend<lb break="no"/>ment myself to the Act as it now stands; but <lb/>
I tell the Government—and I say it with all seri<lb break="no"/>ousness and all determination—that unless they <lb/>
either deal with the subject now, which is the pro<lb break="no"/>per time to deal with it, when they have the Act <lb/>
efore them, or unless they will, during the recess, <lb/>
consider the question, and before the next session <lb/>
bring forard an amendment to the Act in the <lb/>
direction I think it should be amended, then I <lb/>
can tell them that they have not heard the last of <lb/>
this question, and that at a time which shall be <lb/>

<pb n="3909" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03909.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3909</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 14, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">3910</fw>
    
more convenient for raising this discussion it will <lb/>
be raised in this House, and they will be compelled <lb/>
to meet it, and to let the country understand dis<lb break="no"/>tinctly whether or not they are prepared to remove <lb/>
this restriction. I think, Sir, there is nothing else <lb/>
I need say on this question now. I think I am <lb/>
making a reasonable request; I am making a re<lb break="no"/>quest which I am very certain will be supported <lb/>
by a majority—I will not say only of those whom I <lb/>
represent—but a great majority of those who are <lb/>
represented in this House—at any rate, by the <lb/>
members from the Province of Ontario. I think <lb/>
that a similar expression of opinion would be <lb/>
given also by the electors in many other portions <lb/>
of the Dominion. The subject, of course, is one <lb/>
that is comparatively new, for all our dealings <lb/>
with the North-West Territories have been <lb/>
so far tentative, and experimental rather than <lb/>
absolute. We are now, however, going a step fur<lb break="no"/>ther. We are now giving to this Assembly powers <lb/>
which it has not hitherto possessed: and there is <lb/>
one thing which may be taken for granted, that <lb/>
with the acquisition of the new powers given under <lb/>
this Act the people of these territories will enquire <lb/>
why they should be restricted in this great and im<lb break="no"/>portant particular. It is because I think such is <lb/>
the case, and because I do not wish on a future <lb/>
occasion, when this subject comes again before the <lb/>
House for further legislation, that those who think <lb/>
as I do on this system of education should be met <lb/>
with the objection that so many years ago this <lb/>
system was established by law and that, therefore, <lb/>
a vested right is created which the Legislature should <lb/>
not now interfere with. Why, Sir, it would be <lb/>
almost fair to argue that this would come within <lb/>
the provisions of the British North America Act. <lb/>
If not in reality it would by analogy, because <lb/>
the British North America Act secured to the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces which came into Confederation whatever <lb/>
rights were enjoyed by the supporters of separate <lb/>
schools at the time of Confederation, and if we <lb/>
create new provinces out of these territories it may <lb/>
fairly be argued that the analogy of the British <lb/>
North America Act will apply, and that in creating <lb/>
new provinces and bringing them into Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion there will be something like the same rights <lb/>
guaranteed to the supporters of separate schools <lb/>
which were guaranteed to the provinces having <lb/>
separate schools before coming in under the British <lb/>
North America Act. Sir, under all these circum<lb break="no"/>stances, I think I am taking a reasonable course in <lb/>
calling the attention of the Government to this <lb/>
matter, and in telling them that unless they are <lb/>
prepared either to remove this restriction now <lb/>
when the Bill is before the House, or unless before <lb/>
next session they will make up their minds to re<lb break="no"/>move it, the subject will again be brought up, and <lb/>
brought up with perhaps not, as I may say, <lb/>
the studied moderation with which I have brought <lb/>
it forward on this occasion. I can tell the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment that the whole subject of separate schools <lb/>
will come up, and possibly a demand will be made <lb/>
in this House and supported by public opinion in <lb/>
this country which will go a great deal further <lb/>
than the moderate proposal I now submit. Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, I am not going to offer any opposition to <lb/>
the second reading of the Bill. I am not going, as I <lb/>
said, to bring forward myself a resolution on this <lb/>
subject when the Bill is in Committee; but I hope <lb/>
the Government will take the course I suggested, <lb/>
and if they do not take it, then they must be pre<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

pared at the next favourable opportunity, having <lb/>
had full time to consider this question, to state <lb/>
whether or not they will meet the proposal, which <lb/>
I think is a moderate and reasonable one. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDOWALL</persName>. Mr. Speaker, as one of the <lb/>
representatives of the territories I may say that I <lb/>
believe the people of the North-West Territories <lb/>
will be willing to accept this as a temporary mea<lb break="no"/>sure. It can be nothing else than a temporary <lb/>
measure, because it is the hope, not only of the <lb/>
people of the territories, but I believe of the people <lb/>
of all Canada, that the condition of that country <lb/>
may alter and improve so materially that by the <lb/>
end of the next three years another form of legis<lb break="no"/>lature will have to be granted, or perhaps some <lb/>
legislative divisions will have to be made in the <lb/>
Territories. Just now Parliament has been devot<lb break="no"/>ing its attention to the question of immigration, <lb/>
and should the measures taken by the Dominion <lb/>
Government prove of use, and should a large num<lb break="no"/>ber of immigrants come into the country, it is con<lb break="no"/>sidered by the people living there that the popula<lb break="no"/>tion will have increased to such an extent that it <lb/>
may be advisable to divide the territories, and to <lb/>
perhaps carve out one or two provinces. I think, <lb/>
as the territories exist just now, it would be a <lb/>
mistake to alter the conditions affecting the schools. <lb/>
I, for one, am pledged to the maintenance of sepa<lb break="no"/>rate schools at present, and when my hon. friend <lb/>
the member for Muskoka (Mr. O'Brien) warns the <lb/>
Government that if they do not next year bring in <lb/>
a Bill to place the question of schools, and the pro<lb break="no"/>hibition of separate schools, if necessary, in the <lb/>
hands of the Legislative Assembly, I may warn him <lb/>
that as one of the representatives of the territories <lb/>
I am pledged during this Parliament to oppose <lb/>
such a measure. I believe that the people of the <lb/>
North-West are very liberal in their opinions. <lb/>
The Protestants who live there have their own <lb/>
schools, and they do not in the least object to the <lb/>
Roman Catholics educating their children in the <lb/>
manner in which their conscience dictates. I believe at <lb/>
the same time that there is a very strong hope amongst <lb/>
the people of the North-West Territories that the <lb/>
children of Canada may know that there can be <lb/>
nothing very detrimental to religion in learning <lb/>
reading, and writing, and arithmetic, and other <lb/>
teachings such as that, in the common schools of the <lb/>
country. But they recognize that, as long as there <lb/>
is a strong prejudice on the part of a large section <lb/>
of the people throughout the country, arising simply <lb/>
from a good motive, it must be respected. During <lb/>
the last session of Parliament, when my hon. friend <lb/>
from North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) introduced in <lb/>
this House a measure affecting the schools of the <lb/>
North-West, he stated that the different represen<lb break="no"/>tatives of the territories did not represent the feel<lb break="no"/>ing of the people there. Well, Sir, we have had a <lb/>
general election since then. In my district there <lb/>
is not only a large number of Roman Catholics, but <lb/>
also a large number of North of Ireland Orangemen; <lb/>
there are Anglicans, Presbyterians, Methodists, <lb/>
Baptists, and adherents of almost every denomi<lb break="no"/>nation; and at every single meeting I at<lb break="no"/>tended, whether in a Roman Catholic settlement <lb/>
or an Orange one, when I was asked to state what <lb/>
course I would pursue in regard to this school <lb/>
question I boldly replied that I would pursue such <lb/>
a course as would be favourable to maintaining the <lb/>
separate schools and respecting the religious <lb/>

<pb n="3911" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03911.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">3911</fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3912</fw>

opinions of the different sections of the people. <lb/>
There is really no hardship at all to the Protestants <lb/>
of the North-West in the separate schools as they <lb/>
are at present constitued, because the present Act, <lb/>
which I presume will be continued after this Bill <lb/>
passes, provides that Protestants shall be taxed for <lb/>
the maintenance of Protestant schools, and that <lb/>
Roman Catholics shall be taxed for the mainten<lb break="no"/>ance of Roman Catholic schools. No Protestant is <lb/>
taxed for the maintenance of Roman Catholic <lb/>
schools unless he chooses, and at the same time no <lb/>
Roman Catholic is taxed for the maintenance of <lb/>
Protestant schools unless he chooses to be taxed in <lb/>
that way. I do not think there is any great <lb/>
danger from a system of that kind; and if the hon. <lb/>
gentlemen who espouse so warmly the interests of <lb/>
the North-West would turn their attention to the <lb/>
material welfare of that country they will find <lb/>
that the people of the territories are able to take <lb/>
care of their own spiritual interests. Now, the <lb/>
hon. gentleman, in referring to this question, says <lb/>
he is not sure whether the British North America <lb/>
Act controls the question of schools in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories or not. I can hardly believe that <lb/>
it does, for there is a provision at present on the <lb/>
Statute-book providing for the maintenance of separ<lb break="no"/>ate schools in the territories. It, therefore, appears <lb/>
to be plain that this House regulates these matters; <lb/>
and I would warn the hon. gentleman, before he <lb/>
brings a measure before this House for the purpose <lb/>
of abolishing separate schools in the territories, to <lb/>
consider the constitution of this House. The hon. <lb/>
gentleman says I have misunderstood him—that he <lb/>
did not intend to abolish separate schools, but <lb/>
merely wished to give the people the right to say <lb/>
whether they would have separate schools or not. <lb/>
I may say that I am opposed to that while the con<lb break="no"/>stitution of the territories exists in its present <lb/>
form. When those territories are divided into <lb/>
provinces, then they may be given control of their <lb/>
schools; but while they continue to be territories <lb/>
it is better to leave the school question as it is. <lb/>
When they are divided into provinces there will <lb/>
be a sufficient population of the different denomina<lb break="no"/>tions to guarantee that no one denomination shall <lb/>
be treated unfairly. But I believe, further, that <lb/>
when that happens the provinces must be given <lb/>
control of their own lands, and be given proper <lb/>
subsidies to ensure the efficient government of those <lb/>
provinces. I know that the hon. member for Both<lb break="no"/>well will immediately say: Here are those North-<lb break="yes"/>West political highwaymen after our pockets <lb/>
again. But, Sir, it would be useless to establish <lb/>
Provincial Governments in the North-West un<lb break="no"/>less we gave them the means of carrying <lb/>
out their purposes. I consider that the time <lb/>
is not ripe for establishing Provincial Govern<lb break="no"/>ments in the North-West until you give them <lb/>
good and solid means to enable them to re<lb break="no"/>deem their responsibilities. At the same time, I <lb/>
believe that this House has shown its responsi<lb break="no"/>bility in regard to that country. It has chartered <lb/>
railways throughout the North-West in every <lb/>
direction. This is practically the Provincial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of the North-West as well as the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion Government; and when we who represent the <lb/>
North-West appeal to the Government, and the <lb/>
Government appeal to this House for subsidies to <lb/>
assist our railways, I think hon. gentlemen forget <lb/>
that whereas they who belong to the older provin<lb break="no"/>ces have power to obtain assistance from the Provin<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

cial Governments, we in the North-West Territories <lb/>
have no such power: and, therefore, if we were to ask <lb/>
the Government, and the Government were to ask <lb/>
this House to grant double subsidies to railways in <lb/>
the North-West Territories, they would act on a <lb/>
sound basis; because they would grant one-half in <lb/>
their capacity as the Provincial Government and <lb/>
the other half in their capacity as the Federal <lb/>
Government. Now, Sir, there was one other ques<lb break="no"/>tion referred to by my hon. friend from West Assin<lb break="no"/>iboia; that is the question of immigration. I do not <lb/>
think I need say very much on this question to im<lb break="no"/>press upon this House still more strongly than it has <lb/>
hitherto been done that the question of immigration <lb/>
is one of the most material questions in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West. The hon. member of Assiniboia suggested <lb/>
that a sum of money should be provided by this Act <lb/>
to be given to the Government of the North-West to <lb/>
be expended on immigration. I think myself that <lb/>
that would be a very wise thing indeed, and I hope <lb/>
that when the Supplementary Estimates come <lb/>
down we shall find a sum in them for that object. <lb/>
But there is one defect in this Act which I hope <lb/>
will be remedied. The population of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West act was passed, and the electoral districts <lb/>
for the last Provincial Legislature were drawn out. <lb/>
Now, by this Bill you are cutting off the three <lb/>
legal experts of the Council, and I would ask the <lb/>
Minister not to increase the number of Assem<lb break="no"/>bly, but to provide for three new elected represen<lb break="no"/>tatives to take the place of those three legal <lb/>
experts, one of those representatives to come from <lb/>
the district of Saskatchewan, and the other two I <lb/>
think my hon. friend from Alberta (Mr. Davis) is <lb/>
fairly entitled to claim, according to the population <lb/>
of his district. If this is done it will give the <lb/>
greatest satisfaction to the people of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West. I think the Bill will then be satisfactory to <lb/>
them as a temporary measure, because it can only <lb/>
be a temporary measure, if the North-West con<lb break="no"/>tinues to grow as we hope it will. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ARMS3">Mr. ARMSTRONG</persName>. I do not intend to find <lb/>
fault with the Bill; but I would ask the Minister <lb/>
    if subsection (<hi rendition="simple:italic">f</hi>) of sub-section 2 of section 6 gives  <lb/>
power to the Assembly to establish the ballot in <lb/>
local elections? <lb/></p> 

    <p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. Sub-section (<hi rendition="simple:italic">f</hi>) gives power to    <lb/>
the Legislative Assembly to give the ballot. That <lb/>
is the intention. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName>. I was rather astonished at <lb/>
the remarks that fell from the lips of the hon. <lb/>
member of Muskoka (Mr. O'Brien) on this particu<lb break="no"/>lar occasion. We have heard a good deal before <lb/>
on this question of education as well as that of the <lb/>
dual language, and in most of these instances <lb/>
the objections came from representatives of the <lb/>
Province of Ontario, who, being unable to impose <lb/>
their own ideas in their own province, are trying <lb/>
to impose those very ideas outside of the Province <lb/>
of Ontario itself. The question of education is one <lb/>
of those which have been well guarded in the con<lb break="no"/>stitution; and I may say that, upon reading the <lb/>
British North America Act one cannot fail to <lb/>
notice that the spirit, as well as the letter of the <lb/>
constitution, is in favour of separate schools. <lb/>
Clause 93 is as follows:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"In and for each province the Legislature may exclu<lb break="no"/>sively make laws in relation to education, subject and <lb/>
according to the following provisions:— <lb/></p>

<pb n="3913" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03913.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3913</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 14, 1391.]</fw> <fw type="num">3914</fw>

<p>"First, nothing in any such law shall prejudicially <lb/>
affect any right or privilege wrth respect to denomina<lb break="no"/>tional schools which any class of persons have by law in <lb/>
the province at the Union: Second, all the powers, privi<lb break="no"/>leges and duties at the Union bylaw conferred and im<lb break="no"/>posed in Upper Canada on the separate schools and school <lb/>
trustees of the Queen's Roman Catholic subjects shall be <lb/>
and the same are hereby extended to the dissentient <lb/>
schools of the Queen's Protestant and Roman Catholic <lb/>
subjects of Quebec: Third, where in any province a sys<lb break="no"/>tem of separate or dissentieut schools exists by law at <lb/>
the Union or is thereafter established by the Legislature <lb/>
of the province, an appeal shall lie to the Governor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral in Council from any act or decrsion of any provincial <lb/>
authority affecting any right or privileg of the Protestant <lb/>
or Roman Catholic minority of the Queen's subjects in <lb/>
relation to education.'" <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>Therefore, when a system of separate schools <lb/>
existed prior to the Union, or was thereafter estab<lb break="no"/>lished, it was provided that that system could <lb/>
not subsequently be altered: and I say that <lb/>
this being the case, the spirit of our constitu<lb break="no"/>tion is in favour of the system of separate schools. <lb/>
In the case of the North-West Territorics, before <lb/>
we enacted legislation to govern those territories <lb/>
there were schools in existence, and those were <lb/>
separate schools: and when this Parliament, in <lb/>
giving a constitution to those territories, enacted <lb/>
that the schools to be thereafter established would <lb/>
be separate schools, we have only continued the <lb/>
system that was already in existence, and a system <lb/>
already under the pmteetion of the constitution. <lb/>
The British North America Act provided that <lb/>
what existed in the provinces that were then <lb/>
united should be extended also to the provinces <lb/>
afterwards taken into the Union and to-day form <lb/>
part of Confederation, and that provision applies <lb/>
also to the territories we have acquired since. <lb/>
Therefore, I may say. that in leaving what <lb/>
is well alone the Government is only car<lb break="no"/>rying out the spirit of the constitution, as I <lb/>
have already explained. With regard to the feel<lb break="no"/>ing of the people in the Territories. I may say that <lb/>
the feeling out there is just as has been represented <lb/>
by the worthy representative of Saskatchewan (Mr. <lb/>
Macdowall). Last year a large number of peti<lb break="no"/>tions were addressed to this Parliament, asking that <lb/>
the same system which was in existence should be <lb/>
maintained, and protesting against any change such <lb/>
as was then contemplated by some hon. members of <lb/>
this House. This year, I may say, I have a certain <lb/>
number of similar petitions in my desk, which I did <lb/>
not deem advisable to present to this House, because <lb/>
I did not think that this question would he brought <lb/>
up for our consideration. I am glad, however, that<lb/>
    the hon. member for Muskoka has only put in his <lb/>
remarks as a protest, and does not intend to raise <lb/>
otherwise this question during the present session. <lb/>
and I hope we will never hear any more of those <lb/>
very nasty questions, and that of education, which <lb/>
should not have been raised on this occasion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCNE1">Mr. McNEILL</persName>. I desire just to say a few words <lb/>
with reference to this matter. I would not have <lb/>
said anything at all had it not been for the remarks <lb/>
which have fallen from my hon. friend opposite; <lb/>
but I think it is well that I should at once remove <lb/>
what seems to he a complete misapprehension from <lb/>
the mind of my hon. friend. He says that some <lb/>
persons in Ontario, unable to carry their own views <lb/>
as to education into effect there, desire to impose <lb/>
those views upon people in other portions of this <lb/>
Dominion. Now, that is an entire misconception <lb/>
of what has fallen from the hon. member for Mus<lb break="no"/>koka. Nothing more entirely opposed to the <lb/>

<cb/>

remarks which I, at least. had the pleasure of <lb/>
hearing from him, could well be imagined than that <lb/>
statement. What my hon. friend said was this— <lb/>
if I could state the exact logical opposite of what <lb/>
has been cited by the hon. gentleman opposite— <lb/>
not that he desires to impose the wishes of people <lb/>
outside the North-West Territories upon the people <lb/>
of the North-West Territories in reference to this <lb/>
matter, but that, on the contrary, he desires to <lb/>
take care that the wishes of no one outside the <lb/>
North-West Territories shall he imposed upon the <lb/>
people there with reference to this matter. He <lb/>
wishes to have safeguards taken lest at some time <lb/>
the wishes of other people should be imposed upon <lb/>
them. He wishes to take care now that we do not <lb/>
do something which will prevent the people of <lb/>
the North-West having the power to carry out <lb/>
their own views in reference to this matter: and <lb/>
surely it is scarcely fair to my hon. friend to re<lb break="no"/>present that he has any desire to force the wishes <lb/>
of other people on the people of the North-West <lb/>
Territories. When my hon. friend understands <lb/>
what the hon. member for Muskoka really means I <lb/>
hope he will have the kindness to get up in his place <lb/>
and withdraw the observations he has made, which, <lb/>
I am sure, were not meant in unkindness, but, which <lb/>
really were not doing justice at all to what has <lb/>
fallen from my hon. friend. For my part, I should <lb/>
like to see the people of Canada if it were possible, <lb/>
educated in one school. I should like personally <lb/>
to see the young people brought up in the closest <lb/>
possible friendship with one another. I think that <lb/>
would be for the benefit of the people of Canada, <lb/>
but I quite recognize the fact that other people <lb/>
differ from me in that respect. I quite recognize <lb/>
the fact that they may be right and that I may be <lb/>
wrong, and all my hon. friend says and all I say in <lb/>
regard to this is that we should take care that <lb/>
those in Canada who think as we think in regard <lb/>
to this matter should have the opportunity of <lb/>
carrying out their wishes, and that those who <lb/>
think differently should have the opportunity of <lb/>
carrying out their wishes. We simply hope that <lb/>
we shall not now do anything which will prevent <lb/>
the people of the North-West Territories in the <lb/>
future from dealing with this matter in any man<lb break="no"/>ner they please. If they wish separate schools, let <lb/>
them have them; and if they do not wish separate <lb/>
schools, do not force them upon them. That is all <lb/>
my hon. friend says, and if that is not a fair and <lb/>
reasonable propositionl do not see where a fair <lb/>
and reasonable proposition can be found. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName>. When I made my remarks <lb/>
I had in my mind the last fight that took place in <lb/>
Ontario, and from what I read in the newspapers <lb/>
and the speeches that took place I formed the <lb/>
opinion on which I made my remarks. As to <lb/>
leaving this to the Local Legislature the experience <lb/>
we have had in Manitoba is so sad that we cannot <lb/>
agree to leave our interests to a set of demagogues, <lb/>
who try to impose their own views on other people, <lb/>
without any regard to the interests or the welfare <lb/>
of the minority. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. I hope the hon. gentleman <lb/>
will not make a speech, as he has already spoken. <lb/>
He will have an opportunity to speak in Committee. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. I am very glad to see that we <lb/>
will not have a repetition this year of the animated <lb/>
discussions on this subject which took place be<lb break="no"/>fore, but I do not think the occasion should pass <lb/>

<pb n="3915" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03915.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3915</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3916</fw> 

without my stating my views in regard to this <lb/>
matter. I humbly submit that this is a very im<lb break="no"/>portant question, that it has a great deal to do with <lb/>
some rights which we should not infringe upon, <lb/>
that it touches the constitution itself, and the con<lb break="no"/>sent of the parties to that constitution. When <lb/>
the question came up to incorporate Manitoba and <lb/>
the North-West in the Dominion some great <lb/>
troubles arose. Troops were sent there, and then, <lb/>
on the invitation of the Ottawa Govermnent, dele<lb break="no"/>gates were sent here. The Government of Eng<lb break="no"/>land took great care that the incorporation of that <lb/>
province in the Dominion would not be effected with<lb break="no"/>out the consent of the parties interested. The dele<lb break="no"/>gates came to Ottawa with a Bill of Rights. I hope <lb/>
that the hon. gentlemen who place themselves under <lb/>
the flag of equal rights will not desire to see any <lb/>
rights infringed, and they will see that the North-<lb break="yes"/>West would not have joined the Dominion if the <lb/>
claim made by the North-West generally, and not <lb/>
only by Manitoba, had not been accepted. Those <lb/>
delegates who were specially appointed, in confor<lb break="no"/>mity with the invitation of the Government of this <lb/>
country, came to Ottawa and presented their Bill <lb/>
of Rights. The seventh clause of that Bill of Rights <lb/>
says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"That the separate schools be preserved and the money <lb/>
for those schools be divided between the different religious <lb/>
denominations and their respective populations, accord<lb break="no"/>ing to the system followed in the Province of Quebec." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>Section 16 says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"That the French and English languages be common <lb/>
in the Legislature and in the courts, and that all the public <lb/>
documents as well as the Acts of the Legislature be <lb/>
published in both languages." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>And in a report elaborately prepared by His Grace <lb/>
Mgr. Tache, dated the 27th December, all the facts <lb/>
that occurred then are related, and it says at <lb/>
page 7: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The question of separate schools as asked for in Article <lb/>
7 of said Bill of Rights was taken under consideration. <lb/>
The delegates were assured that not only would they have <lb/>
the benefit of the clauses of the British North America <lb/>
Act, but that they might assure their people that in the <lb/>
Red River district the separate schools were guaranteed <lb/>
to them, and the usage of the French language as an <lb/>
official language was also granted as it had been asked in <lb/>
Article 16 of said Bill of Rights. Moreover, it was promised <lb/>
that we would receive what was asked in Articles 17 and <lb/>
18." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>I did not mention that Article 18 states that a judge <lb/>
of the Supreme Court will speak both French and <lb/>
English. The bishop goes on to say that these <lb/>
claims were all granted as a matter of course. If <lb/>
the granting of the same was not in terms <lb/>
identical with the demand which was made, at all <lb/>
events it was substantially granted in order to <lb/>
satisfy the interests of the different parties. <lb/>
That was one of the bases of the convention, and <lb/>
the Dominion of Canada has been allowed by Eng<lb break="no"/>land to acquire those territories on the special con<lb break="no"/>dition that the French language and the separate <lb/>
schools should be maintained. That is a contract. <lb/>
It is the basis of a constitution, and if we begin <lb/>
now to change that constitution we may shake the <lb/>
tree of Confederation in such a way that perhaps it <lb/>
may not live long; we may prevent it from having <lb/>
large branches which would shelter a large, a healthy <lb/>
and a happy population. The hon. gentlemen who <lb/>
look for equal rights must not at the same time try <lb/>
to take away from others the rights which are <lb/>
guaranteed by charters. I may be told that this is <lb/>

<cb/>

not a British charter. That is true. As far as <lb/>
Manitoba is concerned, the charter is British. As <lb/>
far as the North-West is concerned, it is a Dominion <lb/>
charter; but it results from the stipulations which <lb/>
were made when Manitoba was allowed to join the <lb/>
Confederation, that the same basis would be adopted <lb/>
by the Dominion for the North-West Territories, and <lb/>
we cannot now take away the rights and privileges <lb/>
which were granted to the minority in any of those <lb/>
two provinces without abusing our powers and <lb/>
without acting unfairly and unjustly towards <lb/>
those minorities. If there was something against <lb/>
the common good when a man worships his <lb/>
God according to the Catholic religion, if there <lb/>
was something against the public good when <lb/>
a man speaks French, then I would say: all <lb/>
right, you act for the common good; but where <lb/>
is the man of common sense who will say in <lb/>
this House of Parliament of Canada that it is wrong <lb/>
to worship God according to the Catholic religion? <lb/>
Where is the man who will say it is wrong to <lb/>
speak French? Do we not in our language teach <lb/>
our children to respect the property of their neigh<lb break="no"/>bour? Do we not teach them to be loyal to the <lb/>
Queen? Do we not teach our children all those <lb/>
rules of morals necessary for the welfare and safety <lb/>
of a people? If, then, in the Catholic religion, and <lb/>
in the French language, there is nothing against <lb/>
public good, you must respect the conditions <lb/>
concerning them, which were established when <lb/>
those parts of the Dominion joined the Con<lb break="no"/>federation of Canada. I maintain that in our <lb/>
Confederation, under our system of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, we must follow the constitution as it <lb/>
has been agreed upon; and if we go astray from it <lb/>
we lay down principles and make precedents which <lb/>
will bring us into a state of division and trouble, <lb/>
and which might demolish the whole work of Con<lb break="no"/>federation. Those who look for unity instead of <lb/>
union do not understand the system under which <lb/>
we live. There is a great and essential distinction <lb/>
to be drawn between the two things. The essence <lb/>
of a Government by a King or an Emperor, as in <lb/>
England or France, is unity? The essence of <lb/>
a Confederation is not unity, it is union, and there <lb/>
is a wide distinction to be made between the two. <lb/>
On this point, I will quote from a high authority, <lb/>
"Lectures introductory to the study of the Law of <lb/>
the Constitution," by Dicey. I draw to this work <lb/>
the attention of the hon. member for Muskoka, <lb/>
whom I know to be animated with honest and hon<lb break="no"/>ourable motives, who is sincere in his convictions, <lb/>
who acts in what he believes to be the real interests <lb/>
of the country. I ask him to look at that authority <lb/>
and to follow my quotation, and to learn how to re<lb break="no"/>spect the sentiments of those who have not the <lb/>
honour of speaking his language or of professing <lb/>
his religion. We respect his rights; we want equal <lb/>
rights for all—equal rights for the Protestant and <lb/>
for the Catholic religion, for the English and for <lb/>
the French language. Those rights cannot be in<lb break="no"/>fringed upon without troubling the harmony and <lb/>
the welfare of our commonwealth. On page 129 <lb/>
of his work Dicey says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"A second condition absolutely essential to the found<lb break="no"/>ing of a federal system is the existence of a very peculiar <lb/>
state of sentiment among the inhabitants, of the countries <lb/>
which it is proposed to unite. They must desire union, <lb/>
and must not desire unity. If there be no desire to unite, <lb/>
there is clearly no basis for federalism: the wild scheme <lb/>
entertained, it is said, under the commonwealth of form<lb break="no"/>ing a union between the English Republic and the United <lb/>
Provinces was one of those dreams which may haunt the <lb/>

<pb n="3917" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03917.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3917</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 14, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">3918</fw>

imagination ofpoliticians. but it can never be transformed <lb/>
into facts." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>At page 130 he says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The sentiment, therefore, which creates a federal state <lb/>
is the prevalence. throughout the citizens of more or less <lb/>
allied countries, of two feelings which are to a certain ex<lb break="no"/>tent, inconsistent—the desire for national unity and the <lb/>
determination to maintain the independence of each man's <lb/>
separate state." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>At page 132 he says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"From the notion that national unity can be reconciled <lb/>
with state independence by a division of powers under a <lb/>
common constitution. between the nation on the one hand <lb/>
and the individual states on the other, flow the three lead<lb break="no"/>ing characteristics of federalism—the supremacy of the <lb/>
constitution—the distribution among bodies, with limited <lb/>
and co-ordinate authority, of the different powers of gov<lb break="no"/>ernment—the authority of the courts to act as interpret<lb break="no"/>ers of the constitution." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>Now, Mr. Speaker, under our system we have that <lb/>
constitution which must be our sole guide; we must <lb/>
not depart from it in any way. A part of that consti<lb break="no"/>tution has been granted by the Queen, and the other <lb/>
part has been granted by this Parliament, in virtue <lb/>
of the powers given to us by the Queen. The <lb/>
constitution as it stands is the consequence of the <lb/>
act and the direct will of the people at large. <lb/>
It follows that that constitution must be stronger <lb/>
than the courts, stronger than Parliament, stronger <lb/>
than any power in this world. We have consented <lb/>
to enter into Confederation under certain stipula<lb break="no"/>tions, and they must remain our rule. Of course, <lb/>
some human power will have to interpret some <lb/>
acts of the Legislatures to find out whether they are <lb/>
conformable to the constitution, but the constitu<lb break="no"/>tion itself must always remain as our guiding star. <lb/>
What does the hon. gentleman, with a good motive, <lb/>
doubtless, ask us to do? He asks us to change that <lb/>
constitution. I say that he cannot receive the <lb/>
consent of those who look seriously to the future of <lb/>
this country. The generous spirit of all the parts <lb/>
of the Constitution, either Imperial or Federal, <lb/>
is that the two languages shall remain in <lb/>
the right of the different populations, of the <lb/>
different people composing the federation: se<lb break="no"/>condly, that separate schools shall remain <lb/>
intact. Separate Schools are allowed under law to <lb/>
remain separate in the Province of Quebec, and if any <lb/>
member of this House, or any one out of the <lb/>
House came into the Province of Quebec and asked <lb/>
us to do away with separate schools, to keep only <lb/>
the schools of the majority, you would find the <lb/>
whole Catholic population of the Province of Que<lb break="no"/>bec rising as one man and saying, No. The Pro<lb break="no"/>testants are entitled to their Protestant schools; <lb/>
they entered Confederation with that stipulation, <lb/>
and they will keep them. I was happy when I <lb/>
saw in the neighbouring province, the great and <lb/>
prosperous Province of Ontario—when I saw there <lb/>
a Prime Minister, to whatever party he may belong, <lb/>
rising up from his seat and, in the name of a great <lb/>
party, saying: "I will defend the separate schools <lb/>
because they are established by the constitution, <lb/>
and I must observe the constitution." I deprecate <lb/>
the Acts of Martin of Manitoba, to whatever party <lb/>
he may belong, when he got a law passed to change <lb/>
the constitution, which he had not the right to do, <lb/>
concerning the separate schools and the French <lb/>
language in that province. I will not for my part <lb/>
consent to be a part to any law entrenching upon <lb/>
vested rights. The people professing the Catholic <lb/>
religion in the North-West are in a minority to-day: <lb/>
who can tell us that in 100 years, or 200 years, they <lb/>

<cb/>

will not be the majority? Then if the majority be<lb break="no"/>comes Catliolic, and if that majority is asked to <lb/>
establish separate schools and to do away with the <lb/>
Protestant schools, following the rules of the Cath<lb break="no"/>olic Church, the majority, then being Catholic, <lb/>
will say, "No; vested rights must remain vested <lb/>
rights, and nobody must infringe upon them." <lb/>
That is, Mr. Speaker, the general understanding, <lb/>
and we must not infringe upon it; that is my way <lb/>
of looking at the constitution of the country, it <lb/>
must be our guide and our only guide. It is the <lb/>
only way of forming a grand people in union under <lb/>
the British flag, of making everybody happy, feel<lb break="no"/>ing that his rights are respected, that the future of <lb/>
his children is assured, and that his religion, as well <lb/>
as his language, are not exposed to be taken away <lb/>
from future generations for whom he is responsible. <lb/>
Now, the same authority which I quoted a moment <lb/>
ago, gives general rules as to that constitution. He <lb/>
says, page 144: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Under the federal system it is otherwise. The legal <lb/>
supremacy of the constitution is essential to the existence <lb/>
of the state." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>The words are clear. He speaks thus of the United <lb/>
States: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The glory of the founders of the United States is to <lb/>
have advised or adopted arrangements under which the <lb/>
constitution became in reality as well as name the supreme <lb/>
law of theland. This end they attained by adherence to <lb/>
a very obvious principle and by the invention of appro<lb break="no"/>priate machinery for carrying this principle into effect. <lb/>
The principle is clearly expressed in the constitution of <lb/>
the United States. 'The constitution' runs article 6, <lb/>
'and the laws of United States which shall be made <lb/>
in pursuance thereof, shall be the supreme law of the <lb/>
land and the Judges in every state shall be bound thereby, <lb/>
anything in the constitution or laws in any state to the <lb/>
contrary notwithstanding.'" <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>The same authority, speaking of our British North <lb/>
America Act of 1867, page 153, says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Throughout the Dominion, therefore, the constitution <lb/>
is in the strictest sense the immutable law of the land. <lb/>
Under this law, again. you have as you would expect, <lb/>
the distribution of powers among bodies of co-ordinate <lb/>
authority." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>Where is the consent, I will not say of the major<lb break="no"/>ity, but of the minority of the North-West, who <lb/>
joined the Dominion under a special compact, to <lb/>
do away with separate schools or abolish the <lb/>
French language in any part of the public or offi<lb break="no"/>cial proceedings either of courts or of Parliaments. <lb/>
If you do any man in the North-West the injustice <lb/>
of taking away from him vested rights in that re<lb break="no"/>spect, if you do him the injustice of not allowing <lb/>
him to speak in Parliament or read the Acts of <lb/>
Parliament, or the decisions of the court in his own <lb/>
language, you do not act with justice but with tyr<lb break="no"/>anny; you use force towards the minority in order <lb/>
to take away the rights belonging to them, and <lb/>
which the majority had given to that minority. <lb/>
You trespass on private rights, you deprive a body <lb/>
of people of their vested rights without their con<lb break="no"/>sent, and I do not believe it will be noble, fair and <lb/>
even excusable on the part of this enlightened <lb/>
Parliament to do any such action, when we boast<lb/> 
    of the great education and the great liberty <lb/>
which every one enjoys under the British flag. <lb/>
In the name of the constitution, in the name <lb/>
of vested rights, in the name of equal rights, <lb/>
because equal rights do not consist in taking away <lb/>
rights from others, in the name of the future <lb/>
of this country, of the peace, harmony and <lb/>
welfare of every part of this Dominion, I implore <lb/>
this Parliament not to infringe on vested rights and <lb/>

<pb n="3919" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03919.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3919</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3920</fw> 

to maintain for the North-West as for any other <lb/>
part of the Dominion, all rights granted to the <lb/>
people by the constitution, which has received the <lb/>
sanction of Her Most Gracious Majesty Queen <lb/>
Victoria. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. The hon. member for Bellechase <lb/>
(Mr. Amyot) seems to confuse a portion of the con<lb break="no"/>stitution with the constitution itself. That portion <lb/>
of the British North America Act referred to pro<lb break="no"/>vided for a condition of things that was in existence <lb/>
in two provinces of the Dominion when Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion was accomplished, and that is the reason those <lb/>
rights were given to those provinces by that Act. <lb/>
Among the exclusive rights given to a province, as <lb/>
stated in clause 93 of the British North America <lb/>
Act, was: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"In and for each province the Legislature may exclu<lb break="no"/>sively make laws in relation to education, subject and <lb/>
according to the following provisions." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>These provisions were made to apply to a condition <lb/>
of things prevailing only in two provinces of the <lb/>
Dominion when Confederation was about to take <lb/>
place. The hon. member for Bellechasse (Mr. <lb/>
Amyot) forgets that there are some provinces that <lb/>
have not the right to separate schools today, but <lb/>
which came in under the constitution, the same as <lb/>
the North-West Territories or Manitoba did; and <lb/>
it must be remembered that these provisions were <lb/>
applicable to a condition of things that existed in <lb/>
Ontario and Quebec alone, and they were framed <lb/>
to meet that condition, and not to apply to other <lb/>
provinces or territories that might come in here<lb break="no"/>after. The member for Bellechasse says we have a <lb/>
right to maintain that provision. I believe we <lb/>
have the right to do so. We went into Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion on the understanding that the British North <lb/>
America Act should be our future constitution. <lb/>
and there is no violation, when we are giving a <lb/>
constitution to the North-West Territories, in <lb/>
granting the new province the right contemplated <lb/>
to be given to all provinces, to deal exclusively <lb/>
with the subject of education. In New Brunswick <lb/>
the people have that right, in Nova Scotia they <lb/>
have it, but in Ontario and Quebec they have not <lb/>
that right, because separate schools were established <lb/>
anterior to Confederation, and they must be retained <lb/>
in accordance with the constitution. The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Provencher (Mr. LaRiviere) says those provi<lb break="no"/>sions have the sanction of law to-day in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West. The hon. gentleman refers to a section in the <lb/>
old Act. I should like to ask, when was that passed? <lb/>
It was not passed at the time we acquired the <lb/>
North-West Territories but was inserted in a pro<lb break="no"/>visional Act in order to give quasi-legislative power <lb/>
to the Lieutenant Governor in the North-West. <lb/>
If there is any force in the arguments of the hon. <lb/>
members for Bellechasse and Provencher, they <lb/>
must show that by law or usage the educational <lb/>
system of the country, anterior to the time we ac<lb break="no"/>quired Manitoba and the North-West, separate <lb/>
schools existed, and, if such were established, there <lb/>
might be some force in the contention that the <lb/>
people had the right to retain the power they enjoyed <lb/>
and exercised. But I do not understand that the <lb/>
clause of the Act that the hon. member for Mus<lb break="no"/>koka (Mr. O'Brien) read is part and parcel of the <lb/>
constitution, but simply a clause of the North-West <lb/>
Territories Act. The hon. member for Provencher <lb/>
(Mr. LaRivière) said that the people of Ontario <lb/>
should not force their opinion into legislation for <lb/>
the North-West Territories. He forgets that he is <lb/>

<cb/>

adopting that course himself, because he does not <lb/>
belong to the North-West Territories, but to the <lb/>
Province of Manitoba. But it is not a matter of <lb/>
jurisdiction limited to members from those Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, when we are framing a constitution for that <lb/>
western country, but the right to take part belongs <lb/>
to every member of this Parliament. We are mak<lb break="no"/>ing that constitution. and it ought to be in harmony <lb/>
with the provision of the British North America Act, <lb/>
if I rightly interpret it, which is that every province <lb/>
that enters into this Union shall have certain ex<lb break="no"/>clusive rights as laid down in the British North <lb/>
America Act, and one of these rights is, that in <lb/>
and for each province the Legislature may make <lb/>
laws in relation to education. It goes on and says <lb/>
"subject to the following provisions:" but, as I <lb/>
before stated, the provisions were only made to <lb/>
provide for a condition of things that existed in <lb/>
two provinces, not all the provinces, and therefore <lb/>
we may fairly leave that part out of consideration. <lb/>
I must confess that I agree very largely with the <lb/>
sentiments expressed by the hon. member for <lb/>
Muskoka (Mr. O'Brien). If it is possible for us in <lb/>
giving a constitution to the Territories to give it <lb/>
such exclusive rights that they may deal with <lb/>
education, as every other province in the Dominion <lb/>
has the right to deal with education, then I think <lb/>
it is fair and just that we should do so. Nor do I <lb/>
think we should be hammered in the discharge of <lb/>
our duty, notwithstanding the clause of the British <lb/>
North America Act which has been already cited, <lb/>
and a clause which was made long after we bought <lb/>
the North-West Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName>. I would ask my hon. friend <lb/>
to look at sub-section 3 of section 93. My hon. <lb/>
friend has only read up to sub-section 2, but he <lb/>
will find that sub-section 3 applies to the province <lb/>
where a system "will be thereafter established." <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. Sub-section 3 reads: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Where in any province a system of separate or dissen<lb break="no"/>tient schools exists by law at the Union or is thereafter <lb/>
established by the Legislature of the province, an appeal <lb/>
shall lie to the Governor General in Council from any act <lb/>
or decision of any provincial authority affecting any right <lb/>
or privilege of the Protestant or Roman Catholic minority <lb/>
of the Queen's subjects in relation to education." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>This provides fer where the legislation has provided <lb/>
for separate schools, or where separate schools existed <lb/>
when the province was brought into Confederation. <lb/>
I do not understand there was any law to provide <lb/>
for separate schools in the North-West Territories <lb/>
when they came into Confederation, and therefore <lb/>
I say that this cannot fairly apply. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName>. My hon. friend knows that <lb/>
the British North America Act applies to all the <lb/>
provinces. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. It certainly does, but I say <lb/>
that the sub-section which the hon. gentleman has <lb/>
asked me to read: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Where in any province a system of separate or <lb/>
dissentient schools exists by law at the Union—" <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>I claim it did not exist thereby law at the Union. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName> It says "or thereafter shall <lb/>
be established." <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. This is an Act that was passed <lb/>
long after the Union, and it did not exist by law at <lb/>
the time of the Union, and therchre I say that it <lb/>
cannot be fairly applied to this particular case. <lb/>
In view of the trouble we have seen in the Province <lb/>
of Manitoba lately in regard to this question, and <lb/>

<pb n="3921" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03921.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3921</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 14, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">3922</fw>

in view of the troubles that have taken place in <lb/>
other provinces, I think we should be very careful <lb/>
in dealing with this subject here. If there is any <lb/>
one principle more than another by which we should <lb/>
be governed it is that principle that we have ac<lb break="no"/>knowledged, the principle which we have in every <lb/>
province in the Union, save and except the provisions <lb/>
that were made for conditions that existed by law <lb/>
anterior to the Union. I say it is right to give to <lb/>
the provinces the power to deal exclusively with <lb/>
education, as was contemplated by the British North <lb/>
America Act, if I correctly interpret it. I do not know <lb/>
whether at the time that this Act was written <lb/>
this provision for educational powers was over<lb break="no"/>looked, or that it was intended to allow the law to <lb/>
remain, but I think it would he better to give a free <lb/>
constitution to the territories, as they are about to <lb/>
organize a Legislative Assembly, and to give them <lb/>
the same rights and powers that are exercised in <lb/>
every other province of the Union to-day. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. Without the right of changing <lb/>
anything as to education and language. We have <lb/>
been kept as a protection here. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. I have not spoken about lan<lb break="no"/>guage at all. I have spoken with regard to the <lb/>
subject of education, and according to my inter<lb break="no"/>pretation of the British North America Act it <lb/>
allows every province to have exclusive right over <lb/>
that.   <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI9">Mr. DAVIS</persName> (Alberta). Mr. Speaker, before this <lb/>
Bill receives its second reading I wish to say a <lb/>
very few words upon it. I am satisfied that this <lb/>
Bill meets with general approbation in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories, and I shall raise no discussion <lb/>
with regard to the stand that my hon. friend from <lb/>
Muskoka (Mr. O'Brien) takes in reference to it; <lb/>
but I will say this: That this question of education <lb/>
is one on which there is very little said in the <lb/>
North-West Territories, and had it been included <lb/>
in this Bill I, for one, would have stood up for separ<lb break="no"/>ate schools. You may say that ever since the <lb/>
North-West has been the North-West and in fact <lb/>
when it was originally settled, the first schools that <lb/>
were established there were Catholic schools, and <lb/>
I cannot myself see why we should take any rights <lb/>
away from these people which they had. I believe <lb/>
in fair-play the world over. Even if the Roman <lb/>
Catholics are now in a minority, there is no reason <lb/>
why the majority should dictate to them, and say: <lb/>
You shall not have what was granted to you when <lb/>
you first came into Confederation, as we might say. I <lb/>
There will be time enough when we are divided into <lb/>
provinces, which will be, I hope, at no distant date, <lb/>
to discuss this question. Then, if we are to have <lb/>
a new constitution it will be good and seasonable <lb/>
time to discuss this question, but at the present <lb/>
time I say: Let it alone. Now, with regard to <lb/>
the provisions of section 2 of the Bill now before <lb/>
the House. That section provides that there shall I <lb/>
be twenty-two members in the Legislative Assembly, <lb/>
but when the Bill comes up in the Committee I <lb/>
shall move that the number be increased to twenty-<lb break="yes"/>five members. We have had taken from us three <lb/>
of the legal experts, two of whom came from the <lb/>
district of Alberta, and I shall give my reasons for <lb/>
saying that we should have two additional mem<lb break="no"/>bers in that district. When in 1888 the proportion <lb/>
of the members was granted it was taken from the <lb/>
number of names that were on the voters' lists at <lb/>
that time. Alberta was entitled to six members <lb/>

<cb/>

at that time, Assiniboia to eleven, and Sas<lb break="no"/>katchewan to five. As we cannot yet get the <lb/>
proper estimate by the last census, it is only <lb/>
fair that. we should take the same proportion <lb/>
now as was taken three years ago—that is, by <lb/>
number of names on the voters' list. If <lb/>
the division was fair, then it is fair now. <lb/>
I find that in Alberta there were 6,492 on the <lb/>
voters' list, and that divided by six would give <lb/>
1,082 voters which each member in the district. of <lb/>
Alberta represented. In Assiniboia, cast and west, <lb/>
there were 7,255 names, which, for eleven members, <lb/>
would give each a representation of 659 voters, as <lb/>
against 1,082 for Alberta. Now, I am only asking <lb/>
for two members, which will leave me still to the <lb/>
good, with each member representing 816 voters in <lb/>
Alberta as against 659 in Assiniboia. I think I have <lb/>
a just claim in asking for these two additional <lb/>
members, and if there were a redistribution accord<lb break="no"/>ing to the number of names on the voters' list at <lb/>
the present time I think Alberta would be entitled <lb/>
to four members instead of two. I may say that I <lb/>
have heard no complaints from any portion of <lb/>
Alberta with regard to the clauses of this Bill. <lb/>
They have not even found fault with the represen<lb break="no"/>tation, as they thought I would look after that <lb/>
myself. I have my schedule drawn out in refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the representation, and I will produce it <lb/>
before the Committee when it comes to the question <lb/>
of redistribution provided we are allowed the two <lb/>
extra members. I do not propose to detain the <lb/>
House any longer at this stage, but when the Bill <lb/>
comes up in committee I shall have something to <lb/>
say upon it. <lb/></p> 

<!--Unsure of Mr. DAVIES ref-->
<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. DAVIES</persName>. (P.E.I.) Mr. Speaker, I wish to <lb/>
make just one. remark in reference to this question. <lb/>
I regret that the hon. gentleman should have <lb/>
debated at such length, and with, as I thought, <lb/>
unnecessary warmth, the subject of the introduction <lb/>
into the North-West of any provision with respect <lb/>
to education. My hon. friend to my left spoke <lb/>
about this subject as if an attempt were being made <lb/>
to interfere directly or indirectly with the rights <lb/>
which are secured by compact to the Province of <lb/>
Quebec, the Province of Ontario and the Province <lb/>
of Manitoba. I do not understand that any in<lb break="no"/>timation was given in that direction, and if it was, <lb/>
it certainly should not, so far as I understand the <lb/>
question, have any sympathy or support from me. <lb/>
I think those rights are sufficiently guaranteed by <lb/>
the British North America Act, and I have not <lb/>
heard that any agitation exists in any of those pro<lb break="no"/>vinces for the purpose of having any of those rights <lb/>
interfered with. I would not have said a word on <lb/>
this Bill except for the remarks made by these hon. <lb/>
gentlemen; and I desire that it should not he un<lb break="no"/>derstood on this occasion that Parliament is bound <lb/>
by the silence of one or all of its members from <lb/>
expressing its views when those territories are <lb/>
erected into provinces. My opinion is now, and <lb/>
has been for years, that when that time comes you <lb/>
cannot withhold from the provinces so erected <lb/>
the right to determine for themselves the <lb/>
question of education in one way or the <lb/>
other. I would be the last to favour this <lb/>
Parliament imposing upon the people there <lb/>
any system of education, either free or separate. I <lb/>
only claim that when a Bill is introduced to erect <lb/>
those territories into provinces that Bill should <lb/>
contain a provision enabling the people of the dif<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="3923" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03923.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3923</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3924</fw> 

ferent provinces so created to decide what system <lb/>
of education they shall have. I do not discuss that <lb/>
question now. I only express this view, lest I might <lb/>
be supposed by my silence to give assent to some <lb/>
extreme doctrines which hon. gentlemen have pro<lb break="no"/>pounded. In view of the remarks which have been <lb/>
made, I thought it necessary to disclaim that, in <lb/>
assenting to the passage of this Bill, I bound myself <lb/>
for all time on this question of education. I do not. <lb/>
Although we are giving powers almost equal to <lb/>
those conferred upon Local Legislatures, we are not <lb/>
erecting the territories into separate provinces. <lb/>
When that is done. I suppose it will he done by the <lb/>
Queen in Council under the 146th section of the <lb/>
British North America Act, and I simply claim the <lb/>
right when that time comes to determine for my<lb break="no"/>self. In accordance with the view I have always <lb/>
held and hold now. I have no hesitation in express<lb break="no"/>ing, respectfully, that the people of those new pro<lb break="no"/>vinces should have the right to determine what <lb/>
system of education they shall have. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BEAU13">Mr. BEAUSOLEIL</persName>. (Translation.) Mr. Speaker, <lb/>
the question of the representation of the minority <lb/>
in the Legislature of the North-West Territories <lb/>
was brought up last session of the last Parliament, <lb/>
by the reading of a letter from Mgr. Grondin, Bishop <lb/>
of St. Albert, in which is to be found the following <lb/>
passage:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Although in the minority, we might be able, neverthe<lb break="no"/>less. to send two representatives in in the House, but they <lb/>
have succeeded in making this a thing impossible for us. <lb/>
I again charge the Dominion Government, who in mark<lb break="no"/>ing out the electoral districts have divided up the two <lb/>
French centres in such a manner that it is impossible for <lb/>
us to secure representation." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>During the debate on the Bill introduced by the <lb/>
hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy to <lb/>
abolish the French language in the North-West <lb/>
Territories, the question was again brought tip by <lb/>
the hon. member for Saskatchewan (Mr. Macdowall), <lb/>
in a dialogue which took place between him and the <lb/>
hon. Minister of Justice, when the latter introduced <lb/>
his famous amendment. This dialogue is to be <lb/>
found in the last year's debates of the House, column <lb/>
882. I will now read it: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Mr. MACDOWALL. The hon. the Minister of Justice <lb/>
said. before he moved his ammendment the whole <lb/>
North-West should have fair representation in the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Assembly before that question was dealt with by <lb/>
that Assembly. I should like like to ask him does the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment contemplate a re-distribution of seats in the <lb/>
North-West Assembly? because otherwise the population <lb/>
of the North-West will not have the fair representation <lb/>
they are entitled to. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Sir JOHN THOMPSON. That is a matter which will <lb/>
have to be dealt with by Parliament, as the subject-matter <lb/>
of this resolution will be, should it be adopted. The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment will consider that subject before bringing down a <lb/>
Bill. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Mr. MACDOWALL. I understand that there will be <lb/>
a re-distribution of seats for the North-West Territories. <lb/>
and the Wrench population will be, given a representation <lb/>
before this question has to be dealt with. <lb/></p> 

<p>"Sir JOHN THOMPSON. The hon. gentleman will <lb/>
understand that if it is shown to the Government that <lb/>
there is not a fair representation in the present system of <lb/>
distribution this Parliament will beyond doubt remedy <lb/>
the evil." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>I wish to know, Mr. Speaker, whether the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment has studied the question, and whether it is <lb/>
ready to say whether the French population of the <lb/>
North-West is to be represented in the Legislature, <lb/>
for it has been shown that there exists a just griev<lb break="no"/>ance, and the Government has promised to remedy <lb/>
this grievance when it should be shown. In section <lb/>
2 of the Bill now before us the Government refers <lb/>

<cb/>

to a schedule containing a description of the electoral <lb/>
districts, according to which the elections shall he <lb/>
made. However, the Bill contains no new schedule, <lb/>
and before it be read for a second time I wish to <lb/>
know if the Government is ready to fulfil the pro<lb break="no"/>mise which it niade, of giving the French population <lb/>
of the North-West a representation proportionate <lb/>
to its importance? <lb/></p> 

<!--CHECK institions-->
<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). I should have been <lb/>
better pleased myself if the measure we have before <lb/>
us had made some provision for the creation of an <lb/>
executive responsible to the Local Legislature, and <lb/>
controlling the expenditure of moneys placed at <lb/>
the disposal of the Legislature of those territories. <lb/>
I notice in the Estimates which we have before as <lb/>
certain sums of money voted by this House for <lb/>
certain specific purposes: and I think, when the <lb/>
territories have rrown in population to such an <lb/>
extent as to justify them in having a representative <lb/>
Assembly to legislate for them, that we ought to <lb/>
hand over a reasonable sum of money, such as we <lb/>
are voting here for specific purposes, to the control of <lb/>
that Assembly, and allow it to determine how and <lb/>
for what purpose that money shall be applied. <lb/>
When we undertake to confer representative <choice><sic>insti<lb break="no"/>tions</sic><corr>institutions</corr></choice> on the people of the territories we are assum<lb break="no"/>ing that they are in a condition to exercise the <lb/>
functions of self-government: and one of the <lb/>
earliest functions of self-government would be to <lb/>
apply the revenues placed at their disposal to those <lb/>
purposes which they think most necessary for the <lb/>
welfare of the territories. That, I think, is a <lb/>
matter of very considerable importance. I do not <lb/>
overlook the fact that the population of this vast <lb/>
area is not a homogeneous population, in the sense <lb/>
of being united together and capable of understand<lb break="no"/>ing each other's wants, in the same way that a <lb/>
population in a well-settled province could. It is <lb/>
highly probable that it may be found, in the <lb/>
interest of good government in those territories, <lb/>
that at no distant day they should be divided, <lb/>
and that it will be found that they will be capable <lb/>
of carrying on the local legislation in a way more <lb/>
satisfactory to themselves if they had separate dis<lb break="no"/>tricts, each of which is separately represented, than <lb/>
by undertaking to embrace nearly one million <lb/>
square miles within the area of one Local Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and bringing together representatives of <lb/>
distant settlements, who cannot understand each <lb/>
other's wants and can know little or nothing about <lb/>
each other's circumstances. That fact alone will <lb/>
make any Assembly which may be called together <lb/>
there different from what a representative Assem<lb break="no"/>bly would be in a well-settled province. I observe, <lb/>
too, that by section 3 you give to the Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor the powers and prerogatives that belong <lb/>
to the Crown; you give him the power of dissolu<lb break="no"/>tion. I think that is very questionable. You say <lb/>
that the Legislature, when elected, shall be elected <lb/>
for three years, unless sooner dissolved by the <lb/>
Lieutenant Governor; but why should the Lieuten<lb break="no"/>ant Governor have the power of dissolution, when <lb/>
you have not given him any responsible advisers? <lb/>
The advisers he may have are not responsible to the <lb/>
majority of the Legislature. It does seem to <lb/>
me that the evils which might arise from <lb/>
this power being held by an irresponsible officer <lb/>
are far greater than those which would spring <lb/>
from the continuance of the Assembly for the <lb/>
    whole period of its election. The Assembly <lb/>

<pb n="3925" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03925.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3925</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 14, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">3926</fw>

exists, under this section, for a period of <lb/>
three years, unless sooner dissolved. Why should <lb/>
it be sooner dissolved? Why should it not con<lb break="no"/>tinue as a county council does, until the period for <lb/>
which it is elected expires? Why give an officer <lb/>
appointed by the Ministers here the power of dis<lb break="no"/>solution? His Excellency the Governor General <lb/>
exercises that power, but he does so upon the <lb/>
advice of Ministers who are responsible to Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment for the advice they give. But out there you <lb/>
have no Ministers, you have no advisers who are <lb/>
responsible to the Local Legislature and can be dis<lb break="no"/>missed from their positions by the action of the <lb/>
Local Legislature for having given bad advice in <lb/>
this matter. I think that is a power which ought <lb/>
never to be vested in an officer appointed by the <lb/>
Federal Ministers, or His Excellency upon the <lb/>
advice of the Federal Ministers, unless surrounded <lb/>
by men responsible to the. Local Legislature for the <lb/>
advice they give. I especially invite the attention <lb/>
of hon. gentlemen to this section of the Bill, and <lb/>
when we go into committee I think we should <lb/>
amend this, and unless the Government are <lb/>
prepared to say that the time has come when <lb/>
the Lieutenant Government of the territories shall <lb/>
be surrounded by men responsible to the Local <lb/>
Legislature for the advice they give, and that the <lb/>
moneys given by this House shall be handed over as <lb/>
a subsidy to that Legislature to distribute as they <lb/>
may see proper, under the constitutional provisions <lb/>
which pertain wherever parliamentary govern<lb break="no"/>ment exists, we ought not to take this step, be<lb break="no"/>cause it is one which ought necessarily to be <lb/>
accompanied by the others I have mentioned. <lb/></p> 

<p>Motion agreed, and House resolved itself into <lb/>
Committee. <lb/></p> 
</div>
    <div type="debate">
<head rendition="simple:centre">(In the Committee.) <lb/></head> 

<p>On section 3, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. There can be no <lb/>
doubt that the time has not come when the ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, as a whole, should be given the position <lb/>
and powers of a province; and, in all probability, <lb/>
this Parliament will entertain the view that those <lb/>
powers are not to be conferred upon the territories, <lb/>
as a whole, at any time, but that provincial powers <lb/>
should be withheld until the time comes for sub<lb break="no"/>dividing the territories. In the meantime, the <lb/>
provision is that the Legislature shall hold office <lb/>
for three years. Under the present system there <lb/>
was no power of dissolving the Assembly before the <lb/>
expiration of that period. The circumstances <lb/>
under which a dissolution of an assembly of that <lb/>
character, not possessing full constitutional powers <lb/>
and not guided by an executive, should take place, <lb/>
would be very rare indeed; but, the ower of dis<lb break="no"/>solution, I think, ought to be given. It is proposed <lb/>
that that power should be vested in the Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor of the territories. Hon. grentlemen <lb/>
opposite are of opinion that that will make him a <lb/>
despot, who has power at any moment, at his will <lb/>
and pleasure, to dissolve the Assembly. I have <lb/>
only to say that, according to my humble opinion, <lb/>
if the Lieutenant Governor of the North-West <lb/>
Territories should be a person of that disposition, <lb/>
who would dissolve the Assembly of his own <lb/>
motion, he ought to be dissolved himself as Lieu<lb break="no"/>tenant Governor before the election of a new <lb/>
Assembly, because the law provides that he shall <lb/>
govern the territories under instructions given <lb/>

<cb/>

him by the Governor in Council or the Secretary <lb/>
of State for Canada. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). That is the old irres<lb break="no"/>ponsible Colonial Office system. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. Yes. While. the pow<lb break="no"/>ers of the North-West Territories and the func<lb break="no"/>tions of their Government are limited, this Govern<lb break="no"/>ment is the executive for the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. There must be an executive somewhere. <lb/>
We do not propose that there shall be an execu<lb break="no"/>tive in the North-West Territories itself, and we <lb/>
have never yet conferred executive powers on any <lb/>
body there, although we have had an advisory <lb/>
council possessing a shadow of executive authority <lb/>
there. Nevertheless, even when the advisory <lb/>
council had its functions the Govermnent of Can<lb break="no"/>ada was the executive for the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories in the sense that the Provincial Government <lb/>
of the North-West Territories is, to all intents and <lb/>
purposes, the Government of Canada. Therefore <lb/>
it is that executive powers of that kind should <lb/>
be exercised, under the direction of this executive, <lb/>
by the Lieutenant Governor of the North-West <lb/>
Territories. Is there no responsibility in this con<lb break="no"/>nection? If this Parliament is the Parliament <lb/>
which passes the laws for the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, except in so far as we have delegated powers <lb/>
to pass ordinances on certain subjects, this is <lb/>
the Parliament that ought to control executive <lb/>
matters in the North-West Territories, and, there<lb break="no"/>fore, the executive ought to remain the Dominion <lb/>
Government. I said a few moments ago, and I <lb/>
think everybody will agree with me, that it <lb/>
would very rarely occur that a power of <lb/>
this kind would have to be exercised. Never<lb break="no"/>theless, anyone who has listened to or has read <lb/>
the debates which have occurred in reference <lb/>
to North-West matters during the last year or two <lb/>
can realize that an occasion might arise when the <lb/>
dissolution of the Assembly would be very conven<lb break="no"/>ient in the interests of the administration of the <lb/>
affairs of the territories. One of the subjects <lb/>
which might be referred to, as suggested by the <lb/>
debates which took place last year, might be the <lb/>
occurrence of the question as to conferring upon <lb/>
the North-West Assembly powers larger than they <lb/>
have hitherto possessed as to dealing with the <lb/>
liquor question. Last session this House would <lb/>
have been probably willing to agree that the power <lb/>
should be conferred on the North-West Assembly, <lb/>
but we were practically unanimous in the view that <lb/>
it should not be so conferred until the new Assem<lb break="no"/>bly should have been elected under a different <lb/>
system: and so, instead of being able to confer <lb/>
these powers at once, we were obliged to say that, <lb/>
although the interest of the North-West Territories <lb/>
might, in our estimation, induce us to confer <lb/>
such powers at once, such a proposition could not <lb/>
take effect until the expiration of the term of the <lb/>
present Assembly. It would have been more con<lb break="no"/>venient for us to pass an enactment to come into <lb/>
force at once, and to leave the new members to <lb/>
exercise such enlarged powers as this Parliament <lb/>
could confer. This House will be continually <lb/>
hampered in dealing with the North-West Assembly <lb/>
and changing the limits of the districts, and matters <lb/>
of that kind, under the present system, because <lb/>
everything will practically lave to be deferred until <lb/>
the expiration of the period of three years. Suppose <lb/>
that, in the course of a year or two, by a large <lb/>

<pb n="3927" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03927.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3927</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3928</fw> 

increase of population, a considerable portion of <lb/>
the territories should be unrepresented in the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly, it would be practically beyond our powers to <lb/>
change the representation. Of course, this is not <lb/>
likely to occur, but I think the power of dissolution <lb/>
should be vested somewhere. It cannot be vested <lb/>
in the. Assembly itself, and I think it: should be <lb/>
vested in the officer who exercises executive powers <lb/>
under the direction of the Government here. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). I am not. disputing the <lb/>
proposition that the power of dissolution ought to <lb/>
be vested somewhere, but I am simply pointing out <lb/>
that the mischiefs which might arise from the <lb/>
House sitting out its full period would be less <lb/>
likely to be serious than those which might arise <lb/>
from vesting this power in an irresponsible officer. <lb/>
It is true that the Lieutenant Governor is responsible <lb/>
to the Government here for his exercise of these <lb/>
powers, but that is simply in the same way as the <lb/>
Colonial Office, which was responsible to the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Parliament, exercised large powers over this <lb/>
country in the past. For instance, Sir Francis <lb/>
Bond Head was responsible to the Colonial Office, <lb/>
and the Colonial Minister was responsible to the <lb/>
Imperial Parliament, but that did not prevent <lb/>
serious abuses, which led to an insurrection in what <lb/>
is now Ontario and Quebec. I think we might <lb/>
start with this proposition, that although it is not <lb/>
desirable, perhaps, to confer upon the inhabitants of <lb/>
the territories the same wide measure of authority <lb/>
that is conferred upon the Local Legislatures in the <lb/>
provinces, yet, as far as you do confer power upon <lb/>
them, that power ought to be exercised in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with a responsiblc executive. You have got rid <lb/>
of the appointed members of the Local Legislature. <lb/>
You have an Assembly of persons representative of <lb/>
the people. Why should not the limited authority <lb/>
you entrust to that Assembly, and the executive <lb/>
authority in connection with it, be exercised upon <lb/>
the advice of men responsible to the Assembly for <lb/>
the advice which they give? Why, for instance, <lb/>
should we vote a considerable sum of money here, <lb/>
stating remotely the purposes to which it is to be <lb/>
applied, and not allow that money to be under the <lb/>
control of the Local Legislature of that territory and <lb/>
to be distributed upon the advice of the men who <lb/>
enjoy the confidence of that Legislature? I under<lb break="no"/>stand that some difficulties arose two or three years <lb/>
ago between the Lieutenant Governor and the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly in regard to pecuniary ap<lb break="no"/>propriations. You expect that a portion of that <lb/>
territory may be organized into a province at no <lb/>
very distant day. It will then have full provincial <lb/>
rights. You will then have to determine, as in the <lb/>
case of Manitoba, with what amount of debt it may <lb/>
enter the Confederation and what you may <lb/>
charge against it. You may charge your public <lb/>
works, as you did against the older provinces, charge <lb/>
the expenditure on public works which took place <lb/>
before Confederation, and you admit that they <lb/>
are entitled to a certain subsidy for their Local <lb/>
Government. How are you goin to carry this out? <lb/>
Are you going to make up a bill against the new <lb/>
province by putting in the amounts of which you <lb/>
control the expenditure, and which you will not <lb/>
allow the Legislature of the territory to control? It <lb/>
seems to me that, while we should be careful, where <lb/>
people are not in that state of what I might call <lb/>
organic cohesion which exists in the older provinces, <lb/>
where they consist of a number of separate and <lb/>

<cb/>

distinct settlements, still there ought to be a corres<lb break="no"/>ponding executive power to which exists in <lb/>
the older provinces, and that power should be exer<lb break="no"/>cised under the control of the Legislative Assembly. <lb/>
At present we make no provision for that. We <lb/>
give them powers of legislation,which are of no great <lb/>
value as long as we withhold from them the power <lb/>
of control over their expenditure, which is made for <lb/>
the purpose for which they are allowed to legislate, <lb/>
and in this case I say we place them in a position <lb/>
of helplessness. We limit their authority in a way <lb/>
that we should not and which will cause dissatisfac<lb break="no"/>tion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDOWALL</persName>. I do not think this will <lb/>
injure the North-West, because the power will be <lb/>
exercise in Ottawa, and I think the terriroties <lb/>
are safe, at all events, for three years to come. Had <lb/>
the Lieutenant Governor exercised the power of <lb/>
dissolving the Assembly within the last three years <lb/>
I think that would have ended the difficulty, because <lb/>
the difficulty arose from the existence of the Ad<lb break="no"/>visory Board, and if the Advisory Board had been <lb/>
able to advise His Honour to dissolve the House I <lb/>
believe they would have had a majority, and the <lb/>
whole difficulty thing would have been got over. In re<lb break="no"/>gard to creating an Executive Council, that is <lb/>
practically granting Provincial Government to the <lb/>
North-West. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). No. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDOWALL</persName>. It is one of the large steps <lb/>
towards granting executive government. The ex<lb break="no"/>ecutive would have the power of direct taxation, <lb/>
the power to raise a revenue and some means of <lb/>
paying themselves. The sentiment of the people of <lb/>
the North-West is against anything approaching <lb/>
responsible govermnent at present. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) One remark with respect <lb/>
to the quotation the Minister of Justice made from <lb/>
the Act, and which seemed to the hon. member <lb/>
for Saskatchewan to answer the argument. The <lb/>
second subsection of section 4 says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The Lieutenant Governor shall administer the <lb/>
Government under instructions from time to time given <lb/>
him by the Governor in Council, or by the Secretary of <lb/>
State of Canada." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
<p>So far so good; there is not doubt about that. But <lb/>
as a general rule, and in cases which are not expli<lb break="no"/>citly or expressly defined, where the powers are <lb/>
not expressly marked out by the statute, he is to <lb/>
be controlled by the instructions he gets from <lb/>
Ottawa. But that clause does not refer to powers <lb/>
which are expressly conferred by statute upon the <lb/>
Lieutenant: Governor himself, powers which we are <lb/>
conferring here, stating expressly that the Lieut<lb break="no"/>enant Governor should have power to dissolve the <lb/>
Assembly and cause anew one to be chosen. Now, <lb/>
then, the explicit and express powers are not con<lb break="no"/>trolled in any sense by the general declaration in <lb/>
the statute, that, speaking generally, he is governed <lb/>
under instructions from Ottawa. The larger power <lb/>
does not minimize, or control, or negative, or <lb/>
override the specific power which we are giving <lb/>
here. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. I beg to differ from <lb/>
my hon. friend. I think the very power which is <lb/>
vested in him is, by express terms in this statute, <lb/>
subject to the control of the Government here, and <lb/>
that the Government here is responsible for what <lb/>
he does in so far as he acts under our instructions. <lb/>
But the hon. gentleman can readily see that the <lb/>

<pb n="3929" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03929.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">3929</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 14, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">3930</fw>

The first step to take as regards statuary powers of <lb/>
the kind conferred by this Bill will be to give to <lb/>
the Governor instructions as to how he shall exer<lb break="no"/>cise powers of that character. Now, with regard  <lb/>
to the observations of the hon. member for Both<lb break="no"/>well (Mr. Mills), indicating that this is virtually <lb/>
establishing, in regard to the territories, a parental <lb/>
control, such as the Colonial Office exercises, that <lb/>
is undoubtedly true; that is the system under <lb/>
which the territories have been governed ever <lb/>
since we acquired them, and it is the system <lb/>
which prevails now in every Crown colony, and <lb/>
the only alternative which my hon. friend can sug<lb break="no"/>gest is to have a small executive there with limited <lb/>
power, as he has mentioned. Now, I beg to <lb/>
assure him that this subject has received the <lb/>
greatest consideration, and the most careful <lb/>
thought that can be given it, and the expe<lb break="no"/>rience of the past, as well as careful reflection <lb/>
from every point of view, has led us <lb/>
to the opinion that it is unwise to confer upon the <lb/>
executive there executive powers and responsibili<lb break="no"/>ties. If you do that you have, in the first place, a <lb/>
divided executive responsibility: you have an exe<lb break="no"/>cutive responsibility here and you have an exe<lb break="no"/>cutive responsibility there. You have a divided <lb/>
authority likewise. which is an evil of itself; but, <lb/>
above all, the effect of that is to create in the mind <lb/>
of the Territorial Government the impression that   <lb/>
while the principle is conceded to them of respon<lb break="no"/>sible government they do not enjoy a full measure <lb/>
of liberty. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. With the right of appeal here. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. Yes: and people en<lb break="no"/>trusted in that way with partial powers, if <lb/>
the doctrine of self-government is established and <lb/>
the principle recognized, will never submit to be <lb/>
controlled by an appeal from their executive in exe<lb break="no"/>cutive matters: and the effect of it would be simply <lb/>
that you would create an impression that they <lb/>
were not put in the same position as the provinces <lb/>
were, and that only the shadow of authority had <lb/>
been given them. It is better, I think, to retain <lb/>
all the executive powers in one body, and I believe   <lb/>
the people of the territories will be better satisfied <lb/>
themselves, and there will be less agitation in the <lb/>
territories if the people are told in a straightfor<lb break="no"/>ward way at the outset: The time has not come <lb/>
when you can have responsible government; for <lb/>
the present, the greater powers of legislation: must <lb/>
remain in the Parliament of Canada, the executive <lb/>
powers must remain in the executive of Canada, <lb/>
and when the time comes to give you provincial <lb/>
    powers you shall have them <hi rendition="simple:italic">in toto</hi>, and you shall <lb/>
stand on the same footing as any other province. <lb/></p> 

<p>Committee rose: and it being six o'clock, the <lb/>
Speaker left the Chair. <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">AFTER RECESS</head>

<p>House again resolved itself into Committee on   <lb/>
Bill No. 126 to amend the Acts respecting the <lb/>
North-West Territories. <lb/></p>
    </div>
    <div type="debate">

<head rendition="simple:centre">(In the Committee.)</head>
<p>On section 6,</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). There does not appear <lb/>
to be any provision by which the returning officers <lb/>

<cb/>

will be appointed. The absence of such a provi<lb break="no"/>sion is, in my opinion, a very serious defect in the <lb/>
Bill. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">SiR JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. There are no officers <lb/>
in these small districts. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDOWALL</persName>. It is better to allow some <lb/>
latitude, and to leave the matter in the Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor's hands. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). That is a subject on <lb/>
which the legislature should have the power to legis<lb break="no"/>late. If there is any doubt, we should not tie their <lb/>
hands, so that they cannot make provision <lb/>
legislatively for returning officers. I think the <lb/>
words "unless otherwise provided by the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Assembly of the territories" should be added. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. I have no objection <lb/>
to add these words, and I will consider the clause <lb/>
carefully. <lb/></p> 

<p>0n section l3, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). In that section, is it <lb/>
the intention of the Minister to give power to <lb/>
determine the succession of property and to deter<lb break="no"/>mine the mode of registration? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. It is all subject, as <lb/>
  you will see by the main section, to any Act of the <lb/>
Parliament of Canada. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I would like to ask the Minister <lb/>
is there any difficulty in sub-section 4 about bonds <lb/>
issued by a municipality. Then irrigation com<lb break="no"/>panies are excepted, and I think it would he an <lb/>
advantage that they should not be excepted. It <lb/>
may be said that irrigation companies would have <lb/>
to do with the public domain, which is controlled <lb/>
by the Dominion Parliament: but I should think <lb/>
that the territories might have power, subject to <lb/>
certain conditions, to organize irrigation com<lb break="no"/>panies. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). The incorporation of <lb/>
telephone companies in towns is far less important <lb/>
than some of the other powers we give. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. This sub-section will prevent as <lb/>
giving a charter to a little street railway. I would <lb/>
suggest that the Government would permit the <lb/>
municipalities to have a charter from the Local <lb/>
Government for a short railway. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. Is there any reason why the <lb/>
Government should not give them power, as the <lb/>
provinces have, to incorporate any railway com<lb break="no"/>pany? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDOWALL</persName>. I think there is good reason, <lb/>
because this House has assumed the incorporation <lb/>
of railway companies in the North-West Territories. <lb/>
Railways in the North-West cannot be built <lb/>
without financial assistance, and this Parliament <lb/>
should have power to charter them until the North-<lb break="yes"/>West is able to give the necessary assistance. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. The granting of a charter is one <lb/>
thing and the granting of aid to build railways is <lb/>
another. I should think that the people in the <lb/>
immediate locality would be the best authorities to <lb/>
pronounce in favour of a railway, and the corporation <lb/>
afterwards could appeal for aid to whatever source <lb/>
it liked. I am surprised that a member from the. <lb/>
territories should desire to prevent the Legislature <lb/>
incorporating a company. It is a great deal more <lb/>
expensive for men to come to Ottawa to obtain <lb/>
a charter than it would be if they could obtain it <lb/>

<pb n="3931" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03931.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3931</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3932</fw> 

within the limits of their own territory. I can see <lb/>
no possible harm in the territories having that <lb/>
power: they need not exercise it if they do not <lb/>
like. If I represented a constituency in the terri<lb break="no"/>tories I would be in favour of having such power <lb/>
given to the territories, trusting to the wisdom of <lb/>
the people that it would be exercised for the public <lb/>
good. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDOWALL</persName>. I do not agree with the hon. <lb/>
gentleman. In the first place, it is not very much <lb/>
cheaper to get incorporation in the North-West <lb/>
Assembly than it is here. They can get a private <lb/>
Bill passed through here just a mut as cheaply as <lb/>
they could in the Assembly. One object I have in <lb/>
view in saying that this House should keep the <lb/>
power of incorporating these railways is thatI think <lb/>
it would teach this Parliament what its responsi<lb break="no"/>bilities and duties are to the North-West. The <lb/>
incorporation of railway companies is one of the <lb/>
most important things connected with these terri<lb break="no"/>tories. and I think that when a Bill connected with <lb/>
the incorporation of railway companies passes <lb/>
through this House hon. gentlemen will perhaps <lb/>
appreciate their responsibilities to the territories <lb/>
more than at present. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TISD1">Mr. TISDALE</persName>. There is another objection to <lb/>
this. If this power is given to them they would <lb/>
have to pass a General Railway Act, which would <lb/>
involve very heavy machinery, until they are in<lb break="no"/>corporated into provinces, and we would have <lb/>
another set of railway Acts to come in contact <lb/>
with the Railway Act of the Dominion. I think <lb/>
that until the territories become provinces they <lb/>
should not have this power. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). I think that the power <lb/>
to incorporate Railway Acts in that territory, as <lb/>
long as it remains an undivided territory, would be <lb/>
far more extensive than the power to incorporate a <lb/>
railway in the provinces. You do not know what <lb/>
extent of territory you will assign to a province in <lb/>
that country yet. Suppose you were to make a <lb/>
province of the Saskatchewan district at this mo<lb break="no"/>ment, the majority of the people living in that dis<lb break="no"/>trict could incorporate a railway extending all the <lb/>
way to the North Saskatchewan, at the foot of the <lb/>
Rocky Mountains. A railway of immense extent <lb/>
could be incorporated in a territory although the <lb/>
vast majority of the inhabitants may reside in a <lb/>
very limited district. I do not think, however, <lb/>
that would apply to tramways, which are in their <lb/>
nature local, and extend to a very short distance; <lb/>
nor do I think it would apply to telephone com<lb break="no"/>panies in towns. I do not see why, if you confer <lb/>
any municipal institutions upon them, you should <lb/>
not confer the power to incorporate a telephone <lb/>
company. You have given them powers implying <lb/>
a much larger degree of responsibility, and it <lb/>
seems to me that powers relating to tramway and <lb/>
telephone companies might safely be entrusted to <lb/>
the Legislature of the territories. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. I agree with the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber, and there is no objection to striking out the <lb/>
words "tramways and telephones." But I think <lb/>
it advisable that we should keep in our own hands <lb/>
the control of the water powers. That is a very <lb/>
important matter, and I believe that companies <lb/>
will be formed for the development of the water <lb/>
powers there. But until provinces are established <lb/>
in the territories I think we should keep the con<lb break="no"/>trol of the water powers in our own hands. <lb/></p>

<cb/>

<p><persName ref="pers:WATS2">Mr. WATSON</persName>. I think the arguments used by <lb/>
my hon. friend from North York (Mr. Mulock) <lb/>
should have some weight, especially with members <lb/>
from the North-West. I was a little surprised to <lb/>
hear the hon. member for Saskatchewan (Mr. <lb/>
Macdowall express the opinion that we should <lb/>
curtail the powers of the North-West Council. <lb/>
That body represents the people of the territories, <lb/>
and I think they should have all the powers of a <lb/>
Local Legislature, which they ask for. We can <lb/>
easily understand that a North-West company <lb/>
might wish to orgamize for the purpose of building <lb/>
a tramway or short railway <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDOWALL</persName>. Tramways are included <lb/>
now. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WATS2">Mr. WATSON</persName>,—for the purpose of opening up <lb/>
a coal mine, for instance, or a steamship company <lb/>
for the purpose of owning a steamship. Under this <lb/>
Bill that Legislature will not be able to exercise <lb/>
such powers. What harm could arise from the <lb/>
representatives of the North-West having power to <lb/>
grant the privilege of constructing a railway? I <lb/>
do not agree with the hon. member for Saskatche<lb break="no"/>wan that it is necessary to subsidize every railway <lb/>
in that country. I think men might have sufficient <lb/>
interest there, they might acquire sufficiently large <lb/>
tracts of land or coal-fields as to justify them in <lb/>
building a railway without coming here for a <lb/>
subsidy: and I would prefer seeing the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Saskatchewan, with his knowledge of the <lb/>
North-West, showing a disposition not to be tied <lb/>
to the apron strings of the Dominion for so many long <lb/>
years, but rather to have the people of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West depend on their own resources, and do their <lb/>
own business in their own way. The provinces <lb/>
have power to grant railway charters, though that <lb/>
power was interfered with for some time, we know <lb/>
with what result. I do not see why the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Assembly should not have the same power, <lb/>
and I am rather surprised at an hon. gentleman <lb/>
coming from the North-West wishing that it should <lb/>
not be granted. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDOWALL</persName>. I think I can remove <lb/>
some of the surprise of the hon. member. He <lb/>
represents the small Province of Manitoba, and, <lb/>
when I say the small province, I speak compar<lb break="no"/>atively. The North-West Territories are immense, <lb/>
and, compared with them, the Province of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba is of small area though thickly populated; and <lb/>
it has a much larger revenue, because the total <lb/>
revenue of the North-West Territories, from all <lb/>
territorial sources, does not exceed about $20,000. <lb/>
Therefore, it would be premature to grant the <lb/>
North-West Assembly those extensive powers. It <lb/>
is in the interest of the people of the North-West <lb/>
that we should make the hon. members of this <lb/>
House understand that they are the Provincial <lb/>
Government of the North-West Territories, that <lb/>
upon their shoulders rests the responsibility of aid<lb break="no"/>ing the construction of railways in those territories, <lb/>
that they must redeem the responsibilities of the <lb/>
Provincial Government, as well as the Dominion <lb/>
lovernment, so long as they continue to possess <lb/>
those powers. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). It seems to me that we <lb/>
ought to make provision for the constitution of the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly, for conferring upon it power <lb/>
over its own existence, power to provide for the <lb/>
division of the country into electoral districts, for <lb/>

<pb n="3933" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03933.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3933</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 14, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">3934</fw>

the qualifications of members and for the qualifica<lb break="no"/>tion of electors. <lb/></p> 

<p>On section 10, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I would urge upon the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment that they should consider sub-section 2. The <lb/>
next is a very useful sub-section, and will meet a <lb/>
difficulty which occurred in Calgary, but this sub<lb break="no"/>section will work in this way: The Legislative <lb/>
Assembly is to have power to determine by an or<lb break="no"/>dinance where a deputy sheriff may be appointed, <lb/>
and then it is provided that each sheriff "shall <lb/>
appoint a deputy or deputies at such places within <lb/>
the district" as are determined by the Legislative <lb/>
Assembly. I think the sheriff in Regina has juris<lb break="no"/>diction as far as Moose Jaw in the west, and as far <lb/>
as Fort Qu'Appelle and Qu'Appelle Station in the <lb/>
east. Mr. Davidson represents Fort Qu'Appelle, Mr. <lb/>
Sutherland will no doubt again represent Qu'Appelle <lb/>
Station, and Moose Jaw will be represented by an<lb break="no"/>other member. Each of these places will urge the <lb/>
Assembly to pass an ordinance compelling the sheriff <lb/>
to appoint a deputy, so that you will have three de<lb break="no"/>puties. Speaking subject to correction, I believe that <lb/>
all over the Dominion the sheriff is only obliged to <lb/>
have one deputy, but here you put this burden on <lb/>
the sheriff at Regina, who is not paid within one-<lb break="yes"/>tenth as much as most of the sheriffs throughout <lb/>
the Dominion. This will reduce his income, and <lb/>
the Minister of the Interior, who knows the North-<lb break="yes"/>West well, knows what the scanty income of the <lb/>
sheriff amounts to. It will reduce the income of <lb/>
the sheriffs to such a small sum that you cannot <lb/>
get a respectable man to take the office. Let me <lb/>
point out, further, that you are making a provision <lb/>
here for the deputy sheriff giving bonds. The sheriff <lb/>
has given bonds; he is to be responsible for him<lb break="no"/>self, and he is also to be responsible for the deputy <lb/>
sheriff. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. So he is in Ontario. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Ontario is a very much richer <lb/>
province, and he is only to appoint one deputy. <lb/>
Here he may have to appoint three. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. The deputy gets constables <lb/>
often to do his work. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I dare say he does, but so <lb/>
does the sheriff get constables in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West to help him. But I want to point out that <lb/>
you will reduce the income of a sheriff to about <lb/>
$500 a year, and you will not get a respectable man <lb/>
to take it. Now, if there were four or five centres <lb/>
represented by a member in the Assembly you <lb/>
would have each one of them clamouring to have a <lb/>
deputy appointed. We know the state of things <lb/>
in the territories very well, and we know that if <lb/>
you lay before the members of the Assembly any <lb/>
means of increasing their patronage they will try <lb/>
to do it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILLIES</persName>. Would not deputy sheriffs be <lb/>
required? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Let me give an illustration: He <lb/>
will go to Fort Qu'Appelle, he will go down to <lb/>
Qu'Appelle Station, or to Moose Jaw, but at the <lb/>
same time without being compelled to do it. He <lb/>
has a deputy in Moose Jaw, he has a deputy at <lb/>
Fort Qu'Appelle, and at Qu'Appelle Station, and <lb/>
he can take a gentleman engaged in one kind of <lb/>
business or another, pay him a small commission, and <lb/>
the man is ready to act for him. But the minute <lb/>

<cb/>

you make it compulsory to appoint a deputy, then <lb/>
you place somebody in a position to exact a much <lb/>
larger remuneration from him. I never heard <lb/>
that there was any incoinvenience; I doubt very <lb/>
much if either of my hon. friends from Alberta <lb/>
(Mr. Davis) or Saskatchewan (Mr. Macdowall) has <lb/>
heard any complaints as to the way the work of <lb/>
the sheriffs has been done in their district. I <lb/>
never heard any complaint, and it seems to me to <lb/>
be almost wanton to try to remedy a grievance in <lb/>
regard to which there has been no complaint. I <lb/>
think the difficulty arose in regard to the sheriff in <lb/>
Calgary, who insisted, himself, in going long dis<lb break="no"/>tances. I think there was some difficulty of that <lb/>
sort, and it was in order to meet that difficulty <lb/>
that this clause has been introduced. I think, my<lb break="no"/>self, that you might devise a sub-section that would <lb/>
prevent any grievance occurring. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. How are you going to get along <lb/>
with the incapacity of a sheriff? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. There is a sub-section dealing <lb/>
with that afterwards, in case of a vacancy arising <lb/>
by reason of the sheriffs incapacity or otherwise. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. It says his deputy may perform <lb/>
his duties until his successor is appointed. I am <lb/>
supposing that there is no deputy. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. I have had a communication <lb/>
from the sheriff in my district since this Bill was <lb/>
printed, and he did not appear to object to the <lb/>
power of appointing deputies, but he did ask that <lb/>
the deputy should be compelled to give security. <lb/>
There is no particular object in that which I can <lb/>
see. I suppose the sheriff could take security <lb/>
from his deputy when be appointed him. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Because he is respon<lb break="no"/>sible. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. No representation has been <lb/>
made to me, but I understand there have been re<lb break="no"/>quests made for more judicial districts. There <lb/>
was a difficulty in getting different processes and <lb/>
taking out registration papers, and they wanted <lb/>
more judicial districts, which meant more judges <lb/>
and a full court. That was thought to be advis<lb break="no"/>able, but that if it was found necessary, in the <lb/>
interest of the country, that these deputies should <lb/>
be appointed, it would meet their wishes in that <lb/>
regard, and there will be deputy sheriffs in different <lb/>
    points of the territories to get over that difficulty. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. I think it is absolutely neces<lb break="no"/>sary. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FLIN3">Mr. FLINT</persName>. I think there is a great deal of <lb/>
weight in what the member for Assiniboia (Mr. <lb/>
Davin) says. I think that it is almost too hard <lb/>
upon sheriffs to compel them to appoint deputies. <lb/>
I also observe here that the Legislative Assembly <lb/>
is given power to prescribe the duties of the <lb/>
deputies. I should think it would be better <lb/>
that each sheriff should appoint a deputy, leav<lb break="no"/>ing it to be inferred that the powers of the <lb/>
deputy are the usual powers of a deputy <lb/>
under the common law, or under any law of this <lb/>
Parliament. But here we give a legislative body <lb/>
power to confer powers upon deputies, which may <lb/>
possibly differ from the owers of the sheriffs them<lb break="no"/>selves. There is no definition in this Act of the <lb/>
powers of the sheriffs and clerks, and I think <lb/>
we are going out of our way to allow the Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive Assembly to define the powers of deputies <lb/>

<pb n="3935" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03935.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3935</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3936</fw> 

and clerks. I think myself that the sheriffs <lb/>
are probably the most poorly paid officials, as at <lb/>
rule, in the country, and legislation tending to <lb/>
diminish their revenues ought to be very carefully <lb/>
considered. If the Legislature provides that the <lb/>
sheriffs or clerks may appoint deputies it would <lb/>
be ample to protect them and also to protect the the <lb/>
public. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). I understand the Min<lb break="no"/>ister of the Interior to state that there are some; <lb/>
very large districts over which the sheriff's duties <lb/>
extend, and it was found to be some inconvenience <lb/>
to go to the sheriff whenever it was necessary that   <lb/>
that official should be seen, or should be called <lb/>
upon to discharge certain duties, and it is proposed <lb/>
to divide his district into sub-districts, requiring <lb/>
him to appoint deputies in certain portions of the <lb/>
district over which he is sheriff. If that is so, and <lb/>
if it is a choice between requiring the deputy to <lb/>
act and the appointment of a new sheriff, then it <lb/>
might not be possible to leave it as a matter of <lb/>
option with the sheriff to appoint a deputy or not. <lb/>
It might be necessary in the public interest that <lb/>
a deputy sheriff should be named. In this sub<lb break="no"/>section, if it is allowed to stand, I do not think <lb/>
these words are necessary: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"That such powers as are from time to time determined   <lb/>
by an ordinance of the Legislative Assembly." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
        
<p>Of course, there are no ordinances any longer. <lb/>
When the Assembly becomes a representative body <lb/>
its Acts are not ordinances, but Acts. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. They are all called <lb/>
ordinances still. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). That is simply because, <lb/>
as the Minister will remember, there were certain <lb/>
nominated members sitting in the Assembly. The <lb/>
distinction is perfectly clear in law between an <lb/>
ordinance and an Act. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. There is no doubt <lb/>
that that wouldbe a more suitable expression. For <lb/>
three years past there has been no Council, but an <lb/>
Assembly. We have not changed the original Act, <lb/>
which provides that they should be called ordin<lb break="no"/>ances. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). We should do it now. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. Yes. Let me take a <lb/>
general view of the situation as regards sheriffs and <lb/>
clerks. Dealing first with the remarks of the hon. <lb/>
member for Yarmouth (Mr. Flint), I may say that <lb/>
the sheriffs are a little better off in the territories <lb/>
than in some parts of the Dominion, for in the <lb/>
territories, in addition to the fees, which are very <lb/>
liberal, they each receive a salary of $500 a year. <lb/>
During a visit I paid to the North-West I had <lb/>
the same experience as was encountered by every <lb/>
Minister, namely, that at nearly every settlement I <lb/>
heard complaints of delay, of expense and inconve<lb break="no"/>nience in litigation arising from the absence of de<lb break="no"/>puty sheriffs and deputy clerks. They all said: <lb/>
"We want a sheriff: we want a clerk." I explained <lb/>
that the policy was to havea sheriff for each dis<lb break="no"/>trict; but I saw no reason why a deputy sheriff <lb/>
should not be appointed at each place. The North-<lb break="yes"/>West Assembly has to enact the sheriffs' fees and <lb/>
to pass an Act regulating the number of deputy <lb/>
sheriffs and deputy clerks, and to provide a scale <lb/>
of remuneration for the officers, and the whole <lb/>
thing is subject to our review. If the Legislative <lb/> 

<cb/>

Assembly should insist on too many deputies and <lb/>
provide too low a scale of fees, the ordinance <lb/>
must be amended or disallowed. But the dif<lb break="no"/>ficulty presented by the people is a very <lb/>
serious one. Take the district of Alberta, for in<lb break="no"/>stance. The sheriff lives in Calgary. If a person <lb/>
in Edmonton desires to have a writ issued he must <lb/>
    send the writ down to Calgary to be issued. It is <lb/>
delivered to the sheriff at Calgary, the sheriff sends <lb/>
some one upto Edmonton, and he is paid travelling <lb/>
allowances for the whole distance. When the time <lb/>
comes for judgment he cannot get judgment at <lb/>
Edmonton, but he has to send to Calgary. He <lb/>
must get execution, and the officer must then <lb/>
travel to Edmonton again. There is no reason <lb/>
why there should not be a deputy at Edmonton <lb/>
capable of serving a writ the moment it is issued, <lb/>
or of issuing execution on the judgment. But to <lb/>
make it effective, there must be a deputy clerk who <lb/>
can issue a writ. When that is done the creditor <lb/>
at Edmonton having a debtor alongside him does <lb/>
not need to go to Calgary, but he can go to the <lb/>
clerk next door and have the writ issued, and can <lb/>
go to the deputy sheriff near by, and he can serve <lb/>
the writ on the debtor immediately. The whole pro<lb break="no"/>ceeding could be accomplished in a few moments and <lb/>
at very little expense. There would be no cost to the <lb/>
sheriff, but the Local Assembly should provide the <lb/>
way the deputy sheriff should be compensated for <lb/>
the service rendered in serving. When the time <lb/>
came for the creditor in Edmonton to get <lb/>
judgment against a debtor in Edmonton. instead <lb/>
of going to Calgary he goes to the deputy clerk <lb/>
and has execution issued. The execution is en<lb break="no"/>forced by the deputy sheriff. But in order to carry <lb/>
out that system we must give the Local Assembly <lb/>
power not only to say what they shall be paid, but <lb/>
to prescribe their duties, and unless this is done the <lb/>
deputy clerk would have no power to issue a writ <lb/>
unless he received instructions from the clerk, and <lb/>
the deputy sheriff would have no power unless he <lb/>
received instructions from the sheriff. But we <lb/>
enable the Legislative Assembly to introduce a <lb/>
system which is similar to that prevailing in the <lb/>
provinces. <lb/></p>
        <p>
On section 10, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FLIN3">Mr. FLINT</persName>. A sheriff or clerk may have several <lb/>
deputies, and the provision does not say which one <lb/>
shall perform his duties in case of death. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. The object is to keep <lb/>
alive all their powers in their respective districts. <lb/></p> 

<p>On section 80,   <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). These provisions of the <lb/>
North-West Territories Act were inserted at a <lb/>
time when the powers of the North-West Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture were very much more limited than they are <lb/>
at present. When we propose to confer upon them <lb/>
the power for the administration of justice in the <lb/>
North-West Territories, as an incident of that <lb/>
power would be the power to establish gaols and <lb/>
lock-ups, and so on; and yet we retain here all the <lb/>
power of providing places of confimnent, the same <lb/>
as if the original condition of things was to con<lb break="no"/>tinue. It seems to me that these provisions of <lb/>
section 80 ought to be considered, and that our <lb/>
legislation shouid be of a temporary character, and <lb/>
should provide for being superseded by the legis<lb break="no"/>lative functions of the Government of the terri<lb break="no"/>tories. <lb/></p>

<pb n="3937" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03937.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3937</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 14, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">3938</fw> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. The hon. gentleman <lb/>
will see that by section 13, sub-section 3, we give <lb/>
the Assembly power to maintain and manage <lb/>
prisons. By this section we simply take concur<lb break="no"/>rent power with them, in view of the fact that <lb/>
they have not the means at their disposal of keep<lb break="no"/>ing up the prisons necessary. Besides, the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of expense, the duty devolves upon us for <lb/>
providing for long term prisoners. This sec<lb break="no"/>tion simply enables us to exercise concurrent <lb/>
powers in keeping up goals and establishing as <lb/>
penitentiaries any building that may be available <lb/>
for that purpose. We have one at Prince Albert <lb/>
and another at Regina, and under powers like <lb/>
these, we will make them both penitentiaries and <lb/>
we take power here to arrange as to the way pri<lb break="no"/>soners should be kept. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). The Minister will see <lb/>
that he is taking power here to provide places <lb/>
where prisoners may be detained for trial. That is <lb/>
an ordinary gaol and not a penitentiary. It seems <lb/>
to me that this legislation should be temporary, <lb/>
and that we ought to indicate that our powers are <lb/>
temporary. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. We must have power <lb/>
at present, because we must provide the accommo<lb break="no"/>dation. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Or give them the money <lb/>
to do it, which would seem to me to be the better <lb/>
way. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. We keep up the police <lb/>
prisons at present and we do all that kind of work. <lb/>
I fancy that for a good many years to come these <lb/>
are the powers under which the prisoners will be <lb/>
taken care of, and not the powers that we give to <lb/>
the Assembly. The whole Act is temporary of <lb/>
course, in view of the fact that ultimately the dis<lb break="no"/>tricts will be formed in provinces. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). But the Minister knows <lb/>
how much more easy it is to assume expenses of <lb/>
this sort than it is to shift the burden on some one <lb/>
else at a future period; and if we are going to shift <lb/>
the burden, it ought to be clearly indicated. I <lb/>
think it would be a more prudent course in the end <lb/>
tofurnish the North-West Assembly with the means <lb/>
of establishing gaols and lock-ups where the popu<lb break="no"/>lation is verysparse than it would be to undertake <lb/>
to provide them ourselves. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FLIN3">Mr. FLINT</persName>. I see that a change has been made <lb/>
in the wording of Clause 80. It formerly said that <lb/>
the Governor in Council "may cause to be erected" <lb/>
these buildings, and this clause simply says that he <lb/>
may direct that any building or buildings shall be <lb/>
a gaol or lock-up. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. Instead of erecting a <lb/>
building for the purpose, we may want to use one <lb/>
already erected. But the mere power to erect build<lb break="no"/>ings there is practically useless, because we shall <lb/>
have to come to Parliament for the necessary funds. <lb/></p> 

<p>On section 17, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I do not see very well what ad<lb break="no"/>vantage there is in making this change. It seems <lb/>
to me that it will lay entirely into the hands of <lb/>
the North-West Mounted Police. Suppose an in<lb break="no"/>former goes to a policeman, and then the police<lb break="no"/>man goes and lays the information; the policeman <lb/>
will get half the fine and not the informer, although <lb/>

<cb/>

after all it was the informer who brought the guilty <lb/>
act to justice. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. The matter has been <lb/>
brought to our notice by one of the judges in the <lb/>
North-West, who represents that there is great <lb/>
difficulty sometimes in ascertaining who the person <lb/>
is who is entitled to the moiety of the penalty. <lb/>
The informer, using the term in its ordinary <lb/>
sense, may be one person or several who give the <lb/>
information on which the proceedings are taken; <lb/>
and as there is often strife as to who should have the <lb/>
moiety, we think it better to say that the person <lb/>
who lays the information shall be entitled to it. <lb/></p> 

<p>On section 18, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FLIN3">Mr. FLINT</persName>. Suppose the person has no money <lb/>
to pay the fine, should there not be some power of <lb/>
imprisonment? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. That is provided for <lb/>
in the Summary Convictions Act, and the procedure <lb/>
follows that. The change made is simply this: In <lb/>
one of the districts a permit to A.B. to have five <lb/>
gallons of liquor enables C.D. to have it in his <lb/>
custody. If C.D. be a saloon keeper, as he often is, <lb/>
he may have a permit for every letter of the <lb/>
alphabet, and still no permit of his own; and this <lb/>
is to oblige the person who has the liquor to show <lb/>
a permit to himself. It is to make the law as to <lb/>
permits more stringent. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI9">Mr. DAVIS</persName> (Alberta). I would like to explain <lb/>
a case which I have seen happen with my own eyes. <lb/>
Suppose a man has a bottle of brandy, and another <lb/>
man who sees it informs upon him, he will be fined <lb/>
this $200 or go to prison. I think the clause is <lb/>
extreme. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. I suppose it is; that <lb/>
is the case with every law. It is easy for any <lb/>
person who is willing to do so, to fabricate evidence <lb/>
or commit perjury. But with regard to all these <lb/>
laws for the punishment of statutory offences, we <lb/>
have to make the possession of the forbidden article <lb/>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">prima facie</hi> evidence of the guilt of the party. I <lb/>
do not see any other way of doing it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI9">Mr. DAVIS</persName> (Alberta). The way I see of doing <lb/>
it is to do away with the obnoxious law. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Of course the Assembly will have <lb/>
power now to deal with that matter; but it seems <lb/>
pretty hard that a hotel-keeper is liable to be pun<lb break="no"/>ished if the liquor is found upon the person of a <lb/>
guest: The hotel-keeper might be pinished and <lb/>
not the man. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. The man is on the <lb/>
premises, and the liquor is on the man. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. The man might have liquor in his <lb/>
room, and it would be on the premises of the hotel-<lb break="yes"/>keeper <lb/></p> 

<p>On section 20, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. When I had the honour of addres<lb break="no"/>sing a few words to the House on this subject, I <lb/>
quoted some of the clauses of the bill of rights sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to the Government of the Dominion, con<lb break="no"/>cerning the rights and privileges of the minority. I <lb/>
omitted, however, to quote section 10, which says <lb/>
that the transfer by the Hudson's Bay Company to <lb/>
the Government of this country would not pre<lb break="no"/>judice, in any way, the rights of the people of the <lb/>
North-West. If I understood the hon. member for <lb/>
East Grey (Mr. Sproule) rightly, he said that it <lb/>

<pb n="3939" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03939.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3939</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3940</fw> 

would not be contrary to the constitution to deprive <lb/>
to-day the French population, the minority in the <lb/>
North-West, of the right to speak French, because <lb/>
the statute incorporating that country to the <lb/>
Dominion is a federal statute. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. The hon. gentleman misunder<lb break="no"/>stood me, because I never said anything about the <lb/>
French language. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. Then I did not hear sufficiently <lb/>
from my seat what the hon. gentleman said. I am <lb/>
going to draw the attention of the House to a most <lb/>
important question. I humbly submit that we have <lb/>
no right whatever, under the present circumstances, <lb/>
to pass this clause. I admit that the governmnent, <lb/>
in respecting the rights of the minority as to <lb/>
education, have made a step in the right direction, <lb/>
and I fully endorse their action in that respect. I <lb/>
admit also that to preserve the right of the minority <lb/>
to the use of the French language before the courts, <lb/>
is another good feature of the Bill; but they are <lb/>
giving power to a local council to regulate, by <lb/>
ordinance or otherwise, what language they will <lb/>
be pleased to use in their proceedings and the <lb/>
reports of their proceedings. That amounts to <lb/>
    saying that this Parliament <hi rendition="simple:italic">de facto</hi> abolishes the <lb/>
French language, as far as that goes, for, as we <lb/>
well know, the majority there will, on the very <lb/>
first day, declare that the expense and trouble of <lb/>
having their proceedings recorded in both languages <lb/>
will be too great and the French language will be <lb/>
abolished. Moreover, we are admitting a principle <lb/>
I cannot endorse, and which I am sure a great pro<lb break="no"/>portion of the people of this Dominion will not sup<lb break="no"/>port. That is the principle that, at any moment, we <lb/>
may grant to the majority of a province the right to <lb/>
take away the liberties, the franchise and the privi<lb break="no"/>leges of the minorities, with regard to education or <lb/>
religion, which amounts to the same thing, and to <lb/>
language. I am opposed to that principle. The <lb/>
hon. member for Queen's (Mr. Davies) said he was <lb/>
in favour of provincial autonomy, and wanted to <lb/>
leave to the provinces full control in these matters. <lb/>
I am also an autonomist but will not go so far as <lb/>
that. I hold that when interests are common, <lb/>
when it is a material question, when the question <lb/>
is one which relates to commerce or civil property, <lb/>
in which the interests of all are homogeneous, <lb/>
every Parliament should have full power, within <lb/>
its jurisdiction, to deal with such questions. But <lb/>
no authority should be given to Local Parliaments <lb/>
to decide upon questions of education and language, <lb/>
where the interests are not common, where they <lb/>
are often hostile, and in which it is only by the <lb/>
spirit of Christian philosophy and forbearance these <lb/>
hostile interests of religion and language can exist <lb/>
peacefully together. If you touch those questions, <lb/>
by giving the right to a majority to take away the <lb/>
rights of a minority, you are carrying the principle <lb/>
of autonomy too far. You are not only giving the <lb/>
power of preservation to the local authorities but <lb/>
you are giving them a power of destruction. You <lb/>
are giving them power to destroy vested rights, and <lb/>
acting in direct opposition to our censtitution, not <lb/>
only to the law of this Parliament but to the <lb/>
law as formulated by the English Parliament. I <lb/>
have already expressed the sentiment, and I am <lb/>
not ashamed to repeat it, and in doing so I speak <lb/>
the sentiment of a great many, that I am first of <lb/>
all Catholic, that I am, in the second place, an Eng<lb break="no"/>lish subject speaking French, and that it is only in <lb/>

<cb/>

the third place that I am a politician. Whenever <lb/>
the interests of my religion are concerned, they take <lb/>
precedence over all other interests. The question <lb/>
of language occupies the second place, and it is <lb/>
only in the third place that I am a politician; and <lb/>
all the interests possible of party will never make <lb/>
me change one of my convictions with regard to <lb/>
the religion or the language of my forefathers. It <lb/>
is all very well to say that a motto of a party is <lb/>
such and such. My motto is, first, that the vested <lb/>
rights of religion and language shall be respected, <lb/>
and to no party in the world shall I submit my <lb/>
convictions in that respect. My religion teaches <lb/>
me to respect the rights and privileges of others, <lb/>
and I will do so; but in return I ask that the priv<lb break="no"/>ileges, the vested rights, so far as we are concerned, <lb/>
shall be also everywhere respected. In the pre<lb break="no"/>amble of the British North America Act, I find <lb/>
these words: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"And whereas it is expedient that provision be made <lb/>
for the eventual admission into the Union of other parts <lb/>
of British North America." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
        
<p>Now, if we refer to clause 146, we find it is there <lb/>
provided that the future admission of provinces <lb/>
must be subject to the provisions of this Act. That <lb/>
is very explicit. It makes the British North Amer<lb break="no"/>ica Act apply to the other parts of the Dominion, <lb/>
when admitted as provinces. Now, what do we <lb/>
find? I beg to draw the attention of the hon. Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Justice to the Statutes of Canada of 1872, <lb/>
in which he will find a copy of the Address of both <lb/>
the Senate and the House of Commons, praying <lb/>
Her Majesty the Queen to issue the proclamation <lb/>
necessary to bring these territories into the Union. <lb/>
We are today responsible for what was agreed to <lb/>
by the House of Commons and Senate then, and <lb/>
Parliament then said: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"We most humbly beg to express to Your Majesty that <lb/>
we are willing to assume the duties and obligations of <lb/>
government and 1egislation as regards these territories; <lb/>
that in the event of Her Majesty's Government agreeing <lb/>
to transfer to Canada jurisdiction and control over the <lb/>
said regions, the Government and Parliament of Canada <lb/>
will be ready to provide that the local rights of any cor<lb break="no"/>poration, company or individual—" <lb/></p>
</quote>
<p>Company or individual— <lb/></p>
        <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>—"shall be respected." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
        
<p>Do we respect those rights? I say we do not, <lb/>
when we give to the majority the power of taking <lb/>
them away in certain respects, and if we admit the <lb/>
principle once, we commit a wrong that will open <lb/>
the door for future abuses and expose this country <lb/>
to tremendous dangers. If we do that, we will <lb/>
    change the spirit of the constitution, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">entente <lb/>
formelle</hi>, the express agreement, the formal will of <lb/>
the people, and legislate against the interests there <lb/>
protected. We will then see every year claims, <lb/>
either through excessive zeal or other causes, to <lb/>
destroy, one by one, all the guarantees which have <lb/>
been given to us. For my part, I will not propose <lb/>
an amendment. If one is proposed I will vote for <lb/>
but I desire to register my protest, and to say <lb/>
that from my point of view we should in no way <lb/>
extend the principle of autonomy so as to give to <lb/>
the majorities the power to take away from the <lb/>
minorities privileges which they enjoy, where their <lb/>
interests are not common but are hostile. How<lb break="no"/>ever, I have done my duty, and I will take no <lb/>
further responsibility in the matter. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. The clause as it is <lb/>
inserted in the Bill and supported by the Govern<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="3941" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03941.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3941</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 14, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">3942</fw>

ment is not based on any ground of autonomy <lb/>
in regard to the territories. On the contrary, as <lb/>
to the territorial Government, as it is estab<lb break="no"/>lished either by the original Act or by this <lb/>
Bill, the whole system is temporary, and the provi<lb break="no"/>sions of the law now being enacted are temporary. <lb/>
Parliament will have complete control over the <lb/>
whole subject when it lays down the constitution <lb/>
which may be given to any provinces which may be <lb/>
created in the North-West. In the meantime we <lb/>
are simply adopting the terms of the resolution on <lb/>
this subject passed last session, and the language <lb/>
which then received the approval of the House. In <lb/>
fact, this section carefully preserves the language <lb/>
of the resolution of last session, and after the most <lb/>
careful consideration it was then adopted with a de<lb break="no"/>gree of unanimity which was very satisfactory in <lb/>
view of the feelings which were likely to be evoked <lb/>
in dealing with a subject of this kind. In addition to <lb/>
    the provision that the <hi rendition="simple:italic">status quo</hi> shall be maintained <lb/>
for the present, there is the provision that, after <lb/>
the next Assembly is elected, the Assembly shall <lb/>
he allowed to regulate its own proceedings as to <lb/>
the language to be used in the Assembly itself, as <lb/>
to the language in which the proceedings shall <lb/>
he recorded and as to the language in which <lb/>
those proceedings shall be circulated. The hon. <lb/>
gentleman will see that, while it is only a <lb/>
reasonable concession, it is also an inevitable <lb/>
concession, because any legislative body will <lb/>
inevitably regulate the mode in which its <lb/>
business shall he conducted, and, if even there <lb/>
were no obligations resting upon any Legislative <lb/>
Assembly to listen to the views of a gentleman who <lb/>
desired to express himself in any other than the <lb/>
English language, I am sure that in this country <lb/>
and in almost any civilized country, the views he <lb/>
desired to so express would be heard with due re<lb break="no"/>spect. I cited to the House last session, when this <lb/>
matter was under discussion, instances which had <lb/>
occurred to my own knowledge in provinces where <lb/>
there had been no idea of preserving the French <lb/>
tongue by law and yet where that language was heard <lb/>
with as much respect and attention as the English <lb/>
tongue when any gentleman chose to use it. It is <lb/>
also to be observed that we still have a parental <lb/>
handover the territorial Government and Assembly, <lb/>
and that it is in our power, if at any time the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature should not think fit to print the Acts in the <lb/>
French or German or any language required to <lb/>
give complete publicity amongst the settlers in <lb/>
the North-West, to see that that provision is made <lb/>
in the most ample manner. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. I am very much pleased with <lb/>
these remarks of the Minister. I am pleased with <lb/>
his statement that there will bea guarantee in the <lb/>
future, when we want to use the ideas of the <lb/>
framers of the present Bill, and I am not so pre<lb break="no"/>judiced as not to recognize the peculiar circum<lb break="no"/>stances which surrounded the discussion of the Bill <lb/>
of the member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) <lb/>
last session. It is not necessary for me to say now <lb/>
all that I think in regard to this matter, and I am <lb/>
glad to find that this Parliament remains as a safe<lb break="no"/>guard for the rights of the minority. I think we <lb/>
sanctioned a false position last year, and I pro<lb break="no"/>tested by my vote then, and I now protest by <lb/>
my words against the same error. In Manitoba, <lb/>
in spite of the constitutional principle; the statutes <lb/>
are no more printed in French, though a large <lb/>

<cb/>

number of the population are French. They <lb/>
were the majority a few years ago, but they are not <lb/>
so any longer er. Is it not the right of those people <lb/>
who contribute their share to the public purse to <lb/>
have the laws of the land published in their own <lb/>
language? I am sure that no court of justice which <lb/>
has any self-respect will declare that this law is not <lb/>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">ultra vires</hi> according to the laws of this country <lb/>
and according to the laws of England. In the <lb/>
meantime, however, its provisions are carried out. <lb/>
Considering actual circumstances, the declaration <lb/>
of the Minister of Justice is a great satifaction to <lb/>
me, though I have lodged my protest against the <lb/>
present measure. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WALL1">Mr. WALLACE</persName>. I think it is a matter of great <lb/>
satisfaction that this clause has been brought for<lb break="no"/>ward. I regret that the Government has not seen <lb/>
its way clear to have also provided that the pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings before the courts should have been dealt <lb/>
with in the same way as the proceedings in the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly, and that full power in that <lb/>
matter should be given to the North-West Council <lb/>
as it is to the Local Legislatures. We have a much <lb/>
larger French population in Ontario than there <lb/>
will likely be in the North-West Territories for <lb/>
many years to come, and I believe we have found <lb/>
no difficulty or no serious inconvenience from the <lb/>
fact that we have only one official language in <lb/>
the courts in that province. In fact, every <lb/>
man, whether French, English or German—be<lb break="no"/>cause we have a very large German population <lb/>
in this province also—has experienced no prac<lb break="no"/>tical difficulty in regard to this matter in the <lb/>
Province of Ontario, and I apprehend there <lb/>
will be no serious difficulty whatever in the <lb/>
North-West. But this matter is one that the <lb/>
provinces have a right to decide for them <lb/>
selves, and the Government is wisely conferring <lb/>
the power upon the North-West Assembly after <lb/>
the next election to exercise that power so far as <lb/>
the proceedings of the Assembly are concerned. <lb/>
Another question which comes up in the same con<lb break="no"/>nection and which has been referred to this after<lb break="no"/>noon is the question of having separate schools, if <lb/>
it is the wish of the people in the locality. That <lb/>
is a question; as the hon. member for Muskoka <lb/>
(Mr. O'Brien) said in his speech, which is a very <lb/>
large and important one, and I think cannot be <lb/>
fully and freely dealt with at the close of a session <lb/>
such as this. I am gratified by the statement of <lb/>
the Minister of Justice which if I understood it <lb/>
was that Parliament shall have complete and <lb/>
untrammelled power in the future to confer upon <lb/>
those territories the provincial rights which the <lb/>
other, provinces possess, to legislate on all those <lb/>
questions, not only as regards language but as <lb/>
regards schools and all other subjects over <lb/>
which   Local Legislatures have complete control. <lb/>
I am a little surprised at the action of the hon. <lb/>
member for Bellechase (Mr. Amyot), whom I <lb/>
have heard in this House on so many occasions, <lb/>
asserting the inalienable right of the provinces <lb/>
to legislate in their own interests without being <lb/>
trammelled in any way by the Dominion Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, and now taking a complete somersault, <lb/>
and advocating that the provinces should not be <lb/>
given those rights, but that they should be retained <lb/>
by the Dominion Parliament. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man, I think, is performing a somersault too. He <lb/>

<pb n="3943" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03943.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3943</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3944</fw> 

forgets that he has just now made a tumble. Mr. <lb/>
Chairman, I will ask the Minister of Justice again <lb/>
to give his attention to the use of this word "or<lb break="no"/>dinance." The expression is used all through the <lb/>
Bill, "ordinance" instead of "law," and "or<lb break="no"/>dained" instead "enacted." Of course unless you <lb/>
define the word in the sense in which you use it, it <lb/>
would be really necessary to make the law conform <lb/>
to the present state of things, which it does not by <lb/>
the use of that word. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. I will give attention to <lb/>
that before we go into Committee again. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Before the Committee <lb/>
rises I would call attention to section 93 in section <lb/>
18 of the Bill, and to the words "in whose possession <lb/>
or on whose premises any intoxicating liquor or <lb/>
intoxicant of any kind is." The Minister will see <lb/>
    that that is not a <hi rendition="simple:italic">primâ facie</hi> presumption of guilt, <lb/>
it is a conclusive presumption, it is one that cannot <lb/>
be explained away by shifting the burden of proof <lb/>
from the party who will be inculpated. He has <lb/>
no permission to show that the liquor did not <lb/>
belong to him, or that it was brought on his pre<lb break="no"/>mises by some other person. In the criminal law <lb/>
you have a provision that the party in whose <choice><sic>per<lb break="no"/>mises</sic><corr>premises</corr></choice> counterfeit dies are found, is held presumpt<lb break="no"/>ively guilty, but he is not conclusively guilty. He <lb/>
may prove that the dies were brought there by some <lb/>
other person. It seems to me those words would <lb/>
make the guilt conclusive, and the party would not <lb/>
be at liberty to show that the liquor was not his <lb/>
and that it was not brought here by him. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. About the somersault, we may <lb/>
as well settle that question at once, seeing that we <lb/>
are not very much in a hurry. I am surprised that <lb/>
a love for the autonomy of the provinces has arisen <lb/>
so suddenly in the breast of the hon. gentleman <lb/>
from West York (Mr. Wallace). He did not seem <lb/>
to understand that question until he had an oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity to attack the Catholic religion an the <lb/>
French language in the North-West. Then, sud<lb break="no"/>denly he becomes an autonomist, and he under<lb break="no"/>stands the full obligation of this Parliament to <lb/>
grant all possible powers to the Local Legislatures. <lb/>
Before that he did not understand it at all. Here<lb break="no"/>tofore he wanted this Parliament to retain every <lb/>
power, and he desired that the Local Legislatures <lb/>
should have as little power as possible. But when <lb/>
he wanted to give equal rights to the Catholics by <lb/>
taking away from them their right to separate <lb/>
schools, and when he wanted to give equal rights <lb/>
to the French people by taking away from them <lb/>
their right to speak French, then he began to <lb/>
understand provincial autonomy. When he per<lb break="no"/>ceived that in this Parliament he would have to <lb/>
face one-third of the members of the House, he <lb/>
would have to face the possibility of a division <lb/>
within each party, and that he might endanger his <lb/>
own party, then he found the splendid plan of the <lb/>
autonomy of the provinces, and he said Let <lb/>
us give to a majority in the North-West, favour<lb break="no"/>able to the sentiments of my heart, a power that <lb/>
we cannot exercise at Ottawa; let us delegate to <lb/>
them such powers that they may be able to do to <lb/>
the Catholics and to the Frenchmen in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West that which we are not able to do at Ottawa. <lb/>
If ever there was a somersault performed, the <lb/>
hon gentleman has performed it very skilfully <lb/>
and very elegantly. I will tell the hon. gentleman <lb/>
what we understand by the word "autonomy." <lb/>

<cb/>

We believe that Confederation consists of diverse <lb/>
parts. There is a Government for the common <lb/>
interests of the whole, and there are local Govern<lb break="no"/>ments for the diverse interests of the parts. Each <lb/>
Legislature has got special lights defined by the <lb/>
constitution, and within those rights each Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture must be entirely free and all-powerful within <lb/>
the limits of its jurisdiction. That is the autonomy <lb/>
of the provinces under Confederation. One of the <lb/>
principles of Confederation was that the basis of <lb/>
union would not be infringed upon. What was <lb/>
the spirit of the Act at the opening of the <lb/>
conference? It was that the religion and the <lb/>
language of every subject should be respected. <lb/>
Would the hon. gentleman seriously tell us <lb/>
that if, in the beginning, we had been told <lb/>
that under Confederation some means could be <lb/>
devised and attempted to take away from us the <lb/>
right to speak French or to worship God in the way <lb/>
our conscience dictated—does he suppose that we <lb/>
would ever have consented to join the union? <lb/>
He knows bettet than that. It is only by hidden <lb/>
ways, by devices which are not avowed, that he <lb/>
tries to reach his object. I am sure that with <lb/>
his good heart, if he perceived that he was doing <lb/>
a real injustice, he would step backwards. I am <lb/>
sure he will not try to use his influence to take away <lb/>
from a fellow-subject the right to act, or to speak, <lb/>
or to pray as he pleases, and as the sentiment of his <lb/>
heart may inspire him. What would he say if we, <lb/>
in the Province of Quebec, endeavoured to take away <lb/>
from the minority any right that they enjoy as to <lb/>
language or religion? I may tell him that, whether <lb/>
we would be wrong or right, we shall not do it, <lb/>
because we are just. We have learned in our lan<lb break="no"/>guage the laws of nations and the laws of forbear<lb break="no"/>ance; and we have learned in our religion the laws <lb/>
of personal property, and that material property is <lb/>
nothing compared to spiritual property. If he loves <lb/>
Confederation, if he loves the British flag, if he <lb/>
desires to form a grand nation on this continent, let <lb/>
him learn to exercise forbearance. Let him tend <lb/>
to the union of the hearts, let him give to everyone <lb/>
the privileges he cherishes, let him grant liberty to <lb/>
everyone, and he will see that party differences <lb/>
will be no cause of harm, and that whatever may <lb/>
be the party to which we belong we will be all <lb/>
Canadians, loving each other and fighting in com<lb break="no"/>mon for the welfare of the whole people. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WALL1">Mr. WALLACE</persName>. If the hon. gentleman would <lb/>
practise a little more of the virtues he preaches he <lb/>
would be a little more consistent in his character. <lb/>
There was no preposition made by me that any <lb/>
rights and privileges should be taken from any <lb/>
person. On the contrary, I proposed a recommend<lb break="no"/>ation that the people should be given more power <lb/>
to control their own local affairs in accordance with <lb/>
the system prevailing in other provinces, and that <lb/>
a portion of the rights and liberties given to Quebec <lb/>
and other provinces of the Dominion should be <lb/>
given to the people of the North- West Territories. <lb/>
That is a reasonable proposition, and it is one the <lb/>
people will demand and obtain. Although the <lb/>
country is not ready for a complete system of self-<lb break="yes"/>government, and the population is not sufficiently <lb/>
numerous to have all the machinery of the Local <lb/>
Government as in other provinces, yet by this <lb/>
Bill the people of the territories will gradually get <lb/>
their rights, and the measure will have to be ex<lb break="no"/>tended still further to give them the right of con<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="3945" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03945.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3945</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 14, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">3946</fw>

trol over their local matters, the proceedings of <lb/>
their courts, and of their Legislature, and the con<lb break="no"/>duct of their schools. That is all I advocated. If <lb/>
that is an example of want of liberality, of want of <lb/>
Christian spirit and of proper consideration for the <lb/>
feelings of others, I must plead guilty. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BEAU13">Mr. BEAUSOLEIL</persName>. I am perfectly ready to <lb/>
agree to the proposition made by the hon. member <lb/>
for West York (Mr. Wallace). If Parliament will <lb/>
give to the North-West Territories the same laws <lb/>
as they have imposed on Quebec, we shall be satis<lb break="no"/>fied. The hon. member must know that not only <lb/>
the Imperial Statute has not given to the Province <lb/>
of Quebec the right to prevent part of the popula<lb break="no"/>tion from speaking English, but it has gone further, <lb/>
and created a province within a province by enact<lb break="no"/>ing that the limits of 15 counties, in which at <lb/>
that time the majority of the people were English-<lb break="yes"/>speaking, could not be changed without the con<lb break="no"/>sent of the majority of their representatives. Even <lb/>
in the case that the whole of the other 50 members <lb/>
of the Legislative Assembly should consider the <lb/>
change necessary, such a change could not take <lb/>
place without the consent of the majority of those <lb/>
15 members. Far different is the position in the <lb/>
North-West. Not only is there no French pro<lb break="no"/>vince within the province, but to this day we have <lb/>
been unable to obtain a pledge that any represen<lb break="no"/>tation would be given to the French element in the <lb/>
territories. Such is the difference at present <lb/>
between the Province of Quebec and the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories, so far as language is concerned. <lb/>
So far as religious schools are concerned, is the hon. <lb/>
gentleman prepared to give to the territories the <lb/>
same rights and liberties we enjoy in the Province <lb/>
of Quebec? Then give us at once the widest law <lb/>
for separate schools that exists in the Dominion, <lb/>
for such is the school law of the Province of <lb/>
Quebec. The Dominion Parliament has no power <lb/>
to legislate on the question as to the language <lb/>
in which the laws shall be published, or the de<lb break="no"/>bates of Parliament conducted both in the Par<lb break="no"/>liament of the Province of Quebec and in the <lb/>
Dominion of Canada. The Imperial Parliament <lb/>
has put these two questions outside of the limit <lb/>
of provincial legislation, and laid-down these <lb/>
two principles, which are at the basis of the <lb/>
constitution: the equalityof Roman Catholics and <lb/>
Protestants, so far as schools are concerned, and <lb/>
the equality of the French and English-speaking <lb/>
populations, so far as the official languages are con<lb break="no"/>cerned. These two fundamental principles we <lb/>
desire to maintain. We want it formally recognized <lb/>
all over the Dominion that those rights now existing, <lb/>
both by usage and by law, shall be preserved, and <lb/>
therefore we protest against the granting to the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly of the territories of the right <lb/>
to abolish the French language, which is established <lb/>
by the constitution, and which cannot be taken <lb/>
away without violating the constitution, and de<lb break="no"/>stroying the harmony, good-will and happiness of <lb/>
thepopulation of this country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I do not desire to move the <lb/>
clause to which I spoke on the second reading, but <lb/>
I ask the Government to kindly consider it. The <lb/>
section I intended to move was as follows:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>The persons qualified to vote at the election for the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly, shall be male British subjects by <lb/>
birth or naturalization (other than unenfranchised In<lb break="no"/>dians, and members of the North-West Mounted Police), <lb/>
who have attained the full age of twenty-one years, who <lb/>

        
<cb/>

have resided in the North-West Territories for at least <lb/>
twelve months, and in the electoral district for at least <lb/>
three months, respectively, preceding the time of voting. <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
        
<p>The object of inserting such a clause was to pre<lb break="no"/>vent members of the North-West Mounted Police <lb/>
voting for any candidate for the Local Assembly, <lb/>
and I would impress on the Government the reason<lb break="no"/>ableness of this suggestion. Remember, it is a <lb/>
quasi-military body—that the members are shifted <lb/>
from one place to another. These are not the only <lb/>
considerations; they will vote for a candidate for <lb/>
an Assembly which has no power whatever to make <lb/>
laws affecting them. They are outside of its juris<lb break="no"/>diction, and yet they can come in and water, so to <lb/>
speak, the stock of the civil vote. At the election <lb/>
in North Regina there were 360 votes given, and <lb/>
of these 80 were police votes, and all were thrown <lb/>
for one candidate, not a single policeman voting for <lb/>
the candidate who was beaten there. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WALL1">Mr. WALLACE</persName> (York). Is the vote by ballot? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. No, it is an open vote; but by-<lb break="yes"/>and-bye it will be vote by ballot. The Assembly <lb/>
will have power to deal with that matter, but not <lb/>
as regards the next election. I do not press my <lb/>
clause, but I ask the Government, as I understand <lb/>
the Bill will remain in Committee, to consider the <lb/>
suggestion and decide whether this clause is neces<lb break="no"/>sary or not. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDONELL</persName> (Algoma). I am sorry to dif<lb break="no"/>fer from the hon. member for Assiniboia. We all <lb/>
know the members of the North-West Mounted <lb/>
Police are the sons of either Ontario or Quebec far<lb break="no"/>mers who go out there, probably, in the first place, <lb/>
to perfect themselves in militarv organization and in <lb/>
the next place, to become settlers in that district. <lb/>
If at legislative elections in Ontario farmers' sons <lb/>
have the right to vote, I think the Parliament of <lb/>
this Dominion should grant the North-West <lb/>
Mounted Police the same right; and indeed, I <lb/>
think it would be unfair to take away from them <lb/>
the right to vote they enjoyed in Manitoba, Que<lb break="no"/>bec or Ontario. With all due respect to the mem<lb break="no"/>ber, for Assiniboia, I am obliged to differ with him <lb/>
in this respect. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. My hon. friend will see that I am <lb/>
not very particular in pressing the matter. I do <lb/>
not think the members of the police care one pin <lb/>
about having the vote, and so far as I know it is <lb/>
of no advantage to them whatever. If it were <lb/>
any advantage to them I certainly should not wish <lb/>
to take it away. The reason I wish to take it <lb/>
away in regard to Dominion elections is, that it is <lb/>
of no advantage there at all, and they wish to be <lb/>
deprived of it. When they are farmers' sons in <lb/>
Ontario, as farmers' sons the Legislature of On<lb break="no"/>tario can pass Acts that will affect them; but as <lb/>
members of the Mounted Police, how can this <lb/>
Assembly pass any Act that will affect them? <lb/>
However, as the question is not to be pressed to<lb break="no"/>night, I will not speak further on the matter. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TROW1">Mr. TROW</persName>. I think the hon. member for Algo<lb break="no"/>ma (Mr. Macdonell) can speak feelingly in that <lb/>
respect, because I am aware that a very large <lb/>
proportion of those who voted for him were <lb/>
navvies, and have no permanent place of residence, <lb/>
and were from all parts of the Dominion, and <lb/>
many from the United States. I think he, cer<lb break="no"/>tainly, above all other men should advocate that. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDONELL</persName> (Algoma). I say right <lb/>
here to the whip for the Grit party on the other

<pb n="3947" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-14_Page_03947.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3947</fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3948</fw>

side of the House that he is entirely mistaken in <lb/>
what he says. The electors who voted for me were <lb/>
electors who were on the Dominion voters' lists; <lb/>
they were British subjects; they were twenty-one <lb/>
years of age, and they were entitled to vote. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Louder. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDONELL</persName> (Algoma). You need not say <lb/>
"louder," because you can hear me well enough. I <lb/>
defy any man in this House or any man in this coun<lb break="no"/>try to say that anyone voted for me in the district of <lb/>
Algoma who was not entitled to vote. But, under <lb/>
your one-sided Ontario Election Act, one-half of <lb/>
these individuals were not entitled to vote, where<lb break="no"/>as under the Dominion Franchise Act any man <lb/>
who is a British subject, twenty-one years of age, <lb/>
in receipt of an income of $150 a year in our dis<lb break="no"/>trict—it is $300 every place else—was entitled to <lb/>
vote. The hon. gentleman says they were navvies; <lb/>
a navvy, as I understand it, and I have some ex<lb break="no"/>perience in that way, is a man who delves for a <lb/>
living. He is a man who delves with the shovel, <lb/>
and puts it into a wheelbarrow, and wheels it off <lb/>
to a dump on a railway. That constitutes a navvy, <lb/>
and there was not a navvy in the whole district of <lb/>
Algoma during last election, because there were <lb/>
no railways building there. The men who voted for <lb/>
me were railway men, fishermen, farmers, lumber<lb break="no"/>men and miners. I tell the hon. the chief whip <lb/>
(Mr. Trow), on the other side of the House, that he <lb/>
is mistaken when he makes the statement that he <lb/>
did just now. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TROW1">Mr. TROW</persName>. The lists were made out years <lb/>
    before—<lb/> </p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. I would point out <lb/>
that this Bill does not apply to Algoma. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. I may say, Mr. Chairman, <lb/>
that the amendment that is proposed by the hon. <lb/>
member for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) will be <lb/>
considered between now and when the Committee <lb/>
meets again. <lb/></p> 

<p>Committee rose and reported progress. <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
        <head rendition="simple:centre">ADJOURNMENT—PERSONAL EXPLAN<lb break="no"/>ATION.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName> moved the adjournment <lb/>
of the House. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWIGHT</persName>. Before that <lb/>
motion is carried, Mr. Speaker, I desire to say a <lb/>
word or two with respect to an incident in the <lb/>
debate yesterday. The House will remember that <lb/>
an offer was made to me across the floor, by the <lb/>
hon. Minister of Inland Revenue, that I should <lb/>
appoint a couple of persons, if I liked, to inves<lb break="no"/>tigate the names of the persons who had subscribed <lb/>
to a testimonial to him. I desire to say, explicitly, <lb/>
that I made no reference to the Minister of Inland <lb/>
Revenue, or to the testimonial presented to him, <lb/>
because I did not regard the testimonial presented   <lb/>
to him as coming substantially within the lines of <lb/>
my resolution. It may have been—I was not <lb/>
aware of it until he mentioned it himself <lb/>
—that there were a small percentage of <lb/>
those who subscribed to his testimonial who <lb/>
would have been embraced in the resolution <lb/>
that I moved; but I do not think myself that his <lb/>
was a case similar to the others, nor do I believe <lb/>
that he was influenced to the detriment of the <lb/>
service by the subscriptions that he might have re<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

ceived. Therefore, I did not then deem it necessary, <lb/>
nor do I think it necessary now, in any shape, for <lb/>
the clearing of the hon. gentleman's character from <lb/>
imputations—which I beg to say I did not at all <lb/>
level at him—that any investigation should be <lb/>
made. It was very right and proper of him to offer <lb/>
it; but I, for my part, did not intend at all to in<lb break="no"/>clude him within the scope of my remarks. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. COSTIGAN</persName>. Mr. Speaker, I think after <lb/>
the statement made by the hon. gentleman (Sir <lb/>
Richard Cartwright) it is proper that I should <lb/>
express my gratification that he has made this <lb/>
statement. Not only do I consider it satisfactory <lb/>
to myself and my friends, but I think it is one of <lb/>
those incidents that every man in this Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment must feel pleased at the occurrence of. I <lb/>
think it is a pleasant thing that the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man, occupying the position that he does on the <lb/>
other side of the House, and during a session of <lb/>
Parliament ofcousiderahle excitement and acrimony, <lb/>
should have the fairness to make the statement <lb/>
freeing me from any charges of having been impro<lb break="no"/>perly influenced on account of such testimonial. I <lb/>
thank him for the very candid expression he has <lb/>
given, clearing me from any imputations which <lb/>
might be made. <lb/></p> 

<p>Motion agreed to; and House adjourned at 10.45 <lb/>
pm.</p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>