<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-03-13"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-03-13">13 March 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

         
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1905"/>.  
         

         <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="2405" to="2410"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-13_Page_2405.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-13_Page_2407.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-13_Page_2409.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-01-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-01-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-13_Page_2405">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-13_Page_2405.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-13_Page_2407">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-13_Page_2407.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-13_Page_2409">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-13_Page_2409.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="2405" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-13_Page_2405.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2405</fw> <fw type="dateline">MARCH 13, 1905</fw> <fw type="num">2406</fw> 
     
            <p>
    [...] telegraphed to the United States and 
     <lb/>
     to European countries in order to create 
     <lb/>
     the impression that if people come to Can<lb break="no"/>ada they will not find freedom here. There 
     <lb/>
     is nothing to justify such a statement from 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman. I had hoped that some 
     <lb/>
     of his own friends would take him to task 
     <lb/>
     for it ; I had hoped that representatives of 
     <lb/>
     the Conservative party would correct the 
     <lb/>
     impression that might have been made by 
     <lb/>
     his statement, occupying as he does the 
     <lb/>
     prominent position in that party. I hope 
     <lb/>
     they will yet avail themselves of the earliest 
     <lb/>
     oppormnity to say that so far as they are 
     <lb/>
     concerned they are not willing that the im<lb break="no"/>pression should go forth that this is the 
     <lb/>
     opinion of the Conservative party. That is 
     <lb/>
     not the opinion of the Liberal party. Long 
     <lb/>
     before the Liberal party came to power in 
     <lb/>
     Canada they were striving to bring about 
     <lb/>
     freedom of the very best kind, and the best 
     <lb/>
     order in this great country. But how is it 
     <lb/>
     with the Conservative party ? In their press 
     <lb/>
     from end to end of Canada, prominent news<lb break="no"/>papers have undertaken to preach the same 
     <lb/>
     doctrine propounded by the member for 
     <lb/>
     Victoria and Haliburton. If he is desirous 
     <lb/>
    that peace and harmony should reign in 
     <lb/>Canada, let him address himself to the 
     <lb/>newspapers of his own party, and ask them  
     <lb/>to take the lesson that he attempts to preach 
     <lb/>to hon. gentlemen on this side of the House. 
     <lb/>There are many other things that have been 
     <lb/>spoken during the course of this debate that 
     <lb/>I would like to comment upon, but I will not 
     <lb/>detain the House longer. I did not intend 
     <lb/>to say all that I have said. I rose for the 
     <lb/>sole purpose of doing justice to my hon. 
     <lb/>friend from Vancouver (Mr. Macpherson) 
     <lb/>who spoke before six o'clock, and I have 
     <lb/>done so. I have now to ask the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Victoria and Haliburton to say if he 
     <lb/>can that he never authorized this interview 
     <lb/>with the 'Montreal Gazette,' and if he can 
     <lb/>say that, he will do much to remove an un<lb break="no"/>fortunate impression that has been caused 
     <lb/>by that interview. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Mr. T. S. SPROULE (East Grey). The 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Cape Breton (Mr. A. 
     <lb/>
     Johnston) generally contents himself when 
     <lb/>
     he rises to ask a question. But to-night he 
     <lb/>
     is playing a different role. As a general thing 
     <lb/>
     this House recognizes the fact that no man 
     <lb/>
     requires information worse than he does, 
     <lb/>
     and the House takes him good naturedly 
     <lb/>
     and endeavours to satisfy his curiosity. 
     <lb/>
     But sometimes he gets beyond bounds, as 
     <lb/>
     he has done to-night in attacking my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend from Victoria and Haliburton (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Sam. Hughes). It is not my purpose to 
     <lb/>
     defend my hon. friend, he is quite capable 
     <lb/>
     of taking care of himself. I would not have 
     <lb/>
    risen to speak at all were it not that the hon. 
     <lb/>member for Cape Breton unnecessarily, un<lb break="no"/>reasonably, improperly, and I was going to 
     <lb/>say, untruthfully, made a statement with 
     <lb/>regard to myself that I had endeavoured to 
     <lb/>arouse passion among the people of this 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
          
     country, that I appealed to a certain class of 
     <lb/>
     people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     An hon. MEMBER. Hear, hear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. SPROULE. Who is the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man that said hear, hear ? It is the cigar<lb break="no"/>ette smoker. Of course he is entitled to 
     <lb/>
     special consideration. He requires that we 
     <lb/>
     give him two kinds of pardon–I will not 
     <lb/>
     tell him what they are. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. ARMAND LAVERGNE. He does 
     <lb/>
     not write circulars to the papers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. SPROULE. Since the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man has come into this House he has re<lb break="no"/>ceived courtesy from this side of the House, 
     <lb/>
     though his conduct at times has not invited 
     <lb/>
     courtesy ; but if he does not conduct him<lb break="no"/>self with a little more decorum, he will not 
     <lb/>
     receive as much in the future as he has 
     <lb/>
     done in the past. Now, with regard to the 
     <lb/>
     question before the House, the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for Cape Breton says that the member for 
     <lb/>
     East Grey has endeavoured to arouse pas<lb break="no"/>sions and create discord. Upon what author<lb break="no"/>ity does he make that statement ? Is it 
     <lb/>
     upon the authority of the petition that I 
     <lb/>
     sent out to the general community in ac<lb break="no"/>cordance with the right of every British 
     <lb/>
     subject to petition parliament to do a cer<lb break="no"/>tain thing that he thought was right ? Is 
     <lb/>
     that not my right and the right of every 
     <lb/>
     British subject under the Crown? It is 
     <lb/>
     recognized in parliament and out of parlia<lb break="no"/>ment to be the highest right of a British 
     <lb/>
     subject. I was availing myself of that 
     <lb/>
     right, and I was quite within my right. I 
     <lb/>
     shall read the letter so that there may be 
     <lb/>
     no mistake as to what it contains, and if 
     <lb/>
     the careful examiner finds that I have done 
     <lb/>
     a very improper thing I shall be greatly 
     <lb/>
     surprised. In view of this important ques<lb break="no"/>tion that was coming up and was likely to 
     <lb/>
     create discord—and let me remind the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman that it was his leader who 
     <lb/>
     brought it into the arena and not mine, and 
     <lb/>
     that upon this question one of the most im<lb break="no"/>portant ministers resigned, and in doing so 
     <lb/>
     he was quite within his rights—it was in 
     <lb/>
     the endeavour to prevent the calamity and 
     <lb/>
     the political trouble that I foresaw that I 
     <lb/>
     adopted the measures that I did. What did 
     <lb/>
     I do ? I addressed to a society to which I 
     <lb/>
     belonged, which is a law-abiding society, no 
     <lb/>
     matter what part of the country it is in, 
     <lb/>
     composed of tolerant, respectable citizens. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. L. P. DEMERS. Tolerant ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. SPROULE. Yes, tolerant. I address<lb break="no"/>ed them in the following language : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Ottawa, February 16th, 1905. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Dear Sir and Brother,-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>We believe an effort is about to be made to 
     <lb/>
     impose separate schools for all time on the 
     <lb/>
     people of the new provinces, now being estab<lb break="no"/>lished in the Northwest Territories. It behooves 
     <lb/>
     every lover of liberty, and especially every 
     <lb/>
     Orangeman, to lend a helping hand, to prevent 
     <lb/>
     this injustice being perpetrated on a liberty-<lb/>
         
            <pb n="2407" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-13_Page_2407.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2407</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">2408</fw>
            

loving people. Being comparatively weak and 
     <lb/>
     helpless, they must largely depend on others to 
     <lb/>
     fight their battles for them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The effort made in 1896 to compel Manitoba to 
     <lb/>
     grant separate schools nearly drove the people 
     <lb/>
     of that province into rebellion, and had it not 
     <lb/>
     been abandoned, would doubtless have resulted 
     <lb/>
     in serious consequences. In view of this, is it 
     <lb/>
    not little short of criminal folly to attempt to  
     <lb/>deprive the people of these new provinces of 
     <lb/>the right to control their own educational 
     <lb/>affairs as to them seems best. I would suggest 
     <lb/>that every member of our order lend a helping 
     <lb/>hand to prevent this outrage by writing or wir<lb break="no"/>ing and getting others to do so as well, the 
     <lb/>member for his constituency to oppose any 
     <lb/>legislation or enactment for that purpose. If 
     <lb/>we speak out freely and do our duty no govern<lb break="no"/>ment would dare to disobey our request. Bre<lb break="no"/>thren, let us do our duty ; also get accompany<lb break="no"/>ing blank petitions signed by all friendly to our 
     <lb/>cause, giving name and occupation in every 
     <lb/>case, and forward to me to House of Commons 
     <lb/>post office, Ottawa, at earliest possible date. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     T. S. SPROULE. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>
     And here is the petition that accompanied 
     <lb/>
     it : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     To the Honourable the Senate and House of 
     <lb/>
     Commons of Canada, in parliament assembled: 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>We, the undersigned electors of the electoral 
     <lb/>division of [blank] do pray that in granting 
     <lb/>provincial autonomy to the Northwest Terri<lb break="no"/>tories the Dominion parliament will not by any 
     <lb/>enactment or otherwise withhold from the newly 
     <lb/>created provinces full and unrestricted freedom 
     <lb/>of action in all matters affecting the establish<lb break="no"/>ment, maintenance and administration of 
     <lb/>schools-<lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>Is there anything improper in that ? Is 
     <lb/>there any appeal to race prejudice, or to 
     <lb/>passion, or to creed ? Is there any<lb break="no"/>thing but the most respectful prayer that 
     <lb/>could be presented to parliament by any 
     <lb/>British subject in the country, and that for 
     <lb/>the purpose of preventing the importing into 
     <lb/>the political arena of Canada at the present 
     <lb/>time of one of those vexed questions that 
     <lb/>would result in arousing a great deal of 
     <lb/>feeling and doing a great deal of injury ? 
     <lb/>Was I within my rights or was I doing an 
     <lb/>improper thing when I did this ? If I was 
     <lb/>wrong in asking parliament to do that, the 
     <lb/>Minister of the Interior must have been 
     <lb/>wrong in resigning. Who induced me to 
     <lb/>do this, who compelled me ? The very acts 
     <lb/>of the Prime Minister himself by the intro<lb break="no"/>duction of this Bill induced me to do it. 
     <lb/>Then who is responsible for it ? Is it I who 
     <lb/>was trying to prevent it being done or the 
     <lb/>party who was importing the element of 
     <lb/>discord into this House and into the country 
     <lb/>at large, that element which had created 
     <lb/>so much bitter feeling in the past, 
     <lb/>and which experience has told us we 
     <lb/>had better avoid if possible in the 
     <lb/>future ? Which one was doing the proper 
     <lb/>thing ? In view of that, does the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber who has just taken his seat think he 
     <lb/>was justified in his endeavour to castigate 
     <lb/>the member for East Grey in the peculiar 
     <lb/>
           
   
            <!--<p>
     Mr SPROULE. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

            <cb/>
           
     fish-wife style to which some speakers are 
     <lb/>
     so admirably adapted ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Some hon. MEMBERS. Order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. SPROULE. Does he think that he 
     <lb/>
     was within his rights and doing the highest 
     <lb/>
     type of parliamentary duty when he gave 
     <lb/>
     vent to the utterances which we have heard 
     <lb/>
     to-night ? If I was wrong in petitioning in 
     <lb/>
     the direction I did what has the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man to say for himself and his leader and 
     <lb/>
     his friends, who have addressed petition 
     <lb/>
     to their confrères in Quebec, copies of which 
     <lb/>
     are being presented at the present time, 
     <lb/>
     some of which were presented to-day, 
     <lb/>
     against the very petition I have read ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. JACQUES BUREAU (Three Rivers). 
     <lb/>
     I am glad my hon. friend from East Grey 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Sproule) has put the question. I will 
     <lb/>
     continue the history of these petitions. There 
     <lb/>
     is in Montreal a club called Le Club Jacques 
     <lb/>
     Cartier. I think the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Jacques Cartier (Mr. Monk) and the leader 
     <lb/>
     of the opposition (Mr. R. L. Borden) know 
     <lb/>
     the place well. In that club was drafted, 
     <lb/>
     I understand by a man who has been very 
     <lb/>
     notorious of late as being the distributor of 
     <lb/>
     the tory corruption fund in the Sault Ste. 
     <lb/>
     Marie election, the petitions which I hold in 
     <lb/>
     my hand, Le Club Jacques Cartier is the 
     <lb/>
     head of the organization of the Tory party 
     <lb/>
     in Quebec. This petition which I hold in my 
     <lb/>
     hand was sent to the various Catholic 
     <lb/>
     organizations in Quebec, or at least in the 
     <lb/>
     constituency of Three Rivers, but luckily 
     <lb/>
     in my district they were not taken up as the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentlemen expected. Some of them 
     <lb/>
     have been sent here to be presented to this 
     <lb/>
     House, and I am credibly informed, and have 
     <lb/>
     reason to believe, that it is a continuation of 
     <lb/>
     the game started by the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     East Grey. In Ontario and the western 
     <lb/>
     provinces the cry is : Let us Tories take the 
     <lb/>
     lead and not permit this legislation to be 
     <lb/>
     carried, it is against provincial autonomy ; 
     <lb/>
     but in Quebec we will present the other 
     <lb/>
     side of the medal, and we will tell the peo<lb break="no"/>ple to present petitions to the Prime Minis<lb break="no"/>ter and the House. I notice that these peti<lb break="no"/>tions were taken to the Prime Minister and 
     <lb/>
     by him sent back to the members for the 
     <lb/>
     different ridings in which they were signed. 
     <lb/>
     They are worded : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     (Translation.) Whereas in the Bill to estab<lb break="no"/>lish and provide for two new provinces in the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest Territories, the following provisions 
     <lb/>
     are to be found, namely : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     16. The provisions of section 93 of the British 
     <lb/>
     North America Act, 1867, shall apply to the 
     <lb/>
     said province as if, at the date upon which this 
     <lb/>
     Act comes into force, the territory comprised 
     <lb/>
     therein were already a province, the expression 
     <lb/>
     ' the union ' in the said section being taken to 
     <lb/>
     mean the said date. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. Subject to the provisions of the said sec<lb break="no"/>tion 93, and in continuance of the principles 
     <lb/>
     heretofore sanctioned under the Northwest Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories Act, it is enacted that the legislature 
     <lb/>
     of the said province shall pass all necessary 
     <lb/>
             laws in respect of education, and that it shall 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="2409" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-13_Page_2409.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">2409</fw>  <fw type="dateline">March 13, 1905</fw> <fw type="num">2410</fw>

         
     therein always be provided (a) that a majority 
     <lb/>
     of the ratepayers of any district or portion of 
     <lb/>
     the said province or of any less portion or sub<lb break="no"/>division thereof, by whatever name it is known,  
     <lb/>
     may establish such schools therein as they think 
     <lb/>
     fit, and make the necessary assessments and 
     <lb/>
     collection of rates therefor, and (b) that the 
     <lb/>
     minority of the ratepayers therein, whether 
     <lb/>
     Protestant or Roman Catholic, may establish, 
     <lb/>
     separate schools therein, and make the neces<lb break="no"/>sary assessment and collection of rates there<lb break="no"/>for, and (c) that in such case the ratepayers 
     <lb/>
     establishing such Protestant or Roman Catho<lb break="no"/>lic separate schools shall be liable only to as<lb break="no"/>sessment of such rates as they impose upon 
     <lb/>
     themselves with respect thereto. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. In the appropriation of public moneys by 
     <lb/>
     the legislature in aid of education, and in the 
     <lb/>
     distribution of any moneys paid to the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the said province arising from the 
     <lb/>
     school fund established by the Dominion Lands 
     <lb/>
     Act, there shall be no discrimination between 
     <lb/>
     the public schools and the separate schools, 
     <lb/>
     and such moneys shall be applied to the sup<lb break="no"/>port of public and separate schools in equitable 
     <lb/>
     shares or proportion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Whereas in the above mentioned provisions, 
     <lb/>
     the vested rights of the minorities in both 
     <lb/>
     those provinces are sanctioned and provided 
     <lb/>
     for ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Whereas said provisions are agreeable to the 
     <lb/>
     spirit of the constitution which governs the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion of Canada ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Whereas the reasons set forth by the right 
     <lb/>
     hon. the Prime Minister, Sir Wilfrid Laurier, 
     <lb/>
     in support of said provisions, on the 21st of 
     <lb/>
     February, 1905, meet with the entire approval 
     <lb/>
     of the undersigned petitioners, irrespective of 
     <lb/>
     party affiliations ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Whereas efforts are being put forth to have 
     <lb/>
     this legislation amended or withdrawn ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We, the undersigned petitioners, do emphati<lb break="no"/>cally protest against such unfair an attempt, 
     <lb/>
     and respectfully beg that the above mentioned 
     <lb/>
     provisions be passed into law, during this ses<lb break="no"/>sion and maintained in their whole tenor as 
     <lb/>
     they now stand, as a full measure of fair-play 
     <lb/>
     and justice. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And we beg the right hon. the Prime Minister 
     <lb/>
     to lay down this petition on the table of the 
     <lb/>
     House of Commons. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And your petitioners will ever pray. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>
     For the benefit of my colleagues who do 
     <lb/>
     not understand the French language, let me 
     <lb/>
     state that they are asking that separate 
     <lb/>
     schools be established in the Northwest 
     <lb/>
     Territories and that we do not legislate 
     <lb/>
     otherwise than in that direction. I am an 
     <lb/>
     admirer of the hon. member for Victoria 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Hughes) but I certainly do not share 
     <lb/>
     his views and especially so when he talks 
     <lb/>
     as he did in that Toronto interview. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. SPROULE. The hon. gentleman (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Bureau) says there was one petition dis<lb break="no"/>tributed in the west, and a different one in 
     <lb/>
     Quebec. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Some hon. MEMBERS. Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. SPROULE. Permit me to say that I 
     <lb/>
     distributed this petition through the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Quebec the same as in other pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, and it has been signed by the 
     <lb/>
     electors of that province and I presented 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
        
     several petitions from the province of Que<lb break="no"/>bec to the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. BUREAU. I ask my hon. friend (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Sproule) who is one of the leaders of the 
     <lb/>
     party if any of these petitions which I hold 
     <lb/>
     in my hand were distributed in Ontario. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. SPROULE. I never saw them before. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. FIELDING. I am afraid we are 
     <lb/>
     getting perilously near losing sight of the 
     <lb/>
     motion in question before the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. MONK. I rise to make a personal 
     <lb/>
     explanation because my hon. friend (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Bureau) has referred to me by name. For 
     <lb/>
     the first time to-night I have heard of these 
     <lb/>
     petitions. I have not been to Montreal for 
     <lb/>
     quite a time ; I do not think I have been in 
     <lb/>
     the Jacques Cartier Club since the beginning 
     <lb/>
     of the session, and I know nothing whatever 
     <lb/>
     of these petitions. I am sure there is not a 
     <lb/>
     member in this House from the province of 
     <lb/>
     Quebec who would lend himself for a single 
     <lb/>
     moment to the ignoble role which has been 
     <lb/>
     suggested by my hon. friend. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. A. B. INGRAM (East Elgin). Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Speaker, this is the outcome of allowing too 
     <lb/>
     much latitude in debate. If members were 
     <lb/>
     to confine themselves to the actual question 
     <lb/>
     before the House, probably you, Sir, would 
     <lb/>
     have less difficulty in controlling the House, 
     <lb/>
     and probably it would be more creditable 
     <lb/>
     to members on both sides. A good deal has 
     <lb/>
     been said about the legality of these peti<lb break="no"/>tions, and I take it that probably there are 
     <lb/>
     Conservatives throughout the Dominion who 
     <lb/>
     are in favour of the legislation as well as 
     <lb/>
     those who are opposed to it, and both sides 
     <lb/>
     have a right to petition this House so long 
     <lb/>
     as as they do so in proper form. The hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Victoria (Mr. Sam. Hughes) 
     <lb/>
     may have made some statements of a con<lb break="no"/>troversial character but I do not think he 
     <lb/>
     went to the extent which my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     from Cape Breton (Mr. A. Johnston) charges 
     <lb/>
     him with going. If the hon. member (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     A. Johnston) wants to evince a disposition 
     <lb/>
     to allay strife and ill feeling in this country 
     <lb/>
    I can assure him that he has taken the 
     <lb/>wrong method to-night. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Mr. J. B. MORIN (Dorchester). The hon. 
     <lb/>member for Cape Breton (Mr. A. Johnston) 
     <lb/>referred to the member who was sitting 
     <lb/>near the leader of the opposition, and I 
     <lb/>want to know if he alluded to me ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. A. JOHNSTON. Most certainly not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. MORIN. I am told he mentioned the 
     <lb/>
     member for Dorchester. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. A. JOHNSTON. I made no reference 
     <lb/>
     to my hon. friend (Mr. Morin) when I spoke 
     <lb/>
     of the gentleman who sat beside the leader 
     <lb/>
     of the opposition. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. MORIN. I am told you spoke of the 
     <lb/>
     member for Dorchester and if you did I am 
     <lb/>
     the man. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>