<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1896-08-31"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1896-08-31">31 August 1896</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

        
        
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Eighth Parliament, First Session</title>.
          <date when="1896"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="411" to="424"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00411.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00413.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00415.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00417.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00419.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00421.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00423.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-09">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00411">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00411.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00413">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00413.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00415">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00415.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00417">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00417.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00419">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00419.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00421">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00421.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00423">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00423.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="411" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00411.jpg"/>
         
         
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">412</fw>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SUBSIDIES TO NORTH-WEST TERRI<lb break="no"/>TORIES. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName> moved for: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Copies of all memorials, resolutions or other 
     <lb/>
     documents from the legislative assembly of the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories for an increase of sub<lb break="no"/>sidy, and all correspondence in connection with 
     <lb/>
     the same. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     He said: Mr. Speaker. I would ask the 
     <lb/>
     House to listen for a short time to an ex<lb break="no"/>planation of the object for which this mo<lb break="no"/>tion is made. The motion is moved in order 
     <lb/>
     to afford information to the House on a 
     <lb/>
     subject of considerable interest to the House 
     <lb/>
     and to the country. It is a subject in regard 
     <lb/>
     to which efforts have been made for the 
     <lb/>
     enlightenment of the House in the past, or 
     <lb/>
     rather for the enlightenment of the late 
     <lb/>
     Government, but the information never 
     <lb/>
     reached the House, and it seems to me it 
     <lb/>
     would be well to take up a short time of this 
     <lb/>
     sitting in order to arrive at an understanding 
     <lb/>
     of this question. The motion relates to the 
     <lb/>
     financial condition of the legislature of the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories in its connection with 
     <lb/>
     this Government. The position occupied by 
     <lb/>
     the Territories at the present time is very 
     <lb/>
     similar to the position of a province, that 
     <lb/>
     is to say, the territorial government and 
     <lb/>
     legislature have all, or nearly all, the re<lb break="no"/>sponsibilities of a provincial government or 
     <lb/>
     legislature. and at the same time they have 
     <lb/>
     much greater responsibilities than the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of any province, owing to the im<lb break="no"/>mense area of country they are expected to 
     <lb/>
     govern and the difficulties of carrying on 
     <lb/>
     that government. While the North-west 
     <lb/>
     government and legislature have almost 
     <lb/>
     equal power and greater responsibility 
     <lb/>
     than the government of a province, the 
     <lb/>
     government and legislature are con<lb break="no"/>fronted with the position that they 
     <lb/>
     have not adequate finances. and those 
     <lb/>
     finances have been inadequate for some 
     <lb/>
     years past. The area under the government 
     <lb/>
     of the North-west Territories is, roughly 
     <lb/>
     speaking, something like 600 miles square: 
     <lb/>
     it is very much larger than the settled area 
     <lb/>
     of all the eastern provinces of the Dominion, 
     <lb/>
     and settlement being scattered more or less 
     <lb/>
     over this great area, the expense and diffi<lb break="no"/>culty of carrying on the government are 
     <lb/>
     proportionately increased. It is not only 
     <lb/>
     that there is a great area over which settle<lb break="no"/>ment is scattered, but there is also diversity 
     <lb/>
     of interest. There is the wheat raising 
     <lb/>
     interest in the east. the cattle raising 
     <lb/>
     interest in the west, the coal mining 
     <lb/>
     in the mountains, and the trading interest 
     <lb/>
     in the far north—a diversity of interests 
     <lb/>
     that renders legislation and government in 
     <lb/>
     that country more difficult probably than in 
     <lb/>
     any province, or, at all events in any pro<lb break="no"/>vince having a similar population. The popu<lb break="no"/>lation of the Territories in 1891 was stated 
     <lb/>
     as 66,799. and the subsidies at that time de<lb break="no"/>rived from the Dominion Parliament amount<lb break="no"/>ed in 1892 to $211,200. Since that time the 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <pb n="413" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00413.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">413</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 31, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">414</fw>
   
   
     population has increased, so that in 1894. 
     <lb/>according to the census then taken by the<lb/>police, the population was 86,000 and taking<lb/>the same rate of increase down to the end<lb/>of the current fiscal year, it may be placed<lb/>in the neighbourhood of 112,000. While the<lb/>population has increased from 66,000 to 112,<lb break="no"/>000, the subsidy on which the government<lb/>of the Territories is based, has increased<lb/>only from $211,000 to $242,000 : that is to<lb/>say, that while the population has nearly<lb/>doubled. the subsidy on which the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the Territories is conducted. has<lb/>only increased by 15 per cent : to be more<lb/>accurate, while the population has increased<lb/>70 per cent, the subsidy has increased only<lb/>15 per cent. There was difficulty in govern<lb break="no"/>ing those Territories in 1891 with the then<lb/>subsidy, but the difficulty is much<lb/>greater now, with not only a larger popula<lb break="no"/>tion, but a population that has gone into<lb/>new portions of the country, while<lb/>at the same time the Territories<lb/>have receive comparatively less subsidy.<lb/>The duties of the government of the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories are much the the same as the duties of<lb/>the governments in the older provinces,<lb/>and one of the first charges on the treasury,<lb/>both in the Territories and in the provinces,<lb/>is the maintenance of education. In 1982<lb/>there were in the Territories 245 schools in<lb/>operation ; in 1895 there were 395 schools<lb/>in operation and in 1896 there are 489 schools<lb/>organized, of which nearly all are in opera<lb break="no"/>tion, so that in connection with that particu<lb break="no"/>lar charge on the treasury there has been<lb/>nearly a doubling of the expense. The cost<lb/>of education in the Territories is now nearly<lb/>double what it was a few years ago, while<lb/>the grant out of which that cost has to be<lb/>paid has only increased to the extend of 15<lb/>per cent. I admit that the grand in aid of<lb/>education in the Territories is comparatively<lb/>large. that is to say, the aid granted by the<lb/>territorial legislature to the school districts<lb/>in the Territories is relatively large. but<lb/>it has to be large in order that education<lb/>shall be carried on there at all. This is on<lb/>account of the system of land grants which<lb/>have prevailed in that country. It is pro<lb break="no"/>vided that twenty sections out of every<lb/>thirty-six, that is twenty square miles out<lb/>of every thirty-six, shall be reserved from<lb/>settlement. Instead of schools being sup<lb break="no"/>ported by people settled on every quarter<lb/>section in a township, they have to be<lb/>supported by such settlers as may be on<lb/>sixteen out of the thirty-six sections. The<lb/>scattered settlement in that country, is what<lb/>makes it more necessary that there shall<lb/>be a large grant in aid of the schools. With<lb break="no"/>out that large grant these schools could not<lb/>be conducted, and without schools you can<lb break="no"/>not hope to attract settlement, nor can you<lb/>even expect to retain the settlement you<lb/>have. When a settler is not sufficiently in<lb break="no"/>terested in the education of his children to<lb/>demand a school as one of his first require<lb break="no"/>ments, the chances are that such a settler<lb/>
       
       
            <cb/>
        
        
     is no good to the country. The school ex<lb break="no"/>penditure which in 1893-94 was $97,000, has<lb/>increased to such an extent that it will<lb/>amount to $120,000 this year. These are the<lb/>amounts that have been granted to schools<lb/>out of the subsidies allowed to the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. It therefore will be plain to the<lb/>House, that the grater proportion of the<lb/>total subsidy voted to the territorial legis<lb break="no"/>lature by this Parliament, has been expend<lb break="no"/>ed on education. Although at first sight the<lb/>grant would appear to be large it will be<lb/>found upon the inquiry that it is not larger than<lb/>the case requires.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Public works are the second great charge 
     <lb/>on the revenues of the Territories. As we<lb/>all know, in the case of the organized pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, the greater part of the expenditure<lb/>upon public works is borne by the munici<lb break="no"/>palities, and the provincial legislatures bear<lb/>only a small proportion of the cost of<lb/>such works. In the Territories, owing to<lb/>the scattered settlement of the country, and<lb/>owing to the nature of the country, it is<lb/>simply impossible to have such an organiza<lb break="no"/>tion as you have in the older provinces. and<lb/>as a consequence the territorial legislature<lb/>has to bear a larger proportion of the cost<lb/>of works which is usually borne by the<lb/>municipal organizations in the provinces.<lb/>There is therefore a special charge upon<lb/>the territorial treasury, which does not<lb/>bear upon the treasuries of the provinces,<lb/>and that charge exists because of the pecu<lb break="no"/>liar condition of the Territories. This pecu<lb break="no"/>liar condition in its turn is a result of the<lb/>administration of this Parliament in holding<lb/>in reservation from settlement such a large<lb/>proportion of the lands. parliament having<lb/>taken upon itself a certain responsibility in<lb/>regard to that matter and having laid down<lb/>a certain policy must certainly be held<lb/>responsible for the results of that policy.<lb/>When Parliament has absolutely. as may be<lb/>said, prohibited settlement in the greater<lb/>part of that country, it seems to me that<lb/>Parliament must be prepared to make good<lb/>the deficiency in the revenue necessary to<lb/>carry on the proper business of the country.<lb/>As in the case of schools it is in the case of<lb/>public works, especially roads and bridges.<lb/>These roads and bridges which would be<lb/>kept up if there was settlement on every<lb/>section, simply cannot be kept up when<lb/>settlement is on less than half the sections. If<lb/>we are to have public improvements in that<lb/>country, the burden must be borne to a very<lb/>great extent by the treasury of the Territo<lb break="no"/>ries, which again must be supported by a<lb/>subsidy from the Parliament. There are<lb/>not only roads and bridges to construct and<lb/>maintain, but there is also the question of<lb/>the water supply throughout a great portion<lb/>of that country. Without an improved water<lb/>supply, which can only be secured by the<lb/>expenditure of money, settlement cannot in<lb break="no"/>crease as it ought to or as it otherwise<lb/>would. There are other special expenditures<lb/>which have to be made, expenditures which<lb/>
        
        
            <pb n="415" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00415.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">415</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">416</fw>
      
      
     are not needed in any of the older provinces. 
     <lb/>
     For instance, during one year, $8,000 was 
     <lb/>
     paid for wolf bounty, in order to protect the 
     <lb/>
     cattle in the ranching country against 
     <lb/>
     wolves. This is an expenditure peculiar 
     <lb/>
     to the Territories, and it is one which has 
     <lb/>
     to be incurred in the interests of the cattle 
     <lb/>
     industry. There are also special expendi<lb break="no"/>tures in the wheat growing country, such as 
     <lb/>
    the money which has to be paid to try to 
     <lb/>keep down the gopher pest. This gopher 
     <lb/>pest exists chiefly by reason of the fact that 
     <lb/>there is so much vacant land. The gophers 
     <lb/>do not propagate on the cultivated land but 
     <lb/>on the land that is unoccupied, and the pro<lb break="no"/>tection of the cultivated land from the go<lb break="no"/>phers has cost $4,000 in one year. There is 
     <lb/>also the question of the relief of distress 
     <lb/>which has to be provided for by the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. There has to be provision made 
     <lb/>sometimes for the relief of distress, and to 
     <lb/>compensate for losses of crop by hail storms 
     <lb/>and otherwise. In the older provinces the 
     <lb/>municipalities take care of distressed per<lb break="no"/>sons, but in our country, on account of there 
     <lb/>being no municipal organizations, that must 
     <lb/>be done at the expense of the territorial 
     <lb/>government. The cause of humanity must 
     <lb/>prevail in the Territories as well as in the<lb/>provinces, and people cannot be allowed to<lb/>suffer or to die for lack of pecuniary assist<lb break="no"/>ance. We have also a number of hospitals 
     <lb/>which have to receive governmental assist<lb break="no"/>ance. These hospitals receive $4,000 a year. 
     <lb/>When that grant was made the idea was 
     <lb/>that each hospital should receive 40 cents 
     <lb/>per day for each non-paying patient treated. 
     <lb/>However, owing to the increase of patients 
     <lb/>and the increase of hospitals, the grant now 
     <lb/>only amounts to 27 cents per day for non<lb break="no"/>paying patients. This is a charge that has 
     <lb/>increased from year to year and it is a 
     <lb/>charge that must be provided for. There 
     <lb/>has also been $3,000 paid out for the en<lb break="no"/>couragement of the creamery industry, and 
     <lb/> this, I may say, is a most desirable policy 
     <lb/>and a wise expenditure. I allude to all 
     <lb/>these matters for the purpose of showing in 
     <lb/>the first place, the necessity for them, and 
     <lb/>in the second place, the advantage of 
     <lb/>the money being expended in the man<lb break="no"/>ner in which it is expended. The expendi<lb break="no"/>ture is not only of advantage to the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, but it is of advantage to the whole 
     <lb/>of Canada, for I need not remind hon. 
     <lb/>gentlemen that whatever assists the im<lb break="no"/>provement and development of that country 
     <lb/>is also of advantage to the entire Dominion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     While large sums have been used for edu<lb break="no"/>cation and public works, and these sums 
     <lb/>
     have been on the increase from year to year, 
     <lb/>
     those charges which are for what you 
     <lb/>
     may call the running of the machine, have 
     <lb/>
     not increased in proportion to the increase 
     <lb/>
     of population. The grant for clerical as<lb break="no"/>sistance in 1892 was $16,701. and in 1895 it 
     <lb/>
     was $12,460 ; so that that expenditure has 
     <lb/>
     been decreased very materially under the 
     <lb/>
     present North-west administration. The 
     <lb/>
 
 
            <cb/>
        
        
     cost of the executive, or cabinet, has stood 
     <lb/>
     at $5,500 a year for the last five years ; the 
     <lb/>
     expenditure on printing account, which was 
     <lb/>
     $6,000 in 1892, was reduced to $4,000 in 1895. 
     <lb/>
      So that, if a question is asked as to how the 
     <lb/>
     assembly expends the money which is 
     <lb/>
     granted by Parliament, I think it can be 
     <lb/>
     shown that the money is expended judicious<lb break="no"/>ly, both in matters of improvement and in 
     <lb/>
     matters of routine. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There are two grounds upon which the 
     <lb/>
     territorial government or legislature are en<lb break="no"/>titled to an increased grant. One is that 
     <lb/>
     the territorial government is a creation of 
     <lb/>
      this Parliament. It was at one time merely 
     <lb/>
     a branch of the Department of the Interior, 
     <lb/>
    and money was provided through that de<lb break="no"/>partment for the purpose of carrying on the 
     <lb/>business of the Territories. Now, Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, having created a certain institution 
     <lb/>in the North-west Territories, is in duty 
     <lb/>bound to provide the funds necessary to 
     <lb/>carry on that institution. On the other 
     <lb/>hand, the people of the Territories are en<lb break="no"/>titled to stand in exactly the same position 
     <lb/>as the citizens of any province. They are 
     <lb/>citizens of this Dominion as much as are 
     <lb/>the people of the provinces. They contrib<lb break="no"/>ute their share to the revenues of the coun<lb break="no"/>try, as do the people of the provinces : and, 
     <lb/>having been granted control of their local 
     <lb/>government, they are entitled to fully as 
     <lb/>much subsidy for their local purposes in re<lb break="no"/>turn for the amounts they have paid into 
     <lb/>the general treasury as are the people of the 
     <lb/>provinces. Calculating on that basis, I will 
     <lb/>give you a few figures to show that in ask<lb break="no"/>ing for an increase on the moderate amount 
     <lb/>that has been granted during past years, 
     <lb/>they are not asking for more than they are 
     <lb/>entitled to. Taking the increase of popula<lb break="no"/>tion that occurred from 1891 to 1894, and 
     <lb/>assuming the same percentage of increase 
     <lb/>until the end of the present fiscal year, we 
     <lb/>would have a population of 113,000. In the 
     <lb/>case of Manitoba, the amount payable per 
     <lb/>head is based, not on the actual population 
     <lb/>at the time, but on the supposed or expected 
     <lb/>population, two and a half years in advance. 
     <lb/>that is to say, the subsidy per head is re<lb break="no"/>adjusted every five years, and the amount 
     <lb/>is fixed at what it would be on the basis of 
     <lb/>population when half the term of five years 
     <lb/>is up. Applying the same calculation to the 
     <lb/>North-west Territories, it would give us a 
     <lb/>supposed population of 141,000, which, at 
     <lb/>80 cents per head, would entitle us to $112,<lb break="no"/>000 a year. On debt account, the present 
     <lb/>actual population would entitle us to $156,<lb break="no"/>000 a year. Taking the amount allowed to 
     <lb/>Manitoba for the cost of government, that 
     <lb/>is to say $50,000 a year, and an allowance 
     <lb/>on account of the land, such as given in 
     <lb/>Manitoba, say $125,000 a year, the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories would be in a position at the present 
     <lb/>time to claim, in a readjustment of the sub<lb break="no"/>sidy, in the neighbourhood of $440,000 a 
     <lb/>year. Thev are not asking for that amount 
     <lb/>at the present moment ; but they are asking 
     <lb/>for a substantial increase in the amount 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <pb n="417" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00417.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">417</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 31, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">418</fw>
 
 
     which has been granted in past years, so 
     <lb/>
     as to catch up to some extent with the pre<lb break="no"/>sent requirements. Let me say that the 
     <lb/>
     manner in which the subsidy has been cal<lb break="no"/>culated in the past has been this. The ter<lb break="no"/>ritorial government made up an estimate of 
     <lb/>
     what was required. The Department of the 
     <lb/>
     Interior granted either that amount or as 
     <lb/>
     much less as it saw fit. The territorial gov<lb break="no"/>ernment was compelled to keep within the 
     <lb/>
     amount voted. When the territorial govern<lb break="no"/>ment, next year, sent down an estimate for 
     <lb/>
     an increased amount, the department here, 
     <lb/>
     I suppose, argued: " Well. you got along 
     <lb/>
     with so much last year; you can certainly 
     <lb/>
     get on with the same amount this year." 
     <lb/>
     So the amount has been kept at about the 
     <lb/>
     same figure for the last five years. This, it 
     <lb/>
     appears to me. is putting the matter on a 
     <lb/>
     false basis, which is neither in the interest 
     <lb/>
     of the North-west, in the interest of this 
     <lb/>
     Dominion, nor in accord with the dignity of 
     <lb/>
     this Parliament in its dealings with the in<lb break="no"/>stitution which itself has created. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In regard to the grant on account of the 
     <lb/>
     land, I would say a word or two. The pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Manitoba has been granted $100,<lb break="no"/>000 a year in consideration of its public 
     <lb/>
     lands having been administered by Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. In the Territories there is, I sup<lb break="no"/>pose, four or five times as much land as 
     <lb/>
     there is in the province of Manitoba : and, 
     <lb/>
     while it may be argued that the land is not 
     <lb/>
     profitable to the government, that the ad<lb break="no"/>ministration of it has not returned a finan<lb break="no"/>cial profit to the Government, let me put 
     <lb/>
     the matter to you in this way. Parliament 
     <lb/>
     has seen fit in the past to grant off these 
     <lb/>
     lands to the Canadian Pacific Railway, 
     <lb/>
     which is a national work and not a North<lb break="no"/>western work simply, to the extent of 25,<lb break="no"/>000,000 acres. I understand that that land 
     <lb/>
     has been bonded to the amount of $1.25 an 
     <lb/>
     acre ; so that its value stands. under these 
     <lb/>
     bonds. at something like $31,000,000, which, 
     <lb/>
     at 4 per cent, is equivalent to a million and 
     <lb/>
     a quarter dollars a year. This is not 
     <lb/>
     any fancy calculation, but a calculation on 
     <lb/>
     the basis of actual cash. So that when we 
     <lb/>
     say that the Territories are entitled to con<lb break="no"/>sideration on account of the amount of Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment land there, we are not going beyond 
     <lb/>
     the mark when we say that we should be 
     <lb/>
     dealt with at least as favourably as the 
     <lb/>
     province of Manitoba, particularly when we 
     <lb/>
     call your attention to the fact that the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Prince Edward Island has received 
     <lb/>
     a specieal grant of something like $40,000 a 
     <lb/>
     year, in consideration of the fact that at the 
     <lb/>
     time of entering confederation it had not 
     <lb/>
     any public land at all; and that the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of British Columbia has been granted 
     <lb/>
     $100,000 a year, in consideration of what is 
     <lb/>
     known as the railway belt, in which belt 
     <lb/>
     the province still holds the precious metals. 
     <lb/>
     which. I suppose, are really the most valu<lb break="no"/>able part of the land. Now. a statement 
     <lb/>
     has been made by the local government, 
     <lb/>
     asking for a certain increase in the annual 
     <lb/>
     subsidy, based actual requirements. Not 
     <lb/>
 
 
            <cb/>
       
       
     that they do not want a readjustment of 
     <lb/>
     grant on the basis of the provincial sub<lb break="no"/>sidies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The papers I asked for are for the purpose 
     <lb/>
     of showing what is absolutely required for 
     <lb/>
     the carrying on of the government of the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories during the current 
     <lb/>
     fiscal year and not for the purpose of mak<lb break="no"/>ing a permanent arrangement. The govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the Territories, however, as will be 
     <lb/>
     shown by the papers, are prepared at any 
     <lb/>
     time to enter into an arrangement for a 
     <lb/>
     permanent subsidy on a provincial basis 
     <lb/>
     suitable to the special position and circum<lb break="no"/>stances of the Territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I am glad my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     has made this motion and brought the 
     <lb/>
     claims of the Territories before the House. 
     <lb/>
     I do not know whether I understood him to 
     <lb/>
     say that he was bringing these matters be<lb break="no"/>fore the House for the first time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. I said that I understood 
     <lb/>
     that these papers have never been laid on 
     <lb/>
     the Table. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Well, I am exceedingly glad 
     <lb/>
     that my hon. friend has brought this mat<lb break="no"/>ter before the House. As the House is well 
     <lb/>
     aware, I have annually brought before it 
     <lb/>
     the claims of the Territories, and made an 
     <lb/>
     argument in favour of an increased subsidy, 
     <lb/>
     somewhat in the line of that which my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend has made. There cannot be any doubt 
     <lb/>
     that not merely now but, as I pointed out, 
     <lb/>
     either last session or the session before last, 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories were long ago 
     <lb/>
     entitled to far more money than was given 
     <lb/>
     them year after year, and in fact I think 
     <lb/>
     it was either last session or the session be<lb break="no"/>fore last that I argued that there was some<lb break="no"/>thing like a million dollars or more of ar<lb break="no"/>rears due the North-west Territories, bear<lb break="no"/>ing in mind what should have been paid, on 
     <lb/>
     the basis of the calculation made by my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend in his able speech this afternoon 
     <lb/>
     and comparing that with the amount which 
     <lb/>
     has been given. In 1889, the legislative as<lb break="no"/>sembly of the North-west Territories sub<lb break="no"/>mitted a memorandum to the then Minister 
     <lb/>
     of the Interior in which they submitted the 
     <lb/>
     argument that, with an estimated popula<lb break="no"/>tion of 150,000 as a basis to go on—and that 
     <lb/>
     was not too much even then, taking what 
     <lb/>
     had been done for Manitoba—the subsidy 
     <lb/>
     at the rate of 80 cents per head, which was 
     <lb/>
     allowed the provinces. would amount to 
     <lb/>
     $120,000. They further submitted that on 
     <lb/>
     debt account the Territories are entitled to 
     <lb/>
     5 per cent interest on $27.77 per head on an 
     <lb/>
     actual population of 100,000, which would 
     <lb/>
     amount to $138,850, and that the specific 
     <lb/>
     grant for governmental purposes should be 
     <lb/>
     at least as liberal as that made to Mani<lb break="no"/>toba, that is to say. $50,000. And they, fur<lb break="no"/>ther submitted that: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Owing to the vast area of the Territories and 
     <lb/>
     the widely scattered nature of the settlement, 
     <lb/>
     all the local business of the government is ren<lb break="no"/>
  
  
            <pb n="419" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00419.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">419</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">420</fw>
       
       
     dered mere expensive proportionately to popu<lb break="no"/>lation than in any of the provinces. 
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     For these reasons they asked a specific 
     <lb/>
     annual grant for the five years term of 
     <lb/>
     $100,000, and claimed an aggregate sum of 
     <lb/>
     over $400,000. Any man who has listened 
     <lb/>attentively to my hon. friend this after<lb break="no"/>noon will agree that with the population 
     <lb/>they then had, and proceeding on the ratio 
     <lb/>that had been dealt out to Manitoba in 1870,  
     <lb/>the North-west Territories in 1889—that is 
     <lb/>several years ago—were entitled to a grant 
     <lb/>of $400,000. On the 27th February of that 
     <lb/>year, I made a motion in this House some<lb break="no"/>what similar to that made by my hon. friend 
     <lb/>this afternoon. I moved for copies of all 
     <lb/>memorials addressed to the Government by 
     <lb/>the legislative assembly of the North-west 
     <lb/>Territories which had then sat recently at 
     <lb/>Regina, and I presented, as best I could, the 
     <lb/>claims of the North-west Territories, as set 
     <lb/>forth by the legislative assembly of which 
     <lb/>my hon. friend was then a member and had 
     <lb/>been for some time. As will be seen by re<lb break="no"/>ference to page 355 of the "Hansard" of 1889. 
     <lb/>I pointed out that the old council of 1887 
     <lb/>petitioned for responsible government, and 
     <lb/>I stated what the memorial set forth, and 
     <lb/>I pressed for a subsidy very much larger 
     <lb/>than what had been given up to that time 
     <lb/>or than what has been given since. And 
     <lb/>I pointed out that we might take a leaf out 
     <lb/>of the book of the United States and follow  
     <lb/>the example set by that country in dealing 
     <lb/>with its territories. I pointed out that Min<lb break="no"/>nesota, Wyoming, Dakota and Montana each 
     <lb/>got in lands, a large extent of territory for 
     <lb/>subsidizing branch lines. That is some<lb break="no"/>thing which this Government has never con<lb break="no"/>templated doing for the government of the 
     <lb/>Territories, but I contend that the sooner 
     <lb/>we give the giant in the North-west its 
     <lb/>limbs the better. The sooner we give that 
     <lb/>North-west people, now far in excess of 
     <lb/>numbers of what Manitoba was in 1870, 
     <lb/>what it is entitled to, the better ; and as 
     <lb/>anybody will see who visits the giant, as 
     <lb/>the hon. Prime Minister did, at the time 
     <lb/>when the legislative assembly was sitting, 
     <lb/>the representatives in that assembly will 
     <lb/>compare well with the representatives of 
     <lb/>any assembly in the provinces. What is the 
     <lb/>reason this Government should keep that 
     <lb/>giant in leading strings all these years ? I 
     <lb/>appeal to the hon. Minister to cut those 
     <lb/>strings. He is fond of regarding himself as 
     <lb/>a breaker of manacles, let him break those 
     <lb/>manacles that are on the limbs of the 
     <lb/>North-west Territories, let him give the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories provincial autonomy and the annual 
     <lb/>subsidy to which it is entitled by reason of 
     <lb/>its population, according to the calculation 
     <lb/>so ably set forth by my hon. friend this 
     <lb/>afternoon. I would go further than was 
     <lb/>done in the case of' Manitoba, and would 
     <lb/>give the young man, so to speak, when I set 
     <lb/>him up in life, all the implements of man<lb break="no"/>hood. I would give him the means of build<lb break="no"/>ing his own railways. Here is what hap<lb break="no"/>
         
         
            <cb/>
       
       
     pened in these Territories which have been 
     <lb/>
     very successful, as I need not say, below the 
     <lb/>
     line. Minnesota with 83,000 square miles 
     <lb/>
     (Assiniboia has 93,000 square miles) re<lb break="no"/>ceived land for subsidizing 1,800 miles of 
     <lb/>
     railway, and with the swamps, started in 
     <lb/>
            possession of one-third of the territory. 
     <lb/>What does that policy enable these Terri<lb break="no"/>tories to do. I read from my speech seven 
     <lb/> years ago : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     It gives them, while young, that nutriment and 
     <lb/>
     vital force, without which anything young can<lb break="no"/>not thrive. As the Right Hon. the Prime Minis<lb break="no"/>ter is now acting Minister of Railways, I should 
     <lb/>
     like to call his attention to this fact. At this 
     <lb/>
     hour the government of Minnesota receives an 
     <lb/>
     income of $600,000 a year, 3 per cent on the 
     <lb/>
     gross earnings of the lines of railway that it 
     <lb/>
     chartered and subsidized since 1849, when it was 
     <lb/>
     organized. But it may be said : " Ah, but those 
     <lb/>
     territories were very populous." Not at all. 
     <lb/>
     In 1849, when Minnesota was organized, it had 
     <lb/>
     only a population of 6,000— 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     I think my hon. friend said our population 
     <lb/>
     in 1894 was 84,000, and it is more to-day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     —and the aggregate population of all the four 
     <lb/>
     territories at the respective dates of their organi<lb break="no"/>zation did not equal by five or six thousand the 
     <lb/>
     population of the North-west to-day. That is 
     <lb/>
     the point which I submit as well worthy of the 
     <lb/>
     consideration of the Government, because I 
     <lb/>
     think we may err on the side of keeping the 
     <lb/>
     strings too much in our hands here in Ottawa, 
     <lb/>
     and not giving sufficient scope for the young 
     <lb/>
     giant, for which I plead here to-day, to develop 
     <lb/>
     his limbs. Now, it will be said to us, no doubt, 
     <lb/>
     you have got the mounted police. So we have, 
     <lb/>
     and we are very glad to have them ; but else<lb break="no"/>where you have batteries, militia, and military 
     <lb/>
     schools, and we pay for those just as well as you 
     <lb/>
     pay for the mounted police ; and before you knew 
     <lb/>
     where you are, I believe in the next five years, 
     <lb/>
     you will find we shall have a population in those 
     <lb/>
     Territories which will be subscribing to your 
     <lb/>
     military schools, and batteries, and militia just 
     <lb/>
     as much as you are subscribing to the North<lb break="no"/>west mounted police. And remember that in any 
     <lb/>
     case the cost of defence would fall on the Federal 
     <lb/>
     Government ; so that you cannot fairly make 
     <lb/>
     anything of our having the mounted police. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Now what I point out there is of great im<lb break="no"/>portance—that the United States govern<lb break="no"/>ment, in dealing with territories is more 
     <lb/>
     generous than the Government of Canada. 
     <lb/>
     And as I repeat the argument, I repeat to 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman opposite the appeal I 
     <lb/>
     made to the Government of Sir John Mac<lb break="no"/>donald, and I say to him that not only will 
     <lb/>
     these facts justify him in complying with 
     <lb/>
     the demand made by my hon. friend (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Oliver) this afternoon, but they will justify 
     <lb/>
     him in going further. They will justify him 
     <lb/>
     in giving to the Territories responsible gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. They will justify him in giving 
     <lb/>
     the Territories not $260,000 as a grant, but 
     <lb/>
     $400,000 a year as a subsidy, and they will 
     <lb/>
     justify him in going still further—in giving 
     <lb/>
     them lands by which they will be able to 
     <lb/>
    build small local railways, so that in ten 
     <lb/>years from now, they may be in the posi<lb break="no"/>tion that Minnesota is found to be in to-day 
     <lb/>—drawing a large income from investments 
     <lb/>in these railways. My hon. friend very 
     <lb/>
      
      
            <pb n="421" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00421.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">421</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 31, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">422</fw>
     
     
     properly pointed out that the government of 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories really has a more 
     <lb/>
     difficult problem before it than any pro<lb break="no"/>vincial government. As he told you they 
     <lb/>
     have a great area—a far greater area than 
     <lb/>
     any province—they have scattered settle<lb break="no"/>ments and diverse interests. I was very 
     <lb/>
     glad to see that he is a supporter of a 
     <lb/>
     policy that, before I came to this House at 
     <lb/>
     all, I pressed upon the attention of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and which, since I have been in this 
     <lb/>
     House, I have on several occasions, press<lb break="no"/>ed upon the attention of Parliament. I re<lb break="no"/>fer to what the hon. gentleman said con<lb break="no"/>cerning the odd sections which, as now 
     <lb/>
     dealt with, work a very great evil. They 
     <lb/>
     cause a scattered settlement; they enable, 
     <lb/>
    as my hon. friend pointed out, the gopher. 
     <lb/>'to have a great hunting ground: and not 
     <lb/>only that. but to-day, half. a township minus 
     <lb/>four sections has to do the work of a whole 
     <lb/>township. For supporting schools, for mak<lb break="no"/>ing roads and bridges, for all the work of a 
     <lb/>township, you have not half a township, but 
     <lb/>only the settled even-numbered sections, 
     <lb/>minus the four sections, two for the Hud<lb break="no"/>son's Bay Company and two school sections, 
     <lb/>I have advocated a radical change, and I am 
     <lb/>glad now to note that I shall have my hon. 
     <lb/>friend's support, or—which is the same thing 
     <lb/>to me, if he proposes the reform—he shall 
     <lb/>have my support. It is a matter of perfect 
     <lb/>indifference to me who proposes or who 
     <lb/>carries out anything for the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, whoever proposes anything for the 
     <lb/>good of the Territory will have my strenu<lb break="no"/>ous support in this House ; and, if a proposi<lb break="no"/>tion to deal with the odd sections should 
     <lb/>come from my hon. friend. he may be per<lb break="no"/>fectly certain that he shall have my strong 
     <lb/>support. Now, Mr. Speaker, when the idea 
     <lb/>occurred to me of dealing with these odd 
     <lb/>sections. I went and saw Sir William Van 
     <lb/>Horne. then Mr. VanHorne. I told him 
     <lb/>what the conditions of the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories was and what I believed would be 
     <lb/>the advantage to the Territories and to 
     <lb/>Canada if these odd sections were thrown 
     <lb/>open to settlement. For I apprehend that 
     <lb/>nothing could be done so far as the land 
     <lb/>that has been granted to the Canadian 
     <lb/>Pacific Railway without the co-operation of 
     <lb/>that company. I pointed out to Mr. Van 
     <lb/>Horne that if he was ready to agree to re<lb break="no"/>convey these lands to the Government—or 
     <lb/>what would probably be the literal truth, if 
     <lb/>he were ready to forego selecting this land 
     <lb/>—it would pay his railway to do so even on 
     <lb/>a very small, or what might-seem a small, 
     <lb/>consideration. For it is palpable that if 
     <lb/>these odd sections are thrown open for set<lb break="no"/>tlement and if they are taken up by settlers 
     <lb/>the result' must be the Canadian Pacific 
     <lb/>Railway will get double the quantity of 
     <lb/>freight and double the number of passen<lb break="no"/>gers. And not merely that. Sir, but, as we 
     <lb/>know very well. if you had a whole town<lb break="no"/>ship instead of half a township the increase 
     <lb/>in business would not be measured by the 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <cb/>
       
       
     mere multiplication by two, as the business 
     <lb/>
     would become certainly much more 
     <lb/>
    than double what it has been. Sir William 
     <lb/>Van Horne, who, as we know here, 
     <lb/>is an enlightened and far-seeing man, 
     <lb/>and knows well what is for the benefit of 
     <lb/>his railway, said to me that the proposal 
     <lb/>seemed to him a good one, but he said I 
     <lb/>am, of course, in the hands of my directors. 
     <lb/>I ventured then to say what I think is pro<lb break="no"/>bably the case, that if Sir William Van 
     <lb/>Horne advised his directors in a course 
     <lb/>that, in his opinion, would be for the good 
     <lb/>of the railway, the chances are that his 
     <lb/>directors and himself would see eye to eye. 
     <lb/>My idea was this, that the Government 
     <lb/>might buy back the lands for $1.25 an acre. 
     <lb/>and, if they did so, the money paid would 
     <lb/>be well spent by the Government, it would 
     <lb/>be a proper use of publiemoney. and it 
     <lb/>would be a profitable transaction to the 
     <lb/>Canadian Pacific Railway. Well, what hap<lb break="no"/>pened during the late election ? One of the 
     <lb/>planks in my platform was the settlement of 
     <lb/>the odd sections, and the gentleman who 
     <lb/>was running against me, held me up to op<lb break="no"/>probrium. held me up to popular condemna<lb break="no"/>tion, because, as he said. I wanted to get 
     <lb/>the Government to give vast sums to the 
     <lb/>Canadian Pacific Railway for these odd 
     <lb/>sections. To my surprise, I found in many 
     <lb/>parts of my constituency, settlers who took 
     <lb/>the view that they did not want the odd 
     <lb/>sections thus disposed of. It is only fair 
     <lb/>that 1 should tell Parliament this. It would 
     <lb/>not be just to Parliament if I stated an ar<lb break="no"/>gument in favour of the Government reas<lb break="no"/>suming those odd sections, it would not be 
     <lb/>jusr to the hon. gentleman—and I could not 
     <lb/>be unjust to him—it would not be just either 
     <lb/>to the Government or to Parliament, if I 
     <lb/>stated an argument in favour of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment assuming control of those odd sec<lb break="no"/>tions once more, if I did not also mention 
     <lb/>the fact that I found, in going through my 
     <lb/>constituency that a number of settlers took 
     <lb/>a strong view against that proposal. Not 
     <lb/>only so, but a very prominent and active 
     <lb/>gentleman in the neighbouring constituency, 
     <lb/>Mr. Hawkes. has written, I think, to the Re<lb break="no"/>gina " Leader " a long letter, taking my hon. 
     <lb/>friend from Alberta (Mr. Oliver) and myself 
     <lb/>to task because of the views we are known 
     <lb/>to hold on this subject of the settlement of 
     <lb/>the odd sections. So my hon. friend who 
     <lb/>is at the head of the Government will be 
     <lb/>aware that a prominent supporter of his 
     <lb/>considers that it will be a dreadful course 
     <lb/>to take to expend vast sums to get hold of 
     <lb/>these odd Sections. However. that supporter 
     <lb/>is not in this House, and is not likely to be ; 
     <lb/>but the other supporter, who urges him 
     <lb/>here to-day to do something with these odd 
     <lb/>sections, is in the House. and his vote has 
     <lb/>to be considered, and I hope he will have 
     <lb/>more influence with the hon. gentleman at 
     <lb/>the head of the Government than any per<lb break="no"/>son who denounced the proposal when made 
     <lb/>by myself. It is desirable, as the House 
     <lb/>knows is my own opinion, that we should 
     <lb/>
      
      
            <pb n="423" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-08-31_Page_00423.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">423</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> 
               
               
     have a great deal more help than we have 
     <lb/>
     had in the Territories for creameries, and I 
     <lb/>
     think it is desirable that all that should be 
     <lb/>
     done by the local government. But how in 
     <lb/>
     the past, or how in the present, could the 
     <lb/>
     local government do it, when the grant to 
     <lb/>
     them is so contemptibly small and so utterly 
     <lb/>
     inadequate to the needs of the situation ? 
     <lb/>
     But if an adequate sum is given them, the 
     <lb/>
     local government, being on the spot, could 
     <lb/>
     attend to all needs. For instance, we know 
     <lb/>
     that in a vast area like the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories we may have good crops in one 
     <lb/>
     part extending over hundreds of thousands 
     <lb/>
     of square miles ; and in another part we 
     <lb/>
     may have a failure of crops. Now, the pro<lb break="no"/>per government to deal with that question 
     <lb/>
     is the government of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories; but how could the government of 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories deal with it, 
     <lb/>
     when, up to the present, the amount doled 
     <lb/>
     out to them has been weighed, as it were, 
     <lb/>
     in an apothecary's scales with the utmost 
     <lb/>
     nicety, so as to measure it out as regards 
     <lb/>
     the admitted needs of these Territories ? 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Speaker, it was a great pleasure to me 
     <lb/>
     to hear my hon. friend's voice once again, 
     <lb/>
     and I hope that in this House he and I, 
     <lb/>
     while we are colleagues, whether for a long 
     <lb/>
     or a short time, will use our united efforts 
     <lb/>
     for the good of the Territories. and for the 
     <lb/>
     support of any proposal, come from what<lb break="no"/>ever side it may, that will be for the good 
     <lb/>
     of the Territories, and let us not turn our 
     <lb/>
     efforts against each other at the bidding of 
     <lb/>
     either party or faction. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>