<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1897-04-21"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1897-04-21">21 April 1897</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Eighth Parliament, Second Session</title>.
          <date when="1897"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1030" to="1051"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01029.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01031.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01033.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01035.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01037.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01039.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01041.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01043.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01045.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01047.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01049.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01051.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-05">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01029">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01029.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01031">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01031.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01033">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01033.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01035">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01035.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01037">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01037.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01039">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01039.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01041">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01041.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01043">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01043.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01045">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01045.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01047">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01047.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01049">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01049.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01051">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01051.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1029" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01029.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">[APRIL 21, 1897]</fw>  <fw type="num">1030</fw> 
    
    
    
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SUBSIDY OF THE NORTH-WEST TER<lb break="no"/>RITORIES.</head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName> moved for: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Copies of all letters, petitions, memorials and 
     <lb/>
     suggestions received by the Government, or any 
     <lb/>
     member thereof, since the 23rd June, 1896, to 
     <lb/>
     amend the North-west Territories Act with a 
     <lb/>
     view of enlarging the powers of the executive of 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories and to increase the 
     <lb/>
     subsidy of the North-west Territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     He said : This is a motion of a character 
     <lb/>
     such as I have from year to year brought be<lb break="no"/>fore the House, sometimes with successful 
     <lb/>
     results and sometimes without anything 
     <lb/>
     being accomplished. Last session, my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend from Alberta (Mr. Oliver), brought 
     <lb/>
     forward a motion of a similar kind and 
     <lb/>
     nothing resulted from it. Subsequently, a 
     <lb/>
     session of the North-west Assembly was 
     <lb/>
     held and a memorial was passed which was 
     <lb/>
     forwarded to the Dominion Government. 
     <lb/>
    That memorial asked for several things, 
     <lb/>that there is no sign so far that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment intends to grant. During last session, 
     <lb/>in regard to one part of the question that 
     <lb/>that memorial deals with, a member of the 
     <lb/>executive of the North-west Territories 
     <lb/> came down to Ottawa, and one of the papers 
     <lb/>in the Territories had an article on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject, in which it said : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

            <p>
     Mr. Ross's first visit furnishes the Government 
     <lb/>
     a fair occasion to prove that the new-born confi<lb break="no"/>dence of the people in the Territories has not 
     <lb/>
     been misplaced. The attitude of the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment towards our legislative assembly was of 
     <lb/>
     late years most unfriendly. Year after year, the 
     <lb/>
     chairman of the executive journeyed to Ottawa 
     <lb/>
     to lay the fair and just claims of the North-west 
     <lb/>
     Territories before the Government, and year after 
     <lb/>
     year these just claims were contemptuously dis<lb break="no"/>regarded. The assembly appealed time and again 
     <lb/>
     lfor some definite subsidy, to do away with the 
     <lb/>
     ihand-to-mouth system, and allow the framing 
     <lb/>
     and institution of a progressive policy for the ad<lb break="no"/>ministration of local affairs. A deaf ear was 
     <lb/>
     turned to these appeals. Mr. Laurier has thus 
     <lb/>
     an early opportunity to demonstrate that he in<lb break="no"/>tends to deal justly and generously by the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Well, Sir, nothing was done last session by 
     <lb/>
     the Government of the Prime Minister who 
     <lb/>
     was thus appealed to by name, and there 
     <lb/>
     does not appear any evidence, from the 
     <lb/>
     Queen's Speech or from the Estimates now 
     <lb/>
     before us, that there is an intention of doing 
     <lb/>
     anything. There is, however, plenty of 
     <lb/>
     time for the Government to reconsider its 
     <lb/>
     position, and to decide to do something to 
     <lb/>
     show itself, as we are told by that paper, 
     <lb/>
     more generous than the previous Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Let me say, Mr. Speaker, in justice 
     <lb/>
     to that previous Government, that every<lb break="no"/>thing that was done for the North-West 
     <lb/>
       
       
            <pb n="1031" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01031.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1031</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1032</fw>
       
       
     Territories was done by them. They have               
     <lb/>
     done a great deal in the Territories. and             
     <lb/>
     from time to time. at my instance. they did                 
     <lb/>
     advance the bounds of the powers of the                 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories. and they did other                     
     <lb/>
    things for us. not merely at my instance in 
     <lb/>regard to these other things. but at the in<lb break="no"/>stance of myself and my colleagues, and 
     <lb/>those of us who went to wait on the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment as petitioners. But, Mr. Speaker, 
     <lb/>it was on the floor of this House that we 
     <lb/>accomplished the giving to the North-west 
     <lb/>Territories of what was properly described 
     <lb/>in this House last session by the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Alberta (Mr. Oliver), and as de<lb break="no"/>scribed in this memorial passed by the 
     <lb/>legislative assembly: as practically respon<lb break="no"/>sible government. In 1887 the Lieutenant- 
     <lb break="yes"/>Governor of these Territories was a Czar. 
     <lb/>and the assembly had practically no power 
     <lb/>whatever; but in 1887 the Territories were 
     <lb/>represented in this House, and from that 
     <lb/>moment the members of this Parliament 
     <lb/>moved in the direction of giving responsible 
     <lb/>government to the Territories. One of these 
     <lb/>members from the North-west Territories 
     <lb/>had a Bill on the paper providing that full 
     <lb/>responsible government be given to the Ter 
     <lb/>ritories, and thereupon, Sir John Macdonald 
     <lb/>brought down a Bill under which he gave 
     <lb/>us what was called an advisory council. 
     <lb/>That advisory council was found not to 
     <lb/>work well, nor did it give such power as 
     <lb/>should have been given to the Territories. 
     <lb/>and so we subsequently got what was called 
     <lb/>an executive committee. That executive 
     <lb/>committee had most of the powers of the 
     <lb/>government of a province, but the means 
     <lb/>of getting it into existence is awkward, and 
     <lb/>the means of continuing it, if one of its 
     <lb/>members should be destroyed by death or, 
     <lb/>resign, is also awkward. You have not, 
     <lb/>properly speaking, a responsible government 
     <lb/>there, although you have all the powers, 
     <lb/>with two or three exceptions, that are given 
     <lb/>to the provinces. For instance, under the 
     <lb/>present system I do not think you could 
     <lb/>possibly have party government. I do not     
     <lb/>
    
     think you could raise party issues under the 
     <lb/>
     present conditions, if it were found de<lb break="no"/>sirable to do so; because these four men 
     <lb/>
     are not a. government chosen by one man 
     <lb/>
     who is asked to construct. a government 
     <lb/>
     for the Lieutenant—Governor, but they are 
     <lb/>
     chosen by the assembly, and although there 
     <lb/>
     is one first among them called the chairman 
     <lb/>
     of the executive committee, nevertheless, he 
     <lb/>
     has not at all the power of a Prime Min<lb break="no"/>ister. I may tell you that the memorial 
     <lb/>
     passed unanimously in the assembly, and I 
     <lb/>
     wish to call the attention or the Government 
     <lb/>
     here to what it says : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The assembly is of the opinion that to remedy 
     <lb/>
     this undesirable state of things— 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Which I have just now described. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     —it is not necessary to have recourse to grant<lb break="no"/>ing a full provincial status. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     You will observe, Mr. Speaker, that the 
 
 
            <cb/>
         
         
     assembly does not want to have the full<lb/>provincial status given to them. I am not<lb/>going to discuss that. Probably I do not<lb/>know why they do not want it; perhaps I<lb/>cannot gather from the debates why they<lb/>do not want it. I myself now hold the<lb/>same opinion which I held in 1887: that the<lb/>best thing that could be done for these<lb/>Territories would be to give them full re<lb break="no"/>sponsible government. That is my opinion. 
     <lb/>
     but when you have the whole assembly of 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories stating that they 
     <lb/>
     do not want full responsible government, 
     <lb/>
     it would be very improper on the part of 
     <lb/>
     a member of this House. and very impro<lb break="no"/>per even if this whole House were unani<lb break="no"/>mous, to force full responsible government 
     <lb/>
     upon them. Therefore. although I have not 
     <lb/>
     changed my own opinion. I am not here 
     <lb/>
     to-day to ask for anything more than the 
     <lb/>
     people of the Territories have themselves 
     <lb/>
     asked for. I shall point out later on the 
     <lb/>
     very important consequences that follow 
     <lb/>
     fiom their not asking for full responsible 
     <lb/>
     government. When the change was made 
     <lb/>
     by the late Government shortly before it 
     <lb/>
     went out of power. whereby the amount of 
     <lb/>
     money placed at the disposal of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories Assembly was given en 
     <lb/>
     bloe, and not voted as a specific vote, a 
     <lb/>
     course should then have been taken by 
     <lb/>
     legislation to devise a safeguard which no 
     <lb/>
     longer exists in consequence of that change. 
     <lb/>
     It is, of course, necessary to have certain 
     <lb/>
     safeguards-for instance, over the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture of money ; because the Government of 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories has its pupil-like 
     <lb/>
     character of which it has no wish to divest 
     <lb/>
     itself; and we, in voting the money, must 
     <lb/>
     be in a position to ask this Government to 
     <lb/>
     show us how every farthing of the money 
     <lb/>
     has been spent, and whether it has been 
     <lb/>
     properly and judiciously expended ; that is, 
     <lb/>
     of course, speaking broadly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, they want two things—they want a 
     <lb/>
     change in the powers they exercise, and 
     <lb/>
    they want a larger subsidy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     They are of opinion that the time has come 
     <lb/>
     that their executive government should be put on 
     <lb/>
     a firmer basis, by substituting for the executive 
     <lb/>
     committee an executive council. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     I have described what they have at pre<lb break="no"/>sent, and of that the memorial says : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     It is evident that the assembly, having the 
     <lb/>
     power to vote money for distinct services, should 
     <lb/>
     have the right to control the proper carrying out 
     <lb/>
     of its intentions.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As in the present more developed state of the 
     <lb/>
    country, which has as much or more need for an 
     <lb/>intelligent and permanent administration and 
     <lb/>supervision of its resources and requirements as 
     <lb/>any other part of Canada, it is impossible for the 
     <lb/>assembly to act as an executive council ; they 
     <lb/>have been obliged to make provision in their sev<lb break="no"/>eral ordinances to entrust the administering of 
     <lb/> their laws to the Lieutenant-Governor, acting by 
     <lb/>and with the advice and consent of the commit<lb break="no"/>tee created by federal law for the purpose of ad 
     <lb/>vising with relation to expenditure only. They 
     <lb/>cannot, however, be sure that in taking the only 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <pb n="1033" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01033.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1033</fw> <fw type="dateline">[APRIL 21, 1897]</fw> <fw type="num">1034</fw>
          
          
     possible steps within their power to meet the ne<lb break="no"/>cessity, they have not exceeded their powers. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     That is a very important thing. There is to 
     <lb/>
     my mind, as there is evidently to the minds 
     <lb/>
     of the whole assembly, a clear doubt whe<lb break="no"/>ther, in adopting ordinances providing a 
     <lb/>
     modus vivendi, so to speak, they have not 
     <lb/>
     exceeded their powers ; because they are to 
     <lb/>
     some extent in the position of an inferior 
     <lb/>
     assembly amending the legislation of this 
     <lb/>
     supreme Dominion Parliament. Besides, 
     <lb/>
     the memorial points out : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The present machinery does not admit of de<lb break="no"/>velopment, as for instance, in the direction of 
     <lb/>
     division into departments with responsible heads. 
     <lb/>
     The executive committee also has not the right to 
     <lb/>
     advise the Lieutenant-Governor in matters not 
     <lb/>
     contained in the ordinances, notably the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of justices of the peace, and the convening 
     <lb/>
     and dissolving of an assembly. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Now, what they suggest is, that the Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment should amend the section of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories Act of 1891 (54 and 55 Vic<lb break="no"/>toria) which is substituted for section 13 of<lb/>the North-west Territories Act, chapter 50<lb/>of the Revised Statutes. That is the sec<lb break="no"/>tion which defines the powers of the as<lb break="no"/>sembly, and enumerates the various subjects<lb/>on which it may legislate. They suggest<lb/>that in that section this change should be<lb/>made :<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>The legislative assembly shall exclusively have<lb/>power to make ordinances for the government of<lb/>the organized Territories in relation to the classes<lb/>of subjects next hereinafter mentioned, that is to<lb/>say.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
            
            
            <p>While Parliament cannot divest itself of its<lb/>paramount right of legislation in the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, it is desirable that it should not, as<lb/>it often has done, unintentionally perhaps,<lb/>by legislation partly or wholly repeal the<lb/>powers given to the Territories under that<lb/>section 13, as may easily be done under the<lb/>law as it is at present.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Then they suggest that we should add a<lb/>clause to the North-west Territories Act<lb/>giving power to the assembly, notwithstand<lb break="no"/>ing anything in this Act or any other Act<lb/>of the Parliament of Canada, to repeal the<lb/>Territories Real Property Act. The object<lb/>of that is this. You have given them the<lb/>right over property and civil rights. They<lb/>can legislate on subjects dealt with by this<lb/>Real Property Act. They have already<lb/>made ordinances on those subjects. I am<lb/>not sure that you have not on your Table<lb/>at the present moment a Bill dealing with<lb/>matters of this kind. But it is palpable<lb/>that, if their ordinances varies in the least<lb/>from the legislation of this Parliament on<lb/>that subject, it is ultra vires. So that what<lb/>they ask for there is, I think, reasonable,<lb/>and what the Government can hardly re<lb break="no"/>fuse, if it intends that the powers given<lb/>them shall not be illusory.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Then, they suggest the repeal of section<lb/>17 of the North-west Territories Act of<lb/>1894, and to insert :<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     There shall be a council to aid and advise in 
     <lb/>
     the government of the Territories, to be styled 
     <lb/>
      the executive council of the Territories, and such 
     <lb/>
     council shall be composed of such persons and 
     <lb/>
     under such designations as the Lieutenant-Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor shall from time to time think fit.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     It is palpable that this is a demand for 
     <lb/>
     responsible government pure and simple ; 
     <lb/>
     and if you grant that request, the only 
     <lb/>
     difference between the Territories and the 
     <lb/>
     provinces would be that under clause 13 
     <lb/>
     the assembly of the Territories would be 
     <lb/>
     deprived of the authority to legislate on 
     <lb/>
     one or two subjects, and one or two other 
     <lb/>
     powers which a provincial legislature has— 
     <lb/>
     for instance, the power to borrow money ; 
     <lb/>
     but maugre these two or three subjects, 
     <lb/>
     you would give them responsible government 
     <lb/>
     if this third request were granted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      Then, they wish to have sub-clause C of 
     <lb/>
    subsection 7 of section 13 repealed—that 
     <lb/>which relates to insurance companies. They<lb/>very properly say that there is no reason<lb/>for depriving an assembly of men who are<lb/>just as intelligent, enlightened and experi<lb break="no"/>enced as the men in any assembly of any<lb/>province, of the power of giving a charter<lb/>to an insurance company. It is palpable<lb/>that that very elementary right of a civi<lb break="no"/>lized community should be within their<lb/>power.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Then they wish to have inserted a clause<lb/>in the North-west Territories Act giving<lb/>to the Lieutenant-Governor in Council the<lb/>power to appoint sheriffs, and so on. That<lb/>is a mere detail, and I do not attach much<lb/>importance to it. If the Government go as<lb/>far as the Act, they will probably give them<lb/>these powers.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

            <p>
     Then, they suggest that, subject to con<lb break="no"/>ditions, the following subsection should be 
     <lb/>
      inserted :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The establishment, maintenance and manage<lb break="no"/>ment or hospitals, charities and eleemosynary in<lb break="no"/>stitutions in and for the Territories, and repeal 
     <lb/>
      sections 103, 104 and 105 of chapter 50, R.S.C., in 
     <lb/>
      so far as they are inconsistent with the powers 
     <lb/>
     asked for. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Now, you will see that in the Estimates 
     <lb/>
     brought down, on page 67, under the head 
     <lb/>of "Government of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories," you have "Insane patients, Mani<lb break="no"/>toba, $30,000." What happens at present is<lb/>this, that any insane patients we have are<lb/>sent to Manitoba, and there is no reason<lb/>whatever why we should not take charge<lb/>of our own insane. Lunatics from the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories are, under an agreement between<lb/>the federal authorities and the province of<lb/>Manitoba, which expires in 1898, sent to the<lb/>asylums of that province, and at present<lb/>there are in such asylums 74 persons cost<lb break="no"/>ing one dollar per day. Surely the assembly<lb/>is only rational in contending that they<lb/>could perform such service as well and more<lb/>cheaply than Manitoba. An insane man is<lb/>found in some part of the Territories, and<lb/>instead of sending him to an asylum in<lb/>


            <pb n="1035" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01035.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1035</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1036</fw>
    
    
    
     Calgary, or Regina or Moose Jaw, or Medi<lb break="no"/>cine Hat—wherever the asylum might be— 
     <lb/>
     he is sent 300 or 400 miles further into 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba, and the clumsy expedient is used 
     <lb/>
     of charging the Territories with the cost, 
     <lb/>
     under the agreement by which the Mani<lb break="no"/>toba institution takes charge. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As regards hospitals, the assembly already 
     <lb/>
     provides, as far as its means will allow, for 
     <lb/>
     the assistance of a hospital built and kept by 
     <lb/>
     private charity, and we have at Medicine 
     <lb/>
     Hat and at Calgary a magnificent hospital 
     <lb/>
     in each place. We have a hospital at Medi<lb break="no"/>cine Hat due to the enterprise and philan<lb break="no"/>thropy, in the main, of John Niblock—a 
     <lb/>
     hospital which, I have no doubt, some of 
     <lb/>
     my friends on both sides of the House have 
     <lb/>
     visited and which all who have visited it 
     <lb/>
     must admit is not merely a credit to Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Niblock's energy and philanthropy, but to 
     <lb/>
     the philanthropy of the North-west Territo<lb break="no"/>ries also and the passenger public, because 
     <lb/>
     there are wards in it that illustrate the 
     <lb/>
     benevolence of those who have visited it 
     <lb/>
     from time to time. And let me say, in pass-   
     <lb/>
     ing. that I greatly regret, when I bring for<lb break="no"/>ward a subject of this kind, that we have 
     <lb/>
     not the Minister of the Interior in his place. 
     <lb/>
     There is a just claim on the part of this 
     <lb/>
    hospital, outstanding now for some years 
     <lb/>against the Department of the Interior, and 
     <lb/>I have strong hopes that the Minister of the 
     <lb/>Interior will do it the justice of seeing that 
     <lb/>this claim is paid. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The assembly also wants the repeal of 
     <lb/>
     section 21 of the North-west Territories Act 
     <lb/>
     of 1894 and that an Act should be introduc<lb break="no"/>ed respecting roads and road allowance of 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories, with similar pro<lb break="no"/>visions to those contained in chapter 49 of 
     <lb/>
     the Revised Statutes of Canada respecting 
     <lb/>
     roads and road allowance in Manitoba. The 
     <lb/>
     object of this is to do away with the uncer<lb break="no"/>tanties and difficulties connected with the 
     <lb/>
     laying out, improving and acquiring roads 
     <lb/>
     by expropriation and to give to the assembly 
     <lb/>
     the right to delegate such powers to muni<lb break="no"/>cipalities. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then they desire that a clause should he 
     <lb/>
     added giving the assembly the power to re<lb break="no"/>peal, alter, vary or re-enact the provisions 
     <lb/>
     for the appointment of justices of the peace 
     <lb/>
     and their qualifications. That question, 
     <lb/>
     however. is one of detail which I am not go<lb break="no"/>ing to discuss. because if the Government 
     <lb/>
     decide to do the large things asked for, that 
     <lb/>
     will follow, no doubt, as a matter of course. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The other large subject dealt with by this 
     <lb/>
     memorial of the assembly is the subject of 
     <lb/>
     finance. That has been from time to time 
     <lb/>
     placed before this House. It was ably 
     <lb/>
     placed before us last session by my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend from Alberta (Mr. Oliver), and no<lb break="no"/>thing new has since taken place that would 
     <lb/>
     add to the arguments which he put before 
     <lb/>
     this House. I shall just call attention to 
     <lb/>
     what the memorial contains on that subject. 
     <lb/>
     At present, if you look at the Estimates, 
     <lb/>
     you will find that the main grant is for 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <cb/>
          
          
     schools, clerical assistance, printing, &amp;c.; 
     <lb/>
     and as the hon. member for Alberta point<lb break="no"/>ed out last session, the chief thing to be 
     <lb/>
     provided, out of that $242,000 is schools. 
     <lb/>
     This is what the memorial says on that 
     <lb/>
     point: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Owing to the vast area of the Territories and 
     <lb/>
     the widely scattered nature of the settlement, all 
     <lb/>
     the business of the local government is rendered 
     <lb/>
     more expensive and proportionately to the popula<lb break="no"/>tion than in any province. As regards roads this 
     <lb/>
     is apparent, but with respect to schools it will be 
     <lb/>
     found equally true. By considering that, under 
     <lb/>
     the most favourable circumstances, less than 
     <lb/>
     half the area in each township is available for 
     <lb/>
     homesteading, and that, as a rule, only a small 
     <lb/>
    amount is taken up, it will not create surprise 
     <lb/>to see that in 1895 it took 341 schools, with 401 
     <lb/>teachers, to educate 11,972 enrolled pupils, with 
     <lb/>a daily average attendance of 6,600, and that, out 
     <lb/>of these schools, 223 were only open during the 
     <lb/>summer months, with a daily average attendance 
     <lb/>of 11. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Let me call the special attention of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment now to this argument on behalf of 
     <lb/>
     our claim for a larger subsidy: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     In 1891, the population was 66,769; the number 
     <lb/>
     of schools in operation was 224. In 1892, the 
     <lb/>
     number of schools in operation was 237, and the 
     <lb/>parliamentary grant was $208,700. In 1895, the<lb/>
     
     number of schools was 341, being an increase in 
     <lb/>
     four years of over 52 per cent. In 1896, the pop<lb break="no"/>ulation was 104,221, or 10 per cent per year ad<lb break="no"/>ded to the census of 1894, being the ratio of in<lb break="no"/>crease between 1891 and 1894, and the grant from 
     <lb/>
    Parliament was $242,879, not including $25,000 
     <lb/>supplementary vote to recoup the assembly for 
     <lb/>relief expenditure undertaken for and on account 
     <lb/>of the Dominion Government, being an increase 
     <lb/>in five years in population of 56 per cent, and in 
     <lb/>annual grant during the last four years of 16 per 
     <lb/>cent. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
     <lb/>
     FISHERIES</persName> (Mr. Davies). What was the 
     <lb/>
     amount of the supplementary vote ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. $25,000. Thus while the 
     <lb/>
     population increased 56 per cent. the in<lb break="no"/>crease of the annual grant was only a little 
     <lb/>
     over one-quarter of that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, in the Territories the conditions of 
     <lb/>
     the Government are somewhat analogous to 
     <lb/>
     those of Manitoba; and, therefbre, a com<lb break="no"/>parison between Manitoba and the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories is a natural one. Nothing could be 
     <lb/>more natural than that we should ask, as 
     <lb/>we asked in 1887 as we asked in 1888, and 
     <lb/>in 1889, and in 1890, and in 1891, and every 
     <lb/>year including last year through my hon. 
     <lb/>friend from Alberta (Mr. Oliver), that we 
     <lb/>should be treated on precisely the same foot<lb break="no"/>ing as Manitoba. Now, if we were so 
     <lb/>treated what would be the result ? The 
     <lb/>population of the Territories in 1891 accord<lb break="no"/>ing to the census of that year, was 66,799. 
     <lb/>According to the census taken by the North<lb break="no"/>west Mounted Police in 1894, the population 
     <lb/>was 86,851. According to that ratio of in<lb break="no"/>crease. namely, 30 per cent, the population 
     <lb/>in 1897 is 112,906. Now. if we were treated 
     <lb/>on the same basis as Manitoba, according 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="1037" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01037.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1037</fw> <fw type="dateline">[APRIL 21, 1897]</fw> <fw type="num">1038</fw>
        
        
     to subsection B of section 5, of chapter 46, 
     <lb/>
     of the Revised Statutes of Canada, the per 
     <lb/>
     capita grant would be calculated on an ap<lb break="no"/>proximate estimate of the population two 
     <lb/>
     and one-half years from 1897, which, at the 
     <lb/>
     rate of increase that I mentioned in an 
     <lb/>
     earlier part of my remarks, namely, 10 per 
     <lb/>
     cent a year, would be 141,132. Now, the 
     <lb/>
     per capita grant of 80 cents a head for 141,<lb break="no"/>132 would give you the sum of $112,905. 
     <lb/>
     Then on the debt account, on a presumably 
     <lb/>
     actual population in 1887 of 141,132, the 
     <lb/>
     amount would be 5 per cent on $32.44 per 
     <lb/>
     head, making $183,133. An amount for the 
     <lb/>
     support of government and legislation is 
     <lb/>
     given to Manitoba of $50,000 a year. Is 
     <lb/>
     there any reason why we should not get 
     <lb/>
     $50,000 also for the same purpose ? No 
     <lb/>
     reason whatever. Then, Manitoba has been 
     <lb/>
     held to be entitled to an indemnity of 
     <lb/>
     $100,000 a year, because the administration 
     <lb/>
     of its lands it withheld from it. But what 
     <lb/>
     are the lands of Manitoba compared with 
     <lb/>
     the lands of the North-west Territories ? 
     <lb/>
     What are the claims, therefore, of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba as compared with the claims of the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories in this particular ? 
     <lb/>
     The Territories, of course, have a much 
     <lb/>
     stronger claim to compensation, inasmuch 
     <lb/>
     as besides the land grants to railways in 
     <lb/>
     and for the Territories, what has been done 
     <lb/>
     with our lands ? Why, Sir, we have been 
     <lb/>
     a quarry to which they have come from 
     <lb/>
     every quarter to get land grants. 
     <lb/>
     way seeks a land grant, it always looks to 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories. Land grants 
     <lb/>
     have been given for the general benefit of 
     <lb/>
    Canada, and for the special benefit of the 
     <lb/>eastern provinces and British Columbia ; 
     <lb/>land grants have been given within the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories for railways constructed for and in 
     <lb/>Manitoba for which no sufficient land grant 
     <lb/>could be found in that province. The pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Manitoba has been given all lands 
     <lb/>designated as swamp lands. Now, if you 
     <lb/>come to consider what should be given us 
     <lb/>we should get a far larger grant than 
     <lb/>$100,000 on this account. It really ought to    
     <lb/>be $30,000. But suppose you only add $50,<lb break="no"/>000 to what is given to Manitoba, and you<lb/>get a land grant that should be given us of <lb/>$150,000. So the amounts we should get<lb/>would be :<lb/>
            </p>
            
         <table>
            <row><cell>Provincial subsidy.................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$112,903</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Debt account.................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">183,133</cell></row>
            <row><cell>Support of government and legislation...</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">50,000</cell></row>
            <row><cell>On account of lands.........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">150,000</hi></cell></row>
            <row><cell>Making a total of..............</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$496,038</cell></row>
            
         </table>   
            
            
            
            
            <p>And what do we get here in these Estimates<lb/>after this matter has been-<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
     <lb/>
     FISHERIES</persName> (Mr. Davies). What do   I   
     <lb/>understand the hon. gentleman (Mr. Davin)<lb/>to be reading from ? From what does he<lb/>get these figures ?<lb/>
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I am giving the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man a calculation that is not now given in 
     <lb/>
     
        
        
            <cb/>
        
        
     this House for the first time. It was given<lb/>here last session, it was given even before<lb/>that. I am referring to the same calcula<lb break="no"/>tion made in the memorial that has been<lb/>transmitted to the Government after having<lb/>been passed unanimously in the North-west<lb/>assembly.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND <lb/>FISHERIES</persName>. That was what I wished to<lb/>know. I understand the hon. gentleman is<lb/>reading from the memorial.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr DAVIN. These are the figures in the<lb/>memorial.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND<lb/>FISHERIES</persName>. The hon. gentleman referred 
     <lb/>to the speech made by the hon. member for 
     <lb/>Alberta (Mr. Oliver), and I was not sure 
     <lb/>whether he was reading from that speech 
     <lb/>or from the memorial. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I referred to the fact that 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend (Mr. Oliver) had brought 
     <lb/>
     this matter before the House, as had been 
     <lb/>
     done every year. But I wish to point out 
     <lb/>
     that $150,000, the sum I have last mention<lb break="no"/>ed, was not mentioned in the memorial. 
     <lb/>
     The memorial points out that Manitoba gets 
     <lb/>
     $100,000 and says that we are entitled to 
     <lb/>
     more. but does not mention a sum. To 
     <lb/>
     reach an aggregate, I supposed that it 
     <lb/>
     should be made $150,000. So, instead of 
     <lb/>
     $242,000, we should get $496,000. I pointed 
     <lb/>
     this out, two years ago, I think, when the 
     <lb/>
     present Government was not in power, and 
     <lb/>
     when my hon. friend was sitting in Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion—and at that time I got help from hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen who are now sitting, as the 
     <lb/>
     Prime Minister says, enthroned like the 
     <lb/>
     Olympian gods, in a place where they used 
     <lb/>
     not to sit. I used to get help from them. I 
     <lb/>
     do not know whether he (Mr. Davies) gave 
     <lb/>
     me help, but there were gentlemen on that 
     <lb/>
     side who used to give me help in contend<lb break="no"/>ing for what I did contend for from year<lb/>
    to year. And, in fact, two years ago, we 
     <lb/>had more than a million dollars due us by 
     <lb/>the Dominion Government. If we had a 
     <lb/>       commission such as sat the other day in re<lb break="no"/>gard to taxation in Ireland, it would be<lb/>found that the North-west Territories, like<lb/>Ireland, had been paying a large amount of <lb/>taxation that we ought not to have had to<lb/>pay. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:COCH1">Mr. COCHRANE</persName>. Do not suggest a com<lb break="no"/>mission, or we shall have one. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI10">Mr. DAVIS</persName>. This would not be a very 
     <lb/>
    expensive commission, and its work would 
     <lb/>not take very long. The calculation is 
     <lb/>easily made, because we have all the facts. 
     <lb/>And if my hon. friend the Minister of Ma<lb break="no"/>rine and Fisheries will only make the calcu<lb break="no"/>lation, he will easily reach the result. Let 
     <lb/>him for a moment fancy that he has taken 
     <lb/>a brief for the Territories. I am told by 
     <lb/>the chairman of the executive of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories that something like this 
     <lb/>memorial has been sent to every member 
     <lb/>
        
        
            <pb n="1039" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01039.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1039</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1040</fw>
      
      
      
     of the Government and that they are in pos<lb break="no"/>session of it. Let the hon. gentleman read 
     <lb/>
     that. I know he is an able lawyer,—let him 
     <lb/>
     fancy that we have given him a brief and 
     <lb/>
     put a large fee in his pocket and that he is 
     <lb/>
    to make out a case for us. Let him read 
     <lb/>it in that light and he will be perfectly 
     <lb/>astonished what a case he can make out for 
     <lb/>the Territories and against the lethargy of 
     <lb/>his own Government, because this is the 
     <lb/>second session. and. apparently, up to the 
     <lb/>present. they have done nothing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANON1">An hon. MEMBER</persName>. Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. It will be carried in a short 
     <lb/>
    time. By the way, what mavis singing- 
     <lb break="yes"/>bird was that I heard? Now, I have some<lb break="no"/>thing to suggest that I think will be wel<lb break="no"/>comed by every territorial statesman, I mean 
     <lb/>the members of the provincial assembly, 
     <lb/>and it will be welcomed by every man who 
     <lb/>has the interests of the Territories at heart. 
     <lb/>I doubt, Sir, if there is any arrangement; 
     <lb/>that has been made by this Parliament that 
     <lb/>has worked more successfully and to better 
     <lb/>advantage than the arrangement that was 
     <lb/>made by the Parliament of Canada that we ; 
     <lb/>should have an Auditor General perfectly 
     <lb/>independent of the Government of the day.   
     <lb/>I think it has been a great advantage to the 
     <lb/>people, it has been in the interests of eco<lb break="no"/>nomy, and I believe it has been of advan<lb break="no"/>tage to the Government in the past, and 
     <lb/>is an advantage to the Government to-day, 
     <lb/>so far as they desire to act economically. 
     <lb/>Now, let us suppose that the Government 
     <lb/>intends to accede to the prayer of this me-: 
     <lb/>morial, and to give the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories the kind of government they demand; 
     <lb/>but even if they do not do that, what I 
     <lb/>am now about to suggest that they should 
     <lb/>do is to provide an auditor that will be 
     <lb/>appointed by the Government of Canada, 
     <lb/>and will be perfectly independent of the, 
     <lb/>Government of the Territories. Of course, 
     <lb/>when the time comes that a full provincial 
     <lb/>government would be given to the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, that arrangement would cease, and 
     <lb/>we would expect that the Territorial As<lb break="no"/>sembly, when it would take up its full man<lb break="no"/>hood, would re-appoint that auditor, or at 
     <lb/>all events, appoint somebody in his place, 
     <lb/>and continue that very useful oilicial; and 
     <lb/>also appoint him under an ordinance 
     <lb/>such as our Audit Act, that would make 
     <lb/>him independent of the executive of the day. 
     <lb/>I think that would be in the interests of the 
     <lb/>Territories. But at the present moment, 
     <lb/>we are bound, here in this Parliament, to 
     <lb/>see that such an auditor exists. We have 
     <lb/>no means at present of knowing how the 
     <lb/>money is spent that we vote to the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. That executive and that assembly 
     <lb/>are only a function of the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment as long as they do not get full 
     <lb/>provincial autonomy. At present they 
     <lb/>do not want full provincial autonomy, as 
     <lb/>I have already pointed out to my hon. 
     <lb/>friend when I quoted the memorial. 
            </p>
       
       
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
     <lb/>
     FISHERIES</persName> (Mr. Davies). A fuller mea<lb break="no"/>sure of economy might involve the right 
     <lb/>
     and the duty of raising money by taxation ; 
     <lb/>
     and they do not want that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I do not think there will be 
     <lb/>
     any necessity for it, because they do raise 
     <lb/>
     money for taxation at present, that is, they 
     <lb/>
     raise a local fund of $30,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
     <lb/>
     FISHERIES</persName>. How ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:DAVI10">Mr. DAVIS</persName>. By licenses; they have 
     <lb/>
     a local revenue of $30,000—I think it is 
     <lb/>
     about that sum. But I would like to point 
     <lb/>
     out to my hon. friend that they say they 
     <lb/>
     do not wish to get full responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment. This is their language: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The assembly is of opinion, that to remedy this 
     <lb/>
     undesirable state of affairs. it is not necessary to 
     <lb/>
     have recourse to granting the full provincial 
     <lb/>
     status. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     They do not ask for it, and this memorial 
     <lb/>
     passed unanimously. The money they spend 
     <lb/>
     is money voted by this Parliament, and 
     <lb/>
     therefore it is logical that this Parliament 
     <lb/>
     know how that money is spent. 
     <lb/>
     Some years ago we voted a specific sum 
     <lb/>
     for all the work that was done in these 
     <lb/>
     Territories, and the sums used to lapse. 
     <lb/>
     I was one of the persons, with Mr. Haul<lb break="no"/>tain and others, who went to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to get that done away with, and we 
     <lb/>
     got a system adopted whereby you now 
     <lb/>
     vote a block sum, such as we have here—a 
     <lb/>
     grant for schools, clerical assistance. print<lb break="no"/>ing. &amp;c., to be paid half—yearly in advance, 
     <lb/>$242,000. Now, I want to see a far larger 
     <lb/>sum voted, I want to see this House do 
     <lb/>justice to the Territories, and vote them 
     <lb/>a sum of $500,000, which sum is the very 
     <lb/>least that will enable them to manage these 
     <lb/>Territories effectively. But whether we 
     <lb/>vote them that much or not, as we are 
     <lb/>voting money, we ought to have an audit 
     <lb/>independent of the executive, and an inde<lb break="no"/>pendent audit will be welcomed by the ex<lb break="no"/>ecutive. If they do not welcome it, there 
     <lb/>is the more necessity for it; if they wel<lb break="no"/>come it, then there is necessity for it, and 
     <lb/>it should be given at once. What we should 
     <lb/>have is a Dominion auditor, an officer up 
     <lb/>there paid out of the territorial fund, paid 
     <lb/>by the executive, but whose appointment 
     <lb/>would be independent of the executive. That 
     <lb/>would give us an account of how the moneys 
     <lb/>are spent that we now vote en bloc, and 
     <lb/>we have no account of how they are spent; 
     <lb/>whereas when we voted them in the manner 
     <lb/>I desired to see abolished, and which I was 
     <lb/>contributory to abolishing, we did know 
     <lb/>how the money was spent. As long as we 
     <lb/>vote the money, we ought to know how that 
     <lb/>money is spent. Now, it is well known 
     <lb/>that contracts for large sums have been 
     <lb/>given. and I believe that it has been done 
     <lb/>elsewhere also, within recent ,months—but 
     <lb/>contracts for considerable sums have been 
     <lb/>  
   
         
         
            <pb n="1041" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01041.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1041</fw> <fw type="dateline">[APRIL 21, 1897]</fw> <fw type="num">1042</fw>
        
        
        
     given without tenders being called for. Well, 
     <lb/>
     if that is so, a part of this money that we 
     <lb/>
     are voting is spent in that way. It may 
     <lb/>
     be spent well, but we ought to know that 
     <lb/>
     it is spent well, and we ought to have an 
     <lb/>
     auditor to overhaul that. I am not sure 
     <lb/>
     that we should go beyond our function if 
     <lb/>
     we were to insist that contracts for any 
     <lb/>
     considerable amount should be invariably 
     <lb/>
     based upon tenders. I hope the Government 
     <lb/>
     will go into this question, I hope the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment will listen to the prayer of this 
     <lb/>
     memorial, I hope the Government will give 
     <lb/>
     an adequate sum, 1 hope the Government 
     <lb/>
     will alter the character of the executive 
     <lb/>
     and make it of a responsible character, to 
     <lb/>
     the extent that they demand. But in doing 
     <lb/>
     that let the Government make a constitu<lb break="no"/>tion that will be consistent. If you make 
     <lb/>
     a constitution short of perfect provincial 
     <lb/>
     autonomy, such as these gentlemen desire, 
     <lb/>
     and still keep them in 'statu tutelari,' then 
     <lb/>
     you are bound as long as they are spending 
     <lb/>
     money that we vote here. to have an officer 
     <lb/>
     who will give us an account of how that 
     <lb/>
     money is spent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV4">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. I am sure the people of 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories will be very glad 
     <lb/>
     to know that the hon. gentleman (Mr. Davin) 
     <lb/>
     who has just sat down. is advocating their 
     <lb/>
     interests so strongly, and I have no doubt 
     <lb/>
     they will accord him almost that measure 
     <lb/>
     of appreciation that he received at the late 
     <lb/>
     election, in the coming election that is likely 
     <lb/>
     to take place in his constituency. I do not 
     <lb/>
     wish to argue all the different points he has 
     <lb/>
     raised: I will only say that on the general 
     <lb/>
     question the hon. gentleman and myself are 
     <lb/>
     at one. namely, that the Territories are en<lb break="no"/>titled to a greater measure of consideration 
     <lb/>
     at the hands of this Government. I can only 
     <lb/>
    hope that the hon. member will be able, by; 
     <lb/>his arguments. so to influence those who 
     <lb/>sit on the same side of the House as him<lb break="no"/>self, that, what they were able to do when 
     <lb/>they had the power and did not do, that is, 
     <lb/>gran the fuller measure of justice to the<lb/>Territories that the people of those Terri<lb break="no"/>tories desire and expect, they will support 
     <lb/>the new Government in doing when the 
     <lb/>opportunity arises. This question was 
     <lb/>brought before the House on a pre<lb break="no"/>vious occasion. It is before the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment again. Gentlemen representing 
     <lb/>the Government of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories are here now. It is quite within 
     <lb/>the knowledge of the hon. gentleman (Mr. 
     <lb/>Davin) that members of that Government 
     <lb/>are here for the purpose of claiming addi<lb break="no"/>tional subsidy and additional powers. I 
     <lb/>should like to point out to the House that 
     <lb/>while the hon. gentleman made a lengthy 
     <lb/>appeal on behalf of the memorial which 
     <lb/>those hon. gentlemen are advocating, he also 
     <lb/>made an insinuation against the gentlemen 
     <lb/>themselves, and thereby attempted to weak<lb break="no"/>en their case with the Government of the 
     <lb/>day, for he insinuated that the Government 
     <lb/>of which they are the head was not spend<lb break="no"/>
      
      
            <cb/>
        
        ing the money in its hands in a manner that 
     <lb/>
     was for the best interest of the country and 
     <lb/>
     the people, and that they had to be watched 
     <lb/>
     in fact, it was absolutely necessary they 
     <lb/>
     should be watched by a special auditor ap<lb break="no"/>pointed by this Government. 1 say that 
     <lb/>
     while the hon. gentleman was, on the one 
     <lb/>
     hand, declaring that their wishes should be 
     <lb/>
     granted, on the other hand he was trying to 
     <lb/>
     make light of the position of those gentle<lb break="no"/>men and to weaken confidence in them so 
     <lb/>
     that their representations would not be 
     <lb/>
     agreed to. In this case, as in others, the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman has been blowing hot and 
     <lb/>
     cold; one reason that we have not been 
     <lb/>
     able to get what we desired in the past. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I submit that the position of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories at the present time, in so 
     <lb/>
     far as the control of the funds voted to 
     <lb/>
     them by Parliament is concerned should be. 
     <lb/>
     if it is not. exactly the same as that of a 
     <lb/>
     province. Certain money is voted to respon<lb break="no"/>sible representatives of the people of the 
     <lb/>
     Territories for expenditure, under the con<lb break="no"/>trol of responsible advisers, and there is no 
     <lb/>
     reason why that Government should not 
     <lb/>
     have full control of the funds, as has the 
     <lb/>
     legislature of a province. When the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman says that the North-west Govern<lb break="no"/>ment do not ask for full provincial powers. 
     <lb/>
     and advances reasons why they should not 
     <lb/>
     be given control of money, which only they 
     <lb/>
     can properly control, he shows a desire to 
     <lb/>
     weaken and not strengthen their case. They 
     <lb/>
     are the only people who can know to what 
     <lb/>
     purposes this money should be applied, and 
     <lb/>
     how it should be applied. When this Par<lb break="no"/>liament votes money to be expended by the 
     <lb/>
     Territories the control ceases or should 
     <lb/>cease, as regards this Government as to show<lb/>the money should be expended. It is<lb/>
    now expended by the North-west Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. and with all respect to the 
     <lb/>hon. gentleman. I believe it will continue 
     <lb/>to be expended on the responsibility of the 
     <lb/>executive of the North-west Territories, and 
     <lb/>solely on that responsibility. As to the pro<lb break="no"/>vincial powers not asked for: Allow me to<lb/>say that there are certain powers now exer<lb break="no"/>cised by the Government of the North-west 
     <lb/>exactly to the same extent as they are exer<lb break="no"/>cised by a province. This has been done with 
     <lb/>the consent of the Government here, with 
     <lb/>the consent of Parliament, and by reason of 
     <lb/>to continue. The first of these is the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture of money that comes properly within 
     <lb/>the control of the assembly. The other 
     <lb/>matters are in relation to education in re<lb break="no"/>gard to which the Government of the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories has as full powers as the legisla<lb break="no"/>ture of any province: in regard to legis<lb break="no"/>lation with respect to property and civil 
     <lb/>rights, as to which the Territories have the 
     <lb/>same rights as a province, and also in re<lb break="no"/>gard to municipal organization, in respect 
     <lb/>to which also the Territories have the same 
     <lb/>powers as a province. The points in which 
     <lb/>they lack the power of a province are points 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <pb n="1043" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01043.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1043</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1044</fw>
      
      
     of detail rather than of principle; except 
     <lb/>
     this one, that the Territories have not a 
     <lb/>
     fixed subsidy, and have not power to 
     <lb/>
     pledge the credit of the country for a loan. 
     <lb/>
     These are rights belonging to a province, 
     <lb/>
     and they are not asked by the representa<lb break="no"/>tives of the North-west Government. The 
     <lb/>
     reason why they do not ask for a fixed sub<lb break="no"/>sidy is no doubt owing to the fact that the 
     <lb/>
     extent of the country and its progress 
     <lb/>
     vould act against their interests rather than 
     <lb/>
     in their favour if there were a fixed sub<lb break="no"/>sidy granted; that is to say, the country 
     <lb/>
     would outgrow the subsidy so quickly that 
     <lb/>
     if there were a fixed subsidy, instead of 
     <lb/>
     proving advantageous it would be distinctly 
     <lb/>
     disadvantageous. That is the reason why 
     <lb/>
     they do not want a fixed subsidy which 
     <lb/>
     would be the equivalent of a provincial sub<lb break="no"/>sidy, and that is the only important power 
     <lb/>
     they do not ask as compared with the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Manitoba, which occupies the same 
     <lb/>
     position as the Territories as regards the 
     <lb/>
     control of lands. I will not occupy the time 
     <lb/>
    of the House at any greater length. but in 
     <lb/>conclusion I will say that the gentlemen re<lb break="no"/>presenting the North-west Territories, who 
     <lb/>are here now, are entitled personally to the 
     <lb/>full confidence of the Government in any 
     <lb/>negotiations that may take place their re<lb break="no"/>presentations are entitled to full considera<lb break="no"/>tion, and I have every confidence that they 
     <lb/>will receive that consideration at the hands 
     <lb/>of the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I think we have had a 
     <lb/>
     somewhat extraordinary exhibition by an 
     <lb/>hon. gentleman who seemed to be tearing<lb/>mad because he could not agree with me.<lb/>
    The hon. gentleman was ready to rip him<lb break="no"/>self up because he had to agree with the 
     <lb/>propositions I laid down. It was certainly 
     <lb/>a most extraordinary position, that the hon. 
     <lb/>gentleman on being obliged to agree with 
     <lb/>me should have got mad. It would seem 
     <lb/>that the only kind of speaking to which he 
     <lb/>is accustomed is scoiding. and as he had 
     <lb/>not an opponent, he had to scold a friend, 
     <lb/>and some one who advocated propositions 
     <lb/>with which he agreed. I hope the hon. 
     <lb/>member for Alberta (Mr. Oliver) for the 
     <lb/>credit of the North-west, will reconsider his 
     <lb/>parliamentary demeanour. and not treat the 
     <lb/>country to such an exhibition as we have 
     <lb/>just had. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:OLIV4">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. I rise to reiterate what I 
     <lb/>
     stated. I agree with the general proposi<lb break="no"/>tions of the hon. gentleman. but I resent. 
     <lb/>
     and resent strongly, the mean insinuations 
     <lb/>
     he conveyed against gentlemen who repre<lb break="no"/>sent the North-west in negotiations now go<lb break="no"/>ng on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. The hon. gentleman has not 
     <lb/>
     improved his position by his explanation. 
     <lb/>
    He resented something that was not in my 
     <lb/>remarks. He became as mad as a March 
     <lb/>hare, although this is April, because he 
     <lb/>could not find anything in my remarks to 
     <lb/>find fault with, and then he insinuated 
     <lb/>
       
       
            <cb/>
        
        
     something that was not in my remarks. I 
     <lb/>
     referred with the greatest respect to my 
     <lb/>
     friend the chairman of the executive. I 
     <lb/>
     know those two gentlemen from the North<lb break="no"/>west are here. I have never in the past, 
     <lb/>
     here or elsewhere, been blinded by that ex<lb break="no"/>traordinary sentiment that I have seen some 
     <lb/>
     persons blinded with, that they must claim 
     <lb/>
     credit for this, that and the other. I have 
     <lb/>
     never entertained any such feelings as that. 
     <lb/>
     Anything proposed for the good of the coun<lb break="no"/>try or for the North-west Territories, I have 
     <lb/>
     been ready to help forward ; so that when 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman. last session—although 
     <lb/>
     I think his behaviour in a certain way then 
     <lb/>
     was extraordinary for a young member- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     made a motion. I rose and supported him. 
     <lb/>
     I did not manifest the miserable, wretched, 
     <lb/>
     insect spirit he has manifested here. and that 
     <lb/>
     ranks him not on a level with hon. legis<lb break="no"/>lators in this chamber— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. I am afraid both hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen in their last few remarks have 
     <lb/>
     'not been quite in order. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man (Mr. Oliver) spoke of mean insinuations 
     <lb/>
     in regard to the speech of an hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man, and the hon. gentleman who is new ad<lb break="no"/>dressing the House is going pretty far in 
     <lb/>
     the use of language which should not be 
     <lb/>
     used by one hon. member to another. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Mr. Speaker. I am very 
     <lb/>
     much obliged to you for calling me to order 
     <lb/>
     at any time that I in any way transgress 
     <lb/>
     the rules of this House. But, Mr. Speak<lb break="no"/>er, with great respect for you— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
     <lb/>
     FISHERIES</persName>. Chair. The hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Davin) must accept the ruling of the 
     <lb/>
     Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Ruling about what ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
                  <lb/>
                  FISHERIES</persName>. That you are out of order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Pray, in what way out of 
     <lb/>
     order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
                  <lb/>
                  FISHERIES</persName>. Mr. Speaker has explained 
     <lb/>
     that to you. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I wish to know from you, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Speaker, how I was out of order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. The hon. gentleman (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Davin) went beyond what I think is parlia<lb break="no"/>mentary decorum. Perhaps I should have 
     <lb/>
     pointed out before that the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Oliver), who spoke before him, trans<lb break="no"/>gressed in the same way. I do not think, 
     <lb/>
     however, that one transgression justifies the 
     <lb/>
     orher. although perhaps one may have 
     <lb/>
     caused the other. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
      Mr. DAVIN. Am I to understand that it 
     <lb/>
     is henceforth the rule in this House of Par<lb break="no"/>liament, that it is a breach of the rules to 
     <lb/>
     say of a member that he shows a miser<lb break="no"/>able insect spirit? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="1045" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01045.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1045</fw> <fw type="dateline">[APRIL 21, 1897]</fw> <fw type="num">1046</fw>
            
            
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. Yes. I wish to say to       
     <lb/>
     the hon. member (Mr. Davin) that such is          
     <lb/>
     my ruling. Language that one gentleman         
     <lb/>
     would not use to another in any other place        
     <lb/>
     without being ofiensive, should not be used         
     <lb/>
     by one hon. member towards another in this          
     <lb/>
    House. That is the simple rule which I 
     <lb/>would like to see followed.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Shades of Disraeli. I wish 
     <lb/>
     we had Mr. Disraeli here ; I wish we had 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Gladstone here as a witness. I am very  
     <lb/>
     glad to know, Sir, that the Parliament of 
     <lb/>
     Canada has risen to such a high dignity 
     <lb/>
     that we have a Speaker who lays down laws  
     <lb/>
    that would condemn Disraeli and Glad<lb break="no"/>stone—— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Order.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. 'When a ruling has been   
     <lb/>
     given by the Speaker, there is only one 
     <lb/>
     course open to any hon. member who ob<lb break="no"/>jects to that ruling, and that is, to appeal 
     <lb/>
     to the House against the decision. I shall 
     <lb/>
     not permit any more discussion upon the 
     <lb/>
     ruling that I have made.  
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Well, Mr. Speaker, I won't 
     <lb/>show an insect spirit and appeal to the 
     <lb/>House. If I were to appeal to the House 
     <lb/>on the subject, 1 think I would show an 
     <lb/>insect spirit, and I suppose I do not break 
     <lb/>the rules of the House if I refer to myself 
     <lb/>as possibly likely to show an insect spirit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASE3">Mr. CASEY</persName>. Not at all. Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Yes, and I can say in re<lb break="no"/>gard to the hon member for Elgin (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Casey) that I have never shown an insect 
     <lb/>
     spirit, nor a worm-like nature, and I have 
     <lb/>
     never growled and grovelled. I can say a 
     <lb/>
     whole lot of things like that, but, Mr. Speak<lb break="no"/>er, I bow entirely to your ruling. What 
     <lb/>
     I hope, then, is that we shall not have apo<lb break="no"/>theosized in this House the demeanour of 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for Alberta (Mr. Oliver). 
     <lb/>
     I hope that when a member comes to this 
     <lb/>
     House and endeavours to do the best he can 
     <lb/>
     for the country, and when he makes a pro<lb break="no"/>position that an hon. gentleman opposite to  
     <lb/>
     him cannot controvert', that that hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman shall not abuse him and get mad. If 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman does so, I will have 
     <lb/>
     henceforth to declare that that hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman shows a god-like temperament. Now  
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman (Mr. Oliver) said that he 
     <lb/>
     hoped that if I should be able to induce 
     <lb/>
     this Government to bring in a Bill giving 
     <lb/>
     the Territories these things asked for in 
     <lb/>
     the memorial, that then hon. gentlemen on 
     <lb/>
     this side of the House would be ready to 
     <lb/>
     support such a measure. There is nothing 
     <lb/>
     whatever in the past history of the Con<lb break="no"/>servative party to indicate that any good 
     <lb/>
     proposals for the North-west Territories 
     <lb/>
     would not meet with as fair consideration 
     <lb/>
     at their hands as it would at the hands of 
     <lb/>
     the Liberal party. The most determined op<lb break="no"/>ponents that we have had in the past, and 
     <lb/>
     the harshest critics in regard to the North-<lb break="yes"/>
         
         
            <cb/>
            
            
            west Territories were gentlemen—not gentle<lb break="no"/>men of an insect spirit ; but gentlemen of<lb/>magnanimous soul like the hon. member for<lb/>North Wellington (Mr. McMullen) and like<lb/>the hon. member for Elgin (Mr. Casey). Sir,<lb/>I have not the least doubt whatever that<lb/>if a good measure is introduced by this 
     <lb/>
     Government it will require no effort on my 
     <lb/>
     part to induce my friends on this side to 
     <lb/>
     support it ; but you may be perfectly cer<lb break="no"/>tain that I will use any influence I may 
     <lb/>
     be supposed to have with them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, with regard to the suggestion that 
     <lb/>
     I have made. I suggested that there should 
     <lb/>
     be an auditor in the North-west Territories, 
     <lb/>
     precisely in the position of the Auditor 
     <lb/>
     General here. Is the existence of an audi<lb break="no"/>tor such as we have here, any reflection 
     <lb/>
     whatever on the present Government ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
                  <lb/>
                  FISHERIES</persName>. Is there not an auditor there 
     <lb/>
     now ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I do not understand that 
     <lb/>
     that there is an auditor in that position. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. All these accounts are 
     <lb/>
     audited by our auditor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. They were audited in that 
     <lb/>
     way when we had the sums voted individu<lb break="no"/>ally, but I am not aware that they are 
     <lb/>audited in that way now. At any rate, we 
     <lb/>should have an auditor in the North-west 
     <lb/>Territories where the audit could be done 
     <lb/>more efficiently than the present auditor 
     <lb/>can do it. What I suggest is an auditor 
     <lb/>there placed in precisely the same position 
     <lb/>as our Auditor General. We have no au<lb break="no"/>thority in Canada that has power to give 
     <lb/>us an auditor here except ourselves, and 
     <lb/>if we have an auditor what matter who 
     <lb/>gave him the independence that he pos<lb break="no"/>sesses. It is an advantage to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to have such an auditor here, and I 
     <lb/>have often heard Sir John Macdonald say 
     <lb/>that it was a great advantage to him to 
     <lb/>have an auditor that was perfectly inde<lb break="no"/>pendent of the Government. And because 
     <lb/>I suggest that we should have in the North<lb break="no"/>west an auditor in precisely the same posi<lb break="no"/>tion as our auditor here, an hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>gets up and says that I made an insinuation 
     <lb/>against these two gentlemen in the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories. Well, Mr. Speaker, these 
     <lb/>two gentlemen are members of that North<lb break="no"/>west Government, and they will compare 
     <lb/>with any two gentlemen in any provincial 
     <lb/>executive. The head of that executive, Mr. 
     <lb/>Haultain, is a personal friend of mine. He 
     <lb/>is a man than whom there is not in any 
     <lb/>Government in Canada, or in any Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in the world, one more honourable. 
     <lb/>When I am advocating giving these gentle<lb break="no"/>men enlarged powers and larger grants of 
     <lb/>money to spend, is it to be supposed for 
     <lb/>one moment that I would make any sugges<lb break="no"/>tion that would be derogatory to them? I 
     <lb/>am under the impression at the present 
     <lb/>time, although I may be wrong, that there 
     <lb/>
       
       
            <pb n="1047" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01047.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1047</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1048</fw>
      
      
     is not the same audit there that there used 
     <lb/>
     to be, and if there is not, then I say there 
     <lb/>
     should be. I may say further, Sir, that in 
     <lb/>
     performing my duty here, I have never been 
     <lb/>
     afraid of what construction any person in<lb break="no"/>side or outside of this House would put 
     <lb/>
     upon my conduct. My record in this House, 
     <lb/>
     battling for the interests of the North-west. 
     <lb/>
     Territories is not the record of a man who 
     <lb/>
     has shown any petty political spirit, be<lb break="no"/>cause when my own friends were in power 
     <lb/>
     I have asserted my opinions against my 
     <lb/>
     party proclivities. I hope that if the pre<lb break="no"/>sent Government does not do justice to the 
     <lb/>
     Territories, the members from the Territo<lb break="no"/>ries supporting that Government shall fol<lb break="no"/>low my example in that. I do not know 
     <lb/>
     that we shall hear any protest from the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Alberta (Mr. Oliver) against 
     <lb/>
     the indifference of the Government he sup<lb break="no"/>ports, to the North-west Territories. The 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman (Mr. Oliver) professes to be 
     <lb/>
     an independent, but as an hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     on his own side of the House told me, he 
     <lb/>
     professes to be an independent, but he is 
     <lb/>
     the worst Grit among them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Name. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. No, I will not give the name. 
     <lb/>
    That name is perfectly sacred with me. 
     <lb/>Now. Mr. Speaker. I am quite surprised 
     <lb/>that my hon. friend the Minister of Marine 
     <lb/>and Fisheries (Mr. Davies), who is the only 
     <lb/>member of the Government present, has not 
     <lb/>said anything in regard to this motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
                  <lb/>
                  FISHERIES</persName>. I had no opportunity. I 
     <lb/>
     intended to have spoken. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. The Speaker rose after the 
     <lb/>
    hon. gentleman sat down. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
                  <lb/>
                  FISHERIES</persName>. My hon. friend was too 
     <lb/>
     quick for me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I beg pardon—I did not see 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend (Mr. Dobell). I apologize to 
     <lb/>
     him. Nobody recognizes more thoroughly 
     <lb/>
     than I do the important part my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     plays as a member of that Government; 
     <lb/>
     and, as he now comes back after doing 
     <lb/>
     great things in London, it would have been 
     <lb/>
     impossible for me to ignore his presence if 
     <lb/>
     I had known it. But I am surprised that 
     <lb/>
     no Minister rises to speak on this motion. 
     <lb/>
     We have to-day what we have lately been 
     <lb/>
     accustomed to have in this House, day 
     <lb/>
     after day—empty Ministerial seats. We 
     <lb/>
     are told that the Ministers are caucusing, 
     <lb/>
     patching up Cabinet differences and Cabinet 
     <lb/>
     squabbles; and while they are doing that 
     <lb/>
     here, the Minister of the Interior (Mr. Sifton) 
     <lb/>
     has gone to patch up Liberal squabbles in 
     <lb/>
     W'innipeg. That is why we have empty 
     <lb/>
     Ministerial seats in this House. We have 
     <lb/>
     only one Minister with a portfolio present, 
     <lb/>
     and he was going to allow the motion to be 
     <lb/>
     put without saying anything upon it. I 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <cb/>
        
        
     shall be very glad to let him say anything 
     <lb/>
     now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
                  <lb/>
                  FISHERIES</persName>. I was not going to let the 
     <lb/>
     motion pass without making a remark or 
     <lb/>
     two; but the hon. gentleman was rather 
     <lb/>
     quick in getting on his feet, and I had not 
     <lb/>
     an opportunity. The hon. gentleman has 
     <lb/>
     asserted his independence in this House. I 
     <lb/>
     recognize his claim to independence, but 
     <lb/>
     there is this peculiarity about it, that while 
     <lb/>
     he asserts his independence, he does not 
     <lb/>
     support his assertion by his vote. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I rise to a point of order. 
     <lb/>
     That is a statement of fact about myself, 
     <lb/>
     and I say it is not true to fact. I say on 
     <lb/>
     the contrary that I have again and again 
     <lb/>
    supported my speech by my vote, and I dare 
     <lb/>the hon. gentleman to prove what he has 
     <lb/>stated. It is not true. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
               <lb/>
               FISHERIES</persName>. I think I have sat in this 
     <lb/>House as long as the hon. gentleman— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. The hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     iWest Assiniboia (Mr Davin) has made a 
     <lb/>
     statement, and unless the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     is prepared to controvert it. he should ac<lb break="no"/>cept it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
                  <lb/>
                  FISHERIES</persName>. I am not prepared to con<lb break="no"/>trovert it if he says that on any occasion 
     <lb/>he voted against the Government of which 
     <lb/>he was a supporter. I shall be particularly 
     <lb/>pleased if he will point out the occasion, and 
     <lb/>show us the " Hausard " in which the vote 
     <lb/>is recorded. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I will satisfy the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND 
                  <lb/>
                  FISHERIES</persName>. Passing, then, from this mat<lb break="no"/>ter, which does not affect the question be<lb break="no"/>fore the House, to the substantive motion 
     <lb/>
     which the hon. gentleman has made, I quite 
     <lb/>
     appreciate the importance of the subject- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     matter of that motion. It is a motion for 
     <lb/>
     papers relative to the claim of the North<lb break="no"/>west Government for increased executive 
     <lb/>
     powers and increased statutory allowances. 
     <lb/>
     The question was brought before this House 
     <lb/>
     at the first short session of this Parliament, 
     <lb/>
     when my hon. friend from Alberta (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Oliver) made a lengthy statement containing 
     <lb/>
     a very large amount of information on the 
     <lb/>
     question, and he was supported by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman who has just taken his seat (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Davin). The Government have not only 
     <lb/>
     had the advantage of these statements, but 
     <lb/>
     they have had the benefit of receiving 
     <lb/>
     from the North-west executive a memo<lb break="no"/>rial setting forth in detail what the claims 
     <lb/>
     of that Government are. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man in his speech followed very closely 
     <lb/>
     the terms of that memorial—in fact. reading 
     <lb/>
     iit to the House. That memorial has been 
     <lb/>
     presented to the Government by Mr. Haul<lb break="no"/>
         
         
            <pb n="1049" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01049.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">1040</fw>              <fw type="dateline">[APRIL 21, 1897]</fw>          <fw type="num">1050</fw>  
  
  
     tain and Mr. Ross, and they have had inter<lb break="no"/>views with the Government, in which they 
     <lb/>
     have pressed very strongly the claims they 
     <lb/>
     have made. But it is obviously impossible 
     <lb/>
     at the present moment to have an intelli<lb break="no"/>gent discussion, much less to form an in<lb break="no"/>telligent conclusion, until the papers are in 
     <lb/>
     the hands of hon. members. There is no 
     <lb/>
     objection to the hon. gentleman's motion 
     <lb/>
     passing, but I will call his attention to the 
     <lb/>
     fact that while he elaborated the importance 
     <lb/>
     of an audit in the Northwest, he has ig<lb break="no"/>nored the fact that there is an exhaustive 
     <lb/>
     audit of the vote of this House for the 
     <lb/>
     North-west, made by the Auditor General 
     <lb/>
     of the Dominion. and contained in his An<lb break="no"/>nual Report. If the hon. gentleman will 
     <lb/>
     turn to that report he will see. from page 
     <lb/>
     H 15 to page H 40, the details of the expen<lb break="no"/>diture which this House voted in a lump 
     <lb/>
     sum. But in addition to that audit by our 
     <lb/>
     auditor. there is the audit of the North-west 
     <lb/>
     legislative assembly on their own behalf; 
     <lb/>
     and if the hon. gentleman examines the ac<lb break="no"/>count for last year. he will find that some<lb break="no"/>thing like $2,200 was expended for their 
     <lb/>
     audit office. So that the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     may rest assured that,, whether the sum 
     <lb/>
     voted is sufficient or insufficient, there is an 
     <lb/>
     ample check by the Dominion audit and 
     <lb/>
     the North-west audit to insure the proper 
     <lb/>
     expenditure of the money. In addition to 
     <lb/>
     the memorial which has been presented to 
     <lb/>
     the Government, and which has been sup<lb break="no"/>ported ably by oral statements and argu<lb break="no"/>ments by Mr. Haultain and Mr. Ross, the 
     <lb/>
     Government have had the advantage of 
     <lb/>
     having the claims of the North-west pre<lb break="no"/>sented to it by the hon. member for Alberta 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Oliver) and other members of this 
     <lb/>
     House who support the Government. There 
     <lb/>
     is no danger, therefore, of these claims 
     <lb/>
     being lost sight of. Whether any legisla<lb break="no"/>tion on the subject can be carried through 
     <lb/>
     this session or not will depend largely, I 
     <lb/>
     suppose, on the length of. the session. We 
     <lb/>
    have to carry our Estimates and our tariff,<lb/>which will occupy a great deal of time:<lb/>and if hon. gentlemen find it desirable to 
     <lb/>shorten the session so as to enable pro<lb break="no"/>minent members on both sides to attend 
     <lb/>the Queen's Jubilee, it may be that we shall 
     <lb/>not be able to carry through many measures 
     <lb/>that we would like to bring down. I am 
     <lb/>not able to give the hon. gentleman any 
     <lb/>definite assurance at the present moment, 
     <lb/>because the matter is being and has for 
     <lb/>some time past been carefully considered 
     <lb/>by a committee of the Government here; 
     <lb/>but the papers he asks for will be brought 
     <lb/>down as early as may be, and I shall be 
     <lb/>glad to have them thoroughly dis<lb break="no"/>cussed in this House, because I 
     <lb/>recognize the importance of the question. 
     <lb/>The hon. gentleman will remember that an 
     <lb/>autonomy almost equal to provincial auto<lb break="no"/>nomy has already been conceded to the 
     <lb/>North-west territories. With the exception,<lb/>  
     <lb/>
    
    
            <cb/>
      
      
     I think, of the power to legislate on rail<lb break="no"/>ways and one other item given to the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces under section 92 of the British North 
     <lb/>
     America Act, we have conceded to them 
     <lb/>
     every power which a province now pos<lb break="no"/>sesses. But they do desire some change with 
     <lb/>
     reference to the executive powers which 
     <lb/>
     have been conferred upon them, and there 
     <lb/>
     is no doubt that the process of legislative 
     <lb/>
     evolution is going on there, a constitutional 
     <lb/>
     evolution which this House will, at the 
     <lb/>
     proper time, I have no doubt, recognize by 
     <lb/>
     granting the fullest statutory powers to en<lb break="no"/>able it to be brought to a successful com<lb break="no"/>pletion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With regard to the matter in point, the 
     <lb/>
     subsidy which was voted by this House to 
     <lb/>
     the Northwest Territories, that is also be<lb break="no"/>ing considered in great detail by the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. The custom heretofore which has 
     <lb/>
     prevailed. and which has been objected to 
     <lb/>
     by gentlemen from the North-west, was this. 
     <lb/>
     The North-west executive presented in de<lb break="no"/>tail their claim for a subsidy. but an arbi<lb break="no"/>trary sum frequently was deducted from 
     <lb/>
     the amount of that claim. and they then 
     <lb/>
     had, out of the smaller sum granted, to re<lb break="no"/>arrange and appropriate amounts for the 
     <lb/>
     specific purposes as they best could. An 
     <lb/>
     improvement, I hope, will be obtained in 
     <lb/>
     this regard. and while we must and will 
     <lb/>
     recognize fully the claims of the North-west 
     <lb/>
     to generous treatment, we must also recog<lb break="no"/>nize that there are limits to which that 
     <lb/>
     treatment can extend. The whole subject is 
     <lb/>
     now, and has been for weeks past, receiv<lb break="no"/>ing consideration at the hands of a com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASE3">Mr. CASEY</persName>. The hon. member for Assini<lb break="no"/>boia (Mr. Davin) has for a long time been 
     <lb/>
    a perennial spring of joy and amusement to 
     <lb/>this House. His humour has always borne 
     <lb/>that peculiar stamp which distinguishes the 
     <lb/>humour of Irishmen from that of even the 
     <lb/>most talented men of all other countries, 
     <lb/>and perhaps the most remarkable instance 
     <lb/>of this is the fact that the hon. gentleman<lb/>poses constantly as the representative of<lb/>the North-west Territories. When we re<lb break="no"/>member that at present his majority, as re<lb break="no"/>presenting one of these great North-west 
     <lb/>Territories constituencies, is a unit, and that 
     <lb/>the unit which returned him to Parliament 
     <lb/>was the vote of a partisan returning officer, 
     <lb/>we must recognize that his claim is a very 
     <lb/>Irish one indeed to represent the North-west 
     <lb/>Territories. Still, we have enjoyed for many 
     <lb/>years his attempt to be a westerner. He 
     <lb/>has been wild enough perhaps. but he can 
     <lb/>hardly be classed as western or as woolly, 
     <lb/>and in attempting to represent the wild and 
     <lb/>woolly west he has only afforded amuse<lb break="no"/>ment to the House. This was all very well 
     <lb/>while his friends were in power. because at 
     <lb/>that time the coruscations of his humour 
     <lb/>  were under some restraint. but now, since, 
     <lb/>unfortunately for him, he is sitting on the 
     <lb/>wrong side of the House, those corusca<lb break="no"/>
       
       
       
            <pb n="1051" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-04-21_Page_01051.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1051</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1052</fw>
   
   
   
     tions are almost too frequent to be either 
     <lb/>
     dazzling or amusing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Or pleasant. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASE3">Mr. CASEY</persName>. They are pleasant in them<lb break="no"/>selves, but like honey or some other things 
     <lb/>
     we could name, too much of them is not as 
     <lb/>
     pleasant as a mere taste once in a while. 
     <lb/>
     He assures the House to-day that he has 
     <lb/>
     never been bitten with a sentiment, to use 
     <lb/>
     his own peculiar Hibernian way of putting 
     <lb/>
     it, of a certain kind. and he has made re<lb break="no"/>ference to insects. New. insects bite some<lb break="no"/>times. as well as sentiments, and I am not 
     <lb/>
     at all sure that my hon. friend has not 
     <lb/>
     been bitten with a certain kind of insect 
     <lb/>
     called the gadfly, which is known to drive 
     <lb/>
     those it bites into great disorder of mind 
     <lb/>
     and conduct. I should certainly judge from 
     <lb/>
     his reply to the hon. member for Alberta 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Oliver) that something must have bit<lb break="no"/>ten him, if not a sentiment, then a gadfly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I rise to a point of order. I 
     <lb/>
     understand your ruling. Mr. Speaker, is that 
     <lb/>
     no hon. gentleman should use insect illus<lb break="no"/>trations. My hon. friend is transgressing 
     <lb/>
     that ruling by implying that the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Alberta (Mr. Oliver) is a gadfly, 
     <lb/>
     and, in the character of a gadfly, hit me. 
     <lb/>
     I do not care a pin about it, Mr. Speaker, 
     <lb/>
     but your ruling must be respected. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. If the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     will say that the statement of the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Elgin (Mr. Casey) is offensive to 
     <lb/>
     him, I shall consider his point. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. It is not in the least offen<lb break="no"/>sive to me. At that distance my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend, or any other insect, would not annoy 
     <lb/>me.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CASE3">Mr. CASEY</persName>. My hon. friend's interrup<lb break="no"/>tion is rather clever. He wanted to draw 
     <lb/>
     in the hon. member for Alberta again, but 
     <lb/>
     I wish to assure him that there are no flies 
     <lb/>
     on the hon. member for Alberta, neither 
     <lb/>
     gadflies nor any other kind, and that the 
     <lb/>
     gadfly which appears to have been biting 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend must have been one of his 
     <lb/>
     own imagination. It must have been an 
     <lb/>
     insect spirit, in other words, which must 
     <lb/>
     have bitten him. I hope the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     will obtain a supply of insect powder and 
     <lb/>
     get done with this gadfly, and the rest of 
     <lb/>
     us will have peace to attend to serious mat<lb break="no"/>ters of discussion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>