<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-02-14" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-02-14">14 February 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          

         
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
                

          <date when="1905"/>.   
          

         <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="991" to="992"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-14_Page_0991.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
         
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-01-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-01-06">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-14_Page_0991">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-14_Page_0991.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="991" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-14_Page_0991.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">991</fw>
            <fw type="running"> COMMONS</fw> 
           
 <p>[...]tics and a supplementary vote of $10,000 for 
     <lb/>
    general statistics. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:TAYL1">Mr. TAYLOR</persName>. If my hon. friend (Mr. <lb/> Fisher) will refer to
               the estimates now be<lb break="no"/>fore us, on page 32 he will find the figures
               <lb/> I refer to. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH2">Mr. FISHER</persName>. Perhaps the second vote <lb/> I referred to may have
               been $15,000 instead <lb/> of $10,000 as I suggested ; that would make <lb/> the
               $18,200. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:TAYL1">Mr. TAYLOR</persName>. And you are asking the <lb/> same amount this year.
               I want to know <lb/> how that money is expended. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH2">Mr. FISHER</persName>. I shall be glad to give the <lb/> information up to
               the present time. That <lb/> vote has been expended on statistical work, <lb/> part
               of it, the usual statistical work always <lb/> carried on in the department every
               year <lb/> and part of it special statistical work, that <lb/> is work drawn from the
               compilation of <lb/> the census, and it has been found that a <lb/> portion of that
               latter work has been of <lb/> sufficient value to be included probably in <lb/> the
               final reports or volumes of the census. <lb/> The consequence is that I might almost
               say <lb/> that a portion of it has been devoted to <lb/> such work as is contemplated
               in this Bill, <lb/> that I have now before the House, between <lb/> the decennial
               census. It is largely the <lb/> kind of work, although not all of the kind <lb/> of
               work that the Bill contemplates and <lb/> which I would like to see taken up and
                  con<lb break="no"/>tinued by the officers of the department be<lb break="no"/>tween the decennial census years and the <lb/> work which was necessary after our
                  decen<lb break="no"/>nial census year on the compilations of the <lb/> census of
               that year. I can give my hon. <lb/> friend (Mr. Taylor) the expenditure which <lb/>
               has been made with regard to the indivi<lb break="no"/>duals employed &amp;c., if he
               desires it. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MONK1">Mr. MONK</persName>. As this is a somewhat im<lb break="no"/>portant
               measure, I would like the minister to <lb/> give us an outline of what the
               expenditure <lb/> contemplates in connection with this new <lb/> office in the
               immediate future and what <lb/> work would be performed by the officers of <lb/> this
               new department for the first few <lb/> years ? <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH2">Mr. FISHER</persName>. I would say to my hon. <lb/> friend when discussing
               this Bill a few <lb/> days ago in committee, before the financial <lb/> resolution
               was before the House, the ques<lb break="no"/>tion was asked of me as to the probable
               <lb/> expenditure involved in the proposed legis<lb break="no"/>lation. I then said
               that I thought it would <lb/> be about $20,000 more per annum. practi<lb break="no"/>cally immediately, than we are now spend<lb break="no"/>ing on statistical work in
               the department. <lb/> I have since been' going carefully over what <lb/> I would like
               to do under this Bill, and I think <lb/> that the amount which I then indicated <lb/>
               is quite sufficient to accomplish all that I <lb/> contemplate or expect to do for
               several <lb/> years to come with the possible exception <lb/> of some expenditure in
               connection with <lb/> printing which I did not take fully into <lb/>
               <cb/>
     <fw type="num">992</fw> account when I made that estimate. I do <lb/> not know yet that the printing
               would re<lb break="no"/>quire more money than the amount I stated, <lb/> but I want
               to be entirely frank with the <lb/> house and do not wish in any way to say <lb/>
               anything which I am not quite sure is with<lb break="no"/>in the mark. I therefore
               thought that I ought <lb/> now to say that if we are to undertake to <lb/> publish
               monthly bulletins or to publish every <lb/> year a very large amount of statistical
                  infor<lb break="no"/>mation that we gather, in extended form, <lb/> it might be
               that the printing bill would be <lb/> larger than I at first thought. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>An extra thousand or two of dollars 
     <lb/>
     might therefore be required from year to 
     <lb/>
     year for printing. I wanted to give this 
     <lb/>
     explanation of the financial side of the case 
     <lb/>
     so that there would not be any suspicion 
     <lb/>
     that I was minimizing or misrepresenting 
     <lb/>
     it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>My hon. friend from Jacques Cartier has 
     <lb/>
     asked me to give an outline of what is 
     <lb/>
     proposed. We have had under the law a 
     <lb/>
     general census every ten years, and a cen<lb break="no"/>sus of Manitoba taken in the mid-year be<lb break="no"/>tween the regular decennial censuses. In 
     <lb/>
     1885 or 1886 we had a census of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories taken on the same bas1s 
     <lb/>
     as the census of Manitoba; but since that 
     <lb/>
     time there has been no special census taken 
     <lb/>
     of the Northwest Territories. Under this 
     <lb/>
     Act I propose to continue to take every 
     <lb/>
     ten years a census of the whole Dominion 
     <lb/>
     of Canada, and to take in the mid-year be<lb break="no"/>tween the regular census years, a census 
     <lb/>
     of Manitoba, and, if this parliament at the 
     <lb/>
     present session should create two new pro<lb break="no"/>vinces in the Northwest Territories, or any 
     <lb/>
     provinces, to take a census of them in the 
     <lb/>
     same way that the census of Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     is taken. The Manitoba census is taken 
     <lb/>
     by virtue of a provision in the Subsidy 
     <lb/>
     Act. Nobody can say to-day what may 
     <lb/>
     be decided in regard to a new province 
     <lb/>
     or new provinces in the Northwest Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. But whatever is decided in regard 
     <lb/>
     to subsidies for those new provinces, I think 
     <lb/>
     it is well that this Act should provide for 
     <lb/>
     the censuses to be taken in the province of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba and iii the new provinces to be 
     <lb/>
     formed in the Territories. The figures 
     <lb/>
     which I have given do not include any ex<lb break="no"/>penditure which may be necessary in con<lb break="no"/>nection with those censuses. Those figures 
     <lb/>
     indicate what I expect the annual expendi<lb break="no"/>ture to be, in addition to which special pro<lb break="no"/>vision will have to be made for the taking 
     <lb/>
     of the decennial census and for the taking 
     <lb/>
     of the census of Manitoba and the other 
     <lb/>
     northwest provinces. As I have said, I be<lb break="no"/>lieve the value of this work will be very 
     <lb/>
     great; and, as the work will grow, it may 
     <lb/>
     be that a few years from now the minister 
     <lb/>
     will have to come down and ask for a lar<lb break="no"/>ger vote on this account; but, so far as our 
     <lb/>
     expectations or intentions go at the pre<lb break="no"/>sent time, the money I have spoken of will. 
     <lb/>
     I think, cover the necessary expenditure for 
     <lb/>
     several years to come. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>