<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-02-06" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-02-06">6 February 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
           

           <date when="1905"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="599" to="600"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-06_Page_0599.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
          
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-01-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-01-06">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-06_Page_0599">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-06_Page_0599.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="599" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-06_Page_0599.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">599</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">600</fw>

            <p>[...] man able to tell us that any petition came 
     <lb/>
     in against this postmaster. There may 
     <lb/>
     have been, but if so, the petitions were 
     <lb/>
     sent in without the knowledge of the free 
     <lb/>
     and independent electors there, and had 
     <lb/>
     they known it a contrary petition would 
     <lb/>
     have been sent in signed by a great many 
     <lb/>
     Reformers as well as Conservatives. I 
     <lb/>
     think I have given the true solution, namely, 
     <lb/>
     that he was engaged in business and had 
     <lb/>
     a partner in the store. Well, Mr. Speaker, 
     <lb/>
     you know that in small places like that 
     <lb/>
     postmasters often have other business, the 
     <lb/>
     post office business is so small that it does 
     <lb/>
     not occupy much of their time, and it fre<lb break="no"/>quently happens that they employ com<lb break="no"/>petent men to assist them. I say again, I 
     <lb/>
     regret that the hon. gentleman, finding him<lb break="no"/>self unable to give the information, did not 
     <lb/>
     allow the motion to stand, because I would 
     <lb/>
     have been able to enlighten him on many 
     <lb/>
     points. His friends probably misled him. 
     <lb/>
     I think possibly he would not have made 
     <lb/>
     the change had he been cognizant of all 
     <lb/>
     the facts. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Sir WILLIAM MULOCK</persName>. I think my hon. <lb/> friend would have done
               well to reserve <lb/> his judgment. When he receives the papers <lb/> I think he will
               have occasion to change his <lb/> views. A large number of his own friends <lb/>
               asked for it. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     NORTHWEST TERRITORIES PROVIN<lb break="no"/>CIAL AUTONOMY. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MONK1">Mr. F. D. MONK</persName> (Jaques Cartier) moved <lb/> for : <lb/>
               </p>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     Copies of all correspondence between the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of Canada, or any member thereof, and 
     <lb/>
     the government of the Northwest Territories, 
     <lb/>
     or any of its members, in reference to the 
     <lb/>
     granting of provincial autonomy to the said 
     <lb/>
     Territories, since the date of the last proroga<lb break="no"/>tion of parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>

            <p>He said: The object of this motion is to 
     <lb/>
     obtain the correspondence in regard to the 
     <lb/>
     autonomy of the Northwest Territories that 
     <lb/>
     took place since the last prorogation of par<lb break="no"/>liament. We had two returns during the 
     <lb/>
     last parliament, bringing down only a part 
     <lb/>
     of the correspondence. The object of the 
     <lb/>
     motion is to complete it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     POSTAL BUSINESS IN THE DISTRICT 
     <lb/>
     OF ALBERTA. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:ROCH1">Mr. WM. J. ROCHE</persName> (Marquette) moved <lb/> for : <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     A return showing in detail the business done 
     <lb/>
     during each of the past ten years, and also in 
     <lb/>
     the aggregate during the same period, in con<lb break="no"/>nection with the transmission of mail matter; 
     <lb/>
     and with the issue and payment of money orders 
     <lb/>
     and postal notes at each post office in the pro<lb break="no"/>visional district of Alberta. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Hon. Sir WILLIAM MULOCK</persName> (Postmaster <lb/> General). Perhaps
                  my hon. friend would <lb/>
                  <!--</p>
            <p>MR. BARR. 
     <lb/>-->
                  <cb/> explain what he means by the statement <lb/> ' Showing in detail the
                  businesg done dur<lb break="no"/>ing each of the past ten years, and also <lb/> in
                  the aggregate during the same period, in <lb/> connection with the transmission of
                  mail <lb/> matter.' <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:ROCH1">Mr. W. J. ROCHE</persName>. I want to get at the <lb/> amount of
                  business done in that provincial <lb/> district in each post office for each year.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Sir WILLIAM MULOCK</persName>. Does the hon. <lb/> gentleman mean the
                  number of letters and <lb/> the number of the various kinds of mail <lb/> matter ?
                  <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:ROCH1">Mr. W. J. ROCHE</persName>. Yes. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Sir WILLIAM MULOCK</persName>. I would point <lb/> out to him that to
                  give in detail what he asks <lb/> for would be impossible, because there is <lb/>
                  no account kept of each piece of mail mat<lb break="no"/>ter that passes through
                  the post office. <lb/> Every six months an enumeration is made <lb/> of the
                  business of an office for a period of <lb/> about two weeks, and from these
                     enumer<lb break="no"/>ations an estimate is formed of the amount <lb/> of the
                  mail matter of different kinds mailed <lb/> at a particular office. Therefore this
                  could <lb/> only be an estimate. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:ROCH1">Mr. W. J. ROCHE</persName>. It is the general bu<lb break="no"/>siness
                  done that I desire to get at. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Sir WIILLIAM MULOCK</persName>. The secretary of <lb/> the department
                  tells me that they would have <lb/> to correspond with every postmaster in Al<lb break="no"/>berta to get this information, and to get it as <lb/> fast as the
                  hon. gentleman wants it. There<lb break="no"/>fore there would be considerable
                  delay in<lb break="no"/>volved in gathering the information. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:ROCH1">Mr. W. J. ROCHE</persName>. I am anxious to get <lb/> an idea of the
                  business done so that it may <lb/> be discussed when the question of autonomy
                  <lb/> comes up. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Sir WILLIAM MULOCK</persName>. Very well, I will <lb/> give all
                  information we can now. But if <lb/> we have to correspond to get anything, it
                  <lb/> might be better to have a partial return <lb/> made now, and give the rest
                  later. I <lb/> would suggest that we strike out the words <lb/> 'in detail' and
                  substitute the words 'an <lb/> estimate of.' <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p>Motion, as amended, agreed to. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">INLAND AND CUSTOMS REVENUES, 
     <lb/>N.W.T. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:ROCH1">Mr. W J. ROCHE</persName> moved: <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     For a return showing the amount of revenue 
     <lb/>
     collected, (1) by the Department of Inland 
     <lb/>
     Revenue; (2) by the Department of Customs, 
     <lb/>
     during each of the past ten years : and also in 
     <lb/>
     the aggregate during the same period, at the 
     <lb/>
     following points in the Northwest Territories, 
     <lb/>
     viz.: Edmonton, Strathcona, Red Deer, Calgary, 
     <lb/>
     Medicine Hat, Maple Creek, Lethbridge, Coutts, 
     <lb/>
     Cardston and Macleod. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:PATE1">HON. WILLIAM PATERSON</persName> (Minister of <lb/> Customs). When the
                  hon. gentleman says ' in <lb/>the aggrogate' does he mean to have the [...]<lb/>
               </p>
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>