<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-07-14"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-07-14">14 July 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
   
                    

          <date when="1905"/>.
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="9525" to="9530"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-14_Page_9525.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-14_Page_9527.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-14_Page_9529.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-02-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-02-07">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-14_Page_9525">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-14_Page_9525.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-14_Page_9527">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-14_Page_9527.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-14_Page_9529">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-14_Page_9529.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="9525" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-14_Page_9525.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">9525</fw> <fw type="dateline">JULY 14, 1905</fw> <fw type="num">9526</fw>
            

<!-- GL, 2018-02-07, Commented out below, as  it precedes Debate Day  --> 

<!--<p>
     lottery. That is the element that affects 
     <lb/>
     the consumer. And that is the element that 
     <lb/>
     is not touched, as I understand, by the leg<lb break="no"/>islation proposed. Of course, the legisla<lb break="no"/>tion has been rather hastily introduced; and 
     <lb/>
     perhaps it may require amendment at a 
     <lb/>
     future date. But I think it only right on 
     <lb/>
     the occasion of the third reading to give my 
     <lb/>
     view as to the principle which should be 
     <lb/>
     adopted and the legislation which will even<lb break="no"/>tually have to be enacted, if we are to deal 
     <lb/>
     with the real danger which is supposed to 
     <lb/>
     be met by the present Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Rt. Hon. Sir WILFRID LAURIER (Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister). The object of this legislation is 
     <lb/>
     to reach what is known as the trading stamp 
     <lb/>
     —that is, that a certain green stamp which 
     <lb/>
     has attained a rather unenviable notoriety 
     <lb/>
     in every city, town and village of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. I think this legislation will 
     <lb/>
     reach that stamp, and if it does it will fulfil 
     <lb/>
     that object which it is intended to fulfil. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. That particular 
     <lb/>
     stamp ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Sir WILFRID LAURIER. That particu<lb break="no"/>lar stamp. That is the object, and I think 
     <lb/>
     it will attain that object. It may be that 
     <lb/>
     there will develop other forms of duping 
     <lb/>
     the public. If so, other legislation may be 
     <lb/>
     needed at some future time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the third 
     <lb/>
     time, and passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SASKATCHEWAN AND ALBERTA— 
     <lb/>
     ROADS AND ROAD ALLOWANGES. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Hon. FRANK OLIVER</persName> (Minister of the 
     <lb/>
     Interior) moved the second reading of Bill 
     <lb/>
     (No. 195) respecting roads and road allow<lb break="no"/>ances in the provinces of Saskatchewan and 
     <lb/>
     Alberta. He said: This Bill is needed to 
     <lb/>
     carry forward in the new provinces the con<lb break="no"/>ditions that exist in the Territories at the 
     <lb/>
     present time in regard to the setting apart 
     <lb/>
     and control of roads and road allowances. 
     <lb/>
     The object is to place under control of the 
     <lb/>
     provincial government the roads now exist<lb break="no"/>ing and the roads in use, not now legalized 
     <lb/>
     which may hereafter be legalized. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. If the minister will 
     <lb/>
     permit me, I would ask him to explain the 
     <lb/>
     law as it stands at present. Are these roads 
     <lb/>
     and road allowances still vested in the 
     <lb/>
     Crown, or is the title to them vested in 
     <lb/>
     some corporation? In other words, what is 
     <lb/>
     the condition of the title to the roads and 
     <lb/>
     road allowance and under whose supervi<lb break="no"/>sion are they now? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. As I understand it, by 
     <lb/>
     similar provisions to those contained in this 
     <lb/>
     Act, the Dominion government a number of 
     <lb/>
     years ago divested itself of the control of 
     <lb/>
     the roads, and placed that control in the 
     <lb/>
     hands of the Territorial government. The 
     <lb/>
     Territorial government exercises all jurisdic<lb break="no"/>tion over the roads and road allowances of 
     <lb/>
          

            <cb/>
     

     the provinces, that authority having been 
     <lb/>
     delegated by the Dominion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. Is that statute re<lb break="no"/>pealed by this enactment ? Is this enact<lb break="no"/>ment in substitution, so far as the new 
     <lb/>
     provinces are concerned, of the statute to 
     <lb/>
     which the hon. gentleman (Mr. Oliver) has 
     <lb/>
     just referred ? Does it follow the provis<lb break="no"/>ions of that enactment, substantially or 
     <lb/>
     literally ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. Substantially it does. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. Bill read the second 
     <lb/>
     time and House went into Committee there<lb break="no"/>on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On section 2, 
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>
    All road allowances in townships now or 
     <lb/>hereafter surveyed and subdivided, and all road 
     <lb/>allowances set out on block lines now or here<lb break="no"/>after surveyed, in the Northwest Territories 
     <lb/>within the limits of the province of Saskatche<lb break="no"/>wan or the province of Alberta, as those pro<lb break="no"/>vinces are defined in the Saskatchewan Act and 
     <lb/>the Alberta Act respectively, the plans of sur<lb break="no"/>vey of which have been duly approved, and the 
     <lb/>Dominion lands comprised in such road allow<lb break="no"/>ances, shall be vested in the Crown in the right 
     <lb/>of the province within which such road allow<lb break="no"/>ances are situate. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. According to the principle 
     <lb/>
     of provincial rights, do not the municipal 
     <lb/>
     authorities control these roads in any event? 
     <lb/>
     Property and civil rights are given to the 
     <lb/>
     provinces, and they control all the highways 
     <lb/>
     under municipal laws. In our province, all 
     <lb/>
     roads are under the control of the provincial 
     <lb/>
     authorities, and under control of the muni<lb break="no"/>cipal authorities through the power given 
     <lb/>
     to municipal corporations. Now would it 
     <lb/>
     not be the same in the Northwest as in 
     <lb/>
     Ontario ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. I am not versed in the 
     <lb/>
     strictly legal aspect of the question, and I 
     <lb/>
     am not familiar with the conditions in 
     <lb/>
     Ontario ; but I presume this legislation is 
     <lb/>
     based on the fact that the title to the land is 
     <lb/>
     in the Dominion, unless there was some 
     <lb/>
     specific transfer of that right, or title, or 
     <lb/>
     interest, or control. This is a matter of 
     <lb/>
     transfer of control rather than of title. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. What would be the situ<lb break="no"/>ation providing you were pushing a muni<lb break="no"/>cipal road through belonging to the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion, what power would you have to tax 
     <lb/>
     those lands for the upkeep of that road ? 
     <lb/>
     You vest all public highways in the pro<lb break="no"/>vince, but you do not vest lands in the pro<lb break="no"/>vince. Would the province absolutely con<lb break="no"/>trol highways going through Dominion lands 
     <lb/>
     which were still vested in the federal parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, and what power would the munici<lb break="no"/>palities have to tax those lands for keep<lb break="no"/>ing up the roads ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. There is a further provis<lb break="no"/>ion in this Bill for the purpose of doing 
     <lb/>
       

            <pb n="9527" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-14_Page_9527.jpg"/>
         
<fw type="num">9527</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">9528</fw>
        

     what the hon. gentleman has suggested, that 
     <lb/>
     is, placing the control of a road which has 
     <lb/>
     bene forced through the Dominion lands 
     <lb/>
     in the hands of the province. But of course 
     <lb/>
     there is no power given here, nor does any 
     <lb/>
     exist elsewhere, for the taxation of lands 
     <lb/>
     still remaining in the hands of the Dom<lb break="no"/>inion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. What authority will the 
     <lb/>
     province have now to lay out new highways? 
     <lb/>
     If the municipal corporations wish to lay 
     <lb/>
     out highways through Dominion lands, what 
     <lb/>
     power of expropriation would they have ? 
     <lb/>
     Because it is constantly occurring in our 
     <lb/>
     province that municipalities have to make 
     <lb/>
     the road deviate, it cannot follow a straight 
     <lb/>
     line. What would happen in case the muni<lb break="no"/>cipality was obliged to encroach upon land 
     <lb/>
     that did not belong to the province? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. I understand there is a 
     <lb/>
     provision in section 5 of the Bill to cover 
     <lb/>
     that point. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On section 3, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. What right will you 
     <lb/>
     have with regard to the width of the road ? 
     <lb/>
     Some require to be wider than others. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. I think there is a gener<lb break="no"/>ally recognized width of one chain. Many 
     <lb/>
     years ago the old trails were surveyed two 
     <lb/>
     chains in width, but I think that wide 
     <lb/>
     survey has been dropped, and the trails 
     <lb/>
     are now surveyed of the same width as the 
     <lb/>
     ordinary road allowance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. Could they not go over 
     <lb/>
     that width in case of additions or uneven<lb break="no"/>ness of the trail, or where snow blockades 
     <lb/>
     might be heavy ? Otherwise they would be 
     <lb/>
     hampered. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. I think that section 5 cov<lb break="no"/>ers that point while a special survey is re<lb break="no"/>quired in the development of the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On section 5, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. It seems to me there 
     <lb/>
     ought to be some provision recognizing the 
     <lb/>
     necessity for a deviation of the line of roads, 
     <lb/>
     in case for instance, where they have to 
     <lb/>
     cross streams. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. This section is to provide 
     <lb/>
     for deviations of roads. The lieutenant gov<lb break="no"/>ernor shall say where a new road requires 
     <lb/>
     to deviate, and in that case a road shall 
     <lb/>
     be so surveyed, and the road thereby be<lb break="no"/>comes vested in the provincial government. 
     <lb/>
     I would like to draw the attention of the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Justice to these words : ' In 
     <lb/>
     accordance with the system of Dominion 
     <lb/>
     lands survey obtaining in the locality.' It 
     <lb/>
     seems to me those words might conflict with 
     <lb/>
     the idea of a special survey in any direc<lb break="no"/>tion or in any place which the nature of the 
     <lb/>
     country would make necessary to secure a 
     <lb/>
     passage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

  

            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FITZ1">Mr. FITZPATRICK</persName>. I would not like to 
     <lb/>
     say anything about a clause of this sort, 
     <lb/>
     which must have been carefully drafted. 
     <lb/>
     Every word is supposed to have an effect, 
     <lb/>
     and I would not like to suggest any change 
     <lb/>
     in it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On section 6,—filing of returns of survey 
     <lb/>
     to vest lands in the province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. Will you always have 
     <lb/>
     to wait until you get the survey approved 
     <lb/>
     by the surveyor general before you can 
     <lb/>
     act ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. Yes, before the control 
     <lb/>
     finally passes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. Could you take posses<lb break="no"/>sion of the land before the consent is given ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. I think that it is a matter 
     <lb/>
     of adjustment as to how soon possession 
     <lb/>
     can be taken. This provides for the absolute 
     <lb/>
     transfer of control, which cannot be done 
     <lb/>
     satisfactorily until the approval of the plans 
     <lb/>
     and survey by the Surveyor General has 
     <lb/>
     been obtained. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. It would be a very in<lb break="no"/>convenient thing if you had to wait until 
     <lb/>
     you applied to Ottawa, with all the delays 
     <lb/>
     which usually result, before you can take 
     <lb/>
     possession of a piece of land to make or to 
     <lb/>
     deviate a road. If you had power to take 
     <lb/>
     the land and make the road it would not be 
     <lb/>
     so bad, but if you had to wait until you get 
     <lb/>
     the consent of the government here it would 
     <lb/>
     be very inconvenient. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OLIV1">Mr. OLIVER</persName>. I think that it could be 
     <lb/>
     overcome by arrangement between the local 
     <lb/>
     government and the department. That, I 
     <lb/>
     do not think, comes in necessarily in the 
     <lb/>
     consideration of this section. We cannot 
     <lb/>
     positively, finally and actually transfer the 
     <lb/>control until we are satisfied what the limits 
     <lb/>of the land that we transfer are so that we 
     <lb/>would have to have the approval of the Sur<lb break="no"/>veyor General of the territory. I think the 
     <lb/>difficulty which the hon. gentleman suggests 
     <lb/>will not arise, because that will be a matter 
     <lb/>of amicable arrangement between the Do<lb break="no"/>minion government owning the land and the 
     <lb/>provincial government which wants to use 
     <lb/>it for a road. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. I would think that would 
     <lb/>
     be a difficulty for this reason : Suppose you 
     <lb/>
     want to take a piece of land and suppose 
     <lb/>
     this government has some other object in 
     <lb/>
     view with reference to that land, then, sup<lb break="no"/>pose you got the Dominion Land Surveyor 
     <lb/>
     to survey the road, that you took possession 
     <lb/>
     of it, you are afraid to spend money be<lb break="no"/>cause you do not know whether you are 
     <lb/>
     going to get it or not. There should be 
     <lb/>
     some provision in the Act, whereby under 
     <lb/>
     the control of the Lieutenant Governor in 
     <lb/>
     Council a surveyor could be sent out and 
     <lb/>
     survey what is needed, because the local 
     <lb/>
     conditions would be better known there 
     <lb/>
     than elsewhere, and whereby they could 
     <lb/>
        

            <pb n="9529" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-14_Page_9529.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="num">9529</fw>         <fw type="dateline">JULY 14, 1905</fw>                  <fw type="num">9530</fw> 
 

     take what is needed for the road and then 
     <lb/>
     get the consent from the federal government 
     <lb/>
     down here.  If they must always wait be<lb break="no"/>fore doing any work until consent is ob<lb break="no"/>tained I am inclined to think there would be 
     <lb/>
     some difficulty at times.  I do not think you 
     <lb/>
     could do anything unless it were put in the 
     <lb/>
     law.  You cannot leave anything to  be 
     <lb/>
     adjusted between two governments outside 
     <lb/>
     of law.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Bill reported, read the third time and 
     <lb/>
     passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     ARBITRATION WITH THE GRAND 
     <lb/>
     TRUNK RAILWAY. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     House in committee on Bill (No. 199) to 
     <lb/>
     amend an Act respecting an arbitration be<lb break="no"/>tween His Majesty and the Grand Trunk 
     <lb/>
     Railway Company of Canada—Mr. Fitz<lb break="no"/>patrick. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>.  Would the hon. Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Justice be good enough to tell us 
     <lb/>
     what this Bill accomplishes ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FITZ1">Mr. FITZPATRICK</persName>.  I think I cannot do 
     <lb/>
     better than read the memorandum which has 
     <lb/>
     been handed to me by the third arbitrator. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>.  Who are the arbi<lb break="no"/>trators ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FITZ1">Mr. FITZPATRICK</persName>.   Mr. Shepley is the 
     <lb/>
     arbitrator for the government; Mr. Ladeur 
     <lb/>
     of Montreal is the arbitrator for the Grand 
     <lb/>
     Trunk Railway Company and Mr. Justice 
     <lb/>
     Killam is the third arbitrator. The memor<lb break="no"/>andum is as follows :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The Bill now proposes to amend the Act of 
     <lb/>
     1904 by giving the arbitrators power to make 
     <lb/>
     several awards on the different points and dis<lb break="no"/>putes that have arisen. In this way much ex<lb break="no"/>pense will probably be avoided, for if an ad<lb break="no"/>verse award is given upon any particular dis<lb break="no"/>pute it will not be necessary to go into the 
     <lb/>
     amount that may be claimed under it, so that 
     <lb/>
     the expense upon the inquiry into the amount 
     <lb/>
     of damages would be avoided. It also provides 
     <lb/>
     that disputes arising since the beginning of 
     <lb/>
     the proceedings up to 1st January, 1905, may 
     <lb/>
     be referred for adjudication. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     After the reference was made certain 
     <lb/>
     claims were discovered on both sides which 
     <lb/>
     had been put forward in addition to those 
     <lb/>
     which had been put forward at the time the 
     <lb/>
     arbitration was initiated. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     It also provides that clause 13 of the Railway 
     <lb/>
     Act, which enacts that the railway commission<lb break="no"/>ers shall devote the whole of their time to the 
     <lb/>
     Railway Commission, shall not apply to any of 
     <lb/>
     the arbitrators. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     This provision is inserted to avoid dis<lb break="no"/>qualifying Mr. Justice Killam, who has al<lb break="no"/>ready heard a very considerable portion of 
     <lb/>
     the case. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. Is this the board of 
     <lb/>
     arbitrators to whom was referred disputes 
     <lb/>
     in reference to the  traffic  agremeent between 
     <lb/>
     the government and the Grand Trunk Rail<lb break="no"/>way in 1899 or 1898 ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FITZ1">Mr. FITZPATRICK</persName>.  These are the arbi<lb break="no"/>trators who have been appointed to decide 
     <lb/>
     on the claims that have arisen under two 
     <lb/>
     agreements; first the agreement of 1879 which 
     <lb/>
     provided for the acquisition by the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of that portion of the Grand Trunk 
     <lb/>
     Railway from Riviere Du Loup to Levis, 
     <lb/>
     and second under the agreement of 1899 
     <lb/>
     which provides for the acquisition by Can<lb break="no"/>ada of what is called the Drummond County 
     <lb/>
     Railway. In both of these agreements pro<lb break="no"/>vision is made for the submission to arbi<lb break="no"/>tration of difficulties which may arise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Bill reported, read a  third  time  and 
     <lb/>
     passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     SUPPLY—RIGHTS OF CANADIANS IN 
     <lb/>
     SOUTH AFRICA. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Hon. W. S. FIELDING</persName>  (Minister of Fin<lb break="no"/>ance) moved that the House go into Com<lb break="no"/>mittee of Supply. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD7">Mr. A. C. MACDONELL</persName> (South Toronto). 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Speaker, before the House goes into 
     <lb/>
     Committee of Supply, I desire very briefly 
     <lb/>
     at this late stage of the session, to call 
     <lb/>
     the attention of' the government to a matter 
     <lb/>
     of considerable importance to certain Can<lb break="no"/>adian citizens who have been deprived of 
     <lb/>
     their rights in connection with large mining 
     <lb/>
     interests in South Africa. The facts as re<lb break="no"/>presented to me are shortly these: prior to 
     <lb/>
     the year 1897, a gentleman named R. E. 
     <lb/>
     Brown. an American citizen, secured for 
     <lb/>
     himself and certain other persons associated 
     <lb/>
     with him (some of them being Canadians) 
     <lb/>
     about 1,200 valuable mining claims on what 
     <lb/>
     is known as the farm Witfontein in the 
     <lb/>
     district of Potchefstroom in the South 
     <lb/>
     African Republic. These claims were pegged 
     <lb/>
     out and rightfully owned by Mr. Brown, 
     <lb/>
     but the president of' that republic, Mr. Kru<lb break="no"/>ger, denied the right of Mr. Brown and his 
     <lb/>
     associates to these claims and refused to 
     <lb/>
     issue licenses or leases. Mr. Brown, repre<lb break="no"/>senting himself and his associates, applied to 
     <lb/>
     the courts of the South African Republic 
     <lb/>
     and on their behalf brought an action 
     <lb/>
     against Dr. Leyds, the secretary of the exe<lb break="no"/>cutive of Mr. Kruger; and also against the 
     <lb/>
     clerk of the district in which these mining 
     <lb/>
     lands were situated—asking that licenses 
     <lb/>
     should issue to him in accordance with the 
     <lb/>
     law. In that action Mr. Brown recovered a 
     <lb/>
     judgment as prayed for by him. The full 
     <lb/>
     court determined that he was entitled to 
     <lb/>
     have issued to him licenses for these lands, 
     <lb/>
     and in default he was awarded damages 
     <lb/>
     commensurate with the estimated value of 
     <lb/>
     the claims. These damages were assessed at 
     <lb/>
     £720,400, so that it will be seen that the 
     <lb/>
     amount involved is very large. That judg<lb break="no"/>ment was rendered by the High Court of 
     <lb/>
     the Reipublic of South Africa on the 22nd 
     <lb/>
     of January. 1897. Immediately after this 
     <lb/>
     judgment. Mr. Kruger sought to thwart its 
     <lb/>
     execution in order to deprive Mr. Brown 
     <lb/>
     and his associates (some of whom were 
     <lb/>
     Canadians) of the benefits thereof. Mr. [...]
     <lb/>
            </p>
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>