<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-07-07"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-07-07">7 July 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
   
                    

          <date when="1905"/>.
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="9033" to="9034"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-07_Page_9033.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
        
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-02-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-02-07">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-07_Page_9033">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-07_Page_9033.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="9033" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-07-07_Page_9033.jpg"/>
         
     <fw type="num">9033</fw> <fw type="dateline">JULY 7, 1905</fw> <fw type="num">9034</fw> 
     <lb/>
            
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     LIEUTENANT GOVERNORS OF SASKAT<lb break="no"/>CHEWAN AND ALBERTA. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
       House went into committee to consider 
     <lb/>
     the following proposed resolution: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Resolved, That section 2 of chapter 4 of the 
     <lb/>
     Revised Statutes, intitled : An Act respecting 
     <lb/>
     the salaries of certain public functionaries, and 
     <lb/>
     other annual charges on the Consolidated 
     <lb/>
     Revenue, be amended by adding at the end 
     <lb/>
     thereof the following words and figures : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
       The Lieutenant Governor of Saskatchewan, 
     <lb/>
     $9,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
       The Lieutenant Governor of Alberta, $9,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Mr. FIELDING</persName>. This resolution is to 
     <lb/>
     make provision for the payment of the 
     <lb/>
     salaries of the Lieutenant Governors of the 
     <lb/>
     two new provinces. It is proposed to fix 
     <lb/>
     their salaries at $9,000, the same as is paid 
     <lb/>
     to the Lieutenant Governor of Manitoba. 
     <lb/>
     and other provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Resolution reported. read a first and second 
     <lb/>
     time and agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Mr. FIELDING</persName> moved for leave to in<lb break="no"/>troduce Bill (No. 193) to amend the Re<lb break="no"/>vised Statute respecting the salaries of cer<lb break="no"/>tain public functionaries and other annual 
     <lb/>
     charges on the consolidated revenue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. and Bill read the first 
     <lb/>
     and second times and House went into com<lb break="no"/>mittee thereon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HEND1">Mr. HENDERSON</persName>. Does the minister 
     <lb/>
     know who is to receive this $9,000? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Mr. FIELDING</persName>. No, we thought it would 
     <lb/>
     be wise first to get the consent of parliament 
     <lb/>
     to pay the money before we committed our<lb break="no"/>selves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. Is that the same as the 
     <lb/>
     Lieutenant Governor of Manitoba gets ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Mr. FIELDING</persName>. Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Bill reported, read the third time and 
     <lb/>
     passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         
<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SUPPLY—COMPLAINT OF D. G. SEY<lb break="no"/>MOUR, OXBOW, ASSA. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Mr. FIELDING</persName> moved that the House 
     <lb/>
     go into Committee of Supply. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. Before you leave 
     <lb/>
     the chair, Mr. Speaker, may I bring to the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the hon. Minister of the Inte<lb break="no"/>rior (Mr. Oliver) a complaint I have received 
     <lb/>
     from a settler in the west who says that 
     <lb/>
     he cannot find out the reason why he is not 
     <lb/>
     able to procure a homestead, Northwest 
     <lb/>
     sections 22 to 25, 1 west 2nd meridian? He 
     <lb/>
     seems to have complied, according to this 
     <lb/>
     statement, with all the requirements of the 
     <lb/>
     law and he attributes his non-success to the 
     <lb/>
     political partisanship of some person or per<lb break="no"/>sons unnamed. He is very earnest about it 
     <lb/>
     and I thought I would like to bring the mat<lb break="no"/>ter to the attention of the Minister of the 
     <lb/>
     Interior, because it is not desirable that 
     <lb/>
     these settlers should have any ground for 
     <lb/>
     complaint of this character. This one may 
     <lb/>
          

            <cb/>
          

     seem trifling at first blush to bring to the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the House, but I do not regard 
     <lb/>
     it as too trifling to bring to the attention 
     <lb/>
     of the hon. Minister of the Interior and to 
     <lb/>
     ask him for some explanation later on after 
     <lb/>
     he has had an opportunity of looking into 
     <lb/>
     the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Sir WILFRID LAURIER. Might I ask 
     <lb/>
     the name? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. The name of the 
     <lb/>
     man is D. G. Seymour, Oxbow, Assa. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and House went into 
     <lb/>
     Committee of Supply. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Civil government—Department of Trade and 
     <lb/>
     Commerce—contingencies—additional amount 
     <lb/>
     required, $1,200. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. Would the hon. 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Finance state why this addition<lb break="no"/>al amount is required? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Mr. FIELDING</persName>. I cannot speak as to 
     <lb/>
     the details, but I may say that I have been 
     <lb/>
     urging my colleagues to have the supple<lb break="no"/>mentary estimates contain a sufficient sum 
     <lb/>
     of money to close up the accounts for the 
     <lb/>
     year rather than to carry balances forward  
     <lb/>
     into the next year. In conformity with my 
     <lb/>
     request several have sent in additional ap<lb break="no"/>propriations. In this case it happens to be 
     <lb/>
     a small amount of contingencies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Ocean and river service—maintenance and re<lb break="no"/>pairs to government steamers and ice-breakers. 
     <lb/>
     $60,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILS2">Mr. URIAH WILSON</persName> We want some 
     <lb/>
     explanation about that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PREF1">Mr. PREFONTAINE</persName>. This item is to 
     <lb/>
     cover the repairs to two steam ice breakers 
     <lb/>
     under the control of the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Marine and Fisheries. The 'Champlain ' 
     <lb/>
     was one of the ice-breakers secured by the 
     <lb/>
     department last fall and put in commission 
     <lb/>
     in the month of November. She maintained 
     <lb/>
    the ferry service between Murray Bay and 
     <lb/>River Ouelle. Two accidents happened to 
     <lb/>her. She first collided with another steamer, 
     <lb/>but fortunately was not wrecked and she 
     <lb/>continued the service during the winter. 
     <lb/>Then she was damaged in reaching the 
     <lb/>wharf at Riviere Ouelle due to the misman<lb break="no"/>agement of the mate, who has since been 
     <lb/>dismissed. In May or June this steamer 
     <lb/>was put in the dry-dock and thoroughly 
     <lb/>overhauled. The damages were ascertained 
     <lb/>and the repairs which are now finished cost 
     <lb/>$30,000. The other ice-breaker the 'Mont<lb break="no"/>calm' was severely injured in the bow 
     <lb/>while breaking the ice at Cap Rouge, she is 
     <lb/>now being repaired and made stronger than 
     <lb/>when she came off the ways after being 
     <lb/>built. She will be in good condition to 
     <lb/>cope with the ice next winter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAI1">Mr. BLAIN</persName>. Where was she repaired ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PREF1">Mr. PREFONTAINE</persName>. In the dry dock 
     <lb/>
     at Quebec. but the work was done by 
     <lb/>
     Messrs. Davis &amp; Son, under the supervision [...]
     <lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>