<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1896-01-23"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1896-01-23">23 January 1896</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, Sixth Session</title>.
          <date when="1896"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="524" to="560"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00523.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00525.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00527.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00529.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00531.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00533.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00535.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00537.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00539.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00541.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00543.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00545.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00547.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00549.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00551.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00553.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00555.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00557.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00559.html"/>
               </item>
         
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-09">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00523">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00523.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00525">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00525.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00527">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00527.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00529">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00529.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00531">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00531.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00533">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00533.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00535">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00535.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00537">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00537.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00539">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00539.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00541">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00541.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00543">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00543.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00545">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00545.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00547">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00547.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00549">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00549.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00551">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00551.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00553">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00553.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00555">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00555.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00557">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00557.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00559">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00559.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="523" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00523.jpg"/>
          
          
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">524</fw>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     HOUSE OF COMMONS. 
     <lb/>
     
            </head>
            <head rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, 23rd January, 1896. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The SPEAKER took the Chair at Three 
     <lb/>
     o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
         <div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES REPRE<lb break="no"/>SENTATION. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName> moved for leave to introduce 
     <lb/>
     Bill (No. 22) further to amend chapter seven 
     <lb/>
     of the Revised Statutes of Canada, being 
     <lb/>
     the " North-west Territories Representation 
     <lb/>
     Act." He said: In introducing this Bill I 
     <lb/>
     desire to make a few remarks, as the sub<lb break="no"/>ject is one of very great importance indeed 
     <lb/>
     to the Liberals of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. The Bill proposes to undo the legis<lb break="no"/>lation enacted by the House in 1894, which 
     <lb/>
     altered the North-west Territories Repre<lb break="no"/>sentation Act—that is, to undo it so far as it 
     <lb/>
     elects a change in regard to the voters' 
     <lb/>
     lists. It will be remembered that in 1894 
     <lb/>
     the hon. Minister of the Interior introduced 
     <lb/>
     a Bill for the purpose of establishing vote 
     <lb/>
     by ballot in the North-west Territories in 
     <lb/>
     the coming general election. These pro<lb break="no"/>visions were, of course, supported on this 
     <lb/>
     side of the House. There had been a good 
     <lb/>
     deal of agitation in the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories in favour of the ballot, and, of 
     <lb/>
     course, the Liberals were very strongly in 
     <lb/>
    favour of extending to the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>
     
     
     
            <pb n="525" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00525.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">525</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 23,1896]</fw> <fw type="num">526</fw>
          
          
     ritories the law that was in force in other 
     <lb/>
     parts of Canada. During the discussion of 
     <lb/>
     that Bill the question of the voters' lists 
     <lb/>
     came up in this chamber and the condition 
     <lb/>
     of affairs in the North-west Territories was 
     <lb/>
     thoroughly explained. The Bill did not seek 
     <lb/>
     to alter matters at all with regard to the 
     <lb/>
     voters' lists. The Bill was passed by this 
     <lb/>
     House and sent to the Senate, and the 
     <lb/>
     Senate did a very unusual thing, it under<lb break="no"/>took to make a most material change in the 
     <lb/>
     law with regard to elections for this House. 
     <lb/>
    I suppose that never before since Confede<lb break="no"/>ration did the Senate assume to do such a 
     <lb/>thing as change the law with regard to 
     <lb/>elections for members of the House of 
     <lb/>Commons. But in this case they made a 
     <lb/>most vital change, a change which simply 
     <lb/>means that, at the coming general elections 
     <lb/>the Government of the day have the power 
     <lb/>to nominate and elect representatives of 
     <lb/>the four constituencies in the North-west 
     <lb/>Territories. That is to say, this amendment 
     <lb/>makes it impossible for any opponent of the 
     <lb/>Government to get his name upon the 
     <lb/>voters' lists unless the officer appointed by 
     <lb/>the Government is willing that his name 
     <lb/>should be there. There is no opportunity 
     <lb/>for the voter to learn whether his name is 
     <lb/>upon the list or not unless it appears upon 
     <lb/>the first preliminary list that is made up. 
     <lb/>The amendments came back to the House 
     <lb/>of Commons and were passed in this House 
     <lb/>without any discussion or any explanation 
     <lb/>whatever ; they were passed through in such 
     <lb/>a silent and secret way that even the " Han<lb break="no"/>sard " reporters did not discover that they 
     <lb/>had been before the House for considera<lb break="no"/>tion. I find that, according to the journals, 
     <lb/>the Senate amendments to this Bill came 
     <lb/>up for consideration on the 26th June, 1894, 
     <lb/>and were agreed to without any amend<lb break="no"/>ment. In the "Hansard" of 26th June, 
     <lb/>1894, there is no reference whatever to the 
     <lb/>North-west Territories Representation Act, 
     <lb/>and while, no doubt. the hon. Minister of 
     <lb/>the Interior must have moved that the 
     <lb/>House go into committee on these amend<lb break="no"/>ments, there is no record of it whatever.<lb/>As I say, the thing was done in such a way<lb/>that there was not single member of the 
     <lb/>House, unless he had some notice of it from 
     <lb/>the Government, who knew anything of this 
     <lb/>most vital, this most momentous change 
     <lb/>having been made. I must say that I was 
     <lb/>entirely ignorant of it, and I fancy that 
     <lb/>no members of the House were aware of 
     <lb/>it, apart from those coming from the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories who had inspired this, and who had 
     <lb/>taken this means of having it done, of hav<lb break="no"/>ing the amendments made in the Senate, 
     <lb/>in a body that had nothing to do with this   
     <lb/>question, taking good care that no explana<lb break="no"/>tion should be made of the matter in this 
     <lb/>House, taking good care that no opportunity 
     <lb/>should be given to members of this House 
     <lb/>to show how outrageous the change was. 
     <lb/>They no doubt knew that this was going 
     <lb/>through the House, but I fancy, apart from 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <cb/>
      
      
     those few interested ones, and apart from 
     <lb/>
     the members (if the Government, no mem<lb break="no"/>ber of this House had any idea that any 
     <lb/>
     such change had been made. I myself 
     <lb/>
     heard of it during the dying hours of last 
     <lb/>
     session. It appeared that in making the 
     <lb/>
     changes, the hon. Minister of the Interior 
     <lb/>
     had overlooked some minor matters which 
     <lb/>
     also required to be changed, and in 1895 he 
     <lb/>
     brought in a Bill to correct those minor de<lb break="no"/>fects, and it was upon the discussion of that 
     <lb/>
     Bill, and in fact only after that Bill had pass<lb break="no"/>ed its second reading, had gone through com<lb break="no"/>mittee, and was ready for the third read<lb break="no"/>ing, that some members on this side of the 
     <lb/>
     House discovered, upon looking into the 
     <lb/>
     matter, that this vital change had been 
     <lb/>
     made. A very strong appeal was made to 
     <lb/>
     the Minister of the Interior not to force the 
     <lb/>
     amendments through, but he paid no atten<lb break="no"/>tion to that appeal, and he placed on the 
     <lb/>
     statute-book the most outrageous piece of 
     <lb/>
     legislation. Mr. Speaker, that has ever been 
     <lb/>
     enacted by this House of Commons, and 
     <lb/>
     I think in saying that I am saying a good 
     <lb/>
     deal. However, I intend to prove every 
     <lb/>
     word of it, because I say that the legisla<lb break="no"/>tion is not any clearer or more definite than 
     <lb/>
     if the House had passed a section and 
     <lb/>
     added it to the Northwest Territories Re<lb break="no"/>presentation Act, providing that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of the day should have the power 
     <lb/>
     to nominate and elect for the four consti<lb break="no"/>tuencies in the Territories, such men as they 
     <lb/>
     thought proper to represent those four con<lb break="no"/>stituencies. Now. in order to justify that 
     <lb/>
     statement it will be necessary for me to 
     <lb/>
     show, and I shall do so as briefly as I can, 
     <lb/>
     just what the law was prior to 1894, and 
     <lb/>
     what the law is to-day in regard to this 
     <lb/>
     matter. Prior to 1894. there was a voters' 
     <lb/>
     list in the Territories. But that voters' list 
     <lb/>
     was really of no account, because on elec<lb break="no"/>tion day it was possible for any person 
     <lb/>
     otherwise entitled to vote, to get his name 
     <lb/>
     added to the voters' list by the deputy re<lb break="no"/>turning officer; and the only object as ex<lb break="no"/>plained by the hon. member for West As<lb break="no"/>siniboia (Mr. Davin) when we were dis<lb break="no"/>cussing that Bill in 1894, of having a 
     <lb/>
     voters' list at all, was to save time, by pre<lb break="no"/>venting the necessity of swearing every one 
     <lb/>
     that came up, and to make it possible to 
     <lb/>
     poll all the votes at a particular polling 
     <lb/>
     division. Apart from that, the voters' list 
     <lb/>
     was of no use whatever. I myself believed, 
     <lb/>
     at that time that it did not matter at that 
     <lb/>
     time particularly, because there was always 
     <lb/>
     the right for a voter whose name had been 
     <lb/>
     omitted from that list, to have his name 
     <lb/>
     added to the list by the deputy returning 
     <lb/>
     officer. Now, that list is prepared in this 
     <lb/>
     way: Section 28 of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories Representation Act, as amended by 
     <lb/>chapter 10 of the Statutes of 1888, provides 
     <lb/>that the Governor General in Council may 
     <lb/>appoint enumerators for each polling 
     <lb/>division, and if hedoes not do so, the re<lb break="no"/>turning otficer, with the assistance of any 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <pb n="527" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00527.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">527</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">528</fw>
      
      
     justice of the peace. or notary public, and 
     <lb/>
     two electors, is obliged to appoint these 
     <lb/>
     enumerators. That is, instead of having, as 
     <lb/>
     we have in the Dominion Franchise Act, 
     <lb/>
     a revising officer for the whole constituency, 
     <lb/>
     an enumerator is appointed for each polling 
     <lb/>
     division when an election comes on. These 
     <lb/>
     enumerators, of course. are only appointed 
     <lb/>
     in case of an election, and they proceed to 
     <lb/>
     their duties as soon as the proclamation is 
     <lb/>
     issued for the election. Section 20 provides 
     <lb/>
     that the enumerator, as soon as he is ap<lb break="no"/>pointed, shall take an oath of office and 
     <lb/>
     proceed to make the list. The enumerator 
     <lb/>
    is appointed by the Government, and in 
     <lb/>default of an appointment by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. the returning officer is obliged, 
     <lb/>with the assistance of a justice of 
     <lb/>the peace and two electors, to make the 
     <lb/>appointment, so that there must be an 
     <lb/>enumerator for every polling division. It 
     <lb/>may be that an enumerator may act for 
     <lb/>more than one polling division. Then he 
     <lb/>goes on, by section 29, as amended in 1888, 
     <lb/>and compiles the list. Then by section 30: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Each enumerator shall complete, date at his 
     <lb/>
     place of residence, and sign the copies of the 
     <lb/>
     voters' list, or lists, as aforesaid, eight days be<lb break="no"/>fore the polling day ; two of the said copies for 
     <lb/>
     each polling division he shall forthwith post up 
     <lb/>
     in two of the most. public places within such 
     <lb/>
     polling division, and the other he retains for 
     <lb/>
     revision. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Now, that section remains as it was. He 
     <lb/>
     completes the list eight days before polling 
     <lb/>
     day. and posts up two of these lists in two 
     <lb/>
     of the most public places. Then section 31 
     <lb/>
     is the section which provides for revision, 
     <lb/>
     and I shall read that section to the House, 
     <lb/>
     and ask what protection there is to any 
     <lb/>
     one in a revision conducted under the pro<lb break="no"/>vision of this section : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
   
            <p>
     If any enumerator, at any time after posting 
     <lb/>
     up any voters' list, and before the polling day, 
     <lb/>
     is fully satisfied, from representations made to 
     <lb/>
     him by any credible person, that the name of any 
     <lb/>
     qualified voter has been omitted from the voters' 
     <lb/>
     list of the polling division to which such voter 
     <lb/>
     belongs, he shall add such name to the copy of 
     <lb/>
     the list in his possession, below his own signa<lb break="no"/>ture, and shall attest such addition by his ini<lb break="no"/>tials ; if the enumerator in like manner is fully 
     <lb/>
     satisfied that there is on the list the name of 
     <lb/>
     any person who is not qualified as a voter in such 
     <lb/>
     polling division. he may draw erasing lines 
     <lb/>
     through such name and write his own initials 
     <lb/>
     opposite thereto in the column for remarks. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Now, Mr. Speaker, in this voters' list, that 
     <lb/>
    is all the protection there is. Eight days. 
     <lb/>before the election day this man completes        
     <lb/>a list. he posts it up in two places, and 
     <lb/>then, by the Senate amendment, if at any 
     <lb/>time up to within two days of the polling 
     <lb/>day, that is six days after it is posted up. 
     <lb/>and during those six days, he gets any 
     <lb/>credible person to tell him that there is 
     <lb/>a name that ought to be on the list, he 
     <lb/>may put it on : and if any credible person 
     <lb/>informs him that there is some name on 
     <lb/>the list that ought to be struck off, he may 
     <lb/>
   
   
            <cb/>
        
        
     strike it off. That. Mr. Speaker, is all the 
     <lb/>
     protection there is to the opponents of the 
     <lb/>
     Government in these four constituencies, in 
     <lb/>
     the case of an election. Eight days before 
     <lb/>
     the election day the list is made, made by 
     <lb/>
     a man appointed by the (Government. Any<lb break="no"/>body, Tom, Dick and Harry. the most disre<lb break="no"/>putable man in the community, if they like, 
     <lb/>
     they can appoint. There is no restriction 
     <lb/>
     as to whom they may appoint. They may 
     <lb/>
     send in non-residents. the hon. Minister of 
     <lb/>
     the Interior may take Some of the charac<lb break="no"/>ters that the party keep down here—I do 
     <lb/>
     not know that they have got so many up 
     <lb/>
     there—they may send them into the, Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, one for each polling division. and 
     <lb/>
     ask them to make a list eight days before 
     <lb/>
     election. That list may have four names 
     <lb/>
     on it, it may have one name on it. possibly 
     <lb/>
     he may not find a single Voter in the con<lb break="no"/>stituency, or it may have twenty names on 
     <lb/>
     it; there is no limit. He is obliged to take 
     <lb/>
     no application. No elector has the right 
     <lb/>
     to go and make a statutory declaration and 
     <lb/>
     have his name put upon the list. The 
     <lb/>
    agent of the Government may conduct him<lb break="no"/>self without the slightest restriction or limi<lb break="no"/>tation. He can put on every Conservative. 
     <lb/>This man goes into the polling division, and 
     <lb/>he can go to the candidate and ask him: 
     <lb/>Do you think you have any supporters in 
     <lb/>polling division No. 5 ? If so, give 
     <lb/>me the names of those supporters. 
     <lb/>And having got the names of those 
     <lb/>supporters. he puts them upon the list. 
     <lb/>Then he posts it up eight days before 
     <lb/>election day, and during six days an elector, 
     <lb/>if he could not find out where the list was 
     <lb/>posted up, because there was no means of 
     <lb/>telling where it was posted, for all the Act 
     <lb/>says is that it must be posted in two of the 
     <lb/>most prominent places—and in many of the 
     <lb/>polling divisions of the Territories there is 
     <lb/>no polling place, except possibly a post office 
     <lb/>and in some cases there is no place that 
     <lb/>you could call the most public place except, at 
     <lb/>the corner of a fence. according to the mean<lb break="no"/>ing of the Act—the elector could go and ask 
     <lb/>to have his name put on the list. But the 
     <lb/>official can laugh. and say. "I will put 
     <lb/>your name on the list ,' but he need not do 
     <lb/>it. There is no means of finding out whe<lb break="no"/>ther the name has been put on the list or 
     <lb/>not until the man goes to vote on election 
     <lb/>day, and if the name is not on the list, 
     <lb/>there is no possible remedy. because after 
     <lb/>the list is completed two days before polling 
     <lb/>day, it is absolutely final. Section 46 of 
     <lb/>the Act provides that every voter shall be<lb/>entitled to vote whose name is on the voters' 
     <lb/>list, and if a man is not on the list 
     <lb/>he cannot vote. I should like to ask 
     <lb/>politicians whom I see around me on both 
     <lb/>Sides of the House if they would want 
     <lb/>anything better—if they were prepared to 
     <lb/>use it, but I do not suppose any hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber of this House would do so, although 
     <lb/>candidates to the next House might take 
     <lb/>advantage of it—to use than a snap of that 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <pb n="529" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00529.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">529</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 23, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">530</fw>
      
      
     kind with which to carry an election. It 
     <lb/>
     simply means that the Government has the 
     <lb/>
     power to nominate and elect those four mem<lb break="no"/>bers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Annapolis). That is taking a 
     <lb/>
     leaf out of the practice of the local govern<lb break="no"/>ment in Nova Scotia, by which they disfran<lb break="no"/>chised electors. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. On this side of the House 
     <lb/>
     the Franchise Act of the Dominion has been 
     <lb/>
     very much opposed. It has been opposed 
     <lb/>
     for this reason, that we do not believe it, 
     <lb/>
     is right for the Government to appoint an 
     <lb/>
     otiicer of their own to make up the voters 
     <lb/>
     list. But let me refer to the protection there 
     <lb/>
     is under the Franchise Act so far as get<lb break="no"/>ting names on the list is concerned. Sec<lb break="no"/>tion 15 of the Act provides that the revising 
     <lb/>
     officer shall on 1st August prepare to com<lb break="no"/>mence to make his list. He continues to 
     <lb/>
     make up that list up to 1st October. I am 
     <lb/>
     taking the Act as it is at present: it has 
     <lb/>
     been changed in regard to time, but there 
     <lb/>
     has always been an opportunity to add 
     <lb/>
     names during the two months of September 
     <lb/>
     and October, when the revising officer is 
     <lb/>
     supposed to be in his office ready to take 
     <lb/>
     applications, and in fact he is bound to take 
     <lb/>
     them if they are properly sworn to and 
     <lb/>
     placed before him. Every elector in the 
     <lb/>
     constituency has the opportunity of know<lb break="no"/>ing that, according to the law. on let August 
     <lb/>
     —it was in 1894 when the general list was 
     <lb/>
     made up—the revising officer in each consti<lb break="no"/>tuency commences to prepare the list. On 
     <lb/>
     1st October the list is closed. It. is 
     <lb/>
     immediately printed. It is then posted 
     <lb/>
     in various places; copies are sent to the 
     <lb/>
     defeated candidate. to the sitting member. 
     <lb/>
     to the different officials throughout the 
     <lb/>
     constituency and every man can see, if he 
     <lb/>
     will take the trouble to go over the list 
     <lb/>
     and examine it, whether his name is on the 
     <lb/>
     list. If he finds that his name is not on 
     <lb/>
     that list, a reasonable delay is granted in 
     <lb/>
     order that he may get his name placed 
     <lb/>
     there, because after the list has been posted 
     <lb/>
     the revising officer holds the court of re<lb break="no"/>vision. which must be held at least five 
     <lb/>
     weeks after the closing of the list. Note 
     <lb/>
     the difference in time. Weeks and months 
     <lb/>
     in the one case; days. hours and minutes 
     <lb/>
     in the other. Then any person whose name 
     <lb/>
     is not there may put in his appeal. if he 
     <lb/>
     gets it in within two weeks before the 
     <lb/>
     day of revision. He goes there and 
     <lb/>
     gives his evidence and after all these 
     <lb/>
     proceedings have taken place the judge gives 
     <lb/>
     notice that he will make up the list finally. 
     <lb/>
     and both parties have a right to be present. 
     <lb/>
     So far as time is concerned, an opportunity 
     <lb/>
     is given, under the Dominion Franchise Act. 
     <lb/>
     for both sides to be present and to find 
     <lb/>
     out what is going on. These are not the 
     <lb/>
     objections made by the. Liberals; the main 
     <lb/>
     objection taken is to the great power ex<lb break="no"/>ercised by these revising officers and their 
     <lb/>
     appointment by the Government. But in 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <cb/>
        
        
     the Territories there is no protection of the 
     <lb/>
     kind afforded by the Dominion Franchise 
     <lb/>
     Act. There is nothing done until the elec<lb break="no"/>tion almost comes on, and the first the elec<lb break="no"/>tors know what is going on is eight days 
     <lb/>
     before the day they are called on to vote. 
     <lb/>
     Many of them may be away. you can never 
     <lb/>
     count on having all the. electors in the 
     <lb/>
     constituency during the eight days preceding 
     <lb/>
     an election. But that is the only chance 
     <lb/>
     given them. If they can find those two pub<lb break="no"/>lic places where the lists are posted—because 
     <lb/>
     there is no provision for sending the lists 
     <lb/>
     to any one, even to the defeated candidate, 
     <lb/>
     and the people have no means of finding out 
     <lb/>
     anything in regard to it, for the enumerator 
     <lb/>
     has no office and there is no means of find<lb break="no"/>ing him—names may perhaps be added. But 
     <lb/>
     the list may be made up in Toronto, so far 
     <lb/>
     as the law is concerned. and indeed there 
     <lb/>
     is nothing in the law to prevent the prepara<lb break="no"/>tion of the whole list for the. Territories 
     <lb/>
     in an office in this building. All that is ne<lb break="no"/>cessary, so far as the Act is concerned. is to 
     <lb/>
     get some one to put up the lists in two places 
     <lb/>
     in each polling division in the Territories. 
     <lb/>
     But if that is not done, there is no penalty 
     <lb/>
     for failing, to do it. Eight days before the 
     <lb/>
     election the lists are stuck up, and then for 
     <lb/>
     six days an elector (and the House will re<lb break="no"/>member that polling divisions in the North<lb break="no"/>west are frequently larger than a county in 
     <lb/>
     Ontario), if by some chance he learns that 
     <lb/>
     the list has been posted in some place, may 
     <lb/>
     travel fifteen or twenty miles. and he may 
     <lb/>
     find that the list has been torn down in the 
     <lb/>
     meantime. In fact. the enumerator himself 
     <lb/>
     may tear it down immediately after he has 
     <lb/>
     put it up, for there is nothing in the law to 
     <lb/>
     prevent it. The list having been printed and 
     <lb/>
     published throughout the constituency, 
     <lb/>
     there is no possibility of the elector being 
     <lb/>
     able to get his name placed there. 
     <lb/>
     In this case what is the provision ? The 
     <lb/>
     provision is that he could go and ask the 
     <lb/>
     enumerator to have his name on ; that is all. 
     <lb/>
     The enumerator is not bound to put his name 
     <lb/>
     on, and if he does not put his name on the 
     <lb/>
     unfortunate elector has no means whatever 
     <lb/>
     of finding out that it has been left off; ex<lb break="no"/>cept that he goes on polling day, and after 
     <lb/>
     having driven again fifteen or twenty miles 
     <lb/>
     he finds that this enumerator has obeyed 
     <lb/>
     the instructions he received from those who 
     <lb/>
     appointed him and has not put his name on 
     <lb/>
     the list. Mr. Speaker, can it be imagined 
     <lb/>
     that a Government boasting of their strength 
     <lb/>
     as this Government has done during all 
     <lb/>
     these years, deriding the Opposition for 
     <lb/>
     their ill-success at the election, with a ma<lb break="no"/>jority in the House at the time they passed 
     <lb/>
     this Act of 55 or 60; can you imagine this 
     <lb/>
     Government being reduced to the extremity 
     <lb/>
     of passing an Act of Parliament for the 
     <lb/>
     purpose of stealing from us four seats in 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories, in a part of 
     <lb/>
     Canada which has never yet returned a 
     <lb/>
     Liberal to Parliament? The Minister of the 
     <lb/>
     Interior had been up in that country and 
     <lb/>
 
 
            <pb n="531" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00531.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">531</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">532</fw>
       
       
     he had driven through it. He found that the 
     <lb/>
     prestige of the Government had gone, and 
     <lb/>
     that the people there were only waiting 
     <lb/>
     the opportunity of voting against the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment representatives, and so he came to 
     <lb/>
     the conclusion that unless he passed some 
     <lb/>
     Act of this kind, every member from the 
     <lb/>
    North-west Territories would be a supporter 
     <lb/>of the leader of the Opposition. But even 
     <lb/>then you would have thought that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment would have some honour and some 
     <lb/>decency in the matter, and that if they 
     <lb/>were prepared to pass an Act of this out<lb break="no"/>rageous character they would have had at 
     <lb/>least the decency to explain in the House 
     <lb/>in a manly, straightforward way, that they 
     <lb/>did intend to steal these constituencies and 
     <lb/>give us an opportunity of discussing and 
     <lb/>objecting to it. But, no ; the Minister intro<lb break="no"/>duces the Bill without a word. He puts it 
     <lb/>through the House and then he gets some<lb break="no"/>body in the Senate, a body which has no<lb break="no"/>thing to do with the matter, to sneak in 
     <lb/>these amendments so vital and so important, 
     <lb/>and he brings it back here and puts it 
     <lb/>through without the slightest word of ex<lb break="no"/>planation. The hon. gentleman referred in 
     <lb/>another debate to the Manitoba Act in re<lb break="no"/>gard to the elections. Let us look at the 
     <lb/>Manitoba Act and see if there is anything 
     <lb/>in it like this: That Act provides that the 
     <lb/>voters' lists shall be made up from time to 
     <lb/>time when the Government sees fit, and that 
     <lb/>when the voters' lists are to be revised a 
     <lb/>general proclamation is to issue appointing 
     <lb/>a registration clerk for each electoral dis<lb break="no"/>trict in the province. That proclamation 
     <lb/>fixes the day for the closing of the lists, 
     <lb/>which day shall be not less than four weeks 
     <lb/>from the date of the proclamation. During 
     <lb/>these four weeks every elector has an op<lb break="no"/>portunity of sending to that registration 
     <lb/>clerk. a sworn declaration showing that he 
     <lb/>is entitled to vote, and if the registration 
     <lb/>clerk does not put upon the list every one 
     <lb/>of those persons whd furnishes him with a 
     <lb/>proper declaration, he is subject to a heavy 
     <lb/>penalty. After the lists are closed they are 
     <lb/>printed and circulated. Copies are sent to 
     <lb/>defeated candidates at the previous election, 
     <lb/>to the sitting members. to every mayor, 
     <lb/>councillor, alderman and reeve in the' con<lb break="no"/>stituency and to every postmaster. They 
     <lb/>are put up in every school house, and every 
     <lb/>post office, and every municipal office, and 
     <lb/>then there is a revision. A revising officer 
     <lb/>is appointed who must be either a judge or 
     <lb/>a barrister of at least three years standing. 
     <lb/>These lists must be published and posted 
     <lb/>up at least thirty days before the day ap<lb break="no"/>pointed for the final court revision, 
     <lb/>every one has an opportunity, just as they 
     <lb/>have under the Dominion Franchise Act, 
     <lb/>of putting in their appeals. as long as they 
     <lb/>get them in five days before the day for 
     <lb/>the final revision. Then an open court is 
     <lb/>held, and after that the list is completed 
     <lb/>and is published. Twenty-five copies are 
     <lb/>sent to the defeated candidate, twenty-five 
     <lb/>
      
      
            <cb/>
       
       
     copies to the sitting member, and two copies 
     <lb/>
     to every municipal officer in the province. 
     <lb/>
     These are also posted up in the most public 
     <lb/>
     way all over the province. Therefore, under 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion Act and under the Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     Act, which the hon. gentleman criticized 
     <lb/>
     in another connection, there is the most 
     <lb/>
     ample opportunity for every man to get his 
     <lb/>
     name upon the list, unless some of the 
     <lb/>
     officers commit a fraud. But, in the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories, I say that there is no 
     <lb/>
     opportunity, there is no possible chance of 
     <lb/>
     a man getting his name upon the list unless 
     <lb/>
     the enumerator is willing to put him 
     <lb/>
     upon the list. Now. Mr. Speaker, it is well 
     <lb/>
     known by the Government, and also, I think, 
     <lb/>
     generally in this House, that the North-west 
     <lb/>
     Assembly is composed very largely of Con<lb break="no"/>servatives. I shall, with your permission, 
     <lb/>
     Sir, read a resolution which that body pass<lb break="no"/>ed upon this vcry subject; a subject, it is 
     <lb/>
     true, that was not particularly within their 
     <lb/>
     jurisdiction, but a subject in which each 
     <lb/>
     one of them was interested as a citizen of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion, and one in which they felt 
     <lb/>
     there was such a strong public interest in 
     <lb/>
     the Territories that they were justified in 
     <lb/>
     passing this very forcible resolution in regard 
     <lb/>
     to the matter. The following resolution was 
     <lb/>
     moved by Mr. Insinger, and passed unani<lb break="no"/>mously :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Whereas under the " North-west Territories Re<lb break="no"/>presentation Act" the requirements for elec<lb break="no"/>tors in the territories to be allowed to vote at 
     <lb/>
     Dominion elections differ from the require<lb break="no"/>ments for electors in the provinces, inasmuch 
     <lb/>
     as they are not based on the provisions of the 
     <lb/>
     " Electoral Franchise Act ;" 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And whereas, though immediately before Domin<lb break="no"/>ion elections in the Territories lists of voters 
     <lb/>
     are to be made by enumerators appointed either 
     <lb/>
     by the Governor in Council or by the return<lb break="no"/>ing officer, conjointly with any two justices of 
     <lb/>
     the peace, or with one justice of the peace and 
     <lb/>
     a notary public, or with any one of them and 
     <lb/>
     two electors of the electoral district, yet, till 
     <lb/>
     the passing of the Acts to amend the North<lb break="no"/>west Representation Act in the years 1894 and 
     <lb/>
     1895, all electors having the qualifications of 
     <lb/>
     such were allowed to vote independently of the 
     <lb/>
     fact, if they were on such list of voters or not ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And whereas in all elections in the Territories, 
     <lb/>
     both territorial and Dominion, the principle of 
     <lb/>
     allowing a voter's name to be put on the list. 
     <lb/>
     up to the moment of voting prevailed up to 
     <lb/>
     1894;  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And whereas such principle was reailirmed by 
     <lb/>
     the legislative assembly of the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories in their "Territories Elections Ordin<lb break="no"/>ance " of 1894, in which, moreover, the assem<lb break="no"/>bly did not think it advisable to make provis<lb break="no"/>ions for either voters' lists or lists of voters ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And whereas experience at the general election 
     <lb/>
     for the assembly held in the year 1894 showed 
     <lb/>
     such system to be admirably adapted to the 
     <lb/>
     needs of these sparsely-settled territories ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And whereas by the Acts to amend the North<lb break="no"/>west Representation Act, passed in the 57-58 
     <lb/>
     year and 58-59 year, Victoria, the list of voters 
     <lb/>
     made by enumerators will have the same force 
     <lb/>
     as a voters' list prepared under the provisions 
     <lb/>
     of the Electoral Franchise Act, and all such 
     <lb/>
     persons as are not on such list of voters will 
     <lb/>
       
       
            <pb n="533" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00533.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">533</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 23, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">534</fw>
      
      
     be excluded from the right to exercise the 
     <lb/>
     franchise ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And whereas such lists of voters do not offer the 
     <lb/>
     same safeguards to the rights of electors as 
     <lb/>
     do the voters" lists in the provinces, inasmuch 
     <lb/>
     as 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (1) They are necessarily hurriedly prepared 
     <lb/>
     by enumerators between the time of the 
     <lb/>
     receipt of the writ for election and a week 
     <lb/>
     before the day of polling ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (2) The time allowed to electors or their 
     <lb/>
     agents to ascertain if their names are on 
     <lb/>
     such list is, taken in connection with the 
     <lb/>
     distances generally to be travelled in the 
     <lb/>
     territories, and with the fact that no fixed 
     <lb/>
     residences are appointed for such enumer<lb break="no"/>ators, insufficient for the purpose ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (3) The enumerator is the absolute judge of 
     <lb/>
     the right of an elector to be on such list, 
     <lb/>
     and he can put on or strike off names till 
     <lb/>
     within two days of the polling day without 
     <lb/>
     notice from or to such electors ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (4) There is no appeal from the decision of 
     <lb/>
     the enumerator either to a revising officer? 
     <lb/>
     or to a judge: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Therefore, in the opinion of this assembly, it is 
     <lb/>
     desirable that the " North-west Territories Re<lb break="no"/>presentation Act" be further amended so as 
     <lb/>
     to either adopt the system provided for in the 
     <lb/>
     " Territories Election Ordinances," or to bring 
     <lb/>
     into effect the provisions regarding voters' 
     <lb/>
     lists of the " Electoral Franchise Act." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Among the members of the assembly who 
     <lb/>
     supported that resolution, which recapitu<lb break="no"/>lates very well the different points which 
     <lb/>
     I have alleged against this outrage, is Mr. 
     <lb/>
    Haultain, who is the Premier of the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, and the nominated candidate on 
     <lb/>the Government side for the constituency 
     <lb/>of Alberta at the present time. In fact, it 
     <lb/>was at his suggestion that it was proposed; 
     <lb/>that the law should be re-enacted as it was 
     <lb/>before. What the assembly ask for is one 
     <lb/>of three things—first, that the law should 
     <lb/>be re-enacted as it was before ; second. that 
     <lb/>the Territories Franchise Act. should be 
     <lb/>adopted ; third, that the Electoral Franchise 
     <lb/>Act of the Dominion should be brought in<lb break="no"/>to force in the Territories. Of course, it; 
     <lb/>is quite out of the question to attempt, at 
     <lb/>this late day to bring into force the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Franchise Act for the coming elec<lb break="no"/>tions; so that the recommendations of the 
     <lb/>assembly narrow themselves down to thei 
     <lb/>others—either to have their own Franchise 
     <lb/>Act, or to have the old Act as it was. I 
     <lb/>understand that it is suggested as an objec<lb break="no"/>tion to the Act as it was passed that it 
     <lb/>afforded more or less opportunity for; 
     <lb/>fraudulent voting. Now, whether there was 
     <lb/>opportunity for it, or not, I can say truth<lb break="no"/>fully and I think the members from the 
     <lb/>Territories will agree with me—that there 
     <lb/>has not been, to any appreciable extent, 
     <lb/>any fraud in elections there. There has 
     <lb/>been no complaint on the floor of this House, 
     <lb/>so far as I have heard, from members re<lb break="no"/>presenting constituencies in the Territories, 
     <lb/>of the law working in that direction. There 
     <lb/>is no doubt that it is a very crude law. It 
     <lb/>is certainly not a law that should be allow<lb break="no"/>ed to stand ; but the law that has been sub<lb break="no"/>
         
         
            <cb/>
        
        
        stituted for it will bear no comparison with 
     <lb/>
     it whatever. If the Government came to 
     <lb/>
     the conclusion that there was too much 
     <lb/>
     opportunity for persons swearing falsely 
     <lb/>
     that they were entitled to vote, they should, 
     <lb/>
     in 1894, have applied the Dominion Fran<lb break="no"/>chise Act to the Territories. Not having 
     <lb/>
     been prepared to do that, they cannot be 
     <lb/>
     allowed to use this flimsy pretext for the 
     <lb/>
     outrage they committed. I am glad to 
     <lb/>
     notice that the hon. member for West As<lb break="no"/>siniboia (Mr. Davin) apparently takes the 
     <lb/>
     same view of the Government's conduct as 
     <lb/>
     I do, because he has also introduced a Bill 
     <lb/>
     into this House, which has received its first 
     <lb/>
     reading, in exactly the same direction as 
     <lb/>
     mine. My Bill proposes to put the law back 
     <lb/>
     as it was before, that is, to re-enact section 
     <lb/>
     44 of chapter 7 -of the Revised Statutes, 
     <lb/>
     which reads as follows :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The deputy returning officer shall, while the 
     <lb/>
    poll is open, it required by any elector whose 
     <lb/>name is not on the voters' list, administer to 
     <lb/>such elector oath number one in the said form 
     <lb/>P; and such oath having been taken, the de<lb break="no"/>puty returning officer shall at once cause such 
     <lb/>elector's name to be added to the voters' list, 
     <lb/>with the word " sworn " written thereafter. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Now, Mr. Speaker, I would like to know 
     <lb/>
     from the hon. Minister of the Interior whe<lb break="no"/>ther the Government committed this out<lb break="no"/>rage of their own accord, or whether they 
     <lb/>were asked to do so by any member from 
     <lb/>the Territories in the House at the present 
     <lb/>time. We may take it for granted, that the 
     <lb/>hon. member for West Assiniboia (Mr. 
     <lb/>Davin) did not request or advise the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to do so, because he comes here 
     <lb/>and asks to have the same changes made 
     <lb/>that I am asking for. I do not suppose 
     <lb/>that the hon. member for East Assiniboia 
     <lb/>(Mr. McDonald) would request the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to make a change in this direction, 
     <lb/>because he has been discarded by his party 
     <lb/>in his constituency, and another man sub<lb break="no"/>stituted for him as the candidate for the 
     <lb/>coming election. So far as the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Alberta (Mr. Davis) is concerned, 
     <lb/>I am sure I am-quite safe in saying that 
     <lb/>hon. gentleman would never be a party to 
     <lb/>such a disgraceful attempt to steal con<lb break="no"/>stituencies. Then, the hon. member for 
     <lb/>Saskatchewan (Mr. Macdowall) is the only 
     <lb/>member left representing a North-west con<lb break="no"/>stituency. I do not know—I should imagine 
     <lb/>that hon. gentleman would scarcely be 
     <lb/>guilty of forwarding or asking for legisla<lb break="no"/>tion the effect of which must be to give 
     <lb/>him a most unfair advantage over his 
     <lb/>opponent. The Government have always 
     <lb/>expressed themselves as being confident 
     <lb/>of the result of the elections in the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, and I would ask hon. members sup<lb break="no"/>porting the Government from other pro<lb break="no"/>vinces what they think of their expres<lb break="no"/>sion of confidence when they are reduced 
     <lb/>to extremities such, as this. Will any one 
     <lb/>believe that they have any confidence what<lb break="no"/>ever in having the slightest particle of a 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <pb n="535" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00535.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">535</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">536</fw>
     
     
     chance in any one of these constituencies, 
     <lb/>
     if they are obliged to put through this 
     <lb/>
     House in such a secret way, without any 
     <lb/>
     discussion or explanation, without any 
     <lb/>
     chance of their opponents knowing what 
     <lb/>
     they were doing, a Bill of this kind—an 
     <lb/>
     Act which allows men nominated by them<lb break="no"/>selves to go into a polling division and 
     <lb/>
     make up once for all a list from which 
     <lb/>
     they may exclude every likely opponent 
     <lb/>
     from being a candidate, and from which 
     <lb/>
     list there is no possible appeal. Why, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Speaker, I fancy that, outside of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, and outside of any member from 
     <lb/>
     the Territories, if such can be found, who 
     <lb/>
     has urged and supported legislation of this 
     <lb/>
     kind, there is not on the other side of the 
     <lb/>
     House a single member who will justify 
     <lb/>
     and support the Government in keeping 
     <lb/>
     upon the statute-book such an outrage as 
     <lb/>
     this. This is the last session of this House; 
     <lb/>
     it can only last a certain time ; and, so far 
     <lb/>
     as I am concerned, if my voice does not 
     <lb/>
     give out, I will certainly, so long as I am 
     <lb/>
     able to speak, stand up here day after day 
     <lb/>
      and protest against this iniquitous outrage, 
     <lb/>
     and prevent, so far as my efforts can, the 
     <lb/>
     Government getting on with any business 
     <lb/>
     whatever until— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. You are 
     <lb/>
     perfectly correct. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. The hon. gentleman is 
     <lb/>
     not in order ; he is threatening the House 
     <lb/>
     with opposition. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. I withdraw my threat. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. Allow 
     <lb/>
     me for one moment on a question of order 
     <lb/>
     —it is always the rule that the redress of 
     <lb/>
     grievances should precede supplies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. I did not understand the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Winnipeg (Mr. Martin) to 
     <lb/>
     take that position. I understood him to 
     <lb/>
     threaten that he would not allow the busi<lb break="no"/>ness of the House to go on unless this par<lb break="no"/>ticular statute to which he referred was 
     <lb/>
     amended. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. You certainly, Sir, under<lb break="no"/>stood me quite correctly, and as I find I 
     <lb/>
     am out of order, I withdraw the threat ; 
     <lb/>
     but I shall take every parliamentary means 
     <lb/>
     in my power to compel the Government— 
     <lb/>
     there is no use appealing to this Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, I have lost any idea of that kind ; 
     <lb/>
     I do not think there is any use appealing 
     <lb/>
     to their honour or patriotism or fairness—but 
     <lb/>
     I say that I will use my right as a repre<lb break="no"/>sentative here of taking every parliament<lb break="no"/>ary and legitimate opportunity of insisting 
     <lb/>
     that this wrong shall be made right before 
     <lb/>
     this session is over. And I would like to 
     <lb/>
     hear from the hon. Minister of the Interior 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Daly) any justification of this amend<lb break="no"/>ment which he put through this House 
     <lb/>
     without the slightest explanation. I have 
     <lb/>
     been in the Territories since last session, 
     <lb/>
       
       
            <cb/>
       
       
     after the people had learnt of this amend<lb break="no"/>ment. They had no knowledge of it before 
     <lb/>
     last session. I have conversed with gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen there on both sides of politics, and 
     <lb/>
     was requested by them to ask for this 
     <lb/>
     change in the law, and I am satisfied that 
     <lb/>
     the hon. Minister of the Interior has few, 
     <lb/>
     if any, supporters in the Territories who 
     <lb/>
     will justify him in this attempt to take 
     <lb/>
     away from the people their right to vote. 
     <lb/>
     If the hon. gentleman's policy is acceptable 
     <lb/>
     to the people there, let him depend upon 
     <lb/>
     that alone. Let him go before the people 
     <lb/>
     with his policy ; let him give us the op<lb break="no"/>portunity of getting our names on the list ; 
     <lb/>
     let him give us the right to vote—and then 
     <lb/>
     if he is supported by the people, all right ; 
     <lb/>
     if he is condemned, let him take his con<lb break="no"/>demnation. But let him not attempt to 
     <lb/>
     get away from the votes of the people ; 
     <lb/>
     let him not attempt to hide his iniquity in 
     <lb/>
     a parliamentary election of members for 
     <lb/>
     those four constituencies. It is an outrage 
     <lb/>
     which has never been perpetrated even in 
     <lb/>
     this House of Commons, and I am satisfied 
     <lb/>
     it could not have been perpetrated here, if 
     <lb/>
     the members had known what was suggest<lb break="no"/>ed to them, and what was being enacted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. In answer to the very furi<lb break="no"/>ous attack made by the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Winnipeg (Mr. Martin), it seems to me that 
     <lb/>
     it is well for the House and you, Mr. Speak<lb break="no"/>er, to be put in possession of the facts, and 
     <lb/>
     not take for gospel what the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     has said. He has seen fit to impugn the 
     <lb/>
     honour and patriotism of this Government, 
     <lb/>
     and my own personal honour in this mat<lb break="no"/>ter, not only as a member of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, but as a member of the House, be<lb break="no"/>cause he declared that I had sneaked 
     <lb/>
     through this House a clause in the Bill 
     <lb/>
     which came from the Senate. What are 
     <lb/>
     the facts ? They are that in 1894 I introduced 
     <lb/>
     into this House a Bill to amend the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories Representation Act. That 
     <lb/>
     Bill went through this House and had its 
     <lb/>
     third reading. I ask if the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     will find upon record that he took any part 
     <lb/>
     in the discussion of that Bill, during its three 
     <lb/>
     readings. He will find that he did not. 
     <lb/>
     He will find that he did not give any atten<lb break="no"/>tion to it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. It had not this clause 
     <lb/>
     in it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. Did you, or did you not read 
     <lb/>
     the Bill ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. I did. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. So we have the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man on record that he did look at the Bill 
     <lb/>
     and knew what it was when it went through 
     <lb/>
     the Senate. The hon. gentleman has accus<lb break="no"/>ed me of going to the Senate and getting 
     <lb/>
     the members of that chamber to put in 
     <lb/>
     this clause, and conniving with them in do<lb break="no"/>ing a wrong to the North-west Territories. 
     <lb/>
     I tell the hon. gentleman and this House 
     <lb/>
     that I never spoke to a Senator, or any<lb break="no"/>
       
       
            <pb n="537" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00537.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">537</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 23, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">538</fw>
   
   
     body else, with reference to this Bill after 
     <lb/>
     it left this House and went to the Senate; 
     <lb/>
     and I was just as ignorant as the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman is that the clause was put in the 
     <lb/>
     Bill by the Senate repealing clause 44 un<lb break="no"/>til the Bill came back to this House. When 
     <lb/>
     the Bill came back here, I pointed out to 
     <lb/>
     members of the North-west Territories the 
     <lb/>
     changes made by the Senate, because there 
     <lb/>
     was more than one change, and I was told 
     <lb/>
     by these gentlemen that the changes had 
     <lb/>
     been made at their solicitation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. Will the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     give the names ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. The hon. member for East 
     <lb/>
     Assiniboia (Mr. McDonald) was the gentle<lb break="no"/>man who informed me, and he told me the 
     <lb/>
     reason was that in the last elections held 
     <lb/>
     in the North-west Territories this clause 44 
     <lb/>
     gave rise to the committal of per<lb break="no"/>jury by a number of people, who had their 
     <lb/>
     names put on the list without any right. 
     <lb/>
     What does clause 44 say : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The deputy returning officer shall, while the 
     <lb/>
     poll is open, if required by any elector whose 
     <lb/>
     name is not on the voters' list, administer to 
     <lb/>
     such elector oath number one in the said form 
     <lb/>
     P ; and such oath having been taken, the deputy 
     <lb/>
     returning officer shall at once cause such elec<lb break="no"/>tor's name to be added to the voters' list, with 
     <lb/>
     the word " sworn " written thereafter. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     I should like to know if that provision does 
     <lb/>
     not admit of the statement made by the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for East Assiniboia (Mr. Mac<lb break="no"/>donald) to me that it opened the door for 
     <lb/>
     wrong-doing ? The hon. gentleman told me 
     <lb/>
     that in his own electoral division, there 
     <lb/>
     were 150 names put on the list under the 
     <lb/>
     provision of that clause, which would not 
     <lb/>
     have been there if the men whose names 
     <lb/>
     were on had not perjured themselves by 
     <lb/>
     taking the oath. The hon. gentleman went 
     <lb/>
     further. He did not only charge me with 
     <lb/>
     having connived with some one in the Sen<lb break="no"/>ate in order to have the clause added to 
     <lb/>
     the Bill, but he said that the Bill was not 
     <lb/>
     discussed in this House, and that it went 
     <lb/>
     through silently and in an irregular man<lb break="no"/>ner. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. I said as to the amend<lb break="no"/>ments. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. I am talking about them. 
     <lb/>
     The hon. gentleman said that there is no<lb break="no"/>thing in the " Hansard " about this particu<lb break="no"/>lar amendment. He will not find in the 
     <lb/>
     " Hansard" anything about the amend<lb break="no"/>ments to the Bill, but he will find them in 
     <lb/>
     the Journals of the House. Look at the 
     <lb/>
     Journals of the 26th June, 1894. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. I said they were in the 
     <lb/>
     Journal, but that there was no mention 
     <lb/>
     in the " Hansard " about any discussion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. On page 349 of .the Journals 
     <lb/>
     of. the House you will find, by a division that 
     <lb/>
     took place in" the afternoon, that the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Winnipeg was present when the 
     <lb/>
        
        
            <cb/>
         
         
     amendments went through, or that, if not 
     <lb/>
     present, he ought to have been. He was in 
     <lb/>
     the precincts of the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) Does the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman say that on the page 349 of the 
     <lb/>
     Journals of 1894 the particular amendment 
     <lb/>
     to which my hon. friend objects is found ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. Yes; and I call the atten<lb break="no"/>tion of the House to the proceedings that 
     <lb/>
     took place on that day, so that we may 
     <lb/>
     ascertain whether or not these amendments 
     <lb/>
     were sneaked through or whether there was 
     <lb/>
     anything irregular in the manner in which 
     <lb/>
     these amendments that came from the Sen<lb break="no"/>ate were put through this House. We find 
     <lb/>
     that four petitions were presented: we find 
     <lb/>
     that a Bill from the Senate, intituled " An 
     <lb/>
     Act respecting the Speaker of the Senate," 
     <lb/>
     was, according to the Orders. read a third 
     <lb/>
     time, &amp;c., and then we find that the House, 
     <lb/>
     according to order, proceeded to take into 
     <lb/>
     consideration the amendments made by the 
     <lb/>
     Senate to the Bill intituled " An Act further 
     <lb/>
     to amend the North-west Territories Repre<lb break="no"/>sentation Act," and that the same were read 
     <lb/>
     as follows. There was not one amendment 
     <lb/>
     only. but half a dozen, and these were read to 
     <lb/>
     the House in the usual way, and they were 
     <lb/>
     passed through in the usual way. I want 
     <lb/>
     to call the hon. gentleman's particular at<lb break="no"/>tention to the fact that they went through 
     <lb/>
     in the afternoon, so that there was no ex<lb break="no"/>cuse for his not knowing all about them. 
     <lb/>
     He may be frequently absent during the 
     <lb/>
     evening, but these were read in the after<lb break="no"/>noon, and, besides, they were on the Order 
     <lb/>
     paper, so that the hon. gentleman has no 
     <lb/>
     excuse for not knowing about them. And 
     <lb/>
     they were on the Orders of the Day, so 
     <lb/>
     that the hon. gentleman's attention was 
     <lb/>
     called to the matter. Moreover, those 
     <lb/>
     amendments were all spread out upon the 
     <lb/>
     Journals of the House, as follows :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     Clause A. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Section eighteen of the said Act is hereby 
     <lb/>
     amended by adding thereto the following sub<lb break="no"/>section :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " 3. The returning officer shall not receive the 
     <lb/>
     nomination paper of any member of the legisla<lb break="no"/>tive assembly of the North-west Territories. 
     <lb/>
    Page 1, line 15.—After " Council " insert 
     <lb/>clauses B, C and D. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     Clause B . 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Section thirty-one of the said Act is hereby 
     <lb/>
     amended by adding after the word " and " in the 
     <lb/>
     second line thereof the words " two days." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     Clause C. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Section thirty-two of the said Act is hereby 
     <lb/>
     amended by striking out the words " on the day " 
     <lb/>
     in the fifth line thereot and replacing the same  
     <lb/>
     by the words " two days." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     Clause D. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Section thirty-three of the said Act is hereby 
     <lb/>
     amended by leaving out all utter the word " di<lb break="no"/>vision " in the sixth line thereof. ' 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="539" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00539.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">539</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">540</fw>
            <p>
     Page 2, line 6.—Atter " twenty " insert "sec<lb break="no"/>tion twenty-eight." 
     <lb/>
    Page 2, line 11.—After " twenty " insert " two." 
     <lb/>Page 2, line 22,—After " application " insert 
     <lb/>" tor a recount or final addition." 
     <lb/>Page 2, line 23.—Leave out from " Act " to 
     <lb/>" shall" in line 24. 
     <lb/>Page 2, line 26.—Aiter "Territories" insert 
     <lb/>"and the application provided for by the sub<lb break="no"/>section added to the said section by section 
     <lb/>eleven of chapter nineteen of the Statutes of 1891, 
     <lb/>shall be made to the said court in banco." 
     <lb/>Page 3, line 28.—After " forty-one " insert 
     <lb/>" forty-four." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

   </quote>

    

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     This is the amendment the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man objects to. These amendments 
     <lb/>
     were agreed to by this House. Now, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Speaker, this was done in broad 
     <lb/>
     daylight when, I presume, the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man was in his seat in the House. The 
     <lb/>
     Votes and Proceedings show that during that 
     <lb/>
     afternoon or evening a division, took place, 
     <lb/>
     and the hon. gentleman's name is recorded 
     <lb/>
     in the division. So the hon. gentleman was 
     <lb/>
     in the House or within the precincts of the 
     <lb/>
     House when these proceedings took place. 
     <lb/>
     Had the hon. gentleman paid the attention 
     <lb/>
     to his legislative duties that he ought to 
     <lb/>
     have paid, he would have known of these 
     <lb/>
     amendments, for he had the same notice of 
     <lb/>
     the amendments that I had. When these 
     <lb/>
     amendments were made I went into them 
     <lb/>
     to ascertain the eiifect of them, because, as 
     <lb/>
     I said before, they were made without my 
     <lb/>
     knowledge. When my attention was called 
     <lb/>
     to the fact that section 44 was amended, 
     <lb/>
     I went to the hon. member for East Assini<lb break="no"/>boia (Mr. McDonald), who, I think, was the 
     <lb/>
     only representative from the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories about at the time, to ascertain what 
     <lb/>
     the facts were, and he explained to me why 
     <lb/>
     the amendment was made in the Senate. 
     <lb/>
     So the hon. gentleman's charge that I was 
     <lb/>
     responsible for that amendment falls to the 
     <lb/>
     ground. That amendment was made by the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman in charge of the Bill in the 
     <lb/>
     Senate on the advice of the representatives 
     <lb/>
     in that chamber from the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories. I would be quite willing to leave 
     <lb/>
     the matter there but the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     goes further. He seems to wish to make 
     <lb/>
     a little cheap popularity by frequent clap<lb break="no"/>trap discussions of this matter. The hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman would give the members of this 
     <lb/>
     House to understand that by that simple 
     <lb/>
     amendment we have changed the position of 
     <lb/>
     voters in the North-west Territories and 
     <lb/>
     that the provisions he has read were new. 
     <lb/>
     He seeks to impress the people with 
     <lb/>
     same idea, for in an interview with the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman in the Winnipeg " Tribune," 
     <lb/>
     which was sent to me, the impression is 
     <lb/>
     conveyed that there is something new about 
     <lb/>
     it. Why, Sir, the Act the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     has quoted is one of the Acts of 49 Victoria. 
     <lb/>
     Ten years ago thatAct was passed in this 
     <lb/>
     House. So if any injustice was inflicted 
     <lb/>
     upon the people of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, it was inflicted upon them by the 
     <lb/>
        
        
            <cb/>
 
 
     House of Parliament of which many hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen still in the House were members. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). And opposed it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. I do not know; I have not 
     <lb/>
     looked up the debates of the House of that 
     <lb/>
     time. At all events this is the law. Since 
     <lb/>
     then two elections have been held, and I 
     <lb/>
     fail to find that any of the charges made by 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman have been borne out. 
     <lb/>
     I fail to find that either the newspapers or 
     <lb/>
     candidates in the elections have complained 
     <lb/>
     about the way the enumerations were made 
     <lb/>
     up. I was through that country in an elec<lb break="no"/>tion campaign in 1887. 1 saw those lists 
     <lb/>
     there, prepared, as they were, under the 
     <lb/>
     statute and I never heard any complaints, 
     <lb/>
     and we were associated day after day with 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen representing the Opposition. No 
     <lb/>
     discussion at all took place in reference to 
     <lb/>
     the way the lists were being made up. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). They were made 
     <lb/>
     up to the day of the election, which cannot 
     <lb/>
     be done now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. The hon. gentleman is mis<lb break="no"/>taken. The hon. member for Winnipeg says 
     <lb/>
     that under the amendment, if names are not 
     <lb/>
     on the list two days before the election they 
     <lb/>
     cannot be got on at all. Under the old law 
     <lb/>
     persons could swear in their names on the 
     <lb/>
     day of the election. That is the real charge. 
     <lb/>
     If he rested the charge there, I would be 
     <lb/>
     satisfied. But he goes further and makes 
     <lb/>
     the charge against the Government that we 
     <lb/>
     are seeking to disfranchise the electors of 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories by a law that 
     <lb/>
     he would give us to understand was passed 
     <lb/>
     in 1894 or 1895. But the enumeration lists 
     <lb/>
     are made up under a law passed ten years 
     <lb/>
     ago. What are its provisions ? They were 
     <lb/>
     made to suit the peculiar conditions and 
     <lb/>
     requirements of the North-west Territories. 
     <lb/>
     It was well understood by Parliament that 
     <lb/>
     it would not do to apply the provisions of 
     <lb/>
     the Franchise Act to the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. The most suitable law under the 
     <lb/>
     circumstances was passed. In discussing 
     <lb/>
    the provisions of the Act the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>sneers at the idea of the Governor General 
     <lb/>appointing the enumerators, and says that 
     <lb/>disreputable men might be appointed, that 
     <lb/>disreputable men might be sent up from 
     <lb/>here. I think the hon. gentleman reflects 
     <lb/>severely upon the people of the North-west 
     <lb/>Territories. Does the hon. gentleman give 
     <lb/>us to understand by the charge he makes 
     <lb/>that disreputable men prepared the lists 
     <lb/>for the late local elections in Manitoba, I 
     <lb/>do not think that the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>would like to admit that the men who 
     <lb/>prepared the lists in North Winnipeg and 
     <lb/>Brandon City and North Brandon were 
     <lb/>disreputable men. Yet I produced evi<lb break="no"/>dence the other day to show that hundreds 
     <lb/>of men were disfranchised by their names 
     <lb/>being left off the lists. In this case the 
     <lb/>Governor General will do just as he has 
     <lb/>done in the pasts—he will appoint men fit 
     <lb/>for the position. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="541" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00541.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">541</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 23, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">542</fw>
            
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). He will appoint 
     <lb/>
     men whom he is advised to appoint. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. Who advises the Attorney 
     <lb/>
     General at Winnipeg to appoint the enu<lb break="no"/>merators under the Manitoba Franchise 
     <lb/>
     Act ? Do they appoint any person opposed 
     <lb/>
     to the Government or do they appoint their 
     <lb/>
     own friends ? I do not wish the House to 
     <lb/>
     understand that we are going to appoint 
     <lb/>
     Grit enumerators; I do not think the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman expects us to do so. But we 
     <lb/>
     will appoint men capable of performing the 
     <lb/>
     duties assigned to them. I wish to call at<lb break="no"/>tention to the fact that these enumerators 
     <lb/>
     have to take an oath and have to prepare 
     <lb/>
     their lists under the sanction of that oath. 
     <lb/>
     If the hon. gentleman could produce evi<lb break="no"/>dence that, in the elections of 1887 and 1891 
     <lb/>
     enumerators were appointed who proved de<lb break="no"/>relict in their duty, if he could show that 
     <lb/>
     people were disfranchised as he has given 
     <lb/>
     the House to understand, there might be 
     <lb/>
     something in his argument. But I defy 
     <lb/>
     him to produce the slightest proof that any 
     <lb/>
     person has complained, directly or indirectly. 
     <lb/>
     of the preparation of the lists in 1887 and 
     <lb/>
     and 1891. The hon. gentleman does not 
     <lb/>
     give the same credit that I do to his poli<lb break="no"/>tical allies in the North-west Territories. 
     <lb/>
     He has had no experience of those gentle<lb break="no"/>men. I want him to understand that they 
     <lb/>
     are alive and that they have their organiza<lb break="no"/>tions. I speak of what I know. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. It did not make the slight<lb break="no"/>est difference in 1887 and 1891, because they 
     <lb/>
     could get their names on the lists on elec<lb break="no"/>tion day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. Why, Sir, I have been engaged 
     <lb/>
     in contests up there, and I do not think 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman took part inthem. and 
     <lb/>
     it seems to me that no man ever fought hard<lb break="no"/>er to get their names upon the list and to 
     <lb/>
     elect their candidate than did our Grit 
     <lb/>
     friends in Eastern and Western Assiniboia, 
     <lb/>
     and the other constituencies. This Act. as 
     <lb/>
     it is now amended. does not give any ad<lb break="no"/>vantage to the supporters of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment as against those who are opposed to 
     <lb/>
     the Government, because the enumerator is 
     <lb/>
     bound to take their names. The only conclu<lb break="no"/>sion I can arrive at. when hon. gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     say, "Oh, oh" is that they have a differ<lb break="no"/>ent experience in preparing the lists to what 
     <lb/>
     I have. Are we to understand that those 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen know about how those lists are 
     <lb/>
     prepared, and that they do not do the square 
     <lb/>
     thing when. they prepare the lists ?—because 
     <lb/>
     that is the inference I draw from the re<lb break="no"/>marks made by the hon. gentleman. I take 
     <lb/>
     it that a man who is sworn to do his duty, 
     <lb/>
     will do it, and any opponent of this Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, has under the provisions of the 
     <lb/>
     Act, the very some chance of getting his 
     <lb/>
     name upon the list as does any person who 
     <lb/>
     is a supporter of this Government. Now, Sir, 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman sneered at the enumera<lb break="no"/>tors that would be appointed by the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor General in Council, and shortly after<lb break="no"/>
       
       
            <cb/>
       
       wards he came round and said that of 
     <lb/>
     course he could not object to the Governor 
     <lb/>
     General appointing the friends of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. Well, all that the Act presumes 
     <lb/>
     is that the Governor General shall appoint 
     <lb/>
     men who are fit to make up those. lists. 
     <lb/>
     Now what does all this amount to ? It 
     <lb/>
     amounts simply to this, as I said be<lb break="no"/>fore, that the conditions of that country are 
     <lb/>
     not such as to admit of our extending to it 
     <lb/>
     the provisions of the Franchise Act. In 
     <lb/>
     1894 I introduced a Bill into this House for 
     <lb/>
     the purpose of extending the ballot to the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories, and in that Bill cer<lb break="no"/>tain changes had to be made in the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories Representation Act, but 
     <lb/>
     those changes did not affect materially the 
     <lb/>
     mode of the preparation of those lists, other 
     <lb/>
     than the amendment which was made in 
     <lb/>
     the Senate in repealing clause 44. I think 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman will have to make out 
     <lb/>
     a considerably stronger case than he has 
     <lb/>
     made to-day to prove to this House that 
     <lb/>
     any electors in that country will be affect<lb break="no"/>ed in the slightest degree by the changes 
     <lb/>
     that have been made in the Act, because 
     <lb/>
     so far as the appointment of enumerators 
     <lb/>
     is concerned, and so far as the preparation 
     <lb/>
     of the lists is concerned, they will be pre<lb break="no"/>pared as they were in 1887, and as they 
     <lb/>
     were in 1891, and prepared under legislation 
     <lb/>
     that was passed in this House some ten 
     <lb/>
     years ago. So how could the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man. or how can the legislative assembly. 
     <lb/>
     in the petition.the hon. gentleman read, 
     <lb/>
     say that by the Act that was passed last ses<lb break="no"/>sion or the session before, we seek to disfran<lb break="no"/>chise by wholesale the electors of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories ? Sir, the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     threatened, but he had to withdraw the 
     <lb/>
     threat, that he was going to keep this House 
     <lb/>
     here until such time as he accomplished his 
     <lb/>
     purpose. I want to say to the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman that we do not fear his threats. 
     <lb/>
     We are just as desirous of giving to the 
     <lb/>
     people of the North-west Territories a full 
     <lb/>
     franchise as he is. The hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     says that I went through that country and 
     <lb/>
     saw the people, and in consequence of my 
     <lb/>
     visit I came to the conclusion that if the 
     <lb/>
     provisions of the law remained as they were 
     <lb/>
     we could not expect to get the same re<lb break="no"/>presentation. I want to tell the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman that I do not fear the verdict of 
     <lb/>
     the electors of the North-west Territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) You do not show 
     <lb/>
     any signs of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. I do not show any signs of 
     <lb/>
     it'in the slightest degree. I want to say to 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman that remarks such. as 
     <lb/>
     his are very stale. We heard in 1887 that 
     <lb/>
     the whole North-west representation was 
     <lb/>
     going to be opposed to this Government ; we 
     <lb/>
     heard in 1891 that the whole North-west 
     <lb/>
     representation would go against this Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. But as the North-west people did 
     <lb/>
     in 1887, and as they did in 1891, the North<lb break="no"/>west people will do in 1896, and the hon. 
     <lb/>
      
      
            <pb n="543" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00543.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">543</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">544</fw>
   
   
   
     gentleman will find that we will have a 
     <lb/>
     solid representation here supporting the pol<lb break="no"/>icy of this Government the same as we had 
     <lb/>
     in 1891 and 1887. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. For "this 
     <lb/>
     Government," substitute " the Government," 
     <lb/>
     and you will be right. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. Well, for the Government of 
     <lb/>
     the grand old Conservative party, not a Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of the hon. gentlemen opposite, 
     <lb/>
     because I am sure the hon. gentleman will 
     <lb/>
     be a considerable number of years older 
     <lb/>
     before he sits upon the Treasury benches, 
     <lb/>
     notwithstanding his own inclination to get 
     <lb/>
     there. Now, Sir, I say to the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man that the charge he made against me 
     <lb/>
     that this amendment was made by my con<lb break="no"/>niving with the Senate, I have proved to 
     <lb/>
     be untrue. More than that, I had no thought 
     <lb/>
     or idea, when agreeing to the amendment 
     <lb/>
     that was made in the Senate, that it would 
     <lb/>
     affect in the slightest degree the franchise 
     <lb/>
     of the electors of the North-west Territories ; 
     <lb/>
     more than that, the thought never occurred to 
     <lb/>
     me, and has never occurred to me, nor will 
     <lb/>
     it ever occur to me, until the last ballot is 
     <lb/>
     cast, that the North-west Territories will 
     <lb/>
     give any different verdict from the one 
     <lb/>
     they gave in the elections in 1887 and 1891. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). My hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     from Winnipeg (Mr. Martin) has pointed out, 
     <lb/>
     in the speech which he addressed to the 
     <lb/>
     House, the very serious objections that lie 
     <lb/>
     against the law as it stands at this moment. 
     <lb/>
     He has also pointed out the possibility of 
     <lb/>
     disfranchising a very large number of the 
     <lb/>
     electors of the North-west Territories under 
     <lb/>
     the provisions of the law as it is. What de<lb break="no"/>fence or answer has the Minister made to 
     <lb/>
     that ? Why, the hon. Minister says that 
     <lb/>
     the law as it stood before these objection<lb break="no"/>able amendments were made, worked satis<lb break="no"/>factorily, and he gives that statement as an 
     <lb/>
     answer to the argument of my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     that the law was changed for the worse. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. I said with the one exception. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Well, the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman did not say that he was prepared 
     <lb/>
    to take away that exception, the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman did not say that he was prepared to 
     <lb/>remove any of the objections which the 
     <lb/>hon. member for Winnipeg made to the law 
     <lb/>as it at present stands. The hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>did not say one word that can be regarded 
     <lb/>as an argument in defence of the amend<lb break="no"/>ments that were made in 1894 in the Senate, 
     <lb/>and which were allowed to stand in his 
     <lb/>measure of last session. Sir, if he looks at 
     <lb/>the facts as they are stated, what do they 
     <lb/>disclose ? In the first place, the very objec<lb break="no"/>tionable condition of things exists, which 
     <lb/>the hon. gentleman says is to continue, that 
     <lb/>the Government, who stand as one of the 
     <lb/>parties on trial at an election, are to be 
     <lb/>the persons who are to appoint all the offi<lb break="no"/>cers, who are to create the machinery under 
     <lb/>which their trial is to take place. Sir, 
     <lb/>
           
           
            <cb/>
      
      
     there is no analogy between the condition 
     <lb/>
     of things that exists in Ontario and the con<lb break="no"/>dition of things that exists in the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories. The hon. gentleman said 
     <lb/>
     that we appointed Grits to office where an 
     <lb/>
     opportunity occurs. Why, Sir, has the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of Ontario—and I take that as an 
     <lb/>
     illustration—provided for the appointment 
     <lb/>
    of their own friends under the Fran<lb break="no"/>chise Act for the preparation of the 
     <lb/>voters' list ? Has the Government of On<lb break="no"/>tario provided for the appointment of the 
     <lb/>returning officers who are to hold the elec<lb break="no"/>tions, when those elections take place 
     <lb/>in that province ? No, Sir, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Ontario provided by statute that 
     <lb/>certain officers, some of whom may be their 
     <lb/>friends and some of whom may be their 
     <lb/>opponents, are the persons under whose 
     <lb/>authority and responsibility the elections 
     <lb/>are to be held ; but they also provided that 
     <lb/>the preparation of the voters' lists shall be 
     <lb/>in the hands of the municipality, the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of which are elected by the peopIe 
     <lb/>who represent both parties, and the final 
     <lb/>appeal is to the county judge, that is, when 
     <lb/>a new appointment takes place. by the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment who sit here. Now, look at the 
     <lb/>condition of things in the North-west. The 
     <lb/>hon. gentleman says that they take care to 
     <lb/>appoint no Grits, and he says His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency makes the appointments, and therefore 
     <lb/>they will be proper appointments. Sir, the 
     <lb/>hon. gentleman might as well refer to the 
     <lb/>Lieutenant-Governor as a conclusive answer 
     <lb/>to the character of appointments every<lb break="no"/>where. His Excellency, it is true, makes 
     <lb/>those appointments, but he does not choose 
     <lb/>the men. The men are chosen by the hon. 
     <lb/>gentlemen ; they are named by the hon. 
     <lb/>gentlemen, and it is upon their responsi<lb break="no"/>bility thatthe appoinnments are made. The 
     <lb/>hon. gentleman may appoint in the North<lb break="no"/>west, as he or his friends have done else<lb break="no"/>where, bankrupts to office in elections, where 
     <lb/>it is known that if improper conduct takes 
     <lb/>place, no prosecution can be successfully 
     <lb/>had against them. That is the position 
     <lb/>which the hon. gentleman and his friends 
     <lb/>have practically taken, and he has referred 
     <lb/>us to His Excellency, whose name ought 
     <lb/>never to have ben dragged into a discussion 
     <lb/>in this House, as a guarantee that the ap<lb break="no"/>pointments will be all right and proper. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. I rise to an explanation. I do 
     <lb/>
     not see why the hon. gentleman should state 
     <lb/>
     that I brought His Excellency's name into 
     <lb/>
     this discussion. I mentioned the name of 
     <lb/>
     the Governor General as given in the Act, 
     <lb/>
     and a child understands that it means the 
     <lb/>
     Governor General in Council. I never men<lb break="no"/>tioned the name of His Excellency. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man will see, when he reads the report of 
     <lb/>
     his speech, that I am not misrepresenting 
     <lb/>
     him, and that I am not stating what he 
     <lb/>
     did not say on this occasion. What is the 
     <lb/>
     objection made by my hon. friend ? It is, 
     <lb/>
  
  
            <pb n="545" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00545.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">545</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 23, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">546</fw>
       
       
     that by the alteration of the law it placed 
     <lb/>
     in the hands of the enumerator or revising 
     <lb/>
     officer, where there is one, power to disfran<lb break="no"/>chise a portion of the population. Under the 
     <lb/>
     law, as cited, if a man's name is excised 
     <lb/>
    improperly, he could, go before the enumera<lb break="no"/>tor on the day of polling, he could swear 
     <lb/>that he was entitled to have his name on 
     <lb/>the list, he could have it placed on the list 
     <lb/>by the enumerator, and he could there<lb break="no"/>after record his vote. Can he do that<lb/>to-day ? If his name is left off the list, or 
     <lb/>struck off the list, can he go and vote ? 
     <lb/>Everybody knows that he  cannot do so. 
     <lb/>And the hon. gentlemen, by changes made 
     <lb/>by the Senate in a law affecting this House, 
     <lb/>know the position of the matter is this : 
     <lb/>that the party stands in a wholly different 
     <lb/>position from that which he occupied before. 
     <lb/>Why, an unscrupulous enumerator or an un<lb break="no"/>scrupulous revising officer would not under<lb break="no"/>take to excise a name from the list, or leave  
     <lb/>it out after promising to place it there, if 
     <lb/>he thought that the party on the day of 
     <lb/>election would find a fraud had been prac<lb break="no"/>tised, and he could still have his name 
     <lb/>placed on the list and still record his vote. 
     <lb/>There would be no motive under that pro<lb break="no"/>vision of the Act for improper and fraud<lb break="no"/>ulent conduct. But does it stand so to<lb break="no"/>day ; is that the position of the question at<lb/>this moment? No. If a revising officer 
     <lb/>or an enumerator leaves a name off the list,  
     <lb/>and tells the party that he is entitled to 
     <lb/>vote, and that he will place his name on the  
     <lb/>list, and the man goes to the poll and finds 
     <lb/>his name not there, is he entitled to have 
     <lb/>his name on the list and have it then and 
     <lb/>there recorded ? No. He will be told that 
     <lb/>he should have come and had his name add<lb break="no"/>ed two days before. The opportunity is taken  
     <lb/>away ; the temptation to fraud is created for  
     <lb/>the first time, and the list will be not only 
     <lb/>improperly made but it will be full of  
     <lb/>defects, and errors, and omissions, which 
     <lb/>cannot be corrected. The hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>(Mr. Daly)  has said the position of the 
     <lb/>North-west is peculiar, and that he cannot 
     <lb/>apply there the law as it exists in the older 
     <lb/>provinces of the Dominion. I do not dis<lb break="no"/>pute that such may be the case. It may 
     <lb/>be necessary to make special provision for 
     <lb/>the conditions existing in the Territories ; 
     <lb/>but those should be rational conditions. and 
     <lb/>they should be such as to secure the rights 
     <lb/>and privileges of the electors, and not be 
     <lb/>framed for the purpose of taking them away. 
     <lb/>That is the condition of things now exist<lb break="no"/>ing. Men will lose their right to vote—the 
     <lb/>number of voters will be diminished. On 
     <lb/>whose representation are enumerators or 
     <lb/>revising officers appointed ? Upon the repre<lb break="no"/>sentation of the candidates which support 
     <lb/>the Administration, upon the representation 
     <lb/>of gentlemen who for the time being are 
     <lb/>sitting in this House, in so far as they be<lb break="no"/>come candidates again. Is not every officer 
     <lb/>so appointed friendly to them, and though 
     <lb/>the emolument may be small, nevertheless in 
     <lb/>
        
        
            <cb/>
    

        
        
     that country it may be important, and be 
     <lb/>
     sufficient to place these officers under obliga<lb break="no"/>tions to these men. Will they not undertake 
     <lb/>
     to promote their interest ? Will they not feel 
     <lb/>
     that in looking after friends of the candi<lb break="no"/>dates and neglecting applications made by 
     <lb/>
     opponents, they are not doing an improper 
     <lb/>
     act ? They may feel it is none of their busi<lb break="no"/>ness to see that names of persons hostile 
     <lb/>
     to the Administration are placed on the list. 
     <lb/>
     Was the condition of things such that 
     <lb/>
     the list would be full and fair, and 
     <lb/>
     the election an honest and free ex<lb break="no"/>pression of public opinion ? At all 
     <lb/>
     events, the evil has been enormously 
     <lb/>
     aggravated. Under the pretense of having 
     <lb/>
     an innocent provision added to the law, 
     <lb/>
     serious injustice has been done to a large 
     <lb/>
      section of the population, and power is given 
     <lb/>
     to effect serious frauds against which no 
     <lb/>
     remedy can be applied. You may prosecute 
     <lb/>
     a man elsewhere, if he has property which  
     <lb/>
     you can seize or reach, for the misconduct, 
     <lb/>
     but where you require no security of any 
     <lb/>
     kind, where you attach no penalties of any 
     <lb/>
     sort, the House should be specially careful 
     <lb/>
     to guard the interests, rights and privileges  
     <lb/>
     of the electors of the North-west ; but you 
     <lb/>
     destroy every guard, you throw down every 
     <lb/>
     barrier that stands as an obstacle to fraud 
     <lb/>
     and wrong-doing, and the result is that hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen opposite have created a state 
     <lb/>
     of things under the law that will prevent a 
     <lb/>
     free and full expression of the opinion of 
     <lb/>
     the electors in that country. That is a con<lb break="no"/>dition that should not exist. It is not credit<lb break="no"/>able to this House if it permits it to stand ; 
     <lb/>
     and it was an indignity to this House, that 
     <lb/>
     such matters which specially concerned its 
     <lb/>
     own rights and privileges and the represen<lb break="no"/>tation of the people there should have been 
     <lb/>
     dealt with primarily in the Senate and not 
     <lb/>
     in this House of Commons. It is clear to 
     <lb/>
     any one who takes the trouble to look at  
     <lb/>
     the law that the law is seriously defective, 
     <lb/>
     that the amendment suggested by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Winnipeg (Mr. Martin) should 
     <lb/>
     be made, and that full opportunity should 
     <lb/>
     be given to have as full and complete a 
     <lb/>
     voters' list in that country as can be pre<lb break="no"/>pared under the circumstances, and that an 
     <lb/>
      honest and fair opportunity should be given 
     <lb/>
      to the people to elect those candidates whom 
     <lb/>
     they prefer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) I think the import<lb break="no"/>ance of the subject is such as to justify me 
     <lb/>
     in calling the attention of the House to it 
     <lb/>
    for a few moments longer, although I am 
     <lb/>free to admit that the hon. gentleman who 
     <lb/>has just preceded me (Mr. Mills) has pre<lb break="no"/>sented it quite as forcibly as I can hope to 
     <lb/>do, and I only plead as an excuse for my 
     <lb/>observations the great importance and se<lb break="no"/>rious character of the Bill before the House. 
     <lb/>I am absolutely certain in my own mind 
     <lb/>that if hon. gentlemen on both sides of the  
     <lb/>House would give time and attention to the  
     <lb/>question before it for a few moments, they 
     <lb/>
        
        
            <pb n="547" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00547.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">547</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">548</fw>
   
   
     would all agree that injustice has been done. 
     <lb/>
     I am not going to discuss the ancillary point, 
     <lb/>
     as to whether the Minister of the Interior 
     <lb/>
      was or was not responsible for the change 
     <lb/>
     made. He said he was not, and we accept 
     <lb/>
     his denial. We start out with the fact that 
     <lb/>
     an Act was passed ten years ago for the 
     <lb/>
     preparation of voters' lists in the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories. The circumstances of the 
     <lb/>
     country are exceptional, and every hon. 
     <lb/>
     member will at once recognize that it was 
     <lb/>
     rather a crude scheme which was proposed 
     <lb/>
     and suggested, but still it was one which 
     <lb/>
     practically worked pretty well. The Min<lb break="no"/>ister of the Interior pledges his own ex<lb break="no"/>perience in the House and his responsibility 
     <lb/>
     as a Minister, that the Act passed ten years 
     <lb/>
     ago worked passably well in two elections 
     <lb/>
     and that he for one never heard any com<lb break="no"/>plaint about it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. About the preparation of the 
     <lb/>lists.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) The House will 
     <lb/>
     understand that my hon. friend (Mr. 
     <lb/>
    Martin) is simply seeking to put the Act in 
     <lb/>the same position as it was when the Min<lb break="no"/>ister of the Interior said it worked so well. 
     <lb/>The Act vests arbitrary and extraordinary 
     <lb/>powers in the enumerators. An opportunity 
     <lb/>is given to those persons whose names are 
     <lb/>omitted, or to those who think names are 
     <lb/>improperly on, to go to that enumerator 
     <lb/>and to have the omitted names put on or the 
     <lb/>wrong names taken eoff. There is large room 
     <lb/>even there for arbitrary and improper con<lb break="no"/>duct on the part of the enumerator. There 
     <lb/>is large room for partiality and bias and 
     <lb/>prejudices to exhibit themselves. There is 
     <lb/>room there to make a list which may favour 
     <lb/>one side much more than the other. But, 
     <lb/>there was a clause inserted in the Act as 
     <lb/>it existed before the amendment which was 
     <lb/>intended to prevent, if possible, and to over<lb break="no"/>come that evil. That clause was, that if any<lb break="no"/>body was improperly struck off the list 
     <lb/>who was a duly qualified voter he could 
     <lb/>on election day take the oath that he was 
     <lb/>qualified, and be entitled to vote, even if 
     <lb/>a partisan enumerator left him off. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. You cannot do that in 
     <lb/>
     any part of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) My hon. friend (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Sproule) is right, but the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     will see that the Electoral Franchise Act 
     <lb/>
     of the rest of Canada was not applied to the 
     <lb/>
     Territories, that a special law was made 
     <lb/>
     for these Territories alone, and that that 
     <lb/>
     law as it formerly existed, while vesting 
     <lb/>
     extraordinary powers in the enumerator, 
     <lb/>
     had one security to the qualified voter, 
     <lb/>
     namely, that if his name was by accident 
     <lb/>
     or design omitted he could on election day 
     <lb/>
    vote on taking the oath. Now, why was 
     <lb/>that provision struck out ? The Government 
     <lb/> did not advise that it should be struck out ; 
     <lb/> nor did the Government bring a Bill to this 
     <lb/>House and ask that it should be struck out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
       
       
            <cb/>
            <p>
     It was not discussed in the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons, but an amendment—not setting out 
     <lb/>
     what the object of the amendment was—but 
     <lb/>
     simply mentioning among the clauses that 
     <lb/>
     were to be repealed " clause 4 " was insert<lb break="no"/>ed by the Senate. No human being unless 
     <lb/>
     he followed the legislation of this House 
     <lb/>
     most closely, would ever discover what the 
     <lb/>
     object of that was. He would have to get 
     <lb/>
     the original North-west Territories Repre<lb break="no"/>sentation Act, and the amendment, and read 
     <lb/>
     over section 44 to see what the clause was, 
     <lb/>
      which they were seeking to eliminate from 
     <lb/>
     the Act. Who asked the Senate to do that ? 
     <lb/>
     Was there a petition from any one in the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest Territories ; there was  none pre<lb break="no"/>sented to this House. What right has the 
     <lb/>
     Senate—legal and technical right it may 
     <lb/>
     have had—to amend Bills passed by this 
     <lb/>
     House providing for the representation of 
     <lb/>
     members here ? I submit it is not fair that 
     <lb/>
     Bills which pass this House providing for 
     <lb/>
     representation in this House, should be 
     <lb/>
     amended in the Senate ; unless it is on oc<lb break="no"/>casions where some important omissions 
     <lb/>
     have been made and they are solicited to do 
     <lb/>
     so by the Government or by some person 
     <lb/>
     promoting the Bill. This amendment was 
     <lb/>
     slid in and no one knew anything about it. 
     <lb/>
     But we need not discuss bygones here 
     <lb/>
     to-day. The question is: That a great evil 
     <lb/>
     having been committed are we prepared to 
     <lb/>
     remedy it ? The hon. gentleman (Mr. Daly) 
     <lb/>
     asks us to assume that all the enumerators 
     <lb/>
     will do even-handed justice. He knows 
     <lb/>
     well, and every member of this House 
     <lb/>
     knows, that of the two or three hundred 
     <lb/>
     revisers appointed to revise the lists 
     <lb/>
     throughout Canada, with all the security 
     <lb/>
     given by the fact that many of them are 
     <lb/>
     judges and lawyers, it takes an immense 
     <lb/>
     deal of time and money to make even an 
     <lb/>
     approximately accurate list. In the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories you have no revision at all, 
     <lb/>
     but suddenly, after the writ is out the 
     <lb/>
     enumerator is asked to make a list. He 
     <lb/>
     posts that list. One of his friends goes to 
     <lb/>
     him and asks that his name should be put 
     <lb/>
     on, and he can arbitrarily refuse to do it 
     <lb/>
     if he likes, or he may tell the man he will 
     <lb/>
     do it and when the man turns his back, 
     <lb/>
     he does not do it. There is no security to 
     <lb/>
     the voter. There is no court held, no means 
     <lb/>
     of compelling the enumerator to put it on. 
     <lb/>
     The one and only safeguard the electors 
     <lb/>
     had was, that if their names were omitted 
     <lb/>
     by the enumerator, they could go to the polls 
     <lb/>
     on election day and by pledging their oaths 
     <lb/>
     exercise their right to vote. The Minister 
     <lb/>
     of the Interior says that that provision 
     <lb/>
     worked admirably well, and he challenges 
     <lb/>
     criticism upon the practical working of that 
     <lb/>
     Act. I am willing to accept his statement 
     <lb/>
     that the Act as it did stand worked practi<lb break="no"/>cally fairly well, but what we are seeking 
     <lb/>
     to do now is to put back that safeguard 
     <lb/>
     and put the Act where it was before the 
     <lb/>
     Senate foolishly amended it, we propose to 
     <lb/>
     restore the security to the electors which they 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="549" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00549.jpg"/>
         
         
     <fw type="num">549</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 23, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">550</fw> 
    
    
     formerly had, and which they are now 
     <lb/>
     deprived of. If hon. gentlemen find that the 
     <lb/>
      Bill proposed by my hon. friend (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Martin) has the unanimous endorsement of 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Assembly, then I say the 
     <lb/>
     last vestige of opposition to the proposal 
     <lb/>
     should vanish. Why, Sir, I hold in my 
     <lb/>
     hands a resolution which was moved in the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Assembly by Mr. lnsinger, 
     <lb/>
     which after reciting all the circumstances 
     <lb/>
     calls attention to the fact that this Act. 
     <lb/>
     passed in 1894, practically made the voters' 
     <lb/>
    lists final as fixed by the enumerators and 
     <lb/>excluded from the right of the franchise 
     <lb/>every man whose name was not on that 
     <lb/>list two days before the election. The re<lb break="no"/>solution gives the following reasons why the  
     <lb/>Act as it now stands does not offer 
     <lb/>same safeguard to the rights of electors, 
     <lb/>as the voters' lists in the provinces do. It 
     <lb/>says :  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">            
      
      <p>
     And whereas such lists of voters do not offer the 
     <lb/>
    same safeguards to the rights of electors as do 
     <lb/>the voters in the provinces, inasmuch<lb/>as,-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>(1) They are necessarily hurriedly prepared 
     <lb/>
     by enumerators between the time of the 
     <lb/>
    receipt of the writ for election and a week 
     <lb/>before the day of polling ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     (2) The time allowed to electors or their 
     <lb/>
     agents to ascertain if their names are on 
     <lb/>
     such list is, taken in cennection with the 
     <lb/>
     distances generally to be travelled in the 
     <lb/>
     Territories, and with the fact that no fixed 
     <lb/>
    residences are appointed for such enumer<lb break="no"/>ators, insufficient for the purpose ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     (3) The enumerator is absolute judge of the 
     <lb/>
     right of an elector to be on such list, and 
     <lb/>
     he can put on or strike off names till with<lb break="no"/>in two days of the polling day, without 
     <lb/>
     notice from or to such electors ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     (4) There is no appeal from the decision of 
     <lb/>
     the enumerator, either to a revising officer 
     <lb/>
     or to a judge. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     After giving these cogent and to my mind 
     <lb/>
     unanswerable reasons why the amendment 
     <lb/>
     made by the Senate is an unfortunate 
     <lb/>
     amendment which should be rectified at the 
     <lb/>
     earliest possible moment, the resolution 
     <lb/>
     winds up with the following :—  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Therefore, in the opinion of this assembly it is 
     <lb/>
     desirable that the " North-west Territories Re<lb break="no"/>presentation Act " be further amended so as to 
     <lb/>
     either adopt the system provided for in the 
     <lb/>
     "Territories Election Ordinances," or to bring 
     <lb/>
     into effect the provisions regarding voters' lists 
     <lb/>
     in the " Electoral Franchise Act." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     That system of enabling a man to vote on 
     <lb/>
     election day by pledging his oath when his 
     <lb/>
     right to vote is challenged prevails in other 
     <lb/>
     provinces outside of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tory. In the province from which I come, 
     <lb/>
     in all the local elections, if the right to vote 
     <lb/>
     of any duly qualified elector is challenged, 
     <lb/>
     he can, by taking the necessary oath, poll 
     <lb/>
     his vote, and it has been found to work 
     <lb/>
     practically very well. The neighbours all 
     <lb/>
     around know whether the man is qualified 
     <lb/>
     or not and if he perjures himself he can be 
     <lb/>
     punished. In this case, Sir, you have the 
     <lb/>
     whole North-west Assembly, irrespective of 
     <lb/>


            <cb/>
    

         
         
      politics, invoking the aid of this House to 
     <lb/>
      restore to the electors of the North-west the 
     <lb/>
     rights and privileges which they possessed 
     <lb/>
     before the Senate amendments took them 
     <lb/>
     away. My hon. friend (Mr. Martin) has 
     <lb/>
     proposed a Bill to carry out that wish. I 
     <lb/>
     was glad to hear from the remarks of the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of the Interior, that he has not 
     <lb/>
     yet made up his mind to oppose the Bill of 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend (Mr. Martin), that he has 
     <lb/>
     not made up his mind yet. that he will 
     <lb/>
     not restore to the electors the privileges 
     <lb/>
     and rights which they possessed before. 
     <lb/>
     It boots not, Sir, to cite the fact that in 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba, as the hon. gentleman said, or 
     <lb/>
     in Nova Scotia, as another hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     said, there are evils existing in the electoral 
     <lb/>
     laws. We have nothing to do with that. 
     <lb/>
     If wrong was done elsewhere, it does not 
     <lb/>
     justify wrong being done here ; two wrongs 
     <lb/>
     do not make a right. We are dealing with 
     <lb/>
     the fact that a grievous wrong has been 
     <lb/>
     committed- wrong capable of being used 
     <lb/>
     by improper officers to such an extent as 
     <lb/>
     to almost disfranchise a majority of the 
     <lb/>
      electors in any one district. It is a wrong 
     <lb/>
      that would not be tolerated in any part of 
     <lb/>
     Canada outside of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, and, if I know the men there, from 
     <lb/>
      what I have seen of them, they are not the 
     <lb/>
     men to tolerate it, either ; and when we 
     <lb/>
     have the whole North-west Assembly  en<lb break="no"/>tering a public protest against that wrong, 
     <lb/>
     and asking Parliament to remedy it, I say 
     <lb/>
     that it is time that we should rise to the 
     <lb/>
     occasion, irrespective of party feeling or 
     <lb/>
     party affiliation, and determine that the 
     <lb/>
     wrong shall be rectified at the first oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity. My hon. friend from Winnipeg (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Martin) was called to order for threatening 
     <lb/>
     to obstruct the business of this House un<lb break="no"/>less this were done. His words were 
     <lb/>
     stronger than the rules of the House justi<lb break="no"/>fied, but nobody doubts that the action he 
     <lb/>
     proposed to take would have been justified 
     <lb/>
     by the facts. Is it not absolutely intoler<lb break="no"/>able that four districts which send members 
     <lb/>
     to this House should be absolutely and 
     <lb/>
     entirely in the hands of the nominees of 
     <lb/>
     the Government ? Why, Sir, the fact only 
     <lb/>
     needs to be mentioned to excite horror, 
     <lb/>
     surprise and indignation ; and I am satis<lb break="no"/>fied that hon. members, if they calmly and 
     <lb/>
     coolly consider the matter, will repeal the 
     <lb/>
     ill-advised action of the Senate, and place 
     <lb/>
     the electors of the North-west in exactly 
     <lb/>
     the same position they were in before the 
     <lb/>
     Act of 1894 was passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Mr. Speaker, some days be<lb break="no"/>fore the hon. member for Winnipeg (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Martin) arrived here, and before I had any 
     <lb/>
     knowledge that he intended to move in this 
     <lb/>
     matter, I went to the Clerk and gave him a 
     <lb/>
     sketch of a Bill dealing with this matter ; 
     <lb/>
     and as soon as he told me that the Bill 
     <lb/>
     was prepared, I gave notice that, I would 
     <lb/>
     move for leave to introduce it. I think, 
     <lb/>
     Sir, that a great deal more has been made 
     <lb/>
     of this than there was any reason for. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <pb n="551" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00551.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">551</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">552</fw>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. What direction does your<lb/>Bill move in ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. It moves in the direction of<lb/>repealing the legislation of 1894 and 1895,<lb/>and reviving the legislation of 1886. My<lb/>hon. friend from Winnipeg was most unjust<lb/>in the strong attack, as it seems to me it<lb/>may be called, which he made on my hon.<lb/>friend the Minister of the Interior. If ever<lb/>a man was innocent, my hon. friend the<lb/>Minister of the Interior was innocent of<lb/>introducing this clause. After I have<lb/>calmly laid before the House what the law<lb/>was, and how the change came about, I<lb/>rather think the House will see that a great<lb/>deal more has been made of this matter<lb/>than was necessary. My hon. friend the<lb/>Minister of the Interior was quite right in<lb/>saying that in 1887 and in 1891, the law,<lb/>as it was passed in 1886, worked well. In<lb/>my own constituency I did not hear a<lb/>single complaint against the working of<lb/>that law. But that was not the case in<lb/>some other constituencies. In the constitu<lb break="no"/>ency of my hon. friend from Eastern As<lb break="no"/>siniboia (Mr. McDonald), I have been told<lb/>by him and by others, 107 names were<lb/>sworn on the list improperly. In 1894 cer<lb break="no"/>tain gentlemen from the North-west who<lb/>took an interest in politics, and were<lb/>strongly impressed that a wrong had been<lb/>done by those unscrupulous persons swear<lb break="no"/>ing themselves on the list, urged that a<lb/>change should be made in the direction<lb/>which the reform of the law took in 1894 ;<lb/>and an amendment to that effect was placed<lb/>in my hands when the Bill of 1894 was pass<lb break="no"/>ing through the House. I read the amend<lb break="no"/>ment at that time, and while I did not take<lb/>such a strong view of it as is taken by<lb/>hon. gentlemen who have spoken to-day, I<lb/>came to the conclusion that it was undesir<lb break="no"/>able to make such a change, and I did not<lb/>move in the matter. I know I never<lb/>brought it to the attention of the Minister<lb/>of the Interior. That is all I know about<lb/>it. When the Bill came down, it appeared<lb/>that those gentlemen who were interested<lb/>in the matter had moved in it in the Sen<lb break="no"/>ate, and the change had been made there.<lb/>Now, Sir, the change that was made is simply<lb/>this—that instead of a man having the<lb/>power to go on the day of election and make<lb/>an affidavit that he has the qualification en<lb break="no"/>titling him to vote, he can have his name<lb/>put on that list up to two days before the<lb/>election, by appealing to the enumerator,<lb/>should it prove not to be there.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. I beg pardon. There is <lb/>no such provision. It is quite impossible<lb/>to get his name on the list unless the enum<lb break="no"/>erator is willing to put it there.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I think my hon. friend is<lb/>wrong. Up to two days before the election<lb/>he can appeal to the enumerator, and have<lb/>his name put on the list.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. Suppose the enumerator<lb/>refuses ?<lb/>
            </p>
          
          
            <cb/>
           
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. My hon. friend does not un<lb break="no"/>derstand the men in the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. No enumerator there would behave<lb/>in that manner. I quite agree that a critic,<lb/>looking at the legislation as it is, might<lb/>very properly see ground for alarm ; but,<lb/>knowing as I do the districts and the peo<lb break="no"/>ple, and the public criticism under which<lb/>the enumerators would act, I do not ap<lb break="no"/>prehend any such dangers as the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Queen's (Mr. Davies) and the hon.<lb/>member for Bothwell (Mr. Mills) antici<lb break="no"/>pate ; if I did, I would have moved in this<lb/>matter before. But, Sir, there are persons<lb/>in the Territories who do think there is some<lb/>danger, and I grant you that a check on<lb/>the enumerator has been taken away. Un<lb break="no"/>der the circumstances, I am inclined to<lb/>think that it is not worth debating in this<lb/>House for five minutes. I do not believe<lb/>that the change which my Bill and that of<lb/>the hon. member for Winnipeg contemplate<lb/>will affect a single vote in any constituency.<lb/>But if there is any feeling on the eve of<lb/>election amongst any portion of the com<lb break="no"/>munity—I do not care what side of poli<lb break="no"/>tics they belong to—that a check on the<lb/>enumerator had been taken away and that<lb/>somehow the elector was put in a worse posi<lb break="no"/>tion than he was in before it is not a mat<lb break="no"/>ter we should quarrel about in this House,<lb/>and the best way is to get rid of all cause<lb/>for alarm.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. I congratulate the hon.<lb/>member for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin)<lb/>on the tone of his remarks, and I only rise<lb/>now to supplement something that fell from<lb/>the lips of the hon. member for Queen's,<lb/>P.E.I. (Mr. Davies), and I would ask the<lb/>attention of the Hon. Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior for one minute. It appears that the<lb/>Bill complained of was passed through this<lb/>House without much, if any, publicity. I<lb/>think we may admit that its conditions<lb/>were not known to the public intended to<lb/>be affected.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. Is the hon. gentleman re<lb break="no"/>ferring to the Bill or to the Senate amend<lb break="no"/>ments ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. I am speaking of what<lb/>became of the Senate amendments.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. They came down in the day<lb/>time and were discussed in the day time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. I am not referring to<lb/>anything which occurred in the House.<lb/>What I say is that the people of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories learned nothing of this pro<lb break="no"/>position until it was incorporated in the<lb/>statutes, and we have evidence now that<lb/>the people of the Territories are in favour<lb/>of a return to the old law, or, at all event,<lb/>against the continuance of the present<lb/>law. The opinion in the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories is against the law of 1895. That is<lb/>proved by the unanimous resolution of the<lb/>North-west Territories legislature, and also<lb/>by the remarks of my hon. friend from<lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="553" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00553.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">553</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 23, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">554</fw>
     
     
     West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin). It is prob<lb break="no"/>able also that if other hon. gentlemen re<lb break="no"/>presenting the Territories were to give the<lb/>results of their knowledge of public opin<lb break="no"/>ion, they would corroborate what has been<lb/>said by the hon. member for Winnipeg. 
     <lb/>
     My hon. friend from Queen's has suggest<lb break="no"/>ed that. under the circumstances, it is the 
     <lb/>
     duty of the Minister of the Interior to place 
     <lb/>
     no opposition in the way of the measure 
     <lb/>
     proposed by the hon. member for Winni<lb break="no"/>peg. I go further. I think it is his positive 
     <lb/>
     duty—not a merely negative one—to make 
     <lb/>
     this a Government Bill. It was through 
     <lb/>
     the Bill which the Minister of the Interior 
     <lb/>
     introduced that the law get tangled up as 
     <lb/>
     it is, and it is his duty, as a member of 
     <lb/>
     the Government, to adopt this proposed leg<lb break="no"/>islation with the view of having the law 
     <lb/>
     framed so as to meet public opinion in the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories. We all know that 
     <lb/>
     a private member can scarcely expect to 
     <lb/>
     get a public Bill through this House, and 
     <lb/>
     I would venture to say that despite all a; 
     <lb/>
     member can do. there is not the slightest; 
     <lb/>
     chance of a public measure introduced by 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for Winnipeg, or, for the 
     <lb/>
     matter of that, by the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     West Assiniboia. becoming law. The only 
     <lb/>
     way by which this wrong can be redressed 
     <lb/>
    is by action on the part of the Government, 
     <lb/>and I therefore rise to suggest to the Min<lb break="no"/>ister of the interior that it is the duty of 
     <lb/>the Government to undo their mistake by 
     <lb/>seeing that the proper safeguards are secur<lb break="no"/>ed to the electorate before the election of 
     <lb/>1896 comes on. If they do less than that, 
     <lb/>they will fail to do an imperative duty de<lb break="no"/>volving on them. This discussion, this 
     <lb/>waste of public time, occasioned by hasty 
     <lb/>legislation, is an illustration of the manner 
     <lb/>in which, of late years, important measures 
     <lb/>affecting Parliament and affecting the pub<lb break="no"/>lic has been allowed to go through this 
     <lb/>House. We have seen, every session, im<lb break="no"/>portant legislation put through at the last 
     <lb/>days of the session when there was scarce<lb break="no"/>ly a quorum present. We have seen millions 
     <lb/>of dollars voted away on bonuses. We have 
     <lb/>seen most impor ant pieces of legislatioug 
     <lb/>put on the statute-book when but a small 
     <lb/>percentage of the people's representatives 
     <lb/>were here in Parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCLE5">Mr. McLENNAN</persName>. They should be here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. I admit that, but the cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances are such that many hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men find it impossible to remain there. I 
     <lb/>
     was not one of the absent, because I took 
     <lb/>
     exception, in 1895, to the very clause which 
     <lb/>
     has been the subject of discussion to-day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. I want. to relieve the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman from any responsibility on his 
     <lb/>
     part, and other hon. gentlemen on that side 
     <lb/>
     from any responsibility on their part, 
     <lb/>
    through absence from the House. These 
     <lb/>amendments were agreed to one month be<lb break="no"/>fore the session closed. The session did<lb/>not close until the latter portion of July,<lb/>
     
     
            <cb/>
       
       
     and these amendments were agreed to in<lb/>June, one month before the session expired,<lb/>and, according to the records of the House,<lb/>every member of the Opposition must have<lb/>been present, because they all voted on a<lb/>division. There was, therefore, no snap 
     <lb/>
     division by the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. DAVIES</persName>. How is it, it was not 
     <lb/>
     known ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. I do not know. It is for you 
     <lb/>
     to explain that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man never explained. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. I had not the opportunity. 
     <lb/>
     I do not know that I was in the House 
     <lb/>
     when the Bill went through. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I spoke to Sir John Thomp<lb break="no"/>son on the subject, who had charge of the 
     <lb/>
     Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. I was absent from the House 
     <lb/>
     at the time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. No; the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     was in the House and took part in putting 
     <lb/>
     through the amendments from the Senate. 
     <lb/>
     This House prorogued on the 22nd July, 
     <lb/>
    and the Bill was put through on the 26th 
     <lb/>June, that is twenty-three days before pro<lb break="no"/>rogation. The hon. gentleman will remem<lb break="no"/>ber that the session of last year was called 
     <lb/>at probably the most inconvenient period 
     <lb/>that could have been selected. It was call<lb break="no"/>ed at a time when we should have been 
     <lb/>preroguing instead of convening. In the 
     <lb/>month of June, the attendance was slim, 
     <lb/>and the early part of July there were many 
     <lb/>days when scarcely a quorum was present. 
     <lb/>Towards the close, there were times when 
     <lb/>there were not over twenty members pre<lb break="no"/>sent out of the two hundred. While there 
     <lb/>was not such a limited attendance when 
     <lb/>these amendments were passed, still, the 
     <lb/>attendance was very small, indeed, and the 
     <lb/>law which got embodied on the statute- 
     <lb break="yes"/>book had not the sanction of the majority 
     <lb/>of the people's representatives in Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. It was unknown to the people who 
     <lb/>were to be affected. and certainly a most 
     <lb/>irresistible case has been made out for the 
     <lb/>repeal of this measure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. I desire to say a few 
     <lb/>
    words in reply to what has fallen from the 
     <lb/>hon. Minister of the Interior, because he 
     <lb/>resents the suggestion which I made that 
     <lb/>he is to blame for the law as it now stands. 
     <lb/>If only such matters as occurred in 1894 
     <lb/>were in issue. I would be quite prepared to 
     <lb/>accept his statement ; but my charges 
     <lb/>against him were not based on wnat hap<lb break="no"/>pened in 1894 alone, but upon the fact that 
     <lb/>this amendment was brought to his atten<lb break="no"/>tion last session, in 1895, when he was ask<lb break="no"/>ed to make this wrong right. He himself 
     <lb/>was then obliged to introduce a second Bill<lb/>to this House in order to correct some trifl<lb break="no"/>ing errors in his Bill of 1894, because,<lb/>
     
     
            <pb n="555" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00555.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">555</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">556</fw>
          
          
     strange to say, the Bill of 1894, while pro<lb break="no"/>viding that no one could get his name upon 
     <lb/>
     the list on election day, provided that 
     <lb/>
     notices should be stuck up in the polling 
     <lb/>
     division notifying the electors that they 
     <lb/>
     could apply to have their names put upon 
     <lb/>
     the voters' lists, even on the last day, so 
     <lb/>
     that the hon. gentleman was obliged, on 
     <lb/>
     account of this inconsistency and error 
     <lb/>
     in his 1894 Act, to come again in 1895 
     <lb/>
     and ask to have the change made. 
     <lb/>
     It was only when the Bill came up for 
     <lb/>
     discussion, and only upon the third reading 
     <lb/>
     of it, that members on this side learned of 
     <lb/>
     the change that was made in 1894. And a 
     <lb/>
     very strong appeal was then made by the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Bothwell (Mr. Mills) to 
     <lb/>
     the Minister of the Interior to right the out<lb break="no"/>rage that had been perpetrated. More than 
     <lb/>
     that, I went to the hon. Minister in his seat 
     <lb/>
     and discussed the matter with him and urged 
     <lb/>
     him very strongly, as a matter of fair-play 
     <lb/>
     to the Liberals in the Territories, not to in<lb break="no"/>sist upon this change in the old law. But he 
     <lb/>
     took a firm stand, and said it was the policy 
     <lb/>
     of the Government to insist upon the Act 
     <lb/>
     as it had been amended. So I think the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for West Assiniboia (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Davin) was not justified in finding fault 
     <lb/>
     with me for putting the case against the 
     <lb/>
     hon. Minister as I did. The hon. Minister 
     <lb/>
     assumed the responsibility of the change at 
     <lb/>
     that time, and he defends it today. And 
     <lb/>
     for what purpose ? What other purpose can 
     <lb/>
     there be than that I suggest ? It is ad<lb break="no"/>mitted, it must be admitted by everybody 
     <lb/>
     who considers the matter, that, under the 
     <lb/>
     law as it is at present, it is possible for the 
     <lb/>
     most gigantic frauds to be perpetrated in 
     <lb/>
     these elections. As I have said, it is pos<lb break="no"/>sible for the Government to elect every mem<lb break="no"/>ber for the North-west: Territories in the 
     <lb/>
     next general election, through the operation 
     <lb/>
     of this changed law. The hon. Minister, of 
     <lb/>
     course. repudiates the suggestion that he in<lb break="no"/>tends to do any such thing. If he has no 
     <lb/>
     such intention, why, then, does he take the 
     <lb/>
     power to do it ? He offers only one reason 
     <lb/>
     and that is that, in 1891, under the old law, 
     <lb/>
     certain frauds were perpetrated. If that is 
     <lb/>
     all, let him make some change which will 
     <lb/>
     right the wrong he speaks of, without taking 
     <lb/>
     the power to inflict this great wrong upon 
     <lb/>
     us. Surely, he can remedy one without 
     <lb/>
     causing the other. Let the hon. Minister 
     <lb/>
     take any course he likes, but I am going to 
     <lb/>
     protest, as I said before, against the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment taking into their hands the power they 
     <lb/>
     have under this Act. And I hold the hon. 
     <lb/>
     Minister of the Interior wholly responsible 
     <lb/>
     for it. I think I was quite justified, after 
     <lb/>
     the stand he took in 1895, in assuming, as l 
     <lb/>
     did, that his action in 1894 was taken ad<lb break="no"/>visedly, so that the House would not un<lb break="no"/>derstand the change proposed. He says that 
     <lb/>
     the amendments were made in the Senate 
     <lb/>
     without his knowledge. I accept his word 
     <lb/>
     upon that point. But, when those amend<lb break="no"/>ments came before the House, surely, as a 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <cb/>
    
    
     matter of fair-play, he should have ex<lb break="no"/>plained to the House what the changes 
     <lb/>
     were. He stated that he had explained 
     <lb/>
     the changes to members from the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories, but, when I pressed him 
     <lb/>
     for the name of any hon. member to whom 
     <lb/>
     he had explained these changes. the only 
     <lb/>
     name he could give was that of the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for East Assinobia (Mr. McDon<lb break="no"/>ald), who has not had a word to say in de<lb break="no"/>fence of the changes then made. I could 
     <lb/>
     not believe that the hon. member for East As<lb break="no"/>siniboia would suggest this change. For 
     <lb/>
     what interest could he have in the elections? 
     <lb/>
     As I said before, he has been discarded by 
     <lb/>
     his party, he is of no further use to them. 
     <lb/>
     He made a very vigorous fight for the nom<lb break="no"/>ination, but he failed. Now, if it be true 
     <lb/>
     that, before these changes, outrages in the 
     <lb/>
    way of men falsely swearing their names 
     <lb/>upon the lists. is it not an astonishing fact 
     <lb/>to find that the legislative assembly of the 
     <lb/>North-west Territories, in their local elec<lb break="no"/>tions adhere to the system we have aban<lb break="no"/>doned? Under the law of the Territories any 
     <lb/>person can get his name on the list by going 
     <lb/>on election day and swearing that he is a 
     <lb/>British subject and is otherwise entitled to 
     <lb/>vote, just as, prior to 1894, a person could do 
     <lb/>in Dominion elections. It is hardly neces<lb break="no"/>sary for me to refer again to the absurd and 
     <lb/>childish argument of the Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior in support of his plea that this change 
     <lb/>would do no harm. His argument was that 
     <lb/>the old law worked well, and. therefore. the 
     <lb/>new law would work well. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man must surely think there is neither sense 
     <lb/>nor reason in this House. In effect. he says 
     <lb/>that there is no difference between a list 
     <lb/>that means nothing and a list that is final 
     <lb/>and binding. When a list is made up which 
     <lb/>binds nobody, who cares what becomes of 
     <lb/>it or how it is made up. But if in the mean<lb break="no"/>time, you change the law so that the list, 
     <lb/>instead of being, as the hon. member for 
     <lb/>West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) says, a mere 
     <lb/>list for convenience, to save time on elec<lb break="no"/>tion day, and make that list final and bind<lb break="no"/>ing, surely you effect a complete change. 
     <lb/>You could perpetrate any fraud you liked in 
     <lb/>1887 or 1891 in keeping men's names off the 
     <lb/>prepared lists. and we did not need to care, 
     <lb/>because we had privileges under the Act 
     <lb/>which countervailed all that wrong. But, if 
     <lb/>you attempt to perpetrate a fraud in 1896 
     <lb/>which the Act gives you the power to per<lb break="no"/>petrate, we have no protection. The only 
     <lb/>course of safety is to have this vile iniquity 
     <lb/>purged from the statute-book. The hon. 
     <lb/>member for North York (Mr. Mulock) says 
     <lb/>this Bill cannot pass. Well, Mr. Speaker, I 
     <lb/>hope it will pass. The hon. member for 
     <lb/>North York appeals to the Government in 
     <lb/>favour of the Bill. We tried that in 1895. 
     <lb/>But in 1895, unfortunately, when we first 
     <lb/>learned of this wrong, the Government busi<lb break="no"/>ness was done, and we had no chance of 
     <lb/>emphasizing our appeal effectually. We are 
     <lb/>in a different position at this time, Mr. 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="557" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00557.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">557</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 23, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">558</fw>
         
         Speaker. I do not care whether my hon.       
     <lb/>friend's (Mr. Davin's) Bill passes or whether 
     <lb/>my Bill passes; but I ask and demand of 
     <lb/>the Government of the day the righting of 
     <lb/>this wrong. As I have already said, if they 
     <lb/>have no intention of doing us this wrong, 
     <lb/>let them relinquish the power to do it. I 
     <lb/>make the demand at the instance of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of the North-west Territories. They are 
     <lb/>alarmed about this matter, and they have 
     <lb/>shown their alarm in the clearest possible 
     <lb/>way by a resolution passed by an assembly 
     <lb/>which, as I said before, is composed largely 
     <lb/>of Conservatives. The hon. member for 
     <lb/>West Assiniboia will agree with me in that. 
     <lb/>It is true that, among the members of that 
     <lb/>assembly, are the Liberal candidate for 
     <lb/>Alberta and some other Liberals. But 
     <lb/>I know a great many of them, and I 
     <lb/>think I am quite correct in saying that there 
     <lb/>is a considerable majority who are sup<lb break="no"/>porters of the present Government. Mr. 
     <lb/>Haultain, as I said before, the Premier, is 
     <lb/>the Government candidate in Alberta; and 
     <lb/>these gentlemen with. one voice have con<lb break="no"/>demned this outrage in language as strong 
     <lb/>and as clear as any that I have used to-day. 
     <lb/>They have pointed out the possibility of 
     <lb/>great wrong being done. and they have 
     <lb/>asked to have the law changed back into 
     <lb/>its old form, or else into their local Fran<lb break="no"/>'chise Act, but it makes no difference for the 
     <lb/>purpose of the people which is done. I may 
     <lb/>say that I got a letter this day from a mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the legislative assembly urging me 
     <lb/>not to overlook this matter, to be sure and 
     <lb/>bring it up, and endeavour if possible to 
     <lb/>have the wrong made right. I again say 
     <lb/>that if this House does not at this session 
     <lb/>change that law, the prediction of the hon. 
     <lb/>Minister of the Interior will, no doubt, be 
     <lb/>fulfilled. in the elections which will take 
     <lb/>place in 1896, and there will. no doubt. be 
     <lb/>four members returned supporting the Con<lb break="no"/>servative party in the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. I have no doubt about it, it is too 
     <lb/>clear for argument. I do not think that the 
     <lb/>Liberals would put up candidates, I do not 
     <lb/>think we will be able to find four men 
     <lb/>foolish enough to risk $200 under circum<lb break="no"/>stances such as these. The Conservatives 
     <lb/>will get every seat, and possibly by accla<lb break="no"/>mation. But, Mr. Speaker, if they will give 
     <lb/>us a fair chance up there, if they will re<lb break="no"/>peal this iniquity and give us an equal 
     <lb/>chance with them in the election, I think 
     <lb/>the issue will be different. I may be right 
     <lb/>in my prediction that we will get the four 
     <lb/>seats, or the Minister of the Interior may 
     <lb/>beright in his. But there will be some equal 
     <lb/>chance for us, there will be some Oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity for a fight; whereas under this Act 
     <lb/>we have no chance and no opportunity. 
     <lb/>As I said before, it will be entirely useless 
     <lb/>for us to attempt to fight under the circum<lb break="no"/>stances. Therefore, it is my duty, as the 
     <lb/>only representative of Liberal opinions, or 
     <lb/>the nearest representative to the Territories 
     <lb/>of Liberal opinions, to demand in this House 
     <lb/>
       
       
            <cb/>
        
        
     that a change be made. While the hon.<lb/>Minister of the Interior may take thestand, 
     <lb/>
     and his colleagues may support him in it, 
     <lb/>
     that he is going to take into his hands this 
     <lb/>
     enormous power for fraud, I doubt very 
     <lb/>
     much whether the members in this House 
     <lb/>
     supporting the Government on their general 
     <lb/>
     policy, will support them in any such out<lb break="no"/>rageous proceeding as this. If there is any 
     <lb/>
     possibility, under the rules of the House, of 
     <lb/>
     bringing the matter to a vote, I shall cer<lb break="no"/>tainly obtain a vote of the members upon 
     <lb/>
     this question. I hope when the occasion 
     <lb/>
     comes hon. members will see that the people 
     <lb/>
     of these four constituencies in the Territories 
     <lb/>
     have a fair chance to go to the polls and 
     <lb/>
     deposit their ballots, whether they happen 
     <lb/>
     to be in favour of or against the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. I am 
     <lb/>
     not going to prolong the discussion which 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend from Winnipeg (Mr. Martin) 
     <lb/>
     has initiated, although I feel bound to say 
     <lb/>
     that I have failed to hear one single argu<lb break="no"/>ment from the other side of the House in 
     <lb/>
     the slightest degree justifying the assump<lb break="no"/>tion of the monstrous power—and I use the 
     <lb/>
     word advisedly—which the Government 
     <lb/>
     have, without the real knowledge of the 
     <lb/>
     House, taken to themselves. The thing 
     <lb/>
     smacks of fraud of the grossest possible 
     <lb/>
     description. But what I want chiefly to 
     <lb/>
     call the attention of the House to, is this: 
     <lb/>
     As I understand it, this confusion has arisen, 
     <lb/>
     or the ignorance of the House has been 
     <lb/>
     caused, in no small degree, by the very 
     <lb/>
     mischievous practice which prevails in our 
     <lb/>
     legislation of repealing a clause by number, 
     <lb/>
     without giving full details of the clause that 
     <lb/>
     is repealed. I have over and over again 
     <lb/>
     protested against that practice in this House. 
     <lb/>
     I hold that it is the most slovenly possible 
     <lb/>
     legislation, when we are dealing with im<lb break="no"/>portant subjects like this, to say you repeal 
     <lb/>
     such and such a clause, number so and so, 
     <lb/>
     of such and such an Act. Not one man out 
     <lb/>
     of fifty in the House knows anything about 
     <lb/>
     the matter in general when; it is introduced 
     <lb/>
     in that fashion, still less, when it is intro<lb break="no"/>duced in the shape of an amendment from 
     <lb/>
     the Senate. Such a practice ought to be 
     <lb/>
     prohibited. I think, by a rule of this House ; 
     <lb/>
     at any rate, the Government in particular 
     <lb/>
     ought to be exceedingly cautious not to allow 
     <lb/>
     any legislation which passes through their 
     <lb/>
     hands, to be conducted in such an exceed<lb break="no"/>ingly slipshod fashion. I hope and trust that 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friends will get an opportunity of 
     <lb/>
     testing the sense of the House on this 
     <lb/>
     question, because I myself am of the opin<lb break="no"/>ion that if this thing had been fairly pre<lb break="no"/>sented to the House, the members on both 
     <lb/>
     sides would have refused to accord to the 
     <lb/>
     nominees of the Government any such power 
     <lb/>
     as that which appears to be given to them; 
     <lb/>
     and I trust that my hon. friend will take 
     <lb/>
     exceedingly good care that a test vote be 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <pb n="559" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-01-23_Page_00559.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">559</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">560</fw>
         
         
     obtained on this subject before we are much 
     <lb/>
     older. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>