<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1890-02-25" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1890-02-25">25 February 1890</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
<date when="1890"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1069" to="1072"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-25_Page_01069.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-25_Page_01071.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-03">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-03">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-25_Page_01069"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-25_Page_01069.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-25_Page_01071"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-25_Page_01071.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="1069" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-25_Page_01069.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1069</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 25, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">1070</fw> 

<p>[...]presentative. That was received on Saturday <lb/>
night; I sent it to the Minister of Marine and <lb/>
Fisheries on Sunday, and he started yesterday at <lb/>
one o'clock for Washington. <lb/></p> 
</div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">CAUGHNAWAGA RESERVE.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:DOYO1">Mr. DOYON</persName>. (Translation.) Mr. Speaker, before <lb/>
the Orders of the day are called, I desire to call the <lb/>
attention of the Government to the fact that I <lb/>
asked, at the beginning of this Session, for the <lb/>
production of the report of the operations of Mr. <lb/>
McLea Walbank as land surveyor of the Indian <lb/>
Reserve of Caughnawaga. The hon. the Minis<lb break="no"/>ter of the Interior answered me that he had no <lb/>
objection to produce that document. During last <lb/>
Session I made the same request, and I received <lb/>
the same answer; nevertheless, the report has not <lb/>
yet been brought down. Am I to understand <lb/>
that the Government, although having no objection <lb/>
to lay that report before the House, has no inten<lb break="no"/>tion of doing so? If, on the contrary, it is disposed <lb/>
to produce it, I would desire to know how soon, for <lb/>
I might say that it is not without good reason that <lb/>
I ask for it. I thought the matter had been for<lb break="no"/>gotten, and that is why I have taken this oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of recalling it to the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. I understand that the hon. <lb/>
gentleman wants to know when the report and the <lb/>
map of the survey of the Caughnawaga Reserve <lb/>
will be brought down. The map is a very intricate <lb/>
one, and it will take a long time to prepare it, <lb/>
and, therefore, I cannot say when it will be brought <lb/>
down. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DOYO1">Mr. DOYON</persName>. The hon. Minister will recollect <lb/>
that, in a private conversation with him last <lb/>
Session, I asked for that report, and he told me <lb/>
that if he could not produce it during the Session, <lb/>
he would file it during the recess. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. I will bring it down at the <lb/>
earliest possible moment. <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
        

<head rendition="simple:centre">PERSONAL EXPLANATION—DUTIES ON <lb/>
SEEDS.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:COUT1">Mr. COUTURE</persName>. (Translation.) Mr. Speaker, I <lb/>
regret that reasons beyond my control prevented <lb/>
me from attending yesterday's sitting, when the <lb/>
House was called upon to vote on a most im<lb break="no"/>portant question as regards the agricultural class; <lb/>
I refer to the motion of the hon. member for South <lb/>
Huron (Mr. McMillan), in favor of free importation <lb/>
of seeds not produced in Canada and used for the <lb/>
fattening of animals, the improvement of the lands <lb/>
and for silos. Had I been here, I should have <lb/>
voted for the motion of the hon. member for South <lb/>
Huron, as I understand his proposition is calcu<lb break="no"/>lated to do immense service to the agricultural <lb/>
class.   <lb/></p> 
    </div>
<div type="debate">

<head rendition="simple:centre">PRIVILEGE—THE FRENCH LANGUAGE IN <lb/>
THE NORTH-WEST.</head> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. Mr. Speaker, I rise on a question <lb/>
of privilege. It has been spread over the country <lb/>
that by voting as we did the other evening against <lb/>
the amendment of the hon. Minister of Justice, I <lb/>
voted for the Bill of the hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy). I did not take the neces<lb break="no"/>sary time last Friday to explain my view of the <lb/>
matter, because I desired to enable my colleagues <lb/>

<cb/>

to take the train so as to go to their homes. I was <lb/>
of opinion, first, that all the hon. members in <lb/>
favor of Mr. McCarthy's Bill had to vote against <lb/>
any amendment tending to prevent that Bill from <lb/>
being read a second time; second, that all the hon. <lb/>
members in favor of Mr. Davin's amendment had <lb/>
to vote against any sub-amendment tending to <lb/>
prevent that amendment from being affirmed by <lb/>
the House; third, that all the hon. members <lb/>
opposed to any change being made in the existing <lb/>
law had to vote against the sub-amendment <lb/>
offered by the hon. Minister of Justice, as the <lb/>
would have to vote against Mr. Davin's amend<lb break="no"/>ment, and the Bill itself, had they reached a vote. <lb/>
The Bill presented by the hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe was struck off the Order paper for the <lb/>
second reading by the adoption of the sub-amend<lb break="no"/>ment, and no direct vote was practically taken <lb/>
upon the Bill itself. I have consulted very high <lb/>
authorities on this point, and I may quote <lb/>
Bourinot, our worthy Clerk, who has been so <lb/>
justly honored by the Queen lately, who, at page <lb/>
130, says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"If a resolution opposed to the principle of the Bill be <lb/>
resolved in the affirmative, or the motion that the Bill be <lb/>
now read a second time be simply negatived on a division, <lb/>
the measure will disappear from the Order Book." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>So that we never had a vote on the Bill itself. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. Oh, yes, we had. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. The meaning I gave to my vote <lb/>
was that I was opposed to any change in the exist<lb break="no"/>ing law, and I am authorised to make the same <lb/>
statement on behalf of the hon. members for La<lb break="no"/>prairie (Mr. Doyon), Napierville (Mr. Ste. Marie), <lb/>
L'Assomption (Mr. Gauthier), Joliette (Mr. Neveu), <lb/>
Vercheres (Mr. Geoffrion), St. John's, Quebec (Mr. <lb/>
Bourassa), Chicoutimi (Mr. Couture), and I do not <lb/>
doubt that if the hon. members for Berthier (Mr. <lb/>
Beausoleil), and Chambly (Mr. Préfontaine), were <lb/>
here, they would join in the declaration. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. I desire to <lb/>
call the attention of the Government to the fact <lb/>
that, although the right hon. the First Minister <lb/>
himself indicated some time ago that important <lb/>
changes were likely to be made in the tariff, we <lb/>
have not only not yet got the Budget but have no <lb/>
intimation as to when the Budget is likely to come <lb/>
down. It is important, both to the business of the <lb/>
House and the interests of this country, that the <lb/>
period of suspension should not be prolonged any <lb/>
longer than possible, and the Government ought to <lb/>
be in a position to tell us within a day or two when <lb/>
they propose to bring down their financial state<lb break="no"/>ment. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. The hon. the <lb/>
Minister of Finance is not here, and will not be <lb/>
here the first part of the evening unless specially <lb/>
sent for, and, therefore, I cannot speak specifically <lb/>
in answer to the hon. gentleman. But the hon. <lb/>
gentleman must have seen that ever since the Ses<lb break="no"/>sion began, all kinds of deputations have visited <lb/>
Ottawa for the purpose of pressing their various <lb/>
interests on the attention of the Government with <lb/>
respect to the re-adjustment of the tariff. There <lb/>
is too much tendency on the part of the various <lb/>
interests to postpone discussing subjects or calling <lb/>
the attention of the Government to them until <lb/>
Parliament has met, which is really the most in<lb break="no"/>convenient season for that purpose. Still , they <lb/>
come during that period, and, I think, until this <lb/>

<pb n="1071" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-02-25_Page_01071.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1071</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1072</fw> 

last week we have had deputations here represent<lb break="no"/>ing most of the industries of this country. Their <lb/>
representations have been carefully considered by <lb/>
the Minister of Finance and the Minister of Cus<lb break="no"/>toms, and I have no reason to doubt these hon. <lb/>
gentlemen will be able very shortly to bring down <lb/>
the results of their examination. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. I will take <lb/>
the opportunity, then, when the House adjourns, or <lb/>
thereabouts, of asking for some information, and <lb/>
the right hon. the First Minister, I understand, <lb/>
will mention to the Minister of Finance what I <lb/>
have said, in order that he may give the informa<lb break="no"/>tion desired. I am aware of the difficulty which <lb/>
the hon. gentleman speaks of, in the matter of <lb/>
deputatious putting off important questions until the <lb/>
last moment, and I do not think it is fair to the <lb/>
Government or the country that deputations should <lb/>
postpone coming here until within a few days of <lb/>
the Budget. Speaking with some little experience, <lb/>
I know it is utterly impossible for a Minister of <lb/>
Finance, or the Minister of Customs, or the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment generally, to make the requisite enquiries <lb/>
in the course of a week or ten days, which is gen<lb break="no"/>erally the amount of time allowed by these depu<lb break="no"/>tations, but that is, to a certain extent, in the <lb/>
Government's own hands, and the sooner they <lb/>
bring down the Budget, the less likely they are to <lb/>
be troubled with these deputations. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. I would ask the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man whether the return asked for by the hon. <lb/>
member for Muskoka has been brought down yet <lb/>
—with reference to the opinion of the law officers <lb/>
of the Crown on the constitutionality of the <lb/>
Jesuits' Estates Bill?. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. It will shortly <lb/>
be laid before the House. His Excellency was <lb/>
bound to ask for permission to bring the papers <lb/>
down, he has that permission, and we will bring <lb/>
the papers down. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. I would like to make a <lb/>
motion with reference to the printing of this when <lb/>
brought down. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. That is not in <lb/>
order. It will be printed as soon as it comes down, <lb/>
I can tell the hon. gentleman, without a motion. <lb/></p> 
</div>
<div type="debate">


<head rendition="simple:centre">THE ADULTERATION ACT.</head> 

<p>House resolved itself into Committee on Bill <lb/>
(No. 9) further to amend the Adulteration Act, <lb/>
chapter 107 of the Revised Statutes.—(Mr. Cos<lb break="no"/>tigan.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">(In the Committee.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. I understand that some persons <lb/>
engaged in the trade of selling agricultural fertil<lb break="no"/>isers have made representations to the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man with regard to some of the provisions of this <lb/>
Bill. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. COSTIGAN</persName>. They have, but that question <lb/>
will be treated in the Act to amend the Fertilisers <lb/>
Act, and has nothing to do with this Bill. The <lb/>
question of amendments to the Fertilisers Act are <lb/>
entirely distinct from this Act, and the Fertilisers <lb/>
Act amendments will be taken up later in the <lb/>
Session, after I have heard representations from all <lb/>
the parties interested. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:JONE1">Mr. JONES</persName> (Halifax). I have received repre<lb break="no"/>sentations from parties interested in fertilisers, but <lb/>

<cb/>

as the hon. gentleman says they are not affected <lb/>
by the Bill under consideration, but will be dealt <lb/>
with in another Bill, I will wait until that Bill is <lb/>
before the House. <lb/></p> 

<p>On section 4, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WELD1">Mr. WELDON</persName> (St. John). I object to the <lb/>
general principle of amending Acts by simply de<lb break="no"/>claring that certain words are altered or struck <lb/>
out. It makes it very difficult to understand what <lb/>
the law is, and it would be far better to repeal the <lb/>
whole section and re-enact it with the amendment. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. COSTIGAN</persName>. The Bill is prepared by the <lb/>
law officers and they, I suppose, take the course <lb/>
which is generally pursued. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WELD1">Mr. WELDON</persName> (St. John). I think it is a <lb/>
vicious principle to adopt. If a new edition of <lb/>
the Revised Statutes were issued to-morrow, it <lb/>
would contain these amendments, and it is difficult <lb/>
to follow them under the present system. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Some years ago this <lb/>
matter was discussed, and it was agreed that, <lb/>
wherever it was proposed to amend a section, the <lb/>
section should be reprinted in the amending Act <lb/>
with the changes inserted in it, and should be <lb/>
altogether repealed in the original Act. That is <lb/>
certainly a much more convenient system to adopt, <lb/>
and one which makes it nmch more easy to in<lb break="no"/>terpret the statute. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. I remember <lb/>
the discussion referred to by my hon. friend, and <lb/>
there is no question whatever that very great in<lb break="no"/>convenience arises to laymen, at any rate, if not to <lb/>
lawyers, from the practice to which my hon. friend <lb/>
has alluded. I forget who was the Minister of <lb/>
Justice at that time, but I understood that the <lb/>
Government then promised to set a good example <lb/>
in Bills of their own, and to reprint the amended <lb/>
clause in the Bill. It seems to me that reason and <lb/>
common sense are wholly in favor of that course. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. At present, if any one wants to <lb/>
know what the law is, he has to buy half-a-dozen <lb/>
copies of the Statutes in order to understand one <lb/>
paragraph. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PATE1">Mr. PATERSON</persName> (Brant). Are these reports <lb/>
simply to be published at the option of the Minis<lb break="no"/>ter, or will all the reports be published? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. COSTIGAN</persName>. Yes, all reports will be pub<lb break="no"/>lished. <lb/></p> 

<p>On section 8, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WILS5">Mr. WILSON</persName> (Elgin). It strikes me that this <lb/>
is a very undesirable clause. We find in this <lb/>
proviso that any individual who, through no fault <lb/>
of his own, may have purchased an article that is <lb/>
ultimately found to be more or less adulterated, is <lb/>
placed in a position that unless he can show that <lb/>
he sold the article as he received it, and that he <lb/>
has at the same time a warranty from the party <lb/>
from whom he purchased this article, he is liable <lb/>
to a heavy fine. But the clause does not even stop <lb/>
there; for if he has a warranty, if he shows that <lb/>
he purchased this article in good faith and under<lb break="no"/>stood that it was pure when he purchased it, after <lb/>
proving all this, he is still liable to a fine. Why <lb/>
should a man be placed in that position unless It <lb/>
can be shown that he was in some way responsible, <lb/>
and knew he had an article in his possession that <lb/>
was not pure, and sold it knowing that it was not <lb/>
pure? In that case he should be held responsible;[...] <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>