<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1888-03-27"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1888-03-27">27 March 1876</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Second Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1888"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Maclean, Roger &amp; Co., Wellington Street</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="454" to="455"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-03-27_Page_00454.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-03-27_Page_00455.html"/> 
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-03-27_Page_00454">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-03-27_Page_00454.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-03-27_Page_00455">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-03-27_Page_00455.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="454" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-03-27_Page_00454.jpg"/>
            
            
            <fw type="num">454</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">MARCH 27,</fw>
            
            
            <!-- IC, 2018-09-12, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day --> 
            <!--<p>
     [...]a monument which generation after generation will feel 
     <lb/>
     the results of, and future generations will feel the extra<lb break="no"/>vagance that characterised the acts of the Government over 
     <lb/>
     which he presided, and in consequence of the manner in 
     <lb/>
     which public affairs were administered by his Government, 
     <lb/>
     the people Will be called upon to bear the burden and meet 
     <lb/>
     the consequences. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. FERGUSON (Welland), moved the adjournment of 
     <lb/>
     the debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and debate adjourned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN moved the adjournment of 
     <lb/>
     the House. , 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Motion agreed to; and House adjourned at 12:45 a.m., 
     <lb/>
     (Tuesday). 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
         
     <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</head> 
     
     <head rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, 27th March, 1888.</head> 
    
    <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> took the Chair at Three o'clock. 
    </p>
           
   
            <p>
     <emph>PRAYERS.</emph> 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            
            <div type="debate">
           <head>REPORTS OF THE PRINTING COMMITTEE.</head> 
     
           
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BERG2">Mr. BERGIN</persName> moved the adoption of the first, second 
     <lb/>
     and third reports of the Joint Committee on Printing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. Will the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     explain ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BERG2">Mr. BERGIN</persName>. It is simply the account for printing. 
     <lb/>
     The account for printing is the first one, the second one is 
     <lb/>
     the report of the said committee auditing the account, and 
     <lb/>
     the third, the report and the documents ordered to be 
     <lb/>
     printed last meeting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A.MACDONALD</persName>. It is a question of a 
     <lb/>
     quorum. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BERG2">Mr. BERGIN</persName>. Yes, a question of a quorum. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. What is the quorum? 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:BERG2">Mr. BERGIN</persName>. Nine. 
     <lb/>
    Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            </div> 
   <div type="debate">
          
     <head>FIRST READINGS.</head> 
    
           
   
            <p>
     Bill (No. 68) to incorporate the Alberta Railway and Coal 
     <lb/>
     Company.—(Mr. Davis, Alberta.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Bill (No. 69) to confirm a mortgage given by the Central 
     <lb/>
     Railway Company to the Central Trust Company of New 
     <lb/>
     York to secure an issue of debentures—(Mr. Weldon, St. 
     <lb/>
     John.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Bill (No. 70) to incorporate the Montreal Island Railway 
     <lb/>
     Company.—(Mr. Desjardins.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Bill (No. 71) to grant certain powers to the St. John's, 
     <lb/>
     and Iberville Hydraulic and Manufacturing Company.— 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Vanasse. ) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Bill (No. 72) to incorporate the New York, St. Lawrence 
     <lb/>
     and Ottawa Railway Company.—(Mr. Wood, Brockville.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Bill (No. 73) respecting the Stanstead, Shefford and 
     <lb/>
     Chambly Railway Company.—(Mr. Fisher.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Bill (No. 74) to amend the Act to incorporate the 
     <lb/>
     Kincardine and Teeswater Railway Company.—(Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Rowand.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Bill (N). 75) to incorporate the Ottawa and Parry 
     <lb/>
     Sound Railway Company.—(Mr. Ferguson, Renfrew.) 
            </p>
      
   </div>
           <div type="debate">
           <head rendition="simple:centre">GOVERMENT OF THE NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES.</head>
            
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName> moved for leave to intro<lb break="no"/>duce Bill (No. 76) to amend the Revised Statutes of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, chapter 50, respecting the North-West Territories. 
     <lb/>
     He said : I make this motion now for the purpose of having 
     <lb/>
     the Bill stand for a second reading at as early a day as 
     <lb/>
     convenient after the recess, The Bill is on the lines of the 
     <lb/>
     measure introduced by the hon. member for Bothwell 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Mills) when he was Minister of the Interior. It 
     <lb/>
     provides that the North-West Council shall have the 
     <lb/>
     character of a legislative assembly, having not less than 21 
     <lb/>
     nor more than 25 members. A schedule of the constitu<lb break="no"/>encies is now under consideration, and is not yet attached 
     <lb/>
     to the Bill. It is proposed that the nominated members of 
     <lb/>
     the council shall cease; but as there are at present 
     <lb/>
     no legal men in the council, nor is there much chance 
     <lb/>
     of there being many legal men in the first assembly, it is 
     <lb/>
     preposed that the Government may have power to appoint 
     <lb/>
     certain legal experts, not exceeding three, who shall sit and 
     <lb/>
     assist in the drafting of Bills, and have the power of discus<lb break="no"/>sion but not the power of voting, something like the repre<lb break="no"/>sentative delegates from the Territories in the United States 
     <lb/>
     Congress. That provision is intended to apply to the 
     <lb/>
     present term of the legislative assembly; it is hoped that 
     <lb/>
     in the second term some legal gentlemen may find their 
     <lb/>
     way into the assembly, and enable us to do away with that 
     <lb/>
     provision. It is proposed to extend the term of the 
     <lb/>
     existence of the legislature from two or three years. The 
     <lb/>
     qualification will remain the same, household suffrage with 
     <lb/>
     the addition of an income suffrage. The Lieutenant Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor shall no longer sit with the council or assembly, but 
     <lb/>
     shall, as in the Provinces, be a separate estate, and the 
     <lb/>
     assembly will be presided over as this assembly is, by a 
     <lb/>
     Speaker. There is an extension of the powers of the 
     <lb/>
     assembly which I need not trouble the House with now, 
     <lb/>
     but the subject will be fully entered into when the Bill is 
     <lb/>
     under discussion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). What about executive coun<lb break="no"/>cillors. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. We do not propose to 
     <lb/>
     have executive councillors. There is a proposition of that 
     <lb/>
     kind in one of the petitions of the North- West Council 
     <lb/>
     which is before the House, but after consideration those 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen are opposed to it themselves. They say that it 
     <lb/>
     is really a retrogressive step, rather than one in advance. 
     <lb/>
     These are the principal features of the measure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. I am not aware that the resolutions of 
     <lb/>
     the North-West Council with respect to this matter have 
     <lb/>
     been placed before the House. If they have not been, I 
     <lb/>
     suppose the hon. gentleman will place them before the 
     <lb/>
     House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. Certainly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). I am sure the House will be 
     <lb/>
     glad if the hon. gentleman would afford us some further 
     <lb/>
     information on this important Bill. The people in that 
     <lb/>
     country have made considerable progress in number and in 
     <lb/>
     the development of the country, and a government a little 
     <lb/>
     more approaching that of a Province than that which at 
     <lb/>
     present exists there is no doubt required; but in all our 
     <lb/>
     Provinces we have parliamentary responsible government, 
     <lb/>
     and I do not understand from the hon. gentleman's obser<lb break="no"/>vations how he proposes that the executive government 
     <lb/>
     shall be carried on. The proposition he has made relates 
     <lb/>
     purely to matters of legislation. Does he propose that the 
     <lb/>
     Lieutenant Governor of the Territories shall have the 
     <lb/>
     power of vetoing the measures of the Legislative Assembly 
     <lb/>
     of the Territories? Does he propose that when the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature meets and passes a law which it believes to be for the 
     <lb/>
     good of the Territories, within the legislative limits 
     <lb/>
     assigned to it, the Governor in Council here shall 
    
          
            <pb n="455" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-03-27_Page_00455.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">1888.</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">455</fw>
          
     have the power, by instruction, to disallow it? Does he 
     <lb/>
     propose that the Lieutenant Governor of the Territories 
     <lb/>
     shall have an executive council to advise him with 
     <lb/>
     regard to the administration of the affairs of the Territories? 
     <lb/>
     For you will observe that the powers possessed by the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor in Council there, now are not purely legislative 
     <lb/>
     powers, but administrative and executive powers as well. 
     <lb/>
     How are those administrative and executive powers to be 
     <lb/>
     exercised? Are they to be exercised? by the Executive of 
     <lb/>
     the Territories, acting under the advice and approval of the 
     <lb/>
     majority of those whom the people have elected to represent 
     <lb/>
     them? Does the hon. gentleman propose they shall act on 
     <lb/>
     the advice which they may, from time to time, receive from 
     <lb/>
     the Government here? Now, I say that these are matters 
     <lb/>
     of the very first importance, and that before we are asked 
     <lb/>
     to take any step in advance in the legislative and govern<lb break="no"/>mental develpment of that country, we should note precise<lb break="no"/>ly what we are called upon to do; for it does seem me to be 
     <lb/>
     rather extraordinary to admit that the people of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tory are so far advanced, by way of organisation, into a 
     <lb/>
     political and social community, as to make it necessary 
     <lb/>
     that they should have what may be considered a mature 
     <lb/>
     system devised for the purposes of legislation, and yet that 
     <lb/>
     the legislative and administrative affairs of the country 
     <lb/>
     should be in the hands of an irresponsible body. Certainly 
     <lb/>
     the power of legislation and administration should go 
     <lb/>
     hand in hand. If the community are entitled, and I 
     <lb/>
     am inclined to think that the hon. gentleman is doing 
     <lb/>
     right in recognising that they are entitled, to complete 
     <lb/>
     legislative control over those matters which are exclu<lb break="no"/>sively assigned to them, they should have equally indepen<lb break="no"/>dent control over the executive and administrative affairs 
     <lb/>
     of the Territory, within the same limits. They should be 
     <lb/>
     made commensurate with the legislative authority; they 
     <lb/>
     should be governmental to the same extent, and it would be 
     <lb/>
     a wholly anomalous condition of things for the executive 
     <lb/>
     and administrative affairs to be directed, not in consonance 
     <lb/>
     with the views of the majority of those whom the peeple 
     <lb/>
     have returned to the Legislature, but should be controlled 
     <lb/>
     by instructions given, from time to time, to the Lieutenant 
     <lb/>
     Governor from Ottawa. That would be simply Downing-<lb break="yes"/>street over again. It would be simply introducing into the 
     <lb/>
     North-West Territories precisely that condition of things 
     <lb/>
     which existed in Upper and Lower Canada before respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government was established. They had legislative 
     <lb/>
     bodies that represented the people, but they had an 
     <lb/>
     executive Government that represented Downing-street, 
     <lb/>
     and it would be rather a retrograde step to introduce any 
     <lb/>
     analogous system of government into the North-West 
     <lb/>
     Territories. I am sure the House will be anxious to know 
     <lb/>
     precisely what the hon. gentleman proposes to do in this 
     <lb/>
     matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. This is, perhaps, not the 
     <lb/>
               time to discuss, <hi rendition="simple:italic">in extenso</hi>, the various questions which the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman has raised. In the first place, I must tell 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman that in the North-West they have a 
     <lb/>
     most holy horror of responsible government. The 
     <lb/>
     representations are, I may say, without any exception, 
     <lb/>
     against the premature introduction of responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment. If the hon. gentlemen were in the position of the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Interior, he would find that the one cry is: do 
     <lb/>
     not at all at present give us a government of that kind. I 
     <lb/>
     take it the assembly, although sitting separate from the 
     <lb/>
     Government, will have the same administrative as well 
     <lb/>
     as legislative powers which they had when under the name 
     <lb/>
     of a council. The relations between the Lieutenant Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor there and the Government here will continue to be 
     <lb/>
     the same as they were before this Bill was introduced— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName>. They cannot be. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>—or the same as between 
     <lb/>
     the Lieutenant Governors of the Provinces and the Gov<lb break="no"/>
            <cb/>
           ernor General. All these are important matters, and I am 
     <lb/>
     glad the hon. gentleman has called attention to these 
     <lb/>
     points. They will be discussed more conveniently after 
     <lb/>
     the Bill is in the hands of the hon. members. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MITC2">Mr. MITCHELL</persName>. I can understand that a certain class 
     <lb/>
     of the people in the North-West should have a holy horror 
     <lb/>
     of responsible government, but, in my opinion, the experi<lb break="no"/>ence of the past few years shows the people there should 
     <lb/>
     have a holy horror of bureaucratic government. I am glad 
     <lb/>
     this question has come up for discussion. It is a very im<lb break="no"/>portant one, not only for the people of the North-West, but 
     <lb/>
     for the people of the whole of Canada, who are interested 
     <lb/>
     in seeing that administration of public affairs in the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     West should be a little different in the future from what it 
     <lb/>
     has been in the past. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Now the Governor votes with 
     <lb/>
     the council, and if he happens to be in the minority he is 
     <lb/>
     outvoted and has to submit? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). But the hon. gentleman pro<lb break="no"/>poses, by this Bill, to separate the Governor from the legis<lb break="no"/>lative body. What is his position? Has he any voice at 
     <lb/>
     all in the legislative assembly? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. I do not think that he 
     <lb/>
     has much. I take it that the veto by the Lieutenant Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor is like the vote by the Queen. It is, in fact, gone. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). The Queen is advised. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. The utmost we could do, 
     <lb/>
     and I think it ought to be reserved to him, is to reserve 
     <lb/>
     that power.
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. Has he to sanction the Acts passed by 
     <lb/>
     the Legislature? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. I think so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. That is a veto. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. Her Majesty sanctions 
     <lb/>
     all the Bills, but she never has in Her long life exercised 
     <lb/>
     the right to veto. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. She has it in <hi rendition="simple:italic">esse</hi> if not in <hi rendition="simple:italic">posse.</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Her Majesty is advised by those 
     <lb/>
     who sit in both Houses. Now there is nobody responsible 
     <lb/>
     for the legislation. The Governor exercises no control 
     <lb/>
     Whatever in the initiation of measures in this assembly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. Not now. 
     <lb/></p>
              <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read first time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
           </div>
           <div type="debate">
     <head rendition="simple:centre">REPORT.</head> 
     
   
            <p>
     Report of the Department of Agriculture for the year 
     <lb/>
     1887.—(Mr. Carling.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
           </div>
          <div type="debate">
     <head rendition="simple:centre">REPRESENTATION OF RUSSELL.</head> 
    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. I now beg to renew the motion which 
     <lb/>
     I made yesterday: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That the warrant issued by Mr. Speaker for a new writ of election for 
     <lb/>
     the electoral district of the county of Russell. Ontario, as appears in 
     <lb/>
     the Journals of this House, on the 23rd January last, be withdrawn, and 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Speaker do forthwith issue his warrant to the Clerk of the 
     <lb/>
     Crown in Chancery to make a new writ of election for the said elec<lb break="no"/>toral district. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. After considering, I have 
     <lb/>
     come to the conclusion that this motion ought to carry. 
     <lb/>
     The House knows that I consistently and persistently have 
     <lb/>
     pressed that such matters in connection with elections 
     <lb/>
     should go to the Committee on Privileges and Elections, and 
     <lb/>
     in two cases, the one the rather celebrated case of Queen's 
     <lb/>
     county, New Brunswick, and the other that of the county 
     <lb/>
     of Kent, there were points of law raised that had to be[...] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            
         </div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>