<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1889-04-15"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1889-04-15">15 April 1889</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1889"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="1262" to="1263"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-04-15_Page_01262.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-04-15_Page_01263.html"/> 
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-04-15_Page_01262">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-04-15_Page_01262.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-04-15_Page_01263">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-04-15_Page_01263.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1262" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-04-15_Page_01262.jpg"/>
            
            
           
     <fw type="num">1262</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">APRIL 15,</fw> 
    
   
            
     <head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES ACT AMENDMENT.</head> 
     
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName> moved for leave to introduce Bill (No. 136) 
     <lb/>
     to consolidate and amend the North-West Territories Acts. 
     <lb/>
     He said: This Bill preposes to consolidate the three Acts 
     <lb/>
     on our Statute-book in reference to the North West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, chapter 50 of the Revised Statutes, the short Act 
     <lb/>
     passed in 1887, and the Act of last Session constituting the 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Assembly for the Territories. The Bill is 
     <lb/>
     substantially for the consolidation of the present law, and 
     <lb/>
     proposes to give enlarged powers to the Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Assembly. That is the principal amendment. There is 
     <lb/>
     also an amendment giving the Legislative Assembly power 
     <lb/>
     to deal with the question of the sale of liquor to the same 
     <lb/>
     extent as the Local Houses in other Provinces, and retaining 
     <lb/>
     until the new Legislature meets, the present liquor law. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>.  I protest most emphatically against the 
     <lb/>
     introduction of such a Bill at this period. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man cannot expect the House now to go into the subject of 
     <lb/>
     consolidation. If there are urgent amendments required in 
     <lb/>
     the North-West Territories, I am not prepared to say that 
     <lb/>
     we should not grant these amendments, but it is impossible 
     <lb/>
     at this late period to give the Bill the hen. gentleman pro<lb break="no"/>poses to introduce, the attention it requires, and, as far as 
     <lb/>
     this side of the House is concerned, we will not consent to 
     <lb/>
     legislation of this kind at present. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. From the explanation given by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     Minister of the Interior, it seems to me that the amendments 
     <lb/>
     are so simple and so obviously needed— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. I say nothing as to the amendments, 
     <lb/>
     but the hon. gentleman said he was going to consolidate the 
     <lb/>
     whole legislation. This is what I object to. As to the 
     <lb/>
     amendments, we shall deal with them when they are brought 
     <lb/>
     down; but my hon. friend must admit that it is impossible 
     <lb/>
     at this time of the Session to take up an Act consolidating 
     <lb/>
     the whole legislation of the North-West Territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I cannot agree with my hon. friend, be<lb break="no"/>cause the amendments, after all, as I understand them, are 
     <lb/>
     of such a nature that the consolidation will not be an elabo<lb break="no"/>rate affair. The North-West Territories Acts which require 
     <lb/>
     consolidation are not numerous, and I hope that the leader 
     <lb/>
     of the Opposition will not take an attitude so hostile to the 
     <lb/>
     interests of the North West as he has suggested it is his in<lb break="no"/>tention to take. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). If the Government had any im<lb break="no"/>portant legislation to present in regard to the North West 
     <lb/>
     Territories, it ought to have been before the House a long 
     <lb/>
     time ago. We have been in Session two and a half months. 
     <lb/>
     The hon. gentleman expected to bring the Session to a close 
     <lb/>
     within the week, and, at the last week, he proposes to in<lb break="no"/>troduce a Bill for the first time. Surely the officers of the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman's department, if the legislation were neces<lb break="no"/>sary, must have informed him of its necessity long ago; 
     <lb/>
     and if they failed in their duty in that respect the measure 
     <lb/>
     can stand over until another Session. It is a most monstrous 
     <lb/>
     proceeding that would not be tolerated by the strongest 
     <lb/>
     Government that ever sat in England—the introduction, at 
     <lb/>
     the last moment of a Session, of a measure for the consider<lb break="no"/>ation of the House. I have called the attention of the House 
     <lb/>
     over and over again, to the fact that during the last, fifty 
     <lb/>
     years every important measure of an English Administra<lb break="no"/>tion, whether Tory or Reform, was introduced the first 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="1263" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-04-15_Page_01263.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">1263</fw>
          
     month of the Session, although their Sessions last seven 
     <lb/>
     months. Yet the hon. gentleman proposes, the last week 
     <lb/>
     of the Session, to introduce a measure for the first time. 
     <lb/>
     Such a proceeding is intolerable. The hon. gentleman treats 
     <lb/>
     the House as if its business were simply to record whatever 
     <lb/>
     the Government chooses to submit to it, without any serious 
     <lb/>
     consideration. I do not believe hon. gentlemen on this side 
     <lb/>
     are prepared to so interpret their duties. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDOWALL</persName>. I should be sorry to see this Bill 
     <lb/>
     withdrawn. There are certain matters that need attention, 
     <lb/>
     and although the hon. gentleman who has just spoken may 
     <lb/>
     not have a long time to look over the Bill before it comes 
     <lb/>
     up for discussion, still, with his knowledge of the country, 
     <lb/>
     he will be ready promptly to grasp the questions touched 
     <lb/>
     upon, and I am sure it will be a great benefit to the North-<lb break="yes"/>West that the Bill should he proceeded with. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. Whether a benefit or 
     <lb/>
     not, it was the duty of the Government to inform them<lb break="no"/>selves that this was an important measure, and to bring it 
     <lb/>
     down at the proper time. I do not think it is possible that 
     <lb/>
     sufficient consideration can be given to the Bill, unless the 
     <lb/>
     Government are prepared to keep the House sitting for a 
     <lb/>
     very much longer time than now anticipated; and, in any 
     <lb/>
     case, the practice of bringing down a Government Bill four 
     <lb/>
     days before the time the Government declare it was their 
     <lb/>
     desire to adjourn is a practice which cannot be defended on 
     <lb/>
     any precedent or ground whatever, except that of extreme 
     <lb/>
     urgency, in which case we would not desire to fetter the 
     <lb/>
     hands of the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. It is not usual to oppose a 
     <lb/>
     Bill on the first reading; and I think my hon. friends 
     <lb/>
     opposite have been unduly alarmed at the word "consolida<lb break="no"/>tion" which my hon. colleague used in presenting this Bill. 
     <lb/>
     The fact is that the amendments he proposes to make in 
     <lb/>
     the North-West Territories Act are few and simple. He 
     <lb/>
     stated them. I think, as being only three. It will be 
     <lb/>
     desirable to have the three Acts relating to the North-West 
     <lb/>
     Territories—not the whole legislation, as the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     for Quebec (Mr. Laurier) has said, relating to the North-<lb break="yes"/>West—consolidated, as they would be by passing this 
     <lb/>
     Bill, because that would avoid an incoherent kind of 
     <lb/>
     legislation which it would be very difficult for the North 
     <lb/>
     West Legislature to administer. But, as I have said, the 
     <lb/>
     amendments are very simple, and I think, when the Bill is 
     <lb/>
     printed and laid before hon. gentlemen, they will not find 
     <lb/>
     it so formidable or requiring so much attention as the word 
     <lb/>
     " consolidation "seems to lead them to imagine. I do 
     <lb/>
     not think we are open to the reproach of delaying this Bill 
     <lb/>
     until within the last four days of the Session. There is 
     <lb/>
     not, on either side, the slightest idea that the House will 
     <lb/>
     close before the end of next week at the earliest, and, if the 
     <lb/>
     task of consolidating these three Statutes is too formidable 
     <lb/>
     a one, it may be thought desirable that legislation should be 
     <lb/>
     confined to the amendment of the Acts at this Session. I 
     <lb/>
     think, however, that the Bill should be new advanced a 
     <lb/>
     stage, and laid before the House, so that it may see whether 
     <lb/>
     it is of such a formidable character as is supposed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first time.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>