<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1892-04-25" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1892-04-25">25 April 1892</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, Second Session</title>.
<date when="1892"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1551" to="1553"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-04-25_Page_01551.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-04-25_Page_01553.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-23">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-04-25_Page_01551"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-04-25_Page_01551.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-04-25_Page_01553"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-04-25_Page_01553.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="1551" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-04-25_Page_01551.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">1551</fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1552</fw> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-WEST ASSEMBLY RESOLUTIONS.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName> moved for: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>Copies of all resolutions and memorials passed by the <lb/>
North-West Assembly at its last session and addressed to <lb/>
the Government. <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>He said: Mr. Speaker, some of these resolutions <lb/>
relate to matters that I think have been already <lb/>
satisfactorily dealt with by the Government, but <lb/>
there is one resolution in regard to immigration <lb/>
that I wish specially to press upon the attention <lb/>
of the Government and upon the attention <lb/>
of this House. Any one who reviews the history <lb/>
of the proceedings of this Government and of the <lb/>
Government that preceded it, will, I think, come <lb/>
to the conclusion that they have not erred in over-<lb break="yes"/>zeal for the promotion of immigration. Several <lb/>
things have undoubtedly combined to that effect; <lb/>
the principal of which is, that there has been in <lb/>
the cities a strong and influential party influencing <lb/>
elections, who were opposed to assisted immigra<lb break="no"/>tion. Well, Sir, the time came when a wise policy <lb/>
was adopted by the Government of Canada, and <lb/>
that policy was this: Only to pay for results; but, <lb/>
in my opinion, that policy has fallen short of what <lb/>
was needed by the Dominion of Canada because of <lb/>
unwillingness on the part of both sides of this <lb/>
House to supply the money necessary for the pro<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

motion of immigration. The history of immigra<lb break="no"/>tion in the United States has been that immi<lb break="no"/>gration moved on from one basis: a basis <lb/>
along the Pacific coast, a basis stretching <lb/>
down the whole length of the original states <lb/>
that broke away from England. Here in Canada <lb/>
we have had to proceed upon a different basis. <lb/>
First you had a short territory in what were called the <lb/>
Lower Provinces; then you had Quebec, then you <lb/>
had Ontario, and there you had the great lakes <lb/>
stretching between Ontario and the territories, <lb/>
and that has necessitated that in Manitoba and the <lb/>
territories we should proceed upon a perfectly new <lb/>
basis. That has made. migration difficult for us as <lb/>
compared with what it was in the States. The <lb/>
point, therefore, I make is this: that if you are going <lb/>
to people Manitoba and the North-West Territories <lb/>
as you ought to do, and as rapidly as you ought to <lb/>
do, you must make you basis there and act from <lb/>
there; and the little Parliament in Regina has ask<lb break="no"/>ed that a sum of money should be devoted to their <lb/>
use to deal specially with immigration. Now, Sir, <lb/>
what is done by the other provinces? Ontario, <lb/>
New Brunswick, Quebec, Manitoba, has each its <lb/>
agent or agents who are all active in promoting im<lb break="no"/>migration into these provinces, and as a fact we can <lb/>
state the amount of work that has been done in <lb/>
promoting immigration into Manitoba by the very <lb/>
energetic and able man who now controls immigration <lb/>
for that province. You have that man with a num<lb break="no"/>ber of agents in various parts of Ontario for instance, <lb/>
and they are doing work that he himself can measure. <lb/>
He can tell exactly the amount of work they have <lb/>
done, and show the money value which that province <lb/>
has got from those agents. Now, what we in the <lb/>
North-West say is this: Give us the means of doing <lb/>
precisely the same thing for the North-West as has <lb/>
been done for Manitoba. What we need to do, in <lb/>
order to make Canada's position secure in the future, <lb/>
is something large in the way of promoting immi<lb break="no"/>gration. There is no reason why, if you bring in <lb/>
20,000 immigrants, you should not bring in a million. <lb/>
You have a vast field in Europe to draw from—in <lb/>
Germany, in Scandinavia, in Scotland, in England, <lb/>
in Ireland: and if that field is properly exploited, <lb/>
there is no reason whatever why, in a year or a <lb/>
couple of years, you should not bring a million of <lb/>
innnigrants to this country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Hear, hear. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I hear scornful cheers from hon. <lb/>
gentlemen around me. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. MEMBERS</persName>. No. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Are they not scornful? Then <lb/>
hon. gentlemen agree with me. If that million of <lb/>
men costs you $10,000,000, then the $10,000,000 <lb/>
are properly and fruitfully expended, because from <lb/>
that moment you secure the future of Canada, and <lb/>
I will tell you why. Suppose the bringing in of <lb/>
the million men within a year or two should cost <lb/>
$10,000,000, does it not strike every man of sense <lb/>
that that money is far more fruitfully expended <lb/>
than if you got a million of men in by the same <lb/>
expenditure spread over ten or fifteen or twenty <lb/>
years? The fact of getting them in within a short <lb/>
time not only gains the result of the expenditure of <lb/>
$10,000,000, but it secures for the country the best <lb/>
immigration a cute we can possibly have, namely, <lb/>
successful settlers. Now, Sir, in the past we have <lb/>
been trop tard. As the Minister of Agriculture <lb/>
knows, we have in the last two years been getting <lb/>

<pb n="1553" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-04-25_Page_01553.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1553</fw> <fw type="dateline">[APRIL 25, 1892.]</fw> <fw type="num">1554</fw>

most admirable settlers from Dakota, but with <lb/>
    reference to Dakota we have been <hi rendition="simple:italic">trop tard</hi>; if we <lb/>
had begun there a year earlier we should have had <lb/>
far better results. Now, what we want with <lb/>
regard to Canada generally is a large immigration <lb/>
movement. Without that, you cannot build up in <lb/>
Canada what we all want, a nation; but with our <lb/>
vast resources, and our magificent waterways <lb/>
and harbours, there cannot be the least doubt <lb/>
that if we make the same effort to secure immigra<lb break="no"/>tion from the congested districts of Europe that <lb/>
the people of the United States have made, we can <lb/>
make the future position of Canada secure, and <lb/>
that is the only way it can be made secure. So <lb/>
much for the general question. Now, in regard to <lb/>
the particular question of the North-West, it is the <lb/>
great field into which we want to pour the immi<lb break="no"/>grants, because even Manitoba is getting pretty <lb/>
well filled, as well as the other provinces; but in <lb/>
the North-West you have a country that can <lb/>
sustain a hundred million people, and that country, <lb/>
Sir, is the future backbone of Canada. Make the <lb/>
North-West a success, and the future of Canada is <lb/>
secured. I ask, therefore, that the Government here <lb/>
should give the little Government of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West at once the means of dealing with that pro<lb break="no"/>blem, which is the great problem for Canada as <lb/>
well as for the North-West. All the other pro<lb break="no"/>blems will settle themselves; but if we go on <lb/>
without increasing in population, then failure will <lb/>
be the doom of Canada. Suppose you gave the <lb/>
North-West Government $20,000 or $30,000 <lb/>
this year to spend on immigration; why, <lb/>
Sir, $100,000 would be fruitfully expended <lb/>
on immigration to the North-West. Think <lb/>
of our vast harvest of last year; how much <lb/>
of the returns from that has flowed into the pockets <lb/>
of the people of eastern Canada? Merchants who <lb/>
do business with the west will tell you that their <lb/>
best customers, those most certain in sending orders <lb/>
and in meeting their bills, are the people of the <lb/>
North-West; and I say that as a mere matter of <lb/>
prudent investment, you cannot do better than <lb/>
place a large sum in the estimates to be at the dis<lb break="no"/>posal of the Government of the North-West in pro<lb break="no"/>moting immigration. On previous occasions I have <lb/>
dealt with the other questions involved in these <lb/>
resolutions, with regard to some of which I think <lb/>
the Govermnent have already done their part; <lb/>
but this question of immigration, as I have said in <lb/>
this House, is the master question for Canada. It <lb/>
is the question to which the statesmen desiring to <lb/>
build up a great nation here will apply their whole <lb/>
energy; and instead of frittering away our time <lb/>
and spending a few thousand dollars a year upon <lb/>
it, it is something on which we might well concen<lb break="no"/>trate our attention and so build up a great, a pros<lb break="no"/>perous, and a united Canada. <lb/></p> 

<p>Motion agreed to. <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>