<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1892-03-17" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1892-03-17">17 March 1892</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, Second Session</title>.
<date when="1892"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="222"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-03-17_Page_00217.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-03-17_Page_00219.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-03-17_Page_00221.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-23">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-03-17_Page_00217"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-03-17_Page_00217.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-03-17_Page_00219"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-03-17_Page_00219.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-03-17_Page_00221"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-03-17_Page_00221.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="217" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-03-17_Page_00217.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">217</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MARCH 17, 1892.]</fw> <fw type="num">218</fw>

<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</head> 

<head rendition="simple:right">Thursday, 17th March, 1892.</head>

<head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES ACT <lb/>
AMENDMENT.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName> moved for leave to introduce <lb/>
Bill (No. 27) further to amend the North-West <lb/>
Territories's Act. He said: The Bill which I have <lb/>
the honour to introduce deals with two subjects: one, <lb/>
that of duality of language in the North-West <lb/>

<cb/>

Territories, and the other the subject of education. <lb/>
The question of the languages, or of the duality <lb/>
of language in the North-West Territories, was <lb/>
very fully discussed in this House two sessions ago, <lb/>
and, as hon. gentlemen who were members of the <lb/>
House in that session, and who are still here, will <lb/>
remember, it ended in a compromise resolution, <lb/>
which was passed at the instance of the Government <lb/>
and acquiesced in by the great body of gentlemen, <lb/>
I do not think by all those constituting the Oppo<lb break="no"/>sition. That compromise I did not accede to, nor <lb/>
do I now think it was a wise one. It may have <lb/>
been, perhaps, a political necessity, but I do not <lb/>
think that in the interests of the country it was <lb/>
a wise and judicious result. Before that time, the <lb/>
law was, and had been since 1877, that the French <lb/>
language as well as the English should be official in <lb/>
four different matters. That is, it was permissible <lb/>
either to use English or French in the debates of the <lb/>
Assembly which was constituted for the North-<lb break="yes"/>West: it was compulsory that the proceedings of <lb/>
the Assembly should be recorded in both languages: <lb/>
it was permissible to use both languages in the <lb/>
courts; and it was compulsory that the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Legislative Council, as it then was, should <lb/>
publish the ordinances they passed from time to <lb/>
time in both the languages. The compromise <lb/>
which was agreed to, and to which I have already <lb/>
made reference, provided that after the then <lb/>
coming and since happening election in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West the councillors for the North-West should <lb/>
have power to say how their proceedings should be <lb/>
conducted. and they should have authority to <lb/>
declare that the proceedings of the Assembly might <lb/>
be recorded in either one or both languages, but so <lb/>
far as the courts were concerned, and so far as the <lb/>
publication of the laws were concerned, the old <lb/>
provision remained. So that, although I do not <lb/>
think it is generally understood throughout the <lb/>
country, if there is an evil in the preservation or <lb/>
in the permission granted, or rather in the compul<lb break="no"/>sion placed on the people of the North-West to use <lb/>
the two languages, that evil still exists. I did not <lb/>
complain, I do not know anybody complained of the <lb/>
fact that members of the Legislative Assembly <lb/>
might speak in both languages or either language, <lb/>
or in any language. That was a matter, I think, <lb/>
which might be left to the Assembly itself. <lb/>
What I did complain of, and what those who <lb/>
thought as I did felt to be wrong, was that <lb/>
in the North-West Territories it was made compul<lb break="no"/>sory on the people to adopt the two languages; <lb/>
in other words, that the French language should <lb/>
stand, so far as the North-West Territories were con<lb break="no"/>cerned, on a par with the English language. I do <lb/>
not intend to do more than briefly state the history <lb/>
of this question, which will enable the House fully <lb/>
to understand it; and I need only address those <lb/>
members who were not present two years ago, in <lb/>
regard to this double language question. In the <lb/>
early days in the French province, now the province <lb/>
of Quebec, there was the right claimed, and I do not <lb/>
think it was an unreasonable right, by the gentle<lb break="no"/>men elected to the Legislative Council of that <lb/>
province, to speak in their own language. It was <lb/>
impossible for them, probably, to speak in English <lb/>
or any other language, and the request was con<lb break="no"/>ceded, not as a matter of law but of right, to <lb/>
address their fellow members in their own language. <lb/>
I repeat that that appears to have not been at all <lb/>
an objectionable request. But the difficulty that <lb/>

<pb n="219" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-03-17_Page_00219.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">219</fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">220</fw>

arose from that proceeding led in 1840—and I do <lb/>
not desire at this stage of the discussion to intro<lb break="no"/>duce anything of a controversial character, remem<lb break="no"/>bering the rebuke administered to me on the last <lb/>
occasion by the leader of the Opposition—to the <lb/>
perpetuation of race distinctions which unfortun<lb break="no"/>ately, owing to circumstances, existed in Canada. <lb/>
In 1841, in the Bill uniting the two provinces of <lb/>
Upper and Lower Canada the French language <lb/>
was prohibited. That Act remained in force for six <lb/>
or seven years when its repeal took place in England, <lb/>
on the petition of the Parliament of Old Canada, and <lb/>
then again the French language became permissive. <lb/>
At the time of Confederation an Act was passed <lb/>
which declared that the French language should <lb/>
stand, so far as this Parliament was concerned and <lb/>
in the matters referred to in the statutes and in the <lb/>
courts of Canada, on an equality with the English <lb/>
language; and so the law stood in the Province of <lb/>
Quebec. But that law did not extend to the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Ontario. and, of course, it had no reference <lb/>
to the Province of New Brunswick or Nova Scotia, <lb/>
nor did that law apply to the Province of Prince <lb/>
Edward Island when it became part of the confed<lb break="no"/>eracy, nor to the Province of British Columbia. It <lb/>
was, however. unfortunately as I venture to think, <lb/>
made a part of the law of the Province of Manitoba <lb/>
when a constitution was granted to that part of the <lb/>
North-West, and in 1877, when an amendment <lb/>
took place to the North-West Territories Act. it <lb/>
was made compulsory also in the North-West <lb/>
Territories. And so it remained without question <lb/>
until I had the honour to bring the matter before <lb/>
the House a session or two ago, when, after a long <lb/>
and rather acrimonious discussion, the compromise <lb/>
was arrived at to which I have referred. Now <lb/>
that promise was not carried into law until last <lb/>
year, but in the North-West Territories Act of <lb/>
last session, when very enlarged powers were <lb/>
granted to the people of the Territories, this par<lb break="no"/>ticular provision to which I refer was enacted and is <lb/>
now to he found on the statute. The proposition <lb/>
is to eliminate that, to repeal that clause, and that <lb/>
is all, Sir, that I can say in order to make perfectly <lb/>
plain what the object of the Bill is with regard to <lb/>
the duality of languages. I have mentioned that <lb/>
it deals also with the subject of education. Now, <lb/>
the genius of our constitution is: that the subject <lb/>
of education belongs to the Local (Governments, the <lb/>
provincial bodies. That is the general scheme <lb/>
of the British North America Act, and it is <lb/>
upon that basis that province after province <lb/>
which has been added to the Dominion, has been <lb/>
entrusted with the absolute and exclusive control <lb/>
of legislative matters. But between the old <lb/>
provinces of Canada there was an arrange<lb break="no"/>ment come to at the time of Confederation, by <lb/>
which, as we all know, separate school privileges <lb/>
were made perpetual so far as the constitution <lb/>
could make it perpetual upon the people of the <lb/>
Province of Ontario. I am not dealing with that <lb/>
question in the slightest degree. Of course we all <lb/>
know that this Parliament has no power to deal <lb/>
with it. It is an imperial Act which this Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment has no power to alter, change, or amend. <lb/>
But, when in 1875, the constitution was first con<lb break="no"/>ferred upon the Nort-West Territories, there was <lb/>
a clause with regard to education engrafted in that <lb/>
constitution. It is peculiar in this way: that it is <lb/>
not to be found in any other of our statutes or <lb/>
constitutions, and it enacted as follows:— <lb/></p>

<cb/>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The Lieutenant Governor in Council shall pass all <lb/>
necessary ordinances in respect to education: but it shall <lb/>
therein always be provided that a majority of the rate<lb break="no"/>payers of any district or portion of the territories, or of <lb/>
any less portion or subdivision thereof, by whatever name <lb/>
the same is known, may establish such schools therein as <lb/>
they think fit,and make the necessary assessment and <lb/>
collection of rates therefor; and also, that the minority <lb/>
of the ratepayers therein, whether Protestants or Roman <lb/>
Catholics may establish separate schools therein." <lb/></p>
    </quote>
    
    
    
<p>That, the House will perceive, confers upon the <lb/>
majority of every particular locality the right to <lb/>
determine what the school is to be. The language <lb/>
is very wide indeed: <lb/></p>
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>
"May establish such schools that they think fit." <lb/></p>
    </quote>
    
    <p>
Then the minority, no matter how small, may put <lb/>
up a rival separate school in any locality whether <lb/>
that minority he composed of Roman Catholics or <lb/>
Protestants, and they are free from the necessity or <lb/>
obligation of supporting a general school. I ven<lb break="no"/>ture to say—and I do so, of course. merely speaking <lb/>
for myself and with no desire to raise a contro<lb break="no"/>versy—that no more mischievous provision is to be <lb/>
found in any Act of Parliament. If there is any <lb/>
part of the Dominion where schools ought to be not <lb/>
separate,—I am not desiring now to raise the ques<lb break="no"/>tion which divides us upon that point. I am merely <lb/>
speaking with reference to the spargeness of popula<lb break="no"/>tion in the North-West—it is in the North-West <lb/>
Territories. It seems to be an exceedingly unfor<lb break="no"/>tunate provision where there is a small population, <lb/>
that there is a provision made for two schools, one <lb/>
of the majority, and one of the minority. I contend <lb/>
that if there is any part of the Dominion where <lb/>
that provision ought not to he compulsory, it is in <lb/>
the North-West Territories. Now, we added very <lb/>
largely to the powers of the North-West Territories <lb/>
in the last session of this Parliament. We have <lb/>
conferred upon them, I think I am right in saying, <lb/>
almost every power that the ordinary (constitution <lb/>
confers upon Provincial Legislatures. We have not <lb/>
given them power to amend their own constitution; <lb/>
we did not give them power to borrow money; we did <lb/>
not give them power to manage or to sell the public <lb/>
lands, nor was the power conferred upon that body <lb/>
for the establishment or maintenance of hospitals <lb/>
and so on, but there were enormous powers con<lb break="no"/>ferred upon them—power of direct taxation, power <lb/>
towards the establishment of territorial offices and <lb/>
the appointment and payment of territorial officers, <lb/>
the establishment and maintenance of prisons and <lb/>
municipal institutions, in the territories; power to <lb/>
impose licenses for shops, saloons, taverns, and <lb/>
auctioneers and incorporation fees and so on, power <lb/>
to solemnize marriage in the territories, and power <lb/>
over territorial and civil rights. You will, therefore, <lb/>
see that we added very largely to their powers, <lb/>
but we did not enlarge their powers nor did Par<lb break="no"/>liament remove the restriction with regard to <lb/>
education. That was left untouched. Now the <lb/>
proposition is to confer upon that body the power <lb/>
to deal with education as that body may see fit, not <lb/>
by any means to say there shall not be separate <lb/>
schools, not to interfere with them in that sense, <lb/>
but to see that the legislative assemblies of the <lb/>
territories upon whom we have conferred every <lb/>
other power that can be conferred upon legislative <lb/>
assemblies, may deal with the matter of education, <lb/>
as they are competent to decide other matters. <lb/>
These are the provisions which I desire to see in<lb break="no"/>corporated in the law, and therefore I move, <lb/>
seconded by Mr. Denison, for leave to introduce <lb/>
this Bill. I may add one word further. It is with <lb/>

<pb n="221" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-03-17_Page_00221.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">221</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MARCH 17, 1892.]</fw> <fw type="num">222</fw>

some regret that I intrude this question upon the <lb/>
House at this time. I quite see, Mr. Speaker, that <lb/>
the proper opportunity to press these amendments <lb/>
would have been during the last session of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment when the subject of the added power to the <lb/>
constitution was conferred upon the North-West <lb/>
Territories. I can only say in excuse for not press<lb break="no"/>ing it then, that I was not. here at the time the Bill <lb/>
was before the House, and when I left the country <lb/>
on other business connected with my profession <lb/>
—because when I left there was practically no <lb/>
Government—I had every reason to believe that <lb/>
nothing would be done during the session, except <lb/>
to pass the Supply Bill and prorogue Parliament. <lb/>
I was assured when I got to London: I was assured <lb/>
by the High Commissioner, that he understood <lb/>
also that no further business would be done. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) Does the High Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner speak for the Government? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. Well, I think that he had <lb/>
some information. He gave me to understand <lb/>
that my opinion was correct about the business <lb/>
of the House. He gave me to understand that <lb/>
that was the programme, and I thought so myself <lb/>
when I left here, and he corroborated my opinion. <lb/>
However that may be, while I would prefer that <lb/>
this question would not come up session after ses<lb break="no"/>sion, notwithstatnling. I had thought that no <lb/>
great mischief had been done by the delay because <lb/>
the language question was not at all before the last <lb/>
session of Parliament. This Parliament has in no <lb/>
way practically pronounced upon it, and the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of education was brought to the notice of the <lb/>
House last session by my hon. friend from Muskoka <lb/>
(Mr. O'Brien), as I learned from the reading of the <lb/>
debates, with a protest and an intimation that at <lb/>
an early date it would be brought before Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment: so that I do not think much harm has been <lb/>
done by the delay of one session. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName>. Mr. Speaker, I am not sur<lb break="no"/>prised that this question should have been raised <lb/>
once more in the House by the hon. member who <lb/>
has just spoken (Mr. McCarthy). He is only <lb/>
following the course that he has adopted in the <lb/>
past, and perhaps he is only pleasing the friends <lb/>
who have retained him in a case which is similar <lb/>
to the one that we have now before the House. <lb/>
We know very well that some trouble is now <lb/>
pending in the Province of Manitoba upon this <lb/>
very same question. That trouble has been raised <lb/>
in the province by the visit of the hon. gentleman <lb/>
at a time when the question was not before the <lb/>
people at all. Following the same course, the hon. <lb/>
gentleman, though having nothing to do with the <lb/>
representation of the North-West in this House, <lb/>
much less than I have, because I am much nearer <lb/>
the people who are affected by the legislation that <lb/>
he complains of—is again trying to raise this ques<lb break="no"/>tion of religious and national feeling. We have <lb/>
already settled that question. Two years ago it <lb/>
was brought before the House, and the legislation <lb/>
of last session was the result of what the hon. <lb/>
gentleman has termed a compromise. It was <lb/>
a compromise, and it should be treated as <lb/>
such. What was abandoned at that time as <lb/>
one of the rights of the people of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West was abandoned as a compromise, so that the <lb/>
question should remain at rest for all time to come. <lb/>
It was decided then that we should give to the <lb/>
North-West Council the liberty of deciding whether <lb/>

<cb/>

their proceedings should be conducted in one or <lb/>
both of the two languages which were then official. <lb/>
We know what has since been done by the majority <lb/>
of that council who do not understand the French: <lb/>
that language has been abolished. When this <lb/>
question is raised it is always contended that <lb/>
though certain privileges may be granted to the <lb/>
French-speaking population of the Province of <lb/>
Quebec and the Catholics of that province, those <lb/>
privileges should not be extended to the rest of the <lb/>
Catholic or the French population of the Dominion <lb/>
of Canada. When it is stated that the privileges <lb/>
which exist in the Province of Quebec do not exist <lb/>
elsewhere, I answer that when the Confederation <lb/>
Act was entered into, those privileges were <lb/>
well guarded on behalf of the French and <lb/>
Catholic population of the Dominion. Have <lb/>
we not the two languages in this Parliament? <lb/>
Are not the Dominion laws printed in both <lb/>
languages? And not that in pursuance of <lb/>
the arrangement entered into at the time <lb/>
of Confederation? Why should we refuse to the <lb/>
handful of French people in the North-West the <lb/>
same privileges as those enjoyed by the French-<lb break="yes"/>Canadians of the Province of Quebec? Why should <lb/>
not both populations be treated alike? We have <lb/>
two leading languages in this. Dominion: why should <lb/>
they not both be placed on the same footing? <lb/>
Does it injure anyone that I speak French or that <lb/>
I get the laws of the country printed in my <lb/>
mother tongue? Should we disregard rights and <lb/>
privileges for the sake of a few dollars and cents? <lb/>
But, Mr. Speaker, that is not the reason at all. <lb/>
The reason is that certain gentlemen. certain <lb/>
parties, wish to excite public feeling in some parts <lb/>
of the Dominion: because they have nothing else <lb/>
by which to raise themselves above the level of the <lb/>
common people, they adopt the ways of the dema<lb break="no"/>gogue, in the hope of making themselves appear to <lb/>
be of some consequence. <lb/></p> 

<p>Motion agreed to. and Bill read the first time. <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>