<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1888-05-03"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1888-05-03">3 May 1876</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Second Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1888"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Maclean, Roger &amp; Co., Wellington Street</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="1174" to="1175"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-05-03_Page_01174.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-05-03_Page_01175.html"/> 
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-05-03_Page_01174">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-05-03_Page_01174.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-05-03_Page_01175">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-05-03_Page_01175.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1174" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-05-03_Page_01174.jpg"/>
            
            
            <fw type="num">1174</fw>  <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw>  <fw type="dateline">MAY 3,</fw> 
    
           
     <head rendition="simple:centre">CANADIAN PACIFIC RAILWAY LANDS.</head> 
     
            
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WATS2">Mr. WATSON</persName> asked, What amount of lands retained 
     <lb/>
     by the Dominion Government as provided for in 49 Vic<lb break="no"/>toria, chapter 9, is situated within the Province of Manitoba? 
     <lb/>
     Also, what amount of said lands have been retained west of 
     <lb/>
     the boundary of the Province of Manitoba and east of 
     <lb/>
     3rd Meridian? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. The negotiations with 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian Pacific Railway Company for the defining of 
     <lb/>
     the lands which are to be retained under the Act mentioned 
     <lb/>
     have been proceeding, and they will be completed as soon 
     <lb/>
     as possible after the passing of the resolution respecting the 
     <lb/>
     company's land grant now before Parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WATS2">Mr. WATSON</persName> asked, 1. Whether the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     Pacific Railway Company has made a selection of all lands 
     <lb/>
     granted to it under clause 11 of Canadian Pacific Railway 
     <lb/>
     contract? 2. What amount of said lands have been 
     <lb/>
     selected within the boundary of the Province of Manitoba? 
     <lb/>
     3. What amount of said lands have been selected between 
     <lb/>
     the western boundary of the Province of Manitoba and 3rd 
     <lb/>
     Meridian? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. 1. The Canadian 
     <lb/>
     Pacific Railway Company have selected nearly 7,000,000 
     <lb/>
     acres of the lands granted under clause 11 of the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     Pacific Railway contract. 2. The area of lands selected 
     <lb/>
     within the boundaries of Manitoba is, in acres 1,818,330. 
     <lb/>
     3. The area of lands selected between the western bound<lb break="no"/>ary of Manitoba and the 3rd Initial Meridian is, in acres, 
     <lb/>
     2,989,440. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName> asked, 1. What number of acres is there 
     <lb/>
     of unsold lands which the Canadian Pacific Railway Com<lb break="no"/>pany prepose to receive by deed of bargain and sale to 
     <lb/>
               trustees under sub-section <hi rendition="simple:italic">c</hi> of the Resolutions now before 
     <lb/>
     the House? 2 . What portions of such lands lie within the 
     <lb/>
     Railway Belt? 3. How many acres of those lands are 
     <lb/>
     there in Manitoba, and how many in the Territories, east 
     <lb/>
     ofthe 3rd Meridian? 4. How many acres have been sold 
     <lb/>
     by the company, paid for, and the deeds completed? 5. 
     <lb/>
     How many acres have been sold, but the sales are still 
     <lb/>
     incomplete? How much paid on the same, and how much 
     <lb/>
     remains due, and when and how payable? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. I am able to answer one 
     <lb/>
     of these questions, but not the whole satisfactorily, as the 
     <lb/>
     information must be obtained from the Canadian Pacific 
     <lb/>
     Railway Company. I have asked the company to provide 
     <lb/>
     the information and I expect it any moment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. Perhaps you will answer the questions 
     <lb/>
     to-morrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. If you please. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
         </div>
<!--  
         <div type="debate">
            
     <head rendition="simple:centre">LIGHTHOUSE ON STAG ISLAND.</head> 
     
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MONCRIEFF</persName> asked, Whether it is the intention of 
     <lb/>
     the Government to construct and establish a lighthouse 
     <lb/>
     on Stag Island, in the River St. Clair? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. The department has been gathering 
     <lb/>
     information and making enquiries with respect to the 
     <lb/>
     necessity of establishing a lighthouse on Stag Island, and 
     <lb/>
     the matter is now under consideration. At the time the 
     <lb/>
     Supplementary Estimates come down I shall be able to 
     <lb/>
     answer the hon. gentleman definitely. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>
         <div type="debate">  
     <head rendition="simple:centre">PUBLIC BUILDINGS AT STRATHROY.</head> 
    
            
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. McMULLEN</persName> asked, Has a site been selected for the 
     <lb/>
     proposed public buildings at Strathroy? If so, where is 
     <lb/>
     the location? Has any, and what progress been made 
     <lb/>
     towards the erection of such public buildings? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN</persName>. The site has not yet been 
     <lb/>
     selected. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
         -->
          <div type="debate">
     <head>NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES ACT.</head> 
      
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName> moved that the House 
     <lb/>
     resolve itself into Committee, to-morrow, to consider the 
     <lb/>
     following resolution :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That it is expedient to provide that there shall be payable, in respect 
     <lb/>
     of his attendance at each Session of the Legislative Assembly of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West Territories, to each elected member thereof, an indemnity 
     <lb/>
     of $500, and to each legal expert, for the like attendance, an indemnity 
     <lb/>
     of $250, in addition in each case to his actual travelling expenses, sub<lb break="no"/>ject to a proportionate reduction for each day's absence from a sitting 
     <lb/>
     of the Assembly, the amount of such reduction and of such travelling 
     <lb/>
     expenses to be ascertained in such manner as the Governor in Council 
     <lb/>
     prescribes; that there shall be payable to the Speaker of the said Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Assembly an annual salary of $500, and to the Clerk of the said 
     <lb/>
     Assembly acting also as Secretary to the Lieutenant Governor, an 
     <lb/>
     annual salary of $2,000; and that all such payments shall be made out 
     <lb/>
     of the Consolidated Revenue Fund of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). This, of course, relates to the 
     <lb/>
     House of Assembly in the North-West Territory. I would 
     <lb/>
     ask the hon. gentleman whether he has considered the pro<lb break="no"/>priety of placing at the disposal of the Governor and Legis<lb break="no"/>lature of the North-West Territory the same grant as that 
     <lb/>
     which the Provinces receive in proportion to their popula<lb break="no"/>tion; leaving to them to appoint their own clerk, regulate 
     <lb/>
     their own affairs, and to spend the money so given, in the 
     <lb/>
     way that they think best in the public service. The hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman knows at the present time that this assembly 
     <lb/>
     has really no funds with which to carry on the business of 
     <lb/>
     legislation, except such as the Government here may place 
     <lb/>
     at its disposal. If there was an account opened with the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritory, the moment a Legislature is established and money 
     <lb/>
     placed at their disposal, when they come to be admitted as 
     <lb/>
     a Province of course the whole sum so received by that 
     <lb/>
     means could be taken into consideration. It always seemed 
     <lb/>
     to me, that that would be the rational way to deal With 
     <lb/>
     them whenever they had a legislative assembly. I would 
     <lb/>
     like to know whether the hon. gentleman has considered 
     <lb/>
     the subject, and whether he proposes to invite parliamen<lb break="no"/>tary action in the matter? It will be perceived that it 
     <lb/>
     would be a little more reasonable, in conferring on them 
     <lb/>
     the power of legislation and representation, that they 
     <lb/>
     should have funds with which to carry on their operations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. This discussion will 
     <lb/>
     arise more properly on the second reading of the Bill. I 
     <lb/>
     will say to my hon. friend that we do not propose to put in 
     <lb/>
     any such vote for this year. The territories are not quite 
     <lb/>
     without revenue, as the hon. gentleman knows, and I have no 
     <lb/>
     doubt they dispose of that revenue to the best advantage of 
     <lb/>
     the territories. Those revenues are very small, certainly, 
     <lb/>
     and I am quite ready to admit the merits of the suggestion 
     <lb/>
     of the hon. gentleman. The idea is to make as little change 
     <lb/>
     as possible until they have a purely elective assembly re<lb break="no"/>presenting the people. They will be obliged, after the elec<lb break="no"/>tions, to meet very soon, and to consider what the wants of 
     <lb/>
     the country and what administrative action here they think 
     <lb/>
     would be most satisfactory for that country. The measure 
     <lb/>
     before the House is intended merely to carry out the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple, with all due respect to their suggestions for the future. 
     <lb/>
     From time to time we have had a series of resolutions pass<lb break="no"/>ed by the mingled council, in which parties were nomin<lb break="no"/>ated and parties elected. Those are contradictory in them<lb break="no"/>selves and cannot be supposed really to represent the feel<lb break="no"/>ings of the people. We propose to make no appropriation 
     <lb/>
     of a sum to be disposed of by the Governor there, including 
     <lb/>
     the Legislature, until they have really a Local Legislature 
     <lb/>
     and ascertain what their own ideas are on the subject. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Of course I do not propose to 
     <lb/>
     enter into a discussion, and I am making only a suggestion 
     <lb/>
     now. These people are contributing their proportion to 
     <lb/>
     the taxes of the country at the present time. In all the 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="1175" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1888-05-03_Page_01175.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">1888.</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">1175</fw>
            
           
           Provinces a certain portion of the revenue, so much <hi rendition="simple:italic">per 
     <lb/>
     capita</hi>, is paid over to the Provinces as provincial revenue 
     <lb/>
     for provincial purposes. My remarks had reference to the 
     <lb/>
     intention of the Government when the hon. gentleman's 
     <lb/>
     Bill is adopted, and the Legislature made completely elec<lb break="no"/>tive. It does not seem to me, and I do not say it with a view 
     <lb/>
     to provoking controversy, that it is not a matter of nego<lb break="no"/>tiation to know how much they are entitled to. As a mat<lb break="no"/>ter of right they should be entitled to the same amount 
     <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">per capita</hi>, revenue for local purposes, as in the Provinces, 
     <lb/>
     and which should be accounted for at the time of Union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
          </div>
   <div type="debate">
   
          
     <head rendition="simple:centre">THE RAILWAY ACT.</head> 
   
   
            <p>
     House resolved itself into Committee on Bill (No. 24) to 
     <lb/>
     amend and consolidate the Railway Act. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     (In the Committee.) 
     <lb/>
               On section 2, sub-section <hi rendition="simple:italic">p</hi>, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. This clause, defining the word "near," 
     <lb/>
     refers to the proximity of one railway to another. Would 
     <lb/>
     it not be advisable to define the word with reference to 
     <lb/>
     some point as well? In Acts of incorporation the word 
     <lb/>
     "near" is used to define the route taken; but I do not 
     <lb/>
     know how any court could determine whether any railway 
     <lb/>
     was exceeding its powers when it is authorized to go to or 
     <lb/>
     near a point. In this vast continent that might mean 
     <lb/>
     many miles away. While I do not wish to embarrass any 
     <lb/>
     company, I think it would be well to give some statutory 
     <lb/>
     definition of the word "near" under such circumstances. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TISD1">Mr. TISDALE</persName>. It is easy to define the word, having 
     <lb/>
     regard to the relation of one railway to another; but if we 
     <lb/>
     try to define it in relation to the routes of railroads, it 
     <lb/>
     seems to me we should defeat the object the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man has in view, because "at or near " any point, describ<lb break="no"/>ing a route, will depend on all the circumstances. No 
     <lb/>
     difficulty has arisen from the want of such a definition, that 
     <lb/>
     I am aware of. Sometimes a court would hold that a quar<lb break="no"/>ter of a mile was near, and in other cases they might hold 
     <lb/>
     that two miles was near. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. Or fifty miles. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TISD1">Mr. TISDALE</persName>. No. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
      <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. Where will you draw the line? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TISD1">Mr. TISDALE</persName>. The courts will always draw the line 
     <lb/>
     according to the circumstances, and give a reasonable con<lb break="no"/>struction to the word, as they do in other cases. But I 
     <lb/>
     think if we define the word in a railroad Act, we would 
     <lb/>
     create greater difficulties than now exist. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. Suppose a railway was incorporated to 
     <lb/>
     build to or near a certain town which may be near a cer<lb break="no"/>tain other town. It might be within five or ten miles of 
     <lb/>
     the other town, and the engineering difficulties might be 
     <lb/>
     precisely the same in both cases. There might be no such 
     <lb/>
     circumstances as the hon. gentleman suggests to enable the 
     <lb/>
     court to determine how the word "near" should be con<lb break="no"/>strued. I do not think it is right to incorporate a railway 
     <lb/>
     company, giving it the utmost freedom in the choice of a 
     <lb/>
     particular route, thus causing one municipality to compete 
     <lb/>
     with another, and perhaps obliging it, by force of 
     <lb/>
     circumstances, to give a large bonus to bring the 
     <lb/>
     line within its neighborhood. If the route is not defined 
     <lb/>
     by the Act of incorporation, you give the company 
     <lb/>
     practically a roving commission, enabling it not only to 
     <lb/>
     commit the abuse I speak of, but perhaps to affect existing 
     <lb/>
     rights. Therefore I am satisfied that it is in the public in<lb break="no"/>terest that we should not incorporate these companies at 
     <lb/>
     large. I would suggest this. Every railway company 
     <lb/>
     under the general Act, has power to build branches six 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
        
   
         
     miles in length, and I think the word "near" might be 
     <lb/>
     defined here to mean not more than six miles. In the 
     <lb/>
     North-West, where there is a vast prairie country, engineer<lb break="no"/>ing difficulties would not arise to aid the court in determin<lb break="no"/>ing the meaning of the word. Suppose a company were 
     <lb/>
     incorporated to build a road in the North West near to a 
     <lb/>
     certain town. In that vast country fifty miles are equivalent 
     <lb/>
     to not more than five or ten miles in the older Provinces. 
     <lb/>
     Surely a company should not have the power to choose a 
     <lb/>
     location as wide as fifty miles; but what would enable a 
     <lb/>
     court to determine whether it was exceeding its powers or 
     <lb/>
     not? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:EDGA1">Mr. EDGAR</persName>. I think it is just as easy for a court to deter<lb break="no"/>mine when one railway comes near another as it is when 
     <lb/>
     a railway comes near a point; and I think it is quite as 
     <lb/>
     necessary to define the meaning of the word "near" in the 
     <lb/>
     latter as in the former. Not a Session passes in which a 
     <lb/>
     number of Bills are not put through the Railway Committee 
     <lb/>
     saying that the railway shall commence at or near a town 
     <lb/>
     or city or a certain point. This certainly leaves a great 
     <lb/>
     deal of doubt as to the distance intended, and I think that 
     <lb/>
     both for the general purposes of a public railway and for 
     <lb/>
     the legal effect of such a provision, some definition of dis<lb break="no"/>tance, say four, five or six miles, should be covered by the 
     <lb/>
     words "at or near." I would suggest to add to this clause 
     <lb/>
     as it stands, "and near to a point or municipality when 
     <lb/>
     some part of it is within five or six miles thereof." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <!--Unsure about THOMPSON-->
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:THOM21">Mr. THOMPSON</persName>. I do not think it is quite so 
     <lb/>
     easy to define the word "near," in relation to the 
     <lb/>
     construction of a railway, as it is in relation to its 
     <lb/>
     operation. The definition would have to be of an entirely 
     <lb/>
     different character. When we are defining the word "near" 
     <lb/>
     in this sub-section, we are dealing with the interchange of 
     <lb/>
     traffic and matters of that kind, in relation to which prox<lb break="no"/>imity must be pretty close, but when we come to deal 
     <lb/>
     with the word "near" in relation to the termini of a rail<lb break="no"/>way, as the hon. member for York mentioned, a very much 
     <lb/>
     larger limit must be given. Then, take a charter in 
     <lb/>
     which it is provided that a railway shall be built from a 
     <lb/>
     point beginning at or near a certain town. There would 
     <lb/>
     also be a good deal of practical difficulty in defining that 
     <lb/>
     word, because we would be giving a material limitation to 
     <lb/>
     a large number of charters which Parliament has already 
     <lb/>
     passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. It would not be retroactive. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:THOM21">Mr. THOMPSON</persName>. In relation to those railways which 
     <lb/>
     have not been commenced, it probably would. The limit<lb break="no"/>ation of six miles in some cases would hardly do. Some of 
     <lb/>
     the statutes, for instance, are for lines not six miles in 
     <lb/>
     length, and it would defeat the limitation in the charter 
     <lb/>
     altogether if we were to apply so lax a limit to such lines. 
     <lb/>
     The whole thing depends on the kind of country through 
     <lb/>
     which a line passes and the kind of termini it has. The 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman's suggestion, however, deals with a separate 
     <lb/>
     subject, which we can consider later, if he thinks the matter 
     <lb/>
     is of sufficient importance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               On sub-section <hi rendition="simple:italic">r</hi>, 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:THOM21">Mr. THOMPSON</persName>. In this section I do not think there 
     <lb/>
     is any change in the law; it is only a little more full. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WELD1">Mr. WELDON</persName> (St. John). I would suggest to add the 
     <lb/>
     words "or other erection" after "railway bridge." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:THOM21">Mr. THOMPSON</persName>. I will add those words. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BARR6">Mr. BARRON</persName>. I would like to ask the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     if it would not be well to define the meaning of the word 
     <lb/>
     "railway," as including the lessees of a railway. I have 
     <lb/>
     found in my professional practice that the Grand Trunk Rail<lb break="no"/>way, as lessee of the Midland Railway, have escaped all liabili[...]<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>