<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-02-24"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-02-24">24 February 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

         
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
       

          <date when="1905"/>.       
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1671" to="1672"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-24_Page_1671.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
          
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-01-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-01-06">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-24_Page_1671">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-24_Page_1671.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1671" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-24_Page_1671.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1671</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">1672</fw>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     HOUSE OF  COMMONS 
     <lb/></head>

     <p>FRIDAY, February 24, 1905. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The SPEAKER took the Chair at Three 
     <lb/>
     o’clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     FIRST READINGS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Bill (No. 74) respecting the Medicine Hat 
     <lb/>
     and Northern Alberta Railway Company.<lb break="no"/>Mr. P. Talbot by Mr. Parmelee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Bill (No. 76) respecting the. Red Deer 
     <lb/>
     Valley and Coal Company.—Mr. Campbell. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Bill (No. 77) respecting the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     Agency.—Mr. Bickerdike by Mr. Campbell. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Bill (No. 78) respecting the Macleod, Card<lb break="no"/>stone and Montana Railway Company.<lb break="no"/>Mr. Turriff by Mr. Campbell. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head>
     BATTLEFORD AND LAKE LENORE 
     <lb/>
     RAILWAY COMPANY. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. PARMELEE moved for leave to in<lb break="no"/>troduce Bill (No. 75) respecting the Battle<lb break="no"/>ford and Lake Lenore Railway Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. HENDERSON. I would like the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman to explain that Bill. I do not 
     <lb/>
     know if it is a new Bill or an extension. I 
     <lb/>
     have a suspicion that it is extending a very 
     <lb/>
     bad Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. PARMELEE. I think it simply asks 
     <lb/>
     the construction.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. HENDERSON.   I think we are en<lb break="no"/>titled to the explanation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the ﬁrst 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     FIRST READINGS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Bill (No. 79) respecting the Toronto, Ham<lb break="no"/>ilton and Buffalo Railway Company—Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Zimmerman—by Mr. A. Johnston. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Bill (No. 80) to incorporate the Woodstock 
     <lb/>
     and Lake Huron Railway.—Mr.  
     <lb/>
     A. H. Clarke. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Bill (No. 81) respecting the Ottawa River 
     <lb/>
     Railway Company, and to change its name 
     <lb/>
     to the Central Trunk Railway Company.<lb break="no"/>Mr. Piché. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head>
     PROVINCIAL GOVERNMENT IN THE 
     <lb/>
     NORTHWEST. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. FOSTER. Before the Orders of the 
     <lb/>
     Day are called, I would like to ask the 
     <lb/>
     First Minister as to the cause of the delay 
     <lb/>
     in printing of the Autonomy Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Sir WILFRID LAURIER. I think there 
     <lb/>
     has been no delay so far. I am just as 
     <lb/>
     anxious as my hon. friend is to have the 
     <lb/>
     Bill printed immediately and to take it up 
     <lb/>
     as soon as possible. I expect to have it at 
     <lb/>
     the latest on Tuesday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. FITZPATRICK. I ought to say that 
     <lb/>
     I am responsible for some of the delay that 
     <lb/>
     has occurred. In consequence of an error 
     <lb/>
           
   
           <!-- <p>
     Sir WILLIAM MULOCK. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            <cb/>
           
     in the description of the boundaries of the 
     <lb/>
     provinces, I had to get that corrected, which 
     <lb/>
     I did as soon as the Bill was in the hands of 
     <lb/>
     the Clerk of the House, and I returned it 
     <lb/>
     to him yesterday afternoon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head>
     MANITOBA ELECTION RETURNS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. FOSTER. Has the First Minister had 
     <lb/>
     an opportunity to look into the question 
     <lb/>
     which I put to him yesterday as to the 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba election returns? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Sir WILFRID LAURIER. I speak sub<lb break="no"/>ject to correction, but I believe I am right, 
     <lb/>
     when I say that all these returns are in the 
     <lb/>
     hands of the Clerk of the Crown in Chancery, 
     <lb/>
     who is an officer of this House, and it seems 
     <lb/>
     to me that the procedure would be to have 
     <lb/>
     a motion made for his attendance here. I 
     <lb/>
     have been waiting for my hon. friend the 
     <lb/>
     leader of the opposition to return in order 
     <lb/>
     that I might confer with him on that point. 
     <lb/>
     I can see no objection to that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head>
     CONTRACTS FOR GOVERNMENT 
     <lb/>
     WORKS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Hon. CHARLES FITZPATRICK (Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Justice) moved second reading of Bill 
     <lb/>
     (No. 51) respecting contracts for government 
     <lb/>
     works. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, Bill read the second 
     <lb/>
     time and House went into committee there<lb break="no"/>on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On section 1—tenders to be invited; ex<lb break="no"/>ceptions ; contracts to be awarded by the 
     <lb/>
     Governor in Council-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. FITZPATRICK. The ﬁrst clause prac<lb break="no"/>tically re-enacts the law as we have it now ; 
     <lb/>
     that is to say, it provides that the minister 
     <lb/>
     shall invite tenders for all works of which 
     <lb/>
     the estimated cost exceeds $5,000, the ex<lb break="no"/>ceptions being those works which are of 
     <lb/>
     immediate and urgent necessity and those 
     <lb/>
     of which the estimated cost does not exceed 
     <lb/>
     $5,000. The new feature is the second para<lb break="no"/>graph, which provides that all contracts 
     <lb/>
     let by tender are to be let, not by the min<lb break="no"/>ister directly, but by the minister under the 
     <lb/>
     control and with the approval of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor in Council. Having looked into the 
     <lb/>
     law, I found it necessary to make this 
     <lb/>
     change. As a matter of fact, contracts for 
     <lb/>
     works costing less than $5.000 have been 
     <lb/>
     let without tender, but there has been no 
     <lb/>
     legislative sanction for that. I am making 
     <lb/>
     this change so as to provide for the full 
     <lb/>
     approval of council to every contract that 
     <lb/>
     is made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. HAGGART. As the laws stands, I 
     <lb/>
     understand that all contracts must be let 
     <lb/>
     by tender. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. FITZPATRICK. The law as con<lb break="no"/>tained in 31 Victoria, chapter 12, section 20, 
     <lb/>
     re-enacted in the Revised Statutes as chapter 
     <lb/>
     36, section 13 provides that all contracts 
     <lb/>
     shall be let by tender except works of im- 
     <lb/>
            </p>
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>