<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1890-01-29"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1890-01-29">29 January 1890</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1890"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="119" to="122"/>
              
               <biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="160"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-29_Page_00119.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-29_Page_00121.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-29_Page_00159.html"/> 
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-29_Page_00119">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-29_Page_00119.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-29_Page_00121">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-29_Page_00121.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-29_Page_00159">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-29_Page_00159.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="119" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-29_Page_00119.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">119</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">120</fw>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. Judge Clark, 
     <lb/>
     Frank Turner and J. Kennedy were appointed on 
     <lb/>
     the 10th October, 1887, Trent Valley Commis<lb break="no"/>sioners. Judge Clark having to resign, Judge 
     <lb/>
     Charles A. Weller was appointed in his place on 
     <lb/>
     the 1st December, 1887. The entire cost of the 
     <lb/>
     Commission to date is $2,271.39. The Report of 
     <lb/>
     the Commission is expected during the present 
     <lb/>
     Session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <div type="debate">
          
     <head>LETTER OF MGR. GRANDIN.</head> 
     
           
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName> asked, Whether the Government 
     <lb/>
     are aware that the following letter has been 
     <lb/>
     addressed by His Grace Monseigneur Grandin to 
     <lb/>
     persons occupying a high position in the Province 
     <lb/>
     of Quebec :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>
   <div type="debate">
   
          
     <head>DIOCESE OF ST. ALBERT,</head> 
     
           <head rendition="simple:right">ALBERTA, N.W.T., CANADA, 20th Nov., 1889.</head> 
    
            
   
            <p>
     To His Eminence, Monseigneur Taschereau, Cardinal 
     <lb/>
     Archbishop of Quebec, and to Monseigneurs the Arch<lb break="no"/>bishops and Bishops of the late Ecclesiastical Province 
     <lb/>
     of Quebec. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Your Eminence and Most Reverend and Venerable Sirs :— 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Permit one of your humble brothers in the Episcopate, 
     <lb/>overcome by the troubles and anxieties which are crushing 
     <lb/>him, to have recourse again to your affectionate sympa<lb break="no"/>thies, hoping that you will be able to aid him at least 
     <lb/>with your prayers and your advice, and that our Saviour 
     <lb/>himself Will inspire you to devise some plan to succor 
     <lb/>him. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Since the annexation of our Territory to Canada, in the 
     <lb/>
    portion fit for settlement of my diocese, the physical 
     <lb/>hardships of former times have much diminished, they 
     <lb/>have even ceased to exist in certain localities. but I am 
     <lb/>compelled to admit that the moral afflictions which have 
     <lb/>succeeded them, especially those which we anticipated, 
     <lb/>cause us to regret the past years. At the time of the 
     <lb/>annexation the French Canadians and Métis were, we 
     <lb/>may say, the only settlers in the country which their 
     <lb/>fathers had discovered. They lived at peace with the 
     <lb/>traders of the Honorable the Hudson Bay Company, and 
     <lb/>with the few English settlers who had but recently taken 
     <lb/>up land. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After the annexation the immigrants came in great 
     <lb/>
     numbers, and I can tell you that out of every hundred 
     <lb/>
     there were but ten Catholics: the English and Protestant 
     <lb/>
     population thereupon increased rapidly, and in a few 
     <lb/>
     years we must be content to find ourselves in the min<lb break="no"/>ority.  God forbid that I should wish to accuse in a 
     <lb/>
     sweeping manner this new majority of wishing to ill-treat 
     <lb/>
     us; there are among the new comers respectable and 
     <lb/>
     honest families who regret the war that is being made 
     <lb/>
     upon us. This war, my Lords, they will not admit, but I 
     <lb/>
     for one will certify to your Eminence and your Graces 
     <lb/>
     that it is the Dominion Government which, by means of 
     <lb/>
     the staff of the Indian Department, has first declared war 
     <lb/>
     upon us, taking the initiative and with so much the less 
     <lb/>
     fairness, seeing that on their part there has been no dec<lb break="no"/>laration of war; and as for us, not being able to imagine 
     <lb/>
     all, we did not in the beginning make any resistance. Since 
     <lb/>
     the time that the Indians concluded the treaty with the 
     <lb/>
     Government the entire control of the Indian Department 
     <lb/>
     was, in my diocese at least, generally and exclusively 
     <lb/>
     under that of Protestants using the English language. 
     <lb/>
     For reasons which they will not admit at any time these 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen compel our Christian Indians to withdraw 
     <lb/>
     from our establishments, in consequence of which we were 
     <lb/>
     compelled to close them. This conduct was as equally 
     <lb/>
     opposed to the treaty conditions as to the physical and 
     <lb/>
     moral interests of the Indians. When, after that we 
     <lb/>
     desired to establish ourselves among the Indians at their 
     <lb/>
     own request, you could not conceive the difficulties which 
     <lb/>
     they stirred up against us. Without regard to the relig<lb break="no"/>ious faith and the wish of the Indians, Protestant schools 
     <lb/>
     were the only ones granted to them; and the poor Indians 
     <lb/>
     were pressed, even threatened, to compel  them to send 
     <lb/>
     their children to schools where their faith was not re<lb break="no"/>spected. Apart from an industrial school, there is not in 
     <lb/>
     my diocese a single Catholic school which we were not 
     <lb/>
     obliged to establish ourselves, often against a lively oppo<lb break="no"/>sition, and to support in a measure in the beginning. In 
     <lb/>
     November, 1887, I was assured most positively from Otta<lb break="no"/>was that such a course of action was going to cease. I must 
     <lb/>
     certify that the persecution—I can make use of no other 
     <lb/>
     word—is more keen than ever. In spite of all this, you 
     <lb/>
     will be suprised to hear it we are the guilty ones; like 
     <lb/>
           

           
            <cb/>
           
     good sheep we should allow ourselves to be torn and 
     <lb/>
     swallowed without even a bleat. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This fanaticism is an epidemic and has spread from the 
     <lb/>
     reserves to certain centres of civilisation. Our schools 
     <lb/>
     are hunted down. It is a crime for us to take advantage 
     <lb/>
     of the education laws to procure assistance from the 
     <lb/>
     Government. Our reports are studied: they are found 
     <lb/>
     fault with, in order more especially to be able to accuse 
     <lb/>
     us and deprive us of that asslstance which is ours by right. 
     <lb/>
     Although in the minority, we might be able, never<lb break="no"/>theless, to send two representatives to the House, but 
     <lb/>
     they have succeeded in making this a thing imposslble 
     <lb/>
     for us. I again charge the Dominion Government, who 
     <lb/>
     in marking out the electoral-districts have divided up the 
     <lb/>
     two French Catholic centres in such a manner that it is 
     <lb/>
     impossible for us to secure representation. You are also 
     <lb/>
     acquainted with what is going on this very day at Regina. 
     <lb/>
     In spite of the efforts of the Honorable J. Royal, Lieu<lb break="no"/>tenant-Governor of the North-West, and the Honorable 
     <lb/>
     Judge Rouleau, all our representatives, not one of whom 
     <lb/>
     is a Catholic, demand, with two exceptions, the abolition 
     <lb/>
     of our language and the amendment. of our school laws 
     <lb/>
     in order to impose upon us the so-called secular schools 
     <lb/>
     which are nothing else but anti-Catholic schools, even 
     <lb/>
     admitting that they are not Godless schools. Imagine 
     <lb/>
     what will be the consequence of all this, in a new coun<lb break="no"/>try, in a savage country. These petitions were addressed 
     <lb/>
     to His Excellency the Governor General in the name of 
     <lb/>
     the people of the North-West. They are certainly not 
     <lb/>
     ignorant how we are opposed to these doings, but we 
     <lb/>
     count for nothing in the eyes of these gentlemen. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This studied contempt ot the French Catholic opulation 
     <lb/>
     has already had very sad consequences. Although the 
     <lb/>
     Half-breeds gained nothing by their uprising, they are not 
     <lb/>
     on that account more insensible to contempt. Nothing 
     <lb/>
     would at this moment he easier than to fire the powder. 
     <lb/>
     Let one of those so-called loyalists, so ready to question 
     <lb/>
     our loyalty and patriotism, presume that another rebellion 
     <lb/>
     would advantage him, and he will find all the less diffi<lb break="no"/>culty in inciting our population to it because our Catholics 
     <lb/>
     have no longer the same reliance in their clergy. They 
     <lb/>
     have been told so often that we are paid by the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     Government to work for it against them, that they now 
     <lb/>
     believe this. Certainly. we have supported it, as we 
     <lb/>
     always sustain constituted authonty; but we are bound 
     <lb/>
     to acknowledge that we have been very badly requited, 
     <lb/>
     and those who have found fault with us on this account 
     <lb/>
     are partly justified. Nevertheless, the French Catholic 
     <lb/>
     party, which is now in the background, has rights of 
     <lb/>
     which it cannot be deprived without injustice, it even 
     <lb/>
     has a right to the gratitude of the powerful party which 
     <lb/>
     is inclined to oppress it. Are not these French Canadians 
     <lb/>
     and Half-breeds the men who made possible the settle<lb break="no"/>ment of the North-West, who rendered more easy the 
     <lb/>
     intercourse between the white man and the Indian, and 
     <lb/>
     who are to this day the connecting link between them? 
     <lb/>
     But it seems that gratitude, even the remembrance of an 
     <lb/>
     obligation, is not a quality to be met with in the powerful; 
     <lb/>
     and that we, the minority, must submit to being of no 
     <lb/>
     consequence socially, and should only he too glad if we 
     <lb/>
     are allowed to live as conquered outcasts. Although 
     <lb/>
     possessing a certain amount of humility, which I have 
     <lb/>
     tried to practice, I can hardly resign myself to existence 
     <lb/>
     on such terms. I am often told that a French Catholic 
     <lb/>
     immigration into the North-West should be organised. 
     <lb/>
     This is very true; but what can I do towards this immi<lb break="no"/>gration? One can do nothing without money, and I have 
     <lb/>
     none—our population is poor. If, with this object in view, 
     <lb/>
     I appeal to your charity, you will doubtless repeat what 
     <lb/>
     several persons in your dioceses have ver properly said 
     <lb/>
     to me: The Province of Quebec must not be depopulated 
     <lb/>
     in order to people the boundless North-West. Very true, 
     <lb/>
     my Lords, but without impoverishing yourselves, bestow 
     <lb/>
     upon us at least the crumbs which fall from your tables. 
     <lb/>
    How many thousands of your flock leave each year for the 
     <lb/>United States, where they too often lose both spiritual 
     <lb/>and bodily health, and are moreover lost, not only to your 
     <lb/>Province, but to the Dominion, unless we are to imagine 
     <lb/>that the prepare the way for a union between Canada 
     <lb/>and the United States. Both you and I, my Lords, have 
     <lb/>other views and other hopes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     If even one-fourth of those who emigrated from your 
     <lb/>
     Province during the past ten years had come to us, we 
     <lb/>
     would still constitute the majority or would at all events 
     <lb/>
               be a powerful minority which would have to be taken in<lb break="no"/>to account and against which none would think of enact<lb break="no"/>ing extraordinary laws. To people this territory, to peo<lb break="no"/>ple <hi rendition="simple:italic">our land</hi>, as the aborigines call it—and the Half-breeds 
     <lb/>
     and French Canadians have some right to use that ex<lb break="no"/>pression; for French Canadians discovered this vast 
     <lb/>
     country: French Canadians and Half-breeds opened it 
     <lb/>
               up to religion and colonisation—to settle <hi rendition="simple:italic">our lands</hi> there 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="121" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-29_Page_00121.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">121</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 29, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">122</fw> 
     
          
     are sent men from every nation, men without faith and 
     <lb/>
     without religion; Mennonites are brought from a great 
     <lb/>
     distance, even Mormons are admitted and are seemingly 
     <lb/>
     held up as examples to the Blackfeet; yet each year a 
     <lb/>
     multitude of Canadians are allowed to depart—honest 
     <lb/>
     and hard working, but too poor to come this far to settle. 
     <lb/>
     Do you not think, my lords, that this is a great evil? Can 
     <lb/>
     no remedy be found? Since our Government appears to 
     <lb/>
     take no heed, I think that, with the assistance of your 
     <lb/>
     patriotic and devoted clergy, of your pious intelligent 
     <lb/>
     and influential laymen, of generous charity of every one, 
     <lb/>
     you could enable those brave Canadians to settle com<lb break="no"/>fortably in the North-West. You would obtain from the 
     <lb/>
    Dominion Government and from the various railway 
     <lb/>companies the means of preserving to Canada these good 
     <lb/>and upright citizens; and the Provmce of Quebec would 
     <lb/>be none the poorer, but would, on the contrary, acquire 
     <lb/>strength by extending its influence, and would at the 
     <lb/>same time protect the poor Canadians who are threat<lb break="no"/>ened with the fate of outcasts on their own lands. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     I therefore beseech you, my Lords, as well in my own 
     <lb/>
     name as in that of my missionaries, in the name of the 
     <lb/>
     French Catholic party, in the name above all of the inter<lb break="no"/>ests of the Church in the North-West, to see What you can 
     <lb/>
     do, and I appeal to you, in the name of God, to take ac<lb break="no"/>tion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Pardon my pressing entreaty, and believe me, my Lords, 
     <lb/>your most devoted and grateful servant and brother. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     2nd. Have the Government any reason to doubt 
     <lb/>
     Bishop Grandin's word, who signed the said letter? 
     <lb/>
     3rd. Is it the intention of the Government to take 
     <lb/>
     any steps to remedy grievances complained of by 
     <lb/>
     the Bishop, what steps and when? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment have not received the letter set out in the 
     <lb/>
     question, or any copy of it. I have been informed 
     <lb/>
     that it appeared, without signature, in the Montreal 
     <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Witness</hi>. I would simply say that the letter has 
     <lb/>
     never come before the Government except in the 
     <lb/>
     manner I have mentioned. The Government will 
     <lb/>
     attend to the complaints of Monseigneur Grandin, 
     <lb/>
     and those of any other clergyman or person in 
     <lb/>
     Canada who has any complaints to make. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>
            <div type="debate">
            
     <head>CRANE ISLAND MAIL SERVICE.</head> 
     
     
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:CHOQ1">Mr. CHOQUETTE</persName> asked, Whether it is the 
     <lb/>intention of the Government to cause for the future 
     <lb/>the mail service of Crane Island, in the County of 
     <lb/>Montmagny, to be performed by way of Montmag<lb break="no"/>ny or by way of Giles' Bay? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Mr. HAGGART</persName>. The question is now engaging 
     <lb/>
     the attention of the Department. No decision has 
     <lb/>
     yet been arrived at. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="debate">
           
     <head>SUMMERSIDE HARBOR, P.E.I.</head> 
     <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PERR1">Mr. PERRY</persName> asked, Whether a further exami<lb break="no"/>nation for a breakwater at the entrance of Sum<lb break="no"/>merside harbor, Prince Edward Island, has been 
     <lb/>
     made during the year 1889, as promised by the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Public Works during last Session? If 
     <lb/>
     so, has the engineer made a report thereon? 
     <lb/>
     </p>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN</persName>. Yes, an examina<lb break="no"/>tion was made of Summerside harbor last season, 
     <lb/>
     and a report has been submitted. The work pro<lb break="no"/>posed for the improvement of the entrance to the 
     <lb/>
     harbor consists of a breakwater extending south<lb break="no"/>wardly from Willing's Point a distance of 3,800 
     <lb/>
     feet, and a second from the lighthouse 1,000 feet in 
     <lb/>
     a southerly direction towards Indian Head, the 
     <lb/>
     cost of these two structures being placed at 
     <lb/>
    $75,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
               
            </div>
            <div type="debate">
               
            
     <head>MIMINIGASH BREAKWATER, P.E.I.</head> 
    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:PERR1">Mr. PERRY</persName> asked, Whether it is the intention 
     <lb/>
     of the hon. Minister of Public Works to repair the 
     <lb/>
     damages done to the Mimingash breakwater, 
     <lb/>
     Prince Edward Island, as promised last Session by 
     <lb/>
     the Minister? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN</persName>. As the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man puts in his question the words, "As promised 
     <lb/>
     last Session by the Minister," I may say that on 
     <lb/>
               referring to <hi rendition="simple:italic">Hasard</hi>, I find that on April 22nd 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman asked this question: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
      <p>
     "Is the Department of Public Works aware of the 
     <lb/>
     amount of damages done to the breakwater at Mimini<lb break="no"/>gash, P.E.I., last fall? If so, is it the intention of the 
     <lb/>
     department to repair said breakwater immediately?" 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     The answer given by me was : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "The attention of the Department was called to the 
     <lb/>
     damage done to this breakwater, and the matter is now 
     <lb/>
     receiving the attention of my department." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. What do you do this year? 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LANG1">Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN</persName>. That is not asked. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="debate">
           
     <head>THE TRADE IN OLEOMARGARINE.</head> 
     
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIN2">Mr. BAIN</persName> (Wentworth) asked, Is the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     of Canada the British North America referred to 
     <lb/>
     in the official Trade Returns of the United States 
     <lb/>
     for the eleven months ending November 30th last, 
     <lb/>
     which show, among exports to British North 
     <lb/>
     America, "Oleomargarine, 534,146 lbs"? If so, 
     <lb/>
     has the hon. Minister of Customs any reason to be<lb break="no"/>lieve that oleomargarine enters into consumption 
     <lb/>
     in Canada under a fraudulent or assumed name? 
     <lb/>
     Has any recent investigation been made by the 
     <lb/>
     officers of the Department to ascertain whether it 
     <lb/>
     is being brought into the Dominion, in evasion of 
     <lb/>
     the statute forbidding its importation? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOWE1">Mr. BOWELL</persName>. There is reason to believe that 
     <lb/>
     the part of "British North America" to which the 
     <lb/>
     oleomargarine referred to is exported, is the 
     <lb/>
     colony of Newfoundland. There is no evidence 
     <lb/>
     that any of it was imported to Canada, and entered 
     <lb/>
     into consumption in the Dominion. The officers of 
     <lb/>
     Customs are instructed to exercise constant vigil<lb break="no"/>ance everywhere for the prevention of such viola<lb break="no"/>tion of law. A few pounds of the article was sent 
     <lb/>
     to a party in St. Thomas, Ont., from Chicago as a 
     <lb/>
     sample without orders. It was seized by the Col<lb break="no"/>lector of Customs and confiscated by the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment. A consignment of oleomargarine from the 
     <lb/>
     United States to a party in Halifax was entered 
     <lb/>
     for consumption, and was seized by the Customs 
     <lb/>
     officials, but upon evidence being produced that the 
     <lb/>
     entry was made in mistake, it was allowed to be 
     <lb/>
     amended and the article exported to Newfound<lb break="no"/>land. Similar entries were made in Cornwall, Ont., 
     <lb/>
     in December last, which are under seizure, the 
     <lb/>
     parties who imported claiming that they purchased 
     <lb/>
     it as butter, and they are holding it for exportation 
     <lb/>
     to Great Britain. There is reason to believe that 
     <lb/>
     a great quantity of oleomargarine passes through 
     <lb/>
               Canada <hi rendition="simple:italic">in transitu</hi> to other countries, and that in 
     <lb/>
     this as in other articles exported from the United 
     <lb/>
     States, which are forwarded through the Dominion, 
     <lb/>
     are entered in the Export Returns of the United 
     <lb/>
     States as being exported to British North America, 
     <lb/>
     that being the first foreign country which the[...] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="159" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-29_Page_00159.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">159</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">160</fw>
            <p>
     [...]ment. They were posted in small towns where 
     <lb/>
     there were neither express offices nor money order 
     <lb/>
     offices, or banks,or any other mode of transmitting 
     <lb/>
     money, except by registered letter; and if the hon. 
     <lb/>
     the Postmaster General can see his way clear, un<lb break="no"/>der the law, to reimburse the sufferers, I am ex<lb break="no"/>tremely desirous that he should carry out the sug<lb break="no"/>gestion I now make, and allow his sympathies to 
     <lb/>
     be extended towards those poor people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Mr. HAGGART</persName>. The facts of the case are, as 
     <lb/>
     Mr. White has stated, that a robbery was com<lb break="no"/>mitted at the post office and a lot of money taken 
     <lb/>
     from several registered letters lying in the safe. 
     <lb/>
     These parties who have lost the money are entitled 
     <lb/>
     to every sympathy; but it is a rule of the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment, which cannot be departed from in any case, 
     <lb/>
     that losses of that kind are never made good. 
     <lb/>
     This is the rule laid down in England and the 
     <lb/>
     United States, and in other countries which have 
     <lb/>
     similar regulations, and a departure from that rule 
     <lb/>
     would entail a very great responsibility on the 
     <lb/>
     Government which they would not be justified in 
     <lb/>
     assuming. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="debate">
              
           <head rendition="simple:centre">RETURN ORDERED.</head> 
    
   
            <p>
     Statement showing the amount of dredging done dur<lb break="no"/>ing the season of 1889, in Prince Edward Island, by the 
     <lb/>
               dredge <hi rendition="simple:italic">Prince Edward</hi>, the names of harbors and other 
     <lb/>
     places dredged during said season, and the amount 
     <lb/>
     of work done in each harbor.—(Mr. Perry.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN</persName> moved the adjourn<lb break="no"/>ment of the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to; and House adjourned at 
     <lb/>
     4.45 p.m. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="debate">
   
   
          
     <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</head> 
     
   
          
     <head rendition="simple:right">Friday, 31st January, 1890.</head> 
    
     
     
     
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> took the Chair at Three o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
           <p><emph>PRAYERS.</emph></p> 
    
            </div>
            <div type="debate">
           
           
            <head rendition="simple:centre">FIRST READINGS.</head> 
     
   
            <p>
     Bill (No. 33) respecting the People's Bank of 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick.—(Mr. Weldon, St. John.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Bill (No. 34) to amend the Act to incorporate the 
     <lb/>
    Saskatchewan Railway and Mining Company. 
     <lb/>—(Mr. Small.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Bill (No. 35) to incorporate the Calgary and 
     <lb/>
     Edmonton Railway Company. —(Mr. Small.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Bill (No. 36) to confirm the agreement between 
     <lb/>
     the Qu'Appelle, Long Lake and Saskatchewan 
     <lb/>
     Steamship and Railway Company and the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     Pacific Railway.—(Mr. Davis, Alberta.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Bill (No. 37) to amend the Act to incorporate the 
     <lb/>
     Imgerial Trust Company of Canada.—(Mr. Huds<lb break="no"/>peth.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            </div>
            <div type="debate">
   
   
           
     <head rendition="simple:centre">DOMINION ELECTIONS ACT.</head> 
    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName> moved for leave to introduce 
     <lb/>
     Bill (No. 38) further to amend the Dominion Elec<lb break="no"/>tions Act, chapter 8 of the Revised Statutes of 
     <lb/>
     Canada. He said: The object of this amendment 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
          
     is to provide against promises on the part of Candi<lb break="no"/>dates, of Government expenditure in their ridings. 
     <lb/>Another object is to provide that the Government 
     <lb/>shall not expend money for the purpose of influenc<lb break="no"/>ing elections, that being one of the most fruitful 
     <lb/>and dangerous sources of corruption existing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to; and Bill read the first time. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            </div>
               <div type="debate">
               
          <head rendition="simple:centre">THE FRENCH LANGUAGE IN THE NORTH-<lb break="yes"/>WEST.</head>
           
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. Before the Orders of the 
     <lb/>
     Day are called, I would ask the leader of the 
     <lb/>
     House whether it would not be convenient that a 
     <lb/>
     day should be fixed for the second reading of the 
     <lb/>
     Bill that stands in my name with reference to the 
     <lb/>
     North-West Territories Act. I have suggested to 
     <lb/>
     him Wednesday week, if that would be convenient 
     <lb/>
     to the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. This is a subject 
     <lb/>
     that will interest the House a good deal, and it 
     <lb/>
     would be well that a day should be fixed. The 
     <lb/>
     day suggested, Wednesday, the 12th February, 
     <lb/>
     would be a very convenient day, provided it meets, 
     <lb/>
     the convenience of the leader of the Opposition. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. As far as this side is concern<lb break="no"/>ed, we are quite prepared to take it up on that day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:COOK5">Mr. COOK</persName>. I may not be here then, owing to 
     <lb/>
     other business; but I will forestall the course I 
     <lb/>
     intend to take by stating that, if here, I shall cer<lb break="no"/>tainly vote against the Bill.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. This is certainly 
     <lb/>
     an appeal to my hon. friend's magnanimity, and I 
     <lb/>
     think he should consult the hon. member for East 
     <lb/>
     Simcoe, and ascertain what day will suit him. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I would be quite willing to 
     <lb/>
     do that, but as the hon. gentleman has indicated 
     <lb/>
     his intention, before hearing any discussion on the 
     <lb/>
     subject, of voting against the Bill, perhaps that is 
     <lb/>
     unnecessary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:COOK5">Mr. COOK</persName>. I have read the speech of my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend on the subject, and the Bill speaks for itself. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName> moved that the Order for 
     <lb/>
     second reading of Bill (No. 10) further to amend 
     <lb/>
     the Revised Statutes of Canada, chapter 50, respect<lb break="no"/>ing the North-West Territories, be the first Order 
     <lb/>
     of the day on Wednesday, the 12th of February. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
               </div>
            <div type="debate">
                  
           <head rendition="simple:centre">SUPPLY.</head> 
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName> moved that the House resolve itself 
     <lb/>
     into Committee of Supply. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. What rule 
     <lb/>
     does the hon. gentleman propose to adopt? I would 
     <lb/>
     suggest that we should proceed regularly through 
     <lb/>
     these items, and if for any reason the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment wish to alter that course, they should give us 
     <lb/>
     notice the night before, so that we shall know from 
     <lb/>
     day to day what items are likely to be taken up. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. I think the suggestion of the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman is one that will meet the a pro<lb break="no"/>bation of both sides of the House, and I wil see 
     <lb/>
     that this order is carried out. I might also sug<lb break="no"/>gest, before we go into Committee, whether or not 
     <lb/>
     we could agree, as far as possible, in going over 
     <lb/>
     the items of Civil Government, to keep our dis<lb break="no"/>cussion to the items which are before the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee. Last year, as will be remembered, we 
     <lb/>
     were led, while taking up the items of Civil[...] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>