<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-02-23" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-02-23">23 February 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          

         
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
                 

          <date when="1905"/>.     
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1593" to="1596"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-23_Page_1593.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-23_Page_1595.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-01-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-01-06">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-23_Page_1593">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-23_Page_1593.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-23_Page_1595">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-23_Page_1595.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1593" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-23_Page_1593.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">1593</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 23. 1905</fw> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>[...] been, since the lst of July, 1904, replaced by 
     <lb/>
    automatic acetylene gas lights ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>2. What annual saving will these changes 
     <lb/>
     effect ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. How many keepers have in consequence of 
     <lb/>
     these changes been dismissed ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>4. Who were they, and what were their for<lb break="no"/>mer salaries ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>

            <p><persName ref="pers:PREF1">Hon. RAYMOND PREFONTAINE</persName> (Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Marine and
               Fisheries) : <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>1. Thirty-two. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2. $910. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. Five. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>4. Thomas Fraser, Windmill Point light, 
     <lb/>
     $180 ; John Hamilton, Hamilton's island 
     <lb/>
     light, $130 ; Barnaby Malette, lightship No. 
     <lb/>
     1, $250 ; Vital Crépin, lightship No. 2, $300; 
     <lb/>
     Michel Allard, lightship No. 3, $300. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">HALIFAX FISHERY AWARD.</head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. A. MARTIN</persName> asked :</p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            
<p>1. Has the government decided to distribute 
     <lb/>
     among the provinces interested, the amount of 
     <lb/>
     the award received by Canada, generally known 
     <lb/>
     as the Halifax Fishery Award ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2. If so, on what basis is the distribution pro<lb break="no"/>posed to be made ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. If not, is the question to be submitted for 
     <lb/>
     decision to the Privy Council of England or the 
     <lb/>
     Supreme Court of Canada. ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>4. Will the government take action in regard 
     <lb/>
     to the settlement of this question during the 
     <lb/>
     present session of parliament, if not, already 
     <lb/>
     settled ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>


   
            <p><persName ref="pers:PREF1">Hon. RAYMOND PREFONTAINE</persName> (Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Marine
                  and Fisheries) : <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>1. No. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2, 3 and 4, answered by No. 1. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. A. MARTIN</persName>. Is the third section of <lb/> the question
                  answered ? <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:PREF1">Mr. PREFONTAINE</persName>. Yes, it is answer<lb break="no"/>ed by the
                  first. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. A. MARTIN</persName>. It is not answered by <lb/> the first. I must
                  say that these questions <lb/> are not answered. The third section of the <lb/>
                  question reads : <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     If not, is the question to be submitted for 
     <lb/>
     decision to the Privy Council of England or the 
     <lb/>
     Supreme Court of Canada ? 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>Is that answered ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:PREF1">Mr. PREFONTAINE</persName>. Yes, that is an<lb break="no"/>swered, 'no',
                  the same as the first part of <lb/> the question. <lb/>
               </p>

</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">DREDGING AT RUSTICO HARBOUR.</head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. A. MARTIN</persName> asked :</p>
  
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">          
<p>1. What has been done by the government 
     <lb/>
     during 1904 to dredge the harbour at Rustico, 
     <lb/>
     Prince Edward Island ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2. Has the sandbank in the harbour been re<lb break="no"/>moved ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. If not, what steps are to be taken to re<lb break="no"/>move it ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>4. How much has been spent on this work 
     <lb/>
     last season ; what were the means used in 
     <lb/>
     performing the work, and who had charge of it ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">1594</fw>
            <p>5. How many vessels were lost or stranded on 
     <lb/>
     this bar during the season of 1904 ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

   
            <p><persName ref="pers:HYMA1">Hon. CHARLES HYMAN</persName> (Acting Minist<lb break="no"/>er of Public
                  Works). No dredging was <lb/> done during 1904. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>5. According to information supplied by 
     <lb/>
     the Department of Marine and Fisheries, 
     <lb/>
     only one vessel was reported wrecked at 
     <lb/>
     Rustico, during the year 1904. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     RESOLUTIONS RE NORTHWEST TER<lb break="no"/>RITORIES AUTONOMY. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName> (South York). I <lb/> would like to ask the
                  Prime Minister whe<lb break="no"/>ther it is his intention to give notice of re<lb break="no"/>solutions in connection with the Autonomy <lb/> Bill and when we
                  may expect these resolu<lb break="no"/>tions. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. It is not ex<lb break="no"/>pected that
                  the second reading of this Bill <lb/> will be taken for some time to come. I <lb/>
                  cannot say when the resolutions will be in<lb break="no"/>troduced, but they will
                  be introduced in <lb/> ample time for consideration on the second <lb/> reading of
                  the Bill. <lb/>
               </p>
</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     INQUIRY FOR RETURNS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Hon. GEORGE E. FOSTER</persName>. I would <lb/> like to call the
                  attention of the ministers <lb/> to the delay in bringing down returns. The <lb/>
                  delay seems a little inordinate ; may be <lb/> it is not, but I would like to draw
                  the <lb/> attention of the Premier to the following : <lb/> There are the returns
                  from the Minister <lb/> of Railways with reference to the hay <lb/> transport
                  question. We think that by this <lb/> time they should be ready and we would <lb/>
                  like to get them as soon as possible. Then <lb/> there is one with reference to
                  the Royal <lb/> Mint and another, of which I cannot com<lb break="no"/>plain,
                  because it has not been passed so <lb/> long, with reference to public buildings
                  in <lb/> towns of 5,000 population, or less. That is <lb/> a return which should
                  take a very short <lb/> time to prepare and I would be glad to <lb/> have it as
                  soon as possible. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:EMME1">Hon. H. R. EMMERSON</persName> (Minister of <lb/> Railways and Canals).
                  I might explain <lb/> with reference to the motion for a return <lb/> for papers
                  connected with the transporta<lb break="no"/>tion of hay that the mails and trains
                  have <lb/> been so impeded in Cape Breton that we <lb/> have not been able to
                  gather up the cer<lb break="no"/>tificates. They have to be brought in from <lb/>
                  the different stations to Moncton and then <lb/> forwarded on here. We have been
                  waiting <lb/> for a complete return and I can assure my <lb/> hon. friend that the
                  information will be <lb/> brought down at the earliest possible <lb/> moment.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. That is a fair excuse un<lb break="no"/>less we
                  throw it back 9n the minister and <lb/> say he is there to see that the trains are
                  <lb/> kept running. <lb/>
               </p>


            <pb n="1595" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-23_Page_1595.jpg"/>

</div>
<div type="section">         

<head rendition="simple:centre">STEAM COMMUNICATION WITH 
     <lb/>
                 PRINCE EDWARD ISLAND. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. A. MARTIN</persName>. Before the Orders of <lb/> the Day are called I
                  would like to ask the <lb/> Minister of Marine if the steamers have <lb/>
                  succeeded in renewing communication with <lb/> Prince Edward Island ? What was the
                  <lb/> last trip the steamers made ? <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:PREF1">Hon. RAYMOND PREFONTAINE</persName> (Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Marine
                  and Fisheries). I am not <lb/> informed that the ferry has been resumed. <lb/> I
                  understand the last trip was made a <lb/> fortnight or three weeks ago. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. A. MARTIN</persName>. That is very indefinite. <lb/> Is it not four
                  weeks ? <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:PREF1">Mr. PREFONTAINE</persName>. I have not the <lb/> exact date. <lb/> Mr.
                  <persName ref="pers:MART1">A. MARTIN</persName>. Has communication <lb/> been renewed or is it still at a standstill ?
                  <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:PREF1">Mr. PREFONTAINE</persName>. Communication <lb/> has not been renewed.
                  <lb/>   <lb/>
               </p>

</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     QUESTIONS RE TRANSCONTINENTAL 
     <lb/>
             CONSTRUCTION COMMISSION. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MONK1">Mr. F. D. MONK</persName> (Jacques Cartier). Mr. <lb/>
                  Speaker, before the Orders of the Day are <lb/> called, I would like to ask the
                  government <lb/> if questions concerning the doings of the <lb/> Transcontinental
                  Railway Construction <lb/> Commission can be answered and informa<lb break="no"/>tion can be obtained in regard to those <lb/> questions, when they are asked in
                  the usual <lb/> form. I am tempted to seek this informa<lb break="no"/>tion
                  because, on the 20th February instant, <lb/> I put the following question: <lb/>
               </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>1. Did the government, during the months of 
     <lb/>
     October and November, 1904, employ civil en<lb break="no"/>gineers to make a survey for a line of railway 
     <lb/>
     in the county of Joliette, Quebec ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2. For what object was this work and survey 
     <lb/>
     undertaken by said engineers, and was this 
     <lb/>
     work and survey undertaken in connection with 
     <lb/>
     the proposed Transcontinental Railway ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. What was the total cost of this work and 
     <lb/>
     survey already accomplished by said engineers 
     <lb/>
     and their assistants ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>4. Have said engineers made their report con<lb break="no"/>cerning this work and survey ? If so, what was 
     <lb/>
     the date of said report ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>5. Who was the overseer charged with the 
     <lb/>
     direction of this work, and what salary did he 
     <lb/>
     receive ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
   
            <p>This question was answered in the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing form : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><persName ref="pers:EMME1">Hon. H. R. EMMERSON</persName> (Minister
                  of Railways <lb/> and Canals). The government did not during <lb/> the months of
                  October and November employ <lb/> civil engineers to make a survey for a line of
                  <lb/> railway in the county of Joliette, but I have <lb/> reason to assume that
                  the Transcontinental Rail<lb break="no"/>way Commissioners made a survey through
                  that <lb/> county, not under the direction of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment.
                  <lb/>
               </quote>
   
            <p>The point to which I wish to draw the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the government is that it 
     <lb/>
     seems to me that the Transcontinental 
     <lb/>
           

          <!--  <p>  Mr. FOSTER. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">1594</fw>

           
     Construction Commission, is so to speak, a 
     <lb/>
     department of the government. I believe 
     <lb/>
     that under the rules, questions can be put 
     <lb/>
     in this House to the government, to the 
     <lb/>
     ministers and to individual members. This 
     <lb/>
     last form is seldom adopted. Most of these 
     <lb/>
     questions in fact can only be answered by 
     <lb/>
     information sought in the different depart<lb break="no"/>ments, sometimes far from Ottawa. That 
     <lb/>
     information is obtained from officials of the 
     <lb/>
     government at some remote places. It 
     <lb/>
     seems to me that a question put in this 
     <lb/>
     form is pertinent and should have been an<lb break="no"/>swered on the principle that this commis<lb break="no"/>sion is really a servant of the government. 
     <lb/>
     The practical object of my question is to 
     <lb/>
     know in what form, according to the rules, 
     <lb/>
     questions must be put. If they are put in 
     <lb/>
     the form suggested to me by the govern<lb break="no"/>ment, will questions be answered or is the 
     <lb/>
     Transcontinental Railway Commission a 
     <lb/>
     body independent of this House ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. The answer to <lb/> my hon. friend (Mr.
                  Monk) is to be found <lb/> in a motion of which my hon. friend has <lb/> himself
                  given notice, asking all information <lb/> with regard to these surveys. When the
                  <lb/> motion is reached, I have no doubt it will be <lb/> carried, but it will
                  have to be amended, be<lb break="no"/>cause the information has to be obtained
                  <lb/> from the Transcontinental Railway Com<lb break="no"/>mission, and not from
                  the government. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MONK1">Mr. MONK</persName>. Perhaps my right hon. friend <lb/> will allow me to
                  say that that is not the <lb/> information which I sought by my question. <lb/>
                  The information sought by the question I <lb/> put was simply in relation to the
                  fact. In <lb/> the motion I asked for a copy of the report, <lb/> detailed
                  accounts of expenses and the names <lb/> of the parties employed. The question I
                  put <lb/> had reference to a department of the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, and I
                  think should have been <lb/> answered in the form in which it was put. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. If my hon. <lb/> friend wants the
                  information, he will have to <lb/> make a motion. We have not the informa<lb break="no"/>tion in our hands, but shall have to obtain <lb/> it from the
                  commission itself. <lb/>
               </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
            THE CAPITAL OF SASKATCHEWAN. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAMO1">Mr. J. H. LAMONT</persName> (Saskatchewan). Mr. <lb/> Speaker, before
                  the Orders of the Day are <lb/> called, I wish to ask the Prime Minister if <lb/>
                  the Bill providing for the creation of the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of
                  Saskatchewan fixes the permanent <lb/> capital at Regina, as stated in one of the
                  <lb/> evening papers yesterday ? <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. No. It is pro<lb break="no"/>visional
                  only, and subject to the will and <lb/> the determination of the legislature.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
           RAILWAY ACT AMENDMENT. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>House in committee on Bill (No. 36) 
     <lb/>
     to amend the Railway Act, 1903.—Mr. Fitz<lb break="no"/>patrick.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
    </div>     </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>