<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-03-09"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-03-09">9 March 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

        
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
 
                    

          <date when="1905"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="2191" to="2202"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2191.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2193.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2195.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2197.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2199.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2201.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-01-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-01-17">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2191">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2191.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2193">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2193.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2195">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2195.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2197">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2197.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2199">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2199.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2201">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2201.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="2191" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2191.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">2191</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">2192</fw>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>[...]
     from Toronto to Sudbury with the Department 
     <lb/>
     of Railways ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2. If so, does such map show the line to run 
     <lb/>
     on the east side of Lake Couchiching, or the 
     <lb/>
     west of said lake ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. Has the minister finally approved of the 
     <lb/>
     route ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>4. Has the company filed plans for a devia<lb break="no"/>tion, and has the department considered the 
     <lb/>
     same ? 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p><persName ref="pers:EMME1">Hon. H. R. EMMERSON</persName> (Minister of Rail<lb break="no"/>ways and
               Canals) : <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>1. No. They have filed the route map 
     <lb/>
     from Toronto to Parry Sound. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2. To the east of Lake Couchiching. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>4. No. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     MAILS TO VICTORIA HARBOUR. 
     <lb/></head>
<p><persName ref="pers:BENN2">Mr. BENNETT</persName>—by Mr. Taylor—asked : <lb/>
               </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>1. Who is the contractor for carrying the 
     <lb/>
     mail from the railway station to the post oflice 
     <lb/>
     at Victoria Harbour ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2. Were tenders asked for such service? It 
     <lb/>
     so, when ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. When does such contract expire ? 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Hon. Sir WILLIAM MULOCK</persName> (Post<lb break="no"/>master General):
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>1. Mark Vasey. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2 and 3. In December 1896 tenders for 
     <lb/>
     this service were invited ; only one, that of 
     <lb/>
     Mark Vasey was received being at the price 
     <lb/>
     of $120.80, and was accepted. The contract 
     <lb/>
     was renewed at $128.80 a year in 1901 with 
     <lb/>
     the same contractor and was further re<lb break="no"/>newed in 1905 at the same price. It expires 
     <lb/>
     on the 31st of December, 1908. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     COAL FOR GOVERNMENT RAILWAYS. 
     <lb/></head>
<p><persName ref="pers:BARK1">Mr. BARKER</persName>—by Mr. Taylor—asked : <lb/>
               </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>1. In six months ended 3lst December, 1904, 
     <lb/>
     how many tons of coal were accepted from the 
     <lb/>
     Joggins, Strathcona, Kimberley, and Chignecto 
     <lb/>
     mines, respectively, for the government rail<lb break="no"/>ways ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2. What were the prices for the several mines, 
     <lb/>
     and qualities ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. What were the respective places of deli<lb break="no"/>very at the prices ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>

            <p><persName ref="pers:EMME1">Hon. H. R. EMMERSON</persName> (Minister of Rail<lb break="no"/>ways and
                  Canals : <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>1. Joggins mines, 15,084 tons ; Strathcona 
     <lb/>
     mines, 5,160 tons ; Chignecto mines, 14,820 
     <lb/>
     tons ; Kimberly mine, 'nil.' 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2. The price paid to each of the several 
     <lb/>
     mines was $3.25 a ton of 2,240 pounds, and 
     <lb/>
     the quality of coal supplied by each of them 
     <lb/>
     was generally satisfactory. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. The place of delivery at the above price 
     <lb/>
     was for all the mines at Maccan station of 
     <lb/>
     the Intercolonial Railway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     INTERCOLONIAL RAILWAY—SEYMOUR 
     <lb/>
     WOODILL. 
     <lb/></head>
          

   
            <p><persName ref="pers:BARK1">Mr. BARKER</persName>—by Mr. Taylor—asked : <lb/>
               </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>1. Is Seymour Woodill employed on the Inter<lb break="no"/>colonial Railway at Halifax or elsewhere ? It 
     <lb/>
     so, in what capacity, and on what terms ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
           <!-- <p>Mr. GRANT. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            <cb/>
            <p>2. Was he previously employed in the Post 
     <lb/>
     Office Department or any other department ? 
     <lb/>
     If so, where, and in what capacity ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. Was his employment or service discon<lb break="no"/>tinued ? If so, when and why ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p><persName ref="pers:EMME1">Hon. H. R. EMMERSON</persName> (Minister of Rail<lb break="no"/>ways and
                  Canals) : <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>1. Yes. As clerk at a salary of $55 per 
     <lb/>
     month. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2. So far as can be ascertained he was not 
     <lb/>
     previously employed in the Post Office De<lb break="no"/>partment or any other department. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. He is still in the employ of the Inter<lb break="no"/>colonial Railway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     INTERCOLONIAL RAILWAY-CARRIAGE OF 
     <lb/>
     COAL. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:KEMP1">Mr. KEMP</persName> asked: <lb/>
               </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>1. To whom in the city of Ottawa was coal 
     <lb/>
     transported free in the year 1902—3 over the 
     <lb/>
     Intercolonial Railway ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2. Was it for government use ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. It not, for whose use was it ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p><persName ref="pers:EMME1">Hon. H. R. EMMERSON</persName> (Minister of Rail <lb/> ways and Canals)
                  : ' <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>1. The corporation of the city of Ottawa. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>2. No. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>3. It is understood it was sold by the 
     <lb/>
     corporation to those wishing to purchase it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PROVINCIAL GOVERNMENT IN THE 
     <lb/>
     NORTHWEST TERRITORIES. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName> (Carleton, Ont.). Be<lb break="no"/>fore the
                  Orders of the Day are called, I shall <lb/> make a few remarks with respect to a
                  <lb/> matter which I have informed my right hon. <lb/> friend the Prime Minister I
                  would speak <lb/> upon to—day. My remarks will be very <lb/> brief. They are in
                  connection with the in<lb break="no"/>troduction of the Bills for the
                  establishment <lb/> of new provinces in the Northwest Terri<lb break="no"/>tories.
                  I do not of course propose to discuss <lb/> the merits of these measures—the rules
                  of <lb/> the House would not permit me to do so. <lb/> and even if they would,
                  that course is not <lb/> advisable at the present moment, when, as I <lb/>
                  understand, certain questions in connection <lb/> with these Bills are under
                  consideration by <lb/> the government. However, if I were dis<lb break="no"/>posed
                  to enter into a discussion of the <lb/> merits, I would be unable to do so on
                     ac<lb break="no"/>count of the very well known rules of the <lb/> House which
                  do not seem to be thoroughly <lb/> understood in some quarters throughout the
                  <lb/> country. The particular matter to which I <lb/> desire to call attention is
                  : that the Prime <lb/> Minister introduced this legislation, as a <lb/> measure
                  concurred in by all the members <lb/> of the administration, whereas we dis<lb
                     break="no"/>covered afterwards that this was not the <lb/> fact. My right hon.
                  friend has always <lb/> vaunted himself as a strict follower of con<lb break="no"
                  />stitutional usage—he has sometimes done <lb/> more than that, because some ten
                  years <lb/> ago he claimed for himself the attributes of <lb/> foresight and of
                  courage when a somewhat <lb/> similar question as that which arises to-day <lb/>
                  <pb n="2193" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2193.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">2193</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">MARCH 9, 1905</fw>
                  <fw type="num">2194</fw> was to a certain extent agitating the parlia<lb
                     break="no"/>ment and the people of this country. My <lb/> right hon. friend
                  then said: <lb/>
               </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>My courage is not to make hasty promises 
     <lb/>
     and then to ignominously break them. My 
     <lb/>
     courage is to speak slowly, but once I have 
     <lb/>
     spoken I will stand or fall by my words. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>I mention that, because my right hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend though he may have shown a great 
     <lb/>
     deal of courage in his action with regard to 
     <lb/>
     this measure, does not at least seem to have 
     <lb/>
     combined foresight with strict regard for 
     <lb/>
     constitutional usage. It is beyond all doubt 
     <lb/>
     that this House is entitled to regard every 
     <lb/>
     measure brought down by the Prime Min<lb break="no"/>ister, or by any other member of the 
     <lb/>
     cabinet, as a government measure, which is 
     <lb/>
     the result of the collective wisdom of the 
     <lb/>
     cabinet. I need not cite authority for that, 
     <lb/>
     to those who are at all familiar with the 
     <lb/>
     usage as laid down by recognized constitu<lb break="no"/>tional authorities ; let me, however, quote 
     <lb/>
     two or three words from volume II of Todd 
     <lb/>
     on parliamentary government in England 
     <lb/>
     where it is thus laid down : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     Except in the case of an admitted open ques<lb break="no"/>tion, it must be taken for granted that the 
     <lb/>
     whole cabinet have assented to the minister<lb break="no"/>ial policy as officially presented or propounded 
     <lb/>
     by any minister acting or speaking on their 
     <lb/>
     behalf. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>Words could not be plainer. We have 
     <lb/>
     the absolute right to regard the measure 
     <lb/>
     brought down by the Prime Minister on 
     <lb/>
     the 2lst day of February last, as a mea<lb break="no"/>sure in respect of which every member of 
     <lb/>
     the cabinet had been consulted, and which, 
     <lb/>
     whatever differences of opinion might origi<lb break="no"/>nally have existed with regards to its terms, 
     <lb/>
     was in the end concurred in by all the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the cabinet, and had the support 
     <lb/>
     of each of them. Now, it has turned out 
     <lb/>
     since the introduction of the measure, that 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for Brandon (Mr. Sifton), 
     <lb/>
     until recently the Minister of the Interior, 
     <lb/>
     was not consulted about that measure at 
     <lb/>
     all. I do not know how it may be with 
     <lb/>
     regard to other members of the cabinet ; 
     <lb/>
     we have no information with respect to that. 
     <lb/>
     We do not know whether or not the Minister 
     <lb/>
     of Finance was consulted with regard to 
     <lb/>
     the clauses which did not meet with the 
     <lb/>
     approval of the Minister of the Interior, nor 
     <lb/>
     do we know to what extent, if any, the Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Finance was consulted with re<lb break="no"/>gard to the financial terms embodied in 
     <lb/>
     this measure. But we have this peculiar 
     <lb/>
     circumstance, at least, that the measure 
     <lb/>
     was brought down two or three days be<lb break="no"/>fore the return of the Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior. Naturally we would not be led to 
     <lb/>
     suppose that a measure of this importance, 
     <lb/>
     with the terms of which the Minister of 
     <lb/>
     the Interior is so intimately connected, 
     <lb/>
     would be brought down within two or three 
     <lb/>
     days of his return to Ottawa, without his 
     <lb/>
     having had an opportunity to become ac<lb break="no"/><cb/>quainted with its terms. Nor is it to be 
     <lb/>
     supposed. in view of the fact that the Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Finance had sailed about a week 
     <lb/>
     before from Europe to this country, that 
     <lb/>
     legislation of so great importance as the 
     <lb/>
     financial clauses of this Bill, would be in<lb break="no"/>troduced into this House on the eve of his 
     <lb/>
     return, without his having any opportunity 
     <lb/>
     to advise with regard to them, or to give 
     <lb/>
     his colleagues the benefit of the wisdom and 
     <lb/>
     experience which of course he must possess 
     <lb/>
     after occupying for some eight or nine years 
     <lb/>
     the position which he now holds. Under 
     <lb/>
     these circumstances, I think we might well 
     <lb/>
     call for an explanation from the right hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman who leads the House as to why 
     <lb/>
     it was he brought down this measure with<lb break="no"/>out vouchsafing to the House the explanation 
     <lb/>
     that two members of his cabinet had not 
     <lb/>
     been consulted at all with regard to its pro<lb break="no"/>visions, and that, so far as they were con<lb break="no"/>cerned, this was not the act of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>But I need not go to Todd or to any other 
     <lb/>
     authority on parliamentary government in 
     <lb/>
     regard to this matter. This administration 
     <lb/>
     has laid down a rule, peculiar, as it is de<lb break="no"/>clared, to the form of government which 
     <lb/>
     we enjoy in this country. What was the 
     <lb/>
     position of affairs ? The Minister of the 
     <lb/>
     Interior represented in the cabinet the great 
     <lb/>
     west of Canada—represented more than any 
     <lb/>
     other member of the cabinet that portion 
     <lb/>
     of this country which is now being created 
     <lb/>
     into two new provinces. Further than that, 
     <lb/>
     owing to his experience of some eight years 
     <lb/>
     in the position of Minister of the Interior, 
     <lb/>
     he might be supposed to possess a more in<lb break="no"/>timate knowledge of the needs and require<lb break="no"/>ments of that country than any other mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the cabinet. And yet the Minister 
     <lb/>
     of the Interior was not consulted with re<lb break="no"/>gard to this measure, and that in the face 
     <lb/>
     of the most explicit declaration made by 
     <lb/>
     this administration no further back than 
     <lb/>
     the 14th of June, 1904, that he was the 
     <lb/>
     man above all others who should be con<lb break="no"/>sulted on this question. When Lord Dun<lb break="no"/>donald was dismissed from his position as 
     <lb/>
     General Officer Commanding in this coun<lb break="no"/>try, the government passed an Order in 
     <lb/>
     Council which was laid upon the table of 
     <lb/>
     the House, and in which the action of the 
     <lb/>
     administration in that regard was justified 
     <lb/>
     upon certain grounds; and one of the rea<lb break="no"/>sons put forward by the administration for 
     <lb/>
     the interference by the Minister of Agricul<lb break="no"/>ture in a department with which otherwise 
     <lb/>
     he had no concern whatever, indeed, the 
     <lb/>
     only justification for that interference, was 
     <lb/>
     expressed in that Order in Council in these 
     <lb/>
     words :-<lb/>
            </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">In the case of members of the cabinet, while 
     <lb/>
     all have an equal degree of responsibility in a 
     <lb/>
     constitutional sense, yet in the practical work<lb break="no"/>ing out of responsible government, in a coun<lb break="no"/>try of such vast extent as Canada, it is found 
     <lb/>
     necessary to attach special responsibility to 
     <lb/>
            

 <pb n="2195" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2195.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">2195</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">2196</fw>

     each minister for the public affairs of the pro<lb break="no"/>vince or district with which he has close politi<lb break="no"/>cal connection, and with which his colleagues 
     <lb/>
     may not be so well acquainted. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>Well, I would submit to my right hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend that, taking his own standard of 
     <lb/>
     ministerial responsibility thus expressed in 
     <lb/>
     this Order in Council, the Minister of the 
     <lb/>
     Interior was in this case the minister above 
     <lb/>
     all others who should have been consulted 
     <lb/>
     in the first instance about those very pro<lb break="no"/>visions which at the present time are caus<lb break="no"/>ing some discussion in the country, and, if 
     <lb/>
     we may believe all we hear, some dissen<lb break="no"/>sion on the other side of the House ; and I 
     <lb/>
     would like to know from the right hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman how it was that after having de<lb break="no"/>layed some two years before taking up the 
     <lb/>
     question at all, the minister who, under 
     <lb/>
     the constitutional rule laid down by the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment itself, was most to be consulted 
     <lb/>
     with regard to the terms of the measure, 
     <lb/>
     was not consulted at all, although the mea<lb break="no"/>sure was introduced within three days of 
     <lb/>
     his return to Ottawa. My right hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     has been a very strict stickler for constitu<lb break="no"/>tional usage in some of his dealings with 
     <lb/>
     his ministers in days gone by. I will ad<lb break="no"/>vert to only one case. We remember that 
     <lb/>
     the right hon. gentleman felt himself con<lb break="no"/>strained to ask for the portfolio of Public 
     <lb/>
     Works at that time held by the Hon. J. I. 
     <lb/>
     Tarte, because Mr. Tarte had seen fit, in 
     <lb/>
     the words of the Prime Minister, to advo<lb break="no"/>cate a policy which had not yet been adopt<lb break="no"/>ed by the government. Well, if that be a 
     <lb/>
     just reason, have not the colleagues of the 
     <lb/>
     right hon. gentleman a right to demand his 
     <lb/>
     portfolio at the present time, because he 
     <lb/>
     has seen fit not only to advocate, but to 
     <lb/>
     place before parliament and the country, 
     <lb/>
     a measure to which his colleagues have not 
     <lb/>
     all agreed. I do not know on what ground 
     <lb/>
     the right hon. gentleman can justify him<lb break="no"/>self in this regard, because it seems to me 
     <lb/>
     that it is not treating the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons with due respect to bring down a 
     <lb/>
     measure of this kind as one which is con<lb break="no"/>curred in by every member of the adminis<lb break="no"/>tration, and afterwards to acquaint the 
     <lb/>
     House, as we are now acquainted, with the 
     <lb/>
     fact that certain members at least were not 
     <lb/>
     consulted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Have we not the right under the circum<lb break="no"/>stances to inquire respectfully of the First 
     <lb/>
     Minister whether there are any other mem<lb break="no"/>bers of his cabinet outside the member for 
     <lb/>
     Brandon, lately Minister of the Interior, and 
     <lb/>
     the Minister of Finance who were not con<lb break="no"/>sulted with regard to the terms of this 
     <lb/>
     measure. The right hon. gentleman has 
     <lb/>
     adverted to the aid which he obtained from 
     <lb/>
     members of the Executive Council of the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest Territories. May we not also 
     <lb/>
     respectfully inquire whether all the provi<lb break="no"/>sions of this measure were considered at the 
     <lb/>
     conferences which took place between the 
     <lb/>
     members of the cabinet and the members 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
       
     of the Executive Council of the Territories. 
     <lb/>
     There is some further desirable information, 
     <lb/>
     if the right hon. gentleman will not regard 
     <lb/>
     my curiosity as fastidious—because that is 
     <lb/>
     the term he usually applies when any ques<lb break="no"/>tion is in the least degree awkward—might I 
     <lb/>
     ask whether or not any conculsion has been 
     <lb/>
     arrived at with regard to the filling of the 
     <lb/>
     position made vacant by the resignation of 
     <lb/>
     the Minister of the Interior. I would also 
     <lb/>
     respectfully inquire of the right hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man regarding another matter which I men<lb break="no"/>tioned the other day, namely, whether or 
     <lb/>
     not changes in the proposed Bills creating 
     <lb/>
     the new provinces are under consideration 
     <lb/>
     by the government ? We of course, do not 
     <lb/>
     seek to concern ourselves with any differ<lb break="no"/>ences which may have occurred in the 
     <lb/>
     ranks of the hon. gentlemen opposite, but 
     <lb/>
     the shape in which these measures shall 
     <lb/>
     eventually come before parliament is a mat<lb break="no"/>ter in which we are legitimately concerned 
     <lb/>
     and as to which we have a reasonable right 
     <lb/>
     to inquire. It is said over and over again 
     <lb/>
     in the organs supposed to have the confi<lb break="no"/>dence of the government—for example in the 
     <lb/>
     very last issue of that newspaper which is 
     <lb/>
     supposed to be the organ of the Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Agriculture ; it is stated not only that these 
     <lb/>
     matters are being discussed within the cab<lb break="no"/>inet and in the ranks of the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     opposite, but that certain conclusions have 
     <lb/>
     already been arrived at and will be announc<lb break="no"/>ed in due course. I suggested to my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend only the other day that as soon as 
     <lb/>
     those changes—if any are contemplated—be 
     <lb/>
     agreed upon, they should be announced to 
     <lb/>
     the House in order that we may have them 
     <lb/>
     under consideration before the time arrives 
     <lb/>
     for discussing them in parliament. I ven<lb break="no"/>ture to bring this matter before the govern<lb break="no"/>ment to-day. The right hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     told us some ten years ago, when matters of 
     <lb/>
     this kind were discussed in parliament 
     <lb/>
     and the country, that he was not in the bat<lb break="no"/>tle ' No,' he said : 'The battle is there ; 
     <lb/>
     there is the seat of contest ; there is the 
     <lb/>
     raging confiict.' I do not want to make 
     <lb/>
     any special application of those words to<lb break="no"/>day ; but I do think that as soon as the 
     <lb/>
     differences are amicably adjusted, we should 
     <lb/>
     have a statement from the Prime Minister 
     <lb/>
     as to the form this measure will eventually 
     <lb/>
     take when it comes before parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. I am sorry to <lb/> say that I have very
                  little to tell my hon. <lb/> friend of which he is not already aware. <lb/> He is
                  too old a parliamentarian not to know <lb/> the answer I must give him. My hon.
                  friend <lb/> knows well, none better, that the delibera<lb break="no"/>tions of
                  cabinets are secret, that all the <lb/> members of a cabinet are sworn to secrecy.
                  <lb/> and that solidarity exists among them until <lb/> one of them chooses to
                  express his dissent <lb/> because he finds he cannot support any long<lb
                     break="no"/>er the policy of the government. When such <lb/> a thing occurs, it
                  becomes the duty of the <lb/> government to inform parliament of the <lb/>
                  <pb n="2197" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2197.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">2197</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">MARCH 9, 1905</fw>
                  <fw type="num">2198</fw> causes of the differences which have arisen <lb/> between
                  the dissenting member and his col<lb break="no"/>leagues. My hon. friend knows
                  that in <lb/> every government, it must always be pre<lb break="no"/>sumed that
                  there will be some diflerences of <lb/> opinion among the members composing it.
                  <lb/> It is not to be supposed that in a cabinet <lb/> composed of 13 or 14
                  members, all the min<lb break="no"/>isters are of one mind upon all questions.
                  <lb/> It must be expected that there will be some <lb/> differences among them. It
                  is not in hu<lb break="no"/>man nature that they should agree on all <lb/>
                  matters, and therefore some latitude must <lb/> be allowed the individual members,
                  and this <lb/> latitude is always extended until it be<lb break="no"/>comes
                  impossible for one of the members of <lb/> the administration to agree with his
                     col<lb break="no"/>leagues. Let me quote Todd : <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     Upon the formation of a ministry which em<lb break="no"/>braces men of different shades of political opin<lb break="no"/>ion, it necessarily follows that there must be, 
     <lb/>
     to a greater or less extent, mutual concessions 
     <lb/>
     and compromises. But with the rare exception 
     <lb/>
     of certain questions, which by previous consent 
     <lb/>
     it is agreed shall be considered as 'open,' it is 
     <lb/>
     an admitted principle that all the responsible 
     <lb/>
     ministers of the crown are bound to unite in 
     <lb/>
     furthering the measures of government through 
     <lb/>
     parliament, and in otherwise carrying out the 
     <lb/>
     policy which has been agreed upon by the 
     <lb/>
     cabinet. This policy is framed in the first in<lb break="no"/>stance by the prime minister in accordance 
     <lb/>
     with the principle of the party to which he 
     <lb/>
     belongs. It then forms the basis of negotia<lb break="no"/>tion between himself and those whom he may 
     <lb/>
     invite to assist him in carrying on the Queen's 
     <lb/>
     government. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>

            <p>All members of the cabinet should agree 
     <lb/>
     on questions of policy, but if there should be 
     <lb/>
     a disappointment, if, as in the case of the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Brandon, there should be 
     <lb/>
     a difference of opinion, then either a com<lb break="no"/>promise must be reached or the dissenting 
     <lb/>
     colleague resigns from the cabinet. In the 
     <lb/>
     latter case it is the duty of the First Minister 
     <lb/>
     to give the House information of the causes 
     <lb/>
     which led to this unhappy result just as 
     <lb/>
     an explanation of the policies of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment is due to the House when the govern<lb break="no"/>ment is formed. But does my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     expect the government to give to the House 
     <lb/>
     all the different conversations or deliber<lb break="no"/>ations which may have taken place in coun<lb break="no"/>cil—everything which passed either in writ<lb break="no"/>ing or by word of mouth ? If he so expects, 
     <lb/>
     his expectation is not borne out by the au<lb break="no"/>thorities on the subject. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>It will be sufficient for me to quote to 
     <lb/>
     him the author from whom he himself has 
     <lb/>
     quoted, who is recognized as the standard 
     <lb/>
     authority upon these subjects. I quote from 
     <lb/>
     Todd, Vol. 2, page 487. After having stated 
     <lb/>
     that the House is entitled to have full ex<lb break="no"/>planation on the formation of a government, 
     <lb/>
     Todd goes on to say: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote>
     But the House has no right to ask for more 
     <lb/>
     than a general exposition of the main principles 
     <lb/>
     on which a government is formed. It has no 
     <lb/>
     right to inquire into all the conditions which 
     <lb/>
     may have taken place between the several 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     members of the government. Any arrangements, 
     <lb/>
     however, which have been specially referred 
     <lb/>
     to in debate by new ministers as the stipula<lb break="no"/>tions and conditions upon which they agreed 
     <lb/>
     to accept office, may be suitably inquired into 
     <lb/>
     by other members. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>And this rule that is laid down for the 
     <lb/>
     formation of a government is exactly the 
     <lb/>
     rule laid down, as I understand the consti<lb break="no"/>tutional authorities on the point, in rela<lb break="no"/>tion to giving information concerning a gov<lb break="no"/>ernment that, instead of being formed is, to 
     <lb/>
     some extent disrupted. A few days ago, it 
     <lb/>
     was my duty—my painful duty—to com<lb break="no"/>municate to the House the reasons which 
     <lb/>
     had brought about the rupture between the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Brandon (Mr. Sifton) and 
     <lb/>
     the government. I do not know that the 
     <lb/>
     House in entitled to more information than 
     <lb/>
     I gave them. There are the facts, and the 
     <lb/>
     matter has been brought before the House. 
     <lb/>
     My hon. friend (Mr. R. L. Borden) has taken 
     <lb/>
     exception, and when the time comes to dis<lb break="no"/>cuss the matter, he will be able to give 
     <lb/>
     whatever explanation he thinks it well to 
     <lb/>
     give. Until that time, the House must rest 
     <lb/>
     content with the explanation given. The 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman has not stated whether, in 
     <lb/>
     this matter, he refers to the Bill in toto, or 
     <lb/>
     simply to the educational clauses. It will 
     <lb/>
     be open to him to tell the House to what 
     <lb/>
     extent he refers to the Bill as a whole or to 
     <lb/>
     what extent he refers to in toto. Up to this 
     <lb/>
     time, I do not think the House is entitled to 
     <lb/>
     more information from us than that which 
     <lb/>
     has already been imparted.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>My hon. friend asks a second question. 
     <lb/>
     He wants to know whether any action is 
     <lb/>
     to be taken to fill the vacancy in the port<lb break="no"/>folio of the Interior- caused by the resigna<lb break="no"/>tion of my hon. friend from Brandon (Mr. Sif<lb break="no"/>ton). He is entitled to a full and catego<lb break="no"/>rical answer. No action has been taken, 
     <lb/>
     and it is not my intention now to take any 
     <lb/>
     action in the way of filling that portfolio. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>And my hon. friend asks still another 
     <lb/>
     question. He wants to know if any changes 
     <lb/>
     are contemplated in the Bill. Really, the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman is very inquisitive. I said 
     <lb/>
     the other day—and I think my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     will agree with me—that I am not aware of 
     <lb/>
     any measure of any great importance, and 
     <lb/>
     I am aware of very few measures even of 
     <lb/>
     little importance, that have ever gone over 
     <lb/>
     that table without having changes made in 
     <lb/>
     them ; and I shall be much surprised if this 
     <lb/>
     Bill, which is of such great importance 
     <lb/>
     runs the gauntlet of this House without 
     <lb/>
     fault being found with it—perhaps by my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend the leader of the opposition (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     R. L. Borden) ; perhaps by my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     who sits next to him (Mr. Foster) ; perhaps 
     <lb/>
     by my hon. friend who sits behind him (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Monk), or, perhaps by my hon. friend who 
     <lb/>
     sits at his right hand (Mr. Sproule). Per<lb break="no"/>haps fault will be found on one hand, per<lb break="no"/>haps on many. Therefore, I cannot see how 
     <lb/>
     it is possible to gratify my hon. friend and 
     <lb/>
     say anything as to changes being contem<lb break="no"/><pb n="2199" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2199.jpg"/><fw type="num">2199</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">2200</fw>plated. But I must say that I can under<lb break="no"/>stand that my hon. friend is very anxious 
     <lb/>
     to know in advance if there are to be any 
     <lb/>
     changes made in the Bill. I think, judging 
     <lb/>
     from past experience, my hon. friend will 
     <lb/>
     think it important to know in advance what 
     <lb/>
     is to be the precise character of the Bill 
     <lb/>
     when it shall come to the second reading. 
     <lb/>
     I presume—and in so presuming, I think I 
     <lb/>
     do not state anything that is not in accord<lb break="no"/>ance with the truth ; if I do, he will correct 
     <lb/>
     me—and I have reason to believe, that he 
     <lb/>
     is preparing some batteries to attack this 
     <lb/>
     Bill ; and, perhaps it is important for him 
     <lb/>
     to know at this time whether he should 
     <lb/>
     place his batteries on a certain hill or place 
     <lb/>
     them on another hill. I can understand 
     <lb/>
     that my hon. friend is anxious to know whe<lb break="no"/>ther or not the Bill is to be as it is. If there 
     <lb/>
     are to be other provisions, as a matter of 
     <lb/>
     tactics he would like to be in a position to 
     <lb/>
     judge whether his batteries should be placed 
     <lb/>
     in one place or in another. But I can hardly 
     <lb/>
     give myself the pleasure of coming to the 
     <lb/>
     rescue of my hon. friend by giving him to<lb break="no"/>day information to which, in due time, he 
     <lb/>
     will be entitled. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. May I say one word <lb/> to my right hon.
                  friend (Sir Wilfrid Laurier): <lb/> Whatever else I do I shall not retire within
                  <lb/> the lines of Torres Vedras. Might I re<lb break="no"/>spectfully suggest to
                  him that he has not <lb/> at all answered the question which I put to <lb/> him,
                  namely : Why did he so far violate <lb/> constitutional usage as to bring down a
                  Bill <lb/> as the act of the administration when two <lb/> members, who were on
                  the eve of return, <lb/> had not been consulted in regard to it. That <lb/> is the
                  point, the chief point, of my remarks. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName> (South York). The <lb/> right hon.
                  gentleman (Sir Wilfrid Laurier) <lb/> has given no explanation as to the ques<lb
                     break="no"/>tions put to him. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. Mr. Speaker-<lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. I intend to move <lb/> the adjournment-<lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. The House is <lb/> to be moved in supply in
                  a moment, and <lb/>that will give the hon. gentleman (Mr. W. F. <lb/>Maclean) an
                  opportunity to speak. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName> The right hon. <lb/> gentleman had the
                  opportunity to speak, and <lb/> so had the leader of the opposition (Mr. R. <lb/>
                  L. Borden) and I claim the same privilege <lb/> of discussing the matter at the
                  present <lb/> stage. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p>Some hon. MEMBERS. Oh, oh.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. In order to keep <lb/> myself within the
                  rules of the House, I in<lb break="no"/>tend to conclude with a motion. The right
                  <lb/> hon. gentleman (Sir Wilfrid Laurier) has <lb/> made a statement that does
                  not meet the <lb/>point that has been raised. He has been <lb/>asked to explain
                  why he introduced legis<lb break="no"/>lation in this House dealing with the
                     auto<lb break="no"/><cb/>nomy of the Northwest without having the <lb/>
                  approval of his colleagues. And he tells us <lb/> that he does not intend to
                  appoint another <lb/> Minister of the Interior at the present stage <lb/> and to
                  consult that minister in regard to <lb/> these Bills. We heard the other day about
                  <lb/> autocracy in this House ; but what about <lb/> the autocrat of the present
                  occasion ? Not <lb/> only has he got rid of one minister, but he <lb/> intends to
                  go on with this question without <lb/> calling to his cabinet a new Minister of
                  the <lb/> Interior. Apparently, he does not care to <lb/> consult the opinion of
                  the west in regard to <lb/> these things. But surely the west is worth <lb/>
                  consulting. Surely the new provinces of <lb/> the west are just as well entitled
                  to be <lb/> consulted in this matter as are some other <lb/> provinces. But every
                  stage of the right <lb/> hon. gentleman's conduct is on unconstitu<lb break="no"
                  />tional lines. I think the Prime Minister is <lb/> constitutionally bound to tell
                  us whether <lb/> one of his colleagues had not objections to <lb/> the finnancial
                  phase of the Bill that has been <lb/> brought before the House. We are sup<lb
                     break="no"/>posed to have a Minister of the Interior <lb/> especially charged
                  with the affairs of the <lb/> west. We have a Minister of Finance who <lb/> is
                  especially responsible for the financial <lb/> program of the government. Yet we
                  have <lb/> this autonomy measure involving grave <lb/> financial charges, and
                  giving reason to all <lb/> the other provinces for demanding better <lb/> terms,
                  and the Finance Minister (Mr. <lb/> Fielding) so far as we can gather, has not
                  <lb/> even been consulted, as the Minister of the <lb/> Interior was not
                  consulted. Where are we <lb/> to end, if these things continue ? And let <lb/> us
                  refer to another minister. I spoke of this <lb/> matter the other day, but it
                  should be men<lb break="no"/>tioned in this connection also. We have a <lb/>
                  gentleman acting as Minister of Public <lb/> Works who is putting through
                  estimates <lb/> for $10,000,000, and will probably have sup<lb break="no"
                  />plementary estimates for $3,000,000 more. <lb/> The amount will depend on the
                  political ex<lb break="no"/>igencies of hon. gentlemen opposite. Last <lb/>
                  session this gentleman was in the same <lb/> unconstitutional position, and then
                  put <lb/> through estimates of about $10,000,000. And <lb/> yet this
                  unconstitutional method is to be <lb/> continued, and when explanations are ask<lb
                     break="no"/>ed none are forthcoming. There are more <lb/> governments in
                  trouble than this one. If <lb/> you read the papers to-day, you see that <lb/>
                  nearly every government in Europe is in <lb/> trouble for some reason. But there
                  is a <lb/> cure ; there is a solvent for these difficul<lb break="no"/>ties ; and
                  that is to consult the people. If <lb/> the right hon. gentleman (Sir Wilfrid
                     Lau<lb break="no"/>rier) believes in the principle professed by <lb/> his
                  party, he will not carry on the nego<lb break="no"/>tiations that are now going on
                  in the way <lb/> of fights and bickerings in his own cabinet, <lb/> but he will do
                  the constitutional thing and <lb/> go back to the country and submit this ques<lb
                     break="no"/>tion to the people. He has confessed to-day <lb/> that he is afraid
                  to open the constituency <lb/> of London, in Ontario ; he is afraid to open <lb/>
                  a constituency in Manitoba, and bring in a <lb/>
                  <pb n="2201" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-09_Page_2201.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">2201</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">MARCH 9, 1905</fw>
                  <fw type="num">2202</fw> Minister of the Interior. On such unconsti<lb break="no"
                  />tutional lines he has carried his course for <lb/> a good many years. Take for
                  instance, his <lb/> Grand Trunk Pacific Bill. He did not go to <lb/> the people
                  with that before he introduced <lb/> it here? He carried it through two ses<lb
                     break="no"/>sions and then went to the country with it. <lb/> Sir John A.
                  Macdonald, when he introduced <lb/> the national policy, first went to the people,
                  <lb/> and got the approval of the people. The <lb/> right hon. gentleman was
                  afraid to go be<lb break="no"/>fore the people of this country in the last <lb/>
                  election on the Autonomy Bill, and he brings <lb/> it down in the first session in
                  order to <lb/> escape responsibility for it. Now, if he is <lb/> in trouble, as he
                  is in trouble, if he has <lb/> trouble, if the Minister of the Interior--<lb/>
               </p>
            <p>Some hon. MEMBERS. No, no. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. Do hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men opposite
                  mean to say that the Minister <lb/> of Justice has not thrown all the mem<lb
                     break="no"/>bers from the Northwest into fits? There <lb/> is trouble. I will
                  tell you why the right <lb/> hon. gentleman will not appoint a Minister <lb/> of
                  the Interior ; it is because if he gets a <lb/> Minister of the Interior to
                  consent to these <lb/> modifications he proposes, he will have an <lb/> other
                  province on his hands, another re<lb break="no"/>bellion to quell ; and, being in
                  that position, <lb/> he cannot resort to the straight constitu<lb break="no"
                  />tional method of solving these questions. <lb/> He should not have introduced
                  this Bill <lb/> without having had the consent and advice <lb/> of the members
                  from the Northwest ; and <lb/> on behalf of the province of Manitoba to-day <lb/>
                  I ask the hon. member for Brandon (Mr. <lb/> Sifton), I ask the hon. member for
                  Lisgar <lb/> (Mr. Greenway), I ask all the delegation from <lb/> the west, whether
                  they approve of this <lb/> legislation having been introduced without <lb/> their
                  representatives in the cabinet being <lb/> consulted, and whether they propose to
                  <lb/> submit any longer to this legislation being <lb/> proceeded with without
                  having a minister <lb/> in the cabinet representing them and repre<lb break="no"
                  />senting the west. It is not constitutional. <lb/> It may be justified, but it
                  will end in dis<lb break="no"/>aster, it cannot end in anything else. Now, <lb/>
                  if the right hon. gentleman fixes up his <lb/> fences as far as Manitoba is
                  concerned, he <lb/> will find them down in Nova Scotia, and as <lb/> soon as he
                  fixes them up in regard to Nova <lb/> Scotia and the Northwest, he will find them
                  <lb/> down in the province of Quebec ; and, being <lb/> in that position, he has
                  to resort to all these <lb/> tricks. He is afraid of trusting the people <lb/>
                  to-day, he is afraid of the good old principle <lb/> he laid down years ago of
                  provincial rights. <lb/> Now, I want to tell him in regard to this <lb/> education
                  problem, that he can patch it up <lb/> as much as he likes, he can hold what <lb/>
                  caucuses he likes, he can fix up his fences <lb/> in this direction and in that
                  direction ; but <lb/> there is only one thing that will satisfy the <lb/>
                  provinces of Canada to-day, and that is <lb/> complete autonomy for the Northwest
                     pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. the right of the people of the west <lb/> to settle
                  their own educational affairs. They <lb/>
                  <cb/> wish to be free to settle this question ; they <lb/> don't want all these
                  bickerings in the cabi<lb break="no"/>net. They want to be treated as freemen,
                  <lb/> with the right to settle their own educa<lb break="no"/>tional questions ;
                  and it is because they <lb/> dared to assert their freedom in this House, <lb/>
                  because they had a minister in the govern<lb break="no"/>ment who was prepared to
                  assert that right, <lb/> that that minister has been put out, and <lb/> they are
                  to-day to be treated as slaves. <lb/> Again I tell the right hon. gentleman that
                  <lb/> he must have more respect for the consti<lb break="no"/>tution. So far he
                  professes to be upholding <lb/> the constitution. But everything he does is <lb/>
                  irregular—his relations with his ministers, <lb/> these negotiations that are
                  going on to-day, <lb/> all these things that we hear of, and many <lb/> other
                  things that don't get into the press, <lb/> but that we know are going on, with no
                  <lb/> peace in prospect, continued bickerings are <lb/> in store for us. Again I
                  say he is on the <lb/> wrong line, and he must retrace his steps. <lb/> He has
                  spoken to—day of the retreat of the <lb/> late Minister of the Interior. There was
                  <lb/> no retreat on the part of the late Minister <lb/> of the Interior in
                  standing up for the rights <lb/> of the new provinces. He was maintaining <lb/>
                  what I call good doctrine in regard to pro<lb break="no"/>vincial rights. Yet,
                  because he took that <lb/> position in this House, the First Minister <lb/> says
                  he is retreating. Well, the right hon. <lb/> gentleman may say it is a retreat,
                  but I <lb/> say, No. Once again, in the name of the <lb/> people of the great
                  Northwest, I ask the <lb/> government to keep their hands off these <lb/> new
                  provinces in regard to education. Let <lb/> the people up there settle these
                  questions <lb/> themselves. They are well competent to do <lb/> it ; they know
                  what they want without any <lb/> advice from any other province, I do not <lb/>
                  care which. Al lthey ask is that they be <lb/> permitted to settle their own
                  affairs. I do <lb/> not care what batteries may be placed in <lb/> this House, on
                  the one side or the other. <lb/> There is no service in this House but the <lb/>
                  one service—the public service. I want to <lb/> tell the right hon. gentleman
                  this, that it <lb/> may take much longer than he counts on to <lb/> put this
                  session through. I do not see why <lb/> the right hon. gentleman should get one
                  <lb/> dollar of supplies while he has no minister <lb/> of the Interior to take
                  the part of Manitoba. <lb/> I do not see why he should get any legisla<lb
                     break="no"/>tion through this House until he comes for<lb break="no"/>ward with
                  a complete ministry, until he <lb/> comes forward with a man representing that
                  <lb/> portion of the country—if the government <lb/> believe in geographical
                  representation—with <lb/> a man from that portion of the country pre<lb break="no"
                  />pared to assume the responsibilities of this <lb/> government in connection with
                  their pro<lb break="no"/>gramme in dealing with the autonomy of <lb/> the west.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. The hon. gentleman did <lb/> not conclude with a
                  motion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. I beg to move <lb/> that the House do now
                  adjourn. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. In making a motion the <lb/> hon. gentleman
                  should rise. <lb/>
               </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>