<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1891-09-30" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1891-09-20">20 September 1891</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, First Session</title>.
<date when="1891"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="6325" to="6327"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-09-30_Page_06325.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-09-30_Page_06327.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-23">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-09-30_Page_06325"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-09-30_Page_06325.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-09-30_Page_06327"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-09-30_Page_06327.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="6325" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-09-30_Page_06325.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">6325</fw> <fw type="dateline">[SEPTEMBER 30, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">6326</fw>

<head rendition="simple:centre">LOCAL REPRESENTATION OF THE NORTH-<lb break="yes"/>WEST TERRITORIES.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName> moved second reading of <lb/>
Bill (No. 178) further to amend the Acts respect<lb break="no"/>ing the North-West Territories. He said: This is an <lb/>
amendment which I explained yesterday, and its <lb/>
object is to equalize the representation of the <lb/>
several provisional districts of the North-West <lb/>
Territories. It has been found since the census <lb/>
was taken that the arrangement we had made does <lb/>
not give a fair representation to the different <lb/>
provisional districts. The population of Alberta, <lb/>
for instance, is 26,123, of Assiniboia, 30,285, and <lb/>
of Saskatchewan, 11,146. By allowing six repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives to the Saskatchewan district, it gave <lb/>
one representative for each 1,857 inhabitants. By <lb/>
giving twelve representatives to Assinihoia, it gives <lb/>
them one to every 2,523. In Alberta eight repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives gives one to each 3,640 inhabitants; <lb/>
showing that Alberta really suffers more than any <lb/>
of the other districts. It is proposed to take one <lb/>
from Saskatchewan which would then give a re<lb break="no"/>presentative to a population of over 3,000 and <lb/>
equalize it to that extent. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LARI1">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName>. I have no doubt that there <lb/>
is, perhaps, some arguments in favour of basing the <lb/>
representation strictly on population; but I believe <lb/>
there are other considerations that we must remem<lb break="no"/>ber, there is a territorial representation to be con<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

sidered as well. Now, it is true that Assiniboia <lb/>
has a larger population than Saskatchewan, but the <lb/>
territory of Assiniboia is a great deal smaller than <lb/>
that of Saskatchewan, and though the population <lb/>
of Saskatchewan may not be as large, it is more <lb/>
scattered, and perhaps requires a great deal more <lb/>
attention from the representatives than more <lb/>
thickly settled districts. I am sorry that in order <lb/>
to give Assiniboia an increase of representation <lb/>
which I would not deny, as they are perhaps en<lb break="no"/>titled to it—we should be asked to deprive Sas<lb break="no"/>katchewan of a division which has only been <lb/>
granted to it a few days ago. We knew at the <lb/>
time we made these new divisions, what the census <lb/>
was, and it was for those who were responsible to <lb/>
call our attention to this fact, if that was an argu<lb break="no"/>ment strong enough to require us to make the <lb/>
alterations that are asked to-day. I do not see why, <lb/>
after agreeing to these electoral divisions in the <lb/>
district of Saskatchewan, we should now be called <lb/>
upon to stultify ourselves in making a re-arrange<lb break="no"/>ment of those divisions. I am aware, and the <lb/>
House is aware, that the passing of this Bill a few <lb/>
days ago has had the effect of leading the people to <lb/>
select candidates for those divisions we have <lb/>
already created, and those candidates have already <lb/>
begun the campaign for an election which will take <lb/>
place in a short time. Now, these people are <lb/>
greatly dissatisfied and when the rumour was set <lb/>
afloat that such a change was to take place. I, for <lb/>
one, received several telegrams from interested <lb/>
parties, asking whether such changes were going <lb/>
to be made, and why the people should be made <lb/>
mere playthings of by this House, and whether, <lb/>
after creating the electoral divisions for them, we <lb/>
were going to take them away after the people <lb/>
had already begun to act in accordance with the <lb/>
law that has been passed. I, therefore, hope that <lb/>
while this measure may grant an additional elec<lb break="no"/>toral division to Assiniboia, to which I do not <lb/>
object, it will not be to the detriment of Saskat<lb break="no"/>chewan. Add another division, if you like. but <lb/>
do not rob Peter in order to pay Paul. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. I do not think any great <lb/>
harm would be done to any one, even if the Bill <lb/>
was allowed to remain as it came from the Senate. <lb/>
It certainly would do Saskatchewan a little good, <lb/>
because it would then leave for that territory the <lb/>
members which it was understood they were en<lb break="no"/>titled to, and the people there had already made <lb/>
arrangements, I believe, to select members to repre<lb break="no"/>sent the districts which we had created. I may <lb/>
say, in regard to Saskatchewan, that since the com<lb break="no"/>pletion of the railway a large immigration is going <lb/>
in there. During the last few years I have had <lb/>
application to send a surveyor to subdivide two <lb/>
townships, in order that the families who are there <lb/>
waiting may be located on the land. Therefore, <lb/>
in anticipation of a very large immigration into <lb/>
that district it is very desirable to make provisions <lb/>
for a large representation. The hon. gentleman <lb/>
who has spoken knows that in that district a <lb/>
portion of the inhabitants would consider it a hard<lb break="no"/>ship if we did not make a re-arrangement. An <lb/>
understanding was come to between the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) and myself <lb/>
that this change should be made; but of course we <lb/>
cannot go on with the Bill without the unanimous <lb/>
consent of the House, and if the hon. gentleman <lb/>
feels so strongly that we should not do so, of <lb/>
course I can do nothing but withdraw the Bill. <lb/></p>

<pb n="6327" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-09-30_Page_06327.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">6327</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">6328</fw> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LARI1">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName>. I only object to one clause <lb/>
of the Bill, that is, the second clause, taking away <lb/>
from one district what is wanted in the other. I <lb/>
do not object to the other clauses at all. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. The hon. gentleman will see <lb/>
that this is a matter which has just been disposed <lb/>
of. It should have been brought up earlier in the <lb/>
session. It is impossible to say whether the new <lb/>
divisions or the old divisions are right. It is <lb/>
impossible for any man in this House, except per<lb break="no"/>haps the Minister or the hon. members from the <lb/>
North-West, to give it sound judgment on the <lb/>
matter. <lb/></p> 

<p>Motion agreed to, and Bill read the second time. <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>