<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-01-16"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-01-16">16 January 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

         
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
         

           <date when="1905"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="14"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="22"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="32"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="39" to="42"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="46"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0011.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0013.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0019.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0021.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0031.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0039.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0041.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0045.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-01-04">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-01-04">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0011">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0011.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0013">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0013.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0019">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0019.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0021">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0021.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0031">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0031.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0039">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0039.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0041">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0041.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0045">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0045.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="11" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0011.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">11</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS </fw>
            <fw type="num">12</fw>
            <p><add><persName ref="pers:MACD4">Mr. MACDONALD</persName> — </add> [...] practically so as to suit the needs and inter<lb
                  break="no"/>ests of the country from time to time. By <lb/> a large majority the
               Canadian people, not <lb/> so long ago, gave evidence in a manner so <lb/> marked, so
               decidedly expressed, that no one <lb/> can gainsay it of their confidence in the
               <lb/> ability of this government to deal with the <lb/> question of the tariff along
               the lines I have <lb/> indicated. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Another item of great interest to our peo<lb break="no"/>ple is the announcement in the speech of the 
     <lb/>
     appointment of a commission to act with 
     <lb/>
     one similarly appointed by the United States 
     <lb/>
     government with regard to the preservation 
     <lb/>
     of the rivers and other waterways which are 
     <lb/>
     common to the two great countries. That is a 
     <lb/>
     declaration which I am sure, in this land of 
     <lb/>
     mountain and the lake, and this land of rush<lb break="no"/>ing rivers, this land in which our immense 
     <lb/>
     water—powers and waterways are destined to 
     <lb/>
     fill so important a place is one which Will be 
     <lb/>
     welcomed by the House; and the labours of 
     <lb/>
     that commission which was originated by an 
     <lb/>
     Act of Congress passed in 1902, will no doubt 
     <lb/>
     be watched throughout this country with 
     <lb/>
     deep interest and I am confident will result 
     <lb/>
     in good to both nations. No one will gainsay 
     <lb/>
     the statement that Canadians generally re<lb break="no"/>gard the maintenance of friendly relations 
     <lb/>
     with the great English speaking people to 
     <lb/>
     the south of us as of prime importance, and 
     <lb/>
     without exception hope that the time will 
     <lb/>
     never come when those friendly relations 
     <lb/>
     may in anyway be impaired or unsettled; 
     <lb/>
     but while that is the case, and while we 
     <lb/>
     are prepared to discuss with them such mat<lb break="no"/>ters of common interest as I have mentioned, 
     <lb/>
     I am sure that we all cordially endorse the 
     <lb/>
     declaration of the right hon. the First Min<lb break="no"/>ister that we will send no more delegations 
     <lb/>
     to Washington just now, to look for trade 
     <lb/>
     favours. We have now reached that stage 
     <lb/>
     when we have become self-reliant and con<lb break="no"/>fident in our own resources and great future. 
     <lb/>
     We have implicit reliance in the capabilities 
     <lb/>
     of Canada, and while prepared to favour<lb break="no"/>ably consider any proposition in the interests 
     <lb/>
     of both countries, looking towards an im<lb break="no"/>provement in our trade relations, we do not 
     <lb/>
     feel disposed to-day to send any more dele<lb break="no"/>gations on the question of reciproc1ty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The policy announced in the speech of 
     <lb/>
     granting provincial autonomy for the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories marks an important epoch 
     <lb/>
     in our history. It is thirty-four years ago 
     <lb/>
     since the province of Manitoba was admit<lb break="no"/>ted into confederation and given all those 
     <lb/>
     rights, and that status in the federation 
     <lb/>
     which is enjoyed by every province in the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion, and at this moment it may be op<lb break="no"/>portune to indulge in a retrospective glance 
     <lb/>
     and recall some of the advances and de<lb break="no"/>velopments that have occurred since con<lb break="no"/>federation. Thirty—eight years ago when 
     <lb/>
     confederation was established it embraced 
     <lb/>
     but four provinces and covered a territory 
     <lb/>
     stretching between Lake Superior and the 
     <lb/>
     sea. Each one of these provinces was then 
     <lb/>
     imbued mainly by local prejudices and limit<lb break="no"/>ed by provincial aspirations. Each one was 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
         
     unacquainted with the other. There was no 
     <lb/>
     common tie save that of the constitution 
     <lb/>
     which bound them together. Our total trade 
     <lb/>
     then amounted to but one hundred and thirty 
     <lb/>
     one million dollars. Our railway mileage was 
     <lb/>
     but two thousand miles and our postal re<lb break="no"/>venue but one million dollars. Our bank de<lb break="no"/>posits amounted to but thirty-eight million 
     <lb/>
     dollars, and our people generally had but a 
     <lb/>
     limited appreciation of the resources and pos<lb break="no"/>sibilities then awaiting development. Our out<lb break="no"/>look was purely provincial and the aspirations 
     <lb/>
     and ideas of our people were almost exclus<lb break="no"/>ively limited by the boundaries of the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces in which they lived. It is but just 
     <lb/>
     to bear tribute to the foresight of that great 
     <lb/>
     statesman who presided at the inception of 
     <lb/>
     Canada's birth and who watched over this 
     <lb/>
     country when in her swaddling clothes. We 
     <lb/>
     can all, irrespective of party, regard him as 
     <lb/>
     one who did great things for Canada and 
     <lb/>
     whose name will always be embalmed in the 
     <lb/>
     history of this Dominion. In 1870, when the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest was a seething mass of rebellion 
     <lb/>
     and discontent, the Territories were brought 
     <lb/>
     into confederation. In 1871, British Columbia 
     <lb/>
     entered the union. In 1873 the little island 
     <lb/>
     of Prince Edward followed her example and 
     <lb/>
     in 1875 the Northwest was placed under the 
     <lb/>
     jurisdiction of a lieutenant governor. Then 
     <lb/>
     in 1880 all the British possessions in North 
     <lb/>
     America were placed under the Dominion of 
     <lb/>
     our federal parliament with the exception 
     <lb/>
     of Newfoundland. Then followed the con<lb break="no"/>struction of the Canadian Pacific Railway, 
     <lb/>
     which bound all the provinces together and 
     <lb/>
     gave to the eastern provinces a common 
     <lb/>
     interest in the western heritage, and gave 
     <lb/>
     birth to that newer patriotism which has 
     <lb/>
     shown such rapid development in the last 
     <lb/>
     few years. Following the building of this 
     <lb/>
     railway, came new settlements. From all 
     <lb/>
     portions of the habitable globe came settlers 
     <lb/>
     into this new country, so that no less than 
     <lb/>
     three hundred and twenty-four thousand 
     <lb/>
     eight hundred and ninety-eight people during 
     <lb/>
     the past four years have gone into this new 
     <lb/>
     land—a number exceeding the population of 
     <lb/>
     some of our provinces and equalling that of 
     <lb/>
     others. When we stop to consider the fact 
     <lb/>
     also, that during the past four years 94,791 
     <lb/>
     homesteads have been taken up in that coun<lb break="no"/>try, we can form some conception of the 
     <lb/>
     rapidity of its growth. In those western 
     <lb/>
     territories, which are to be given provincial 
     <lb/>
     autonomy, there exists a country which ex<lb break="no"/>ceeds in extent the countries of France, 
     <lb/>
     Germany and Italy taken together. This 
     <lb/>
     is indeed a precious heritage, this great 
     <lb/>
     Northwest land, which to-day forms part of 
     <lb/>
     our territory and in which we are about to in<lb break="no"/>augurate a system of government which will 
     <lb/>
     place that country on an equal footing with 
     <lb/>
     the other provinces in confederation. Realiz<lb break="no"/>ing the advantages which Canada offers to 
     <lb/>
     new settlers, We have men from all lands 
     <lb/>
     and every clime taking up homesteads in 
     <lb/>
     that vast territory, where they will enjoy 
     <lb/>
     constitutional rights and privileges from 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="13" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0013.jpg"/>
         <fw type="num">13</fw> <fw type="dateline">JANUARY 16, 1905</fw> <fw type="num">14</fw>

     which they are debarred in lands from 
     <lb/>
     which they come. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The making of this new province, or these 
     <lb/>
     new provinces, as the case may be will es<lb break="no"/>tablish a continuous line of provinces from 
     <lb/>
     sea to sea, and will, to a certain extent, 
     <lb/>
     round off confederation. As a result of this 
     <lb/>
     growth which I have but roughly outlined, 
     <lb/>
     a great change has been coming over (Can<lb break="no"/>ada. Our outlook has widened during the 
     <lb/>
     thirty-eight years that have gone. We have 
     <lb/>
     ceased to view matters from a provincial 
     <lb/>
     or narrow point of view; our outlook has 
     <lb/>
     become a Dominion, a continental one. And, 
     <lb/>
     especially during the last eight years has 
     <lb/>
     this development gone on in so remarkable 
     <lb/>
     a degree that I may be pardoned for refer<lb break="no"/>ring to it. One of the advantages of this 
     <lb/>
     marked advance of the last eight years is 
     <lb/>
     that old race and creed issues have been for<lb break="no"/>gotten, and from sea to sea men do not now 
     <lb/>
     stop to consider these things, but we realize 
     <lb/>
     in a way we never did before that we are 
     <lb/>
     Canadians one and all. There is coming to 
     <lb/>
     Canada, but more particularly to young 
     <lb/>
     Canada, a realization of the great resources 
     <lb/>
     and extent of our country which was not 
     <lb/>
     present with us even a few years ago. 
     <lb/>
     When we recall that, in Canada we have an 
     <lb/>
     area that is more than one-third of the 
     <lb/>
     whole British empire, and as that idea has 
     <lb/>
     permeated the whole life of our people, 
     <lb/>
     there has grown a patriotic pride and a 
     <lb/>
     feeling of interest in and devotion to our 
     <lb/>
     country which, in other nations and in 
     <lb/>
     other times, it has required the stern teach<lb break="no"/>ing of war to evoke. And our pride in our 
     <lb/>
     institutions, in our literature, in our rapid 
     <lb/>
     growth in national life, has been enhanced 
     <lb/>
     by our faith in our country's resources, and 
     <lb/>
     by a realization of the fact that during the 
     <lb/>
     past eight years our trade increase has ex<lb break="no"/>ceeded that of every other country in the 
     <lb/>
     history of the world. I have already given 
     <lb/>
     some figures showing our position at 
     <lb/>
     the time of confederation. To-day, our 
     <lb/>
     railway mileage exceeds 20,000 miles; our 
     <lb/>
     postal revenue is over $6,000,000 a year; 
     <lb/>
     the deposits in our banks instead of being 
     <lb/>
     $38,000,000, as they were thirty-eight years 
     <lb/>
     ago, are close upon $600,000,000. Once 
     <lb/>
     these facts are realized, we contemplate the 
     <lb/>
     position of Canada With growing exultation 
     <lb/>
     and pride. We realize that here in Canada, 
     <lb/>
     we have all the elements by which we may 
     <lb/>
     become the great flour, paper, cheese, but<lb break="no"/>ter and provision producer, as well 
     <lb/>
     the great woodenware manufacturing cen<lb break="no"/>tre of the world. These natural conditions 
     <lb/>
     are beginning to be appreciated, and 
     <lb/>
     are certain of early exploitation. But our 
     <lb/>
     outlook widening, as it has been on the 
     <lb/>
     federal and continental side, looks also to<lb break="no"/>ward the imperial field; andI am proud to 
     <lb/>
     say that I believe there is not in Canada any 
     <lb/>
     desire for any other future than in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with \the great empire to which we be<lb break="no"/>long. At the same time, we should remem<lb break="no"/>ber that he who would artificially or un<lb break="no"/><cb/>naturally hasten the solution of the problem 
     <lb/>
     of our future relations to the empire may 
     <lb/>
     create the worst stumbling block in the 
     <lb/>
     way of reaching the end which he desires 
     <lb/>
     to see attained. There are those who are 
     <lb/>
     accustomed to say that Canada has done 
     <lb/>
     nothing towards paying her debt of 
     <lb/>
     gratitude to the empire. I think they 
     <lb/>
     forget the efforts that have been put forth 
     <lb/>
     by Canada, and the help that has been ren<lb break="no"/>dered by Canada in constructing already 
     <lb/>
     one great transcontinental line and prepar<lb break="no"/>ing for the immediate construction of 
     <lb/>
     another. The first of these already has 
     <lb/>
     been, and both of them must be, tremendous 
     <lb/>
     factors in binding the empire together, whe<lb break="no"/>ther in peace or in war. In addition to that, 
     <lb/>
     Canada has shown herself, by her attitude 
     <lb/>
     at the time of the South African war, to be 
     <lb/>
     ready to stand by the empire in the hour 
     <lb/>
     of national necessity. We are going on 
     <lb/>
     with the inception of a Canadian navy—a ' 
     <lb/>
     small navy it may be, but we are moving 
     <lb/>
     along the proper line by arranging that 
     <lb/>
     when Canada spends her money on behalf 
     <lb/>
     of the empire she shall oversee that expen~ 
     <lb/>
     diture. It may be true—it is true—that 
     <lb/>
     Canada must make some sacrifices in order 
     <lb/>
     that the problem of the empire may be 
     <lb/>
     solved. Those of us who believe in 
     <lb/>
     imperial connection and the future of the 
     <lb/>
     empire are ready that these sacrifices should 
     <lb/>
     be made. At the same time, Canada's in<lb break="no"/>terests must be guarded, and there must be 
     <lb/>
     corresponding sacrifices in every other part 
     <lb/>
     of the empire, in order that a harmonioas 
     <lb/>
     and a successful future may be assured. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>The next paragraph of the address to 
     <lb/>which I will refer announces that satisfac<lb break="no"/>tory progress has been made in carrying out 
     <lb/>the policy of a national transcontinental 
     <lb/>railway which was approved by parliament 
     <lb/>two years ago and reaffirmed last session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I am sure that hon. gentlemen opposite <lb/>appreciate to—day, perhaps more even than
               <lb/>they did in the past, the great importance <lb/>to Canada of carrying to a
               successful issue <lb/>the construction of this great railway. It is <lb/>only fair to
               say that, although some of these <lb/>hon. gentlemen, at the inception of this pro<lb
                  break="no"/>position, were disposed to combat the idea <lb/>that the new
               Transcontinental Railway was <lb/>necessary, at the conclusion of the discus<lb
                  break="no"/>sion of that question, they frankly admitted <lb/>that it was a good
               thing to have the new <lb/>railway. But they interjected into the dis<lb break="no"
               />cussion a proposition which was utterly <lb/>opposed to all the traditions of their
               party, <lb/>when they suggested the government owner<lb break="no"/>ship and
               operation of that railway. <lb/>Today, I am sure, they will join with us <lb/>in the
               satisfaction we all feel in learn<lb break="no"/>ing that a great many of the
                  difficul<lb break="no"/>ties that were expected in the inaugur<lb break="no"
               />ation of this enterprise are rapidly disap<lb break="no"/>pearing. Thus, we were
               told that the coun<lb break="no"/>try through which the railway is to pass
               <lb/>between Quebec and Winnipeg was a coun<lb break="no"/>try of muskeg and stunted
               poplar. I am <lb/>
               <pb n="19" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0019.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">19</fw>
               <fw type="num">COMMONS</fw>
               <fw type="num">20</fw> <persName ref="pers:PARE1">Mr. PARENT</persName> conflicts of opinion which its
               discussion will <lb/> set forth, the principles of toleration and <lb/> equal rights
               which should be sanctioned <lb/> thereby. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It has been stated that 'Experience is a 
     <lb/>
     physician called in too late' ; and I may not 
     <lb/>
     be wrong in thinking that the experience 
     <lb/>
     acquired of late years in the province of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba has been of that kind. The young 
     <lb/>
     men of my generation, undoubtedly, have 
     <lb/>
     not wholly realized the painful ordeal which 
     <lb/>
     our country was made to undergo at a time 
     <lb/>
     when the cry of race and religion prevented 
     <lb/>
     the quiet discussion of the question of sep<lb break="no"/>arate schools and of the use of the French 
     <lb/>
     language. We were not in the heat of that 
     <lb/>
     battle, wherein galling epithets and hateful 
     <lb/>
     words were most dangerous missiles: we 
     <lb/>
     did not smell the powder of that fanatical 
     <lb/>
     warfare. But its rumblings reached our 
     <lb/>
     ears; we heard its echo. It may be that 
     <lb/>
     owing to our lack of experience, we have 
     <lb/>
     taken a somewhat exaggerated view of the 
     <lb/>
     situation; but we could not help trembling 
     <lb/>
     at the sight of the turmoil into which that 
     <lb/>
     bitter struggle of uncompromising principles 
     <lb/>
     might have fled our country, made up of vari<lb break="no"/>ous elements, had not the present govern<lb break="no"/>ment had the happy thought of negotiating 
     <lb/>
     a truce which will be some day final peace, 
     <lb/>
     let us hope. That result was effected, on 
     <lb/>
     the one hand, through the advice given to 
     <lb/>
     the Catholic minority from a quarter famil<lb break="no"/>iar to them, Rome, and, on the other hand, 
     <lb/>
     through the gentle promptings of diplomacy, 
     <lb/>
     whereby the Protestant majority were in<lb break="no"/>duced to take a stand making concessions 
     <lb/>
     easier all the time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The young men of my age are witnesses 
     <lb/>
     to—day, as it were, of the aftermath only of 
     <lb/>
     the storm; but that hurricane of prejudice 
     <lb/>
     has left on its train enough ruins, it has 
     <lb/>
     hurled too violently one against the others 
     <lb/>
     the sons of beautiful France and those of 
     <lb/>
     noble England, born on Canadian soil to 
     <lb/>
     live side by side, it has caused too much 
     <lb/>
     pain, brought about too many quarrels; in 
     <lb/>
     a word, it has done too much harm to the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian nation for us not to concern our 
     <lb/>
     selves with its possible recurrence. 1 am 
     <lb/>
     confident that the present government, in 
     <lb/>
     constituting these new provinces of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion, will foresee all the consequences of 
     <lb/>
     the setting in motion of the administrative 
     <lb/>
     and legislative machinery which they intend 
     <lb/>
     to install, and will thus prevent the crisis, 
     <lb/>
     the terrible effects of which have been set 
     <lb/>
     forth by recent events. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     But if I consider from another standpoint 
     <lb/>
    the conferring of provincial autonomy on the 
     <lb/>Territories, I cannot but rejoice at the 
     <lb/>thought of that fine page we are about to 
     <lb/>add to the history of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The entrance of a new province into the 
     <lb/>
     fold of the Dominion is always greeted with 
     <lb/>
     a hearty welcome. If that great and beau<lb break="no"/>tiful Northwest has reached manhood, so 
     <lb/>
     to speak, if it is mature for the grave func 
     <lb/>
     tion of self government, let, in the first place, 
     <lb/>
     all the other provinces offer their warmest 
     <lb/>

         <!--   <p>
     Mr. PARENT. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            <cb/>
         
     congratulations, and let the country as a 
     <lb/>
     whole rejoice as well. For the birth of a 
     <lb/>
     new province within the Dominion is not 
     <lb/>
     merely an indication of our prosperity, is 
     <lb/>
     not only a vindication of the manner in 
     <lb/>
     which public affairs have been managed 
     <lb/>
     since 1896. It is, besides, a step forward, 
     <lb/>
     made by Canada, and above all it is the 
     <lb/>
     certain pledge that our dream of becoming 
     <lb/>
     a great nation will soon be carried out. The 
     <lb/>
     gap which almost separates the extreme 
     <lb/>
     west from the east of Canada is thereby 
     <lb/>
     filled, our countly becomes almost homo<lb break="no"/>geneous and one stride more is taken in our 
     <lb/>
     countiy's noble and rapid progress towards 
     <lb/>
     its great destiny. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Sir, if I may be allowed to express a hope, 
     <lb/>
     let it be this: when self government will 
     <lb/>
     have been conferred on western Canada, 
     <lb/>
     self government which we love so much be<lb break="no"/>cause it is akin to liberty, when the major<lb break="no"/>ity of that countrv will be left to manage 
     <lb/>
     its affairs, may they turn their eyes towards 
     <lb/>
     the province, one of whose humble repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives I am here and whence so many 
     <lb/>
     courageous missionaries have gone to these 
     <lb/>
     distant lands; may they not close their eyes 
     <lb/>
     to the examples of toleration and good will 
     <lb/>
     which our legislators give in their dealings 
     <lb/>
     with the minority; may the breezes from 
     <lb/>
     our mountains when gently passing over the 
     <lb/>
     wheat fields of Assiniboia and Alberta bring 
     <lb/>
     with them their perfume of kindliness and 
     <lb/>
     generosity. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If I feel at ease in thus greeting these pro<lb break="no"/>vinces whose advent is announced in the 
     <lb/>
     speech from the Throne, it is because I re<lb break="no"/>call the measures taken beforehand by the 
     <lb/>
     government on their behalf. The older pro<lb break="no"/>vinces have extended a helping hand to that 
     <lb/>
     younger sister and to ensure her growth and 
     <lb/>
     normal development, the construction of a 
     <lb/>
     gieat 1ailway is now ensured. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Now, Sir, it is not my intention to deal 
     <lb/>
     at any length with the advantages offered 
     <lb/>
     by the Grand Trunk Pacific scheme. All 
     <lb/>
     that could be said on that subject has, or at 
     <lb/>
     any rate. should have been said, and to 
     <lb/>
     agree with me, one need only recall the in<lb break="no"/>numerable speeches delivered in the course 
     <lb/>
     of the recent electoral contest. If, never<lb break="no"/>theless, I make a passing reference to this 
     <lb/>
     gigantic undertaking, if I recall the dream 
     <lb/>
     of general prosperity which its carrying out 
     <lb/>
     will suggest for the country as a whole, if 
     <lb/>
     I corroborate the gratitude of my western 
     <lb/>
     brethren with my own humble congratula<lb break="no"/>tions, it is because I already can see the 
     <lb/>
     heavy wheat trains steaming towards my 
     <lb/>
     native city, crossing the river at Quebec, 
     <lb/>
     over that marvellous bridge, whose construc<lb break="no"/>tion was, in my childhood, so often repre<lb break="no"/>sented to me as impossible; and in the com<lb break="no"/>pletion of that bridge I recognize the reward 
     <lb/>
     due to the constant efforts, to the unrelent<lb break="no"/>ing unceasing labour of which I was the 
     <lb/>
     |witness in my father's home. And should 
     <lb/>
     such words seem presumptuous, please be 
     <lb/>
     indulgent towards a son who is the witness 
     <lb/>
         
            <pb n="21" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0021.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">21</fw> <fw type="dateline">JANUARY 16, 1905</fw> <fw type="num">22</fw> 
   
     as well of attacks of all sorts directed 
     <lb/>
     against his father.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Sir, unskilled as I am at dealing with 
     <lb/>
     political problems, having only my good will 
     <lb/>
     to offer for my country's service, I have not 
     <lb/>
     the right to claim your attention any longer; 
     <lb/>
     and as I must admit, I feel a certain fright 
     <lb/>
     at the mere sound of my voice in this House, 
     <lb/>
     1 long, as you will understand, to resume 
     <lb/>
     my seat. My last thought, that which has 
     <lb/>
     inspired me a courage which seemed to fail 
     <lb/>
     me at times, and one which you will greet 
     <lb/>
     most warmly, is, as you surmise, for the 
     <lb/>
     man whom all here respect and admire, to<lb break="no"/>wards him who not only has won the esteem 
     <lb/>
     and love of his fellow countrymen of all 
     <lb/>
     parties, of all creeds, of all races, but who 
     <lb/>
     has set his striking individuality in such 
     <lb/>
     brilliant light, that from the banks of the 
     <lb/>
     Thames and from those of the Seine, rays 
     <lb/>
     of his glory are reflected on the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     home land. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     My last thought, which is one of gratitude, 
     <lb/>
     goes to my representative, the right hon. 
     <lb/>
     Prime Minister, at whose feet I lay the hom<lb break="no"/>age of the most enthusiastic love of the Can<lb break="no"/>adian youth. Of course, my testimony will 
     <lb/>
     not have much weight when compared with 
     <lb/>
     the almost unanimous acclamations which, 
     <lb/>
     from the maritime provinces to British Col<lb break="no"/>umbia, have hailed his name, a name which 
     <lb/>
     on the battle field was worth a flag. . My 
     <lb/>
     testimony appears still more insignificant, if 
     <lb/>
     we recall the anguish shown throughout the 
     <lb/>
     country when, in the course of the last par<lb break="no"/>liament, a terrible disease and out of which 
     <lb/>
     it was terribly sought to take advantage, 
     <lb/>
     struck the idol of the Canadian people. And 
     <lb/>
     lastly, my testimony would dwindle into 
     <lb/>
     nothingness when compared with the feelings 
     <lb/>
     of joy which harkened his return to health, 
     <lb/>
     had it not to touch the heart of the greatest 
     <lb/>
     amongst us, that feature of almost filial 
     <lb/>
     feeling, independent of noisy manifestations, 
     <lb/>
     that feature of inward reverence which 
     <lb/>
     makes of my words the sincere, though im<lb break="no"/>perfect echo of the very feelings of the 
     <lb/>
     whole Canadian nation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I second the motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:FOST1">Hon. G. E. FOSTER</persName> (North Toronto). <lb/> Mr. Speaker, I think I
               shall be entirely <lb/> within my rights if I ask the kindly indul<lb break="no"
               />gence of the House usually accorded to a <lb/> new member on first rising to
               address this <lb/> august assembly. It is not often that it <lb/> falls to the lot of
               a new member to follow <lb/> and in some degree to criticise the speeches <lb/> of
               the new members who ordinarily move <lb/> and second the reply to the address. Such,
               <lb/> however, is my position to-day. In the first <lb/> place, I congratulate very
               heartily the hon. <lb/> gentlemen who have moved and seconded the <lb/> address, in
               their maiden efforts in this House. <lb/> The hon. gentleman who represents the
               county <lb/> of Pictou (Mr. Macdonald) displayed an ad<lb break="no"/>mirable
               confidence and a flow of words elo<lb break="no"/>quent and copious, and his ideas,
               if they <lb/> do not altogether run current with mine, cer<lb break="no"/>tainly
               commended themselves to the atten<lb break="no"/><cb/>tion of this House.
               Unfortunately, I was <lb/> not able to follow as closely the remarks <lb/> made by
               the hon. gentleman (Mr. Parent) <lb/> who seconded the address, but if I have a <lb/>
               proper understanding, both of these speeches <lb/> were exceedingly optimistic in
               their trend <lb/> and eulogistic in their purpose. The coun<lb break="no"/>try
               obtained a due share of the remarks, <lb/> and attention of these hon. gentlemen and
               <lb/> my right hon. friend who leads the House <lb/> (Sir W'ilfrid Laurier) was not
               bereft of a be<lb break="no"/>coming share, as well in their regards and <lb/> their
               attentions. In both these respects the <lb/> country is pleased to have the
               congratulations, <lb/> my right hon. friend is pleased to have these <lb/> renewed
               expressions of fidelity, and we on <lb/> this side of the House have no fault to find
               <lb/> with either. I, speaking for this side of the <lb/> House, may at the outset
               say that we heartily <lb/> agree with the hon. gentlemen who have <lb/> spoken, in
               extending our warm congratula<lb break="no"/>tions to the distinguished gentleman who
               is <lb/> our new Governor General. We welcome him <lb/> as we have welcomed all
               Governors General <lb/> to this Dominion of Canada. We welcome <lb/> him especially
               as one of a long line of ances<lb break="no"/>tors who have done grand service for
               the ex<lb break="no"/>tension and government of this great empire <lb/> to which we
               all belong. and I do not think <lb/> even in this age with all the rights and pri<lb
                  break="no"/>vileges of self-government, that the over-seas <lb/> dominions have
               and possess, and intend to <lb/> maintain, that the field is at all closed for <lb/>
               the exertion of similar influences, not of ex<lb break="no"/>tension or of conquest,
               but of organization <lb/> of development and the knitting together of <lb/> all parts
               of the empire. Who does not <lb/> know that the Canada of today exercises <lb/> a
               very large influence on the policies and <lb/> the tendencies of government in the
                  Bri<lb break="no"/>tish empire? Though no expression of <lb/> opinion may be made
               in this House, though <lb/> no expression of opinion may be officially <lb/> tendered
               in anyway, yet there is the atten<lb break="no"/>tive heed paid to what are the
               tendencies <lb/> and thoughts and wishes of the great de<lb break="no"/>pendencies
               beyond the seas, which have <lb/> their influence in determining policies and <lb/>
               in determining the trend and action of the <lb/> British government itself. Is it not
               equally <lb/> true that distinguished men, members of the <lb/> empire, coming from
               the mother islands to <lb/> the dependencies and over-seas dominions <lb/> such as
               this, have also a very strong part to <lb/> play and to fulfil in so knitting
               together, in <lb/> so carrymg out the idea of co-operation of <lb/> sentiment and of
               effort, that this great, but <lb/> yet to a large extent, unorganized world-wide
               <lb/> empire may become more firmly and securely <lb/> united than it is at the
               present time? So <lb/> that our Governor General, welcomed here <lb/> for himself and
               for his ancestry, is wel<lb break="no"/>comed here also by us for the work which
               <lb/> he has to do, and which we will welcome <lb/> and co-operate with him in doing.
               <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> In reference to the speeches, we may say <lb/> that the statements which have been
               made by <lb/> the two hon. gentlemen who have moved and <lb/> seconded the address,
               could be characterized <lb/>
               <pb n="31" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0031.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">31</fw>
               <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
               <fw type="num">32</fw> <persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName> the majority of my right hon.
               friend ? And <lb/> is be proud of a majority swelled by appeals <lb/> of this kind ?
               And here is another extract : <lb/></p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     <p>(Translation) 
     <lb/></p>
   <p>  TO THE ELECTORS OF THE COUNTY OF 
     <lb/>
     MONTMAGNY. 
     <lb/>
     The   Courrier de Montmagny,' October 31, 
     <lb/>
     Up to now I have been the Liberal candidate. 
     <lb/>
           </p> </quote>
   
            <p>
     Was not that glory enough for one man 
     <lb/>
     to be the Liberal candidate ? It appears 
     <lb/>
     not. 
     <lb/></p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p> (Translation) 
     <lb/></p>
           
   <p>  To-day, at the request of a large number of 
     <lb/>
     Conservatives, 1 become the nationalist candi<lb break="no"/>date. that is to say, I take the field as the 
     <lb/>
     champion of French and Catholic Canada, and 
     <lb/>
     of its right to a fair representation at Ottawa. 
     <lb/>
     I am a Liberal, but before all, I am against 
     <lb/>
     imperialism, militarism and against Quebec 
     <lb/>
     being crushed under the heel of the Tories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     They will try to buy your votes, my friends, 
     <lb/>
     but think of your old flag, think of our dear 
     <lb/>
     province, remember our ancestors and our re<lb break="no"/>ligion. The motto of Quebec is: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     ' I remember ' 
     <lb/></p>
<p>
     Do ye remember! . 
     <lb/></p>
<p rendition="simple:right">
     ARMAND LAVERGNE. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Now, I leave that as a side thought for my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend, and I ask him does he approve 
     <lb/>
     of that method of canvass, and does he think 
     <lb/>
     that is one of the filings that will bind this 
     <lb/>
     country together, will promote high public 
     <lb/>
     political ideas '2 Taking all these things into 
     <lb/>
     consideration, there are some points, which 
     <lb/>
     serve, may be, to diminish the apparent value 
     <lb/>
           
     of the great victory of the third of Novem<lb break="no"/>ber. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>But, I have been too long upon these 
     <lb/>details, and I now wish to come to the 
     <lb/>speech. The speech from the Throne itself 
     <lb/>—well there is not much to come to in this 
     <lb/>speech. It seems to have sprung from bar<lb break="no"/>ren and unfruitful soil. It looks to me like 
     <lb/>either the product of utter exhaustion—due, 
     <lb/>1 suppose, to the great eflorts of the election 
     <lb/>--or the product of a proud and superior 
     <lb/>carelessness, as though the hon. gentlemen 
     <lb/>opposite had earned a holiday and a good 
     <lb/>time, without thinking very much about the 
     <lb/>country. But there is one thing in the speech 
     <lb/>and that is the autonomy of the Northwest. 
     <lb/>We are not permitted to know what this 
     <lb/>measure will be. But it is a measure that 
     <lb/>has long been asked for by the people of 
     <lb/>the. Northwest, a measure that has been sup<lb break="no"/>ported by His Majesty's loyal opposition in 
     <lb/>the late parliament, as it is in this House, 
     <lb/>but which has been consistently and per<lb break="no"/>sistently denied by my right Ihon. friend and 
     <lb/>the government which he leads. in this 
     <lb/>speech, we have a promise of autonomy 
     <lb/>for the Northwest. Was that a late pre<lb break="no"/>election repentance? Was the letter that my 
     <lb/>right hon. friend Wrote on the eve of the 
     <lb/>election promising that something should be 
     <lb/>done to this end wrung from him by the fear 
     <lb/>of antagonizing votes? Whatever the reason, 
     <lb/>there was a promise, and this time there is 
     <lb/>the fulfilment so far as the speech from the 
     <lb/>    
   
            <cb/>
          
     Throne goes. I hope that my right hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend, in bringing down this measure, will 
     <lb/>
     give to the new province a geographical 
     <lb/>
     area that will be sufficient. For myself, I 
     <lb/>
     am opposed to dividing this country up into 
     <lb/>
     small provinces with their burden of judical 
     <lb/>
     and administrative oflicers, duties and ex<lb break="no"/>penses. I hope also there will be no stingi<lb break="no"/>ness with reference to the resources with 
     <lb/>
     which the new province shall be endowed. 
     <lb/>
     I think it would be a mistake if it were left 
     <lb/>
     to come to this parliament year after year 
     <lb/>
     voicing its demands for means to meet what 
     <lb/>
     must be great expenses, and increasing ex<lb break="no"/>penses as the development of the province 
     <lb/>
     proceeds. I hope the powers to be given to 
     <lb/>
     that province will be so definite, so clear and 
     <lb/>
     so full that the measure will be satisfactory 
     <lb/>
     to the sturdy pioneers who are to make 
     <lb/>
     that province great, and will avoid griev<lb break="no"/>ances and recriminations of every sort. We 
     <lb/>
     have no jealousy of the great west. There 
     <lb/>
     is no rivalry between the west and the 
     <lb/>
     east. The east bought the patrimony of that 
     <lb/>
     country, the money of the east paid for it. 
     <lb/>
     The brawn and brain of the east pioneered 
     <lb/>
     that great country and to-day our sons, our 
     <lb/>
     brothers and our fathers are the dominant 
     <lb/>
     race of the province that is to be. Every 
     <lb/>
     power which can be given to them should 
     <lb/>
     be given to enable them to lay the founda<lb break="no"/>tions of a province with an almost illimit<lb break="no"/>able future and one that will justify the 
     <lb/>
     confidence which we had in it when we made 
     <lb/>
     it a part of this great Dominion, a confidence 
     <lb/>
     which every succeeding year has increased. 
     <lb/></p>
<p>
    There is a further mild allusion made-<lb/>
no, there is no allusion made to that Old- 
     <lb break="yes"/>time indispensable market to the south of 
     <lb/>us. What has happened hon. gentlemen 
     <lb/>opposite? Have they discarded some more 
     <lb/>of their theories ? I know that it is impos<lb break="no"/>sible for heated steel always to retain its 
     <lb/>initial heat, but one would never have 
     <lb/>thought that that ardent party which called 
     <lb/>for commercial union, which vociferated its 
     <lb/>demands for unrestricted reciprocity, which 
     <lb/>reiterated its adhesion to the idea that the 
     <lb/>market to the south of us and its reciprocal 
     <lb/>enjoyment was worth more to us than the 
     <lb/>markets of all the world besides, should 
     <lb/>have lost all its intrinsic heat and warmth. 
     <lb/>Yet to-day the only paragraph we have in 
     <lb/>the speech that touches the country to the 
     <lb/>south of us, is that somewhat obscure one in 
     <lb/>which it is stated that an International 
     <lb/>Commission composed of three representa<lb break="no"/>tives from each country will be appointed 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     To investigate and report upon the conditions 
     <lb/>
     and uses of the waters adjacent to the bound<lb break="no"/>ary line between the United States and Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p> What that may mean I do not know, but <lb/> We will have to possess ourselves in
                  pat<lb break="no"/>ience until we find out the meaning of the <lb/> clause. But
               for ever and for ever, it would <lb/> seem, the old flag Which was nailed to the
               <lb/> top of the mast by my hon. friend, and of <lb/> which he said that it would
               float there un<lb break="no"/><pb n="39"
                  facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0039.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">39</fw>
               <fw type="num">COMMONS</fw>
               <fw type="num">40</fw> <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir. WILFRID LAUTIER</persName> the eyes of my hon.
               friend would be a merit <lb/> in the eyes of every one; it has the merit <lb/>of
               being concise and to the point. I believe <lb/>my hon. friend rather rejoices in high
               and <lb/>loud redundant sentences, and that the mere <lb/>clatter of syllables has
               some charm for his <lb/>ears, especially when the syllables fall from <lb/>his own
               tongue. I remember a time when <lb/>the speech was not so concise. In the olden
               <lb/>days, it was rather prone to conceal the <lb/>paucity of material under a
               verbosity of <lb/>expression. My hon. friend (Mr. Foster) <lb/>should have realized
               that the people will not <lb/>be fed upon words and wind, but prefer <lb/>a bill of
               fare reduced to a single course if <lb/>there is some substance in it. There is not
               <lb/>much legislation in the speech because we <lb/>do not propose to introduce much
               legislation. <lb/>There is only one great measure which it is <lb/>proposed to
               introduce and that is a Bill <lb/>granting autonomy to the western territories.
               <lb/>We think the time has come when the west<lb break="no"/>ern territories should
               have full partner<lb break="no"/>ship in confederation, when we should admit
               <lb/>them as members of the Canadian family <lb/>as full provinces. My hon. friend
               alluded to <lb/>the fact that for two or three years there <lb/>has been an appeal
               from the territories for <lb/>full autonomy. Some two years ago we <lb/>received
               delegations and requests from the <lb/>legislature and in some instances from the
               <lb/>people also, to have the territories at once <lb/>admitted as full provinces,
               but we repre<lb break="no"/>sented to the people and to the legislature <lb/>that the
               time was scarcely opportune to have <lb/>this introduced, that we could not be very
               <lb/>far from a general election and that at <lb/>that time the representation of the
               territories <lb/>in this House was small while after a gen<lb break="no"/>eral
               election there would be a larger repre<lb break="no"/>sentation. They had only four
               members in <lb/>the last parliament, they have now ten and <lb/>I think the wisdom of
               our judgment has now <lb/>been justified. It is true that we found some <lb/>doubting
               Thomases in the territories who <lb/>thought that we would not implement our
               <lb/>promises, but there is to-day in the speech <lb/>from the Throne an indication
               and the cer<lb break="no"/>tainty that on this occasion as on every oc<lb break="no"
               />casion this government fulfils its pledges <lb/>and carries out its promises. My
               hon friend <lb/>(Mr. Foster) does not know the character <lb/>of the legislation
               which we are about to in<lb break="no"/>troduce. I am sure my hon. friend does not
               <lb/>expect that we shall tell him at this time <lb/>the principal features of the
               Bill. We are <lb/>working on it now ; it is far advanced, but <lb/>in respect to
               three or four salient features <lb/>we thought it better to wait for the repre<lb
                  break="no"/>sentations of the Northwest government and <lb/>also the advice of our
               friends on the floor <lb/>of this House. <lb/>
            </p>
  
    

            <p>
     There is another suggestion in the speech 
     <lb/>
     upon which my hon. friend requires some 
     <lb/>
     information. He has not fully apprehended 
     <lb/>
     what is meant by our statement with regard 
     <lb/>
     to the commission which we have appointed 
     <lb/>
     to deal with the waterways between the 
     <lb/>
     United States and Canada. I am very glad 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
         
     to give my hon. friend and the House the in<lb break="no"/>formation to which they are entitled on this<lb/>
     point. It is within the knowledge of every<lb break="no"/>body that along a very great part of the 
     <lb/>
     boundary between Canada and the United 
     <lb/>
     States is the water system of the St. Law<lb break="no"/>rence. Now, I am sure. that every one will 
     <lb/>
     admit that it is to the interest of Canada as 
     <lb/>
     well as the United States that the surface of 
     <lb/>
     the water should be kept at as high a level as 
     <lb/>
     possible. Some few years ago, when it was 
     <lb/>
     rumoured that the state of Illinois intended 
     <lb/>
     to connect the waters of Lake Michigan 
     <lb/>
     with the waters of the Mississippi river by 
     <lb/>
     means of a canal, there was an apprehen<lb break="no"/>sion expressed, not only in this country but 
     <lb/>
     in the United States, that that work might 
     <lb/>
     have the effect of lowering the level of. the 
     <lb/>
     waters of Lake Michigan and adjacent 
     <lb/>
     waters'. As the event turned out, this fear 
     <lb/>
     was groundless, as the volume of water 
     <lb/>
     taken away by the canal is not sufficient to 
     <lb/>
     materially affect the level of the lakes. But 
     <lb/>
     if similar works were to be undertaken 
     <lb/>
     right and left, if the waters of Lake Erie 
     <lb/>
     and our system of waterways generally 
     <lb/>
     were to be tapped at different points, it is 
     <lb/>
     possible that the volume of water removed 
     <lb/>
     from the lakes would be so great that the 
     <lb/>
     level might be appreciably lowered. That 
     <lb/>
     is not all. In sections of the country where 
     <lb/>
     the boundary is not water, but land, there 
     <lb/>
     are streams and large rivers which have 
     <lb/>
     their sources in one country and which flow 
     <lb/>
     into the other. Complaint has been made 
     <lb/>
     by the United States that Canadians have 
     <lb/>
     constructed some works upon rivers which 
     <lb/>
     have their sources in Canada and which 
     <lb/>
     flow into the United States, and that these 
     <lb/>
     works affect the flow of the waters in their 
     <lb/>
     country. We also have made complaints 
     <lb/>
     to the United States that Americans have 
     <lb/>
     constructed upon some rivers, the St. John 
     <lb/>
     river, for instance, works which affect the 
     <lb/>
     flow of the waters in our country. It is, 
     <lb/>
     therefore, to the mutual interest and advan<lb break="no"/>tage of both countries to have this question 
     <lb/>
     properly investigated with the view of hav<lb break="no"/>ing concurrent legislation if such should be 
     <lb/>
     found necessary. From olden times it has 
     <lb/>
     been a principle of Roman law, which has 
     <lb/>
     been adopted by most civilized nations, that 
     <lb/>
     the riparian owner of any stream has the 
     <lb/>
     right to use the water of that stream for 
     <lb/>
     his own benefit, provided he does not im<lb break="no"/>pair the flow of the water beyond the boun<lb break="no"/>dary of his property. This is a principle 
     <lb/>
     of law which dominates in almost every 
     <lb/>
     country; but it is not possible to have this 
     <lb/>
     principle followed and carried out when 
     <lb/>
     the works are in one country and the boun<lb break="no"/>dary of the property is in another country. 
     <lb/>
     For these reasons we have thought it ad<lb break="no"/>visable to respond to the invitation of the 
     <lb/>
     United States to have this question inves<lb break="no"/>tigated. We have agreed to a commission 
     <lb/>
     to be composed of six members, three to 
     <lb/>
     represent the government of the United 
     <lb/>
         
            <pb n="41" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0041.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">41</fw> <fw type="dateline">JANUARY 16, 1905</fw> <fw type="num">42</fw>
           
     States and three to represent the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada. The instructions to the 
     <lb/>
     commission shall be laid on the table at 
     <lb/>
     an early day ; but in the meantime, to give 
     <lb/>
     all the information to my hon. friend to 
     <lb/>
     which he is entitled, I may mention the 
     <lb/>
     names of the commissioners who are to re<lb break="no"/>present the government of Canada—Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Maybee, K.C., an eminent lawyer of the 
     <lb/>
     city of Toronto; Mr. Louis Coste, of the 
     <lb/>
     Department of Public Works, an eminent 
     <lb/>
     hydraulic engineer, and Mr. King, the chief 
     <lb/>
     geographer of the Department of the In<lb break="no"/>terior. These gentlemen are to represent 
     <lb/>
     Canada at the conference, and we have rea<lb break="no"/>son to hope that they will bring in a report 
     <lb/>
     which will be satisfactory. I may say that 
     <lb/>
     this commission has no power to decide 
     <lb/>
     anything. It is not to lay down the basis 
     <lb/>
     of a treaty. It is simply to study the con<lb break="no"/>ditions and to report whether it is possible 
     <lb/>
     to devise remedies to meet an existing evil. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     My hon. friend has entered into a discus<lb break="no"/>sion of questions which I do not think it ad<lb break="no"/>visable for me to discuss at this moment. 
     <lb/>
     He has referred, for instance, to the de<lb break="no"/>fence of the country. This is a matter 
     <lb/>
     which may engage discussion later on, 
     <lb/>
     when my hon. friend the Minister of Mili<lb break="no"/>tia and Defence is in his seat. As to the 
     <lb/>
     question of the tariff and the question of the 
     <lb/>
     Audit Act, I can only say to my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     that at this moment I do not propose to dis 
     <lb/>
     cuss these questions. They will be dealt 
     <lb/>
    with fully, and to his satisfaction, I hope<lb break="no"/>though perhaps this is too much to expect<lb break="no"/>when the Minister of Finance is in his seat. 
     <lb/>Unfortunately, he has been obliged to go 
     <lb/>to Europe for domestic reasons. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     I may say, Mr. Speaker, that we do not 
     <lb/>
     propose this session to have any very ser 
     <lb/>
     ious or important legislation beyond the Act 
     <lb/>
     with reference to the Northwest Territor<lb break="no"/>ies. I agree to everything that has been 
     <lb/>
     said by my hon. friend as to the import<lb break="no"/>ance of that measure, though I would not 
     <lb/>
     subscribe to all his contentions. We pro<lb break="no"/>pose, if possible, to have a short session. 
     <lb/>
     We have not been blessed with a short ses<lb break="no"/>sion for a long time. We have had a ses<lb break="no"/>sion of seven months and another session of 
     <lb/>
     five months; but I think, if my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     will make a bargain with me, to make an 
     <lb/>
     effort to stop the flow of eloquence 
     <lb/>
     on both sides of the House, to keep within 
     <lb/>
     bounds, we may hope to see summer in 
     <lb/>
     the country, or spring by the time the sugar 
     <lb/>
     flows. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. I will go to the sugaring- <lb break="yes"/> up with
               you. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. We meet at <lb/> this time under a
               combination of happy <lb/> auspices. We have not only a new parlia<lb break="no"
               />ment, but a new Governor General. It has <lb/>become a trite observation that
               Canada has <lb/>been exceptionally fortunate in the charac<lb break="no"/>ter of
               those who have been entrusted with <lb/>the high prerogative of representing the <lb/>
               <cb/> Crown in this the first of all the British do<lb break="no"/>minions beyond the
               seas. Our present Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor General has been received with per<lb
                  break="no"/>haps more favour than any of his predeces<lb break="no"/>sors, and
               there is cause for this. His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency has the good fortune to bear
               a name <lb/> dear to all the friends of liberty and con<lb break="no"/>stitutional
               government in every part of the <lb/> empire, and especially in Canada. The il<lb
                  break="no"/>lustrious name of Grey recalls the name <lb/> of the great man whose
               persistent energy <lb/> wrung from unwilling peers and a reluctant <lb/> king the
               measure of reform which changed <lb/> the face of England, which averted a revo<lb
                  break="no"/>lution, and which transferred the govern<lb break="no"/>ment from a
               class to the nation. The name <lb/> of Grey also recalls to the people of this <lb/>
               country the illustrious names of Durham <lb/> and Elgin—the name of the man whose
               bold <lb/> genius conceived and designed the policy <lb/> which has revolutionized
               the colonial sys<lb break="no"/>tem of England by transferring the govern<lb
                  break="no"/>ment of Canada from the hands of a grasp<lb break="no"/>ing oligarchy
               to the people themselves; <lb/> and the name of the man whose strong <lb/> courage
               carried that policy to a successful <lb/> issue. Therefore, I say we meet under a
               <lb/> combination of happy circumstances, and <lb/> there is reason to hope and
               expect that the <lb/> illustrious name of Grey will be associated <lb/> with still
               further blessings to the people of <lb/> Canada. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName> (South York). Mr. <lb/> Speaker, it is not my
               intention to continue <lb/> the line of banter which has more or less <lb/>
               characterized the preceding speeches. I in<lb break="no"/>tend just for a few moments
               to ask the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the House to some incidents of <lb/> the
               recent election in this country. If <lb/> there is one thing that may be taken as a
               <lb/> lesson to us from that election, it is this<lb break="no"/>that in it there
               disappeared, especially in <lb/> my own province of Ontario-a province <lb/> which I
               am glad to say did not send a ma<lb break="no"/>jority in favour of the present
               government, <lb/> as was stated by the hon. member for Pic<lb break="no"/>tou (Mr.
               Macdonald)—a number of gentle<lb break="no"/>men who forgot why they had been sent
               <lb/> to parliament. They had forgotten what <lb/> representative institutions in
               this country <lb/> mean. They had forgotten that they were <lb/> sent here to
               represent the people. They <lb/> thought they were sent here to represent <lb/> the
               interests of great corporations, and their <lb/> constituents found them out, and
               they have <lb/> disappeared from the public life of this <lb/> country.   <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Without presuming to give any advice to 
     <lb/>
     the new men in this House, I would say to 
     <lb/>
     them, no matter on what side they may be, 
     <lb/>
     that more and more is it becoming incum<lb break="no"/>bent on the representatives of the people to 
     <lb/>
     give some concern to the interests of the 
     <lb/>
     people rather than the interests of corpor<lb break="no"/>ations. Only the other day I met a very 
     <lb/>
     worthy friend of mine who occupied a seat 
     <lb/>
     in this House in the last parliament, who 
     <lb/>
     came from Ontario, and supported hon. gen<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-01-16_Page_0045.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">45</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">JANUARY 16, 1905 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <fw type="num">46</fw>
            
<p>
     Ontario. There are a hundred ways of 
     <lb/>
     putting an end to monopolies if we have 
     <lb/>
     men enough in office willing to do it, but. 
     <lb/>
     neither the government nor the Liberal 
     <lb/>
     party are prepared to do anything. Neither 
     <lb/>
     will take the requisite steps to secure to the 
     <lb/>
     people travelling between Montreal and 
     <lb/>
     Toronto the two-cent rate to which they are 
     <lb/>
     entitled. These monopolies are the curse 
     <lb/>
     of parliament and the country. From time 
     <lb/>
     to time we have the doctrine laid down that 
     <lb/>
     parliament ought not to interfere. But I 
     <lb/>
     contend that it is the duty of parliament to 
     <lb/>
     regulate every one of these corporations, 
     <lb/>
     and give a warning to any corporation which 
     <lb/>
     is not treating the public fairly, that it must 
     <lb/>
     mend its ways or we will wipe it out of 
     <lb/>
     existence. Instead, however, of giving these 
     <lb/>
     corporations a warning, we give them addi<lb break="no"/>tional concessions every time they ask for 
     <lb/>
     them, and the public are told to go into the 
     <lb/>
     courts and recover their rights if they can, 
     <lb/>
     but that they need expect no assistance 
     <lb/>
     from the Minister of Justice or the Minister 
     <lb/>
     of Railways. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There is another point to which attention 
     <lb/>
     has been called of late, and which is well 
     <lb/>
     worthy of attention, and that is that in the 
     <lb/>
     United States, whose institutions we some<lb break="no"/>times think but little of, they have what is 
     <lb/>
     known as the grand jury, which is pos<lb break="no"/>sessed of powers of inquiry at important 
     <lb/>
     stages. In this country it was left to a 
     <lb/>
     private citizen to investigate the shameful 
     <lb/>
     ballot-box frauds that were attempted in 
     <lb/>
     the recent election. We were told that the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Justice was active in the matter 
     <lb/>
     but still it was left to a private citizen to 
     <lb/>
     expose the crime that had been attempted. 
     <lb/>
     Had we had a grand jury system as in the 
     <lb/>
     United States, the Crown Attorney could 
     <lb/>
     have issued a warrant and an investigation 
     <lb/>
     could have been held. And the same with 
     <lb/>
     other scandals in the recent election. But, 
     <lb/>
     as things are. there is no promise of an in<lb break="no"/>vestigation there is no likelihood of the 
     <lb/>
     air being cleared through the action of any 
     <lb/>
     one identified with the government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Returning for a moment to the position 
     <lb/>
     of railway corporations and their influence, 
     <lb/>
     we find that the greatest evil prevailing in 
     <lb/>
     the United States today in connection with 
     <lb/>
     railroading is the granting of discriminating 
     <lb/>
     rates in favour of certain corporations. 
     <lb/>
     There are great trusts in the United States, 
     <lb/>
     and these have been built up by railroad 
     <lb/>
     discriminations. The people of the United 
     <lb/>
     States are trying in some way to stop these 
     <lb/>
     discriminations. The plan that they have 
     <lb/>
     adopted is that of establishing a court such 
     <lb/>
     as our Railway Commission. But this plan 
     <lb/>
     has not succeeded. The president has been 
     <lb/>
     forced to take up the question. But the pub<lb break="no"/>lic there see more and more clearly that the 
     <lb/>
     only substantial cure is in government own<lb break="no"/>ership of the railways. And that, I believe, 
     <lb/>
     is equally true of this country. It is true 
     <lb/>
     that hon. gentlemen opposite say they do 
     <lb/>
     not believe in government ownership. But 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
         
     government ownership is the new principle 
     <lb/>
     of this century of which the right hon. 
     <lb/>
     Prime Minister professes to be the exponent. 
     <lb/>
     He has not read aright the sentiment of the 
     <lb/>
     country if he thinks that government owner<lb break="no"/>ship is not the only cure of the grievances 
     <lb/>
     arising from the operation of railways in 
     <lb/>
     this country and in the United States. But, 
     <lb/>
     instead of proposing government ownership, 
     <lb/>
     the right hon. gentleman leaves us in doubt. 
     <lb/>
     As the hon, member for North Toronto (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Foster) has pointed out, we are entitled to 
     <lb/>
     an explanation in regard to our state-owned 
     <lb/>
     railway, the Intercolonial. Is the rumour 
     <lb/>
     true that that railway is to be given over 
     <lb/>
     to the Grand Trunk ? We know that it is 
     <lb/>
     true that when the opportunity presented 
     <lb/>
     itself recently to couple up the Canada 
     <lb/>
     Atlantic with our state-owned road, the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment failed to improve that opportunity, 
     <lb/>
     thereby injuring the interests of the people 
     <lb/>
     and of the people's railway. The govern<lb break="no"/>ment had the opportunity of strengthening 
     <lb/>
     the Intercolonial, but apparently their policy 
     <lb/>
     is to let that road run down and turn it 
     <lb/>
     over to the Grand Trunk Pacific. Such a 
     <lb/>
     policy is not in line, I believe, with the 
     <lb/>
     demand of the times. The people see that 
     <lb/>
     there is no cure for the transportation pro<lb break="no"/>blems of this country except in government 
     <lb/>
     ownership. And if gentlemen opposite think 
     <lb/>
     they have a mandate from the people to 
     <lb/>
     destroy government ownership, I venture to 
     <lb/>
     tell them that they are mistaken. There 
     <lb/>
     is a party in this country, a national, a 
     <lb/>
     growing party, a party favoured by the 
     <lb/>
     young men of Canada, which holds that the 
     <lb/>
     best thing that could happen to this country 
     <lb/>
     would be the nationalization of the Grand 
     <lb/>
     Trunk Pacific. And the agitation to nation<lb break="no"/>alize that railway at an early stage of its 
     <lb/>
     career will go on. The carrying out of that 
     <lb/>
     policy will give hope of relief to the people, 
     <lb/>
     and especially to the people of Ontario and 
     <lb/>
     Quebec. The grievances of these people 
     <lb/>
     against the Grand Trunk today are worse 
     <lb/>
     than ever they were. The grievances of 
     <lb/>
     Toronto and Montreal, the grievances of the 
     <lb/>
     manufacturers and the shippers and otther 
     <lb/>
     people who live along that line are constant<lb break="no"/>ly increasing, and the feeling of these people 
     <lb/>
     is that state-ownership of that great railway 
     <lb/>
     is the only cure for those grievances. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Reference has been made to the promise 
     <lb/>of increased autonomy to the Northwest. 
     <lb/>It is high time that this idea should be car<lb break="no"/>ried out. I hope that the measure will be 
     <lb/>a wide one, and one that will allow for the 
     <lb/>growth and development of that country. 
     <lb/>But when we speak of increased autonomy 
     <lb/>for the Northwest, I think there is something 
     <lb/>to be said of the need of greater autonomy 
     <lb/>for the Dominion. The time has come 
     <lb/>when the bounds of our powers as a country 
     <lb/>should be widened. I am not afraid of the 
     <lb/>future and of the problems it will present 
     <lb/>for solution. I am not afraid to say that 
     <lb/>Canada should be more autonomous than 
     <lb/>she is to-day. I am not afraid to say that [...]
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>