<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1896-04-13"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1896-04-13">13 April 1896</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, Sixth Session</title>.
          <date when="1896"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="6111" to="6112"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-13_Page_06111.html"/>
               </item>
       
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-10">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-10">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-13_Page_06111">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-13_Page_06111.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="6111" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-04-13_Page_06111.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">6111</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">6112</fw>
 
 
 
 
     <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</head> 
    
    
            <head rendition="simple:right">Monday, 13th April, 1896.</head>
   
            <p>
     The SPEAKER took the Chair at Three 
     <lb/>
     o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <emph>PRAYERS.</emph>   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <div type="section">
           
      
      <head rendition="simple:centre">
     NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES REPRE<lb break="no"/>SENTATION ACT. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName> moved for leave to introduce 
     <lb/>
     Bill (No. 94) to amend the Acts respecting 
     <lb/>
     the Representation of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories in the Parliament of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. Explain, please. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. As hon. gentlemen are aware, 
     <lb/>
     at present the Territories are represented in 
     <lb/>
     this House by four members, from Saskatch<lb break="no"/>ewan, East Assriniboia, Western Assiniboia 
     <lb/>and Alberta. We propose under this Bill, to 
     <lb/>divide Alberta into two constituencies giving 
     <lb/>an additional representative to Alberta, and 
     <lb/>in consequence an addtional representative to 
     <lb/>the North-west Territories. Clause 44 of the 
     <lb/>original Act was struck out some two years 
     <lb/>ago, and I have received a petition from 
     <lb/>the Assembly of the Territories asking that 
     <lb/>the clause should be restored. I am restor<lb break="no"/>ing clause 44 by this Bill, but providing that 
     <lb/>the oath is not to be taken by the elector pre<lb break="no"/>senting himself at the poll in the manner set 
     <lb/>forth in the original Act. He must sub<lb break="no"/>scribe to and take the oath in the form pre<lb break="no"/>scribed in the schedule. I am informed that 
     <lb/>clause 44 was struck out of the original Bill 
     <lb/>in the Senate, because a great deal of perjury 
     <lb/>had taken place in Eastern Assiniboia, and I 
     <lb/>have endeavoured under this Bill to prevent 
     <lb/>anything of that kind, by providing that those 
     <lb/>who apply to the deputy returning officer to 
     <lb/>have their names put on the list, shall sub<lb break="no"/>scribe to the oath and swear to it before the 
     <lb/>deputy returning officer. It is believed that 
     <lb/>there will be less danger of perjury if the 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <cb/>
        
        
     person has to sign the affidavit. I have 
     <lb/>
     changed the oath of the enumerator, making 
     <lb/>
     it similar to the oath of the revising officer 
     <lb/>
     under the Franchise Act. The oath provided 
     <lb/>
     for in the Bill is as follows :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     I, enumerator for the polling 
     <lb/>
     district No. (or as the case may be), of 
     <lb/>
     the Electoral District of swear 
     <lb/>
     (or solemnly affirm) that I will well and faithfully 
     <lb/>
     discharge the duties assigned to me, without 
     <lb/>
     favour or partiality ; that I will place no name 
     <lb/>
     on the list of voters for the said polling district 
     <lb/>
     and will strike no name off the said list, unless 
     <lb/>
     I shall be satisfied that the said name should 
     <lb/>
     by law be placed on or struck off the said list ; 
     <lb/>
     and that I will in all respects conform to the 
     <lb/>
     law to the best of my judgment and ability. 
     <lb/>
     So help me God. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     These are the only provisions of the Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. This Bill, as I understand, 
     <lb/>
     meets the point that was intended to be met 
     <lb/>
     in the Bill which I placed upon the paper, 
     <lb/>
     and I think also the Bill that my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Martin) placed there. There is in ad<lb break="no"/>dition to that, an additional member provid<lb break="no"/>ed for in the North-west Territories. The 
     <lb/>
     chief thing which the peeple up there are in<lb break="no"/>terested in is met by the first part of the Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. Do I understand the Min<lb break="no"/>ister of the Interior to say that Alberta is 
     <lb/>
     simply divided into two, and that he does 
     <lb/>
     not alter Eastern or Western Assiniboia ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. It is simply a division of Al<lb break="no"/>berta by the line which is the southern 
     <lb/>
     boundary of Saskatchewan being extended 
     <lb/>
     2westerly to the western boundary of Alberta. 
     <lb/>
     This line runs south of Innisfail. It is nearly 
     <lb/>
     as equal a division of the population of Al<lb break="no"/>berta as it is possible to make. The boun<lb break="no"/>daries of Eastern and Western Assiniboia 
     <lb/>
     remain as before. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Is there any pro<lb break="no"/>vision for another Senator ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
   <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. That is provided for in a Bill 
     <lb/>
     that is being introduced in the Senate by the 
     <lb/>
     Premier. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. The deputy returning officer 
     <lb/>
     on polling day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. Provision ought to be 
     <lb/>
     made for the deputy returning officer having 
     <lb/>
     these forms ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. That system might cause 
     <lb/>
     delay on polling day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. I do not think there will be 
     <lb/>
     any trouble about that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>