<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1891-05-13" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1891-05-13">13 May 1891</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, First Session</title>.
<date when="1891"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="174" to="176"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-05-13_Page_00173.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-05-13_Page_00175.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-10">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-10">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-05-13_Page_00173"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-05-13_Page_00173.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-05-13_Page_00175"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-05-13_Page_00175.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="173" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-05-13_Page_00173.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">173</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 13, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">174</fw>

<head rendition="simple:centre">WEDNESDAY, 13th May, 1891.</head>

<p><emph>PRAYERS.</emph></p> 
</div>
    <div type="debate">
<head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES ACT AMEND<lb break="no"/>MENT.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName> moved for leave to introduce <lb/>
Bill (No. 33) to amend the North-West Territories <lb/>
Act. He said: The Bill needs but little explana<lb break="no"/>tion, at least one portion of it, when one remem<lb break="no"/>bers the long discussion which took place with <lb/>
reference to this subject at the last session of the <lb/>
last Parliament. I would only say now, that the <lb/>
object I have in view is to repeal the clause with <lb/>
reference to the dual language in the North-West <lb/>
Territories, and I do so because I am convinced <lb/>
that the direction in the North-West Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories Act that there shall be two official lan<lb break="no"/>guages in the country is calculated to perpetuate <lb/>
race distinctions which it ought to be, and which <lb/>
I hope it is, the object of this House to do away <lb/>
with. I believe I was able to show that, however <lb/>

<pb n="175" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-05-13_Page_00175.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">175</fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">176</fw> 

some hon. gentlemen thought the measure was <lb/>
a harsh one, it was at all events in the right <lb/>
direction so far was these North-West Territories <lb/>
are concerned. It is, of course, well to remember <lb/>
that this Bill merely deals with the North-West <lb/>
Territories and that the right to the dual language <lb/>
is one based upon the British North America Act, <lb/>
and is to be found in that enactment alone. It is <lb/>
not a right conferred upon our French Canadian <lb/>
subjects at the time of the cession of the old Pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Quebec to the British Crown, and is <lb/>
not to be found earlier than the date of the <lb/>
British North America Act, and in that it is <lb/>
limited to the proceedings of this House, the <lb/>
proceedings of the Senate, and the proceed<lb break="no"/>ings of the Assembly of the Province of <lb/>
Quebec. No one who has given any attention to <lb/>
this subject can be otherwise than convinced that <lb/>
the perpetuation of these race distinctions is not <lb/>
in the public interest, and that nothing is more <lb/>
calculated to prevent the growth of the common <lb/>
nationality of the people of the Dominion than the <lb/>
encouragement of the additional language in the <lb/>
French tongue. I do not desire to interfere with <lb/>
the right which everyone has to speak in any <lb/>
language which seems right to him, but I desire to <lb/>
prevent anything which will foster race distinctions <lb/>
in our North-West without warrant, and, as I <lb/>
believe, without public object or public benefit. <lb/>
This Bill, however, goes further than that of last <lb/>
Session, in that it purports to deal with the school <lb/>
question. According to the genius of our con<lb break="no"/>stitution, as destined in the British North America <lb/>
Act, the subject of education is one belonging <lb/>
exclusively to the Provinces, is one of local concern <lb/>
to be dealt with by the Provinces. It is truth that, <lb/>
owing to difficulties which existed in the old <lb/>
Province of Canada, there are certain limitations <lb/>
and restrictions in regard to school matters <lb/>
imposed upon the Provinces of Ontatio and <lb/>
Quebec, but these restrictions end there, and <lb/>
I know no good reason why the people in <lb/>
the North-West Territories should be limited <lb/>
or restricted in the matter of education. As <lb/>
the law now stands, separate schools are made <lb/>
imperative. Wherever there are two religious <lb/>
communities, there is the right to have separate <lb/>
schools. I propose not to interfere with that, but <lb/>
simply to give to the people of the North-West the <lb/>
right to deal with the question of education as to <lb/>
them seems fit. My Bill is, perhaps, not so objec<lb break="no"/>tionable in another respect as the one of last year, <lb/>
because I omit the preamble, which to some of my <lb/>
friends, was a stumbling block. I have found that <lb/>
hon. gentlemen who were quite willing to adopt <lb/>
the enacting part of the Bill, hesitated somewhat <lb/>
at the wide terms of the preamble. That preamble, <lb/>
of course, was unnecessary for the purposes of the <lb/>
enacting cleanse, and as I have no desire to increase <lb/>
the difficulties, already sufficiently great, that I <lb/>
have before me in order to repead this particular <lb/>
clause, I have left out the preamble in the short <lb/>
Bill. <lb/></p> 

<p>Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first time. <lb/></p> 
<cb/>
<p>[...]Lawrence, in the County of Soulanges, Province <lb/>
of Quebec: and if so, at what date has said Order <lb/>
been passed? Has a survey been made? How <lb/>
much has been already paid for survey and other <lb/>
expenses connected therewith: the probable esti<lb break="no"/>mated cost of said canal: and whether it is the <lb/>
intention of the Government to proceed at an <lb/>
early date with its construction? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LANG1">Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN</persName>. An order in <lb/>
Council was passed on the 7th February, 1891. A <lb/>
survey has been made, and there has been paid for <lb/>
the survey and other expenses connected with <lb/>
it. $28,151. The probable cost of the canal is <lb/>
$4,800,000. It is the intention of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to proceed at an early date with its con<lb break="no"/>truction. <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>