<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1889-02-28"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1889-02-28">28 February 1889</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1889"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="105" to="105"/>
               <biblScope unit="page" from="371" to="383"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00105.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00371.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00372.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00373.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00374.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00375.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00376.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00377.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00378.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00379.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00380.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00381.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00382.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00383.html"/> 
               </item>
          
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-18">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-18">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00105">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00105.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00371">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00371.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00372">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00372.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00373">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00373.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00374">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00374.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00375">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00375.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00376">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00376.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00377">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00377.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00378">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00378.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00379">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00379.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00380">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00380.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00381">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00381.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00382">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00382.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00383">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00383.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="105" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00105.jpg"/>
            
            
            <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">105</fw>
            
            
          
     <head rendition="simple:centre">THE NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES ACT.</head> 
     
         
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName> asked, Whether it is the intention of the 
     <lb/>
     Government to bring in a Bill amending the North-West 
     <lb/>
     Territories Act, so as to secure to the Territories Govern<lb break="no"/>ment powers as full as those of the Provinces, with the 
     <lb/>
     exception of the power of borrowing money? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. It is not the intention of 
     <lb/>
     the Government to bring in such a Bill this Session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="371" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00371.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">371</fw>
          
         </div>
          <div type="debate">
          
     <head rendition="simple:centre">LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY OF THE NORTH-WEST 
     <lb/>
     TERRITORIES.</head> 
    
          
   
            <p>
     House resumed consideration of the proposed motion of 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. Davin</persName> for an Address to His Excellency the Governor 
     <lb/>
     General, praying for all memorials addressed to the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment by the Legislative Assembly of the North-West 
     <lb/>
     Territories which sat recently at Regina. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. I wish to say a few words on this 
     <lb/>
     motion of my hon. friend from West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin), 
     <lb/>
     and I propose to review very briefly the leading points in 
     <lb/>
     the policy of the Government with reference to the admin<lb break="no"/>istration of North-West affairs in connection with the sale 
     <lb/>
     and management of public lands. It is a matter of the ut<lb break="no"/>most importance to this country that that vast stretch of 
     <lb/>
     wilderness should be settled, and I presume, Sir, that all 
     <lb/>
     parties of Canadians are ready to unite in recommending 
     <lb/>
     and approving any policy calculated to produce that desir<lb break="no"/>able result. I must further say that I consider the policy 
     <lb/>
     of the Government from the time its first regulation was 
     <lb/>
     issued in July, 1879, down to the present moment, as hav<lb break="no"/>ing been a policy not calculated to secure the development 
     <lb/>
     of that great country. It has been a policy not conceived 
     <lb/>
     and not carried out in the interests of the settlers who live 
     <lb/>
     in that country or who may be induced to go there. 
     <lb/>
     The Reform party of this Dominion—the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion in this House—challenged this policy of the 
     <lb/>
     Government as long ago as April, 1880, and for 
     <lb/>
     nine years we have continued to protest against the 
     <lb/>
     course that the Government have chosen to pursue with 
     <lb/>
     regard to the administration of our great public domain in 
     <lb/>
     the North-West. The regulation issued on the 9th July, 
     <lb/>
     1879, provided for the setting apart of five belts upon each 
     <lb/>
     side of the assumed line of the railway. The first belt was 
     <lb/>
     to be five miles wide, the second belt was to be fifteen miles 
     <lb/>
     wide, the third belt twenty miles wide, the fourth belt twenty 
     <lb/>
     miles wide, and the fifth belt fifty miles wide. Lands in 
     <lb/>
     the first belt were to be held at $6 per acre, in the second 
     <lb/>
     belt at $5, in the third belt at $3.50, in the fourth belt at 
     <lb/>
     $2, and in the fifth belt at $1 per acre. The lands not set 
     <lb/>
     apart for homestead and pre-emption were to be sold upon 
     <lb/>
     credit, requiring the payment of one-tenth down and the 
     <lb/>
     balance in nine equal annual instalments, bearing interest 
     <lb/>
     at 6 per cent. It was then held by the Opposition that the 
     <lb/>
     opening for sale upon credit of a vast amount of land 
     <lb/>
     at $1 per acre, requiring the payment of only 10 cents 
     <lb/>
     per acre upon the land, the granting of easy terms 
     <lb/>
     on the balance, and the sale of this land in un<lb break="no"/>limited quantities, was a policy calculated to foster 
     <lb/>
     and produce speculations in this land. These regulations 
     <lb/>
     were modified on the 14th October, 1879. The lands under 
     <lb/>
     the modified regulations in belt "A" were held at $5 per 
     <lb/>
     acre, in belt "B" at $4, in belt "C" at $3, in belt "D" at 
     <lb/>
     $2, and in belt "E"  at $1 per acre, with the same policy 
     <lb/>
     continued as to selling upon credit, and with the same 
     <lb/>
     objectionable feature of the policy in encouraging specula<lb break="no"/>tion in the public lands of the North-West. There was 
     <lb/>
     one modification of those regulations in May, 1881, and on 
     <lb/>
     the 1st January, 1882, regulations were issued which, I 
     <lb/>
     believe, are still in force. These regulations provided two 
     <lb/>
     schemes for colonisation, which were in point of fact, two 
     <lb/>
     schemes calculated to still further promote the operations 
     <lb/>
     of speculators in these public lands. Colonisation "plan No. 
     <lb/>
     1" provided that lands in alternate sections could be pur<lb break="no"/>chased by colonisation companies at $2 per acre, the price 
     <lb/>
     at which they were held to settlers, with a provision that 
     <lb/>
     upon compliance with some requirements as to settlement, a 
     <lb/>
     rebate of one-half should be made; the effect of this being 
     <lb/>
     to give the colonisation companies—organisations of 
     <lb/>
     capitalists—an opportunity to buy lands at half-price, 
     <lb/>
     and this led to a good deal of speculation. Plan 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="372" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00372.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="num">372</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 28,</fw> 
    
           
   
          
     "No. 2" provided for the sale of the entire amount 
     <lb/>
     of land in townships at $2 per acre for cash, with the 
     <lb/>
     same provision as to rebate of one-half of the amount 
     <lb/>
     paid, upon compliance with certain conditions. Here was 
     <lb/>
     a policy which could not be said to have been conceived or 
     <lb/>
     executed in the interests of the settlers; here was a policy 
     <lb/>
     in both those instances, to sell the public lands in unlimited 
     <lb/>
     quantities at a dollar per acre on credit, and a policy which 
     <lb/>
     encouraged the organisation of those colonisation companies 
     <lb/>
     that were practically calculated to promote speculation in 
     <lb/>
     the lands of the North-West, and that were not conceived in 
     <lb/>
     the interests of the settlers. The Opposition challenged 
     <lb/>
     this policy as early as 1880. On the 6th April, 1880, the 
     <lb/>
     following resolution was moved with regard to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment's land policy: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "Mr. Charlton moved that the House do now go into Committee of 
     <lb/>
     the Whole to consider the following resolutions :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "1. Resolved, That in the Opinion of this House, the proper policy 
     <lb/>
     with reference to the disposition of the public lands of Canada should be, 
     <lb/>
     as far as practicable, to sell such lands to actual settlers only, on reason<lb break="no"/>able conditions of settlement, and in lots or quantities limited to the 
     <lb/>
     area which can be reasonably occupied by a settler and that the sale 
     <lb/>
     of public lands to speculators, free from conditions of settlement, is im<lb break="no"/>politic and calculated to injuriously affect the settlement of the country, 
     <lb/>
    by keeping large quantities of land locked up for years, and by obliging 
     <lb/>the settlers thereon ultimately to pay a price much larger than that 
     <lb/>which is paid into the public Treasury for the same." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     " 2. Resolved, That, as under the existing regulations respecting the 
     <lb/>
     disposal of public lands, for the purposes of the Canadian Pacific Rail<lb break="no"/>way, large quantities of fertile lands are being offered for sale, and sold 
     <lb/>
     to speculators at one dollar per acre, for one-tenth cash down, and the 
     <lb/>
     balance in nine equal annual instalments, with interest at 6 per cent. 
     <lb/>
    per annum - terms which enable the speculator to obtain control of 
     <lb/>lands for a cash outlay of ten cents per acre; thereby, not only in effect, 
     <lb/>loaning to the speculator on the part of the Government, nine-tenths 
     <lb/>of the capital required for speculative investments, but giving rise, as 
     <lb/>experience shows, to great expense in the keeping of accounts, and to 
     <lb/>indefinite delays in the realisation of the stipulated price; that, so long 
     <lb/>as the system of selling public lands to speculators without conditions 
     <lb/>of settlement or restrictions as to quantity is continued, the price at 
     <lb/>which such lands are sold should be paid in full in cash, at the time of 
     <lb/>sale. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</quote>

    
   
            <p>
     It was moved in amendment by Mr. White, of Cardwell: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That all the words after 'That' he left out, and the following inserted 
     <lb/>
     instead thereof: 'the policy of the Government for the disposal of the 
     <lb/>
     public lands in Manito a and the North-West, is well calculated to pro<lb break="no"/>mote the rapid settlement of that region, and to raise the moneys re<lb break="no"/>quired for the construction of the Canadian Pacific Railway, without 
     <lb/>
     further burthening the people, and that it deserves the support and ap<lb break="no"/>proval of this House." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     Well, Sir, that policy received the approval of the House 
     <lb/>
     by a vote of 120 to 40, but the allegation of the amendment, 
     <lb/>
     that the policy was one calculated to promote the rapid 
     <lb/>
     settlement of the country and to raise the moneys necessary 
     <lb/>
     to pay for the construction of the Canadian Pacific Rail<lb break="no"/>way, has been belied by subsequent events. So far from 
     <lb/>
     its promoting the rapid settlement of that country, there 
     <lb/>
     are to-day, according to the estimate made by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, but 132,000 settlers in Manitoba and but l00,000, in<lb break="no"/>cluding lndians, or about 50,000 whites, in the North-West 
     <lb/>
     Territories—a pepulation of from 170,000 to 180,000 set<lb break="no"/>tlers who have gone into the whole of that vast region dur<lb break="no"/>ing the nine years that have elapsed since the question was 
     <lb/>
     discussed in this House; and so far from realising the $58,<lb break="no"/>000,000, or any portion of it, that we were told was to be 
     <lb/>
     realised by 1891 from the sale of lands, we have realised 
     <lb/>
     nothing. The sale of lands has not paid the expenses of 
     <lb/>
     management; and in place of having any considerable sum to 
     <lb/>
     apply to the liquidation of the expenses incurred by the <choice><sic>Gov<lb break="no"/>rnmentin</sic><corr>Government</corr></choice> the construction of the railway, we are actually out 
     <lb/>
     $70,000,000 in hard cash, the sum given to the railway in the 
     <lb/>
     form of bonuses, the cost of the portion which was constructed 
     <lb/>
     and handed over to the company, and the $10,000,000 given 
     <lb/>
     to the company in exchange for a portion of its land grant. 
     <lb/>
     Now, it is evident that the predictions made by the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment with reference to the results that would follow the 
     <lb/>
     inauguration of this policy in 1879 have not been fulfilled; 
     <lb/>
     that, in point of fact, the whole thing has proved in a great 
     <lb/>
     
            
            <cb/>
            
     measure a flat failure; that we have not induced settlement 
     <lb/>
     to the North-West; that the country has not prospered; 
     <lb/>
     that something has been the matter; and I shall show, a 
     <lb/>
     little further on, that in addition to its policy towards the 
     <lb/>
     settlers, the Government has erred in other matters. The 
     <lb/>
     Opposition steadily adhered to the policy it laid down in 
     <lb/>
     1879. On the 16th of March, 1881, when the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     Lands Act was under consideration in this House, amend<lb break="no"/>ments to that Act were moved in the following directions. 
     <lb/>
     The first was by <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. Mills</persName>, who moved: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That the Bill be recommitted, with instructions to amend the fourth 
     <lb/>
     clause by providing a limitation of the area of land which may be sold 
     <lb/>
     by the Government to one person." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>
     Which, of course, was lost. It was moved by <persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. Charlton</persName>: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That the Bill be recommitted, with instructions to amend the fourth 
     <lb/>
     clause by enacting that except or otherwise provided by resolution of 
     <lb/>
     this House, all lands shall be disposed of subject to conditions of actual 
     <lb/>
     settlement." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     Which, of course, was lost. It was moved by <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Mr. Holton</persName>: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That the Bill be recommitted, with instructions to amend the fourth 
     <lb/>
     clause by providing that the unappropriated even-numbered sections in 
     <lb/>
     each township shall be disposed of only upon conditions of actual settle<lb break="no"/>ment." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     Which was lost. <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> then moved: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That the Bill be recommitted, with instructions to amend the fourth 
     <lb/>
     clause by providing that the price of Dominion lands, sold without con<lb break="no"/>ditions of settlement, shall be payable in cash at the time of sale." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     Which was lost. All these amendments were in the direc<lb break="no"/>tion of the public interest. There was not one of them that 
     <lb/>
     did not contain a principle that ought to have been em<lb break="no"/>bodied in the Bill, without the necessity of any amendment 
     <lb/>
     being offered by the Opposition at all, and the passage of 
     <lb/>
     these amendments in the negative was in every case detri<lb break="no"/>mental to the interest of the country. Then, following 
     <lb/>
     these challenges of the Government's land policy, we have 
     <lb/>
     other votes on record with regard to the same matter. On 
     <lb/>
     the 27th of March, 1882, the leader of the Opposition in the 
     <lb/>
     House challenged the policy of the Government with refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the disposition of coal lands and pasture lands, by 
     <lb/>
     the following motion :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That the future of the vast Territories of the North-West is largely 
     <lb/>
     dependent on the supply of fuel at a moderate rate; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That the present information as to the country and the coal areas is 
     <lb/>
     not sufficient to warrant Parliament in creating long-enduring interests 
     <lb/>
     in large quantities of coal areas; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That the regulations as to coal lands laid on the Table make no 
     <lb/>
     provision for the application, as a general rule, of the just principle of 
     <lb/>
     public competition to the acquisition of these valuable lands, and thus 
     <lb/>
    leave open the door to disadvantageous cessions of the public domain 
     <lb/>for the benefit of individuals; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     "That the said regulations make no adequate provisions to check the 
     <lb/>
     consolidation of large blocks of the coal lands in a few hands and the 
     <lb/>
     consequent restriction of competition and enhancement of the price of 
     <lb/>
    coal; 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     "That the said regulations make no adequate provision to secure any 
     <lb/>
     working of the coal mines by the lessee; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That the said regulations provide, by arrangement, for 21-year 
     <lb/>
     leases, renewable, for the creation of interests of longer duration than 
     <lb/>
     prudence at this time would, as a general rule, lay down; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That they make no proper provision for the settlement of the terms 
     <lb/>
     of renewal; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That the said regulations do not become operative, if disapproved 
     <lb/>
     of by this House; and the House is responsible for their coming into 
     <lb/>
     operation; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That this House disapproves of said regulations." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     Which was lost on a division. Then <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> moved: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That in the opinion of this House the existing system of granting 
     <lb/>
     timber limits is liable to result in gross abuse, and in the cession of 
     <lb/>
     valuable interests in the public domain for inadequate considerations to 
     <lb/>
     favoured individuals;       
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That it is expedient to apply the just principle of public competi<lb break="no"/>tion to the granting of timber limits." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     That liability to abuse was fully realised in the history 
     <lb/>
     of the granting of timber limits since the year 1882. We 
     <lb/>
     have still further an amendment moved to Bill No. 145, 
     <lb/>
     relating to public lands of the Dominion. In 1883, on the 
     <lb/>
     2nd of May, <persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. Charlton</persName> then moved: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="373" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00373.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">373</fw>
            
             <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
             <p>
     "That the said Bill be referred back to the Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
     in order to amend the same by striking out all after the words 
     <lb/>
     'Governor in Council' in line five, sub-section one, section twenty-<lb break="yes"/>four, and substituting the following: 'provided that all sales of agricul<lb break="no"/>tural lands shall, unless  under exceptional circumstances, applicable to 
     <lb/>
     particular lots, be made on condition of actual settlement by the pur<lb break="no"/>chaser, and in quantities limited to the number of acres which can be 
     <lb/>
     reasonably occupied by one settler.'" 
     <lb/>
            </p>
             </quote>
            <p>
     Now, the line of the Opposition as developed was, first, and 
     <lb/>
     that was the primary point in the principle they adopted, 
     <lb/>
     that the sale of lands in the North-West should be made to 
     <lb/>
     actual settlers only, subject to conditions of settlement. 
     <lb/>
     That was a salutary and just provision which would have 
     <lb/>
     effectually prevented the Operations of speculative companies 
     <lb/>
     in that country, and in failing to adopt it the Government 
     <lb/>
     are largely responsible for the evil consequences that have 
     <lb/>
     followed in the settlement of the country and the dissatis<lb break="no"/>faction that has existed there. Then, the Opposition took 
     <lb/>
     ground distinctly in favor of the competitive principle with 
     <lb/>
     regard to the placing of coal lands, pasture leases and tim<lb break="no"/>ber limits. The Opposition have always held that these 
     <lb/>
     being the property of the public, it was the duty of the 
     <lb/>
     Government to secure as large a return from them as pos<lb break="no"/>sible. We held that the granting of pasture leases at one 
     <lb/>
     cent an acre, without inviting competition, that the grant<lb break="no"/>ing of coal lands and of timber limits upon the terms on 
     <lb/>
     which the Government did grant them, without inviting 
     <lb/>
     competition, was detrimental to the interests of the people, 
     <lb/>
     and not comment with the principles of just and honest 
     <lb/>
     government. What do we find with reference to timber 
     <lb/>
     licenses? We find that at the time the last return was 
     <lb/>
     made, over 25,000 square miles of timber limits had been 
     <lb/>
     granted by Order in Council, at a uniform rate, without re<lb break="no"/>ference to the value of the limits; and hon. gentlemen know 
     <lb/>
     that in many cases these limits, which were granted for $5 
     <lb/>
     per square mile, without inviting competition, were worth 
     <lb/>
     vastly more in many cases than the small amount received 
     <lb/>
     by the Government. It has been ascertained since that an 
     <lb/>
     hon. member of this House was interested in a limit for 
     <lb/>
     which $50,000 was received by those interested, but which 
     <lb/>
     had been obtained from the Government for the sum of $250. 
     <lb/>
     The whole system was rotten, and the Government failed 
     <lb/>
     to secure for the country the large revenue that would have 
     <lb/>
     been secured from the sale of timber lands, coal leases, or 
     <lb/>
     the leasing of pasture ranches. The only restriction im<lb break="no"/>posed with regard to pasture ranches was, that no friend of 
     <lb/>
     the Government could have a lease of more than 50,000 
     <lb/>
     acres. The leases should have been put up at auction, and 
     <lb/>
     the Government should have taken pains to secure for the 
     <lb/>
     property the price it was worth, and that public competi<lb break="no"/>tion alone could determine. The system adapted of selling 
     <lb/>
     timber licenses at a uniform rate of $5 per square mile when, 
     <lb/>
     perhaps, in the one case they might be worth a hundred 
     <lb/>
     times as much as in another, and of leasing pasture lands at 
     <lb/>
     one cent per acre, and of granting coal leases on the terms 
     <lb/>
     on which the Government granted them, has worked in the 
     <lb/>
     interests of the friends of the Government, but not in the 
     <lb/>
     interests of the people. We have had attempts made to 
     <lb/>
     justify the conduct of the Government; we have had feeble 
     <lb/>
     attempts made to show that the development of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West should be considered on the whole as satisfactory. I 
     <lb/>
               deny <hi rendition="simple:italic">in toto</hi> that that is the case. I maintain, on the con<lb break="no"/>trary, that the policy of the Government has been uni<lb break="no"/>formly in the interest of the speculator and the moneyed 
     <lb/>
     man, and uniformly against the interest of the settler 
     <lb/>
     and the poor man. By the system of credit sales of unlim<lb break="no"/>ited areas at one dollar an acre, requiring but the 
     <lb/>
     payment of ten cents per acre down, the policy of the 
     <lb/>
    Government with regard to colonisation companies has 
     <lb/>enabled the latter to obtain large areas of land at but 
     <lb/>half the price which the settlers must pay, and by their 
     <lb/>system of leasing of pasture lands, timber lands and coal 
     <lb/>lands; by all these things they have militated against the 
     <lb/>
           

    
            <cb/>
          
     interest of the North-West. Then the Government have 
     <lb/>
     steadily persisted in charging prices to the population of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West much higher than those charged by the United 
     <lb/>
     States. They have steadily persisted in homestead regula<lb break="no"/>tions less liberal and less productive of settlement than those 
     <lb/>
     of the United States. They have seemed to be unaware of 
     <lb/>
     the fact that our public lands, as compared with these of the 
     <lb/>
     United States, are remote; they seem to be unaware of the 
     <lb/>
     fact that a settler going to the lands of Manitoba or the 
     <lb/>
     North-West would necessarily pass almost through, or very 
     <lb/>
     nearly by, a territory offering vast acres of public land at 
     <lb/>
     great inducements to settlers, and that, other things being 
     <lb/>
     equal, settlers would be more liable to take up land in 
     <lb/>
     Dakota than in our North-West. Yet, in face of the fact 
     <lb/>
     that in the Territory of Dakota public lands within the 
     <lb/>
     limits of the railway grants are sold at $2.50, and outside 
     <lb/>
     of the railway grants at $1.25 per acre, and that this 
     <lb/>
     land is more eligibly situated, being nearer the railways, 
     <lb/>
     nearer markets, where agricultural implements and other 
     <lb/>
     goods can be more readily and cheaply obtained, and offer<lb break="no"/>ing attractions to the settler infinitely greater than those 
     <lb/>
     offered in our North-West,—as if those inducements were 
     <lb/>
     not enough, the Government, in order to shut out immi<lb break="no"/>gration more effectually, must place our lands at a figure 
     <lb/>
     higher than lands can be obtained in the United States, and 
     <lb/>
     their policy in this respect has been very effective, as shown 
     <lb/>
     by the immigration returns. Now, we have here a memorial 
     <lb/>
     from the North-West Assembly, and these men upon the 
     <lb/>
     spot, knowing the wants of the country, petition the 
     <lb/>
     Government in exactly the line the Opposition has advo<lb break="no"/>cated for nine years past. They ask the Government to 
     <lb/>
     make the price of pre-emptions within twenty miles of the 
     <lb/>
     railways at $2 per acre, and outside of that at $1 per 
     <lb/>
     acre. If the Government were to do that they would 
     <lb/>
     then be offering inducements to settlers somewhat better 
     <lb/>
     than those offered by the United States Government, and 
     <lb/>
     would have some show of securing that settlement we desire 
     <lb/>
     and which it is necessary we should have, and which 
     <lb/>
     we never can have with higher prices on our side 
     <lb/>
     besides the other disadvantages to settlers. What 
     <lb/>
     we want in the North-West is not that friends of the 
     <lb/>
     Government may make money out of timber limits, 
     <lb/>
     not that friends of the Government may acquire cattle 
     <lb/>
     ranches and coal mine licenses and timber licenses 
     <lb/>
     at low rates, but what we want is the entry of settlers who 
     <lb/>
     will bring that country under cultivation; and to order to 
     <lb/>
     secure settlers we have to consider their interests. That is 
     <lb/>
     what we have not yet done. The policy of the Government 
     <lb/>
     has been, practically, to leave out of view the interests of the 
     <lb/>
     settler in the North-West. Now I hold, without detaining 
     <lb/>
     the House much longer, that the true policy of this Govern<lb break="no"/>ment is to make the inducements for settlement in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West greater than those offered by the United States. Our 
     <lb/>
     policy is to offer our lands cheaper than the American Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment offer theirs. Our policy is to give homestead regu<lb break="no"/>lations at least as attractive as those in the United States. 
     <lb/>
     In the United States, the homestead settler can take up 
     <lb/>
     public lands wherever he can find them. The chequer-board 
     <lb/>
     system is not adopted there, that system which has created 
     <lb/>
     the isolation of one settler from another, and has made it 
     <lb/>
     difficult for the settlers to have schools, and roads, and other 
     <lb/>
     advantages. But the homestead settlers in the United 
     <lb/>
     States can take lands in bodies and in blocks wherever they 
     <lb/>
     can find them. The United States will grant lands to home<lb break="no"/>stead settlers without restriction as to location, their policy 
     <lb/>
     being to get settlers to take up the lands and have the 
     <lb/>
     wilderness converted into a cultivated country. Let our 
     <lb/>
     Government adopt that policy in our North-West. If a 
     <lb/>
     homesteader wants a piece of land, let him take it 
     <lb/>
     where ever it can be found belonging to the Government. 
     <lb/>
     If he wants to buy land, sell him that land at a reasonable 
     <lb/>
     price, $2 an acre within railway limits, and $1 an acre out<lb break="no"/>
           
            <pb n="374" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00374.jpg"/>
           
           <fw type="num">374</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 28,</fw> 
     
           
   
          
     side. If the Government would adopt that policy, we 
     <lb/>
     would see a larger movement of settlers to the North-West 
     <lb/>
     than we have in the last nine years. We would not have 
     <lb/>
     in the next nine years the beggarly showing which we have 
     <lb/>
     for the last nine years, of an influx of 132,000 peeple to 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba and 40,000 to the North-West. I believe that we 
     <lb/>
     have not, by 25 per cent., as many native-born Canadians in 
     <lb/>
     the North-West as there are in the Territory of Dakota in 
     <lb/>
     the United States. The reason is that the settler in Dakota 
     <lb/>
     has had greater inducements held out to him, while the 
     <lb/>
     policy of this Government has been such as to repel him 
     <lb/>
     from our North-West. It is time that a change should be 
     <lb/>
     made, and I hope that the hon. gentleman who now oc<lb break="no"/>cupies the position of head of the great Department of the 
     <lb/>
     Interior, who has lived in the North-West and must neces<lb break="no"/>sarily know the wants of that country and the feelings of 
     <lb/>
     the settlers in that country, will administer the affairs of 
     <lb/>
     that department in a different spirit, in a spirit favorable 
     <lb/>
     to the settlers, and that, under his administration, we may 
     <lb/>
     secure for that great country the influx of a great body of 
     <lb/>
     settlers, and the development of its resources. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD20">Mr. MACDOWALL</persName>. As this is a question which interests 
     <lb/>
     particularly those members who come from the North-West, 
     <lb/>
     I will ask permission to occupy a few minutes of the time 
     <lb/>
     of the House in regard to it. The range which has been 
     <lb/>
     opened before us is extremely wide, as the memorials of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West Assembly embrace a great many subjects, but 
     <lb/>
     these are all of great interest to the settlers in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West. The question of the Dominion lands, to which the 
     <lb/>
     member for North Norfolk (Mr. Charlton) has referred, is 
     <lb/>
     one of great importance, because, of course, the settlers 
     <lb/>
     come in there with the intention of settling on the land, and 
     <lb/>
     making their living upon it as farmers. I do not think, 
     <lb/>
     however, that we can find very great fault with the land 
     <lb/>
     laws as they stand, or, at any rate, with the new regulations 
     <lb/>
     which I understand the Minister of the Interior is likely to 
     <lb/>
     introduce, in order that things be made so much easier and 
     <lb/>
     better for the settler so that it would be difficult to improve 
     <lb/>
     upon them. Of course, it is a matter of very great import<lb break="no"/>ance to have the land for the settlers as cheap as possible, 
     <lb/>
     but at the same time, we have to bear in mind that 
     <lb/>
     a great deal of money is being spent on the develop 
     <lb/>
     ment of the North-West, and that country must bear 
     <lb/>
     to some extent, its share of the cost. The price of land at 
     <lb/>
     $2 and $3.50 an acre is not too high. If land is worth 20 
     <lb/>
     cents an acre, it is certainly worth $2, and I do not think 
     <lb/>
     any settler who has occupied what he considers a good 
     <lb/>
     location, when he has got his patent, would sacrifice it for 
     <lb/>
     such a small sum as $2 an acre. In addition to this, the 
     <lb/>
     only thing the members from the North-West would urge 
     <lb/>
     upon the Government is this. As a rule, the people who come 
     <lb/>
     in there are not very rich. They have hard times before 
     <lb/>
     them for the first few years, and, if they are not able to pay 
     <lb/>
     for their land within the stipulated three years, they should 
     <lb/>
     be given a certain time within which to pay, and the in<lb break="no"/>terest should not be too high. For my part, I should like 
     <lb/>
     to see the interest thrown off altogether, but this cannot be 
     <lb/>
     done, because the sale of land, whether it is by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, or by individuals, is a business transaction, and must 
     <lb/>
     be carried on in a business manner. While on this land 
     <lb/>
     question, I must refer to the remarks made by the mover of 
     <lb/>
     the resolution (Mr. Davin), in regard to second home<lb break="no"/>steading. He referred to a discussion which took place in 
     <lb/>
     this House on that subject in 1887, and he urged that the 
     <lb/>
     granting of second homesteads should be extended for a 
     <lb/>
     longer period to settlers now in the North-West. 
     <lb/>
     I should be sorry to see this done. In 1887, when this 
     <lb/>
     matter was before the House, I took the same stand, and, 
     <lb/>
     when I returned to the district of Saskatchewan, I found 
     <lb/>
     that my conduct was endorsed by the people there. What 
     <lb/>
     we ought to consider is what is the proper spirit of the 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     Homestead Act. I understand it to be to encourage people 
     <lb/>
     to settle upon the lands who will become actual settlers 
     <lb/>
     and who mean to make their homes in the country, and to 
     <lb/>
     reside there with their families, but, if you give a homestead 
     <lb/>
     to one man and allow him to throw it up and to take another 
     <lb/>
     homestead in another place, you are creating a class of specu<lb break="no"/>lators. When this was before the House, I compared two 
     <lb/>
     of the prominent cities of the North-West, Winnipeg on the 
     <lb/>
     one hand and Prince Albert on the other—and I compared 
     <lb/>
     the country which surrounded those cities. The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Marquette (Mr. Watson) smiles at the idea of com<lb break="no"/>paring Winnipeg with Prince Albert, but I think that I 
     <lb/>
     compared the two cities which were most fit for comparison. 
     <lb/>
     If you go out from Winnipeg for many miles around, you 
     <lb/>
     will find a large proportion of the country unsettled. These 
     <lb/>
     lands were scriped by speculators, and the land remains un<lb break="no"/>settled, but, in the country surrounding Prince Albert, you 
     <lb/>
     will find that it is occupied by men who are 
     <lb/>
     making improvements on their farms, and I do 
     <lb/>
     not think there is any comparison at all between 
     <lb/>
     the country surrounding these two cities. I know 
     <lb/>
     that the people of Winnipeg have endeavored, to the best 
     <lb/>
     of their ability, to get the lands immediately surrounding 
     <lb/>
     the city into the market. Winnipeg has to depend now, to 
     <lb/>
     a great extent, on its wholesale business. The retail busi<lb break="no"/>ness is small, because there are so few people surrounding 
     <lb/>
     the city, and it is principally confined to those who live in 
     <lb/>
     the town. I believe that, if you wish to have prosperous 
     <lb/>
     towns, you must have the country settled close up to the 
     <lb/>
     town, so as to give a retail business first and a wholesale 
     <lb/>
     business afterwards. One of the memorials from the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Council, to which I desire to call special attention, is 
     <lb/>
     a memorial to the Dominion Government praying them to 
     <lb/>
     make such arrangements as to ensure the immediate con<lb break="no"/>struction of a railway to the settlements on the North Sas<lb break="no"/>katchewan. I am in hearty sympathy and accord with that 
     <lb/>
     memorial. In the preamble they first state that the build<lb break="no"/>ing of the Canadian Pacific Railway had cut off the markets 
     <lb/>
     of those settlements, and that, in consequence of that, the 
     <lb/>
     people were unable to find means of getting rid of the pro<lb break="no"/>duce which they raised. The consequence was that they 
     <lb/>
     were being brought into a most undesirable state of poverty. 
     <lb/>
     I do not want to enter into great details at this time on that 
     <lb/>
     subject, because I am happy to state that arrangements are 
     <lb/>
     being carried on by a certain railway company pointing 
     <lb/>
     towards the construction of the road to Prince Albert and 
     <lb/>
     Battleford, which I hope will be concluded next month, and 
     <lb/>
     which will give the needed railway communication. If 
     <lb/>
     these arrangements are not concluded at that time, I shall 
     <lb/>
     have a motion to lay before the House, and shall then have an 
     <lb/>
     opportunity to go further into details in regard to the subject. 
     <lb/>
     I will simply say now that I cannot urge too strongly on 
     <lb/>
     the Minister of Interior and his colleagues that there is a 
     <lb/>
     great necessity, in fact an immediate necessity, that the 
     <lb/>
     land grants for railways in that country should be located 
     <lb/>
     at once, if any work is to be carried out. It is absolutely 
     <lb/>
     necessary that those who invest their money in these under<lb break="no"/>takings should know exactly what security they have got, 
     <lb/>
     and it is impossible for them to tell what the security is 
     <lb/>
     worth until they know where these lands are, the lands 
     <lb/>
     being security for building the railways. Another question 
     <lb/>
     to which I wish to refer is that of granting scrip to the 
     <lb/>
     half-breeds of the North-West. This question has raised a 
     <lb/>
     great deal of discussion in the House before. The half- <lb break="yes"/>breeds in the North-West have petitioned to the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Assembly, and the North-West Assembly has 
     <lb/>
     petitioned the hon. gentlemen who form the Government of 
     <lb/>
     this country, that scrip should be granted to the children of 
     <lb/>
     all half-breeds who were born before March, 1885. 
     <lb/>
     They consider that they are justly entitled to it, 
     <lb/>
     because an arrangement was not made with the half-<lb break="yes"/>breeds in the North-West until 1885, when scrip was issued 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="375" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00375.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">375</fw>
          
     to them. We know that the half-breeds in Manitoba were<lb/>settled with in 1870, but the half-breeds in the North-West 
     <lb/>
     were not settled with until 1885; and, as my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     from Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) very wisely and very well 
     <lb/>
     pointed out, the half-breeds in the North-West were a dif<lb break="no"/>ferent class, in a way, from the half-breeds in Manitoba, 
     <lb/>
     they were in the same position with regard to the half-<lb break="yes"/>breeds in Manitoba as the Blackfeet Indians would hear to 
     <lb/>
     the Cree Indians; consequently, when a settlement was 
     <lb/>
     made with the half-breeds in Manitoba, it did not 
     <lb/>
     follow that a settlement was made with the half-<lb break="yes"/>breeds in the North-West—in fact, it rather follows 
     <lb/>
     that a settlement was not made with them, as no 
     <lb/>
     steps were taken to settle their claims. I should like, 
     <lb/>
     therefore, to hear the hon. Minister express himself in a 
     <lb/>
     manner that will enable me to say to my half-breed friends 
     <lb/>
     in the North-West that they are likely to get scrip; 
     <lb/>
     because no settlement has been made with them, they had 
     <lb/>
     no word in making the treaty as to surrendering their 
     <lb/>
     rights; they accepted what was given them, but with this 
     <lb/>
     protest, they demanded that this scrip should be issued to 
     <lb/>
     all children who were born at the time of settlement. 
     <lb/>
     The next question I wish to come to is the liquor question. 
     <lb/>
     Ever since representation was granted to the maple of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West in the local assembly, this has been a question 
     <lb/>
     of more or less interest. I was a member of that assembly 
     <lb/>
     some years ago, in the earlier days of representative govern<lb break="no"/>ment in the North-West, and memorials were forward<lb break="no"/>ed to Ottawa every year on this question. I think it is 
     <lb/>
     only natural that this should be the case, when you consider 
     <lb/>
     the relative position of the people in the North West and 
     <lb/>
     the people in the rest of Canada. On this question there 
     <lb/>
     is an arbitrary Act which applies to the people of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, and to them only, affecting their comforts and their 
     <lb/>
     every day life; and this arbitrary Act was passed by a 
     <lb/>
     Parliament in which the people to whom alone it applies 
     <lb/>
     had no voice. Consequently, I maintain that it became an 
     <lb/>
     unconstitutional Act as soon as representation was 
     <lb/>
     given to the North-West in this House. The hon. mem 
     <lb/>
     here who, with me, have represented the North- West in 
     <lb/>
     this House, for the last three Sessions, have always been 
     <lb/>
     directing attention to this matter, and the North-West 
     <lb/>
     Assembly has now placed itself on record with regard to 
     <lb/>
     it. What they demand is that either this question be sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to a popular vote, so that the people themselves may 
     <lb/>
     decide it, or that the North-West Territories be placed in 
     <lb/>
     the same position as the older Provinces in respect to the 
     <lb/>
     license question, and the admission of liquor into the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. I, myself, would go even a little further, and say 
     <lb/>
     that there is a third alternative which, I think, would be 
     <lb/>
     better still, and that is, to refer the liquor question to the 
     <lb/>
     North-West Assembly, and give them power to deal with 
     <lb/>
     it. My reason is that I believe that the people of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West are sufficiently intelligent to know themselves 
     <lb/>
     a great deal better than anyoue else what would be best for 
     <lb/>
     them in this respect. At the same time, if a license system 
     <lb/>
     is established in the North- West, it would be necessary, I 
     <lb/>
     presume, to follow the rule that applies to other Provinces, 
     <lb/>
     and to grant the fees, &amp;c., collected for licenses within the 
     <lb/>
     Territory to the North-West Government; so, I think that, 
     <lb/>
     perhaps the fairest way of settling this question would be 
     <lb/>
     to give the North-West Assembly power to deal with the 
     <lb/>
     liquor question. While I am on this subject I would point 
     <lb/>
     out that there is a great difference between the way in 
     <lb/>
     which the liquor question stands in the older Provinces, and 
     <lb/>
     the way in which it stands in the North-West. In the older 
     <lb/>
    Provinces the people themselves have been allowed to say 
     <lb/>whether any restriction should be imposed; but when this res<lb break="no"/>triction has been imposed under the Canada Temperance Act, 
     <lb/>although liquor is not allowed to be sold at the bars in those 
     <lb/>counties which are under the operation of that Act, still liquor 
     <lb/>can be manufactured in those counties, and exported from 
     <lb/>
           

    
            <cb/>
           
     them. In older Provinces you can manufacture liquor and 
     <lb/>
     you can export it, but in the North-West you are allowed 
     <lb/>
     by a permit from the Lieutenant Governor, to import it, 
     <lb/>
     but you are not allowed to manufacture it, and that is a 
     <lb/>
     very remarkable difference. Now, we who live in the 
     <lb/>
     North-West think that we ought to be allowed to manu<lb break="no"/>facture the liquor that we are now allowed to import. We 
     <lb/>
     think that long ago we might have been allowed to manu<lb break="no"/>facture the beer that was imported into the country, and I 
     <lb/>
     believe that if we had been allowed to manufacture beer 
     <lb/>
     and sell it, it would have been a very admirable thing, and 
     <lb/>
     probably would have prevented, in a great measure, the 
     <lb/>
     agitation that has now arisen throughout the North-West 
     <lb/>
     for an alteration in the liquor laws. Now, I just want to 
     <lb/>
     return to the question of the land board. My hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     from West Assiniboia thought it would be better if the land 
     <lb/>
     board were transferred further west, and located at Regina. 
     <lb/>
     For my part, I think it would be a very admirable thing to 
     <lb/>
     have the land board in a central place in the Territory, 
     <lb/>
     but if we want to make it convenient to the people I am sure 
     <lb/>
     that the present location of the land board in Winnipeg 
     <lb/>
     is a great deal better, because at present Winnipeg is most 
     <lb/>
     accessible to the people in all parts of the Territory. Peo<lb break="no"/>ple coming from the northern districts, such as Touchwood 
     <lb/>
     Hills, Prince Albert, Batoche, and along the line of the 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba and North-Western Railway, when they come 
     <lb/>
     from their homes and reach a railway, would have to 
     <lb/>
     go back to Regina. The usual tendency is to go east to do 
     <lb/>
     their business, but in that case they would have to go west 
     <lb/>
     to Regina, and then resume their journey again, retracing 
     <lb/>
     the distance they had already travelled. The land board 
     <lb/>
     is a great deal more accessible in Winnipeg, because it does 
     <lb/>
     away with this extra travel. I also wish to say a few 
     <lb/>
     words with reference to scrip being granted to the 
     <lb/>
     North-West Mounted Police. During last Session of 
     <lb/>
     Parliament this matter came up on a motion of my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend for West Assiniboia, and it was promised 
     <lb/>
     at that time that this question should be reconsidered. 
     <lb/>
     I urged at that time, very strongly, that this scrip should 
     <lb/>
     be given to the police, because I believed they deserved it. 
     <lb/>
     They are, as everybody knows, a very fine body of men. 
     <lb/>
     They did their duty at the time of the rebellion, but before 
     <lb/>
     the rebellion occurred they did a greater duty than they did 
     <lb/>
     even then, for they did a great work for Canada. It is Well 
     <lb/>
     known that before the Indian Department was organised 
     <lb/>
     throughout the North West, the mounted police were station<lb break="no"/>ed at posts throughout that vast territory, and I believe 
     <lb/>
     the credit, in a great measure, is due to the police for 
     <lb/>
     having handled the Indians so well as to control the country 
     <lb/>
     without shedding a single drop of blood. This is a matter of 
     <lb/>
     very great importance, although notice has not often been 
     <lb/>
     called to it, and therefore it may appear to be a very small 
     <lb/>
     matter. I believe the mounted police, from the very first 
     <lb/>
     day they entered the country up to the present time, have 
     <lb/>
     done their duty thoroughly, and are as much entitled to 
     <lb/>
     scrip for services rendered during the rebellion as were 
     <lb/>
     the provisional corps sent up there from Kingston, Quebec, 
     <lb/>
     Toronto and other places which received scrip. They are 
     <lb/>
     all alike enrolled to serve the interests of the Dominion at 
     <lb/>
     large, and whether they serve in the North-West or in the 
     <lb/>
     older Provinces, still they are doing their duty by their 
     <lb/>
     country, and if rewards are going I think it is only a matter 
     <lb/>
     of justice that all the corps should be rewarded alike. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WATS2">Mr. WATSON</persName>. I do not intend to occupy the time of 
     <lb/>
     the House at any length on this occasion. We have lis<lb break="no"/>tened with interest to the remarks of the member for West 
     <lb/>
     Assiniboia (Mr. Davin), and the other members who have 
     <lb/>
     spoken today. I have simply to say that I must back up, 
     <lb/>
    in a great measure, the sentiments of my hon. friend, the 
     <lb/>member for North Norfolk (Mr. Charlton), with regard to 
     <lb/>the past policy of the Government in dealing with public 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="376" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00376.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="num">376</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 28,</fw> 
    
   
          
     lands in the North-West. It has always been contended by 
     <lb/>
     me since I have had a seat in this House, that the lands of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion should be administered in the interests of 
     <lb/>
     tha Dominion at large. It is to be regretted that we have 
     <lb/>
     not a larger population in the North-West and Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     to-day, and I hold that the land regulations of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment have had much to do with the lack of population 
     <lb/>
     there. The system pursued by the Government of grant<lb break="no"/>ing large tracts to colonisation companies, and of making 
     <lb/>
     large reservations that were held exclusively for sale, has 
     <lb/>
     had a great deal to do with the sparse settlement that 
     <lb/>
     exists in the North-West today. I am pleased to be able 
     <lb/>
     to state that the land regulations of to-day are better than 
     <lb/>
     the regulations that prevailed a few years ago, and I 
     <lb/>
     was also glad to learn from the Minister of Interior, 
     <lb/>
     in an interview I had with him this morning. that 
     <lb/>
     some changes will be introduced during the present Session 
     <lb/>
     which will considerably improve the land regulations of 
     <lb/>
     the North-West. In regard to the price of land referred 
     <lb/>
     to by the member for Saskatchewan (Mr. Macdowall), I 
     <lb/>
     entirely differ with him in regard to that matter. It is a 
     <lb/>
     bad policy to place the land at such prices that actual 
     <lb/>
     settlers cannot afford to buy them and enter into the actual 
     <lb/>
     work of farming. The price of $250 per acre to the actual 
     <lb/>
     settler is too high for any man to pay for land in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, to be devoted exclusively to farming purposes. As I 
     <lb/>
     have always contended, having some knowledge of the 
     <lb/>
     early settlement of that country, I hold that all the lands, 
     <lb/>
     odd and even sections, in the interest of Canada, should 
     <lb/>
     have been administered for the actual settlers instead of 
     <lb/>
     holding them for sale. I know that as regards a consider<lb break="no"/>able portion of the country I represent, the land sales of 
     <lb/>
     1880-81 proved a curse to the settlers. The odd sections 
     <lb/>
     were sold by public competition, and the average price 
     <lb/>
     realised was about $2.60 per acre, the upset price being 
     <lb/>
     $2.50 per acre. Speculators entered into a combination to 
     <lb/>
     pay as little as possible over the upset price, and the lands 
     <lb/>
     were sold at that figure. I know they have been held by 
     <lb/>
     the speculators who purchased them and who hold them 
     <lb/>
     today, and they are waiting in order to try and realise the 
     <lb/>
     amount they paid at that sale. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <!--Unsure about Mr, WILSON ref.-->
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILS2">Mr. WILSON</persName>. They cannot do it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WATS2">Mr. WATSON</persName>. The hon. gentleman owns some of the 
     <lb/>
     land himself. He purchased it at $2.60 per acre and has 
     <lb/>
     never had an opportunity of realising that price for it 
     <lb/>
     since. This has prevented settlement in regard to land 
     <lb/>
     grants for railway companies, I believe it is necessary for 
     <lb/>
     the Government to give large tracts to encourage railway 
     <lb/>
     building, for the country can only be opened up by the 
     <lb/>
     construction of railways, and it is necessary to give a por<lb break="no"/>tion of the public domain for their assistance; but instead 
     <lb/>
     of giving land grants as in the past, I would suggest to the 
     <lb/>
     House and the Government that a different policy should 
     <lb/>
     be pursued, and that instead of giving alternate sections 
     <lb/>
     the Government should give alternate townships. This 
     <lb/>
     would be in the interest of settlement. Out of a township 
     <lb/>
     of thirty-six sections there are only sixteen sections avail<lb break="no"/>able for homesteading; two sections belong to the Hudson's 
     <lb/>
     Bay Company, two sections are public school lands, and all 
     <lb/>
     the remaining odd sections are reserved for sale or for rail<lb break="no"/>way grants. That being the case, there are only six<lb break="no"/>teen sections in a township of six miles square 
     <lb/>
     that are available for homesteaders. I submit, from 
     <lb/>
     what knowledge I have in regard to settlement 
     <lb/>
     in that country, that it would be much better, 
     <lb/>
     in the interests of the settler and of settlement, to reserve 
     <lb/>
     for railway purposes, or for sale, alternate townships 
     <lb/>
     instead of alternate sections. I have stated that 
     <lb/>
     I had been informed that some amendments were to 
     <lb/>
     be introduced to improve the land regulations of 
     <lb/>
     the North-West, and I will reserve anything further I have 
     <lb/>
          

            <cb/>
          
     to say until these amendments are before the House, and 
     <lb/>
     until they have been acted on by the Minister of Interior. 
     <lb/>
     I must say, however, that I approve of the principle that 
     <lb/>
     has been adopted by the Minister of Interior in consulting 
     <lb/>
     the members for Manitoba and the North-West with respect 
     <lb/>
     to the regulations in force in that part of the country, and 
     <lb/>
     I am glad to know that some matters which I have brought 
     <lb/>
     before this House and the department for years are now 
     <lb/>
     being acted upon, particularly with respect to settlers 
     <lb/>
     being allowed to procure dead timber for fuel, and some 
     <lb/>
     other matters which I suppose will be explained by the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Interior. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     It being Six o'clock, the Speaker left the Chair. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
          </div>
         <div type="debate">
             
           <head rendition="simple:centre">After Recess.</head> 
     
           
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. Mr. Speaker, I must say that I speak under 
     <lb/>
     very unusual circumstances to-night. It is not often that 
     <lb/>
     we have such a beggarly array on the other side of the 
     <lb/>
     House. I do not know whether or not the announcement 
     <lb/>
     that I was about to address the House after recess is the 
     <lb/>
     occasion for my hon. friends of the opposite side of the 
     <lb/>
     House staying away. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <!--Unsure about Mr. DAVIES ref-->
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI3">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) They are more pleasantly en<lb break="no"/>gaged elsewhere. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName>. Be that as it may, I am glad to see that 
     <lb/>
     they have left the warhorse of Prince Edward Island here, 
     <lb/>
     and he will probably know how to take care of me. I re<lb break="no"/>gret, however, that the member for North Norfolk (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Charlton) is not here, because I would not have spoken on 
     <lb/>
     this occasion had it not been that that hon. gentleman got 
     <lb/>
     on his feet and made some remarks which I did not think 
     <lb/>
     it right to pass without making some reference to, and cor<lb break="no"/>recting his statements. During the three Sessions that I 
     <lb/>
     have been in Parliament that hon. gentleman has taken oc<lb break="no"/>casion upon every opportunity to discuss the affairs of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West and Manitoba, and to make attacks upon 
     <lb/>
     the land laws in force there. He has reiterated 
     <lb/>
     here this afternoon what he stated last year and the 
     <lb/>
     year previous, and I learn from gentlemen who sat in this 
     <lb/>
     House before I did, that he repeated this afternoon what he 
     <lb/>
     stated during Sessions before this present Parliament opened. 
     <lb/>
     I do not see what is to be gained by the hon. gentleman (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Charlton) standing in this House and continually reiterat<lb break="no"/>ing and making statements which have been refuted, time 
     <lb/>
     and time again, from the floor of Parliament. I have had 
     <lb/>
     occasion during the past two years, as I have the occasion 
     <lb/>
     now, to refute the statements made by the hon. gentleman, 
     <lb/>
     and particularly the allegation which he made this after<lb break="no"/>noon that the land laws of the United States were far 
     <lb/>
     more liberal to the settlers than the land laws of Canada at 
     <lb/>
     present in operation in Manitoba and the North-West. I 
     <lb/>
     showed the hon. gentleman last year that this was not so. 
     <lb/>
     I proved to him the year previous that it was not the fact, 
     <lb/>
     and my hon. friend the member for Lisgar (Mr. Ross) did 
     <lb/>
     the same, but, notwithstanding that, he gets up and makes a 
     <lb/>
     general statement against the land laws without giving us 
     <lb/>
     any particulars to support it. If, in the opinion of the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman, the land laws of the United States are more 
     <lb/>
     liberal than the land laws of Canada, why does he not 
     <lb/>
     make some specific statement to bear out the allegations he 
     <lb/>
     makes? Are the land laws of the United States more 
     <lb/>
     liberal than the same laws of Canada? I say that they 
     <lb/>
     are not as liberal as our laws, and I will prove it. 
     <lb/>
     All that we require is that if a young man 
     <lb/>
     comes to Manitoba he should be 18 years of age, 
     <lb/>
     and that he should have not homesteaded previously. That 
     <lb/>
     young man goes to the land office, he says that he is eigh<lb break="no"/>teen years of age, that he had not homesteaded previously, 
     <lb/>
     and he is given his entry. He goes out to the land, 
     <lb/>
     performs six months duty in each year for three years, 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="377" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00377.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">377</fw>
         
     and at the end of that time he gives notice to the nearest land 
     <lb/>
     agent that he wants to apply for his patent. He has not to 
     <lb/>
     travel thirty, or forty, or fifty miles, as the case may be, to 
     <lb/>
     the nearest land office, but on receipt of that notice, which 
     <lb/>
     he sends, an inspector is sent out, and that inspector takes 
     <lb/>
     the evidence of the settler and the evidence of his neighbors 
     <lb/>
     to show that he has fulfilled the conditions. The conse<lb break="no"/>quence is that within a very short time the report of the 
     <lb/>
     inspector is made, and the settler receives a notification 
     <lb/>
     from the land office to the effect that his land is recommend<lb break="no"/>ed for patent. Now, Sir, if the settler in the North-West 
     <lb/>
     is a foreigner, we do not ask, when he goes to the land 
     <lb/>
     office, that he should become a subject of Her Majesty 
     <lb/>
     the Queen. We do not ask him to forswear allegi<lb break="no"/>ance from the country whence he came, but if a 
     <lb/>
     young man goes to a land office in the United States 
     <lb/>
     they require that he should be twenty-one years 
     <lb/>
     of age and in addition, if he is the subject of a foreign nation 
     <lb/>
     he is required to take the oath of allegiance to the President 
     <lb/>
     of the United States, and to forswear allegiance from the 
     <lb/>
     country from which he came, and particularly the Queen of 
     <lb/>
     Great Britain and Ireland. As I have stated before, the 
     <lb/>
     young settler requires to put in three years homestead duty 
     <lb/>
     in our lands in Manitoba or the North-West Territories. 
     <lb/>
     But if a young man requires a homestead in Dakota or the 
     <lb/>
     Territories of the United States, he has to put in five years. 
     <lb/>
     We offer to settlers 160 acres of a homestead, and 160 acres 
     <lb/>
     pre-emption, but they have no such regulation in the United 
     <lb/>
     States. A man cannot pre-empt after he has homesteaded, 
     <lb/>
     and his pre-emption means that he has gone to the land 
     <lb/>
     office and sworn that he is 21 years of age, that he has put 
     <lb/>
     in six months' residence on that pre-emption, and then he 
     <lb/>
     buys it at $2.50 an acre. The best way I can describe the 
     <lb/>
     matter, so far as this question of pre-empting lands in 
     <lb/>
     Dakota is concerned, is to read an extract from the very 
     <lb/>
     able pamphlet of W. A. Webster, which is now in the 
     <lb/>
     hands of most of the members of this House. At page 5, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Webster says as follows :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "The land laws here are greatly abused. To enter on land one must 
     <lb/>
     be a citizen 21 years old, and must reside on the land five years before 
     <lb/>
     he can get his patent; but the homesteader takes advantage of a clause 
     <lb/>
     in the set, which allows him to commute, after six months' residence, 
     <lb/>
     by paying $2.50 an acre, if, during these six months, he shall have built 
     <lb/>
     a habitable house and cultivated ten acres of land. Now, this is the 
     <lb/>
     practice: Four young men enter for the land at the land office. They 
     <lb/>
     go to the place where the four corners of their sections meet, and there 
     <lb/>
     build a sod cabin 12 feet square, as a joint house for all four. They dig 
     <lb/>
     four holes a few feet deep and call them wells; borrow a yoke of steers 
     <lb/>
     and plough a few furrows around the house, and call that forty acres; 
     <lb/>
     sleep a few nights in the cabin and 'prove up;' mortgage their home<lb break="no"/>steads to the speculators and get money to get their patents. If they 
     <lb/>
     have a few dollars left they look on that as clear gain, put them in their 
     <lb/>
     pockets, go off to some other county where they are not known and go 
     <lb/>
     through the same operation again and again, while the speculator gets 
     <lb/>
     the land and tries to sell it for $10 an acre. One man told me that he 
     <lb/>
     had homesteaded nine times and was going to do so once more. The 
     <lb/>
     remains of those cabins are to be met with all over the prairie, without 
     <lb/>
     a sign of life about them. One of those deserted cabins, with a board 
     <lb/>
     nailed across the door, had a notice on it, of which the following is a 
     <lb/>
     verbatim copy:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     "Four miles from a nayber, 
     <lb/>
    "Sixty miles from a post ofis, 
     <lb/>"Twenty miles from a ralerode, 
     <lb/>"A Hundred and Atey from timber, 
     <lb/>"250 feet from water. God bless our Home. 
     <lb/>"We have gone east to spend the winter with my wife's relations." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            
            
            <p>Now, Sir, it is not necessary for me to quote further from this 
     <lb/>pamphlet. I have met men in Canada who have lived in 
     <lb/>Dakota, and I have met men who are coming across again 
     <lb/>from the States to Manitoba and the North-West, and they 
     <lb/>curse the day that ever they set foot on American soil. I 
     <lb/>heard the member for Marquette (Mr. Watson), the other 
     <lb/>day, say that Canadians were returning from Dakota and 
     <lb/>Minnesota. There is no question about that fact, for they 
     <lb/>are making entries at our customs house every day. 
     <lb/>When the hon. member for South Norfolk (Mr. Charlton) 
     <lb/>stated this afternoon, that our land laws were not as liberal 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
          
     as the land laws of the United States, that gentleman must 
     <lb/>
     have known, from the reiterated statements of myself and 
     <lb/>
     other members of the North-West, who probably know 
     <lb/>
     more about these matters than he does, that he was stating 
     <lb/>
     what was not correct. I cannot understand why, Session 
     <lb/>
     after Session, he should make that statement, if it were not 
     <lb/>
     for the fact that he is more interested in peopling the 
     <lb/>
     American North-West, than he is in peopling the North-<lb break="yes"/>West of Canada. The hon. gentleman says that we have 
     <lb/>
     a very poor showing as regards the population in Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     and the North-West. He stated to the House this after<lb break="no"/>noon, that the population of Manitoba is 132,000. New, 
     <lb/>
     Sir, according to the census of 1885, only three years ago, 
     <lb/>
     the pepulation was 108,000. So we have increased 24,000 
     <lb/>
     people in population in three years. I do not think that is 
     <lb/>
     a bad showing, and if the hon. gentleman will examine the 
     <lb/>
     ratio of increase according to the census returns of the 
     <lb/>
     United States, he will find that our percentage of increase 
     <lb/>
     is as large as the percentage of increase of any state in 
     <lb/>
     the Union. Now, as regards immigration, I do 
     <lb/>
     not think that the member for South Norfolk 
     <lb/>
     will say that the Government is pursuing a wrong policy, 
     <lb/>
     as I contend they are, in not voting a larger annual sum 
     <lb/>
     for immigration. I think the hon. gentleman holds the same 
     <lb/>
     ideas with the hon. member for South Oxford (Sir Richard 
     <lb/>
     Cartwright), in effect that the Government should not 
     <lb/>
     be blamed for not making a larger appropriation for immi<lb break="no"/>gration. Let us consider where the population of Dakota 
     <lb/>
     and Minnesota come from. It comes from the people of 
     <lb/>
     the Eastern States as well as from foreign countries. Immi<lb break="no"/>gration from foreign countries has been flowing into Dakota 
     <lb/>
     and Minnesota for the last thirty or forty years. I contend 
     <lb/>
     that the best immigration agent for any country is a man 
     <lb/>
     who comes to our country and prospers and who goes back 
     <lb/>
     to the land from which he came and tells the friends 
     <lb/>
     amongst whom he lived in his early days, of his success. Give 
     <lb/>
     us the same length of time Dakota and Minnesota have had 
     <lb/>
     to populate, and I maintain that in Manitoba and the North- <lb break="yes"/>West we will have a larger population than they have to-<lb break="yes"/>day. I was told by an agent of the Local Government of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba in Ontario, a month ago, that there were over 2,000 
     <lb/>
     Manitobans in Quebec and Ontario. Those 2,000 men will 
     <lb/>
     do more to populate our country—and possibly to de<lb break="no"/>populate your older Provinces down here—than all the 
     <lb/>
     immigration pamphlets you could have printed. If we 
     <lb/>
     look at the Argentine Republic, which is seeking to 
     <lb/>
     increase its population, we will find that it is spend<lb break="no"/>ing five million dollars this year on immigration. 
     <lb/>
     It is making every possible effort to take people there. 
     <lb/>
     What I maintain is, that if our Government gave us a more 
     <lb/>
     liberal immigration grant, our population would probably 
     <lb/>
     increase at a greater ratio. But, however that may be, I 
     <lb/>
     am perfectly satisfied that it is only a matter of time when 
     <lb/>
     our population will be just as great as that of Dakota and the 
     <lb/>
     other western territories of the United States. Any hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman from that country will tell you today that we 
     <lb/>
     have a contented, a happy and a prosperous people. When 
     <lb/>
     I tell you that the little town I come from, although 
     <lb/>
     scarcely seven years old, in 1887 shipped 8,000,000 pounds 
     <lb/>
     of freight, you will come to the conclusion that we have 
     <lb/>
     made great progress. We, last year, shipped 1,500,000 bushels 
     <lb/>
     of wheat. All that ought to be required of the members of 
     <lb/>
     this House, either those from our Province, or those from 
     <lb/>
     the other Provinces, is to have faith in our great North-<lb break="yes"/>West—to believe that it is only a matter of time when that 
     <lb/>
     country will be peopled; and if the people who are to come 
     <lb/>
     in should be of the same class as those there now, we shall 
     <lb/>
     have the fairest Province in this great Confederation. The 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman, by his remarks this afternoon, would give 
     <lb/>
     those who are imperfectly informed to understand that it 
     <lb/>
     is better for a man who wants to emigrate to go to Dakota, 
     <lb/>
     or some other part of the United States, than to go to 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="378" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00378.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="num">378</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 28,</fw> 
    
   
           
     Manitoba, or our own North-West. That must be the 
     <lb/>
     natural conclusion to be drawn from his remarks, because 
     <lb/>
     he made the general statement that Dakota and Minnesota 
     <lb/>
     were more prosperous than the Canadian North-West, and 
     <lb/>
     that their land laws were more liberal. Let any Ameri<lb break="no"/>can newspaper man or railway man take the speech of the 
     <lb/>
     hon gentleman, and he could obtain half a dozen emigrants 
     <lb/>
     with it. Now, what is the condition of the people of 
     <lb/>
     Dakota, as compared with the condition of our own people? 
     <lb/>
     Take the matter of taxation. Mr. Webster states in his 
     <lb/>
     pamphlet, among other things, at page 14: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "And I further affirm that there is no emigration from Manitoba to 
     <lb/>
     Dakota, for the above and other reasons; and, further, the near future 
     <lb/>
     of Dakota, financially, is not of the kind to inspire confidence in the 
     <lb/>
     mind of a thoughtful immigrant farmer. On the 1st of June, 1887, the 
     <lb/>
     farm mortgage debt of Dakota was $45,000,000. That sum, if equally 
     <lb/>
     divided, would be a mortgage of $400 on every family in Dakota. But 
     <lb/>
     all are not farmers; so much the worse for those that are. At the same 
     <lb/>
     date the average six mortgages on six sections of 160 acres was $800, 
     <lb/>
     drawing an interest of 10 per cent. Add to this the county debts, aver<lb break="no"/>aging $30,000, and the thoughtful farmer can see why taxes are high, 
     <lb/>
     and why it is hard to make wheat growing profitable in Dakota." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>
     He says with regard to Manitoba: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "I know of no country in which municipal taxes are as low as in Mani<lb break="no"/>toba. Nature made the roads, leaving only the bridges for the muni<lb break="no"/>cipalities to build." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>In this connection, I may say that our municipal taxes in 
     <lb/>Manitoba in the last few years have been very much reduced, 
     <lb/>and there are several municipalities in the county of Bran<lb break="no"/>don that have balances in the bank. The city of Brandon, 
     <lb/>on the 1st of January, after providing for the interest on its 
     <lb/>coupons and for every other demand, had $3,500 to its 
     <lb/>credit in the bank; the municipality of Elton had $4 000; 
     <lb/>and the municipality of Cornwallis had $1,500. The munici<lb break="no"/>pality of Oak Lake and the municipality of Blanchard, in 
     <lb/>the county of Marquette, had also large balances in the bank. 
     <lb/>If the municipalities are prosperous, I think that is good 
     <lb/>evidence that the people must be prosperous. Now, I say 
     <lb/>in answer to the hon. member for North Norfolk (Mr. 
     <lb/>Charlton), that our land laws are far more liberal than 
     <lb/>those prevailing in Dakota and the western States; and it 
     <lb/>does not behoove him, or any other member of this House, to 
     <lb/>make the general statement he has made. Our land laws 
     <lb/>have not been all that we could have wished them to be; 
     <lb/>but if any hon. gentleman imagines that the land laws of the 
     <lb/>United States are perfect, all he has to do is to go to the 
     <lb/>library to find volume after volume of the decisions of the 
     <lb/>land officers at Washington, and to find that they have had 
     <lb/>more trouble with their land laws than we have had. There 
     <lb/>are certain matters that we would like to have changed, but 
     <lb/>we are glad to have as Minister of the Interior a gentleman 
     <lb/>who has spent eight or ten years of his life in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, and is conversant with our wants and requirements; 
     <lb/>and as the hon. member for Marquette (Mr. Watson) said 
     <lb/>this afternoon, from the interview that we had with the hon. 
     <lb/>Minister to-day, we are satisfied that he is desirous of giving 
     <lb/>the settlers of that country all that is required to make the 
     <lb/>land laws of this Parliament satisfactory to them. I do 
     <lb/>not wish to state anything of what occurred at that inter<lb break="no"/>view; but as the representative of one of the constituencies 
     <lb/>of Manitoba, I am well satisfied with what the hon. Minister 
     <lb/>promised. When the new land regulations are laid before 
     <lb/>the House, we shall have a full discussion of the question, 
     <lb/>and I will reserve any further remarks I have to make 
     <lb/>until that occasion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCMU1">Mr. McMULLEN</persName>. I am very glad indeed to hear the 
     <lb/>
     glowing accounts given by the hon. gentleman of the pros<lb break="no"/>perity of the North-West. I am sure it is a matter of 
     <lb/>
     great satisfaction to us all to learn that the prospects of the 
     <lb/>
     country are so bright. We shall indeed be pleased to see 
     <lb/>
     a large influx of population into that country. I also 
     <lb/>
     listened with great interest to the remarks made by the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin). He put 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
          
     the case of the settlers in very plain and pointed terms, and 
     <lb/>
     endeavored to show what changes were, in his opinion, 
     <lb/>
     necessary in the land regulations. I think it will not be 
     <lb/>
     denied that things occurred in that country which we have 
     <lb/>
     to regret, and that mistakes have been made in connection 
     <lb/>
     with the land regulations. It was a very unfortunate ar<lb break="no"/>rangement by which the Government permitted large sec<lb break="no"/>tions of that country to be taken up by colonisation com<lb break="no"/>panies and withheld from actual settlers for years, so that 
     <lb/>
     many persons who went in there were prevented from set<lb break="no"/>tling where they wanted to. If the arrangements had been 
     <lb/>
     such that the actual settler could have gone in and taken 
     <lb/>
     up land wherever he wished to locate, I believe a larger 
     <lb/>
     population would be there than there is at present. These 
     <lb/>
     are matters that we have to deplore, and I earnestly 
     <lb/>
     hope, along with the gentlemen who have spoken, 
     <lb/>
     that the Minister now in charge of that department 
     <lb/>
     will make such changes as will give the actual settler 
     <lb/>
     greater advantages than he has enjoyed in that coun<lb break="no"/>try hitherto. But while we are prepared to lend our hearty 
     <lb/>
     encouragement to every movement that will tend to fill that 
     <lb/>
     country with population and promote its development, 
     <lb/>
     that would tend to bring it up to the standard where I 
     <lb/>
     would like to see it, a great populous and wealthy country. 
     <lb/>
     There is another side of the question that has not been 
     <lb/>
     touched by any hon. gentleman opposite, the question of 
     <lb/>
     expense. I hold that in their arrangements the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment have expended enormous sums of money for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of meeting the wishes of political friends and finding 
     <lb/>
     soft and easy resting places for those who were pressing 
     <lb/>
     upon them for lucrative positions. When we come to con<lb break="no"/>sider the condition of things as we find them by the Auditor 
     <lb/>
     General's Report, we have to deplore the fact that an enor<lb break="no"/>mous amount of money has been expended compared with 
     <lb/>
     the amount received in return. I find that we expended 
     <lb/>
     altogether last year, including the expenses of the Winni<lb break="no"/>peg board, and the expenses west of Winnipeg, as follows: 
     <lb/>
     Dominion lands, outside service, $149,536.61. We expended 
     <lb/>
     on the Half breed Commission $6,714.39, and we expended 
     <lb/>
     on the registrars, of whom we have seven, $13,386.32. 
     <lb/>
     Now this is in all an expenditure for officials in the 
     <lb/>
     North-West, including the Land Board at Winnipeg, and 
     <lb/>
     all west of that, of $169,637.32. Now, what were our 
     <lb/>
     receipts? Our entire income last year from the sales of 
     <lb/>
     lands, mainly coal lands, ranching grants, and all other 
     <lb/>
     sources was $267,973.51, leaving a balance to our credit 
     <lb/>
     of $98,336.18. That virtually means that for all the money 
     <lb/>
     received in the North-West, we have actually paid out 60 
     <lb/>
     per cent. for hired service, agents, inspectors, travellers, 
     <lb/>
     and the like. I want to give a resume of the account, as it 
     <lb/>
     now stands, for the last year. As I stated before, we have 
     <lb/>
     expended $149,534.61 under the head of Dominion lands 
     <lb/>
     account. That includes contingencies. Then we have 
     <lb/>
     expended in the Department of the Interior, inside service, 
     <lb/>
     salaries here at Ottawa, $35,011.43; on surveys, $136,009.02; 
     <lb/>
     salaries at Ottawa, Dominion lands, $76,604,67; contingen<lb break="no"/>cies at Ottawa belonging to Department of Interior, 
     <lb/>
     $22,137.02. In all we have expended in the Department of 
     <lb/>
     Interior, including the expenses in Ottawa, and the expenses 
     <lb/>
     in the North-West, and the surveys, $420,744.76. Now, let 
     <lb/>
     us look at the receipts. We have received from Dominion 
     <lb/>
     lands and ranching leases, &amp;c., $217,688.01; from ordnance 
     <lb/>
     lands, $36,239.88; from the registry office, 87,212.02; fines 
     <lb/>
     and forfeitures, $7,065.76; and other fines $372.79; in all 
     <lb/>
     we have collected $267,973.50. Deducting that from our 
     <lb/>
     expenditure, we are actually at a positive less in the Opera<lb break="no"/>tion of the Department, including the surveys for last year, 
     <lb/>
     of $166,172.22, but allowing that the surveys performed 
     <lb/>
     last year, which cost $106,000, should be charged to capital 
     <lb/>
     account, we are actually at a loss of $60,172.22, on last 
     <lb/>
     year's operations. Now, to give the House a little idea of 
     <lb/>
     the manner in-which this condition of things is brought 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="379" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00379.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">379</fw>
           
     about I will just give you the list of the different receipts 
     <lb/>
     and expenditures of the Dominion land agencies in the 
     <lb/>
     North-West: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <table>
               <row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Receipts.</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Expenditure.</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Battleford......... . .............</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$ 245 38</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$ 4,899 32</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Birtle ...................................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">9,088 14</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,402 16</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Calgary ....... .. ................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">18,538 99</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">10,447 53</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Coteau ...... . ...... ... ..........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,277 95</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,651 58</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Dufferin ............................ ...</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">12,368 60</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,456 40</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Edmonton ..... ......... ..........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">8,603 58</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">6,270 88</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Lethbridge ...........................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,288 80</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,553 95</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Little Saskatchewan ..............</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">5,655 43</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,590 90</cell></row>
               <row><cell>New Westminster ......... . ........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">36,154 20</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">10,032 31</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Prince Albert .................. .......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">4,389 90</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">7,219 48</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Regina, Qu'Appelle..... . .....</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">5,852 19</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">8,149 92</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Rocky Mountains Park.. ........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,951 58</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,203 01</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Souris....................... ................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">14,574 66</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">5,675 96</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Touchwood..... ....... ................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">403 65</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">536 11</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Turtle Mountain .....................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">12,042 68</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">3,404 39</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Winnipeg ............ ....... . ..........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">59,204 74</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">85,206 34</cell></row>
            </table>
   
            <p>
     In all the North-West, we collected during the last year 
     <lb/>
     for lands, ranching grants, coal dues, and for all purposes 
     <lb/>
     that come within the range of Dominion lands, $193,640.43, 
     <lb/>
     and we actually expended for the services of registrars, 
     <lb/>
     inspectors, agents and others, $153,740.24, leaving a net 
     <lb/>
     balance to our credit of $38,900.15. I will give you a 
     <lb/>
     little idea of the expenses at Winnipeg. They are really 
     <lb/>
     surprising. To begin with, Mr. William Pearce, superin<lb break="no"/>tendent of mines, has a salary of $3,200; Mr. H. H. Smith, 
     <lb/>
     commissioner, has a salary of 85,000 a year; Mr. Rufus 
     <lb/>
     Stephenson, inspector of color isation companies, gets $3,000; 
     <lb/>
     and I venture to say that there are people in the Province 
     <lb/>
     of Ontario who will make a declaration before any judge 
     <lb/>
     or jury that Mr. Stephenson was not in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West altogether four months, and was in his comfort<lb break="no"/>able home in Ontario at least eight months of 
     <lb/>
     the gear for which he drew $3,000 as inspector, 
     <lb/>
     and over $3,000 for expenses. Then we come to Mr. D. J. 
     <lb/>
     Macdonnell. He is employed in the Land Office at Winnipeg, 
     <lb/>
     and gets $3 a day. Mr. J. M. Gordon, inspector of agencies, 
     <lb/>
     receives $2,000 a year. Mr. Dolbear receives $3 a day. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Burpé receives $1,800 a year; and so it goes on. The total 
     <lb/>
     expense of the Land Board at Winnipeg is $30,745.57. But 
     <lb/>
     we have seven agencies in the North-West, and to give an 
     <lb/>
     idea of the expenses of these agencies, I will read some of 
     <lb/>
     the items. Mr. E. T. Smith, the agent at Brandon, has a 
     <lb/>
     salary of $1,200 a year. Mr. W. H. Hiam has a salary of 
     <lb/>
     $1,200 a year. Mr. A. W. Reynold s, in the same agency, 
     <lb/>
     receives $3 a day. Mr. O. D. Rickards has about the same 
     <lb/>
     salary, and there are a lot of other men. At Calgary, we 
     <lb/>
     have Mr. Amos Rowe receiving $1,200. Mr. Meyer receiv<lb break="no"/>ing over $1,000 a year. Mr. Michael Harris the same, and 
     <lb/>
     Mr. McQuilken receiving about the same. In addition to 
     <lb/>
     that, there is Mr. T. A. McLean, registrar, receiving $1,200 
     <lb/>
     a year, and Mr. Rochester receiving $3 a day, and many 
     <lb/>
     others. The sums paid in that agency run up in the same 
     <lb/>
     ratio. I cannot understand how hon. gentlemen opposite 
     <lb/>
     can expect that the people will put up with the extrava<lb break="no"/>gance which exists in the North West. It appears to be filled 
     <lb/>
     up by officials who never did anything and, since they 
     <lb/>
     have been sent there, do nothing. At Prince Albert, 
     <lb/>
     I find that Mr. J. McTaggart, agent, receives $1,200; Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Schmidt, clerk, is employed at $3 a day; Mr. Sproat, regis<lb break="no"/>trar, receives $1,200; and Mr. Waggoner, crown timber 
     <lb/>
     agent, receives the same amount. In addition to that, $240 
     <lb/>
     is paid to Mrs. E. W. Sproat for rent for the registry 
     <lb/>
     office, and there are a number of other officials who receive 
     <lb/>
     smaller salaries. At Regina, Mr. W. H. Stevenson, agent, 
     <lb/>
     receives $1,200; A. J. Fraser, clerk, $1,095. There is also 
     <lb/>
     there a Mr. P. M. Barker, instructor of registrars. This is 
     <lb/>
     a most peculiar thing. We have only seven registrars in 
     <lb/>
     the North-West, and, in order to give these men informa<lb break="no"/>tion as to how they should do their duty, we have to send 
     <lb/>
     up an instructor. I do not know for a certainty who this 
     <lb/>
    Mr. Barker is, but I think he once lived in Orangeville, and 
     <lb/>
           

    
            <cb/>
           
     I think he is related to the hon. member for Simcoe. If I 
     <lb/>
     am wrong, I can be corrected. However, Mr. Barker is 
     <lb/>
     there, and for instructing the registrars in these seven 
     <lb/>
     offices he receives $1,600 a year and travelling expenses. 
     <lb/>
     I say it is an outrage on the people of this country to ask 
     <lb/>
     them to put up with this condition of things. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment have inaugurated a most extravagant course in the 
     <lb/>
     North-West. The average salary paid at the different 
     <lb/>
     offices, leaving out Winnipeg, where the cost is over 
     <lb/>
     $30,000 a year, is $7,700 for each of the 16 agencies. 
     <lb/>
     I think it is time that a host of these unnecessary officers 
     <lb/>
     were discharged from the service, and that the Government 
     <lb/>
     should cut down the expenses within reasonable and decent 
     <lb/>
     limits. When we consider the glowing statements that 
     <lb/>
     were made in this House from year to year, as to what 
     <lb/>
     would likely be the result in the North-West, we cannot 
     <lb/>
     forget what Sir Charles Tupper stated we might expect. 
     <lb/>
     The Premier, when he was trying to induce the House to 
     <lb/>
     pass the vote of $30,000,000 to the Canadian Pacific Rail<lb break="no"/>way Company, said he had made a careful calculation 
     <lb/>
     based on his extended experience and also on information 
     <lb/>
     received from other sources, and that he was in a position 
     <lb/>
     to assure the House that we might reasonably anticipate 
     <lb/>
     that by the year 1890 we would have gathered out of that 
     <lb/>
     country $71,305,000. Instead of that, in 1889, we find that 
     <lb/>
     we are $160,000 short of expenses. Then Sir Leonard 
     <lb/>
     Tilley in his Budget Speech delivered shortly before he left 
     <lb/>
     us, gave a very glowing account of what he looked forward 
     <lb/>
     to as the result of our enterprise in the North-West. He 
     <lb/>
     told us that he had carefully made out his figures, and he 
     <lb/>
     was a little more careful than the First Minister, but he 
     <lb/>
     said he believed that by the year l891 we would have a 
     <lb/>
     net balance from the North-West of $53,693,251. If 
     <lb/>
     it had not been for these statements, if it had 
     <lb/>
     not been for the assurance given by men of experience 
     <lb/>
     and possessing, as they did largely, the confidence 
     <lb/>
     of the people of the country, I say that the people would 
     <lb/>
     never at the last election have endorsed the course which 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentlemen took in connection with the construction of 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian Pacific Railway. We are perfectly willing to 
     <lb/>
     acknowledge that it was a necessity, that it was desirable 
     <lb/>
     that it should be built, but the course of extravagance 
     <lb/>
     which was followed in building it, and in the way in which 
     <lb/>
     money was dealt out in order to keep members of this 
     <lb/>
     House in line, was nothing short of a disgrace, and the 
     <lb/>
     people were deceived in regard to the prospect of the result 
     <lb/>
     of the building of that road. Instead of our getting 
     <lb/>
     seventy-one millions as we were promised in 1890, 
     <lb/>
     or fifty-three millions as we were promised in 1891, we find 
     <lb/>
     a large balance chargeable to that country for managing 
     <lb/>
     expenses alone, and we do not take into account the im<lb break="no"/>mense amount of money which was spent on the unfortunate 
     <lb/>
     war there, in which about $8,000,000 were spent unneces<lb break="no"/>sarily, because, if the proper steps had been taken, that war 
     <lb/>
     would not have occurred. We do not take into account 
     <lb/>
     the cost of the Mounted Police, the number of which was 
     <lb/>
     raised from 500 to 1,000. The expense of that force last 
     <lb/>
     year was $860,000, and $876,000 was expended for feeding 
     <lb/>
     Indians. Putting these sums with the amount on the 
     <lb/>
     debit side for the administration of the land office alone, 
     <lb/>
     we find that we are over $2,000,000 short on the transac<lb break="no"/>tions of last year. When these men from Manitoba and 
     <lb/>
     the North-West are urging extended and liberal action 
     <lb/>
     towards that country, I think it behoves the people to cry 
     <lb/>
     a halt in the expenditures there. There are a number of 
     <lb/>
     useless officials in the North-West who are enjoying a good 
     <lb/>
     time at the expense of the country, and the sooner they 
     <lb/>
     are removed, and the staff cut down to the number required 
     <lb/>
     for the necessities of the service, the better for the people. 
     <lb/>
     When a short time ago the leader of the House, who is not 
     <lb/>
     at present in his seat, characterised it as being a "happy 
     <lb/>
     hunting ground for political hacks," he called it really what 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="380" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00380.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="num">380</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 28,</fw> 
    
  
           
     it had been made by hon. gentlemen opposite, and it is time 
     <lb/>
     we should put a stop to it. Why, Sir, hon. gentlemen should 
     <lb/>
     feel ashamed that a man like Rufus Stephenson should be 
     <lb/>
     foisted upon this country, both he and his son, he himself 
     <lb/>
     drawing $3,000 a year and travelling expenses, and a son 
     <lb/>
     in an office in Winnipeg drawing $2,000; and I do not 
     <lb/>
     know how many more relations he has living upon the 
     <lb/>
     country, I believe that every relation he has will be pro<lb break="no"/>vided for at the public expense if this Government con<lb break="no"/>tinues much longer in power. Now, Sir, I say it is time 
     <lb/>
     that we called a halt; it is time the Government were 
     <lb/>
     in a position to announce to this House that they intend 
     <lb/>
     to step the extravagance that exists in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West. We shall be glad to encourage them in the 
     <lb/>
     direction of securing an increase of settlement. We do not 
     <lb/>
     deny that it is absolutely necessary in the interest of this 
     <lb/>
     Dominion that the country should be settled. We will 
     <lb/>
     offer then every encouragement, we will say every word 
     <lb/>
     we can in its favor. I believe myself it is going to be a 
     <lb/>
     great country, I believe it is the best unsettled country on 
     <lb/>
     the continent of America to-day. But I am sorry to say 
     <lb/>
     that by the blunders of this Government, by the manner in 
     <lb/>
     which that country has been handled and operated in the 
     <lb/>
     interests of political friends, by the manner in which her 
     <lb/>
     resources have been squandered, timber limits, land grants, 
     <lb/>
     and one thing and another having been used for political 
     <lb/>
    purposes, to serve political ends, that country in the past 
     <lb/>has been cursed, and I hope that curse will now be removed, 
     <lb/>and that in the future every inducement possible will be 
     <lb/>held out to the people of the old world to come there and 
     <lb/>make comfortable homes for themselves, and that the re<lb break="no"/>strictions that have weighed upon settlement there, and 
     <lb/>have driven people across the border, will be removed. I 
     <lb/>say, that so far as the older sections of the country is con<lb break="no"/>cerned, we cannot afford to go on and spend recklessly, in 
     <lb/>the way we have been doing, the money of the people of 
     <lb/>this country in a manner that is altogether unnecessary. 
     <lb/>I claim that it is quite unnecessary. I claim that no man 
     <lb/>who will go through that country, as I went through it, 
     <lb/>and see on every hand fellows in official position, fellows 
     <lb/>occupying easy quarters and drawing large salaries, but 
     <lb/>will come to the conclusion that that country has been 
     <lb/>cursed. I hope the Minister, now in charge will put in the 
     <lb/>pruning hook at once, and that whatever the evils of the 
     <lb/>past may have been in regard to officials there, these evils 
     <lb/>will now be put a stop to. Why, Sir, there are evils in 
     <lb/>other directions. I am sorry to say, that my hon. friend 
     <lb/>from West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) is no exception, because 
     <lb/>I see that the organ of which undoubtedly be is chief—or 
     <lb/>used to be, and I suppose he is still—is getting $5,000 a 
     <lb/>year for printing. It appears that every one who supports 
     <lb/>the Government thinks he must get some little picking, 
     <lb/>some little advantage for himself. New, I say we have 
     <lb/>had enough of this thing, it has just gone far enough, 
     <lb/>in the interests of the people of this country, and I 
     <lb/>hope that the members of this House will stand shoulder 
     <lb/>to shoulder, and persistently sit upon this thing, and not 
     <lb/>permit it to exist any longer, cut off these unnecessary 
     <lb/>and extravagant officials, and come down to a common 
     <lb/>sense position. The course that we have been pursuing 
     <lb/>in the past in the North West, has been a curse to 
     <lb/>the country; we have cursed it by our land regulations; 
     <lb/>we have cursed it by our mining regulations, by our rail<lb break="no"/>way regulations and in other ways; now let us remove all 
     <lb/>the restrictions and give the people an opportunity to rise, 
     <lb/>let us take off the unnecessary burden put upon them in the 
     <lb/>way of officials that are now roaming around that country, 
     <lb/>and cut down the expenditure to what is actually necessary. 
     <lb/>Then I believe that the country will prosper and will go on 
     <lb/>prospering. ButI believe if you do not do that, if you 
     <lb/>allow this horde of Officials and these monopolies to continue 
     <lb/>to exist as they have in the past, the same curse will con<lb break="no"/>
            
            <cb/>
          
     tinue to rest upon that country. Now, I consider it my 
     <lb/>
     duty, in the interest of the constituency I represent, and 
     <lb/>
     the Province from which I come, to make these remarks. 
     <lb/>
     I do not offer any objection to one word that has been 
     <lb/>
     said by the representatives of that country; I give them 
     <lb/>
     credit for advocating the cause of their country; they 
     <lb/>
     would not be doing their duty if they did not advocate it, 
     <lb/>
     but I also hold that it is our duty to keep control of these 
     <lb/>
     things. We, in the older Provinces, have an interest in that 
     <lb/>
     country, because we have to help to bear the burden, we 
     <lb/>
     have got to pay the taxes, we have to contribute towards 
     <lb/>
     the enormous sums that will annually fall upon the shoulders 
     <lb/>
     of the people of this country to meet the annual expense 
     <lb/>
     and the enormously increased interest on our public debt, 
     <lb/>
     to pay for the improvements that have been made up there; 
     <lb/>
     and I say it is our duty to raise our voice in the interests 
     <lb/>
     of the people and to declare that we object to see the taxes 
     <lb/>
     increased from year to year, that we object to see imposed 
     <lb/>
     upon them new burdens which cannot be rolled away for 
     <lb/>
     many years to come. I hope the course of this House will 
     <lb/>
     show the Minister of Interior that we desire him to put in 
     <lb/>
     the pruning hook, and let us begin at once to do what we 
     <lb/>
     ought to have done long ago. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI9">Mr. DAVIS</persName> (Alberta). In Speaking upon these resolu<lb break="no"/>tions passed by the Legislative Assembly of the North-West 
     <lb/>
     last November, and that have been laid upon the Table 
     <lb/>
     by my hon. friend from West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin), 
     <lb/>
     I wish to say he has echoed my sentiments exactly. 
     <lb/>
     In the first part of his speech he also gave us a glow<lb break="no"/>ing description of the agricultural capacity of the North- <lb break="yes"/>West. There was one industry, however, which he 
     <lb/>
     did not speak of, and that is the ranching industry. We 
     <lb/>
     have in the district of Alberta, as you all know, a large 
     <lb/>
     expanse of open prairies, where we can graze cattle the 
     <lb/>
     year round. We have in the northern portion of the terri<lb break="no"/>tory some of the finest, if not the very finest, farming land 
     <lb/>
     that lies out of doors. All we require is a railway in the 
     <lb/>
     North Saskatchewan country in order to develop that im<lb break="no"/>mense wheat country. Speaking of the ranching country, 
     <lb/>
     I may say that in the southern portion of Alberta you will 
     <lb/>
     see herds of cattle which have been put into that country 
     <lb/>
     during the last five years. There are at present, I suppose, 
     <lb/>
     about 130,000 horned cattle in the district of Alberta. The 
     <lb/>
     first year we had to import cattle, but last year I suppose 
     <lb/>
     the district of Alberta exported 5,000 head of steers, and 
     <lb/>
     probably as many more were consumed for home consump<lb break="no"/>tion, making 10,000 head of steers, while, five years ago, 
     <lb/>
     we had to import all the beef that was used in the country 
     <lb/>
     from the United States. Now these 10,000 head of steers, 
     <lb/>
     at $40 a piece—which they would bring at least, while 
     <lb/>
     many of them brought $50— would make $400,000 for that 
     <lb/>
     new industry that has been established in the North-West. 
     <lb/>
     Then we have another industry that has just been estab<lb break="no"/>lished in that country, and that is the raising of horses. 
     <lb/>
     We have at present, I presume, at least 20,000 in the district 
     <lb/>
     of Alberta, and I wish to remind the Minister of Agriculture 
     <lb/>
     that in his quarantine list he has left out horses. I see he 
     <lb/>
     has discriminated against all other animals except horses, 
     <lb/>
     I wish he would include horses on the list in his quarantine 
     <lb/>
     regulations. They are raising a great many horses in the 
     <lb/>
     vast country to the south of us, and we know at the present 
     <lb/>
     time there is some disease amongst horses on the south 
     <lb/>
     side of the line; therefore I think the Minister ought to 
     <lb/>
     put horses on the list, but I would not advise him to 
     <lb/>
     give as many days as he does in the case of cattle. 
     <lb/>
     Then within the last few years in the district of Alberta 
     <lb/>
     there have been large tracts of land held by speculators 
     <lb/>
     from the east who never intended to put stock on them. 
     <lb/>
     The present Minister of Interior, since he assumed Office, 
     <lb/>
     has thrown open at least 1,500,000 acres which, otherwise, 
     <lb/>
     would not have been opened to settlers, and this has 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="381" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00381.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">381</fw>
          
     brought a great many people to our section of the country 
     <lb/>
     with a view to settling there, while previously no one 
     <lb/>
     thought of going there as it was considered that if the land 
     <lb/>
     was leased a man could not settle on it. This action of the 
     <lb/>
     Government has removed all cause of complaint in that 
     <lb/>
     direction. There is now sufficient land of the very finest 
     <lb/>
     class thrown open to which settlers can go and have the 
     <lb/>
     advantage of being near towns where they can carry on 
     <lb/>
     mixed farming and enjoy the best advantages. The first 
     <lb/>
     resolution passed by the Legislative Assembly reads as 
     <lb/>
     follows:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That this Assembly regards the question as of first importance and 
     <lb/>
     urges the Dominion Government to take immediate action in giving an 
     <lb/>
     outlet by railway to the pioneer settlements of the North Saskatchewan." 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
     
</quote>
     
            <p>Edmonton, Prince Albert and St. Albert are old settlements, 
     <lb/>I suppose Fort Edmonton was established 100 years ago, 
     <lb/>and all that these towns and the outlying country require 
     <lb/>is railway communication to make them, as I have said,the 
     <lb/>Garden of Eden. The next resolution is with respect to the 
     <lb/>half-breeds resident in the electoral districts bordering on 
     <lb/>the North Saskatchewan. The North Saskatchewan runs 
     <lb/>both through my district, that of Alberta, and the Saskatch<lb break="no"/>ewan district. There are a great many half-breeds who 
     <lb/>live on the border of the Saskatchewan River, having settled 
     <lb/>there in old days. The resolution to which I refer reads as 
     <lb/>follows:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "Whereas it has been represented to this Assembly by some of its 
     <lb/>
     members that among the half-breeds resident in the electoral districts 
     <lb/>
     bordering on the Saskatchewan, who preferred claims for losses during 
     <lb/>
     the rebellion at 1885 before the Commissioners on such claims, and 
     <lb/>
     whose claims have been rejected, some, who were known to have been 
     <lb/>
     loyal, had their claims rejected, while others who were known to have 
     <lb/>
     been directly implicated in the uprising have had their claims allowed. 
     <lb/>
     That such apparent discrimination has given rise to a wide spread feel<lb break="no"/>ing among the half-breeds referred to that those who remained loyal 
     <lb/>
     have not received the justice intended by the Government at the hands 
     <lb/>
     of the Commissioners. Be it resolved, &amp;c." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>
     I think that a commission should be appointed, as the reso<lb break="no"/>lution sets forth, consisting of a judge of the Supreme 
     <lb/>
     Court of the North-West Territories, so that all claims may 
     <lb/>
     be wiped out, and not be brought before Parliament year 
     <lb/>
     after year. The next resolution upon which I will touch 
     <lb/>
     was passed on the 23rd of last November, and it sets forth : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That in the opinion of that Assembly a vote of the Territories on 
     <lb/>
               the question of license <hi rendition="simple:italic">versus</hi> prohibition should immediately be taken." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     This is one of the most burning questions of the North- <lb break="yes"/>West. The people should be allowed to decide whether 
     <lb/>
     they would have free whiskey or high license, or have the 
     <lb/>
     liquor as in the Eastern Provinces. Lliquor is now 
     <lb/>
     brought into the country, and the Government derive no 
     <lb/>
     revenue from it. I have no doubt, if a vote of the people 
     <lb/>
     were taken to-morrow, every man in the business of 
     <lb/>
     selling liquor would vote against free whiskey and with 
     <lb/>
     the temperance party, simply because to do otherwise 
     <lb/>
     would be to destroy his means of livelihood. There 
     <lb/>
     are in Calgary to-day not less than 25 saloons selling 
     <lb/>
     liquor. Neither the town of Calgary nor the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     Government derive any revenue from that sale. It will be 
     <lb/>
     asked, where does the liquor come from? It comes from 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia, Manitoba and Montana. Under these 
     <lb/>
     circumstances, it would be better if the people of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West were allowed to have a vote on this subject, 
     <lb/>
     or at least be placed on the same footing as the people 
     <lb/>
     in other portions of the Dominion, so that they could pass 
     <lb/>
     the Scott Act or not as they desired. It is certain that you 
     <lb/>
     can never prohibit the sale of liquor in the North-West as 
     <lb/>
     long as it is manufactured. I hope, therefore, that the 
     <lb/>
     Government will take this resolution more especially under 
     <lb/>
     their consideration, and will endeavor to deal with it in 
     <lb/>
     such a way that we can have this question settled either by 
     <lb/>
     the vote of the people or by the Dominion Parliament. 
     <lb/>
    The next resolution takes up the question of immigration. 
     <lb/>I think the Government should without doubt grant more 
     <lb/>
           

    
            <cb/>
         
     liberal aid to immigration to the North-West than they 
     <lb/>
     have given hitherto. There should be immense quantities 
     <lb/>
     of pamphlets circulated through all portions of Europe, the 
     <lb/>
     United States and even Eastern Canada. I venture to say 
     <lb/>
     that the United States Government have sent out ten car 
     <lb/>
     loads of immigration pamphlets to one sent by the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government, and the reason why their country has 
     <lb/>
     been settled is because it has been advertised. With regard 
     <lb/>
     to placing agents in Great Britain and the United States, I 
     <lb/>
     fully agree with the resolution and the remarks of the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin). It is asked 
     <lb/>
     that the sum of $15,000 be placed at the disposal of 
     <lb/>
     the Territories, and this would be a mere drop in the bucket 
     <lb/>
     as compared with other expenses that are going on, and it 
     <lb/>
     would benefit the country tenfold. The next resolution 
     <lb/>
     deals with the subject of the settlers being allowed to use 
     <lb/>
     dry wood for fuel. That, I believe, has been already 
     <lb/>
     arranged, and I have simply to say that the people of the 
     <lb/>
     North West should be allowed to burn up the dry wood that 
     <lb/>
     is going to waste without paying revenue to the Dominion. 
     <lb/>
     There is another question I wish to urge upon the Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Inland Revenue, and that is the appointment of a 
     <lb/>
     hide inspector at McLeod and Calgary. At the present 
     <lb/>
     time when so many cattle are being shipped out of the 
     <lb/>
     country, it has become very important that all the hides 
     <lb/>
     should be inspected before the cattle leave the country. 
     <lb/>
     Even if a man kills meat on the prairie he should be com<lb break="no"/>pelled to bring in the hides, so that it would be known 
     <lb/>
     whether he had killed his own animals or those of his 
     <lb/>
     neighbors. The cost would be but very light and it could 
     <lb/>
     easily be paid out of the revenue, by simply putting a fee 
     <lb/>
     upon our hide inspector. In this same resolution the 
     <lb/>
     Assembly recommends as follows:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "As under the Half-breed Commission of the 20th March, 1885, the 
     <lb/>
     Indian title, in as far as half-breeds are concerned, only extends to 
     <lb/>
     those born prior to 15th July, 1870, and as a number have been born to 
     <lb/>
     parents coming under the said Commission of 1885, who in the opinion 
     <lb/>
     of this Assembly have equal rights to those already dealt with: This 
     <lb/>
     Assembly would draw the attention of the Dominion Government to the 
     <lb/>
     fact and urge that steps be taken to finally end all halt-breed claims." 
     <lb/>
     
     </p>
</quote>
            <p>We all know that there are quite a number of half-breeds 
     <lb/>in the North-West Territories who when this treaty was 
     <lb/>made with them in 1870 were in Manitoba, but before they 
     <lb/>were settled with they moved to the North-West. Those 
     <lb/>people were not settled with until 1885 and then only those 
     <lb/>who were included in the Treaty of 1870 had their claims 
     <lb/>met by the Government, leaving the children born between 
     <lb/>1870 and 1885 out of the treaty. There is no reason in the 
     <lb/>world why those children should not receive the same 
     <lb/>benefits as the other so long as their title is not extinguished. 
     <lb/>If the Government had paid eveiyone of them in 1870 
     <lb/>there would probably have been no rebellion in 1885. I 
     <lb/>would strongly recommend to the Government that this 
     <lb/>matter should be attended to at once and that the claims of 
     <lb/>those excluded from the treaties should be considered in the 
     <lb/>same way as the claims of the others, viz, by a commission 
     <lb/>of the judges of the North-West Territories. The Assembly 
     <lb/>also recommends: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That the Dominion Government be asked to grant scrip to all those 
     <lb/>
     acting during the North-West Rebellion as scouts under the Police Act." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     They also recommend that the North-West Mounted Police, 
     <lb/>
     who rendered valuable services during the rebellion, should 
     <lb/>
     be rewarded. I think that this is a very fair request to make 
     <lb/>
     to the Government. There is not the slightest doubt that 
     <lb/>
     any one who acted as a scout duiing the rebellion, as well 
     <lb/>
     as the members of the North-West Mounted Police force 
     <lb/>
     should receive the same compensation as others. They are 
     <lb/>
     certainly better entitled to recognition at the hands of the 
     <lb/>
     Government than many of those who received it. I cannot 
     <lb/>
     see why the scouts and the Mounted Police should not be 
     <lb/>
     treated the same as the militia and volunteer forces. They 
     <lb/>
     did as good work as any of the others, and they should 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="382" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00382.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="num">382</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 28,</fw> 
     
   
           
     receive the same reward. They have been precluded from 
     <lb/>
     even the small recompense of receiving medals, with the 
     <lb/>
     exception of just a few who were in actual combat. I 
     <lb/>
     know that some of the home guards who never left their 
     <lb/>
     homes at all were presented with medals, but the police 
     <lb/>
     and the scouts who took an active part were left out in the 
     <lb/>
     cold. Whether the police were in action or not, I hold that 
     <lb/>
     every man of them who was in the field should at least 
     <lb/>
     receive a medal. Those medals would not cost much; I 
     <lb/>
     suppose not more than $1.25 each, and that amount would 
     <lb/>
     never be felt by the Dominion of Canada. Another reso<lb break="no"/>lution of the Assembly says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "We, your committee, find that several trails are made use of for 
     <lb/>
     carrying Her Majesty's mails, as well as being the main highways lead<lb break="no"/>ing from one settlement to another. We find that certain streams, rivers 
     <lb/>
     and sloughs on those trails form strong impediments, not only to settle<lb break="no"/>ment, but interfere, to a great extent, in the conveyance of Her Majesty's 
     <lb/>
     mails, besides causing an increased expenditure of that very important 
     <lb/>
     item. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "The condition of some of those trails, at certain seasons of the year, 
     <lb/>
     has proven to be dangerous to life and property, and communication 
     <lb/>
     between the different settlements made most difficult and supplies not 
     <lb/>
     only rendered much dearer, but, in fact, almost impossible to obtain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Such a condition of affairs is a most important element in retarding 
     <lb/>
     settlement and the proper development of the Territories, and as the 
     <lb/>
     funds at the disposal o the Territorial Government are insufficient to 
     <lb/>
     make the necessary improvements, and we consider the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment especially interested in those trails, we would, therefore, urge 
     <lb/>
     that the Dominion Government appropriate a special sum to be ex<lb break="no"/>pended on the following trails, viz.:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "From Macleod to Calgary. 
     <lb/>
    "From Calgary to Edmonton and Athabasca Landing. 
     <lb/>"From Swift Current to Battleford. 
     <lb/>"From Qu'Appelie to Prince Albert." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

   </quote>

    
   
            <p>
     I call particular attention to the necessity for improving 
     <lb/>
     the trail between McLeod and Calgary. There are four 
     <lb/>
     rivers on that trail which during at least four months in 
     <lb/>
     the year are almost impossible to cross, and only one, at 
     <lb/>
     Elbow River, is bridged at the present time. I would 
     <lb/>
     urge on the members of the Cabinet, and especially on the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Public Works, to see that an appropriation is 
     <lb/>
     put in the Estimates for the bridging of these streams. 
     <lb/>
     <choice><sic>Tho</sic><corr>The</corr></choice> work is most important to the people of that district, 
     <lb/>
     and it should not be neglected. The same remarks apply 
     <lb/>
     to the trail from Calgary to Edmonton, and the trail from 
     <lb/>
     Lethbridge to McLeod. This latter trail is only a short 
     <lb/>
     distance of thirty miles, and we have two of the largest 
     <lb/>
     rivers of the North-West to cross on it, which at all seasons 
     <lb/>
     of the year are unfordable. In the spring when the ice is 
     <lb/>
     soft and coming down, it is almost impossible to get 
     <lb/>
     across this river in any way. Not only are those rivers 
     <lb/>
     dangerous to property, but scarcely a spring passes that 
     <lb/>
     there are not lives lost there. Permit me to make 
     <lb/>
     some comments on the statements of the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for North Wellington (Mr. McMullen) with regard to 
     <lb/>
     colonisation companies in the North-West, for I have 
     <lb/>
     some experience up there, and I know something about 
     <lb/>
     the condition of things in the Territories. Let me tell the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman that the two colonisation companies in the 
     <lb/>
     district of Alberta have been a great benefit to the country, 
     <lb/>
     instead, as he would try to make out, an injury and a dis<lb break="no"/>advantage. There are only two companies in operation at 
     <lb/>
     the present time in the North-West, as the lands held by 
     <lb/>
     the others have been thrown open, but I can say that these 
     <lb/>
     two companies have been a boon to that section of the 
     <lb/>
     country. The hon. gentleman has spoken of the expenses 
     <lb/>
     incurred in connection with the administration of affairs in 
     <lb/>
     the North-West and it is a subject which he has been con<lb break="no"/>stantly growling about in this House. It has got to be a 
     <lb/>
     chestnut with the hon. member and I have heard him sing<lb break="no"/>ing the same old song for the last three years. If we ask 
     <lb/>
     for the expenditure of public money up there it is because 
     <lb/>
     we need it to develop our great country, and whatever is 
     <lb/>
     expended on us now is in asense only borrowed money, for 
     <lb/>
     <choice><sic>n</sic><corr>in</corr></choice> a few years we will be able to pay it back to the <choice><sic>Dom<lb break="no"/>nion</sic><corr>Dominion</corr></choice> Treasury one hundred fold. The hon. member has 
     <lb/>
     
            <cb/>
          
     spoken of the high salaries paid to Dominion land agents. 
     <lb/>
     They get the small sum of $1,200 a year each and when a 
     <lb/>
     man has to board himself out of that in the Territories it 
     <lb/>
     cannot be considered in any sense a high salary. Why, we 
     <lb/>
     have to pay a cowboy $600 a year and board him into the 
     <lb/>
     bargain, and if he is a first class man we have to pay him 
     <lb/>
     $1,800 a year and board him too. Talk about $1,200 a year to 
     <lb/>
     a Dominion land agent who must be an educated and in<lb break="no"/>telligent man, who knows the country, when we have to pay 
     <lb/>
     sometimes nearly double that to a good cowboy. I should say 
     <lb/>
     that the Government ought raise the salaries of the land 
     <lb/>
     agents to $1,500 a year and then it would look more like de<lb break="no"/>cent pay. The hon. gentleman has also spoken of the Office 
     <lb/>
     expenses of those registry offices. What does he want to 
     <lb/>
     do with them? Does he want to close them all up and let 
     <lb/>
     them take care of themselves? I suppose that would be his 
     <lb/>
     remedy and that would be his policy to bring population 
     <lb/>
     and settlers into the North-West Territories. There is 
     <lb/>
     another matter to which I wish to call the attention of hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen opposite who are constantly complaining in this 
     <lb/>
     House about the expense of feeding the Indians. I have 
     <lb/>
     lived a good while in the North-West and know more 
     <lb/>
     about the Indians than some of the hon. gentlemen who 
     <lb/>
     pretend to dictate to us the way in which we should treat 
     <lb/>
     them. Let me tell those members that they will find it a 
     <lb/>
     great deal cheaper to feed the small number of Indians that 
     <lb/>
     we are feeding at the present time than to have constantly 
     <lb/>
     a row on our hands. It is a good deal easier to feed the 
     <lb/>
     Indians than to fight them, a fact which they have learned 
     <lb/>
     in the United States, and of which they have bitter experi<lb break="no"/>ence. I shall not take up the time of this House further 
     <lb/>
     on this question. There are other matters effecting the 
     <lb/>
     interests of the North-West which will be brought to the 
     <lb/>
     attention of Parliament and the members interested in that 
     <lb/>
     district will probably have an opportunity of referring to 
     <lb/>
     them again. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. I do not propose to occupy the time 
     <lb/>
     of the House with any lengthened remarks on this subject 
     <lb/>
     to-night, because I think several opportunities will be 
     <lb/>
     afforded before the close of the Session for dealing with 
     <lb/>
     almost every subject touched on by hon. gentlemen today. 
     <lb/>
     I think, by this time the House will have found out that there 
     <lb/>
     is more than one "funnel" through which we can obtain 
     <lb/>
     very valuable and interesting information, with regard to 
     <lb/>
     North-West matters. I am sure, we feel very much in<lb break="no"/>debted to the hon. member for West Assiniboia (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Davin) for bringing up these questions, and not only making 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentlemen acquainted With the resolutions passed by 
     <lb/>
     the Legislative Assembly last autumn, but affording an op<lb break="no"/>portunity for an expression of views by hon. gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     who are interested in our western country, and giving 
     <lb/>
     myself and the Government an opportunity for giving a 
     <lb/>
     greater and more intelligent consideration to the several 
     <lb/>
     matters included in his resolution. The hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
               went over these resolutions <hi rendition="simple:italic">seriatim</hi>; but I do not think an 
     <lb/>
     extended reply will be expected from me, because hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen are aware, that all these memorials are now 
     <lb/>
     under the cousideration of the Government, and the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment's reply to them, will in a very short time be for<lb break="no"/>warded to the Lieutenant Governor for the information of 
     <lb/>
     his Legislative Assembly. The hon. gentleman was kind 
     <lb/>
     enough, in connection with the resolution which 
     <lb/>
     he considered of great importance, the prohibition 
     <lb/>
     resolution, to say, that he sympathised with me dur<lb break="no"/>ing the years that the permit system was placed 
     <lb/>
     under my control. All I can say in reference to that 
     <lb/>
     is that I did not find the duty a very pleasant one, and 
     <lb/>
     I sympathise with my successor who is now in my shoes in 
     <lb/>
     dealing with it. I shall only be too glad to see some change 
     <lb/>
     made in that respect. As I said to my constituents last 
     <lb/>
     autumn when addressing them, I do not care much what 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="383" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-28_Page_00383.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num"><choice><sic>382</sic><corr>383</corr></choice></fw>
            
     change may be made, because I think no change can be 
     <lb/>
     made that will not be an improvement on the present 
     <lb/>
     system. During the seven years that I occupied the position 
     <lb/>
     of Lieutenant Governor, I carried out the duties connected 
     <lb/>
     with that disagreeable portion of my office to the best of 
     <lb/>
     my ability; and in looking back over those years, I do not 
     <lb/>
     consider that if I had to perform those duties over again, I 
     <lb/>
     could perform them with greater justice or conscientious<lb break="no"/>ness than I did. In regard to another important matter 
     <lb/>
     which has been referred to by my hon. friend from 
     <lb/>
     Saskatchewan (Mr. Macdowall), namely, the appeal made 
     <lb/>
     on behalf of the half-breeds, I may say that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment are giving very serious attention to that matter, and 
     <lb/>
     I am sure that they feel inclined to do all they possibly can 
     <lb/>
     to carry out the views expressed by my hon. friends from the 
     <lb/>
     North West. With regard to the appeals also made on behalf 
     <lb/>
     of the scouts and the Mounted Police who were engaged dur<lb break="no"/>ing the rebellion, for scrip, that is a matter which it appears 
     <lb/>
     to me should receive the favorable consideration of the 
     <lb/>
     Government, and I shall exercise what little influence I 
     <lb/>
     have to bring about the wishes of my hon. friend. With 
     <lb/>
     regards to the remarks of the hon. member for North Nor<lb break="no"/>folk (Mr. Charlton), I may say that I do not agree with 
     <lb/>
     him in the views he has expressed with regard to our land 
     <lb/>
     laws. The hon. member for Selkirk (Mr. Daly) spoke very 
     <lb/>
     freely on that subject, when I think my hon. friend from 
     <lb/>
     Norfolk was not in the House, stating that on several occa<lb break="no"/>sions he has differed from the hon. gentleman on the subject 
     <lb/>
     of our land laws as compared with those of the United 
     <lb/>
     States. He, as well as some other hon. members, consider our 
     <lb/>
     land laws as liberal if not more liberal than those of the 
     <lb/>
     United States. However, I am not as well acquainted with 
     <lb/>
     those laws as the hon. gentleman opposite; but it does 
     <lb/>
     appear to me very singular that hon. gentlemen should 
     <lb/>
     differ so much in that respect. One feature of the United 
     <lb/>
     States land regulations may be more liberal than ours, 
     <lb/>
     for while within the railway belt, some 50 to 80 miles 
     <lb/>
     on each side of the railway, what is known as the 
     <lb/>
     chequer-board system is adopted, outside this belt a settler 
     <lb/>
     can homestead on every quarter-section. That may be 
     <lb/>
     better than our policy, and I do not see how our 
     <lb/>
     policy can be improved except as suggested by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Marquette (Mr. Watson) by giving land grants 
     <lb/>
     to railways in alternate townships instead of in alternate 
     <lb/>
     sections. I agree with him in that entirely, and I may say 
     <lb/>
     that the Government in dealing with any application made 
     <lb/>
     to them are acting upon that view, and in future when any 
     <lb/>
     land grants are given, they will be given in that way. The 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for North Wellington (Mr. McMullen) and 
     <lb/>
     several other members have diverged a good deal from 
     <lb/>
     what I expected would be the line of the debate. That hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman came loaded with figures which I was not quite 
     <lb/>
     able to follow, and which I am not able at present to con<lb break="no"/>trovert. I may say that I was also loaded up with figures, 
     <lb/>
     but unfortunately I have left my gun behind me. But I 
     <lb/>
     differ from the hon. gentleman in the conclusions he has 
     <lb/>
     arrived at, and I hope to take some other opportunity of 
     <lb/>
     giving a comparison as to the cost of management of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West under the present Government with the cost 
     <lb/>
     during the years the hon. gentleman's friends were in 
     <lb/>
     power. I can show him that our management has been 
     <lb/>
     infinitely more economical than theirs. Now the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for South Norfolk stated that he thought that our 
     <lb/>
     policy had been wrong in not putting up to competition coal 
     <lb/>
     lauds, pasture lands and timber lands. Well, we have a very 
     <lb/>
     large coal area, and I am not aware that there is any great 
     <lb/>
     demand or rush for those coal lands, and I do not think that 
     <lb/>
     if they were put up at auction we would derive more benefit 
     <lb/>
     from them than we do now. It requires very large capital 
     <lb/>
     to enter into the coal mining enterprise, and for that reason 
     <lb/>
     there is not avery great demand in that direction. Our 
     <lb/>
     coal area is of immense extent, and the coal is a very 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     valuable commodity, which should be carefully handled and 
     <lb/>
     protected, and in whatever we do our great aim should be 
     <lb/>
     to have it worked as economically as possible, and get it 
     <lb/>
     into the hands of the settlers at as cheap a rate as possible. 
     <lb/>
     I intend to take measures similar to those taken in the 
     <lb/>
     United States in order to prevent any monopoly of our coal 
     <lb/>
     deposits, and will bring in an amendment to this effect 
     <lb/>
     when dealing with our Lands Act. With regard to our 
     <lb/>
     ranche lands, I do not think, if they were put up at auction, 
     <lb/>
     we should derive any more financial benefit from them 
     <lb/>
     than we do the policy, when leases were first established, 
     <lb/>
     was to induce ranchemen to bring capital into the country 
     <lb/>
     in order to start the cattle industry there. The price 
     <lb/>
     we have obtained for those leases has not been extravagant, 
     <lb/>
     but a great many of those who have leases are not paying 
     <lb/>
     their rent, and I do not think they intend paying it, as they 
     <lb/>
     do not consider the privileges they derive from their leases 
     <lb/>
     sufficient to induce them to pay their rent. I do not think 
     <lb/>
     if we were to put those ranches up at auction that we would 
     <lb/>
     get any greater benefit from them than we do. As regards 
     <lb/>
     timber limits, no doubt the hon. gentleman knows that for 
     <lb/>
     some years past they have been put up at competition. 
     <lb/>
     With regard to the land law generally, in which of late I 
     <lb/>
     have taken special interest, I feel very much in the same 
     <lb/>
     way as do my colleagues in the North-West. I am an 
     <lb/>
     anxious as they are that we should do all we can in the in<lb break="no"/>terest of the settlers. In all new countries, whether mining 
     <lb/>
     or agricultural, the early pioneer is the one who has to face 
     <lb/>
     the greatest difficulties, and the one we ought to protect 
     <lb/>
     and assist as much as possible. I was glad to hear from 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member from Marquette and others that the inter<lb break="no"/>view we had this morning in regard to matters generally 
     <lb/>
     in the North-West was satisfactory, and that some 
     <lb/>
     conclusions I had arrived at were satisfactory to those 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentlemen. I shall be always willing at any 
     <lb/>
     time to receive their suggestions and do my share 
     <lb/>
     in bringing about any changes which will be in the 
     <lb/>
     interests of the settlers. It is hardly the time for me 
     <lb/>
     to answer the hon. member from North Wellington. I 
     <lb/>
     may say that my impression is that the officials are not 
     <lb/>
     overpaid, and I may tell the hon. gentleman that I had this 
     <lb/>
     morning an appeal from the members of the west who 
     <lb/>
     waited upon me, and who certainly know what they are 
     <lb/>
     talking about, to increase the salaries of certain officials in 
     <lb/>
     the North-West Territories. I do not think I need detain 
     <lb/>
     the House longer except to thank my hon. friend from 
     <lb/>
     Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) for bringing this matter up, and 
     <lb/>
     giving me an opportunity of hearing the different views of 
     <lb/>
     hon gentlemen, which will be of great assistance to the 
     <lb/>
     Government in coming to a conclusion on the subject under 
     <lb/>
     discussion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>