<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1896-02-17"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1896-02-17">17 February 1896</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, Sixth Session</title>.
          <date when="1896"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1871" to="1888"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01871.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01873.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01875.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01877.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01879.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01881.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01883.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01885.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01887.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-10">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-10">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01871">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01871.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01873">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01873.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01875">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01875.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01877">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01877.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01879">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01879.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01881">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01881.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01883">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01883.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01885">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01885.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01887">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01887.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1871" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01871.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1871</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1872</fw>
           
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">THE NORTHWEST TERRITORIES.</head>
            
            
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Mr. Speaker, the motion 
     <lb/>
     which I have on the paper is one that 1 hope 
     <lb/>
     the House will rcgard at this time as special<lb break="no"/>ly appropriate : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That it is necessary to (1) the prosperity and 
     <lb/>
     progress of the North-west Territories, important 
     <lb/>
    to the stability and progress of the Dominion, 
     <lb/>and of great moment to the Empire that the 
     <lb/>North-west Territories shall be treated on a dif<lb break="no"/>ferent footing from that heretofore ; (2) That 
     <lb/>the self-respect of the people of the North-west, 
     <lb/>not less than the material interests of those vast<lb/>territories demands that the Territories shall not 
     <lb/>be treated on a plane of inferiority ; (3) That the 
     <lb/>climate, soil and conditions generally of the 
     <lb/>North-west are different from those of other parts 
     <lb/>of Canada, and a policy specially adapted to its 
     <lb/>needs and resources is called for in order that 
     <lb/>the settlers shall be rendered prosperous and 
     <lb/>immigration policies be made effective. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). That is a vote of 
     <lb/>
    want of confidence in the Minister of the 
     <lb/>Interior (Mr. Daly). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. My friend the member for 
     <lb/>
     Bothwell says this is a vote of want of con<lb break="no"/>fidence in the Minister of the Interior. I 
     <lb/>
     beg to say that it is nothing of the kind. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). The vote has not 
     <lb/>
     come yet. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Mr. Speaker, in the earlier 
     <lb/>
     clauses of this motion I refer to our treat<lb break="no"/>ment: of the North-west Territories ever 
     <lb/>
     since we had anything to do with them. I 
     <lb/>
     consider that we shall have to take the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories more seriously than 
     <lb/>
     we have done. We have seen in the papers 
     <lb/>
     —and it has even been brought before the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the Empire—evidence of the 
     <lb/>
     readiness of the authorities at Washington, 
     <lb/>
     on occasion, to put on, or pretend to put 
     <lb/>
     on, their war paint. A short time ago we had 
     <lb/>
     a reference made to the attitude of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of the United States and to the position 
     <lb/>
     of England, and that reference has attract<lb break="no"/>ed widespread attention. When the people 
     <lb/>
     of the United States talk about difficulties 
     <lb/>
     with England, they are not thinking of petty 
     <lb/>
     disputes connected with bickering republics 
     <lb/>
     in South America. They are thinking of Can<lb break="no"/>ada, and when they think of Canada, they are 
     <lb/>
     thinking of the North-west Territories and 
     <lb/>
     of Manitoba. We have had, as I have stated 
     <lb/>
     in this House before, visits to the North<lb break="no"/>west from prominent American statesmen; 
     <lb/>
   
   
            <cb/>
      
      
     and the impression these vast territories, 
     <lb/>with millions of arable acres, has made upon<lb/>them, has been such as to wake them from<lb/>the indifference with which they have re<lb break="no"/>garded Canada generally, especially the<lb/>North-west. A Mr. Thompson has published<lb/>an essay in one of the American magazines<lb/>in which he gives an account of a visit he<lb/>made to the Territories in 1895. He stopped<lb/>at Regina, stopped at Calgary, went up to<lb/>Edmonton, and made, if I may say so, a lit-<lb break="yes"/>early survey of the country ; and what did<lb/>he do when he went back ? He quoted<lb/>official utterances on the part of the United<lb/>States officials as to the unimportance of the <lb/>North-west Territories and Manitoba, and<lb/>told his countrymen through this magazine,<lb/>that they were entirely mistaken-that Can<lb break="no"/>ada had more than half of North America,<lb/>and had to-day fertile regions stretching<lb/>over the North-west Territories equal to<lb/>seven or eight or nine of the greatest and<lb/>most fertile states of the Union. Mr. Speak<lb break="no"/>er, int eh " Evening Journal." published in<lb/>this city, there appeared on the 15th in<lb break="no"/>stant a leading article, the writer of which<lb/>copied a long letter from an American doc<lb break="no"/>tor. I think in Philadelphia, which appeared<lb/>in the London " Time." This gentleman<lb/>argues that it is for the good of hu<lb break="no"/>manity generally, especially for the food<lb/>of this continent and its peace, that<lb/>the United States should wake up from<lb/>their indifference and take Canada in hand.<lb/>Now, the same writer, Mr. Thompson, points<lb/>out that the waste lands of the United<lb/>States have all been taken up. They are<lb/>no longer these vast extents of fertile ter<lb break="no"/>ritory which that country formerly had ;<lb/>there are no longer fields for their restless<lb/>spirits to go to, and they are becoming<lb/>anxious ; and there cannot be the least<lb/>doubt that it would be a solution of one of<lb/>the most difficult problems that concern the<lb/>United States at present, if, by any pos<lb break="no"/>sible arrangement, they could get hold of<lb/>the vast territory which we posses. The<lb/>reason why I give so wife a bearing to this<lb/>question is my belief that the future of the<lb/>Dominion, and perhaps the strength of the<lb/>whole Empire, is involved in our treatment<lb/>of the North-west Territories. I say that the<lb/>prosperity and progress of the North-west<lb/>Territories demand that they be treated<lb/>differently. They have been treated too<lb/>much on this line- that all you had to do<lb/>was to open up the country, send railways<lb/>in there, dot it with post offices, five it<lb/>telegraph and postal commun cation, and<lb/>give it a large share of provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and that would be sufficient in the<lb/>past, and I am certain that it is not at pre<lb break="no"/>sent. There is one feature of our dealing<lb/>with the North-west Territories which we<lb/>shall have, in my opinion, to revolutionize.<lb/>I mean the feature of immigration into these<lb/>territories. The hon. member for Bothwell<lb/>
    (Mr. Mills) has said that this is a vote of 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <pb n="1873" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01873.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1873</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 17, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">1874</fw>
      
      
     want of confidence in my hon. friend the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of the Interior (Mr. Daly). When 
     <lb/>
     that hon. gentleman took charge of the In<lb break="no"/>terior Department, he told us that he was 
     <lb/>
     going to give us a vigorous immigration 
     <lb/>
     policy ; and some people, both in the news<lb break="no"/>papers and out of them, have charged that 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman's policy was not as 
     <lb/>
     vigorous as he promised and as we desired. 
     <lb/>
     But, Mr. Speaker, I am bound to say that 
     <lb/>
     the Parliament of Canada did not give my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend the means of prosecuting such a 
     <lb/>
     vigorous immigration policy as we expect<lb break="no"/>ed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Yes, but he has a majority 
     <lb/>
     in Parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI10">Mr. DAVIS</persName>. My hon. friend from Ottawa 
     <lb/>
     County says that he has a majority in Par<lb break="no"/>liament, but if he will look back to the de<lb break="no"/>bates in this House he will find—I do not 
     <lb/>
     know whether he was guilty in that par<lb break="no"/>ticular or not—that hon. members on the 
     <lb/>
     opposite side have always denounced the 
     <lb/>
     amount of money that was expended on im<lb break="no"/>migration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MARTIN</persName>. Because it was wasted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. That is a point into which 
     <lb/>
     I cannot go just now : but I have heard 
     <lb/>
     criticisms in this House on immigration ex<lb break="no"/>penditure that did not bear on the question 
     <lb/>
     of waste at all, but were confined to the 
     <lb/>
     preposition that the amount put down in the 
     <lb/>
     Estimates was altogether too large a sum 
     <lb/>
     for such a purpose. What we want there<lb break="no"/>fore—and I should like to know if my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend from Ottawa. County (Mr. Devlin) will 
     <lb/>
     support me in this—is to have a far larger 
     <lb/>
     sum spent on immigration. My hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     the leader of the Opposition has frequently 
     <lb/>
     denounced the millions which he said had 
     <lb/>
     been spent within the last fifteen years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. But the more millions 
     <lb/>
     you spend, the less immigrants you get. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. No, immigration is a busi<lb break="no"/>ness like any other. If you put capital into 
     <lb/>
     it and manage that capital properly, you 
     <lb/>
     will have results. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. It has been very badly 
     <lb/>
     managed then. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I shall not go into that just 
     <lb/>
     now. because that would belong to more pro<lb break="no"/>perly to a motion dealing with the adminis<lb break="no"/>tration of the vote for immigration, and 
     <lb/>
     that is not my purpose here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. McMULLEN</persName>. Nor anywhere else ? 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName> My hon. frlend from Wel<lb break="no"/>lington (Mr. McMullen), who has been very 
     <lb/>quite this session, remarks that it is not my 
     <lb/>purpose to do so anywhere else. I hope that 
     <lb/>we shall hear from the hon. gentleman in 
     <lb/>this debate. He. has been very quite. I 
     <lb/>rather think that his financial critical 
     <lb/>sphere has been narrowed by his leaders 
     <lb/>this session lest he might prove too injurious 
     <lb/>
      
      
            <cb/>
       
       
     to them. Suppose we go on in the North<lb break="no"/>west as we have been going on. Suppose 
     <lb/>
     we only increase there in the ratio we have 
     <lb/>
     increased ; the result will be that ten or 
     <lb/>
     twenty years will pass, and yet the North<lb break="no"/>west will not have its farms of 160 acres 
     <lb/>
     each, each containing a family, and what 
     <lb/>
     would be the result? It would be that the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories will not be the, 
     <lb/>
     strength to Canada that they might be 
     <lb/>
     otherwise, nor the strength to the Empire 
     <lb/>
     which they should be. I lay stress on this. 
     <lb/>
     I say that if you are to fill up these Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories with an English. a Scandinavian, a 
     <lb/>
     Scotch and an Irish population. let us have 
     <lb/>
     them filled rapidly, and any vaporings about 
     <lb/>
     annexation may he laughed to scorn. In 
     <lb/>
     fact, I believe that any such vaporings may 
     <lb/>
     he laughed to scorn to—day. But, sir, there 
     <lb/>
     is a great opportunity before our Parliament 
     <lb/>
     and Government at present with regard to 
     <lb/>
    out North—west Territories. That oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity is this. The English people are 
     <lb/>thoroughly awake just new to the importance 
     <lb/>of the colonies. The opinion which obtained 
     <lb/>some twenty-five years ago, that the colonies 
     <lb/>were of little importance, is now at a dis<lb break="no"/>count, the English people are thoroughly 
     <lb/>awake to, the importance of their colonies, 
     <lb/>and the notion of an Imperial Zollverein 
     <lb/>has undoubtedly made considerable pro<lb break="no"/>gress. I believe that in the mood in which 
     <lb/>England is at present, you ought to be able 
     <lb/>to get the statesmen of England to join 
     <lb/>with the statesmen of Canada in a great 
     <lb/>immigration scheme. If you do this. if you 
     <lb/>turn the tide of immigration to the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories, if you do not Confine your<lb break="no"/>self, to the stray efforts made by charitable 
     <lb/>associations and the scanty efforts that can 
     <lb/>be made on the small sums hitherto voted 
     <lb/>by Parliament. we would get a considerably 
     <lb/>larger immigration from England than we 
     <lb/>have had in the past. Then, Sir, if a larger 
     <lb/>scheme be entered into, we ought tohe able 
     <lb/>larger immigiation from Scandi<lb break="no"/>navia than we have had and a far larger 
     <lb/>immigiation from Germany , and under 
     <lb/>those circumstances. I think that the first 
     <lb/>part of my resolution should commend it<lb break="no"/>self to the House, namely, that it is of great 
     <lb/>importance to the stability and progress of 
     <lb/>the Dominion, and of great moment to the 
     <lb/>Empire. that the North-west Territories be 
     <lb/>treated on a different footing from 
     <lb/>that which has obtained heretofore. In 
     <lb/>1891, or perhaps in 1890. I brought before 
     <lb/>this House a scheme for irrigation. Since 
     <lb/>my hon. friend (Mr. Daly) has 
     <lb/>passed an admirable Bill—he was notthen 
     <lb/>Minister ofthe Interior—dealing with irriga<lb break="no"/>tion, and the settlers of Alberta have made 
     <lb/>use of it. When I brought forward that 
     <lb/>scheme, I remember the then Minister of 
     <lb/>the Interior complained that I was casting 
     <lb/>doubt upon theNorth—west Territories as a 
     <lb/>fertile country. I need hardly say there 
     <lb/>was not much likelihood of my casting any 
     <lb/>doubt upon the North-west Territories as a 
     <lb/>
          
          
            <pb n="1875" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01875.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1875</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1876</fw>
         
         
     fertile country. But what I said, and what 
     <lb/>
     has since been proved in Alberta, and what 
     <lb/>
     has been proved up to the handle in the 
     <lb/>
    United States was that you can get no bet<lb break="no"/>ter result from any land in the world or by 
     <lb/>any system of cultivation than you get from 
     <lb/>that soil than by means of irrigation. Irri<lb break="no"/>gation makes you independent of the varia<lb break="no"/>tions of the seasons. In other parts of the 
     <lb/>North-west, in all parts of Assiniboia, where-<lb break="yes"/>ever we have had a partial failure of the 
     <lb/>crops, it has been due to drought. There 
     <lb/>is no part of the Territories where an 
     <lb/>abounding crop cannot be secured, year 
     <lb/>after year, if you have sufficient moisture. 
     <lb/>In India, among other systems, they have 
     <lb/>in the dry parts, far from rivers, a system 
     <lb/>of irrigation by means of wells. These 
     <lb/>wells are found to produce an enormous 
     <lb/>amount of fertility. In some parts of the, 
     <lb/>United States, also, a system of irrigation 
     <lb/>by means of wells, has been introduced. 
     <lb/>Windmills are employed to pump up the 
     <lb/>water all the time, the water being dis<lb break="no"/>tributed in troughs, and thence, through 
     <lb/>smaller troughs, to all parts of the land. 
     <lb/>The proposition I made in 1891 was this— 
     <lb/>that the Government of Canada, which had 
     <lb/>great advantages because it had complete 
     <lb/>power, should take into its own hands the 
     <lb/>providing of means of irrigation where it 
     <lb/>was known that the land was fertile, but 
     <lb/>where it was also known that the rainfall 
     <lb/>was not sufficient. There are parts of As<lb break="no"/>siniboia where we have farms, the occu<lb/>pants of which have to go great distances 
     <lb/>for water. Now, I hold that money appro<lb break="no"/>priated for irrigation purposes could not 
     <lb/>be better spent than by providing water 
     <lb/>for these farmers. not exactly at their doors. 
     <lb/>but contiguous to their farms. If this were 
     <lb/>done, on every farm you would have a man 
     <lb/>sending letters abroad telling of abundant 
     <lb/>crops year after year, and of a condition 
     <lb/>of things enabling him to despise the muta<lb break="no"/>tions of the seasons. There is another point. 
     <lb/>one that, probably, would not commend it<lb break="no"/>self to free traders or revenue tariffists, but 
     <lb/>that would commend itself to those of us 
     <lb/>who believe in protection, and who are not 
     <lb/>afraid of the sneers against " paternalism." 
     <lb/>I believe that there are parts of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories where we ought to aid the<lb/>farmers, through helping little bodies of<lb/>farmers in establishign creameries where<lb/>they are not able to do so themselves. Some<lb/>assistance should be given, but not exactly<lb/>in the form I suggested before. Some as<lb break="no"/>sistance was given some years ago in one<lb/>part of my own district, and the result has<lb/>been most gratifying; it has been such as<lb/>to justify the Government in the course<lb/>they took at that time. The second clause<lb/>of the resolutions is this:<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>(2) That the self-respect oi the people of the
<lb/>North-west, not less than the material interests
<lb/>of those vast territories demands that the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories shall not be treated on a plane of in<lb break="no"/>feriority.<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p></quote>
            


            <cb/>
            <p>
     I think it was in 1880 that I proposed that 
     <lb/>
     we should have full responsible government 
     <lb/>
     for the Territories; and what was done 
     <lb/>
     then was to pass a Bill—my late illustrious 
     <lb/>
     leader, the Right Honourable Sir John A. 
     <lb/>
     Macdonald was leading the Government, 
     <lb/>
     and it was his Bill—which gave us a small 
     <lb/>
     advisory board. And now we have a finan<lb break="no"/>cial committee. which has not the right to 
     <lb/>
     advise the governor on any subject but 
     <lb/>
     finance. The powers of the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories are, I think, with the exception of 
     <lb/>
     one or two items, coextensive with those of 
     <lb/>
     a province. But, for what reason, I never 
     <lb/>
     could make out, we hesitate to give full re<lb break="no"/>sponsible government to the Territories. 
     <lb/>
     The result of giving full responsible gov<lb break="no"/>ernment would be to set that giant, the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories, upon its mettle. It 
     <lb/>
     is just as important, for instance, as British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia—much more important from one 
     <lb/>
     point of view— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. PRIOR</persName>. Query. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. From one point of view. 
     <lb/>
     My hon. friend may be quite certain that I 
     <lb/>
     would not disparage the importance of any 
     <lb/>
     part of Canada to Canada at large. I know 
     <lb/>
     full well the importance of that magnifi<lb break="no"/>cent province of the Pacific. But what I 
     <lb/>
     say is that there is no part of Canada so 
     <lb/>
     important at this hour to Canada as the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories, with their boundless 
     <lb/>
     fertile acres awaiting the plough of the 
     <lb/>
     immigrant. If provincial government be 
     <lb/>
     good for the provinces, why should it not 
     <lb/>
     be good for the North-west Territories ? 
     <lb/>
     We have a population—again to refer to the 
     <lb/>
     Pacific province—as large as that of British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia. That is shown by the last cen<lb break="no"/>sus. And we have more fertile land than 
     <lb/>
     any province or any two provinces in Can<lb break="no"/>ada. We have vast resources, mineral and 
     <lb/>
     agricultural, as well as resources of the 
     <lb/>
     forest, and the fishery. The same principle 
     <lb/>
     that leads us, as federalists, to give power 
     <lb/>
     to the province to deal with its own affairs, 
     <lb/>
     should lead us to give similar powers to the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories. Local self-govern<lb break="no"/>ment is based upon the principle that if you 
     <lb/>
     have Ministers on the spot who are close<lb break="no"/>ly interested in the local affairs, and have<lb/>much better opportunities to manage those<lb/>affairs wisely than persons at a distance,<lb/>things will in a large sphere of civil gov<lb break="no"/>ernment be better done. There is also the<lb/>
    principle of the division of labour. We 
     <lb/>divide the work of the government in 
     <lb/>this country. We find that the provin<lb break="no"/>ces can do the purely provincial work 
     <lb/>better than it could be done here in 
     <lb/>Ottawa, and, of course, we are able 
     <lb/>to do the work that is allotted to us better 
     <lb/>than if it were scattered over five or six de 
     <lb/>partments. in five or six different parts of 
     <lb/>Canada. What we want, therefore, in my 
     <lb/>opinion, and in the opinion of the most 
     <lb/>thoughtful people in the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, is that the last link be given; we 
     <lb/>
          
          
            <pb n="1877" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01877.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1877</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 17, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">1878</fw>
      
      
     want to have the additional power that is 
     <lb/>
     necessary to cover the whole field of provin<lb break="no"/>cial functions, and we want to have the Min<lb break="no"/>isters, as we virtually have at present. We 
     <lb/>
     have my friend Mr. Haultain, who is called 
     <lb/>
     the Premier ; he is chairman of the execu<lb break="no"/>tive. He has got another colleague, paid as 
     <lb/>
     much as a Minister, and he is a member of 
     <lb/>
     the executive. These, with two other gentle<lb break="no"/>men, are a committee of the House chosen by 
     <lb/>
     the House, to advise His Honour on financial 
     <lb/>
     questions. The result is, that instead of hav<lb break="no"/>ing a little executive responsible to the as<lb break="no"/>sembly, and responsible to the people of the 
     <lb/>
     North-west, you have a committee appointed 
     <lb/>
     to spend the money that we give them a 
     <lb/>
     committee appointed by the assembly really 
     <lb/>
     to spend that money, as it is directed by the 
     <lb/>
     assembly. And what is the consequence of 
     <lb/>
     that? The consequence is, that the system 
     <lb/>
     of log-rolling still prevails. Now, Mr. Speak<lb break="no"/>er, my friend Mr. Haultain, who is chairman 
     <lb/>
     of the executive, promised that he would 
     <lb/>
     get out of that : he promised that he 
     <lb/>
     would certainly give that up, and a step 
     <lb/>
     has been taken in the way of focussing the 
     <lb/>
     responsibility. But I cannot think that you 
     <lb/>
     can have the expenditure of money, say, for 
     <lb/>
     public works, placed in a satisfactory posi<lb break="no"/>tion, unless you have men as a body re<lb break="no"/>sponsible to the assembly, and who shall 
     <lb/>
     hold that responsible position in face of the 
     <lb/>
     electors of the country. Under these circum<lb break="no"/>stances, the result will be that you will have 
     <lb/>
     what seems to be necessary to our system 
     <lb/>
     of government, you will have the politicians, 
     <lb/>
     the people who take an interest in the affairs 
     <lb/>
     of that country, divided into parties. No<lb break="no"/>body is more sensible than I am of the evils 
     <lb/>
     that can gather around party government 
     <lb/>
     But all things are capable of degenerating 
     <lb/>
     into abuses. We cannot find anything in our 
     <lb/>
     human affairs that cannot be abused, and I 
     <lb/>
     cannot see how it is possible to work our 
     <lb/>
     constitution without having paities. In fact, 
     <lb/>
     we see from the management of affairs up 
     <lb/>
     there, that, probably, there would be an 
     <lb/>
     economy there would be a real economy, if 
     <lb/>
     there were an opposition, if there were 
     <lb/>
     parties in the House, a regular ministry, 
     <lb/>
     and an opposition to criticise the con<lb break="no"/>duct of that ministry, and criticise its ex<lb break="no"/>penditure. I may say, in passing, that I do 
     <lb/>
     not see why we should not, in the theory of 
     <lb/>
     our constitution, acknowledge patties. It 
     <lb/>
     may be a useful thing to recognize what the 
     <lb/>
     writers call fiction. But, Sir, no fiction that 
     <lb/>
     has become an absolute fiction can be 
     <lb/>
     useful ; in the nature of things it must cease 
     <lb/>
     to be useful. On the other hand, any real 
     <lb/>
     fact. anything that is a controlling fact, as 
     <lb/>
     ' party is, in the government of a country, it 
     <lb/>
     seems to me to be a great affectation on our 
     <lb/>
     part to refuse to acknowledge. Here we are, 
     <lb/>
     framing a constitution, and all the time ig<lb break="no"/>noring one of the great wheels by which the 
     <lb/>
     country is governed. The third clause of 
     <lb/>
     this resolution is :   
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That the climate, soil and conditions generally 
     <lb/>
     of the North-west are different from those of 
     <lb/>
     othe1 parts of Canada, and a policy specially 
     <lb/>
     adapted to its needs and resources is called for 
     <lb/>
     in order that the settlers shall be rendered pros<lb break="no"/>perous and immigration policies be made effec<lb break="no"/>tive. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Now, I forget who it was. when this motion 
     <lb/>
     was read—I believe it was my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     from Queen's. P.E.I., (Mr. Davies)—who 
     <lb/>
     seemed to think the last part, especially, was 
     <lb/>
     a reflection on the immigration policy of my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend the Minister of the Interior. 
     <lb/>
     What I meant was this : That, if you want 
     <lb/>
     to make your immigration policy effective, 
     <lb/>
    you must have the farmer in the North-west 
     <lb/>shaking hands, so to speak, and co-operating 
     <lb/>with your agent in England. If you do that, 
     <lb/>then, in my opinion, you will make that 
     <lb/>circle which will be one of the most effective 
     <lb/>and potent powers to secure your object. 
     <lb/>Not that I condemn in any way the immigra<lb break="no"/>tion policy of this department, for I say that, 
     <lb/>so far as I have been able to judge, my hon. 
     <lb/>friend the Minister of the Interior, with the 
     <lb/>means at his disposal, has done as well in 
     <lb/>securing immigration as any Minister could 
     <lb/>possibly do. But, when I speak of making 
     <lb/>it more effective, I mean that whatever 
     <lb/>efforts are put for and by the immigration 
     <lb/>function of his department, should be sec<lb break="no"/>onded by a contented and prosperous yeo<lb break="no"/>manry in our North-west Territories. Now, 
     <lb/>Sir, to effect all this you will have in my 
     <lb/>opinion, to make a new departure. In fact, 
     <lb/>peculiarities of the conditions in the 
     <lb/>North-west Territories are such that you 
     <lb/>may gain immense results, almost im<lb break="no"/>measurable results. if you only adopt 
     <lb/>wise, paternal policy. Such are the 
     <lb/>peculiarities of that country, and so different 
     <lb/>is it from most European countries, that it 
     <lb/>is not a country into whichyou may invite 
     <lb/>people accustomed to other conditions, and 
     <lb/>then leave them there without any further 
     <lb/>attention. Some of them will succeed when 
     <lb/>brought in in that way ; but what I say is, 
     <lb/>that the true policy wouldbe to exercise an 
     <lb/>interest in the settlers that go, into the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, to devise schemes for the ameliora<lb break="no"/>tion of their condition, and, above all, to see 
     <lb/>that the conditions are supplied that will fit 
     <lb/>the land they settle on, that will fit it year 
     <lb/>after year for producing, to a certainty, a 
     <lb/>good crop. Now, Mr. Speaker, a great bug<lb break="no"/>bear against the North-west Territories used 
     <lb/>to be the frost. Well, I lay this down, that 
     <lb/>the frost is a comparative trifle in the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories. Give moisture, have moist<lb break="no"/>ure any year you like, have moisture in any 
     <lb/>part of the country you like, and, no matter 
     <lb/>how severe the frost, you will have results 
     <lb/>that will enable the farmer to prosper, that 
     <lb/>will enable the farmer to make money, that 
     <lb/>will enable the farmer to have his bacon, 
     <lb/>and his pork, and his flour, and to have all 
     <lb/>the conditions that are necessary to a con<lb break="no"/>tented and prosperous farm life. Well, how 
     <lb/>is it to be done ? I have indicated one scheme 
     <lb/>
       

    

    
            <pb n="1879" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01879.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1879</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1880</fw>
          
          
     that is, in my opinion. of absolute import<lb break="no"/>ance, and that is a scheme of irrigation by 
     <lb/>
    means of wells. That is not new in this 
     <lb/>House. I proposed it before, but it fell on 
     <lb/>deaf ears. In fact, the suggestion of irriga<lb break="no"/>tion at all, when I proposed it in 
     <lb/>1889 or 1890, raised a certain amount 
     <lb/>of resentment in the minds of some 
     <lb/>of my hon. friends. I suggested at that 
     <lb/>time that we should have artesian wells. 
     <lb/>All parts of the country are not fit for ar<lb break="no"/>tesian wells but these palts fit for artesian 
     <lb/>wells can be irrigated in that way most suc<lb break="no"/>cessfully. I remember I gave an instance 
     <lb/>of what I have seen in Dakota. I was rid<lb break="no"/>ing and saw what seemed to be a lake. From 
     <lb/>the conformation of the country it was like 
     <lb/>tht driest prairie country we have, and I 
     <lb/>galloped up to where the lake was, and said   
     <lb/>to a lad  who was attending some cattle: 
     <lb/>You have a fine lake of water there : where 
     <lb/>does it come from and where does it empty ? 
     <lb/>He replied that it was purely artificial. that 
     <lb/>it was from an artesian well, and he directed 
     <lb/>me to where the well was. I rode there, 
     <lb/>and saw a pipe emptying water into a vast 
     <lb/>tank, the overflow passing down the side of 
     <lb/>the hill and in one of the hollows making a 
     <lb/>fine lake, useful for the watering of cattle 
     <lb/>and also for purposes of irrigation. These 
     <lb/>are the courses which I think should be pur<lb break="no"/>sued. Let me make a general proposition. 
     <lb/>In the North-west Territories we have, ac<lb break="no"/>cording to the last census as large a popu<lb break="no"/>lation as British Columbia ; we have an area 
     <lb/>transcending that of any province of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion by many multiples: we have that 
     <lb/>which at the present time is one of the most 
     <lb/>important possessions a country can possess, 
     <lb/>and that is vast fertile plains; we have a 
     <lb/>population that man for man will compare 
     <lb/>with the population of any province of Can<lb break="no"/>ada. What we say is this, and we feel very 
     <lb/>strongly about it—we do not want to be 
     <lb/>treated on any other footing than that on 
     <lb/>which the provinces are treated. We do not 
     <lb/>want, for instance, to have this kind of feel<lb break="no"/>ing: Well. we can treat the North-west in a 
     <lb/>different way from Ontario. Quebec, British 
     <lb/>Columbia or Nova Scotia. The North-west 
     <lb/>wants the same consideration, the same 
     <lb/>means of asserting itself in the federation, 
     <lb/>the same means of making its importance 
     <lb/>felt, and it wants also to be treated with the 
     <lb/>same respect, to have its citizens, the men 
     <lb/>who have thrown in their lot with it and 
     <lb/>identified their lives with its development 
     <lb/>and progress, treated precisely on the same 
     <lb/>plane as the men are treated who live in the 
     <lb/>older provinces. A wholly different sentiment 
     <lb/>from that pervades the minds of all eastern 
     <lb/>politicians, I do not care whether they be<lb break="no"/>long to the Liberal or Conservative party, a 
     <lb/>sentiment that the North-west can be treated 
     <lb/>differently, and that something will do for 
     <lb/>the North-west that would not do for British 
     <lb/>Columbia, Nova Scoria, New Brunswick, On<lb break="no"/>tario or Quebec. We entirely object to that 
     <lb/>attitude we entirely object to that state of 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <cb/>
         
         
     mind. We say that is not respectful to us, 
     <lb/>
     on the contrary it is quite offensive to us: 
     <lb/>
     and we say moreover, although that may be 
     <lb/>
     construed as a social or a civic sentiment 
     <lb/>
     merely, it is closely related to the material 
     <lb/>
    progress of those vast Territories on which 
     <lb/>so much can be built, out of which so much 
     <lb/>can be made for the Dominion of Canada, 
     <lb/>and out of which so much can be made for 
     <lb/>the Empire too. We say it would be a dan<lb break="no"/>gerous and bad thing, vicious in every pos<lb break="no"/>sible way if the people of the Territories, 
     <lb/>now when public opinion is being formed 
     <lb/>there, were deprived of these conditions for<lb/>the production of the sense of dignity which<lb/>exist in other parts of the Dominion. The<lb/>view too much taken in the past has been, 
     <lb/>and it is the view taken in this House—hon.<lb/>gentlemen cannot make any party capital 
     <lb/>out of this—it is the view that has obtained 
     <lb/>in this House, and probably obtains here yet 
     <lb/>—is what I would call the greengrocer view, 
     <lb/>the view of trying to make so much out of it. 
     <lb/>When I hear hon. gentlemen speak about the 
     <lb/>amount spent on the North-west Territories 
     <lb/>and speak of the debt incurred for the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories, they speak as though the 
     <lb/>Territories were not part of Canada, and that 
     <lb/>if the Territories have been brought into ex<lb break="no"/>istence, and are now a great factor in the 
     <lb/>wealth of Canada, the North-west owes that 
     <lb/>to the Dominion ; but I say here that Canada 
     <lb/>owes more to the North-west than the North<lb break="no"/>west owes to Canada. Eastern Canada. On<lb break="no"/>tario, Quebec and other provinces, have open 
     <lb/>ed up the country, and we thank them for 
     <lb/>that. And whom have we mainly to thank 
     <lb/>for opening up the country ? I think a good 
     <lb/>deal of thanks is due to the present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, in regard to which it is said that this is 
     <lb/>a motion of want of confidence. But let it be 
     <lb/>considered for one moment as to what has 
     <lb/>been the result of the expenditure on rail<lb break="no"/>ways going into that country, what has been 
     <lb/>the result of the expenditure in opening up 
     <lb/>that country. You have at the present mo<lb break="no"/>ment areturn of over 50 per cent to the 
     <lb/>wealth of Canada for every $100 spent in 
     <lb/>that country. Take Winnipeg to-day. The 
     <lb/>assessed value of property there is over   $22,<lb break="no"/>000,000, the assessed value of Brandon is 
     <lb/>$5,000,000 or $6,000,000, then there is the as<lb break="no"/>sessed value to Moosomin, Qu'Appelle, Wol<lb break="no"/>seley, Regina, Moose Jaw, Medicine Hat, 
     <lb/>and Calgary right along the line, and leav<lb break="no"/>ing altogether aside the value of the farm,. 
     <lb/>you have in the wealth brought into exist<lb break="no"/>ence in these towns more than 50 per cent 
     <lb/>of the amount that has been Spent in opening 
     <lb/>up the North-west. You talk about the debt. 
     <lb/>The hon. member for South Oxford (Sir 
     <lb/>Richard Cartwright) talks about debt. as 
     <lb/>though going into debt was some great evil. 
     <lb/>Going into debt and spending the money that 
     <lb/>has been obtained is no evil. Spending 
     <lb/>such money wastefully or squandering 
     <lb/>would be a great evil, it is true : but if you 
     <lb/>can borrow money at 3% per cent and invest 
     <lb/>it so as to yield 10, 15, 20 or even 50 per cent, 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <pb n="1881" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01881.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1881</fw> <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 17, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">1882</fw>


       
     as some of our investments are yielding, this 
     <lb/>
     is one of the most advantageous results in 
     <lb/>
     the way of statesmanship the Government 
     <lb/>
     can accomplish. Let me say this about the 
     <lb/>
     debt, that if you will take the debt of Can<lb break="no"/>ada—and I will make this general statement 
     <lb/>
     as hearing on the North-west—for the time 
     <lb/>
     usually taken {or purposes of comparison. 
     <lb/>
     sixteen or seventeen years, if you take the 
     <lb/>
     difference between the debt at that time and 
     <lb/>
     the net debt to-day. and then take the 
     <lb/>
     amount of capital that has been brought in<lb break="no"/>to existence by the expenditure of that debt. 
     <lb/>
     I venture to say that the whole increase will 
     <lb/>
     be wiped out as with a sponge. and a large 
     <lb/>
     asset will still remain. All that is true in 
     <lb/>
     every detail in regard to the North-west. I 
     <lb/>
     must not refer to a past debate. and I need 
     <lb/>
     not, do so : but in the press and in other 
     <lb/>
     quarters I have seen some statements about 
     <lb/>
     the old sections in the North-west Territories 
     <lb/>
     and l have been asked why I did not take 
     <lb/>
     up a question like the settlement of the odd 
     <lb/>
     sections of the country. As early as 1885. 
     <lb/>
    before I was a member of the House. I pro<lb break="no"/>posed a plan to the Government. It is on 
     <lb/>record in the Library and hon. members 
     <lb/>have only to go there and they will see my 
     <lb/>plan. I proposed that' the Government 
     <lb/>should buy back all the land alienated to the 
     <lb/>Canadian Pacific Railway and open all those 
     <lb/>lands to settlement. The six million odd 
     <lb/>acres that were brought back, were, I think. 
     <lb/>bought back at $1.50 per acre. Now , suppose 
     <lb/>that same price were given for what re<lb break="no"/>mains.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. What quantity remains ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I expect there are about<lb/>7,000,000 or 8,000,000 acres still remaining.<lb/>probably more. I maintain that you cannot<lb/>do better than to buy back these odd sec<lb break="no"/>tions and open them for settlement. Here<lb/>is my point : Suppose you open them for<lb/>settlement, and a farmer comes in, and<lb/>brings in his family of four, and they eat and<lb/>drink and travel ; the railway company, in<lb break="no"/>stead of losing by alienating the lands<lb/>which it was holding, at $3 or $3 an acre,<lb/>would be the gainer. I must say, however,<lb/>for the Canadian Pacific Railway, that they<lb/>have been selling lands at a very low figure,<lb/>and no complaint can be brought against<lb/>them on that head. But, however low or<lb/>however high they have been selling, they<lb/>cannot get such a good return for their<lb/>lands, as the return they would get by hav<lb break="no"/>ing a farmer settled there, whose wife and<lb/>children and friends would travel, as well<lb/>as himself. On the other hand, the Gov<lb/>ernment could not invest money better than<lb/>by buying back these lands, because they<lb/>would have the revenue swelled by the in<lb break="no"/>direct taxation on the farmer. Besides that,<lb/>if every settler is worth $1,000, then every<lb/>family of three or four on a farm, would<lb/>add considerably to the wealth of the coun<lb break="no"/>try.<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Mr. Speaker, I proposed this in 1885,<lb/>and if my friend from Guysborough (Mr.<lb/>
          
          
            <cb/>
    

    

      
      Fraser) were here, I would suggest to him 
     <lb/>that he should remember that. I cannot. 
     <lb/>recollect that any member of the Opposition 
     <lb/>took the matter up when I spoke of it be<lb break="no"/>fore ; but a thing has occurred within the 
     <lb/>last, two years that I am very glad of, and 
     <lb/>which has made a great change and a great 
     <lb/>improvement in the temper of this House. 
     <lb/>The hon. gentleman who leads the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion has visited North-west Territories. 
     <lb/>together with my hon. friend from Lincoln 
     <lb/>(Mr. Gibson). and my hon. friend from Ox<lb break="no"/>ford (Mr. Sutherland) and a number of lead<lb break="no"/>ing men in the Reform party. The result 
     <lb/>of that visit has been most gratifying, and, 
     <lb/>in my opinion, most useful. In their 
     <lb/>speeches, whether in or out of this House, 
     <lb/>these gentlemen take a wholly different 
     <lb/>tone in regard to these Territories from 
     <lb/>what they were accustomed to. The fact 
     <lb/>is, that before visiting these Territories, 
     <lb/>they did not realize what they were ; and I 
     <lb/>have. never met a politician, whether of my 
     <lb/>own political thought or not, whoever would  
     <lb/>say that he had any idea what these Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories were until after he had visited them. 
     <lb/>But after visiting there, he never again has 
     <lb/>any doubt as to what a significance these 
     <lb/>Territories have for the people of Canada. 
     <lb/>He knows well that there the battle of our 
     <lb/>national life will be fought and won, and 
     <lb/>that there, also, the greatest battle for the 
     <lb/>Empire can he fought and won. We are 
     <lb/>all of us-at all events in the party to which 
     <lb/>I belong-we are all of us in favour of what 
     <lb/>is called preferential trade within the Em<lb break="no"/>pire. That is nothing more than an Im<lb break="no"/>perial Zollverein. Now, Sir, that idea was 
     <lb/>suggested, I forget how long ago, by Mr. 
     <lb/>Justice Byles, who, when he wrote his book. 
     <lb/>the " Fallacies of Free Trade," was not, I 
     <lb/>think, then on the bench, but was a thought<lb break="no"/>ful, able barrister, in London. Justice Byles 
     <lb/>pointed out how absurd it was for England,<lb/> 
            and how absurd it was for the colonies to<lb/>remain apart, when by an Imperial Zoll<lb break="no"/>verein they could do the greatest possible<lb/>good to themselves, commercially, aye, and<lb/>especially for England, politically, as well<lb/>I say here, that if Canada is to be to the<lb/>Empire what Canada is capable of being,<lb/>those Territories must be filled up. If they<lb/>are not populated, Canada cannot be the<lb/>right arm, as she is capable of being, to the<lb/>Empire. After all, Mr. Speaker, Manitoba<lb/>and the North-west Territories should be <lb/>looked at as one. If you of to the Lake of<lb/>the Woods, and run a diagonal line right up<lb/>to the Yellowhead Pass, you will find that<lb/>all south of that you have got a vast region<lb/>of fertile land, and from five miles on this<lb/>side of the Rockies, right to the foot of the<lb/>Rockies, you have coal fields that are them<lb break="no"/>selves potentialities to the Empire. We<lb/>have the finest coal beds in the world in the<lb/>North-west Territories, we have the finest<lb/>lands in the world and the greatest amount<lb/>of them in the North-west Territories, and<lb/>these are greatly needed for the develop<lb break="no"/>
       
       
            <pb n="1883" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01883.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1883</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1884</fw>
       
       ment of Canada. In fact, they are the great 
     <lb/>
     conditions to the development of a country 
     <lb/>
     like this. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILLMOR</persName>. And you have them. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. We have them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILLMOR</persName>. That is right. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. Why do not the people 
     <lb/>
     go there to develop them ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. That is a very important 
     <lb/>
     question. and let me say in regard to that 
     <lb/>
    " why," if my hon. friend (Mr. Mulock) had 
     <lb/>visited those Territories as I visited them, 
     <lb/>in 1882, and wandered around those fertile 
     <lb/>fields, and dug down eight feet in the rich<lb break="no"/>est loam,— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILLMOR</persName>. Eight feet ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Yes, eight and nine feet of 
     <lb/>
     the richest loam you could dig there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILLMOR</persName>. It would never exhaust 
     <lb/>
     you in the world. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. It would not be exhausted 
     <lb/>
     for many a year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILLMOR</persName>. You could not plough 
     <lb/>
     that ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. In the course of years you 
     <lb/>
     could. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. GILLMOR</persName>. No, you would have to 
     <lb/>
     dig the top off before you could plough it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. My hon. friend employs 
     <lb/>
     words differently from what I do. I like to 
     <lb/>
     hear my hon. friend (Mr. Gillmor) speak. 
     <lb/>
     Unless when he speaks on the tariff, he is 
     <lb/>
     a man of a cheerful turn of mind, but when 
     <lb/>
     he speaks on the tariff, he is the Mrs. Gum<lb break="no"/>midge of the Reform party. My hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     from York (Mr. Mulock) asks the question : 
     <lb/>
     Why are not these lands populated ? What 
     <lb/>
     I say is this : If you had visited these Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories in 1882 you would have thought, as 
     <lb/>
     we all thought, as I dare say my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend from Winnipeg (Mr. Martin) thought, 
     <lb/>
     that these Territories were going to fill up ; 
     <lb/>
     in fact, that the population would flow into 
     <lb/>
     them. That was our opinion, and we were 
     <lb/>
     perfectly certain of it. And now take the 
     <lb/>
     calculations that were made by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     baronet, the Secretary of State, when he 
     <lb/>
     was Finance Minister. These calculations 
     <lb/>
     have been quoted here as though they were 
     <lb/>
     some reproach to him. Take the calcula<lb break="no"/>tions made by my late right honourable 
     <lb/>
     friend Sir John A. Macdonald, as to how 
     <lb/>
     that land would fill up, how many thousands 
     <lb/>
     would be there in 1891, how much 
     <lb/>
    money would be got, and so on, and 
     <lb/>which calculations are quoted in the 
     <lb/>Liberal newspapers, and elsewhere as 
     <lb/>against the Conservative party. Sir, 
     <lb/>I say that the mistakes of calculation 
     <lb/>that were made were mistakes that were in<lb break="no"/>evitable, looking at the conditions of the 
     <lb/>country at that time. No man, I do not care 
     <lb/>
    
    
            <cb/>
        
        
     how pessimistic he was, how gloomy may 
     <lb/>
     have been his mental liver, how prone he 
     <lb/>
     may have been to take a jaundiced view of 
     <lb/>
     things—no man could visit those Territories 
     <lb/>
     in 1882 without believing that, in the course 
     <lb/>
     of ten or fifteen years, there would be mil<lb break="no"/>lions of people there. As the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for Winnipeg (Mr. Martin) and the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for West Huron (Mr. Cameron), who 
     <lb/>
     visited the Territories at that time, know, 
     <lb/>
     you could not visit any part of the world 
     <lb/>
     where the conditions promised more comfort 
     <lb/>
     or more prosperity for the farmer. Was it 
     <lb/>
     not natural. then. that sanguine men should 
     <lb/>
     make the calculations they did ? The atti<lb break="no"/>tude of mind that was shown by Sir 
     <lb/>
     John Macdonald. and by others at that 
     <lb/>
     time, was a natural one. It was sincere. 
     <lb/>
     They thought what everybody else thought. 
     <lb/>
     What made us go up there and invest what 
     <lb/>
    money we had in farm property ? We 
     <lb/>thought people would crowd in. homesteads 
     <lb/>would fill up, and then they would come and 
     <lb/>buy from us the railway lands we had 
     <lb/>bought. Men like Sir Charles Tapper, the 
     <lb/>Secretary of State, and Sir John Macdonald, 
     <lb/>men of sanguine mind, naturally made cal<lb break="no"/>culations roseate with hope. Now, let me 
     <lb/>say this. There was more power in such 
     <lb/>calculations—aye, and more truth—than in 
     <lb/>the gloomy and despairing views taken by 
     <lb/>the hon. gentlemen who opposed them. 
     <lb/>There were two things in these calculations. 
     <lb/>There was, first, power—steam—go-ahead; 
     <lb/>in the next place, they were more true to 
     <lb/>what has taken place since. I heard Mr. 
     <lb/>Blake, I think when he was a member of 
     <lb/>this House—I certainly heard him out of the 
     <lb/>House—calculate that the Canadian Pacific 
     <lb/>Railway, as it was built, was an impossibil<lb break="no"/>ity. We know how, at Aurora he spoke of 
     <lb/>the impossibility of getting through the " sea 
     <lb/>of mountains." I say there was more con<lb break="no"/>sonance with the ultimate fact in the calcu<lb break="no"/>lations of Sir Charles Tupper and Sir John 
     <lb/>Macdonald than in the somewhat gloomy va<lb break="no"/>ticinations of those who opposed them. But, 
     <lb/>Sir, what form did the adverse criticisms 
     <lb/>upon their policy take ? Their opponents 
     <lb/>went about, saying that the building of the 
     <lb/>Canadian Pacific Railway would ruin the 
     <lb/>country. What was the answer ? The an<lb break="no"/>swer was: You will have such and such 
     <lb/>Wealth in return; lands will be sold ; and, 
     <lb/>as Sir John Macdonald pointed out—in 1891, 
     <lb/>I think it was—every cent of the cost of the 
     <lb/>Pacific Railway will have been paid. Well, 
     <lb/>Sir, every cent of the cost of the Pacific 
     <lb/>Railway has been paid, but not in that 
     <lb/>way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. Hear, hear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. My hon. friend laughs. 
     <lb/>
     not expect anything else. They belong to 
     <lb/>
     the spirit that denies. They are a party 
     <lb/>
     wanting in faith. They are a party of poli<lb break="no"/>tical unbelief. They have no confidence 
     <lb/>
     whatever in the future of anything, and they 
     <lb/>
     can only realize that it exists when it actu<lb break="no"/>
          
          
          
            <pb n="1885" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01885.jpg"/>
        <fw type="num">1885</fw>    <fw type="dateline">[FEBRUARY 17, 1896]</fw> <fw type="num">1886</fw>
          
          
     ally comes before them. Well, Mr. Speaker, 
     <lb/>
     what I want to say is this, that the attitude 
     <lb/>
     taken by Sir John Macdonald, in conse<lb break="no"/>quence of these criticisms,continued too long. 
     <lb/>
     I remember when it was determined—I hap<lb break="no"/>pened to be here in Ottawa at the time—de<lb break="no"/>termined, not by Sir John Macdonald, but 
     <lb/>
     by another gentleman, to close up the mile 
     <lb/>
     belt, and to close up Southern Manitoba; 
     <lb/>
     and a man whom we all honoured greatly. 
     <lb/>
     and whose memory we honour in this House, 
     <lb/>
     the late John Henry Pope. who was then 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Agriculture, told me of this, and 
     <lb/>
     said he thought it was a very serious step. 
     <lb/>
     I thought so, too, and I went to the Acting 
     <lb/>
     Minister and tried to argue him out of it: 
     <lb/>
     but I failed to do it, and Southern Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     and the mile belt were closed. It was a 
     <lb/>
     very bad policy. I commenced at once to 
     <lb/>
     attack the policy ; and in the papers down 
     <lb/>
     in the cast I was attacked for attacking the 
     <lb/>
     policy of the Department of the Interior of 
     <lb/>
     that day. To his honour, be it said, the late 
     <lb/>
     Sir John Macdonald, my leader of that day, 
     <lb/>
     wrote to me: " Don't mind these attacks 
     <lb/>
     upon you; you express the opinion of the 
     <lb/>
     country where you are, and it would be a 
     <lb/>
     most disastrous thing if you expressed the 
     <lb/>
     opinion of Ottawa; I have the utmost con<lb break="no"/>fidence in you—go on and express the opin<lb break="no"/>ions of the country where you are." And, 
     <lb/>
     when Sir John Macdonald was again taking 
     <lb/>
     charge of the Department of the Interior, I 
     <lb/>wrote to him in this language: "In the<lb/>history of human ineptitude, there never was<lb/>such a damnable—"<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Oh. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Yes, that was the word I 
     <lb/>
     used—" such a damnable act of policy as 
     <lb/>
     closing up Southern Manitoba and the mile 
     <lb/>
     belt." We got them opened up, and I went 
     <lb/>
     and saw Burgess. I said, " Burgess, I think 
     <lb/>
     the old chief must have resented the lan<lb break="no"/>guage of the letters I wrote to him."—I wrote 
     <lb/>
     in strong language. He said, " Not at all. 
     <lb/>
     He brought out the letter in which you spoke 
     <lb/>
     of the damnable act of folly, and he said, 
     <lb/>
    " Burgess, when "Davin speaks in that way, 
     <lb/>something is wrong.' " I had broken away 
     <lb/>from my conventional and inveterate reti<lb break="no"/>cence, and I had talked in the large language 
     <lb/>of the earlier gods. What I say is, that the 
     <lb/>party and the government that I support 
     <lb/>have piled up such great services to this 
     <lb/>country that they can afford to have mis<lb break="no"/>takes of this or that man referred to. The 
     <lb/>result of their closing up Southern Manitoba 
     <lb/>and the mile belt, in the teeth of the advice 
     <lb/>of the late John Henry Pope and myself— 
     <lb/>against my persistent protest—was, as every<lb break="no"/>body knows who has lived in Manitoba, that 
     <lb/>there was a great deal of discontent and a 
     <lb/>great deal of retardation in the country. The 
     <lb/>results of that act linger with us to-day. 
     <lb/>Now, why was that done ? The gentleman 
     <lb/>who closed them up spoke to me in this wise 
     <lb/>—and it illustrates what I want to strike. He 
     <lb/>said : " What is the value of land in Southern 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <cb/>
          
          
     Manitoba to-day ?" I said, "I believe 
     <lb/>
     it is worth about $7 an acre: but 
     <lb/>
     what do you mean by asking me that 
     <lb/>
     question ? Do you mean that you would 
     <lb/>
     regard it as a private person would ? 
     <lb/>
     There is the greatest possible difference 
     <lb/>
     between a trading corporation or a private 
     <lb/>
     individual and a government. The govern<lb break="no"/>ment, by holding lands at $7 an acre, may 
     <lb/>
     make a stroke of policy most foolish, but 
     <lb/>
     an individual or a corporation, the more 
     <lb/>
     they get for their lands, the more money 
     <lb/>
     they gain. The proper way for a govern<lb break="no"/>ment to treat districts, lands and territories, 
     <lb/>
     is to consider the country as a family, and 
     <lb/>
     to consider that all which makes for the 
     <lb/>
     wealth and advancement of each part of 
     <lb/>
     that family adds so much to the wealth of 
     <lb/>
     the family. What I want, therefore, is to 
     <lb/>
     rid hon. gentlemen of the idea of looking to 
     <lb/>
     the North-west with the view of making 
     <lb/>
     money out of it or of getting an income out 
     <lb/>
     of it. The proper way to regard the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment of the Interior is not to regard it as a 
     <lb/>
     department from which to obtain income, 
     <lb/>
    but as the means of filling up the country 
     <lb/>with immigrants. The view of getting so 
     <lb/>much income out of the country is an en<lb break="no"/>tirely mistaken one. I hope that in these 
     <lb/>few remarks I have made my meaning 
     <lb/>clear. I mean that the development of 
     <lb/>these Territories is of vital importance to 
     <lb/>Canada and the Empire : I mean that they 
     <lb/>should be treated on the same footing of 
     <lb/>dignity as the other parts of the Dominion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. What do you propose to 
     <lb/>
     do ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I suggest that a very small 
     <lb/>
     change be made and that the local legisla<lb break="no"/>ture be placed precisely on the footing of a 
     <lb/>
     provincial legislature. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. Hate it made into a pro<lb break="no"/>vince ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Have it made into a pro<lb break="no"/>vince. I am glad my hon. friend referred 
     <lb/>
     to that. Now is the time to do it. We see 
     <lb/>
     the folly of having small provinces down by 
     <lb/>
     the Atlantic. We do not want petty pro<lb break="no"/>vinces—   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. No reflections on the mari<lb break="no"/>time provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I make none. But every 
     <lb/>
     statesman from the maritime provinces, 
     <lb/>
     with whom I have discussed this subject, 
     <lb/>
     has admitted it would be a good thing to 
     <lb/>
     have Nova Scotia, New Brunswick and 
     <lb/>
     Prince Edward Island all in one. It would 
     <lb/>
     be foolish to look forward to Assini<lb break="no"/>boia, Saskatchewan and Alberta being made 
     <lb/>
     into separate provinces. The only persons 
     <lb/>
     who will clamour for that are people who 
     <lb/>
     have moneyed interests in certain towns. 
     <lb/>
     You will get a few people in Calgary to 
     <lb/>
     clamour, for making Alberta a pro<lb break="no"/>vince, a few people in Regina to clamour 
     <lb/>
     for making Assiniboia a province, and a 
     <lb/>
      
      
            <pb n="1887" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1896-02-17_Page_01887.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">1887</fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">1888</fw>
      
      
     few people in Prince Albert to urge that 
     <lb/>
    the Saskatchewan district be made a pro<lb break="no"/>vince. Everybody knows that you cannot 
     <lb/>expect to have in those Territories. for many 
     <lb/>a year, such a dense population as would 
     <lb/>justify the existence of three or four pro<lb break="no"/>vinces there. I do not want to enter into 
     <lb/>particulars. l merely point out the way in 
     <lb/>which the North-west expects to be treated. 
     <lb/>Everybody understands how undesirable it 
     <lb/>is that I should particularize, but in every 
     <lb/>way we expect to be treated on a footing 
     <lb/>with the other provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MULO1">Mr. MULOCK</persName>. I ask the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman to particularize to the extent of tell<lb break="no"/>ing us what his proposed remedy is, and in<lb/>what way the Territories are now treated<lb/>different from other provinces.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Mainly this. At present the 
     <lb/>
     money voted is practically under the con<lb break="no"/>trol of the assembly. Practically. the as<lb break="no"/>sembly controls it. although not technically. 
     <lb/>After this Government has handed it over 
     <lb/>to the assembly, the assembly is allowed 
     <lb/>to control it. Although this Government 
     <lb/>hold a certain control. yet that is never 
     <lb/>fully exercised. At present there are four 
     <lb/>gentlemen there. who are called the execu<lb break="no"/>tive of the assembly. These gentlemen ad<lb break="no"/>vise the Lieutenant-Governor as to the. ex<lb break="no"/>penditure, and they are chosen by the as<lb break="no"/>sembly. What I propose is that we should 
     <lb/>have a small local government, just as they 
     <lb/>have in Prince Edward Island. It will not cost 
     <lb/>more than the executive costs at present. 
     <lb/>Mr. Haultain and Mr. Ross will draw a sal 
     <lb/>ary as large as two Ministers will in Prince 
     <lb/>Edward Island. I propose that they should 
     <lb/>be in a position to take a responsible course<lb/>as do the Ministers in other parts. I pro<lb break="no"/>pose, also, that all high officials, now chosen 
     <lb/>elsewhere, should be chosen from the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories. But I do not dwell on that, because 
     <lb/>that follows as a mere corollary. That is 
     <lb/>what I mean by saying that we should be 
     <lb/>treated on an equal footing with the other 
     <lb/>provinces. The subject is one which should 
     <lb/>be treated in more detail and at more 
     <lb/>length. in order to do full justice to it. But I 
     <lb/>think I have sufficiently explained my views 
     <lb/>in order that we should take practical ac<lb break="no"/>tion. A very slight change in the law would 
     <lb/>be sufficient, but, of course, I do not ex<lb break="no"/>pect anything to be done this session. The 
     <lb/>matter would require more careful consid<lb break="no"/>eration and a carefully prepared measure, 
     <lb/>so that I do not expect anything to be done 
     <lb/>this session. All I desired to accomplish 
     <lb/>was to give expression to the opinion of my 
     <lb/>constituents, and of the whole Territory, as 
     <lb/>to the matters I have brought before the 
     <lb/>House. I have ventured to make a sug<lb break="no"/>gestion that will entail some more expendi<lb break="no"/>ture. My remarks on that particular may, 
     <lb/>I hope, influence my hon. friend the Fi<lb break="no"/>nance Minister, when preparing supple<lb break="no"/>mental Estimates. There are certain prac<lb break="no"/>tical things that may he done for the Ter<lb break="no"/>
    
    
            <cb/>
          
          
     ritories in those supplemental Estimates. But         
     <lb/>what I wanted especially to clear from the<lb/>minds of this House and of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment is that the North-west Territories<lb/>have in any way failed to give a good return<lb/>for the outlay we have made there. The<lb/>North-west at present, with its developed<lb/>wealth, has so added to the assets on Can<lb break="no"/>ada that the amount of money spent in 
     <lb/>opening: it up is a very minor matter, in 
     <lb/>my opinion, indeed. If once we accept the 
     <lb/>view that the North-west has paid its way, 
     <lb/>that it has no large. debit against it, then, 
     <lb/>when the Council come to. consider the pro<lb break="no"/>posals of expenditure, they will not be so<lb/>unlikely to take an illiberal view as they<lb/>would if the notion that somehow money 
     <lb/>had been spent there which had not met 
     <lb/>with an adequate return. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DALY1">Mr. DALY</persName> moved the adjournment of the 
     <lb/>
     debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and debate adjourned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>