<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-02-27" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-02-27">27 February 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          

          
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
      
                    

           <date when="1905"/>.    
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1745" to="1770"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1745.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1747.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1749.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1751.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1753.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1755.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1767.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1769.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-01-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-01-06">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1745">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1745.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1747">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1747.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1749">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1749.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1751">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1751.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1753">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1753.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1755">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1755.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1767">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1767.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1769">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1769.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1745" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1745.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">1745</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 27. 1905</fw> 

<!-- GL, 2017-01-06, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day -->
           <!-- <p>Mr. HYMAN. Private members' work 
     <lb/>
     will be taken up, and if we get through with 
     <lb/>
     that we will go into supply. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Mr. INGRAM. On what items ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Mr. HYMAN. I cannot answer that, but 
     <lb/>
     it will not be on the Public Works esti<lb break="no"/>mates. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Mr. INGRAM. Could any of the minis<lb break="no"/>ters say what estimates they will discuss? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Mr. HYMAN. It is a difficult matter. If 
     <lb/>
     the hon. Minister of Agriculture is here, I 
     <lb/>
     think he will go on with his estimates, but 
     <lb/>
     I would not like to be bound down to saying 
     <lb/>
     exactly what we will go on with. It will 
     <lb/>
     be private members' day, and I suppose it 
     <lb/>
     will be taken up with private members' 
     <lb/>
     business. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Motion agreed to, and House adjourned at 
     <lb/>
     11.05 pm. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     HOUSE OF COMMONS. 
     <lb/></head>

<head rendition="simple:right">
     MONDAY, February 27, 1905. 
     
            </head>
   
            <p>The SPEAKER took the Chair at Three 
     <lb/>
     o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     FIRST READING. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>Bill (No. 82) to incorporate the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     Annuity Company.—Mr. Bole. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     RIGHTS OF THE PROVINCES. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName> (South York). Mr.
                                          <lb/> Speaker, before the Orders of the Day are <lb/>
                                          called, I intend to ask the attention of the <lb/> House
                                          to a very grave matter ; and, if neces<lb break="no"/>sary, to put myself in order, I will con<lb break="no"/>clude with a motion. The very important <lb/> matter to
                                          which I propose to call attention <lb/> has reference to
                                          provincial rights, particu<lb break="no"/>larly the rights
                                          of the province of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba, and I regret
                                          very much that neither <lb/> the Minister of the Interior
                                          (Mr. Sifton) nor <lb/> the late premier of Manitoba (Mr.
                                                 Green<lb break="no"/>way), who has now a seat in
                                          this House <lb/> is in his place. It is largely because
                                          these <lb/> hon. gentlemen have not chosen to call the
                                          <lb/> attention of the House to this matter that <lb/> I
                                          do so today. I think I can best bring <lb/> the question
                                          immediately within the view <lb/> of hon. members by
                                          reading a translation <lb/> of an article that was
                                          published in 'Le <lb/> Soleil' of Quebec, on February 11.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:EMME1">Mr. EMMERSON</persName>. Read the original.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. I will read the
                                          <lb/> original, but for the benefit of the Minister <lb/>
                                          of Railways, I will translate it ; I am quite <lb/>
                                          competent to do both. 'Le Soleil,' which <lb/> claims to
                                          be under the personal control of <lb/> the Prime Minister
                                          and to speak for him, <lb/> in its issue of February 11,
                                          made this de<lb break="no"/>claration : <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">1746</fw>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     We declare once for all that 'Le Soleil' is 
     <lb/>
     the organ of the Liberal party, and by that fact 
     <lb/>
     is under the direction and absolute control of 
     <lb/>
     Sir Wilfrid. The supporters of Sir Wilfrid, and 
     <lb/>
     those who affirm themselves to be such, are 
     <lb/>
     begged to take notice of the present declara<lb break="no"/>tion. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>On February 17, that paper, in an edi<lb break="no"/>torial, discussed the rights of the province 
     <lb/>
     of Manitoba in this way: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>In proportion to her big sisters Manitoba will 
     <lb/>
     count as little more than a large county. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>This is one of the reasons invoked by Mani<lb break="no"/>toba's delegates to obtain an enlargement of 
     <lb/>
     her territory. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>There is another. Quebec and Ontario have 
     <lb/>
     extended their limits, the one to the west, the 
     <lb/>
     other to the east, to attain on the north the 
     <lb/>
     shores of James bay. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Manitoba aspires to the shores of Hudson bay, 
     <lb/>
     on the northeast. It would be necessary to 
     <lb/>
     withdraw her boundaries several hundred miles 
     <lb/>
     towards the north, to cut the districts of Sas<lb break="no"/>katchewan and Athabaska, and encircle that of 
     <lb/>
     Keewatin. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Manitoba is asking for treble her existing 
     <lb/>
     territory. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>This enlargement is hardly possible. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>The district of Saskatchewan opposes it, at 
     <lb/>
     least the part directly interested. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>The finances of Manitoba in their actual state 
     <lb/>
     are not made to attract the free residents of 
     <lb/>
     the districts. Manitoba has a debt of $4,000,000. 
     <lb/>
     The school legislation of the little province is 
     <lb/>
     not of a nature to attract the immigrants who 
     <lb/>
     people the districts. The Northwest has its 
     <lb/>
     separate schools. Manitoba has abolished them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Every good act has its reward, every bad act 
     <lb/>
     its chastisement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Manitoba. will remain lowest with her pre<lb break="no"/>tentious law. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>


            <p>In other words, a threat is here held out 
     <lb/>
     by the Quebec organ of hon. gentlemen op<lb break="no"/>posite that Manitoba is to be kept in her 
     <lb/>
     inferior position, as compared with the other 
     <lb/>
     provinces, as a punishment because she 
     <lb/>
     chose to vindicate her provincial rights. 
     <lb/>
     She is to be denied territory, and worse 
     <lb/>
     things than that are to befall her. Again 
     <lb/>
     I say I regret the absence of the Minister 
     <lb/>
     of the Interior and the late Prime Minister 
     <lb/>
     of Manitoba. Among the laws of this coun<lb break="no"/>try is a very important Act called the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Lands Act. Reading from the Re<lb break="no"/>vised Statutes of 1886, I find that section 
     <lb/>
     23 of that Act, under the head of School 
     <lb/>
     Lands, says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     Sections eleven and twenty-nine in every sur<lb break="no"/>veyed township throughout the extent of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion lands, are hereby set apart as an en<lb break="no"/>dowment for purposes of education, and shall 
     <lb/>
     be designated school lands ; and they are here<lb break="no"/>by withdrawn from the operation of the clauses 
     <lb/>
     of this Act, which relate to the sale of Domin<lb break="no"/>ion lands and to homestead rights therein ; and 
     <lb/>
     no right to purchase or to obtain homestead 
     <lb/>
     entry shall be recognized in connection with 
     <lb/>
     the said sections, or any part of them. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>'Sections 24 and 25 provide how these 
     <lb/>
     lands shall be sold. Subsection 3 of section 
     <lb/>
     125 says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     All moneys, from time to time, realized from 
     <lb/>
     the sale of school lands shall be invested in 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="1747" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1747.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">1747</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> 


     securities of Canada, to form a school fund, and 
     <lb/>
     the interest arising therefrom, after deducting 
     <lb/>
     the cost of management, shall be paid annu<lb break="no"/>ally to the government of the province or terri<lb break="no"/>tory within which such lands are situated, to<lb break="no"/>wards the support ot public schools therein ; 
     <lb/>
     and the moneys so paid shall be distributed for 
     <lb/>
     that purpose by the government of such pro<lb break="no"/>vince or territory in such manner as it deems 
     <lb/>
     expedient. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>Now, from the statement which was made 
     <lb/>
     to all Canada the other day, we must infer 
     <lb/>
     that the Dominion Lands Act is to be chang<lb break="no"/>ed, and that in the province of Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     these school lands, which are now conse<lb break="no"/>crated to public schools, not to separate 
     <lb/>
     schools, are to be sold, and the proceeds dis<lb break="no"/>tributed in an entirely different way. That 
     <lb/>
     follows from the statement made here the 
     <lb/>
     other day, and on behalf of Manitoba I pro<lb break="no"/>test to-day against any such change in the 
     <lb/>
     law, or any such chastisement being meted 
     <lb/>
     out to that province as is proposed by this 
     <lb/>
     organ of the government. That organ 
     <lb/>
     wants Manitoba chastised because of cer<lb break="no"/>tain laws which that province has passed 
     <lb/>
     in connection with the school lands, and yet 
     <lb/>
     this same organ is the mouthpiece of this 
     <lb/>
     government, of which the Minister of the 
     <lb/>
     Interior (Mr. Sifton) is a member, and of 
     <lb/>
     which the late premier of Manitoba (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Greenway) is an ardent supporter. If any 
     <lb/>
     wrong has been wrought to the Roman 
     <lb/>
     Catholic minority of Manitoba in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with the school question, is not that 
     <lb/>
     due to the Minister of the Interior and the 
     <lb/>
     late premier of Manitoba ? They it was 
     <lb/>
     who caused the Manitoba legislation now 
     <lb/>
    complained of to be enacted. It was the 
     <lb/>Liberal party which passed it, and did so 
     <lb/>in the interests of that province. Yet to-day 
     <lb/>we have the Dominion government, of which 
     <lb/>these gentlemen are the mainstay, threaten<lb break="no"/>ing, through its leading organ, to chastise 
     <lb/>Manitoba because of that very legislation. 
     <lb/>That organ says to the province of Manito<lb break="no"/>ba : You shall not extend your bounds, you 
     <lb/>shall continue in the lowly inferior position 
     <lb/>you now occupy. On behalf of that pro<lb break="no"/>vince, and because these gentlemen are not 
     <lb/>here to raise their voices in its behalf, I 
     <lb/>raise mine. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Some hon. MEMBERS. Oh. oh. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. I raise my protest
                                          <lb/> because the proposal about to be made here <lb/> is
                                          of a most far reaching character. Not <lb/> only the
                                          school lands of Manitoba, but the <lb/> whole educational
                                          fund of that province, is <lb/> to be changed by a general
                                          Act, which must <lb/> follow from what was said here the
                                          other <lb/> day. I draw the attention of the right hon.
                                          <lb/> gentleman to this. If these important <lb/> changes
                                          are to be made on the lines laid <lb/> down by him, then
                                          it follows that remedial <lb/> legislation is in order as
                                          concerns Mani<lb break="no"/>toba. The argument is an a
                                          fortiori one. <lb/> Remedial legislation must follow, and
                                          it <lb/> will be introduced in this House by the <lb/>
                                          right hon. gentleman who warned the coun<lb break="no"/><cb/>
     <fw type="num">1748</fw>try against such legislation eight years ago. <lb/>
                                          There is this prospect for Manitoba, that all <lb/> her
                                          schools lands are, in every probability, <lb/> to be
                                          diverted this very session of parlia<lb break="no"/>ment
                                          to other purposes than those to which <lb/> they are
                                          devoted to-day by a general Act <lb/> amending the
                                          Dominion Lands Act. Fur<lb break="no"/>thermore the
                                          Manitoba school funds are to <lb/> be diverted by
                                          legislation which must follow <lb/> as a logical sequence
                                          from the statement <lb/> made the other day. Logically the
                                          right hon. <lb/> gentleman is bound to introduce a Bill
                                                 re<lb break="no"/>medying the school grievances of
                                          the minor<lb break="no"/>ity in the province of Manitoba,
                                          and yet <lb/> these very so called grievances are due to
                                          <lb/> the Minister of the Interior of this govern<lb break="no"/>ment and his friend (Mr. Greenway) who,
                                          <lb/> I am told, is to be his immediate successor in <lb/>
                                          this government. It was to give these hon. <lb/> gentlemen
                                          an opportunity here to repudiate <lb/> this language, to
                                          say they could not be par<lb break="no"/>ties to any such
                                          legislation, that I brought <lb/> this mattter up to-day ;
                                          and in all proba<lb break="no"/>bility the absence of the
                                          hon. the Minister <lb/> of the Interior from this House
                                          ever since the <lb/> beginning of this session and the
                                          absence <lb/> of the hon. member for Lisgar, (Mr. Green-
                                                 <lb break="yes"/> way) to-day are due to their
                                          desire to shirk <lb/> their manifest duty in connection
                                          with this <lb/> matter. The hon. the Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior was here only for a moment the
                                          other <lb/> day, and his absence no doubt is due, as <lb/>
                                          well as that of the other hon. gentleman, <lb/> to what is
                                          in the immediate future in store <lb/> for them. If what
                                          was foreshadowed the <lb/> other day is to happen, it must
                                          follow that <lb/> those school lands are to be diverted
                                          from <lb/> their present purpose and a Remedial Bill <lb/>
                                          introduced this session, and the party, which <lb/> claims
                                          to be the defender of provincial rights <lb/> from one end
                                          of the country to the other, is <lb/> to-day doing nothing
                                          to prevent the shackles <lb/> being put on the provinces
                                          of this great and <lb/> free Dominion. These provinces are
                                          to-day <lb/> free, and my-right hon. friend must know
                                          <lb/> that if there is one thing which the people <lb/>
                                          who breathe the free air of the prairies, the <lb/> people
                                          of the great west, value, it is their <lb/> political
                                          liberty ; and if the right hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman
                                          insists on shackling these people <lb/> in connection with
                                          the dispossession of their <lb/> school lands, he will
                                          make a great mistake. <lb/> He apparently does not
                                          understand the <lb/> genius of. the western people if he
                                          thinks <lb/> that by aid of any constitutional argument,
                                          <lb/> he can interfere with the school lands of the <lb/>
                                          province of Manitoba. I leave the case for <lb/> the
                                          present but may have to return to it. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p>Some hon. MEMBERS. Hear, hear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. But I shall wait
                                          <lb/> until the Minister of the Interior is in his <lb/>
                                          place. Again I call the attention of the <lb/> right hon.
                                          gentleman to the absence of a <lb/> number of his
                                          ministers from this House. <lb/> The Minister of Public
                                          Works (Mr. Suther<lb break="no"/>land) is not here. I
                                          regret that he is ill, <lb/> but the constitutional
                                          practice is that when <lb/> a minister is not able to take
                                          his place in <lb/>
                                          <pb n="1749" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1749.jpg"/>
                                          <fw type="num">1749</fw>
                                          <fw type="dateline">February 27, 1905</fw>
                                           the House he ought to vacate the
                                          position, <lb/> both in his own interest and that of the
                                          <lb/> country. The hon. member for London, (Mr. <lb/>
                                          Hyman), who is discharging the duties of <lb/> the
                                          Minister of Public Works, is contra<lb break="no"/>vening
                                          the constitution every day under the <lb/> circumstances.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p>Some hon. MEMBERS. Oh, oh ! 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. Hon. gentlemen
                                          <lb/> opposite laugh, but they used to attack <lb/> the
                                          late government about this very thing. <lb/> I regret that
                                          the Minister of the Interior, <lb/> (Mr. Sifton) was not
                                          in his place at the <lb/> time when these provincial
                                          rights which he <lb/> held at one time to be most dear to
                                          the <lb/> people of Manitoba, were being assailed. I <lb/>
                                          recollect when that hon. gentleman came <lb/> down to the
                                          province of Ontario and told the <lb/> people of Haldimand
                                          that of all things the <lb/> people of Manitoba did not
                                          want separate <lb/> schools or remedial legislation
                                          imposed upon <lb/> them. He came to the province of
                                          Ontario <lb/> for sympathy on that score and he got it.
                                          <lb/> But now if we are to believe the right hon. <lb/>
                                          gentleman's organ, all that is to be taken <lb/> back, the
                                          school lands are to be diverted <lb/> from their proper
                                          purpose, and the hon. <lb/> gentleman is bound, if he
                                          carries out what. <lb/> he promised, to introduce this
                                          session, an <lb/> Act to remedy the school grievances of
                                          the <lb/> minority of Manitoba. If any such thing <lb/> be
                                          attempted, the wrong will be done, pro<lb break="no"/>vincial rights will be taken away, and to-day, <lb/> in
                                          the absence of the two hon. gentlemen to <lb/> whom I
                                          especially referred, I rise to protest <lb/> against the
                                          policy outlined by the right <lb/> hon. gentleman in
                                          connection with these mat<lb break="no"/>ters. I move that
                                          the House do now ad<lb break="no"/>journ. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Right Hon. Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName> <lb/>(Prime Minister). One could
                                          hardly imagine <lb/>that any hon. gentleman would rise to
                                          move <lb/>the adjournment of the House for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose ot inflicting on us such a
                                                 ramshackle<lb break="no"/>if I may use such an
                                          expression—delivery <lb/>as we have had from my hon.
                                          friend. He <lb/>has given us a very modern exemplification
                                          <lb/>of the old story of Don Quixote tilting <lb/>against
                                          wind mills. My hon. friend is be<lb break="no"/>coming
                                          every session more and more quix<lb break="no"/>otic in
                                          his views and methods. Take this <lb/>item which he has
                                          just read from the Soeil<lb break="no"/>eil' and on which
                                          he has built so unwar<lb break="no"/>ranted a conclusion
                                          that the government <lb/>contemplates introducing a
                                          Remedial Bill <lb/>to amend the law of Manitoba. There is
                                          <lb/>not a scintilla in the article of the 'Soleil'
                                          <lb/>which can warrant any such conclusion. <lb/>The whole
                                          thing is manufactured—I will <lb/>not say wilfully—but if
                                          not, I know not <lb/>how to characterize in what manner it
                                          was <lb/>manufactured. Where is there a single <lb/>word
                                          to warrant what the hon. gentleman <lb/>sees there
                                          ?--<lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. <lb/> I did not say that it
                                          was there. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">1750</fw>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. My hon. friend
                                          <lb/> admits there is nothing there to warrant his <lb/>
                                          outbreak. The whole thing is in my hon. <lb/> friend's own
                                          mind, and it is from his own <lb/> mind alone that he has
                                          evolved the notion <lb/> that this government contemplates
                                          any such <lb/> thing as introducing a Remedial Bill for
                                          the <lb/> province of Manitoba. That is the only <lb/>
                                          authority he has for his remarks this after<lb break="no"/>noon. The thing is too absurd for consider<lb break="no"/>ation. My hon. friend professes to have <lb/> his soul
                                          harrowed by the prospect be con<lb break="no"/>templates.
                                          Let me tell him once and for <lb/> all that the government
                                          since 1896 has never <lb/> contemplated introducing any
                                          Remedial Act <lb/> affecting the province of Manitoba and
                                          does <lb/> not intend doing so. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. What about the
                                          <lb/> school lands ? <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. I may say to
                                          <lb/> the hon. gentleman that the government has <lb/> not
                                          contemplated and does not contemplate <lb/> to introduce
                                          any law to amend the School <lb/> Law. Is that categorical
                                          enough for the <lb/> hon. gentleman? <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. You cannot change
                                          <lb/> the School Law without changing the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Lands Act. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. Then I will
                                          <lb/> make my answer more categorical yet. The <lb/>
                                          government has not contemplated, does not <lb/>
                                          contemplate and will not contemplate any <lb/> amendment
                                          to the Dominion Lands Act. <lb/> I do not understand what
                                          the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man ls aiming at to-day. If
                                          he has any <lb/> object it must be to try and create a
                                          false <lb/> impression to arouse prejudices somewhere.
                                          <lb/> But the hon. gentleman began by express<lb break="no"/>ing his deep regret that the Minister
                                          of the <lb/> Interior and the hon. member from Lisgar
                                          <lb/> (Mr. Greenway) the former premier of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba, were not in their seats. Why,
                                          Sir, <lb/> it would have been very easy for the hon. <lb/>
                                          gentleman to secure their presence in their <lb/> seats if
                                          he wanted them to be present. Why <lb/> did he not notify
                                          them that he wanted to <lb/> bring before the House some
                                          question re<lb break="no"/>quiring their presence, and
                                          which required <lb/> them to make some defence to charges
                                          that <lb/> he intended to bring against them. Did <lb/>
                                          the hon. gentleman notify the Minister of <lb/> the
                                          Interior that he wanted him here to<lb break="no"/>day?
                                          Did he notify the hon. member for <lb/> Lisgar that he
                                          desired his presence here to<lb break="no"/>day? I am in
                                          the judgment of the House <lb/> when I say that the hon.
                                          gentleman, when <lb/> he intended to bring charges against
                                          the <lb/> members of the House. wilful and deliber<lb break="no"/>ate charges, has not had the manliness
                                          to <lb/> notify them that he intended to do so. As <lb/>
                                          to the ' Soleil,' I have no interest whatever <lb/> in
                                          that newspaper, financial or otherwise. <lb/> It generally
                                          supports the government, but <lb/> sometimes opposes it.
                                          It the hon. gentle' <lb/> man expects me to be responsible
                                          for any<lb break="no"/>thing that is published in the '
                                          Soliel.' be is <lb/> asking more from me than one would
                                          ask <lb/>
                                          <pb n="1751" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1751.jpg"/>
                                          <fw type="num">1751</fw>
                                          <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
                                           from any other member of
                                          parliament. The <lb/> hon. member may be responsible for
                                          what <lb/> appears in the Toronto ' World,' I have <lb/>
                                          not had the same connection with the 'Soleil., <lb/> I
                                          have nothing to do with the article in the <lb/> '
                                          Soleil,' which I had not read and had not <lb/> heard of
                                          until it was read on the floor of <lb/> the House. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. Mr. Speaker, the
                                          <lb/> right hon. gentleman is trying to draw a <lb/> red
                                          herring across the track. This news<lb break="no"/>paper
                                          which declares it is his organ, and <lb/> he has not
                                          repudiated it, says that the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of
                                          Manitoba is to be chastised be<lb break="no"/>cause of its
                                          pretentious school law, it is <lb/> to be chastised by the
                                          right hon. gentleman <lb/> and his party, and the
                                          chastisement is in <lb/> evidence now before all the
                                          people. Mani<lb break="no"/>toba expected that her
                                          boundaries would be <lb/> extended, and she expected that
                                          the Minister <lb/> of the interior would be here to see
                                          that <lb/> her boundaries were extended, but Manitoba
                                          <lb/> is being chastised to-day, as the organ of <lb/> the
                                          right hon. gentleman says, because of <lb/> her
                                          pretentious school laws. They are not <lb/> pretentious,
                                          they are constitutional, she had <lb/> a right to make
                                          them, yet she is to be chas<lb break="no"/>tised to-day.
                                          The right hon. gentleman <lb/> said practically the other
                                          day that the <lb/> province was entitled to have its
                                          boundaries <lb/> enlarged, it was entitled to be put on an
                                          <lb/> equality with the other provinces. All over <lb/>
                                          the country the statement has been publish<lb break="no"/>ed that Manitoba is being chastised because <lb/> of her
                                          manliness in connection with public <lb/> schools. The
                                          right hon. gentleman says he <lb/> does not propose to
                                          interfere with the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Lands Act. He
                                          does in substance, <lb/> he does in a certain measure
                                          which I know <lb/> of, where it is all outlined that the
                                          public <lb/> school lands and the public funds in re<lb break="no"/>lation to education are to be
                                          interfered <lb/> with. It may be in a special Bill, but
                                          the <lb/> intention is to make laws in that direction.
                                          <lb/> What follows then is this, that in the way <lb/> the
                                          right hon. gentleman aproaches this <lb/> question he is
                                          making flesh of one and fish <lb/> of the other ; certain
                                          provinces are to enjoy <lb/> certain school lands and
                                          others are to be de<lb break="no"/>nied them. If that is
                                          not an injustice and <lb/> an interference with the lands
                                          of the pro<lb break="no"/>vince, I do not know what it is.
                                          The right <lb/> hon. gentleman is trying to get away from
                                          <lb/> this question in saying that he does not <lb/>
                                          propose to introduce remedial legislation. <lb/> He is
                                          bound to introduce it if there is any<lb break="no"/>thing
                                          in the constitutional argument he <lb/> made here the
                                          other day. There is nothing <lb/> in that constitutional
                                          argument, but there is <lb/> a great deal in the
                                          constitutional argument <lb/> that Manitoba is entitled to
                                          remedial legis<lb break="no"/>lation. If that is true, I
                                          will have to put <lb/> up for the present with the trivial
                                          reply of <lb/> the right hon. gentleman; but before two
                                          <lb/> weeks are over, before another week is <lb/> over,
                                          he will sing on the other side of his <lb/> face. He will
                                          find that the people of Can<lb break="no"/>ada are in
                                          favour of the maintenance of <lb/> provincial rights; they
                                          are not in favour of <lb/>
                                          <cb/>
     <fw type="num">1752</fw> a paternalized autonomy like that which <lb/> the
                                          hon. gentleman proposes. The people <lb/> of this country
                                          believe in provincial rights <lb/> as they have been
                                          defined and won out by <lb/> the province of Manitoba.
                                          Again I say that <lb/> the hon. gentleman is attempting a
                                                 revolu<lb break="no"/>tion, and the Minister of the
                                          Interior ought <lb/> to be in his place here to-day, since
                                          these <lb/> things are being done in the department <lb/>
                                          over which he presides. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man
                                          asks why I did not notify the Min<lb break="no"/>ister of
                                          the Interior? Am I the Minister of <lb/> the Interior's
                                          keeper? If he is not in his <lb/> place, where shall I
                                          have to go to find him? <lb/> It is not for the right hon.
                                          gentleman to say <lb/> to me that I should notify this man
                                          or <lb/> notify that man; let them be here to look <lb/>
                                          after themselves. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:GUTH1">Mr. HUGH GUTHRIE</persName> (South Welling<lb break="no"/>ton). The hon. member for South York
                                          <lb/> (Mr. Maclean) Who has just resumed his <lb/> seat,
                                          may not be the keeper of the Minister <lb/> of the
                                          Interior. But there is a rule of <lb/> courtesy recognized
                                          in this House which re« <lb/> quires that when an hon.
                                          member intends <lb/> to bring up a matter pertaining
                                          particularly <lb/> to any department, the minister
                                          presiding <lb/> over that department must be notified.
                                                 Min<lb break="no"/>isters have all sorts of reasons
                                          for not be<lb break="no"/>ing in the House. Deputations
                                          wait upon <lb/> them from time to time, as we all know.
                                          <lb/> We know not why the Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior is not in his place to-day; but there is <lb/>
                                          this much about it, it is a small thing and <lb/> a mean
                                          thing for the hon. member for South <lb/> York to make
                                          these remarks without hav<lb break="no"/>ing intimated to
                                          the Minister of the Interior <lb/> that he desired his
                                          presence here. Now I <lb/> desire on this occasion to
                                          enter my protest <lb/> against such interruptions and
                                          interjections, <lb/> on the Orders of the Day being
                                          called, as <lb/> have been made by the hon. member for
                                          <lb/> South York. If there is anything cal<lb break="no"/>culated to stir up strife and trouble in this <lb/>
                                          country it is speeches such as that hon. <lb/> gentleman
                                          has delivered, and articles that <lb/> appear in his
                                          newspaper. If hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers in this House
                                          would treat the question <lb/> which the hon. member for
                                          South York has <lb/> introduced, with calmness, with
                                          candour, <lb/> with that liberality which no doubt they
                                          <lb/> all possess, there would be no danger of <lb/>
                                          producing that storm and that inflamed <lb/> condition of
                                          the public mind which appears <lb/> in the party press and
                                          among the people, <lb/> which we see to-day, and will see
                                                 through<lb break="no"/>out Canada. Now, the hon.
                                          member cites <lb/> the case of Manitoba. I am not going to
                                          <lb/> dwell on that, I merely say that so far <lb/> as I
                                          am concerned, as a member of this <lb/> House supporting
                                          the government, the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of schools in
                                          the province of Manitoba <lb/> is a settled question.
                                          There is no analogy <lb/> whatever between the conditions
                                          of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba and the new provinces which
                                          are to <lb/> be admitted in to the confederation; I say
                                          <lb/> this now, although these are matters which <lb/>
                                          will more properly come up when the Bill <lb/> is read the
                                          second time. But when we per<lb break="no"/><pb n="1753" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1753.jpg"/>
                                          <fw type="num">1753</fw>
                                          <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 27 1905</fw>
                                          mit a province to come into this
                                                 confeder<lb break="no"/>ation, we permit it to come
                                          in on such terms <lb/> as this House deems proper and
                                          equitable. <lb/> It was so with the other provinces, and,
                                          I <lb/> presume, will be so with the provinces that <lb/>
                                          are to come in. Mr. Speaker, I only rise <lb/> to protest
                                          against interjections and inter<lb break="no"/>ruptions by
                                          hon. members such as those of <lb/> the hon. member for
                                          South York (Mr. W. F. <lb/> Maclean) who seeks both by his
                                          voice <lb/> in this House and by the newspaper, which,
                                          <lb/> fortunately or unfortunately, he controls, an <lb/>
                                          inflammatory condition of indignation in the <lb/>
                                          country. I think that, when the Bill is before <lb/> us
                                          and when discussion is proper, then the <lb/> hon. member
                                          for South York can enter any <lb/> protest he sees fit.
                                          But, untiI that time, it is <lb/> much better for the
                                          House and the country <lb/> that we should remain silent
                                          on the subject. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p>Motion (Mr. W. F. Maclean) to adjourn, 
     <lb/>
     negatived. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

   <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     STEAM COMMUNICATION WITH P.E.I.— 
     <lb/>
     SNOW BLOCKADE IN MARITIME 
     <lb/>
     PROVINCES—DELAY OF MAILS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LEFU1">Mr. A. A. LEFURGEY</persName> (Prince, P.E.I).
                                          Mr. <lb/> Speaker, I would like to ask the attention <lb/>
                                          of the Postmaster General (Sir William <lb/> Mulock)
                                          through the right hon. Prime Min<lb break="no"/>ister (Sir
                                          Wilfrid Laurier) to the condition <lb/> of the mail
                                          service in Prince Edward Island. <lb/> I received on
                                          Saturday a despatch from a <lb/> resident of Tignish
                                          saying that, in answer <lb/> to communications addressed
                                          to the post<lb break="no"/>master of Charlottetown they
                                          have received <lb/> absolutely no information as to the
                                          carriage <lb/> of the mails, and the people throughout the
                                          <lb/> district have now undertaken the service <lb/>
                                          themselves, and the mails have been started <lb/> by
                                          sleighs sent out by private individuals. <lb/> It seems to
                                          me that this is very unsatis<lb break="no"/>factory, and,
                                          I should think, an illegal <lb/> method of handling the
                                          public mails of this <lb/> country. I will ask the right
                                          hon. First <lb/> Minister to bring this subject to the
                                                 atten<lb break="no"/>tion of the Postmaster General
                                          and have <lb/> some inquiry made into it. And. if the
                                          train <lb/> service is so blocked that the mails cannot
                                          <lb/> be brought through by the trains a service <lb/>
                                          should be established by means of sleighs <lb/> under
                                          official auspices, so that His Majesty's <lb/> mails may
                                          not be entrusted to private indi<lb break="no"/>viduals as
                                          they have been. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:PREF1">Hon. RAYMOND PREFONTAINE</persName> (Min- <lb break="yes"/> of Marine and Fisheries). I beg leave
                                          to <lb/> communicate to the House a despatch I <lb/> have
                                          just received : <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     Charlottetown, P.E.I., 27th Feb. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Steamers last crossing twenty-fourth ultimo, 
     <lb/>
     ice blockade still continues: tried dynamite 
     <lb/>
     Pictou barrier Saturday, found useless; ' Stan<lb break="no"/>ley ' unable to get past Cape Bear. No crossing 
     <lb/>
     at Capes since twenty-third instant. Boats can<lb break="no"/>not overcome lolly. broken ice and deep snow ; 
     <lb/>
     railway blocked for two weeks. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

          <p rendition="simple:right">
     A. LORD. 
     <lb/>
     Agent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">1754</fw>

            <p><persName ref="pers:EMME1">Hon. H. R. EMMERSON</persName> (Minister of
                                          <lb/> Railways and Canals). Apropos the sub<lb break="no"/>ject raised by my hon. friend from Prince <lb/> Edward
                                          Island (Mr. Lefurgey). I beg to <lb/> inform the House and
                                          the country that the <lb/> snow-blockade which has for
                                          some time <lb/> existed on the Intercolonial—or that
                                          portion <lb/> of it in the province of Nova Scotia—has
                                          <lb/> been raised. I had communications to-day <lb/>
                                          stating that the trains are now moving in <lb/> and out of
                                          Halifax, and also between <lb/> Sydney and Truro—so that
                                          the road is com<lb break="no"/>pletely free. The Dominion
                                          Atlantic line <lb/> which is the line running between
                                          Halifax <lb/> and Yarmouth, had been closed for a week
                                          <lb/> or ten days. Even the highways are entirely <lb/>
                                          impassable. With the assistance of the In<lb break="no"/>tercolonial and the using of the appliances of <lb/>
                                          that road, the Dominion Atlantic has been <lb/> opened up,
                                          and trains are now running over <lb/> it. The blockade, of
                                          course has been a very <lb/> great drawback to the
                                          business interests of <lb/> the maritime provinces.
                                          Regretful for the <lb/> past, I shall endeavour to make
                                          such <lb/> arrangements as are possible with the clerk
                                          <lb/> of the weather to prevent a repetition of <lb/>such
                                          a stoppage of Intercolonial trains. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:HUGH1">Mr. J. J. HUGHES</persName> (King's, P.E.I.). In
                                          <lb/> reference to the question raised by the hon. <lb/>
                                          member for Prince (Mr. Lefurgey), I might <lb/> say that I
                                          made representations to the Post <lb/> Office Department
                                          some time ago and was <lb/> informed that the postmaster
                                          at Charlotte<lb break="no"/>town had full power to employ
                                          teams to <lb/> convey the mails when the trains were <lb/>
                                          stalled—full powers to have the mails <lb/> brought
                                          through by any means he thought <lb/> advisable in the
                                          public interest. I have <lb/> no doubt at all that the
                                          postmaster at <lb/> Charlottetown is using the power
                                          intrusted <lb/> to him to the best of his judgment and
                                          <lb/> ability. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LEFU1">Mr. LEFURGEY</persName>. I do not wish to make
                                          <lb/> this a subject of controversy. But, as I <lb/> have
                                          a message from a resident of Tignish, <lb/> I might read
                                          that to the House, and possibly <lb/> it may satisfy hon.
                                          gentlemen as to my <lb/> position : <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     Tignish, P.E.I., Feb. 25. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LEFU1">A. A. Lefurgey</persName>, M.P., <lb/>Ottawa. Ont. <lb/>
                                          </p>

            <p>Mails started by private individuals without 
     <lb/>
     notice. Whear insolently answers. No expla<lb break="no"/>nation. Bring up demoralization before orders 
     <lb/>
     of day. Agnew wired Yeo to-day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>So, it would appear that the postmaster 
     <lb/>
     at Charlottetown had been appealed to in 
     <lb/>
     the matter and the people had received no 
     <lb/>
     satisfactory explanation of his conduct, and 
     <lb/>
     consequently had to use conveyances of 
     <lb/>
     private individuals to deliver the mails. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PROVINCIAL GOVERNMENT IN THE 
     <lb/>
     NORTHWEST. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Mr. HAGGART</persName>. I would ask the right
                                          <lb/> hon. Prime Minister (Sir Wilfrid Laurier) <lb/> when
                                          the Bills establishing the provinces <lb/>
                                          <pb n="1755" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1755.jpg"/>
                                          <fw type="num">1755</fw>
                                          <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
                                           of Saskatchewan and Alberta will
                                          be print<lb break="no"/>ed ? <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. I expect they
                                          <lb/> will be printed to-day or to-morrow. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FITZ1">Hon. CHARLES FITZPATRICK</persName> (Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Justice). The Bills were
                                          placed in <lb/> the hands of the clerk of the House on
                                          <lb/> Thursday last. <lb/>
                                   </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">PRIVATE BILLS.</head>


            <head rendition="simple:centre">THIRD READING.</head>

            <p>Bill (No. 34) respecting the Nicola, Kam<lb break="no"/>loops and Similkameen Coal and Railway 
     <lb/>
     Company.—Mr. Galliber. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CONSIDERED IN COMMITTEE—THIRD 
     <lb/>
     READING. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>Bill (No. 33) respecting certain patents of 
     <lb/>
     Jean Effront—Mr. L. P. Demers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     MOLSONS BANK. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>House in committee on Bill (No. 14) re<lb break="no"/>specting the Molson's Bank.—Mr. Ames. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>0n section 1, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:CAMP3">Mr. CAMPBELL</persName>. I may just say that
                                          <lb/> when this Bill was before the committee <lb/> there
                                          was some opposition to it on account <lb/> of the question
                                          not being settled as to wheth<lb break="no"/>er the
                                          shareholders had authorized this <lb/> change. Since then
                                          I have received a tele<lb break="no"/>gram from the
                                          general manager saying that <lb/> the shareholders were
                                          notified and author<lb break="no"/>ized the change at a
                                          special general meet<lb break="no"/>ing called for that
                                          purpose. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p>Bill reported, read the third time and 
     <lb/>
     passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SOVEREIGN FIRE ASSURANCE CO. OF 
     <lb/>
     CANADA. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
<p>House in committee on Bill (No. 26) to in<lb break="no"/>corporate the Sovereign Fire Assurance Co. 
     <lb/>
     of Canada—Mr. E. F. Clarke. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. Mr. Chairman,
                                                 be<lb break="no"/>fore you report the Bill as the
                                          hon. Minister <lb/> of Finance is in his place—and I am
                                          very <lb/> glad to see him here looking so well-I wish
                                          <lb/> to call his attention to the general insurance <lb/>
                                          question, and particularly to the question <lb/> which has
                                          arisen over in the United States. <lb/> I am only going to
                                          take a moment because <lb/> I would like to discuss this
                                          matter with him <lb/> later on in the session, but I wish
                                          to give <lb/> him notice today that a very serious ques<lb break="no"/>tion has arisen in the United States in
                                          regard <lb/> to life insurance as controlled by private
                                          <lb/> companies. He must know, as every one. I <lb/>
                                          imagine, knows, that it came out the other <lb/> day in
                                          the city of New York that the great <lb/> Equitable Life
                                          Insurance Company of that <lb/> city. that now controls
                                          five hundred millions <lb/> of money in trust for its
                                          policyholders, is <lb/> absolutely under the control of
                                          one man, <lb/> who, with his family, owns $75,000 of the
                                          <lb/> paid up stock of $100,000 which gives him <lb/> the
                                          control of that company. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
          <!--  <p>Mr. HAGGART. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
<cb/>
     <fw type="num">1756</fw>
   
            <p>It has been pointed out by very import~ 
     <lb/>
     ant men in the United States and by the 
     <lb/>
     great newspapers of the United States that 
     <lb/>
     an effort was being made in New York by 
     <lb/>
     great capitalists represented by Harriman 
     <lb/>
     Gould and the great bond house represented 
     <lb/>
     by Mr. Schiff, of New York, to control this 
     <lb/>
     company and that they were willing to give 
     <lb/>
     $5,000,000 of ready money for the controlling 
     <lb/>
     interest in the shares of the Equitable Life. 
     <lb/>
     This has proved to be a matter of supreme 
     <lb/>
     interest to the people of the United States, 
     <lb/>
     that a few men with a very small capital 
     <lb/>
     could control the immense reserve fund for 
     <lb/>
     the benefit of the policy holders. It is pro<lb break="no"/>posed there now—and we will have to do 
     <lb/>
     the same thing, we will have to change our 
     <lb/>
     insurance laws—to enact that the policy 
     <lb/>
     holders shall have a great deal to say in the 
     <lb/>
     disposition of these immense trust funds, 
     <lb/>
     and I take this opportunity of calling the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the minister to it. I trust that, it 
     <lb/>
     not this session at a very early date, we will 
     <lb/>
     be able to cope with this great question, be 
     <lb/>
     cause if there is one thing of importance in 
     <lb/>
     connection with an insurance company it is 
     <lb/>
     that the trust moneys which are there for 
     <lb/>
     the security of the policy holders ought to 
     <lb/>
     have the best possible administration. I do 
     <lb/>
     not think the best administration of these 
     <lb/>
     funds can be secured when it is possible for 
     <lb/>
     their management to fall into the hands of 
     <lb/>
     two or three men who by controlling the 
     <lb/>
     shares of the proprietary company are free 
     <lb/>
     to do what they like with great funds of this 
     <lb/>
     kind. It is openly charged by the leading 
     <lb/>
     newspapers in the United States to-day that 
     <lb/>
     Harriman and Gould are anxious to get con<lb break="no"/>trol of the Equitable Insurance Company in 
     <lb/>
     order that they may play ducks and drakes 
     <lb/>
     with the $500,000,000 of trust money which 
     <lb/>
     is the absolute property of the policy holders, 
     <lb/>
     in order that they may use it for their great 
     <lb/>
     railway propositions, and we are in danger 
     <lb/>
     of reaching the same condition in this coun<lb break="no"/>try. I trust that later on some proper provi<lb break="no"/>sion will be introduced into our General In<lb break="no"/>surance Act for the protection of the policy 
     <lb/>
     holders. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Hon. W. S. FIELDING</persName> (Minister of
                                                 Fin<lb break="no"/>ance). The proper
                                          (protection—shall I say <lb/> the adequate protection—of
                                          the moneys <lb/> which are invested in the hands of the
                                                 vari<lb break="no"/>ous insurance companies of our
                                          country, <lb/> must always be a question of the utmost
                                          <lb/> importance, and if at any time there may be <lb/>
                                          doubt as to whether our legislation is suf<lb break="no"/>ficient on that point I am sure that my hon. <lb/>friend
                                          (Mr. W. F. Maclean) or any other <lb/>member would be only
                                          doing his duty in <lb/>bringing the matter before the
                                          attention of <lb/>the House. I hope it will be found, on
                                          an <lb/>examination of the general insurance law <lb/> and
                                          of the charters of the various companies, <lb/>that our
                                          legislation in Canada is not open to <lb/>the objections
                                          which might be taken in the <lb/>case of United States
                                          companies. However, <lb/>if there are some companies as to
                                          which <lb/>that criticism might be offered, I quite admit
                                          [...] <lb/>
                                   </p>

    
            <pb n="1767" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1767.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1767</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> 
        
<p>[...] made by the Board of Trade. I must at 
     <lb/>
     once dissent from that interpretation. It 
     <lb/>
     cannot be admitted that the government will 
     <lb/>
     simply till the part of a mere recording 
     <lb/>
     clerk for the Board of Trade. When re<lb break="no"/>commendations are made to the govern<lb break="no"/>ment by the Board of Trade, the govern<lb break="no"/>ment is bound to consider the fitness of the 
     <lb/>
     persons proposed, but naturally would ac<lb break="no"/>cept those recommendations unless there 
     <lb/>
     was cause to the contrary. At all events, 
     <lb/>
     that is the interpretation we have given to 
     <lb/>
     the statute, and I think that interpretation 
     <lb/>
     will be accepted by parliament. In this 
     <lb/>
     case the recommendations made by Toronto 
     <lb/>
     were accepted without dissent. So were 
     <lb/>
     the recommendations made by Winnipeg. 
     <lb/>
     But some dissent was expressed to the re<lb break="no"/>commendations made by the Montreal Board 
     <lb/>
     of Trade. I do not mean that the fact that 
     <lb/>
     Messrs. Carrnthers and Metcalfe were 
     <lb/>
     passed over would indicate anything against 
     <lb/>
     those gentlemen. I do not think it would 
     <lb/>
     be fair to imply or accept anything of that 
     <lb/>
     kind. But the Minister of Trade and Com<lb break="no"/>merce informs me that these gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     have been passed over for good and suffi<lb break="no"/>cient reasons. which will appear upon the 
     <lb/>
     face of the papers when they are brought 
     <lb/>
     down. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     STEAMSHIP OLD STORAGE-THER<lb break="no"/>MOGRAPH RECORDS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:HEND1">Mr. HENDERSON</persName> (Halton) moved: <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     For copies of all thermograph records of tem<lb break="no"/>perature taken on board Atlantic steamships 
     <lb/>
     during the calendar year 1903, stating: (1) 
     <lb/>
     name of steamship ; (2) date when thermograph 
     <lb/>
     was put in chamber ; (3) date when the steamer 
     <lb/>
     left the report; (4) whether chamber was (a) 
     <lb/>
     cold storage; (b) cool air; (c) mechanically 
     <lb/>
     ventilated ; (d) ordinary, or whether the record 
     <lb/>
     was taken on deck or other place where the 
     <lb/>
     natural temperature of the air would be regis<lb break="no"/>tered, unexposed to the sun's rays; (5) where 
     <lb/>
     practicable, in what part of the chamber the 
     <lb/>
     thermograph was placed. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName> (Prime Min<lb break="no"/>ister). There is no objection to the
                                          motion, <lb/> but I understand that it will take a very
                                          <lb/> long time to prepare this return. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:HEND1">Mr. HENDERSON</persName>. This information <lb/>
                                          was moved for last year, and was brought <lb/> down. But
                                          it is not in the possession of <lb/> the clerk of routine
                                          and records—it is not <lb/> available to members of the
                                          House. I am <lb/> under the impression that the whole
                                          matter <lb/> is in the hands of the Department of <lb/>
                                          Agriculture. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p>Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section" rendition="simple:centre">

     <head>FREIGHT AND STORAGE CHARGES-<lb/>
           
            SYDNEY INTERCOLONIAL RAIL<lb break="no"/>WAY STATION. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. A. MARTIN</persName> (Queen's) moved: <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     For a return showing in detail all the col<lb break="no"/>lections for freight and storage at Sydney In<lb break="no"/><cb/>
     <fw type="num">1768</fw>tercolonial Railway station for 1900, 1901, 1902, 
     <lb/>
     1903 and 1904; giving the names of shippers 
     <lb/>
     and consignees; a description of the merchan<lb break="no"/>dise ; where from ; weight of each package : 
     <lb/>
     the amount received for storage, and from 
     <lb/>
     whom. Also a reference to the authority under 
     <lb/>
     which storage has been collected; the rate, 
     <lb/>
     and by whom fixed. Also any refunds for freight 
     <lb/>
     and storage, and to whom paid. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName> (Prime Minis<lb break="no"/>ter). I am informed by the Railway
                                                 De<lb break="no"/>partment that it is not customary
                                          to fur<lb break="no"/>nish such information as is asked
                                          for by <lb/> this motion. It involves private business.
                                          <lb/> Moreover, I am informed it will take almost <lb/> a
                                          year to prepare such a. return. I would <lb/> advise my
                                          hon. friend (Mr. A. Martin) to <lb/> allow the matter to
                                          stand and have a con<lb break="no"/>ference with the
                                          Minister of Railways. Per<lb break="no"/>haps the minister
                                          can give the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man the.
                                          information he wants. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. A. MARTIN</persName>. The reason I have
                                          <lb/> moved for this return is that I have re<lb break="no"/>ceived letters from parties. who
                                          complain <lb/> that there is discrimination in freight and
                                          <lb/> storage charges, some parties being charged <lb/>
                                          more than others. I do not know any other <lb/> way to get
                                          that information. If the order <lb/> is too large. perhaps
                                          we might shorten it <lb/> by making it apply only to one
                                          year. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. If my hon. <lb/>
                                          friend were to have a conference with the <lb/> Minister
                                          of Railways. perhaps they could <lb/> agree upon a form in
                                          which the motion <lb/> could be carried. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:CLEM1">Mr. Clements</persName>, the debate 
     <lb/>
     was adjourned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     BOUNDARIES OF MANITOBA. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
<p><persName ref="pers:ROCH1">Mr. W. J. ROCHE</persName> (Marquette) moved:
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     For copies of all petitions, memorials and 
     <lb/>
     resolutions from the legislative assembly of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba. the executive of that province, and 
     <lb/>
     any correspondence relative to the extension of 
     <lb/>
     the boundaries of Manitoba to the west or 
     <lb/>
     north. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. I would ask
                                          <lb/> my hon. friend not to move this to-day. <lb/> The
                                          correspondence is not complete yet, but <lb/> it may be
                                          completed next Monday. Allow <lb/> it to stand. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. If any
                                                 correspon<lb break="no"/>dence is received between
                                          now and then, <lb/> will that be included? <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. Yes. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Mr. HAGGART</persName>. I suppose we will have
                                          <lb/> it before the discussion of the Bills ? <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. I do not see
                                          <lb/> any connection at all between the Bill now <lb/>
                                          before the House and this question regard<lb break="no"/>ing the province of Manitoba, I cannot see <lb/> that
                                          they have any relation whatever. It <lb/> is intended to
                                          have the correspondence com<lb break="no"/>plete as soon
                                          as possible, probably this <lb/> week. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <pb n="1769" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-02-27_Page_1769.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">1769</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 27, 1905</fw> 

            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. Is it not a fact
                                          <lb/> that the province of Manitoba has asked <lb/> some
                                          of this very territory which it is now <lb/> proposed to
                                          include in Saskatchewan ? <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. Yes. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. I think therefore
                                          <lb/> the question is pertinent. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. I do not think
                                          <lb/> it is, because the legislature of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories has passed a
                                          resolution <lb/> against such a grant of their territory.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:ROCH1">Mr. W. J. ROCHE</persName>. They have also <lb/>
                                          passed a resolution favouring the incorpor<lb break="no"/>ation of a portion of that territory in the <lb/>
                                          province of Manitoba. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. Yes. and I <lb/>
                                          can inform my hon. friend that this terri<lb break="no"/>tory is not at all included in the boundaries <lb/> of
                                          Saskatchewan. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:HAGG1">Mr. HAGGART</persName>. The right hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man has introduced this very subject in
                                          his <lb/> speech introducing the Bill. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. Certainly, I
                                          <lb/> introduced it to say that we could not grant <lb/>
                                          the prayer of the province of Manitoba, <lb/> because the
                                          province of Manitoba asked for <lb/> a certain portion of
                                          the territories under the <lb/> jurisdiction of the
                                          Northwest legislature, <lb/> and the legislature had
                                          refused to grant <lb/> such territory. At the same time, I
                                          stated <lb/> there was a portion of territory north of
                                          <lb/> Lake \Vinnipegosis and Lake Manitoba as <lb/> to
                                          which the legislature had expressed no <lb/> objection to
                                          granting it to Manitoba. But <lb/> we have reserved this,
                                          it is not included in <lb/> the boundaries of the new
                                          province. There<lb break="no"/>fore it has no relation at
                                          all. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACL4">Mr. W. F. MACLEAN</persName>. I still hold that
                                          <lb/> Manitoba has an interest in the territories to <lb/>
                                          the west, which are still territories and not <lb/>
                                          provinces. Manitoba has been looking for<lb break="no"/>ward all along to acquiring them, and I <lb/> believe
                                          the Minister of the Interior has <lb/> made statements to
                                          that effect, that some <lb/> day Manitoba might look
                                          forward to in<lb break="no"/>cluding a portion of the
                                          territory of Sas<lb break="no"/>katchewan. I think
                                          correspondence of that <lb/> character is in the
                                          possession of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment. and we ought
                                          to have it in connection <lb/> with the new Bill. <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. Stand. <lb/>
                                   </p>
</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">COLD STORAGE OF FISH. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. ALEXANDER MARTIN</persName> moved for: <lb/>
                                   </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     A return showing the number and location, 
     <lb/>
     cost and earnings, of the cold storage establish<lb break="no"/>ments called ' bait freezers,' of maritime Can<lb break="no"/>ada; together with the returns, duly certified, 
     <lb/>
     of all such institutions, since 1900; the names 
     <lb/>
     and the salaries of all superintendents, officials 
     <lb/>
     and keepers of same; and the amounts in 
     <lb/>
     pounds of the different kinds of fish therein 
     <lb/>
     stored ; the amount of bait from them used by 
     <lb/>
     bona fide fishermen, and the names of the same; 
     <lb/>
     together with all such information as may per<lb break="no"/><cb/>
     <fw type="num">1770</fw>mit of the thorough examination of the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of government assisted refrigerators. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:PREF1">Hon. RAYMOND PREFONTAINE</persName>. I <lb/>
                                          must inform the hon. gentleman (Mr. A. <lb/> Martin) that
                                          some of the documents he <lb/> asks for cannot be laid on
                                          the table. I am <lb/> informed that the names of the
                                          fishermen <lb/> are not on record. I do not know What the
                                          <lb/> latter part of his motion means. Of course, <lb/>
                                          the government has no objection to pro<lb break="no"/>ducing whatever papers can be produced. <lb/> but the
                                          latter part of his motion cannot be <lb/> complied with. I
                                          might suggest to the hon. <lb/> gentleman that he call at
                                          the Department <lb/> and indicate what papers he desires
                                          to <lb/> obtain. The Department will furnish him <lb/>
                                          with a list of those that can be produced. <lb/> Let the
                                          motion stand in the meantime. <lb/>
                                   </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     MOTIONS AGREED TO WITHOUT DIS<lb break="no"/>CUSSION. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>For a copy of the report of Mr. Matheson 
     <lb/>
     relating to the alleged fraud in payment of 
     <lb/>
     fishing bountics.—Mr. Ganong. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>For copies of all correspondence, letters, re<lb break="no"/>ports, petitions, memoranda, in possession of 
     <lb/>
     the government, or any member or omeial there<lb break="no"/>of. relating to the location and erection of a. 
     <lb/>
     railway station at Grand View, on the Murray 
     <lb/>
     Harbour branch of the Prince Edward Island 
     <lb/>
     Railway—Mr. A. Martin. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>For a return showing the total number of 
     <lb/>
     officers. civil engineers and other employees 
     <lb/>
     now engaged in the surveys of the Transconti<lb break="no"/>nental Railway, and works connected therewith, 
     <lb/>
     under the Transcontinental Railway Construc<lb break="no"/>tion Commission : the name and place of resi<lb break="no"/>dence of each of the above persons at the time 
     <lb/>
     of his appointment; and the functions and 
     <lb/>
     salaries of each of the above.—Mr. Gervais. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>For a return showing the business done in 
     <lb/>
     the Exchequer Court of Canada, under its ad<lb break="no"/>miralty jurisdiction, since the Admiralty Act 
     <lb/>
     of 1891 came into force; giving by districts, 
     <lb/>
     (1) the number of actions instituted; (2a) the 
     <lb/>
     number of interlocutory applications, and (b) 
     <lb/>
     trials: (3) the amount involved.—Mr. A. H. 
     <lb/>
     Clark. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     LABOUR UNION LABELS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>House again in committee on Bill (No. 10) 
     <lb/>
     respecting Labour Union Labels. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>On section 7, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:GUTH1">Mr. GUTHRIE</persName>. When this Bill was last
                                          <lb/> in committee, the question was on an <lb/> amendment
                                          proposed by the hon. member <lb/> for St. John and
                                          Iberville (Mr. L. P. De<lb break="no"/>mers), to the
                                          eifect that the word ' incorpor<lb break="no"/>ated'
                                          should be inserted in subsection A <lb/> of subsection 1
                                          of the Act. That motion <lb/> was not disposed of at the
                                          time the com<lb break="no"/>mittee rose and asked leave to
                                          sit again. <lb/> I would like to draw attention to that
                                          clause <lb/> of the Bill before it is passed over, or
                                          <lb/> before any other clause is taken up. Now <lb/>
                                          objection was taken seriously by many <lb/> members that a
                                          labour union or association <lb/> acquiring rights under
                                          this Bill to register- <lb break="yes"/> trade marks or
                                          designs of their own, were <lb/> not amenable to the
                                          common law, or to the [...]
                                   </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>