<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1889-02-27"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1889-02-27">27 February 1889</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1889"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="348" to="352"/>
               <biblScope unit="page" from="354" to="357"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00348.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00349.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00350.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00351.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00352.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00354.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00355.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00356.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00357.html"/> 
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00348">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00348.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00349">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00349.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00350">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00350.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00351">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00351.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00352">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00352.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00354">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00354.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00355">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00355.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00356">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00356.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00357">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00357.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="348" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00348.jpg"/>
            
           
     <fw type="num">348</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 27,</fw> 
     
           
   
          
     <head rendition="simple:centre">LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY OF THE NORTH-WEST 
     <lb/>
     TERRITORIES.</head> 
     
           
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName> moved for: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Copies of all memorials addressed to the Government by the Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive Assembly of the North-West Territories which sat recently at 
     <lb/>
     Regina. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     He said : In making this motion I desire to occupy the 
     <lb/>
     time of the House for a few moments, and that the House 
     <lb/>
     listen, not to my words, but to the voice of what, without a 
     <lb/>
     figure of speech, may be properly called a New World. 
     <lb/>
     It has been opened up by you, and it is under your charge. 
     <lb/>
     It is some six years since that greater Canada was opened 
     <lb/>
     up by a railway, a railway which not merely opens up that 
     <lb/>
     great territory, but constitutes a highway for the world. 
     <lb/>
     It is a railway which will always be connected with the 
     <lb/>
     name of the right hon. gentleman, and had he nothing else 
     <lb/>
     upon which his fame might rest, that railway would secure 
     <lb/>
     his memory. It is a railway that realises the dreams of 
     <lb/>
     great and enthusiastic men. Lachine, near Montreal, 
     <lb/>
     marks the object of one, and the English Franklin aimed at 
     <lb/>
     doing, and gave his life in trying to do, what this great 
     <lb/>
     work has accomplished for the world. Now, Sir, six years 
     <lb/>
     ago I witnessed the opening of the first North-West Council, 
     <lb/>
     not the first North-West Council held in the Territory, but 
     <lb/>
     the first held at Regina. That council was crude, but in 
     <lb/>
     the succeeding years it did good work and laid the founda<lb break="no"/>tion of our educational and municipal systems, and our 
     <lb/>
     criminal and civil jurisprudence. At that time Brandon, 
     <lb/>
     which is now a flourishing city, whence we get one of our 
     <lb/>
     ablest members of this House, the hon. member for Selkirk 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Daly)—at that time Brandon was crude, and I re<lb break="no"/>member that my hon. friend welcomed us to a test club.<lb/>
     
            
            <pb n="349" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00349.jpg"/>
        
     <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">349</fw> 
     
   
         
     Earlier than that time, a little over six years ago, Calgary 
     <lb/>
     had no existence-it was merely Fort Calgary; Medicine 
     <lb/>
     Hat had no existence, Moose Jaw had no existence, 
     <lb/>
     and none of the flourishing little towns that stretch 
     <lb/>
     across the prairie now, had any existence. The 
     <lb/>
     prairie itself was practically virgin of the plough. Now 
     <lb/>
     it produces millions of bushels of grain, and we ex<lb break="no"/>ported such quantities of grain the year before last, as to 
     <lb/>
     almost embarrass the Canadian Pacific Railway. Not only 
     <lb/>
     so, but coal mines have come into existence, sawmills, flour 
     <lb/>
     mills, cheese factories, dairies. Ranching and horse raising 
     <lb/>
     are carried on to a very large extent, and the day is at 
     <lb/>
     hand when we shall have smelting and reducing works 
     <lb/>
     there, and there is no reason why, at this moment, we 
     <lb/>
     should not have tanneries flourishing in Regina, Moose 
     <lb/>
     Jaw and Calgary. Every year at Calgary you have 10,000 
     <lb/>
     hides, and 3,000 sheep-skins, so tanning could be carried 
     <lb/>
     forward successfully. The council has, within a short time, 
     <lb/>
     owing to the action of Parliament last year, grown into a 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Assembly. That Assembly sat last year, and I 
     <lb/>
     am only echoing the language of persons who visited it from 
     <lb/>
               the east, when it was in session, in stating that that As<lb break="no"/>sembly need not fear comparison with any Provincial As<lb break="no"/>sembly in the Dominion in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">personnel</hi> of its members, 
     <lb/>
     in their intelligence, and in the zeal with which they give 
     <lb/>
     themselves to legislation. During that time the Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Interior presided over the destinies of that country, and took 
     <lb/>
     a deep interest in its welfare, and it is due to him to say, 
     <lb/>
     that the educational progress we have made has been largely 
     <lb/>
     due to the great interest he took in education in the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. I ask without fear the attention of members of this 
     <lb/>
     House for that portion of the Dominion, because I 
     <lb/>
     think this House is now sensible that in that vast and 
     <lb/>
     fertile region we have the solution of the difficulty in the 
     <lb/>
     way of Canada becoming one day, however distant, a self-<lb break="yes"/>contained nation. As regards the settlers who are in that 
     <lb/>
     prairie region, I will say this for them, that there are not 
     <lb/>
     in the whole Empire men more calculated by reason of 
     <lb/>
     their intelligence, morality and business qualities to lay the 
     <lb/>
     foundations of a great and prosperous community. They 
     <lb/>
     are all energetic, most of them are reading men, some are 
     <lb/>
     cultured men, and there is no doubt whatever, that the free 
     <lb/>
     and independent hearing which characterises the men in 
     <lb/>
     the North-West is due in part, possibly wholly, to their 
     <lb/>
     free surroundings. It may be that even the associations of 
     <lb/>
     the North-West have some influence on them. The associa<lb break="no"/>tions connected with the North-West are of the most 
     <lb/>
     inspiring kind, for though a new land, it is a land which 
     <lb/>
     has historical associations of which people can never read 
     <lb/>
     or think of without enthusiasm. Some 150 years ago Pierre 
     <lb/>
     Gauthier de Varennes traversed those very regions, and 
     <lb/>
     Forts Du Pas, Fort du Grands Rapide, at the Rapids of the 
     <lb/>
     Saskatchewan, Fort La Corne, and other places familiar to 
     <lb/>
     North-West travellers, are among their footmarks that are 
     <lb/>
     living yet. That prairie region alone contains 123,000 square 
     <lb/>
     miles, reaching up from the arid plateau of the Missouri to the 
     <lb/>
     forests of the Saskatchewan and stretching away from Mani<lb break="no"/>toba to the foot of the Rocky Mountains. That whole region 
     <lb/>
     maybe described as one vast wheat mine. There can be no 
     <lb/>
     doubt in the mind of any man who knows that country 
     <lb/>
     that it is destined to be the great wheat-producing region 
     <lb/>
     of the future. My hon. friends from Hamilton visited the 
     <lb/>
     country last year. Both of them went north and south and 
     <lb/>
     saw what sort of a country was there. The correspondent of 
     <lb/>
               the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Empire</hi>, Professor Dawson, visited the country, and pro<lb break="no"/>bably some hon. members have read his letters about the 
     <lb/>
     country; but my hon. friends from Hamilton, with visitors 
     <lb/>
     from Ontario, at an earlier period, saw with wonder 
     <lb/>
     the extraordinary crops produced. It is not merely, 
     <lb/>
     as I have already stated, a wheat-producing country. We 
     <lb/>
     have farmers in every part of the North-West who are also 
     <lb/>
     engaged in stock raising. If you go north of Regina or 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     Moose Jaw, you will find farmers who came in there with<lb break="no"/>out $100, as they will tell you, owning herds with 
     <lb/>
     nearly their whole homestead cultivated. In the Qu'Apelle 
     <lb/>
     valley you will find several herds increasing at an a most 
     <lb/>
     mathematical ratio every year, and horse ranching south of 
     <lb/>
     Regina is most successful. I have here a pamphlet just 
     <lb/>
     issued by the Regina board of trade. I will not trouble the 
     <lb/>
     House with the details contained in this pamphlet. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MITC2">Mr. MITCHELL</persName>. Read it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I will not read it, even though that desire 
     <lb/>
     be expressed by the Third Party without a single dissenting 
     <lb/>
     voice, but I will give the House some idea of the character 
     <lb/>
     of the pamphlet. On page 13, there is the testimony of 
     <lb/>
     Rebert Green, who came to the country without very much 
     <lb/>
     money, and who is now a prosperous man. He says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "This year (1888) I had eighty acres cropped as follows: Wheat— 
     <lb/>
     29 acres, yielding 30 bushels per acre, which will grade No. 1. Oats— 
     <lb/>
     48 acres, yielding 60 bushels per acre, first-class quality and weighing 
     <lb/>
     42 lbs. per bushel. Potatoes (Early Rose) —3 acres, yielding 350 
     <lb/>
     bushels per acre. The binding of the grain averaged 3 lbs. of binding 
     <lb/>
     twine per acre. I have also a garden consisting of one acre of land on 
     <lb/>
     which I raised cabbages, cauliflower, turnips, beets, mangolds, &amp;c., 
     <lb/>
     which for size and quality may be equalled but not excelled in any 
     <lb/>
     agricultural district in the world." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     Then there is the testimony of Charles Martin to the same 
     <lb/>
     effect. Then there is the testimony of Walter Simpson, 
     <lb/>
     who spoke in a like manner. Adam Traynor, who spoke in 
     <lb/>
     a similar strain, said: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "I broke 100 acres here in 1888 with a gang plow drawn by four to 
     <lb/>
     seven oxen, the dryest season we have had since the place was settled 
     <lb/>
     and backsat 70 acres of the same, besides doing what other work I 
     <lb/>
     had to do. Cool days I broke 3 1/2 acres per day, but my average during 
     <lb/>
     the month of June was about 3 acres per day in backsetting about seven 
     <lb/>
     to eight inches deep with six to seven oxen, I averaged about 2 1/2 acres per 
     <lb/>
     day, on half mile furrows. I have my homestead all broke but about 
     <lb/>
     three-quarters of an acre where my house and granary stand, and nearly 
     <lb/>
     finished backsetting." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            
            <p>
     He goes on to give like testimony to the fruitfulness of the 
     <lb/>
     soil. J. W. Reynolds, eighteen miles north of Regina, ad<lb break="no"/>vises young men to go to the country. He says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
  <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "Yes; I like the country, climate good, health ditto; going to have 
     <lb/>
     school house right on my farm; Regina and Long Lake Railway runs 
     <lb/>
     across corner of my land. Have oxen, ten head of cattle, farm imple<lb break="no"/>ments, good farm house. Just thrashed, wheat gone over thirty bushels 
     <lb/>
     to the acre, No. 1 hard at that, and no frost. I think this is the country 
     <lb/>
     for good practical farmers, would like to see every half section taken 
     <lb/>
     up, and have no hesitation in advising energetic young men to come 
     <lb/>
    here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

  </quote>
   
            <p>
     Neil Martin gives similar testimony. Then we have the 
     <lb/>
     testimony of a Crofter, Donald McFayden, a hardy Scotch. 
     <lb/>
     man of 57 years, who makes the following statement: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "I came to the Regina district on July 15th, 1887. I am located on 
     <lb/>
     Section 34, Township 20, Range 19. I have a wife and five children; 
     <lb/>
     built a good log house 19x15 last year; put in ten acres this spring on 
     <lb/>
     breaking; it is a beautiful crop. We have a good school house and a 
     <lb/>
     Scotch minister in our midst. When I landed in the country from Scot<lb break="no"/>land I had no money. I like the country well, have good health, and I 
     <lb/>
     can in good conscience advise all in my native country who are not 
     <lb/>
     doing well to come to this country. All the Crofters in this section are 
     <lb/>
     doing well and like the country very much." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     James Bole tells us : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "This year, 1888, I had 105 acres under crop (eighty acres wheat, 
     <lb/>
     twenty oats and five barley, potatoes and rye). The wheat on new land 
     <lb/>
     yielded thirty-five bushels to the acre, and took four lbs. of binding 
     <lb/>
     twine per acre. The oats were the finest I ever saw, standing nearly 
     <lb/>
     five feet high all over the field, and yielded eighty bushels to the 
     <lb/>
     acre,—this was fourteen acres on old land, part of which was cropped 
     <lb/>
     three years and part five years in succession. I had six acres of oats 
     <lb/>
               harrowed in on stubble <hi rendition="simple:italic">without ploughing</hi>. This is a style of farming 
     <lb/>
     I do not approve of, but the spring was very late and I thought I would 
     <lb/>
     try it and grow green fodder if nothing else, but to my surprise it came 
     <lb/>
     on as thick and looked as well as any of the crop in the district; the 
     <lb/>
     field is not yet thrashed, but I feel confident the six acres will yield 500 
     <lb/>
     bushels. Mr. Ira Morgan, president of the Ontario Agricultural and 
     <lb/>
     Arts Association, who saw this field while standing, and Mr. McDonald, 
     <lb/>
     editor Mark Lane Express, who saw it in the sheaf, can testify to the 
     <lb/>
     correctness of this statement. My wheat this year grades No. 1 hard, 
     <lb/>
     and I have already sold 800 bushels to Regina dealers from $1.06 to 
     <lb/>
     $1.11 per bushel.
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " At the present time I have seven horses and a small start in 
     <lb/>
     thoroughbred cattle; seven hogs ready for pork by Christmas, a binder, 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="350" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00350.jpg"/>
            
      
      <fw type="num">350</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 27,</fw>
            
          
     sulky plough,  two hand ploughs, two waggons,  sleighs, harness, a 
     <lb/>
     small house, comfortable stable, good well of water, and everything 
     <lb/>
     else necessary, all of which are paid for or at least provided for, and 
     <lb/>
     will have at least a thousand dollars additional to further improve the 
     <lb/>
     farm, enlarge the house and stables, and provide comforts which pioneer 
     <lb/>
     days did not afford. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      "Considering that I am now past 60 years of age, and that I started 
     <lb/>
     without capital (having lost my farm in Ontario by endorsing and sub<lb break="no"/>sequent business failure), I think I can with clear conscience advise 
     <lb/>
     every man of sober habits and a determination to succeed to come to 
     <lb/>
     this country. Farming is pleasant, and to every man who knows his 
     <lb/>
     business and attends to it, is profitable. No forests to cut down, no 
     <lb/>
     draining, no taxes, as nature has given us good roads, everything man 
     <lb/>
     could desire is here for the man who desires to use them." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     John McIntyre, a brother of Mr. Duncan McIntyre, 
     <lb/>
     who has a very large farm, gives similar testimony. 
     <lb/>
     Thomas Barton, an Englishman whose farm I have visited 
     <lb/>
     myself, corroborates this. Mr. Barton's farm is certainly 
     <lb/>
     one of the most interesting places that one could visit, 
     <lb/>
     because it is a piece of England transferred to the wilds of 
     <lb/>
     the west. He has a cottage buried in flowers, and it is hard, 
     <lb/>
     when sitting in his parlor and looking at the wealth of 
     <lb/>
     flowers around you, to realise that you are in a cottage 
     <lb/>
     which was raised there five or six years ago when all was 
     <lb/>
     a wilderness around. Mr. Barton says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "This year I invested in a threshing machine, and for the past month 
     <lb/>
     have been threshing in the district, and I can testify to the great pro<lb break="no"/>ductiveness of the soil. Have just got through at Mr. Henry Fisher's 
     <lb/>
     farm, where we threshed over 8,000 bushels of grain. Wheat is yield<lb break="no"/>ing all the way from 22 to 42 bushels to the acre, and oats from 50 to 
     <lb/>
     90, and in a few cases, on my own farm, for example, over 100. I find 
     <lb/>
     Regina a good market for all kinds of farm produce, grain, butter, eggs, 
     <lb/>
     pork, and fat cattle always find ready sale. As to how I like the 
     <lb/>
     country, I say first-class. If a man works hard, and is a good manager, 
     <lb/>
     he wil get rich quicker farming than in any other country in the world 
     <lb/>
     that I know anything about. All branches of farming can be carried on, 
     <lb/>
     dairying, cattle raising, wheat growing. Large areas of land can 
     <lb/>
     be put under cultivation in a short time, and there is plenty of pasture 
     <lb/>
     to start as big a herd of cattle as a man likes. Don't think I have any 
     <lb/>
     more to say, unless I might add that this appears to me to be the right 
     <lb/>
     country for good, hard working men, who are hung in the old country 
     <lb/>
     from hand to mouth. To all such I say, sell all you have and come out 
     <lb/>
     here and start over again. If you are not a practical farmer, you will 
     <lb/>
     soon learn, if you are willing to learn and willing to work. Hoping, 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen, you will succeed in getting us more neighbors." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     So, Sir, I could mention case after case. There is a gentle<lb break="no"/>man here at present, Mr. Carss, who was a Carleton farmer 
     <lb/>
     well-known in this district, and he is now one of the most 
     <lb/>
     successful men in the whole North-West. He has a large 
     <lb/>
     herd, farms extensively, and has probably made some 
     <lb/>
     $20,000 in the North-West. He is here at the present 
     <lb/>
     moment, speaking to his friends in Carleton and giving 
     <lb/>
     them some idea of the Land of Promise where he himself 
     <lb/>
     has succeeded so well. A moment ago I spoke about the 
     <lb/>
     schools in the North-West, and I shall now refer to them 
     <lb/>
     again. This House will be glad to know that in that new 
     <lb/>
     region opened up six years ago we have 167 schools at the 
     <lb/>
    present time; the teachers are carefully examined, they 
     <lb/>have to have certificates just as your teachers have here; 
     <lb/>and as I have visited many of the schools I can bear testi<lb break="no"/>mony to their great efficiency. I would like to impress on 
     <lb/>the Government, and especially on the Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior, that I really think a step might be taken further in 
     <lb/>the matter of education and something done in the way of 
     <lb/>having a high school at some central place. The children 
     <lb/>that went to our ordinary schools six years ago have now 
     <lb/>grown beyond the teachers, and we ought to have a high 
     <lb/>school for them. I spoke to you a moment ago about that 
     <lb/>Assembly which has charge of so important a part of our 
     <lb/>interests. It has very wide powers now and it is gliding into 
     <lb/>responsible government. That Assembly passed a number 
     <lb/>of memorials which it desired should be brought before this 
     <lb/>House. I do not intend to occupy your time at any great 
     <lb/>length, and I will rapidly describe what those memorials are. 
     <lb/>The first relates to a subject which need not be impressed 
     <lb/>upon any hon. member: it is the necessity of opening up as 
     <lb/>rapidly as possible the Saskatchewan district by railway 
     <lb/>communication. I believe the Government have done 
     <lb/>

            <cb/>
           
     their part in this matter and that we shall soon have a 
     <lb/>
     railway opening up the Saskatchewan territory. It is a 
     <lb/>
     district of the North-West which is, if anything, more 
     <lb/>
     attractive than even our prairies along the line, because it 
     <lb/>
     is varied with hill and forest and stream, and the House 
     <lb/>
     will easily understand what an attractive place for immi<lb break="no"/>gration it will be when a railway gives facilities for the 
     <lb/>
     ingress of immigrants and for the egress of the crops and 
     <lb/>
     products which they grow. Of course, at the present mo<lb break="no"/>ment there is no encouragement to settlers to grow crops, 
     <lb/>
     because, if they grow them, they have no market within 
     <lb/>
     reach. The next memorial relates to what are called 
     <lb/>
     the loyal half-breeds. I do not know much about the 
     <lb/>
     subject myself, but my hon. friend from Saskatchewan (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Macdowall) will be better acquainted with the particulars. 
     <lb/>
     It is contended that there were some loyal half-breeds 
     <lb/>
     who suffered losses, and, notwithstanding their loyalty, their 
     <lb/>
     losses have not been recouped. The Assembly now pray 
     <lb/>
     that His Excellency will be authorised to have such steps 
     <lb/>
     taken as will cause a reconsideration of the whole subject 
     <lb/>
     of the claims of half-breeds for losses during the rebel<lb break="no"/>lion, with a view to compensate those who proved them<lb break="no"/>selves to have been loyal, with such amounts as may 
     <lb/>
     be shown to be equal to their losses. The next memorial 
     <lb/>
     relates to providing seed grain for any person in a part of 
     <lb/>
     the North-West Territories whose crops may have failed. 
     <lb/>
     In the district with which I am connected there have been 
     <lb/>
     no failures whatever, and I am not aware of any failure in 
     <lb/>
     crops along the line. But I suppose there must have been 
     <lb/>
     failure in some districts, or this resolution would not have 
     <lb/>
     been passed by the Assembly. I come now to a resolution 
     <lb/>
     which deals with a burning question in the North- <lb break="yes"/>West, that is the liquor question. Ever since I went 
     <lb/>
     in there that question has created great restlessness, 
     <lb/>and I think myself it has created unreasonable restless<lb break="no"/>ness when we remember that no man went into 
     <lb/>the territory without knowing that it was a prohibitory 
     <lb/>territory. Every man that went there knew that prohibi<lb break="no"/>tion obtained, and as I have often said to some of my 
     <lb/>friends who grumbled very loudly on this subject, it was 
     <lb/>one on which they had no right to grumble about, because 
     <lb/>they knew it was a prohibitory territory when they went 
     <lb/>in there. Notwithstanding this, however, the question has 
     <lb/>created a great deal of feeling. The settlers somehow seem 
     <lb/>to think it hard that they had to ask a permit from anyone, 
     <lb/>and I have heard men, because they were refused a permit, 
     <lb/>talk as though they had good grounds for flat rebellion. I 
     <lb/>will say this in passing: The hon. gentleman who is Minis<lb break="no"/>ter of Interior, and who had the administering of that 
     <lb/>permit system, had one of the most difficult tasks to per<lb break="no"/>form that any man could undertake. No one course would 
     <lb/>please everybody, and to do one's duty in refusing a permit 
     <lb/>to men who ought not to get it was sure to make enemies. 
     <lb/>I always sympathised with the hon. gentleman in the difficult 
     <lb/>task he had to perform in dealing with that permit system. 
     <lb/>Now, here is the position at present. The four per cent. 
     <lb/>beer has been admitted wholesale by a special permit. It is 
     <lb/>not strong enough for some people, and it is too strong for 
     <lb/>others; the consequence is that there is a great desire to 
     <lb/>have this question settled, both on the part of those in favor 
     <lb/>of high license and on the part of those strictly temperance 
     <lb/>people who would like to see prohibition established, even 
     <lb/>unqualified by permit. There is a great deal to be said in 
     <lb/>favor of settling this question rapidly. In the first place, 
     <lb/>we can grow in the North-West the finest barley that ever 
     <lb/>rewarded farmer's toil, and beer and whiskey are both 
     <lb/>brought in from outside. Over 7,000 gallons of whiskey 
     <lb/>was brought in last year by permit, yielding a revenue of 
     <lb/>over 83,000 from permits; and yet the amount of whiskey 
     <lb/>brought in contraband from Montana Colonel Herchmer 
     <lb/>will tell you, is simply incalculable. Parties bring it in, 
     <lb/>cache it two miles from the town, and on moonlight nights 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="351" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00351.jpg"/>
            
               
             <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">351</fw>
            
           
     go out and bring it in in small quantities. In this way a 
     <lb/>
     large amount of money is being sent out of the territory, 
     <lb/>
     while beer is being brought in and drunk which we could 
     <lb/>
     manufacture there. Again, we had manufacturies of what 
     <lb/>
     is called Moose Jaw beer, a kind of beer made from hops, 
     <lb/>
     without malt in it. The four per cent. beer coming from 
     <lb/>
     Winnipeg has shut all these up. Mr. Allen, the son of 
     <lb/>
     a Toronto brewer, had $10.000 or $12,000 invested in a 
     <lb/>
     brewery at Moose Jaw, and this man has been ruined by 
     <lb/>
     this four per cent. beer coming in. Now, what is to be done? 
     <lb/>
     There is a great desire on the part of many people for a 
     <lb/>
     plebiscite, but a plebiscite is not known to the British con<lb break="no"/>stitution, and it might be a doubtful way of settling this 
     <lb/>
     matter. Let me tell you that Mr. Bliss, who is at the head 
     <lb/>
     of one of the temperance organisations, visited the North-<lb break="yes"/>West last summer, and stop at Medicine Hat, Calgary, 
     <lb/>
     and other places; and after returning to Winnipeg he issued 
     <lb/>
     a pronunciamento in which he said that it was of vital im<lb break="no"/>portance that the liquor question should be settled in the 
     <lb/>
     North-West Territory, and that the morals of the com<lb break="no"/>munity required that it should be settled—how? By pro<lb break="no"/>hibition? No, but by high license. This Mr. Bliss will, 
     <lb/>
     no doubt, be known to my hon. friend from Norfolk. The 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Assembly proposed themselves to take the 
     <lb/>
     opinion of the people on the subject, and to pay the cost of 
     <lb/>
     doing so out of their own funds; but the judges whom they 
     <lb/>
               consulted told them that would be <hi rendition="simple:italic">ultra vires</hi>. Then they 
     <lb/>
     passed this resolution : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That, in the opinion of this Assembly, a vote of the Territories on 
     <lb/>
     the question of license vs. prohibition should immediately be taken. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That in the event of provision for the taking of such vote not being 
     <lb/>
    made by the Dominion authorities at the next Session of the Dominion 
     <lb/>Parliament, it is the opinion of this assembly that powers similar to 
     <lb/>those enjoyed by provisions under the British North American Act in 
     <lb/>respect to the liquor question should forthwith be granted." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
</quote>
            <p>Of course, if the power were granted before they could 
     <lb/>legislate, one of two things should be done. They should 
     <lb/>not be allowed to use the power until after their term ex<lb break="no"/>pired and they went to the country, or a dissolution should 
     <lb/>take place, in order that they might go to the country, and 
     <lb/>have the question decided at the polls. That would, no 
     <lb/>doubt, be a constitutional course; and, as we have practi<lb break="no"/>cally manhood suffrage in the Territories, such a vote would 
     <lb/>effect the same purpose as a plebiscite. The next resolution 
     <lb/>deals With a matter of the greatest possible moment to the 
     <lb/>Territories, immigration, and makes suggestions: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "Your Committee would further recommend that a sum of $5,000 
     <lb/>
     be voted from the general revenue fund of the Territories, and that this 
     <lb/>
     House, by every means at its disposal, press upon the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment the advisability of granting us the sum of $10,000; both of said 
     <lb/>
     sums to be used for immigration purposes. With such sums at the dis<lb break="no"/>posal of this House, your Committee are of the opinion that greater 
     <lb/>
     results would be had, both to the Dominion as a whole, and to these 
     <lb/>
     Territories in particular, than can be had by the expenditure of a like 
     <lb/>
     sum under the general immigration schemes of the Dominion. We 
     <lb/>
     would suggest that two permanent officials, selected by this House, be 
     <lb/>
     located in Great Britain; also that four agents be appointed by this 
     <lb/>
     House, one being from each of the Dominion electoral districts, who 
     <lb/>
     shall be located for a period of three months at four of the principal 
     <lb/>
     points in Eastern Canada and the United States, as, say, Montreal, Que<lb break="no"/>bec, Toronto and Chicago. We would further suggest that several 
     <lb/>pamphlets be prepared, giving a full description of the various localities 
     <lb/>suitable for settlement within these vast Territories, believing, as we 
     <lb/>do, that it is impossible in a single pamphlet to do justice to the varied 
     <lb/>natural resources of our Territories. We would report that we have 
     <lb/>made an estimate of the probable cost of the scheme. We propose, as 
     <lb/>follows :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
   
   
         </div>
   <div type="debate">
      
      <head><hi rendition="simple:italic">Salaries.</hi></head>
      
   <table>
      <row><cell>Two permanent officials in Great Britain, at $100 per 
     <lb/>month, each ................. .... ......... ...........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$3,400</cell></row>
      <row><cell>Four men located in Eastern Canada and Chicago, 
     <lb/>three months, at $100 per month............... ......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,200</cell></row>
   </table>
            
   </div>
         <div type="debate">
            
            <head><hi rendition="simple:italic">Travelling Expenses.</hi></head>
            
            <table>
               <row><cell>Two oflicials in Great Britain, at $5 per day, each...</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">3,600</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Four agents in Eastern Canada, at $5 per day, each..</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,800</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Office expenses ... ....  ... ...... ................................... ...... ...</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,000</cell></row>
               <row><cell>Preparing and printing pamphlets ........ ........ .......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">4,000</hi></cell></row>
               <row><cell>Total ...................................................................................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$15,000</cell></row>
            </table>
            
            
            <cb/>
            <p>
     The Government will perceive that they propose to give 
     <lb/>
     out of their own revenue $5,000, if $10,000 is given for the 
     <lb/>
     same purpose by the Dominion. Now, Sir, I cannot help 
     <lb/>
     thinking that greater benefits would result if the Local 
     <lb/>
     Government had to deal with this matter, and not the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. The Department of Agriculture will necessarily 
     <lb/>
     deal very generally with the question of immigration; but 
     <lb/>
     if we had local agents controlled by the Advisory Board 
     <lb/>
     in Regina, their action would be focussed in certain 
     <lb/>
     channels, and the immigrants' attention would be directed, 
     <lb/>
     not to the North-West in a vague way, but to particular 
     <lb/>
     parts of the North-West having special attractions, and 
     <lb/>
     they would be put on board the train at Halifax and sent 
     <lb/>
     on to these destinations. The next resolution relates to 
     <lb/>
     half-breeds: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "The Assembly recommends that granting of scrip to half-breeds of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba and the North-West Territories be extended to such half-<lb break="yes"/>breed heads of families and their children who, on the 15th day of July, 
     <lb/>
     1870, were resident of non-ceded territory, and who have since moved 
     <lb/>
     to either Manitoba or the North-West Territories." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "The Assembly would further recommend that half-breeds residing 
     <lb/>
     in the North-West Territories on the 20th April, 1885, who were other<lb break="no"/>wise entitled to scrip, but who failed to comply with the conditions of 
     <lb/>
     the Order in Council of the 20th April, 1885, be granted scrip notwith<lb break="no"/>standing such Order in Council. As under the Half-breed Commission 
     <lb/>
     of the 20th of March, 1885, the Indian title, in so far as the half-breeds 
     <lb/>
     are concerned, only extends to those born prior to the 15th July, 1870, 
     <lb/>
     and as a number have been born to parents coming under the said com<lb break="no"/>mision of 1885, who, in the opinion of this Assembly, have equal rights 
     <lb/>
     to those already dealt with, this Assembly would draw the attention of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion Government to the fact and urge that steps be taken to 
     <lb/>
     finally end all half-breed claims. This Assembly would also urge the 
     <lb/>
     appointment of judges of the North-West Territories as permanent com<lb break="no"/>missioners, to adjust and investigate halt-breed claims, as the system of 
     <lb/>
     the flying commission is very unsatisfactory to the people and unneces<lb break="no"/>sarily expensive to the Government." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     Now, I would state this argument to the House. Under 
     <lb/>
     the Manitoba Act of 1870, 1,400,000 acres of land were set 
     <lb/>
     apart for half-breed children. These did not extend out<lb break="no"/>side of Manitoba. Therefore, the primitive contract made 
     <lb/>
     between the Government and the half-breeds did not ex<lb break="no"/>tend outside of Manitoba, or to any other half-breeds or 
     <lb/>
     bands of half-breeds. We acknowledge the Indian title in 
     <lb/>
     the half-breed; we acknowledge that he has the Indian title. 
     <lb/>
     When we come to extinguish the Indian title with a band 
     <lb/>
     of Indians, what do we do? We make a treaty with them. 
     <lb/>
     We do not insist that Treaty six shall do for what we after<lb break="no"/>wards call Treaty seven. We do not insist that a treaty 
     <lb/>
     with the Blackfeet will do for a treaty with the Crees, but 
     <lb/>
     we act, as do sensible men in ordinary life; we deal frankly 
     <lb/>
     with the persons with whom we have to deal, in regard to 
     <lb/>
     the interests they control. Those half-breeds in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West were not in Manitoba at the time the Manitoba Act 
     <lb/>
     was passed, and the arrangement made to extinguish the 
     <lb/>
     Indian title in Manitoba. As we took no steps—and 
     <lb/>
     it was our fault that we took none—to extinguish the title 
     <lb/>
     in 1870 of the half-breeds in the North- West, and did noth<lb break="no"/>ing in 1885, how can we say to the half-breeds in the 
     <lb/>
     North-West in 1885: Now, we are going to deal with you as 
     <lb/>
     though on had been dealt with already in 1870 in Mani<lb break="no"/>toba. Iy could never see the reason which would justify 
     <lb/>
     that position being taken, and I am perfectly certain 
     <lb/>
     the matter has only to be brought to the attention of Par<lb break="no"/>liament and the Government to lead them to do what is 
     <lb/>
     statesmanlike and proper—to lead them to deal with the 
     <lb/>
     half-breeds to-day who were not in Manitoba and were not 
     <lb/>
     dealt with at that time, on the looting of the present, 
     <lb/>
     and on the same principle on which was based the 
     <lb/>
     settlement with the half-breeds in Manitoba, and give to the 
     <lb/>
     children that exist today what was given to the children 
     <lb/>
     in 1870. As a fact, the name of every half-breed child born 
     <lb/>
     in the country, up to the 20th April, 1885, is on record in 
     <lb/>
     the Department of the Interior, so that it is not necessary 
     <lb/>
     to do more than look into the affidavits. Then comes the 
     <lb/>
     third resolution in regard to the question of scrip : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="352" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00352.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="num">352</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 27,</fw> 
    
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That the Dominion Government be requested to grant scrip to all 
     <lb/>
     those acting during the North-West rebellion as scouts under the Police 
     <lb/>
     Act." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     I am happy to state that this matter of scrip, which has so 
     <lb/>
     often occupied our attention, is on the way to be satisfac<lb break="no"/>torily settled by the Government. The next resolution re<lb break="no"/>lates to a body of men which is a credit to Canada. 
     <lb/>
     No Canadian visits the North-West without feeling 
     <lb/>
     proud of the Mounted Police. We have had English gen<lb break="no"/>eral officers visiting the North-West, and they looked 
     <lb/>
     with envy on that body of 1,100 men, each one of 
     <lb/>
     whom would be a model for a statue. These men 
     <lb/>
     who took part in putting down the rebellion, fought, 
     <lb/>
     when they had the opportunity, as gallantly as did the 
     <lb/>
     volunteers. They endured hardship, they did everything 
     <lb/>
     they had an opportunity of doing, and all they complain of 
     <lb/>
     is that they did not get more opportunity; and if they 
     <lb/>
     had had more opportunity, I believe we might have brought 
     <lb/>
     the rebellion to a close more rapidly and not less gloriously. 
     <lb/>
     Many of these policemen endured hardships, and it is no 
     <lb/>
     new thing for them to endure hardships. Their whole life, 
     <lb/>
     especially in the winter, is one of continuous strain, and 
     <lb/>
     there is no soldier's life as trying as the life of the Mounted 
     <lb/>
     Police, in the winter, up in the North-West. The Assembly 
     <lb/>
     passed this resolution: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "We would beg leave, respectfully, to point out that in great measure 
     <lb/>
     the services of this force were insufficiently appreciated in Canada, that 
     <lb/>
     the arguments advanced against their receiving such awards are, in our 
     <lb/>
     opinion, to a great extent, fallacious, and that we are confident such a 
     <lb/>
    bestowal will be hailed throughout the North-West as a satisfaction, 
     <lb/>and as an act of justice." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>
     What they ask for is the same award of scrip as has been 
     <lb/>
     conferred on other corps, but I can tell you that many of 
     <lb/>
     the mounted police have told me they cared very little for 
     <lb/>
     scrip, but that certainly, as they had borne the brunt and 
     <lb/>
     heat of the day as well as others, they would like to have 
     <lb/>
     it; but they should also have a medal. Then comes a reso<lb break="no"/>lution with regard to the main trails. I do not expect to 
     <lb/>
     be able to clear up the mystery of the main trails and to 
     <lb/>
     enlighten Parliament on this recondite subject. The trails 
     <lb/>
     are from Macleod to Calgary, from Calgary to Edmonton 
     <lb/>
     and Athabasca Landing, from Swift Current to Battleford, 
     <lb/>
     and from Qu'Appelle to Prince Albert. These trails will 
     <lb/>
     require for some time to be kept in good order, and the 
     <lb/>
     Assembly reports: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "The condition of some of these trails at certain seasons of the year 
     <lb/>
     has proved to be dangerous to life and property, and communication 
     <lb/>
     between the different settlements made most difficult and supplies 
     <lb/>
     not only rendered much dearer but in fact almost impossible to obtain. 
     <lb/>
     Such a condition of affairs is a most important element in retarding 
     <lb/>
     settlement and the proper development of the Territories, and as the 
     <lb/>
     funds at the disposal of the Territorial Government are insufficient to 
     <lb/>
     make the necessary improvements and we consider the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment especially interested in those trails, we would therefore urge 
     <lb/>
     that the Dominion Government appropriate a special sum to be expen<lb break="no"/>ded on the following trails: From Macleod to Calgary. From Calgary 
     <lb/>
     to Edmonton and Athabasca Landing. From Swift Current to Battle<lb break="no"/>ford. From Qu'Appelle to Prince Albert." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>
     Now I come to a great question in the North-West. The 
     <lb/>
     resolution is very long but very important, which the 
     <lb/>
     council has passed, and I will ask the attention of hon. 
     <lb/>
     members while I read. It is as follows:—That it is desir<lb break="no"/>able, in the interest of the settlers and of the settlement in 
     <lb/>
     the Territories, that the time of payment for pre-emption in 
     <lb/>
     arrears should be extended five years from the 1st of 
     <lb/>
     January, 1889, without interest, and on condition that 
     <lb/>
     homesteaders remain on and continuously cultivate their 
     <lb/>
     homesteads during that period: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That it would be only just to those who entered the lands in the 
     <lb/>
     Territories, during the operation of the Act permitting second home<lb break="no"/>steading, that the right to second homesteading should in all cases 
     <lb/>
     be extended to them, provided they have continuously cultivated their 
     <lb/>
     first homesteads. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That in the year 1885 a regulation was in force whereby persons en<lb break="no"/>tering for cancelled lands could secure only eighty acres or a home<lb break="no"/>stead and eighty acres as a pre-emption, and as this regulation was 
     <lb/>
        
            <cb/>
         
     acknowledged to be unwise and unjust by its withdrawal, settlers in 
     <lb/>
     such a disadvantageous position should be allowed the some rights and 
     <lb/>
     privileges as other bonafide settlers, by being granted a full quarter 
     <lb/>
     section as a homestead." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     The Assembly does not seem to be aware that in 1887 the 
     <lb/>
     late Minister of the Interior did away with the eighty acre 
     <lb/>
     homesteads and the eighty acre pre-emptions. What they 
     <lb/>
     do pray for, and what many contend should be done, is that 
     <lb/>
     those who have got the eighty acres homestead, and the 
     <lb/>
     eighty acres pre-emption, and have paid for the eighty 
     <lb/>
     acres pre-emption, should have the money returned, but 
     <lb/>
     since 1887 there have been no eighty acre pre-emptions or 
     <lb/>
     homesteads, the smallest being 160 acres. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That, whereas in the years 1884, 1885 and 1886 persons entering for 
     <lb/>
     lands that had been cancelled, were charged, in addition to an extra fee 
     <lb/>
     for inspection, besides value for improvements that had been made, also 
     <lb/>
     an additional price for pre-emptions, varying from 25 cents to $1 per 
     <lb/>
     acre, which additional price was demanded at the time of making entry; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "And, whereas there was no good reason, in the greater value of 
     <lb/>
     such lande, for the additional charge per acre; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Therefore, the prices of such pre-emptions should be reduced to the 
     <lb/>
     prices charged for uncancelled lands in the same districts; and moneys 
     <lb/>
     paid thereon should be applied to the payment of such pre-emptions at 
     <lb/>
     the said reduced price. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That, whereas it has been proved that, for the success of the settler, 
     <lb/>
     it is necessary for him to engage in both grain and stock raising, and 
     <lb/>
     it has been demonstrated that for this purpose the settler requires not 
     <lb/>
     less than 320 acres of land; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "And whereas from the fact that many settlers have been unable to 
     <lb/>
     pay for their pre-emptions, it has been shown that the prices for pre-<lb break="yes"/>emptions have been placed at too high a figure, thus practically depriving 
     <lb/>
     many homesteaders of the benefit of pre-emptions, which are essential 
     <lb/>
     for success in mixed farming; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That, in cases where pre-emptions have been cancelled during the 
     <lb/>
     past three years, because settlers were unable to pay for the same, these 
     <lb/>
     lands should not he held open for homesteading until the whole matter 
     <lb/>
     regarding pre-emptions has been further considered. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Therefore, it is advisable that the prices of pre-emptions be reduced 
     <lb/>
     to the following figures, viz.: For lands within twenty miles of an oper<lb break="no"/>ated railway, two dollars per acre, and for lands at a greater distance 
     <lb/>
     from an operated railway, one dollar per acre. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That, in the interests of the Territories, specially of the prairie 
     <lb/>
     districts, it is desirable that every possible encouragement should be 
     <lb/>
     given to tree-culture;
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Therefore, it is desirable that arrangements should be made, whereby 
     <lb/>
     tree planting, with continued and successful cultivation, should be 
     <lb/>
     permitted to stand in the place of grain cultivation, acre for acre, as 
     <lb/>
     fulfilment of homestead duties; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That, in paying for pro-eruption, tree planting be allowed to count 
     <lb/>
     at the rate of five cents for each tree planted by the settlers and found 
     <lb/>
     growing on their homestead or pre-emption for two years next preceding 
     <lb/>
     such payment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That the present system of having odd-numbered sections withdrawn 
     <lb/>
     for homesteadin is pernicious; that it is an injury to settlers, inasmuch 
     <lb/>
     as, preventing close settlement, it throws additional burdens on them 
     <lb/>
     for carrying on schools and for necessary improvements. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Above all, because the settlement of the land is of more value, and 
     <lb/>
     will bring more revenue into the Treasury, than the possible sale of 
     <lb/>
     lands thus withheld from settlement will, and because the throwing open 
     <lb/>
     or these sections for homesteading would be further inducement for 
     <lb/>
     emigrants to come to these Territories, seeing they would then be able 
     <lb/>
     to enjoy the advantages of close neighborhood to other settlers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That should it be found necessary in future to withhold public lands 
     <lb/>
     from homesteading for railway purposes, it would be well to provide 
     <lb/>
     that alternate quarter-sections be granted instead of alternate sections. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Therefore, it is advisable that arrangements be made, where pos<lb break="no"/>sible, to throw open all odd-numbered sections for homesteading, seeing 
     <lb/>
     that this would he in the true interests of the Territories, and also there<lb break="no"/>fore of the Dominion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That, as the large portion of the Dominion lands is in the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, it is most desirable, in the interest of the settler, the Territories 
     <lb/>
     and the Dominion, that a Dominion Land Board should be established 
     <lb/>
     at some central and convenient point in the Territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That His Honor the Lieutenant Governor will be pleased to transmit 
     <lb/>
     a memorial embodying this report so the proper authorities at Ottawa, 
     <lb/>
     for the consideration of His Excellency the Governor General in 
     <lb/>
    Council."
     <lb/>
            </p>

   </quote>
   
            <p>
     I have troubled the House with reading this long document 
     <lb/>
     to them, but it is so important, and deals with matters which 
     <lb/>
     are so important for the settlers, that I may be excused. 
     <lb/>
     Remember, it is the voice of an Assembly elected by a suf<lb break="no"/>frage practically extending to every man over twenty-one 
     <lb/>
     years of age in the North-West erritories, and, as you 
     <lb/>
     have really the administration of our affairs in your hands, 
     <lb/>
     it is only right and proper that I should bring the views of 
     <lb/>
     these people before you. One of the main questions dealt[...] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="354" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00354.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="num">354</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 27,</fw> 
    
   
            <p>
     [...]policy, and I condemned it as a bad policy. But I say that the 
     <lb/>
     act of its being a bad policy does not always relieve you 
     <lb/>
     from your obligation that you entered into, which obligation 
     <lb/>
     you must carry out,even though it is under a bad policy. Now, 
     <lb/>
     Sir, it is not a good thing to drink champagne, for instance. 
     <lb/>
     If you drink enough of it, and drink it often enough, it 
     <lb/>
     will tear your liver to pieces. But if a man who is fond 
     <lb/>
     of champagne were to order some from Mr. Bate, and then, 
     <lb/>
     when Mr. Bate sent the bill, he were to sit down and write 
     <lb/>
     to him and say: "Dear Sir, drinking champagne is a mis<lb break="no"/>take; it is bad for the liver; it is not conductive to general 
     <lb/>
     health; I have given up drinking champagne and as a mat<lb break="no"/>ter of principle I won't pay your bill." Why, what would 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Bate say to him? He would say, "You are under 
     <lb/>
     obligation to pay. and I will hold you to it." Well, I will 
     <lb/>
     not trouble the House with the letters, but I have letters 
     <lb/>
     here from a number of these men who say they came in 
     <lb/>
     here having before their eyes pamphlets in which this 
     <lb/>
     very North-West Act of 1883 was quoted; they came 
     <lb/>
     in here with that promise of a second homestead playing 
     <lb/>
     on their wills, and what did they find? Why, they 
     <lb/>
     had scarcely fulfilled the conditions for getting a second 
     <lb/>
     homestead―three years it takes; on the 25th of May 
     <lb/>
     the clause was put in and it requires three years 
     <lb/>
     to perfect the conditions to get a second homestead; 
     <lb/>
     and on the 2nd June, 1886, the second homestead was done 
     <lb/>
     away with. They, of course, point out what a very unjust 
     <lb/>
     thing it is. You see how irritating it is to those who came 
     <lb/>
     in, in 1884, 1885 and 1886. The men who came in from the 
     <lb/>
     25th May, 1883, or before, up to the 2nd June, 1884, could 
     <lb/>
     go, owing to the change that my hon. friend the late Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Interior made, and get a second homestead. The 
     <lb/>
     principle has been acknowledged. But men who came in in 
     <lb/>
     1885 and 1886, with this same Act on the statute-book, 
     <lb/>
     cannot get a second homestead, because, as I tell you, the 
     <lb/>
     amendment that I was able to effect in 1887 only went the 
     <lb/>
     one year. Last year I did not bring it up, for a lamentable 
     <lb/>
     reason—because we had lost the man who had been such an 
     <lb/>
     ornament to this House. It may be said—I know that 
     <lb/>
     arguments of this kind are sometimes used—that this was 
     <lb/>
     permissive. I will say this for the late Minister, that he 
     <lb/>
     never attempted to press that objection; but I will call the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the Minister of Interior to the argument on 
     <lb/>
     that head. The 37th clause of the Dominion Lands Act, 
     <lb/>
     1883, reads as follows:— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " Any person who has obtained a homestead patent after two years' 
     <lb/>
    residence, or a certificate countersigned by the Commissioner of Dom<lb break="no"/>inion Lands, as in the next receding clause mentioned, with the addi<lb break="no"/>tional statement that there as been three years' residence, may obtain 
     <lb/>another homestead and pre-emption entry." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
   
   
            <p>Of course it would be quite unworthy of a Government to 
     <lb/>rest anything on that word " may" ; but if anybody at<lb break="no"/>tempted to do so, what have we? We have that declared 
     <lb/>by the statute to be a right, so that any difficulty on that 
     <lb/>head is entirely removed. If we look at section 2, chapter 
     <lb/>54 of the Revised Statutes, we find that pre-emption entry 
     <lb/>means: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "The entering on the books of a local agent for a preferential claim 
     <lb/>
     to acquire by purchase, in connection with the homestead, and on be<lb break="no"/>coming entitled to the patent for the homestead, a quarter section, or 
     <lb/>
     part of a quarter section of land adjorning such homestead; and existing 
     <lb/>
     pr-emption right means the right of obtaining, and right to such 
     <lb/>
     quarter section"
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>
     If we turn to section 3, what do we find? It is declared 
     <lb/>
     with regard to pre-emptions: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " And further, such person shall forfeit his homestead and pre-emption 
     <lb/>
     right." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
           
            <p>
     So that in one part of the Act, in regard to a matter where 
     <lb/>
     it is said he may obtain pre-emption, we have it declared 
     <lb/>
     that that is a right. But mark the language of section 43: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " No person who has obtained a homestead patent or a certificate 
     <lb/>
     countersigned by the Commissioner of Dominion Lands or a member of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion Lands Board, as in the next preceding clause mentioned, 
     <lb/>
        
            <cb/>
            
     shall be entitled to obtain another homestead entry; but nothing con<lb break="no"/>tained in this clause shall take away the right of any person who, be<lb break="no"/>fore the 2nd day of June, 1886, had received such certificate or recom<lb break="no"/>mendation for a patent." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>
     So that the Act of 1886, in so many words, declares that it 
     <lb/>
     was taking away, not a possibility of getting a second 
     <lb/>
     homestead at the discretion of the Minister, but taking 
     <lb/>
     away a right which it acknowledges in express terms. It 
     <lb/>
     is hardly necessary to take up the time of the House with 
     <lb/>
     the second branch of the second homestead question, be<lb break="no"/>cause the Minister can deal with that administratively. 
     <lb/>
     But I will say this, as I have pointed out before, that I can 
     <lb/>
     see no advantage and no magic in the six-mile limit, and I 
     <lb/>
     pointed out, when I had the honor of an interview with the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Interior when I first came down, that one of the 
     <lb/>
     best settlers north of Pense, Joseph Young, who has cul<lb break="no"/>tivated every acre of his homestead and pre-emption 
     <lb/>
     cultivatable, has next to him a cancelled homestead, but he 
     <lb/>
     cannot enter on it. It would be a very desirable thing for 
     <lb/>
     him if he could do so, for he has two stalwart sons and a 
     <lb/>
     family, and he is one of our best farmers. He came into the 
     <lb/>
     country with nothing and he is a well-to-do man to-day, and in 
     <lb/>
     no year, not even in 1886, did he fail to have a crop; he has had 
     <lb/>
     a crop every year, but he is a thoroughpaced farmer and is a 
     <lb/>
     first-rate man. He cannot, however, homestead that can<lb break="no"/>celled homestead adjoining his own, and what is the use of 
     <lb/>
     his going away? He is forty-five years old and does 
     <lb/>
     not want to go away six miles. But that, I repeat, 
     <lb/>
     is a matter which can be dealt with administratively, and 
     <lb/>
     so I will not trouble the House further with it beyond 
     <lb/>
     calling attention to a petition I have here which was pres<lb break="no"/>ented to the Minister. It was sent to him by a large num<lb break="no"/>ber of agricultural societies, urging this question of second 
     <lb/>
     homesteading, and also urging that time be give for pay<lb break="no"/>ment of pre-emptions. I will say this, as I said to the 
     <lb/>
     farmers, that I think there is no need of their being very 
     <lb/>
     anxious about their being allowed time. So far as my 
     <lb/>
               experience of the department goes, no <hi rendition="simple:underline">bona fide</hi> farmer has 
     <lb/>
     ever been pressed for his pre-emption payment if he could 
     <lb/>
               show that he was going along in a <hi rendition="simple:underline">bona-fide</hi> manner. I 
     <lb/>
     have always found that Mr. Smith, and the department here, 
     <lb/>
               the moment they were satisfied that the man was a <hi rendition="simple:underline">bona 
     <lb/>
     fide</hi> settler, were willing to agree to any reasonable represent<lb break="no"/>ations made, provided the matter was all right. So I never 
     <lb/>
     felt nervous in regard to that matter. I will only add this 
     <lb/>
     further, that <choice><sic>tha</sic><corr>the</corr></choice> farmers around Moose Jaw and elsewhere 
     <lb/>
     are very anxious they should be given five years in which 
     <lb/>
     to pay for their pre-emptions. I will make a further com<lb break="no"/>ment on this resolution, because there is one clause in it 
     <lb/>
     with which I do not agree. It reads: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "Should it be found necessary in the future to withhold public lands 
     <lb/>
     from homesteading for railway purposes, it should be provided that 
     <lb/>
     alternate quarter sections be granted instead of alternate sections." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     In the same resolution it is stated: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " It has been proved that for the success of the settler it is necessary 
     <lb/>
     for him to engage in both stock raising and grain. and it has been de<lb break="no"/>monstrated that for this purpose a settler requires not less than 320 
     <lb/>
     acres." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     So one part of the resolution is, inadvertently, contrary to 
     <lb/>
     the other. In one part it says that 320 acres are necessary, 
     <lb/>
     and in another part it states that alternate quarter sections 
     <lb/>
     should be given to the railway. I have here a long commu<lb break="no"/>nication that I received this morning from the agricultural 
     <lb/>
     society of Moose Jaw, referring to this part of the resolution 
     <lb/>
     and strongly condemning it, strongly emphasising this view, 
     <lb/>
     that they require to summer fallow, to go into mixed 
     <lb/>
     farming, and that farmers cannot raise crops profitably in 
     <lb/>
     the North-West unless they summer fallow. Part of the 
     <lb/>
     land has to be fallowed this year while crops are 
     <lb/>
     raised on another part, and crops should be grown 
     <lb/>
     this year on land which was summer fallowed last year. 
     <lb/>
     If you do not adopt that you will not farm successfully, and 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="355" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00355.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">355</fw> 
  
   
          
     that is the way Mr. Young, to whom I referred a moment 
     <lb/>
     ago, farms. I want to say one word about the last part of 
     <lb/>
     that resolution, which asks for the establishment of a 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Lands Office in the Territories. This, I think, is 
     <lb/>
     a very important matter, and I may point out that the right 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman, in his report of 1882, declares it necessary 
     <lb/>
     to establish in the North-West a land board. However, 
     <lb/>
     when it was decided to establish this land board, instead of 
     <lb/>
     placing it in the North-West it was established at Winnipeg, 
     <lb/>
     in Manitoba. I think it would be a very wise thing to do 
     <lb/>
     what the Legislative Assembly suggests, and to move that 
     <lb/>
     land board to the North-West. At the present moment 
     <lb/>
     you are getting an enormous revenue from the North-West. 
     <lb/>
     This year I see gladly, by the report of the Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Interior, the revenue of the Department of the Interior is 
     <lb/>
     $540, 605. No doubt some of that comes from Manitoba, 
     <lb/>
     but the main portion of it undoubtedly comes from the 
     <lb/>
     North- West Territory, and as the principal business of the 
     <lb/>
     land board will be done in the North-West Territory, I 
     <lb/>
     believe that if it were established at Regina, instead of at 
     <lb/>
     Winnipeg, it would be a great improvement. The last 
     <lb/>
     resolution of these gentlemen deals with the question of 
     <lb/>
     responsible government. It says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That there is no permanent responsible body whose business it is to 
     <lb/>
     prepare legislation for the consideration of this Assembly, and in conse<lb break="no"/>quence its legislative functions cannot be satisfactorily performed. For 
     <lb/>
     instance, the Assembly has had to present an humble address to His 
     <lb/>
     Honor the Lieutenant Governor, praying that he may be pleased to 
     <lb/>
     appoint a Committee to draft during the recess certain measures deemed 
     <lb/>
     advisable by the Assembly; measures which it should be the duty of 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Government to submit. That on these and other accounts 
     <lb/>
     the Assembly believes the present system to be unsatisfactory. That, 
     <lb/>
     therefore, the Assembly recommends to His Excellency the Governor 
     <lb/>
     General in Council that full responsible government should be given 
     <lb/>
     to the Territories with the other powers, in addition to those already 
     <lb/>
     possessed by the Assembly." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     And a further resolution: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "That the amount annually voted by the Dominion Parliament for 
     <lb/>
     the expenses of government, &amp;c., in the North-West Territories, should 
     <lb/>
     be given in the form of a definite grant instead of a rate which lapses 
     <lb/>
     at the end of the fiscal year for which it is voted; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That the said grant should be placed at the disposal and subject to 
     <lb/>
     the vote of the North-West Legislative Assembly; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That although the North-West Territories have not been admitted 
     <lb/>
     into Confederation as a Province, yet they consider that the fact of 
     <lb/>
     their paying taxes to the Federal Treasury, under the same laws, rules 
     <lb/>
     and regulations and provisions as the people of other parts of Canada, 
     <lb/>
     and having been called upon to exercise the functions of local self- <lb break="yes"/>government by the Parliament of Canada, they are entitled to receive 
     <lb/>
     a return on the amount paid by them into the Federal Treasury of a 
     <lb/>
     sum similar to that received by the various Provinces comprising the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian Confederation; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That they consider that a greater proportion of taxation per head 
     <lb/>
     is paid by the people of the North-West Territories than by the people 
     <lb/>
     of any other part of Canada; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That the cost of administrating the Government of the North-West 
     <lb/>
     Territories is much larger in proportion to the population than in any 
     <lb/>
     other part of Canada by reason of the greater area and more widely 
     <lb/>
     scattered settlements; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That the maintenance and improvement of main trails in the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories should be the subject at special consideration at the hands of the 
     <lb/>
     Federal Parliament; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "That inasmuch as the lands, timber and minerals of the North-West 
     <lb/>
     Territories are held for sale by the Federal Government, which deprives 
     <lb/>
     the North-West Government of any revenue from these sources, and 
     <lb/>
     the Provinces of Confederation, with the exception of Manitoba, having 
     <lb/>
     revenues from said sources; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Therefore your committee are strongly of opinion that a largely in<lb break="no"/>creased grant should be given to the North-West Territories for expenses 
     <lb/>
     of North- West Government, construction of roads and bridges, the im<lb break="no"/>provement of main trails, and other public improvements." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>
     The House wlll be glad to know, sir, that the Advisory 
     <lb/>
     Board has worked wonderfully well. Although I do not 
     <lb/>
     think any more than do those gentlemen, or the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Assembly, that that board is as effective 
     <lb/>
     a machine of government as complete responsible 
     <lb/>
     government would be, yet, Sir, I had an opportunity 
     <lb/>
     of observing the chamber during its session and I will 
     <lb/>
     say this, that the Advisory Board and the admirable manner 
     <lb/>
     in which Governor Royal fell in with the idea of making it 
     <lb/>
     a sliding scale to responsible government worked admir<lb break="no"/>
           
            <cb/>
          
     ably and gave a new character altogether to the assembly 
     <lb/>
     as compared with the council. In the North-West Council, 
     <lb/>
     as my friend the Minister of Interior will remember, they 
     <lb/>
     discussed matters more like men in committee, but with the 
     <lb/>
     Advisory Board they at once fell in with the parliamentary 
     <lb/>
     practice, and the intelligence displayed by the gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     who are now members of that assembly and the capacity 
     <lb/>
     which they showed in their conduct of the proceedings, 
     <lb/>
     are fraught with the best promise for the future of that 
     <lb/>
     country. I wish to call the attention of the House for one 
     <lb/>
     moment to what might be called our claims on the Federal 
     <lb/>
     Government. Many gentlemen in this House and else<lb break="no"/>where think that we are always asking for something, and 
     <lb/>
     that we are, in fact, asking for too much. They think 
     <lb/>
     we are unreasonable in the North-West, while the fact is 
     <lb/>
     that we are entitled to a great deal more than we get. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SCRI1">Mr. SCRIVER</persName>. You are astonished at your own modera<lb break="no"/>tion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. My friend on the right says " we are 
     <lb/>
     astonished at our own moderation," and I have no objection 
     <lb/>
     to accept his language. The old council of 1887 petitioned 
     <lb/>
     for responsible government and the memorial set forth: 
     <lb/>
     That by the census of 1885 the population of the North- <lb break="yes"/>West Territories was 28,000, larger by 11,000 than that of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba when she was admitted into Confederation. The 
     <lb/>
     population has much increased since that census, as eviden<lb break="no"/>ced from the new electoral districts erected. Manitoba was 
     <lb/>
     erected into a Province in 1870, and as we see in 33 Vic., 
     <lb/>
     cap. 3, sec. 25, she received $30,000 in support of govern<lb break="no"/>ment, 80 cents per head of the population, which was esti<lb break="no"/>mated at 17,000, and the salaries of the Lieutenant 
     <lb/>
     Governor, judges, charges in respect to customs, postal, 
     <lb/>
     fisheries, militia, geological, penitentiary department, and 
     <lb/>
     so on, were all paid by the Federal Treasury. In 1882, 
     <lb/>
     according to 45 Vic., cap. 5, when the population of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba, according to the census of 1881, was 69,954, that 
     <lb/>
     Province was allowed 80 cents or head on 150,000 souls, 
     <lb/>
     indemnity for want of public lands of 845,000; and in 1870, 
     <lb/>
     because the Province was not in debt, 5 er cent. 
     <lb/>
     on $472,000, making altogether $238,000. By 48-49 
     <lb/>
     Vic, cap. 50, she got swamp lands and 150,000 
     <lb/>
     acres for a university and the indemnity for 
     <lb/>
     want of public lands increased to $100,000. Now 
     <lb/>
     I ask the attention of the House to this argument. It 
     <lb/>
     is an argument of proportion, such an argument as we all 
     <lb/>
     have made when learning the rule of three at school. If 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba, in 1882, with a census pupulation of 65,954, was 
     <lb/>
     allowed 80 cents a head on a population of 150,000, 
     <lb/>
     then the North-West, four years after, it was declared 
     <lb/>
     by the census of 1885, to have a population of 28,000, 
     <lb/>
     must be entitled to 80 cents a head on about 80,000 people. 
     <lb/>
     But take the ratio adopted after one year, and we are 
     <lb/>
     entitled to 80 cents a head on 70,000, or 856,000; for gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, 850,000; and for want of our public lands, 815,000. 
     <lb/>
     Then, if Manitoba with a population of 17,000, not having 
     <lb/>
     any debt, was entitled to 5 per cent. on 8472,000, the 
     <lb/>
     North-West Territories, with a census population of 28,000, 
     <lb/>
     would be entitled to 5 per cent. on $774,000, or 838,700; and 
     <lb/>
     as we have more land than Manitoba, our gross revenue 
     <lb/>
     should amount to $239,700. We should also have 150,000 
     <lb/>
     acres of land for a university, and money for our own 
     <lb/>
     lunatic asylum, as well as Manitoba. Now, Sir, the tone 
     <lb/>
     taken towards that western country is a tone which I 
     <lb/>
     believe will not be often taken in this House after hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen come to see what its claims are; because at the 
     <lb/>
     present minute we must regard that western country as 
     <lb/>
     composed of Manitoba, the North-West Territories and 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia, all west of the great lakes; and what do 
     <lb/>
     you find? If you compare the amount that western 
     <lb/>
     country pays in customs duties with the amount paid by 
     <lb/>
     an old Province like Nova Scotia or New Brunswick, you 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="356" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00356.jpg"/>
            
               
     <fw type="num">356</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 27,</fw>  
    
          
     will find that it pays more; and the paper which was put 
     <lb/>
     into my hands a few days ago by the Inland Revenue 
     <lb/>
     Department shows that we drink a great deal more beer 
     <lb/>
     per head west of the great lakes, and pay a great deal more 
     <lb/>
     of inland revenue than the two Provinces of Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>
     and New Brunswick put together. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">An hon. MEMBER</persName>. It is a bad sign. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. It may be a bad sign, but it shows that 
     <lb/>
     the people there are a very prosperous people, and can 
     <lb/>
     afford to spend a good deal of money on the four articles of 
     <lb/>
     beer, wine, tobacco and whiskey. I find also that the 
     <lb/>
     banking business done, taking into account discounts, the 
     <lb/>
     amount of capital invested, and all the details of banking, 
     <lb/>
     shows well for the western country. Now, my right hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend, in reply to a question, told me a few days ago that 
     <lb/>
     he did not intend to bring in a Bill this year giving full 
     <lb/>
     responsible government to the Territories; but, in passing, 
     <lb/>
     I wish to say that when that Bill is brought in, or probably 
     <lb/>
     it might be done now, a large portion of territory should be 
     <lb/>
     given to the Local Government to be used by it for subsidiz<lb break="no"/>ing branch lines of railway. I am not fond, as this House 
     <lb/>
     knows of drawing comparisons with what is done in the 
     <lb/>
     United States; but I may state that when they organise a 
     <lb/>
     territory in the United States, they pay out of the Federal 
     <lb/>
     treasury all the expenses that we do, they give the territories 
     <lb/>
     the school lands and the swamp lands, as we have done in the 
     <lb/>
     case of Manitoba; but they do more than that. When Minne<lb break="no"/>sota, Wyoming, Dakota and Montana were organised, each of 
     <lb/>
     these Territories got a large extent of territory for subsi<lb break="no"/>dising branch lines. Minnesota, with 83,000 square miles 
     <lb/>
     (Assiniboia has 93,000 square miles), received land for sub<lb break="no"/>sidising 1,800 miles of railway, and with the swamps, started 
     <lb/>
     in possession of one-third of the Territory. What does that 
     <lb/>
     policy enable these Territories to do? It gives them, while 
     <lb/>
     young, that nutriment and vital force, without which any<lb break="no"/>thing young cannot thrive. As the right hon. the Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister is now acting Minister of Railways, I should like 
     <lb/>
     to call his attention to this fact. At this hour the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Minnesota receives an income of $600,000 a year, 3 
     <lb/>
    per cent. on the gross earnings of the lines of railway that 
     <lb/>it chartered and subsidised since 1849, when it was organ<lb break="no"/>ised. But it may be said: " Ah, but those Territories were 
     <lb/>very populous. Not at all. In 1849, when Minnesota was 
     <lb/>organised, it had only a population of 6,000, and the 
     <lb/>aggregate population of all the four Territories at the respec<lb break="no"/>tive dates of their organisation did not equal by five or 
     <lb/>six thousand the population of the North-West to day. That 
     <lb/>is a point which I submit as well worthy of the considera<lb break="no"/>tion of the Government, because I think we may err on the 
     <lb/>side of keeping the strings too much in our hands 
     <lb/>here at Ottawa, and not giving sufficient scope for the young 
     <lb/>giant, for which I plead here to-day, to develop his limbs. 
     <lb/>Now, it will be said to us, no doubt, you have got the 
     <lb/>Mounted Police. So we have, and we are very glad to have 
     <lb/>them; but elsewhere you have batteries, militia, and mili<lb break="no"/>tary schools, and we pay for those just as well as you pay 
     <lb/>for the Mounted Police; and before you know where you 
     <lb/>are, I believe in the next five years, you will find 
     <lb/>we shall have a population in those Territories which 
     <lb/>will be subscribing to your military schools, and 
     <lb/>batteries, and militia just as much as you are sub<lb break="no"/>scribing to the North West Mounted Police. And re<lb break="no"/>member that in any case the cost of defence would 
     <lb/>fall on the Federal Government; so that you cannot fairly 
     <lb/>make anything of our having the Mounted Police. The 
     <lb/>feeling amongst the people, and especially amongst the 
     <lb/>members of this assembly, who now represent the people, 
     <lb/>is in favor of full responsible government. Now, I am not 
     <lb/>going to use the rhetorical language we sometimes hear in 
     <lb/>this House, and which I always regret to hear, used by men 
     <lb/>
  
            <cb/>
          
     who should speak with the balance and restraint of states<lb break="no"/>men. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCA3">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. Hear, hear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. My hon. friend from Simcoe says "hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear," but if he was rightly reported in a speech that he 
     <lb/>
     made not far from here, he himself fell into this same 
     <lb/>
     rhetorical exaggeration. We sometimes hear it said in this 
     <lb/>
     House, that we are not free unless we have the right to 
     <lb/>
     make our own treaties. My hon. friend was reported as 
     <lb/>
     having said that we were not free unless we were repre<lb break="no"/>sented in the Imperial Parliament, and took up our full 
     <lb/>
     share of Imperial responsibility. Of course when the noun 
     <lb/>
     "freedom" or the adjective "free" is used in this manner, 
     <lb/>
     it is used in a purely rhetorical sense and not in the broad 
     <lb/>
     signifcation, in which constitutional writers use it. 
     <lb/>
    When people speak properly of being free, what they mean 
     <lb/>is that their liberty cannot be interfered with, without their 
     <lb/>being tried before their peers, that they are not taxed with<lb break="no"/>out representation. The various ingredients of civil liberty 
     <lb/>that we are familiar with, we have in the North-West, but 
     <lb/>I do not think we have all the advantages that you have 
     <lb/>here. We suffer there from some disabilities that you 
     <lb/>do not suffer from, but I regard our position as a free 
     <lb/>and liberal condition. Every man can there speak the 
     <lb/>thing he will. I believe the North-West Territories will 
     <lb/>develop at a rapid rate. I see by the report of the Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Interior that a far larger number of homesteads 
     <lb/>were taken up last year than the year before. In 1886, 
     <lb/>294,960 acres in homesteads were taken up; in 1887, 
     <lb/>319,500; in 1888, 420,333. From that you see the pro<lb break="no"/>gressive rate of increase at which homesteads have been 
     <lb/>taken up. Now, with the crop we had last year and the 
     <lb/>report of that crop going all over the world—for we have 
     <lb/>had visits from men from every part of the world—I believe 
     <lb/>you will find that next year, instead of 420,000 acres being 
     <lb/>taken up, that number will be greatly increased. I believe 
     <lb/>that certainly 700,000 or 800,000 acres in homesteads will 
     <lb/>be taken up, and the increase will go on at the same 
     <lb/>rate. There are many documents to which I might 
     <lb/>refer to show the progress made by the North-West. 
     <lb/>I have not said one word about what the committee of 
     <lb/>Senator Schultz, now Lieutenant Governor, showed we 
     <lb/>possessed in the Mackenzie River Basin; and in the present 
     <lb/>report of the Interior Department, I see that Mr. Burgess 
     <lb/>refers in glowing terms to the Yukon River district. Take 
     <lb/>the report of two years back in which there is an account 
     <lb/>given of the Yukon River, and you will find that men make 
     <lb/>as much as $500 a day mining gold in that district. They 
     <lb/>have made $300 and $350, and some $500 in one day. I do 
     <lb/>not say that happened as a general thing, but still it shows 
     <lb/>the value of that region. In the North-West Territories we 
     <lb/>have a large area of prairie land, most fertile and most 
     <lb/>abundant in its yield; we have gold, iron, coal, all the fruits 
     <lb/>of the earth, the forest, and the finest cattle raising country 
     <lb/>in the world. I say that there is the place that the means 
     <lb/>will be found to make this country a great and contented 
     <lb/>nation. I always regret when, in regard to this country, 
     <lb/>anything like sectional feeling, arising from race or religion 
     <lb/>or from any other source, is developed; and it is a great 
     <lb/>consolation to me to know that up in the North-West, we 
     <lb/>are freer than in any other part of Canada from those pre<lb break="no"/>judices of race and religion which are really more inimical 
     <lb/>to our progress than anything else. I desire to see this 
     <lb/>great Canada of ours peopled with French, English, Scotch, 
     <lb/>Irish, Germans—and in the North-West we have Germans 
     <lb/>whose settlements are perfect wonders as evidences of 
     <lb/>what can be done by thrift and energy—I desire to see all 
     <lb/>these elements moulded into one nation. What I hope to see 
     <lb/>and what we ought to aim at—French, English, Irish and 
     <lb/>Scotch—and it will come some day, is to have a United 
     <lb/>
           

    

    

    
            <pb n="357" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-02-27_Page_00357.jpg"/>
            <fw type="dateline">1889.</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="num">357</fw>
        
     Canada with a Canadian race inhabiting it, and I should 
     <lb/>
     like very much to say a few words especially to my   
     <lb/>
     French Canadian friends about the North West. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some hon. MEMBERS</persName>: <hi rendition="simple:underline">En français.</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr.DAVIN</persName>. If the House will bear with me, since 
     <lb/>
     some of my French Canadian friends desire it, I will 
     <lb/>
     say a few words to them in their language, though I do 
     <lb/>
     so with a great deal of diffidence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Je prétends, M. l'Orateur, qu'il est du devoir des Ecossais,<lb/>des Irlandais, des Français et des Anglais de se fusionner<lb/>pour former ici une race canadienne. Nous formerons ainsi<lb/>une race plus grande que celle des Allemands, plus grande<lb/>que celle des Celtes, plus grande que celle des Anglo-Saxons ;<lb/>une race qui réunira au jugement, à l'abnégation, à la disci<lb break="no"/>pline, à la sincérité du Saxon, la vivacité d'esprit, le goût<lb/>des arts, le génie, l'ardeur, la puissance créatrice du Celte.<lb/>J'espère que nous verrons cette race se développer en gran<lb break="no"/>deur héroïque et recevoir du Nord-Ouest une inspiration de<lb/>pouvoirs magnifiques.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Je me bornerai à dire en ce moment aux Canadiens-<lb break="yes"/>Français d'imiter l'exemple de leurs pères dont les faits et 
     <lb/>
     gestes dans le passé au Nord-Ouest sont dignes d'une admi<lb break="no"/>ration spéciale. Connaissons-nous nous-mêmes, rendons-nous 
     <lb/>
     compte de notre position, et prenons les moyens de fonder 
     <lb/>
     ici une nation canadienne. Et, M. l'Orateur, lorsque viendra 
     <lb/>
     le jour où nous aurons dans le Nord-Ouest une population 
     <lb/>
     plus considérable que dans les provinces d'Ontario et de 
     <lb/>
     Québec, lorsque le Nord-Ouest comptera au delà de 10,000,<lb break="no"/>000 d'habitants, nous pourrons braver les contempteurs, 
     <lb/>
     les insulteurs et les intrigants, et peut-être adresser aux 
     <lb/>
     Wiman et autres les mots magnifiques qui s'échappent de 
     <lb/>
     l'âme du Cid quand il apprend que Chimène peut devenir 1e 
     <lb/>
     prix de sa valeur :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "Est-i1 quelqu'ennemi qu'à présent je ne dompte ? 
     <lb/>
     Paraissez Navarrois, Macres et Castillans, 
     <lb/>
     Et tout ce que l'Espagne a nourri de vaillants. 
     <lb/>
     Unissez-vous ensemble, et faites une armée, 
     <lb/>
     Pour combattre ma main de la sorte animée. 
     <lb/>
     Joignez tous vos efforts contre un espoir si doux ; 
     <lb/>
     Pour en venir à bout, c'est trop peu que de vous." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>
     What I have been saying in French, I can repeat in 
     <lb/>
     English in a word or two. I was emphasising the fact, that 
     <lb/>
     we should make ourselves here a patriotic people, and that 
     <lb/>
     instead of trying to emphasise the angles of difference that 
     <lb/>
     divide us, we should try to pare away the angles, so that 
     <lb/>
     by-and-by we might become one Canadian peeple, because 
     <lb/>
     we have the finest country in the world, and, when we 
     <lb/>
     have a larger population, with sentiments such as I have 
     <lb/>
     indicated pervading them, there is no power in the world 
     <lb/>
     that could affect us, but we could stand four square against 
     <lb/>
     all the blasts that blow. That is the best free translation 
     <lb/>
     that I can give of the magnificent words that Corneille puts 
     <lb/>
     in the mouth of the Cid. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. I will endeavor to say a few words 
     <lb/>
     on this subject before six o'clock. I am very much pleased 
     <lb/>
     that the member for West Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) has 
     <lb/>
     brought up the question of the proper policy to be pursued 
     <lb/>
     by the Government in regard to the settlement of our vast 
     <lb/>
     domain in the North-West. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName> There will probably be 
     <lb/>
     an interesting discussion on this subject, and, as it cannot 
     <lb/>
     go on after six o'clock, I would suggest that it had better 
     <lb/>
     stand over. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     It being Six o'clock, the Speaker left the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>