<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-04-28" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-04-28">28 April 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          

          
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
        

          <date when="1905"/>.
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="5083" to="5132"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5083.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5085.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5087.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5089.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5091.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5093.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5095.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5097.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5099.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5101.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5103.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5105.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5107.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5109.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5111.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5113.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5115.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5117.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5119.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5121.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5123.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5125.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5127.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5129.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5131.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-01-19">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-01-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>

<change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-02-14">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5083">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5083.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5085">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5085.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5087">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5087.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5089">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5089.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5091">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5091.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5093">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5093.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5095">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5095.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5097">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5097.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5099">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5099.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5101">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5101.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5103">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5103.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5105">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5105.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5107">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5107.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5109">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5109.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5111">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5111.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5113">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5113.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5115">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5115.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5117">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5117.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5119">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5119.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5121">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5121.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5123">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5123.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5125">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5125.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5127">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5127.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5129">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5129.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5131">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5131.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="5083" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5083.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">5083</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
            
            <p>As a matter of fact one of the reasons 
     <lb/>
     given for the refusal of the United States 
     <lb/>
     to recognize Canadian certificates is that 
     <lb/>
     in Canada there are various certificates, and 
     <lb/>
     the American authorities could not under<lb break="no"/>take to examine into the different associa<lb break="no"/>tions which issue them. The natural 
     <lb/>
     answer was : If you will recognize Cana<lb break="no"/>dian national certificates, we will make our 
     <lb/>
     certificates national. That is one of the 
     <lb/>
     reasons why this movement has, attained 
     <lb/>
     such force. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:INGR1">Mr. INGRAM</persName>. Has the hon. gentleman <lb/> communicated with the
               United States gov<lb break="no"/>ernment regarding this matter of certifi<lb break="no"/>cates and regarding also the admission of <lb/> Canadian thoroughbreds
               free of duty ? <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH2">Mr. FISHER</persName>. The first point is with <lb/> regard to the
               recognition of our certificates <lb/> to entitle an animal to exhibition as a <lb/>
               thoroughbred. I think that that would fol<lb break="no"/>low the recognition of our
               certificates by <lb/> the customs authorities. I may say how<lb break="no"/>ever that
               the United States exhibition <lb/> authorities have recognized our certificates.
               <lb/> At the St. Louis exhibition last year, ani<lb break="no"/>mals that were
               registered in the herd books <lb/> were accepted as thoroughbreds and allowed <lb/>
               to compete. We could not however get free <lb/> entry of those animals for sale. That
               is a <lb/> question of customs over which the exhibi<lb break="no"/>tion authorities
               have no control. They re<lb break="no"/>ferred the matter to the customs authorities.
               <lb/> and these authorities applied their ordinary <lb/> rule which does not
               recognize Canadian <lb/> certificates of registration. The conse<lb break="no"/>quence was that any animal exhibited at <lb/> St. Louis had to pay the customs duty
                  be<lb break="no"/>fore it could be sold. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:INGR1">Mr. INGRAM</persName>. Am I to understand that <lb/> the hon. minister made
               no representations <lb/> to the authorities at Washington at. all ? <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH2">Mr. FISHER</persName>. We made representations <lb/> to the exhibition
               authorities and they told <lb/> us that we would have to deal with the <lb/> custom
               authorities, but we had been already <lb/> dealing with the customs authorities many
               <lb/> years and knew exactly what they would <lb/> say. They always told us they
               could make <lb/> no change in their rules so that there was <lb/> no object in
               appealing to them again. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Motion agreed to and Bill read the first 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PROVINCIAL AUTONOMY IN THE 
     <lb/>
     NORTHWEST. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>House resumed adjourned debate on the 
     <lb/>
     proposed motion of Sir Wilfrid Laurier for 
     <lb/>
     the second reading of Bill (No. 69) to estab<lb break="no"/>lish and provide for the government of the 
     <lb/>
     province of Alberta, and the amendment of 
     <lb/>
     Mr. R. L. Borden thereto. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName> (North Wellington). As <lb/> a new member, I
                  feel that I should apologize <lb/> for taking up the time of the House after <lb/>
                  the lengthy discussion we have had on this <lb/>
                  <!-- <p>Mr. FISHER. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
                  <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5084</fw> Bill. The question however is so important, <lb/> more especially as the
                  Bill before us is not <lb/> only one of the very first measures that has <lb/> to
                  be considered by myself as well as other <lb/> new members, but extends our
                  confederation <lb/> by the admission of new provinces, great <lb/> in area and
                  rich in future possibilities, that <lb/> I think I may fairly claim the indulgence
                  <lb/> of the House while I take up its attention <lb/> for a short time. I
                  listened last night with <lb/> pleasure to the speech from another young <lb/>
                  member of the House (Mr. Lalor), and while <lb/> I congratulate him on the
                  excellent address <lb/> he made as his maiden effort. I was very <lb/> much
                  astonished at some of his remarks. <lb/> Indeed I thought that he skated around
                  <lb/> the question very carefully ; and I noticed <lb/> in the past few days an
                  inclination among <lb/> members opposite to sail all around the <lb/> subject and
                  not face it as it should be faced. <lb/> I would refer, in the first place, to the
                  <lb/> speech of the hon. member for Calgary <lb/> (Mr. McCarthy) in which he
                  challenged the <lb/> government to open up a constituency in <lb/> the west and
                  appeal to the people to elect <lb/> its Minister of the Interior. You will notice
                  <lb/> in that speech that he almost tells us that <lb/> if the government had
                  courage enough to <lb/> place this matter before the country he <lb/> would have
                  very little objection to the Bill <lb/> afterwards ; that is, if any member from
                  <lb/> the west was appointed Minister of the <lb/> Interior and was elected by his
                  constituents. <lb/> I am sorry he is not in his place to-day, and <lb/> I am sorry
                  to say that that good looking <lb/> young man has not been in his place since
                  <lb/> the 25th day of this month. He seems to <lb/> have already commenced to
                  think that it <lb/> is time to go back on what he has said. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:SCHA1">Mr. SCHAFFNER</persName>. Did I understand the <lb/> hon. gentleman to
                  say that the hon. member <lb/> for Calgary had not been in his place ? <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. I only said that I had <lb/> not seen him and
                  I have not seen him here <lb/> in the House. The hon. member for South. <lb/> York
                  (Mr. W. F. Maclean) has made several <lb/> speeches, one particularly, challenging
                  the <lb/> government to appoint a Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior and to
                  go to the country, to open any <lb/> constituency in the west and elect a minister
                  <lb/> there. We find that since the 25th of this <lb/> month that courageous
                  gentleman's chair has <lb/> also been vacant. I call attention to the <lb/> fact
                  that even the shepherd of the flock, the <lb/> member for Leeds (Mr. Taylor) has
                  made <lb/> some statements in this House that I think <lb/> are worth calling the
                  attention of the House <lb/> to. He said : <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     I wish to make a proposition to the Minister 
     <lb/>
     of Justice which I shall ask the Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Finance to convey to him as he is not in his 
     <lb/>
     place. I suggest to the Minister of Justice that 
     <lb/>
     if the statements of the Minister of Finance 
     <lb/>
     and the ex-Mlnister of the Interior are true, he 
     <lb/>
     should let the lawyers on both sides of the 
     <lb/>
     House get together and frame an amendment 
     <lb/>
    in accordance .with the statements of these two 
     <lb/>gentlemen, an amendment which shall contain 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="5085" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5085.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">5085</fw> <fw type="dateline">APRIL 28, 1905</fw> 
            
     nothing more, but which shall be put in plain 
     <lb/>
     language so that the man on the street may 
     <lb/>
     know what it means. Then, so far as I am con<lb break="no"/>cerned, there will be no opposition because it 
     <lb/>
     is a national school as both of these hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen say, a national school with only one 
     <lb/>
     half hour's religious teaching between 3.30 and 
     <lb/>
     4 o'clock in the afternoon. And I am sure the 
     <lb/>
     people of the Northwest or of Ontario, or at 
     <lb/>
     any other section of. the Dominion will raise no 
     <lb/>
     objection to that. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:TAYL1">Mr. TAYLOR</persName>. Read further. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. Then we come to the <lb/> speech of my hon.
                  friend from Haldimand <lb/> (Mr. Lalor) last night. He was very par<lb break="no"/>ticular on four different occasions to state <lb/> and he wound up his speech by
                  stating: <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     When I vote in favour of the amendment of 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend the leader of the opposition (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     R. L. Borden), I am not voting against separate 
     <lb/>
     schools, and I want that distinctly understood. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>I would say to these gentlemen that after 
     <lb/>
     we have spent something like six weeks on 
     <lb/>
     this question we would ask them to at once 
     <lb/>
     drop the discussion and fall in with us and 
     <lb/>
     make the passage of the Bill unanimous. If 
     <lb/>
     they want to vote for separate schools they 
     <lb/>
     can have all the opportunity they wish. 
     <lb/>
     The hon. member for Haldimand (Mr. Lalor) 
     <lb/>
     also said in his speech that the leader of the 
     <lb/>
     government was a coward, that one of the 
     <lb/>
     greatest acts of cowardice that had ever been 
     <lb/>
     perpetrated upon this country was the ap<lb break="no"/>appointment of the present Minister of 
     <lb/>
     the Interior because he had had a large 
     <lb/>
     majority in the last election. I never 
     <lb/>
     knew that it was a crime to have a 
     <lb/>
     large majority in this country ; I never 
     <lb/>
     knew'that a man had to sit on the back 
     <lb/>
     benches all his life because he had a 
     <lb/>
     large majority, and I believe that no fairer 
     <lb/>
     and no wiser act could have been done under 
     <lb/>
     the circumstances than the premier's action 
     <lb/>
     in appointing as Minister of the Interior the 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Mr. Oliver. The hon. member also 
     <lb/>
     stated that he does not believe there is a 
     <lb/>
     more clever man in this Dominion than Pre<lb break="no"/>mier Haultain. I believe he is correct, I 
     <lb/>
     presume he is. But I notice in an interview 
     <lb/>
     with the Toronto ' News ' that Premier Haul<lb break="no"/>tain when interviewed at Winnipeg spoke on 
     <lb/>
     this subject. The interview appears under 
     <lb/>
     the heading 'No Significance in Mr. Oliver's 
     <lb/>
     Election.' Mr. Haultain believed there was 
     <lb/>
     no significance, but the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Haldimand believes there was a great deal 
     <lb/>
     of significance. In Mr. Haultain's interview 
     <lb/>
     he was asked it' there was any probability 
     <lb/>
     of the Northwest legislature being called to<lb break="no"/>gether to pass a resolution on the question. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Haultain replied in the negative. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve Mr. Haultain is a clever man, but I 
     <lb/>
     say that when the hon. member for South 
     <lb/>
     York (Mr. W. F. Maclean) was challenging 
     <lb/>
     the Postmaster General to throw up his seat 
     <lb/>
     and run an election he might have gone one 
     <lb/>
     further and challenged Premier Haultain to 
     <lb/>
     call his council together and see what they 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5086</fw>
            
     would say on the question. I believe Pre<lb break="no"/>mier Haultain knows to-day that he dare not 
     <lb/>
     call his council together, I believe that if he 
     <lb/>
     called that council together he would be de<lb break="no"/>feated in an attempt to pass any resolution 
     <lb/>
     or any measure that would be in any way 
     <lb/>
     against the Bill that we have now before us. 
     <lb/>
     I believe that there is no greater coward, 
     <lb/>
     that no man has shown himself the coward 
     <lb/>
     so much as Mr. Haultain. Mr. Haultaln has 
     <lb/>
     written a letter to the premier, a letter 
     <lb/>
     which I have in my hand, and in it you can 
     <lb/>
     easily see that if it were possible that he 
     <lb/>
     could make any political capital out of 
     <lb/>
     calling his legislature together, he would do 
     <lb/>
     so and have a resolution passed opposing 
     <lb/>
     this measure. He has not been able to do so, 
     <lb/>
     he has been afraid to attempt to do so. 
     <lb/>
     Therefore I fall back upon what I said in 
     <lb/>
     the first place that it was rather amusing 
     <lb/>
     when we listened to the remarks of the 
     <lb/>
     speakers last night how they all skated 
     <lb/>
     around the question, how they were trying 
     <lb/>
     to get some way crawl out the back door, 
     <lb/>
     stating in their arguments if you can call 
     <lb/>
     them arguments, as the member for Haldi<lb break="no"/>mand said : ' I am not voting against separ<lb break="no"/>ate schools; I want that distinctly under<lb break="no"/>stood.' 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LALO2">Mr. LALOR</persName>. Are you voting for separate <lb/> schools? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. Now you leave me <lb/>alone, I will attend to
                  that before I get <lb/>through. At the very outset I wish to take <lb/>strong
                  objection to some statements made <lb/>by that member in his speech. He said :
                  <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     I want to tell them there is no mutiny on 
     <lb/>
     this side. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>It did not look like it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     The leader of the Conservative party told us 
     <lb/>
     both in caucus and out-<lb/>
            </quote>

            <p>I suppose that means there would have 
     <lb/>
     been a mutiny if the leader had not told them 
     <lb/>
     so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     The leader of the Conservatiye party told 
     <lb/>
     us both in caucus and out to vote as our con<lb break="no"/>sciences dictated to us on this Bill, and that is 
     <lb/>
     the way we are voting on the measure. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>Evidently, the leader of the opposition 
     <lb/>
     had reached a point where he had to tell 
     <lb/>
     his followers that there would have been 
     <lb/>
     an end to his authority. We have the evi<lb break="no"/>dence of half a dozen hon. members on the 
     <lb/>
     opposition side to prove that that is the 
     <lb/>
     case. And, gentlemen. I wish to go one 
     <lb/>
     step further and tell my hon. friend from 
     <lb/>
     Haldimand that he is entirely wrong when 
     <lb/>
     he makes this statement : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     The hon. member says their consciences will 
     <lb/>
     not allow them to follow him. I would like to 
     <lb/>
     see the consciences of some members on the 
     <lb/>
    other side of the House who are compelled to 
     <lb/>follow the Prime Minister whether they want 
     <lb/>to or not, the men who are whipped into line, 
     <lb/>the men who have had the whip lashed over 
     <lb/>their backs, and have been brought to the cen<lb break="no"/>tre with a round turn and made to support the 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="5087" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5087.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">5087</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
            
          
     Prime Minister notwithstanding the fact that 
     <lb/>
     they know when they are doing so that the 
     <lb/>
     people who sent them to this parliament are 
     <lb/>
     opposed to this measure. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>Now, I do not wish to make any joke of 
     <lb/>
     this, but to speak earnestly about it. And 
     <lb/>
     I say truthfully—and I challenge contra<lb break="no"/>diction—that in no case, in caucus or out 
     <lb/>
     of caucus, in this House or out of this 
     <lb/>
     House, has one member of the government 
     <lb/>
     or one member of this House on the govern<lb break="no"/>ment side, even asked me what I intended 
     <lb/>
     to do on this question. Now, gentlemen, I 
     <lb/>
     say. that openly-<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:TAYL1">Mr. TAYLOR</persName>. I rise to a point of order. <lb/> The hon. gentleman
                  (Mr. T. Martin) thinks <lb/> he is before a country audience. He should <lb/>
                  address the Chair. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. Mr. Speaker, if I am <lb/> out of order, I
                  apologize and am ready at <lb/> once to conform to the rule of the House. <lb/>
                  But if the hon. member for Leeds (Mr. Tay<lb break="no"/>lor), the whip of the
                  Conservative party, <lb/> had called his freshman to order last night, <lb/> I
                  think he would have done well. It is <lb/> astonishing that he, an old member of
                  this <lb/> House could sit and listen for an hour and <lb/> a half to such
                  nonsense, to such stuff, and <lb/> yet, lose his head before I have been speak<lb break="no"/>ing fifteen minutes. It seems to me that if <lb/> leniency should
                  be shown in this House. <lb/> new members should have the benefit of it. <lb/> I
                  was quite willing that all leniency should <lb/> be shown to my hon, friend from
                     Haldi<lb break="no"/>mand (Mr. Lalor) even though, he did allow <lb/> himself
                  such latitude. Had he been before <lb/> a country audience and made such a speech
                  <lb/> as he made last night. he would have been <lb/> told a dozen times that he
                  was very fresh. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LALO2">Mr. LALOR</persName>. There is a pair of us. <lb/>
               </p>

    
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. We are both from the <lb/> country, and I am
                  not ashamed of the <lb/> country. Now, I wish to be thoroughly un<lb break="no"/>derstood, and I wish these words of mine <lb/> to go to the country, when I say
                  that <lb/> on no occasion have I—and I believe <lb/> the same is true of every
                  hon. member on <lb/> the government side of the House—been re<lb break="no"/>quested, even so much as requested, to vote <lb/> for the Bill now in
                  consideration. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p>An <persName ref="pers:ANON1">hon. MEMBER</persName>. Or any other Bill. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. Yes, or any other Bill. <lb/> I was very sorry
                  also that the young mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Haldimand (Mr. Lalor) should at<lb break="no"/>tack so recklessly and with so little con<lb break="no"/>science
                  that grand man the right hon. leader <lb/> of this House (Sir Wilfrid Laurier).
                  The <lb/> hon. member used language with reference <lb/> to the Prime Minister
                  that no young mem<lb break="no"/>ber of this House is entitled to use. The <lb/>
                  Prime Minister of this country has a record, <lb/> and by that record he is to be
                  judged. <lb/> He has behind him a record of twenty- <lb break="yes"/> three years
                  of publlc service, a lifetime <lb/> in itself. He has a record of. never <lb/>
                  failing tolerance. He has a record of clean <lb/>
                  <!--<p>Mr. T. MARTIN. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
                  <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5088</fw> and able administration, such a record as <lb/> we have seldom had among the
                  public men <lb/> of Canada. Can any man charge the Prime <lb/> Minister of this
                  Dominion with having mis<lb break="no"/>used in any way a penny of the public
                  <lb/> funds? Can any man charge the Prime <lb/> Minister with intolerance or with
                  any dis<lb break="no"/>regard of the rights or feelings of any sec<lb break="no"/>tion of the people? I say that it is unbe<lb break="no"/>coming of any young
                  member of this House, <lb/> of any man of little experience either poli<lb break="no"/>tical or parliamentary, to use such language <lb/> with reference
                  to the right hon. leader of <lb/> this House as was used by the hon. member <lb/>
                  for Haldimand. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>I was much pleased to hear the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Peel (Mr. Blain) the other day quote 
     <lb/>
     the utterances of a Presbyterian minister 
     <lb/>
     and declare, as he did, that any one would 
     <lb/>
     accept the statement of the gentleman whose 
     <lb/>
     name he gave and whose words he quoted. 
     <lb/>
     I belong to that church myself. and I am 
     <lb/>
     proud of the church and of the men it has 
     <lb/>
     produced. Therefore, I desire to follow the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Peel and give the opinions 
     <lb/>
     of some members of that denomination, to 
     <lb/>
     show that the school system of the North<lb break="no"/>west as it now stands is satisfactory to the 
     <lb/>
     people of these new provinces and that 
     <lb/>
     therefore, we are right in voting for this 
     <lb/>
     Bill. This quoting of the opinion of mem<lb break="no"/>bers of one church may seem a little sec<lb break="no"/>tional, but I am sure that hon. members 
     <lb/>
     will bear with me when they hear the names 
     <lb/>
     of those whose words I desire to give. 
     <lb/>
     First I would refer to the late Rev. Dr 
     <lb/>
     Robertson, and I am sure, when I mention 
     <lb/>
     his name, those hon. members who belong 
     <lb/>
     to the Presbyterian church—and I am glad 
     <lb/>
     to say there are a large number in this 
     <lb/>
     House who belong to it—and all the adhe<lb break="no"/>rents of that church throughout the coun<lb break="no"/>try, will receive almost as final evidence 
     <lb/>
     any utterance of Dr. Robertson with regard 
     <lb/>
     to the Northwest. Dr. Robertson became a 
     <lb/>
     superintendent of missions of the Presby<lb break="no"/>terian church in 1882 and continued in that 
     <lb/>
     work until his death in 1902. And I believe 
     <lb/>
     that I state only the simple truth when I 
     <lb/>
     say that in the twenty years of his service 
     <lb/>
     no man ever did more for the Northwest, 
     <lb/>
     or said more for the Northwest, than this 
     <lb/>
     great man whose name I have given. Those 
     <lb/>
     of us who have had the honour and pleas<lb break="no"/>ure of receiving him at our own firesides 
     <lb/>
     know that his whole conversation was of 
     <lb/>
     the Northwest. And those of us who have 
     <lb/>
     attended the courts of the church to which 
     <lb/>
     he belonged, know that his great theme in 
     <lb/>
     the courts of our church was the 
     <lb/>
     building up of the Northwest and 
     <lb/>
     the extending of religious ordinances 
     <lb/>
     to the people of that great country. 
     <lb/>
     Dr. Robertson was a broad man. Dr. Rob<lb break="no"/>ertson was a man who could see past his 
     <lb/>
     own church. I have heard him say time 
     <lb/>
     and again that the was glad to see other 
     <lb/>
     churches in the Northwest, he wanted other 
     <lb/>
     churches to prosper, but one of his greatest 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="5089" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5089.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">5089</fw> <fw type="dateline">APRIL 28, 1905</fw> 
     
     troubles in the Northwest was that there 
     <lb/>
     was an overlapping of churches. He felt 
     <lb/>
     that in many cases that overlapping was 
     <lb/>
     not doing the good it ought to do. I men<lb break="no"/>tion these facts to remind hon. gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     who did not know Dr. Robertson, but who 
     <lb/>
     had perhaps heard of him, that he was a 
     <lb/>
     broad-minded man, a man who could take 
     <lb/>
     a broad view of all questions. From the 
     <lb/>
     year 1882 to 1902, I have followed every 
     <lb/>
     one of Dr. Robertson's reports presented to 
     <lb/>
     our church. I have followed these reports 
     <lb/>
     for twenty years, I have carefully looked 
     <lb/>
     into them, I have been myself a delegate 
     <lb/>
     to the assemblies of the Presbyterian 
     <lb/>
     church and I know that Dr. Robertson's re<lb break="no"/>ports were full of information and dealt 
     <lb/>
     in the most comprehensive manner with the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest Territories. When I mention 
     <lb/>
     the fact that in all these reports I failed 
     <lb/>
     to find one single word in twenty years 
     <lb/>
     against these schools in the Northwest it 
     <lb/>
     should have great weight with Protestants 
     <lb/>
     all over this country. If there was any<lb break="no"/>thing wrong with these schools in 1882, 
     <lb/>
     would not a broad-minded man like Dr. 
     <lb/>
     Robertson. whose life work was in the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest, have mentioned it in his first 
     <lb/>
     report? Would he not have mentioned it 
     <lb/>
     in his second report, or would he not, in 
     <lb/>
     the twenty reports that he presented to 
     <lb/>
     the general assembly, have had something 
     <lb/>
     to say regarding that question ? I have a 
     <lb/>
     great many of these reports here. He gives 
     <lb/>
     first a general sketch of the character and 
     <lb/>
     resources of the country and then he goes 
     <lb/>
     into the question as, it appeared at that 
     <lb/>
     time, of the economic and social develop<lb break="no"/>ment of the Northwest and his firm belief 
     <lb/>
     at that time was that the west was to be 
     <lb/>
     one of the most important parts of our 
     <lb/>
     land; it was to be one of the parts of our 
     <lb/>
     land that would contain more people than 
     <lb/>
     even the grand province of Ontario. He 
     <lb/>
     believed the day was coming when mil<lb break="no"/>lions would live in peace and luxury in 
     <lb/>
     that country. In giving his opinion on 
     <lb/>
     all these things he was always pressing 
     <lb/>
     for men and money to help on the work 
     <lb/>
     of the church and I am glad to say. now 
     <lb/>
     that that great man is gone. that he was 
     <lb/>
     broad minded enough to find no fault with 
     <lb/>
     any other church in all the reports he made 
     <lb/>
     to our church. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LANC1">Mr. LANCASTER</persName>. May I ask the hon. <lb/> gentleman (Mr. T.
                  Martin) a question? Did <lb/> Dr. Robertson at any time report against <lb/> the
                  provinces themselves dealing with the <lb/> school question? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. No, he did not. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LALO2">Mr. LALOR</persName>. Is the hon. gentleman (Mr. <lb/> T. Martin) aware
                  that the Presbytery in <lb/> his own county passed a resolution in con<lb break="no"/>demnation of this Bill? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. In my own county ? <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LALO2">Mr. LALOR</persName>. Part of your own county. <lb/>
               </p>
            
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5090</fw>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. Are you sure that is <lb/> the case? <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LALO2">Mr. LALOR</persName> I am informed so by gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen here.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. Who are they? I would <lb/> like to have those
                  gentlemen rise and make <lb/> that statement. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:CHIS3">Mr. CHISHOLM</persName>. I had a resolution sent <lb/> to me and I have
                  a resolution here from <lb/> the Presbytery of Saugeen and it stated <lb/> that
                  the resolution was to be sent to me <lb/> and also to my hon. friend from North
                  <lb/> Wellington (Mr. Martin). <lb/>
               </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. It so happens that I <lb/> do not live in the
                  same Presbytery as my <lb/> hon. friend from East Huron (Mr. Chis<lb break="no"/>holm). I know that in some Presbyteries <lb/> resolutions have been passed, but
                  the fact <lb/> that he may have received the resolution to <lb/> which the hon.
                  gentleman refers does not <lb/> prove that I did. We were told by the <lb/> hon.
                  member for Haldimand (Mr. Lalor) <lb/> that there was no one-<lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. I suppose the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman (Mr.
                  T. Martin) will not deny that <lb/> the Presbytery of Owen Sound, represent<lb break="no"/>ing some 2,500 families-<lb/>
               </p>
            <p>Some <persName ref="pers:ANON1">hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Order, order. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. I do not know it. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>Some hon. MEMBERS. Order. order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. I am in order. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FITZ1">Mr. FITZPATRICK</persName>. Mr. Speaker, I rise <lb/> to a point of
                  order. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. I am in order. Two can <lb/> play that game.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>Some hon. MEMBERS. Order. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. Order. With the con<lb break="no"/>sent of the
                  Speaker the hon. gentleman has <lb/> the right to ask him a question. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. The hon. member (Mr. <lb/> T. Martin) is living
                  in an adjoining county <lb/> to my own. As a matter of courtesy I <lb/> propose to
                  ask him a question which I <lb/> think I have a perfect right to do. I wish<lb break="no"/>ed to ask him if he was aware of the fact <lb/> that the Presbytery
                  of Owen Sound, repre<lb break="no"/>senting 2,500 families, had passed a strong
                  <lb/> resolution in opposition to the school clause <lb/> of this Bill. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOHN2">Mr. A. JOHNSTON</persName>. Write us a letter <lb/> about it. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. I was not aware of it. <lb/> I have no doubt
                  it is true. I have noticed <lb/> in the papers that several Presbyteries have
                  <lb/> done so, but I do not live in the Presbytery <lb/> of Owen Sound. I live in
                  the Presbytery <lb/> of Saugeen. It was stated by the hon. <lb/> member for
                  Haldimand last night that the <lb/> people of the Northwest Territories were <lb/>
                  very much apposed to the school clause in <lb/> the Bill. I have a letter here.
                  dated April <lb/>
                  <pb n="5091" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5091.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">5091</fw>
                  <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
                   28, from a gentleman in Regina and I have <lb/> also
                  another letter dated April 18, from an<lb break="no"/>other gentleman living in
                  the Northwest <lb/> Territories. I think it might be well to <lb/> give quotations
                  from these letters just to <lb/> put that hon. gentleman right in this res<lb break="no"/>pect. One of these letters states: <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     As far as the people out here are concerned, 
     <lb/>
    there is very general satisfaction with the Bill 
     <lb/>in all particulars, and I presume we ought to 
     <lb/>be the ones who are most directly interested 
     <lb/>and know best about it. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>The other letter says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     All here are satisfied with the school clause 
     <lb/>
     1n the Autonomy Bill, even Conservatives are 
     <lb/>
     finding very little fault. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>These letters are from gentlemen who 
     <lb/>
     have been living in the Northwest for 
     <lb/>
     twenty-two years, two prominent men in 
     <lb/>
     the Territories. I would also read a fur<lb break="no"/>ther extract for the benefit of the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for East Grey (Mr. Sproule) in re<lb break="no"/>gard to a matter upon which he seemed to 
     <lb/>
     be a little misty last night. I refer to the 
     <lb/>
     question of school books. The writer of 
     <lb/>
     this letter says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     We sell the same books to both schools. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>This is a long letter and I need not read 
     <lb/>
     it all through as it would only be taking 
     <lb/>
     up the time of the House. But, he inciden<lb break="no"/>tally mentions in this letter that they sell 
     <lb/>
     to both parties the same school books. I 
     <lb/>
     trust that that will set at rest the mind 
     <lb/>
     of the hon. member for East Grey, and 
     <lb/>
     that he will be able to keep his seat now 
     <lb/>
     until I get through. I was very glad also 
     <lb/>
     to hear from the hon. member for Haldi<lb break="no"/>mand (Mr. Lalor). He stated—I think I 
     <lb/>
     have his words here exactly—that there 
     <lb/>
     was no more independent paper in Canada 
     <lb/>
     than the 'Witness,' that it was a very in<lb break="no"/>dependent paper. I have the 'Witness' 
     <lb/>here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p><persName ref="pers:LALO2">Mr. LALOR</persName>. I did not make that state<lb break="no"/>ment. I
                  never mentioned the 'Witness.' <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. The Montreal 'Wit<lb break="no"/>ness' <lb/>
               </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:LALO2">Mr. LALOR</persName>. I never mentioned it at <lb/>all. <lb/>
               </p>

    

            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. What paper did you <lb/> mention ? <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LALO2">Mr. LALOR</persName>. The 'Farmers' Sun.' <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>An hon. MEMBER. Oh. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LALO2">Mr. LALOR</persName>. 'Hansard' shows it. Read <lb/> 'Hansard.' <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. I think I heard every <lb/> word that was
                  said. I think he mentioned <lb/> the ' Witness ' also. However, I will take
                  <lb/>that back. I do not want to use the hon.<lb/>gentleman's words in a way that
                  should<lb/>not be done, but I will read an extract<lb/>from the 'Witness.' I know
                  that the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of western Ontario believe that the<lb/>
                  <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5092</fw> 'Witness' is as reliable a paper from a <lb/> Protestant standpoint as we
                  have in Can<lb break="no"/>ada. It is an old established paper and <lb/> it seems
                  to have run in a very independent <lb/> course for many years. This paper is <lb/>
                  dated April 25th. A clergyman writing to <lb/> the paper on the school question
                  says this: <lb/>
               </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>To the editor of the 'Witness ' : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Sir,—As a reader of the ' Witness ' from boy<lb break="no"/>hood I am very much surprised at your atti<lb break="no"/>tude on the Autonomy Bill. You seem to think 
     <lb/>
     that too much stress is being laid on provincial<lb break="no"/>ism by us in Ontario. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>Well, I am afraid there has been, and I 
     <lb/>
     think that some of the members of the 
     <lb/>
     opposition in this House, when they look 
     <lb/>
     over their speeches a couple of years hence 
     <lb/>
     will come to the conclusion that they have 
     <lb/>
     gone too far in that direction. The letter 
     <lb/>
     continues : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Yet who were they who refused to enter into 
     <lb/>
     legislative union at confederation, and insisted 
     <lb/>
     on a federal union ? Who were the ones who 
     <lb/>
     at that time demanded provincial rights in cer<lb break="no"/>tain matters, of which education was one ? The 
     <lb/>
     Roman Catholics of Quebec were the opponents 
     <lb/>
     then of a legislative union. They were then 
     <lb/>
     advocates of provincialism, but what they 
     <lb/>
     claimed for themselves at that time they now 
     <lb/>
     are unwilling to grant the people of the west. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>No, Mr. Editor, the people of Ontario are true 
     <lb/>
     to the principles of confederation. It is the 
     <lb/>
     people of Quebec who have gone back on their 
     <lb/>
     principles. To my mind there has been no more 
     <lb/>
     audacious and treacherous act in our history 
     <lb/>
     than the attempt to fasten separate schools 
     <lb/>
     upon the west. Sir Wilfrid Laurier, as a faith<lb break="no"/>ful child of the Roman Catholic church, has de<lb break="no"/>termined before he retires from public life to 
     <lb/>
     do all he can for his church. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>We do not want a second Quebec in this Do<lb break="no"/>minion. One 'solid Quebec' is sufficient. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>For this reason I am extremely sorry to find 
     <lb/>
     that the 'Witness' is not on the side of the 
     <lb/>
     freedom and liberties of the people on this oc<lb break="no"/>casion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>The editor of the ' Witness replies to 
     <lb/>
     that letter in an article headed 'Is it treach<lb break="no"/>cry,' and he says: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">            
<p>That it was the Roman Catholics who opposed 
     <lb/>
     a legislative union when the provinces of Brit<lb break="no"/>ish North America came together, and insisted 
     <lb/>
     not only on a provincial autonomy for Quebec, 
     <lb/>
     but demanded that the interests of education 
     <lb/>
     should be under provincial jurisdiction ; so 
     <lb/>
     that it is they, and not the people of Ontario, 
     <lb/>
     who have gone back on the principles of con<lb break="no"/>federation ; what they then claimed for them<lb break="no"/>selves they are now unwilling to grant to the 
     <lb/>
     people of the west. Is this quite fair to them ? 
     <lb/>
     They certainly did demand to control their own 
     <lb/>
     educational system through the provincial gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, but they did not claim to control the 
     <lb/>
     education of the minority. The minority was 
     <lb/>
     to control its own educational system and has 
     <lb/>
     always done so. The majority would probably 
     <lb/>
     have acted rightly by the minority, even if they 
     <lb/>
     had been free to ac otherwise, but at confed<lb break="no"/>eration the minority demanded that their edu<lb break="no"/>cational freedom should be guaranteed by the 
     <lb/>
     national compact, and so it was. Now when 
     <lb/>
     new provinces are being created the Roman 
     <lb/>
     Catholics ask for the minorities there, what 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="5093" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5093.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">5093</fw> <fw type="dateline">APRIL 28, 1905</fw> 
           
     the minority here enjoys, namely, control by 
     <lb/>
     constitutional right of its own education. No 
     <lb/>
     doubt the two systems are different in charac<lb break="no"/>ter. The one is sectarian and sectionalizing 
     <lb/>
     and estranging ; the other is unsectarian and 
     <lb/>
     uniting. The latter is without question, in our 
     <lb/>
     mind, the best ; but our neighbours conscien~ 
     <lb/>
     tiously take a distinctly opposite view. Each 
     <lb/>
     part of the community would prefer that, its 
     <lb/>
     own system should be universal, but we can 
     <lb/>
     scarcely imagine how the minority of this pro<lb break="no"/>vince would feel or act if the system of the 
     <lb/>
     majority was forced upon it. The Protestants 
     <lb/>
     of Quebec would say that their religious liberty 
     <lb/>
     was invaded and would probably rise in revolt 
     <lb/>
     against such despotism. Determined to have 
     <lb/>
     their own conscientious convictions respected, 
     <lb/>
     they cannot but respect the convictions of their 
     <lb/>
     neighbours, however much they may deplore 
     <lb/>
     them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>What our correspondent asks is, that the ma<lb break="no"/>jority in the new provinces should have the de<lb break="no"/>termination of all school questions absolutely 
     <lb/>
     in their hands. Our belief is that they would 
     <lb/>
     use such a power in a way as liberal to the 
     <lb/>
     minority as the Autonomy Act proposes. In 
     <lb/>
     fact what is proposed is to extend the system 
     <lb/>
     which has been brought into shape under local 
     <lb/>
     legislation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>I would like the hon. member for Leeds 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Taylor) to take note of that because 
     <lb/>
     he seems to be doubtful on that question. 
     <lb/>
     I am sure that if his mind is clear on that 
     <lb/>
     point, he will do as he promised in his 
     <lb/>
     speech and vote for the Bill. He is now 
     <lb/>
     not only getting the views of members on 
     <lb/>
     this side of the House. but he can take his 
     <lb/>
     authority from the editor of the Montreal 
     <lb/>
     ' Witness.' 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     But we cannot blame the minority for wanting 
     <lb/>
     to have the minority right constitutionally 
     <lb/>
     guaranteed, as that of the Protestants is in 
     <lb/>
     Quebec, nor can we think that for proposing to 
     <lb/>
     give them this security, a premier who is seek<lb break="no"/>ing only to be true and fair to all should be 
     <lb/>
     spoken of as guilty of the most audacious and 
     <lb/>
     treacherous act in our history. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>That statement ought to be of some value 
     <lb/>
     to the hon. member for Haldimand (Mr. La<lb break="no"/>lor) and I will read it again. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     Nor can we think that for proposing to give 
     <lb/>
     them this security a premier who is seeking 
     <lb/>
     only to be true and fair to all should be spoken 
     <lb/>
     of as guilty of the most audacious and treacher~ 
     <lb/>
     one act in our history. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>I do earnestly hope that when we see the 
     <lb/>
     very best amongst the newspapers of our 
     <lb/>
     country taking up the question in this way, 
     <lb/>
     the members of the opposition in this House 
     <lb/>
     will become more tolerant; they will show 
     <lb/>
     more respect for the minority in this coun<lb break="no"/>try, and that they will not try to inflame the 
     <lb/>
     public mind into outbursts of passion be<lb break="no"/>tween Roman Catholics and Protestants. I 
     <lb/>
     have been one of those who lived amongst 
     <lb/>
     Catholics all my life; I have Catholic 
     <lb/>
     neighbours on all sides of me; by jumping 
     <lb/>
     over the fence I can get into the field of a 
     <lb/>
     Catholic, and I can say this, and there 
     <lb/>
     are members of the opposition here who 
     <lb/>
     know it is true; we have lived together 
     <lb/>
     like friends, we have lived together like 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5094</fw>
       
     brethren, and I ask : cannot we be allowed 
     <lb/>
     to continue to live in that way? Cannot the 
     <lb/>
     minority be allowed to have religious teach<lb break="no"/>ing in their schools as they have in On<lb break="no"/>tario, without anybody being the worse for 
     <lb/>
     it? I have lived in my township for 48 
     <lb/>
     years and I cannot see Where any Pro<lb break="no"/>testant has lost one iota because there are 
     <lb/>
     two separate schools in that township. 1 
     <lb/>
     appeal to the members of the opposition in 
     <lb/>
     this House to come down to fair-play. I 
     <lb/>
     appeal to them to leave this intolerance 
     <lb/>
     aside and to frown upon the injustice per<lb break="no"/>petrated in this paper before me which 
     <lb/>
     contains the most scandalous cartoons which 
     <lb/>
     ever appeared in print. Let the incidents of 
     <lb/>
     the past couple of months he blotted out 
     <lb/>
     for ever, and let us as members of this legis<lb break="no"/>lature show that we at least are possessed 
     <lb/>
     of a good deal of common sense and that 
     <lb/>
     we have the spirit of fair-play and of wis<lb break="no"/>dom about us. Let us not endorse the un<lb break="no"/>just warfare that the Toronto ' News' has 
     <lb/>
     indulged in for some time past with its 
     <lb/>
     tremendous headings : ' A free west, a Com<lb break="no"/>mon school, provincial rights, religious equal<lb break="no"/>ity.' The idea conveyed by these headings 
     <lb/>
     is a false one. Who can deny that there 
     <lb/>
     is a free west, and who can deny that 
     <lb/>
     there are not common schools in the west ? 
     <lb/>
     Where is the evidence that provincial rights 
     <lb/>
     are infringed upon ? Are we infringing 
     <lb/>
     upon provincial rights before they have a 
     <lb/>
     province? We must create a province be<lb break="no"/>fore they can have provincial rights, and 
     <lb/>
     I guarantee the members of this House 
     <lb/>
     that so far as I am concerned, that after 
     <lb/>
     the provinces of Alberta and Saskatchewan 
     <lb/>
     are created on the first day of July next, 
     <lb/>
     if there is any attempt to take away their 
     <lb/>
     rights, I shall be the first to jump up and 
     <lb/>
     defend provincial rights. But how can we 
     <lb/>
     defend provincial rights until they are pro<lb break="no"/>vinces ? The ' Witness ' continues to say : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     We should like to ask our correspondent to 
     <lb/>
     put to himself one question. Let him imagine, 
     <lb/>
     if he can, that the present prospect was that 
     <lb/>
     of a large Roman Catholic majority in one of 
     <lb/>
     these provinces, and of a large Mormon majo[r]<lb break="no"/>ity in the other, and then ask himself if, under 
     <lb/>
     such an outlook, he would be-quite as sure as 
     <lb/>
     he is that the constitution guarantee those 
     <lb/>
     majorities the right to legislate with regard to 
     <lb/>
     education just as they might like, and would be 
     <lb/>
     be quite as sure as he is that they ought to 
     <lb/>
     have that unlimited power. If he finds his 
     <lb/>
     mind revolt against giving absolute power to 
     <lb/>
     the provinces in such a case, he will be able to 
     <lb/>
     see the attitude of mind of those who are de<lb break="no"/>manding that some limit be placed on possible 
     <lb/>
     majority despotism. Practically the system of 
     <lb/>
     schools which prevails in the provinces, and 
     <lb/>
     which it is proposed to perpetuate, seems to us 
     <lb/>
     an excellent one. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>I think these words are particularly appli<lb break="no"/>cable to the members of the oppos1tion. 
     <lb/>
     They never have seemed to realize that fact, 
     <lb/>
     and if they will not take the word of the 
     <lb/>
     Prime Minister for it. if they will not take 
     <lb/>
     the word of any member of the government, 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="5095" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5095.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">5095</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> 
         
     surely they will take the word of a news<lb break="no"/>paper like the Montreal 'Witness' which 
     <lb/>
     as an independent paper has stood up for 
     <lb/>
     Protestantism ever since it was first pub<lb break="no"/>lished. Surely we can give these gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     the credit of being fairly good men ; and 
     <lb/>
     surely we can claim that we are not strain<lb break="no"/>ing our conscience when we have the plea<lb break="no"/>sure of voting for the Bill now before the 
     <lb/>
     House. This paper goes on to say : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     Schools are necessarily carried on and man<lb break="no"/>aged by the local majority. What is guaran<lb break="no"/>teed is, first, that religious teaching shall not 
     <lb/>
     invade the hours of general study ; and, second, 
     <lb/>
     that if any religious minority feels dissatisfied 
     <lb/>
     with majority management, it shall be free to 
     <lb/>
     have a school under its own management, but 
     <lb/>
     that such school shall be required to come up 
     <lb/>
     to the same standard of teaching and be under 
     <lb/>
     the same limitations. This is of course a guar<lb break="no"/>antee for Protestant minorities as well as for 
     <lb/>
     Roman Catholic ones. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>I believe that is an article well worth 
     <lb/>
     studying and considering. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:GUNN1">Mr. GUNN</persName>. Will the hon. member give <lb/> us the date of that
                  paper ? <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. I will give you the <lb/> paper itself ; but I
                  would rather you would <lb/> not read it while I am speaking. There is <lb/>
                  another point I wish to refer to. The hon. <lb/> member for Haldimand (Mr. Lalor)
                  made a <lb/> rather mean insinuation about the interfer<lb break="no"/>ence of the
                  Papal ablegate. I know that that <lb/> has been part of the stock-in-trade of the
                  <lb/> opposition—to try to fix upon the premier <lb/> that by some means he had
                  mentioned the <lb/> matter to the Papal ablegate, or that the <lb/> Papal ablegate
                  had mentioned the matter <lb/> to him. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LALO2">Mr. LALOR</persName>. Mr. Speaker, I rise to a <lb/> point of order. The
                  hon. gentleman has <lb/> again misstated. I never insinuated that <lb/> the
                  premier had an interview with the Papal <lb/> ablegate. I said that the member for
                     Bran<lb break="no"/>don (Mr. Sifton) had made insinuations from <lb/> which we
                  inferred-<lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. I did not say that. <lb/> The hon. gentleman
                  should not put words <lb/> in my mouth. I said that he had referred <lb/> to the
                  Papal ablegate, and so he did ; and <lb/> not only the hon. member for Haldimand,
                  <lb/> but other members of the opposition have <lb/> attempted to drag his name
                  into this dis<lb break="no"/>cussion. While I believe there is no war<lb break="no"/>rant for that, still, as a citizen of the pro<lb break="no"/>vince
                  of Ontario, I do not suppose it would <lb/> be out of place for me to call the
                  attention <lb/> of the House to some dealings of govern<lb break="no"/>ments with
                  Protestant ministers. I propose <lb/> to mention to the House certain facts in
                  <lb/> our provincial history, and in doing so I am <lb/> not breaking any
                  confidence. I am able to <lb/> state that the late Sir Oliver Mowat more <lb/>
                  than once consulted eminent divines in my <lb/>own church. I do not say that he
                  did not <lb/>consult divines of other churches, but I am <lb/>going to speak
                  particularly of my own <lb/>church, and then perhaps people cannot find <lb/>
                  <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5096</fw> so much fault with me. It is well known <lb/> that the late Principal Caven,
                  head of Knox <lb/> Theological College in Toronto, stood very <lb/> near to Sir
                  Oliver Mowat, and was frequent<lb break="no"/>ly consulted by him, and that on
                  matters <lb/> pertaining to the state. It is also a matter <lb/> of history, as
                  stated in the life of the late <lb/> Principal Grant, the head of another Pres<lb break="no"/>byterian college. written by his own son, <lb/> that he was invited
                  by Sir Oliver Mowat to <lb/> take a seat in his cabinet as Minister of <lb/>
                  Education. That was somewhere in the <lb/> early eighties. There is nothing
                  private <lb/> about that ; but the conclusion I wish to <lb/> draw from it is
                  this. If the present premier, <lb/> or any other Liberal premier, dared in the
                  <lb/> same way to consult with any clergyman of <lb/> the Catholic Church, what an
                  enormous up<lb break="no"/>roar would be raised in this House, and <lb/> also, I
                  am sorry to say, in some parts of the <lb/> province of Ontario. We know that a
                  great <lb/> deal of the present excitement and intoler<lb break="no"/>ance is
                  batched in the city of Toronto, and <lb/> it is sent broadcast by some of our
                  daily <lb/> papers, by means, not only of large head<lb break="no"/>lines, but
                  also by scandalous and shameful <lb/> cartoons, which the best press of our
                     coun<lb break="no"/>try should be ashamed of and will be asham<lb break="no"/>ed of five or ten years hence. I have it <lb/> from pretty good authority—if I
                  am wrong <lb/> I will stand corrected—that another Presby<lb break="no"/>terian
                  divine. Dr. Pringle, of the Yukon, <lb/> when he was in Ottawa, was consulted, or
                  <lb/> at least conversed with, by the right hon. <lb/> leader of the government
                  about the affairs <lb/> of the Yukon ; and as the hon. leader of <lb/> the
                  opposition yesterday left it open to me <lb/> to propose some one who would make a
                  <lb/> first-class Governor of the Yukon. I believe <lb/> Dr. Pringle would be a
                  good man to fill that <lb/> position. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>Now, Mr. Speaker, I will not take up much 
     <lb/>
     more of the time of the House. The educa<lb break="no"/>tional clauses in the Bill are of a very in<lb break="no"/>teresting and important character, and no 
     <lb/>
     doubt that is why there has been so little 
     <lb/>
     discussion of the other clauses. The consti<lb break="no"/>tutional question I do not propose to dis<lb break="no"/>cuss. Like the speaker who preceded me, 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for Haldimand (Mr. Lalor), 
     <lb/>
     I do not belong to the legal profession, and 
     <lb/>
     therefore shall leave constitutional points to 
     <lb/>
     be discussed by men who are versed in legal 
     <lb/>
     science. I believe, however, that laymen 
     <lb/>
     are quite capable of judging from the 
     <lb/>
     speeches we have had in this House who 
     <lb/>
     has had the best of the argument ; and I 
     <lb/>
     am sure that there is no man in this House, 
     <lb/>
     who wishes to express an opinion consistent 
     <lb/>
     with his own conscience and who is not tied 
     <lb/>
     down by the leader of his party, who will 
     <lb/>
     say that the weight of the argument on the 
     <lb/>
     constitutional question has not been on the 
     <lb/>
     government side. Let me also say that I 
     <lb/>
     stand up for provincial rights ; and if we 
     <lb/>
     want more evidence that we are doing so 
     <lb/>
     than the hon. member for Centre York (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Campbell) gave us last night, then we are 
     <lb/>
     pretty hard to please. I believe he proved 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="5097" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5097.jpg"/>
         <fw type="num">5097</fw> <fw type="dateline">APRIL 28, 1905</fw> 


     conclusively that we are on the side of pro<lb break="no"/>vincial rights. and I shall not attempt there<lb break="no"/>fore to add anything to what he has said. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>A public school system is no doubt an 
     <lb/>
     agent in the promoting of unity among our 
     <lb/>
     settlers, but there is another side to be con<lb break="no"/>sidered. As I have said before, I belong to 
     <lb/>
     a church which has exerted itself to create 
     <lb/>
     a religious sentiment in the west, and I 
     <lb/>
     have given you from leading men in that 
     <lb/>
     church evidence to show that the schools, 
     <lb/>
     as they are now constituted in the west, 
     <lb/>
     are satisfactory to the people belonging to 
     <lb/>
     that church. For twenty years—and to 
     <lb/>
     that fact we should attach a great deal of 
     <lb/>
     weight—the man who took such an interest 
     <lb/>
     in education in the Northwest, Dr. Robert<lb break="no"/>son, never said a word against the school 
     <lb/>
     system as it existed there in 1882. And if 
     <lb/>
     we read through the ordinances, we cannot 
     <lb/>
     but help coming to the conclusion that. 
     <lb/>
     from a Protestant standpoint, these schools 
     <lb/>
     are very lunch nearer a national system 
     <lb/>
     than they were even at that date. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:BLAI1">Mr. BLAIN</persName>. Wonld the hon. gentleman <lb/> be good enough to
                  give to the House the <lb/> name of any leading Presbyterian minister <lb/> who
                  has endorse this Bill ? <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCKE4">Mr. D. D. MCKENZIE</persName>. Is the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman
                  looking for a living Presbyterian? <lb/> I am alive and I am one. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART4">Mr. T. MARTIN</persName>. My hon. friend knows <lb/> as well as I do
                  that he cannot get one out <lb/> of ten Presbyterians who is not in favour <lb/>
                  of the Bill. I have a number of letters in <lb/> my desk from Presbyterian
                  ministers which, <lb/> if they were not private, I would read to <lb/> the House,
                  in support of the Bill ; and if <lb/> the hon. gentleman thinks I am not stating
                  <lb/> what is true, I shall let him read them. I <lb/> have also letters from
                  Presbyterian minis<lb break="no"/>ters which I have been authorized to show <lb/>
                  to the right hon. the First Minister, in <lb/> which they state they are heartily
                  in sym<lb break="no"/>pathy with him on the school question. <lb/> There is not
                  one Presbyterian out of ten in <lb/> the province of Ontario who will not stand
                  <lb/> up in favour of this measure. For the ben<lb break="no"/>efit of my hon.
                  friend I may also state that <lb/> these letters—and I have more if I wished <lb/>
                  to read them—are from members of the <lb/> Presbyterian church—and not only
                  members <lb/> but elders. For my part, I cannot resent <lb/> any one's desire to
                  have his religious views <lb/> taught to his children just as etiiciently as <lb/>
                  arithmetic or geography. I am one of those <lb/> who believe in having rellgion
                  taught in <lb/> the schools, and I would say in all earnest<lb break="no"/>nes
                  that if forty per cent of the Dominion-<lb/> or forty—one per cent to be more
                  accurate-<lb/> instead of wishing to have religion taught <lb/> in the schools
                  were in favour of ostracising <lb/> religion from our schools—if forty per cent
                  <lb/> of the province of Ontario or of the Dom<lb break="no"/>inion were in that
                  state of mind that they <lb/> wanted their children to go to Godless <lb/>
                  schools, I would say: God help the parents ! <lb/> But because forty-one per cent
                  of our people <lb/>
                  <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5098</fw> are asking for separate schools in order <lb/> that they may have their
                  children taught <lb/> their religion in those schools—and we know <lb/> that
                  unfortunately Protestants and Catho<lb break="no"/>lics cannot teach their
                  respective religions <lb/> together—I shall not be the one to raise <lb/> my voice
                  and hand against granting their <lb/> wish. I say further, with all earnestness,
                  <lb/> that I trust the time is coming when the <lb/> Protestants will unite and
                  also plead for <lb/> more religion to be taught in the schools. <lb/> As we grow
                  up in years, we see the other <lb/> side of life and a great deal of it ; and I
                  <lb/> tell you gentlemen it is a very serious <lb/> thing, when we are raising our
                  families, to <lb/> know that they are not being raised in the <lb/> fear of God.
                  If we are to have good citi<lb break="no"/>zens and a great country, surely we
                  must <lb/> remember that righteousness exalteth a na<lb break="no"/>tion. But how
                  can we have righteousness, <lb/> if it is not taught to our children at every
                  <lb/> opportunity? I come from Scotland, where, <lb/> in many of our schools,
                  there was but very <lb/> little taught besides the Bible and the <lb/>
                  Presbyterian Catechism, and I have yet to <lb/> meet a Scotchman who is ashamed of
                     him<lb break="no"/>self and his education. Where will you <lb/> find men better
                  educated than the Scotch<lb break="no"/>men ? I come from that country, and I
                  <lb/> feel that, as noble sons of Canada, we should <lb/> imbue into our school
                  system a little more <lb/> religion. Perhaps our boys and girls might <lb/> not
                  have such an education as they other<lb break="no"/>wise would in some other
                  things, but we <lb/> know that the teaching of the Bible will <lb/> impart to them
                  a moral training which no <lb/> other teaching can give. It gives them a <lb/>
                  training such as no other book can give. <lb/> Why should we, a lot of intelligent
                  men, <lb/> spend weeks and weeks in this House dis<lb break="no"/>cussing the
                  question of whether we should <lb/> try to deprive forty per cent of our people
                  <lb/> of the privilege of having religion taught in <lb/> their schools if they
                  wish it ? I am speaking <lb/> as a citizen of Canada and a member of <lb/>
                  parliament from the province of Ontario <lb/> representing a constituency which I
                  do not <lb/> believe is equalled by half a dozen other con<lb break="no"/>stituencies in this Dominion. We have not <lb/> only a country of which we are
                  proud, we <lb/> have not only land that cannot be beaten on <lb/> the face of the
                  earth for the production of <lb/> the best articles of human food, but we have
                  <lb/> also a class of farmers in the county of <lb/> Wellington who are known from
                  end to end <lb/> of this country. It is a pleasure to visit <lb/> the homes of the
                  farmers of Wellington <lb/> county and to go about their houses and <lb/> their
                  farms. Their farms would stand com<lb break="no"/>parison with some of the best
                  farms in <lb/> Midlothian, in Scotland ; I have the honour <lb/> of representing
                  such a class of people, in<lb break="no"/>telligent men, tolerant men, and a great
                  <lb/> majority of them Protestants, and I am not <lb/> afraid to take the stand I
                  have taken in <lb/> this House. Or if the member for South <lb/> York (Mr. W. F.
                  Maclean) with all his chal<lb break="no"/>lenges wishes to come up some night or
                  <lb/>some day I will see that the largest build<lb break="no"/><pb n="5099" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5099.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">5099</fw>
                  <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
                  ing in my riding is obtained for the purpose <lb/> of a
                  meeting. I will give him all the time <lb/> he wishes, and I will see that the
                  meeting <lb/> is well advertised. I shall go there al<lb break="no"/>though I am
                  only one of the members of <lb/> this House, only a country member and I <lb/>
                  shall put my case before my people myself <lb/> and he may put his case as he
                  likes ; he <lb/> may take under his arm all these cartoons <lb/> that have been in
                  his paper and hang them <lb/> around the walls ; he may take all the in<lb break="no"/>flammatory articles that have appeared in <lb/> his paper and
                  distribute them among the <lb/> people. But I am not afraid to go up there <lb/>
                  and lay the whole case before my people <lb/> and I know what the verdict will be.
                  I <lb/> know that nine-tenths of the people will <lb/> back me up in the position
                  which I have <lb/> taken to-day and in the vote which I intend <lb/> to give.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>I sympathize with the determination to 
     <lb/>
     have separate schools in some form, and 
     <lb/>
     since that determination exists we must 
     <lb/>
     consider well the question whether it is fair 
     <lb/>
     to tax minorities for public schools which 
     <lb/>
     they do not use. To create such a grievance 
     <lb/>
     would divide rather than unite the elements 
     <lb/>
     of our population. We have been told very 
     <lb/>
     often in this House that the best system 
     <lb/>
     would be for the children to be brought up 
     <lb/>
     together, but under our present circum<lb break="no"/>stances is it not true also that we would 
     <lb/>
     thus divide rather than unite the ele<lb break="no"/>ments of population ? Of course it may be 
     <lb/>
     said, I hope it will not prove true, that the 
     <lb/>
     provinces could continue the privileges for 
     <lb/>
     which this Bill provides. I quite under<lb break="no"/>stand that the provinces might do that, but 
     <lb/>
     we can easily understand why minorities 
     <lb/>
     should be eager that the constitutional 
     <lb/>
     guarantee which only federal legislation can 
     <lb/>
     give, should be established. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>In conclusion, I wish to say a word in 
     <lb/>
     favour of the right hon. gentleman who 
     <lb/>
     leads the government (Sir Wilfrid Laurier) 
     <lb/>
     in addition to what I have already said. 
     <lb/>
     Can we find evidence of one instance—I 
     <lb/>
     know we hear the charges—but can we find 
     <lb/>
     evidence to show that in any case the right 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman has ever given himself away 
     <lb/>
     to the church to which he belongs ? I have 
     <lb/>
     already spoken of Sir Oliver Mowat even 
     <lb/>
     asking a Presbyterian minister to join his 
     <lb/>
     cabinet, and I would say that I believe there 
     <lb/>
     are very few men who have ever sat in 
     <lb/>
     parliament who have kept themselves freer 
     <lb/>
     from such a course as the premier is charged 
     <lb/>
     with than that right hon. gentleman has 
     <lb/>
     done. Let me remind the House of the 
     <lb/>
     patriotism of the Prime Minister (Sir Wilfrid 
     <lb/>
     Laurier) what a true patriot he has been to 
     <lb/>
     this Canada of ours, what a broad-minded 
     <lb/>
     far-seeing statesman, and yet we find hon. 
     <lb/>
     members of this House abusing him in such 
     <lb/>
     a manner as did the hon. member for Haldi<lb break="no"/>mand (Mr. Lalor) last night. I am glad that 
     <lb/>
     the leader of the opposition (Mr. R. L. Bor<lb break="no"/>den) has been tolerant in his remarks. It is 
     <lb/>
     a credit to him, but I am sorry he has not 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5100</fw>
           
     been able to vote for the question, and to 
     <lb/>
     induce his followers to be a little more toler<lb break="no"/>ant in their remarks. Such inciting and 
     <lb/>
     inflammatory articles as we have seen in 
     <lb/>
     their press, such inciting and inflammatory 
     <lb/>
     speeches as we have heard from oppo<lb break="no"/>sition members in this House cannot 
     <lb/>
     be of benefit to this Dominion. I deplore 
     <lb/>
     the use of such language in this coun<lb break="no"/>try, I regret that we have men in Canada 
     <lb/>
     who will come to parliament and raise their 
     <lb/>
     voices in such an intolerant way against the 
     <lb/>
     Roman Catholics of this country and in 
     <lb/>
     opposition to their having the schools which 
     <lb/>
     they wish to have. I would urge them to 
     <lb/>
     for ever drop such a course, to be tolerant 
     <lb/>
     and instead of raising these flames of re<lb break="no"/>ligious prejudice and cries of religious in<lb break="no"/>equality, to help on the good work which our 
     <lb/>
     great premier has carried on with such great 
     <lb/>
     success, the unification of the people of this 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:ELSO1">Mr. P. ELSON</persName> (East Middlesex). Mr. <lb/> Speaker, in rising
                  to make a few remarks <lb/> on this very important question, the Auton<lb break="no"/>omy Bill, I wish to say to the House that I <lb/> shall be very
                  brief and shall not weary the <lb/> members by a long speech. Neither do I <lb/>
                  intend to allude to any extent to the remarks <lb/> which have been made by the
                  hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man who has just taken his seat. 1 know <lb/> that at
                  this late stage in the debate it is <lb/> difficult to bring forward anything new
                  that <lb/> would be of interest to the House, and there<lb break="no"/>fore I
                  shall be very brief, but at the same <lb/> time I shall advance a few ideas of my
                  own. <lb/> Being as I am, a native born Canadian. <lb/> there is no portion of the
                  face of the earth in <lb/> which I feel so much interest as in that <lb/> portion
                  which is bounded by the outward <lb/> boundaries of the Dominion of Canada. <lb/>
                  There are no people who live and move and <lb/> have their being upon the face of
                  the globe, <lb/> in whom I feel so much interest as in those <lb/> persons who are
                  Canadians and who at <lb/> least live on Canadian soil. We have in our <lb/>
                  country a very great variety of most valu<lb break="no"/>able natural resources,
                  which have been <lb/> given us by the bountiful hand of a bounti<lb break="no"/>ful Giver ; and upon these resources and <lb/> with these resources, it is
                  altogether likely <lb/> a great nation will be built up in the Do<lb break="no"/>minion of Canada. Now. Sir, it is the duty <lb/> of the government of the day,
                  in connection <lb/> with the people of the country, to develop <lb/> these
                  resources as quickly and as reasonably <lb/> as we can. Most certainly, Sir, do I
                  feel it <lb/> to be the duty of the government to so <lb/> govern the people that
                  contentment will <lb/> rest on their minds. To so govern the <lb/> people that—Mr.
                  Speaker, I cannot find <lb/> words to convey the meaning I desire <lb/> to convey
                  to the House unless I am <lb/> permitted to use a few of those words <lb/> which
                  you so reverently read on every <lb/> occasion when you open the sitting of this
                  <lb/> House, and when you pray. That the de<lb break="no"/>liberations of the
                  three branches of the <lb/>
                  <pb n="5101" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5101.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">5101</fw>
                  <fw type="dateline">April 28, 1905</fw>
                   federal parliament shall be such and shall <lb/> have
                  such effect that peace and happiness, <lb/> truth and justice, religion and piety
                  shall <lb/> be established amongst us for all genera<lb break="no"/>tions. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>Now, Sir, I feel that these words apply, 
     <lb/>
     not only to the hon. members of the House, 
     <lb/>
     and to the hon. members of the Senate of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, and to His Excellency the Governor 
     <lb/>
     General, but also to the masses of the 
     <lb/>
     people. I hope that these words will apply 
     <lb/>
     to those people who are residents or who 
     <lb/>
     may hereafter become residents of that por<lb break="no"/>tion of the Northwest Territories which are 
     <lb/>
     about to blossom forth into two fine pro<lb break="no"/>vinces known as Alberta and Saskatchewan. 
     <lb/>
     ' Peace and happiness ;' it is indeed diffi<lb break="no"/>cult for me to explain really the meaning 
     <lb/>
     of those words. And yet, happiness is 
     <lb/>
     something that we are all seeking after, 
     <lb/>
     that we are all trying to grasp, something 
     <lb/>
     we are endeavouring to obtain as much of 
     <lb/>
     as we can before we shuffle off this mortal 
     <lb/>
     coil. And how can we expect to obtain this 
     <lb/>
     boon ? Will it come to us of itself ? Will 
     <lb/>
     it come to us spontaneously? Will it flow 
     <lb/>
     upon us like a river and envelop us ? No, 
     <lb/>
     Sir, it will not come that way. It will 
     <lb/>
     not come except by preparation on our part, 
     <lb/>
     by elfort on our part, to cultivate a social, 
     <lb/>
     friendly feeling between ourselves and those 
     <lb/>
     persons with whom we are brought in con<lb break="no"/>tact. And when ought we to begin to culti<lb break="no"/>vate this friendly feeling ? Is it When we 
     <lb/>
     reach the middle years of life ? Is it when 
     <lb/>
    we are on the downward incline? No, I 
     <lb/>hold that that is not the time—though per<lb break="no"/>haps better late than never. I hold that 
     <lb/>the right time for us to cultivate, that, 
     <lb/>friendly, social feeling which ought to exist 
     <lb/>between the people of our country is when 
     <lb/>we are young, when our hearts are sus<lb break="no"/>ceptible to good impressions. And there is 
     <lb/>no place in my opinion better than the public 
     <lb/>school for boys to become acquainted with 
     <lb/>one another and to cultivate that feeling of 
     <lb/>friendliness and sociability that it is so 
     <lb/>desirable to have amongst neighbours and 
     <lb/>citizens of the same country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>I am sure, Mr. Speaker, you will pardon 
     <lb/>
     me if for a moment I allude to my own 
     <lb/>
     experience as a boy in the public schools, 
     <lb/>
     because, Sir, sometimes the experience of 
     <lb/>
     one person may be taken as a type of the 
     <lb/>
     experience of thousands. When I attend<lb break="no"/>ed the public schools as a boy, a son of 
     <lb/>
     Protestant parents, I met there boys of 
     <lb/>
     about my own age who were sons of Ro<lb break="no"/>man Catholic parents. These boys whom I 
     <lb/>
     met were strictly taught in the religious 
     <lb/>
     faith of their parents, the Roman Catholic 
     <lb/>
     faith. Now, Mr. Speaker, I am pleased to 
     <lb/>
     say, I am delighted to say that I formed 
     <lb/>
     an attachment for those boys and they for 
     <lb/>
     me. We became very agreeable and friend<lb break="no"/>ly towards one another. We sat in the 
     <lb/>
     same classes, we helped each other with 
     <lb/>
     our lessons, we played together upon 
     <lb/>
     the old school-house green with the 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5102</fw>
           
     joyful hilarity which is one of the 
     <lb/>
     greatest possessions of boyhood. And 
     <lb/>
     I am delighted to be able to say 
     <lb/>
    that that same pleasant feeling continued 
     <lb/>between myself and the friends I made at 
     <lb/>school. When we reached the years of man<lb break="no"/>hood and dealt together in various ways, 
     <lb/>it was always with a degree of confidence 
     <lb/>in one another and in a friendly, social 
     <lb/>spirit. And that feeling lasts with us up to 
     <lb/>the present time, and I am satisfied that it 
     <lb/>will continue so long as we live. Now, 
     <lb/>suppose there had been a separate school in 
     <lb/>that particular school section to which I 
     <lb/>belonged, and in which I attended school. 
     <lb/>Had that been the case, no doubt these 
     <lb/>friends of mine would have attended the 
     <lb/>separate school and I would have attend<lb break="no"/>ed the public school. Possibly we might 
     <lb/>never have become acquainted at all. Or, 
     <lb/>we might have known one another simply 
     <lb/>as living in the same school section two or 
     <lb/>three miles apart—for I speak of rural 
     <lb/>schools altogether—and perhaps we might 
     <lb/>be a little acquainted. When we met each 
     <lb/>other on the country road it would be a 
     <lb/>cool nod of the head on the part of one 
     <lb/>and a formal 'good morning ; ' and a cold 
     <lb/>nod of the head on the other side and an 
     <lb/>equally formal ' How do you do '—and that 
     <lb/>would be all the friendliness between us. 
     <lb/>There would not be the social feeling and 
     <lb/>pleasantness that ought to exist between 
     <lb/>people of the same neighbourhood. And 
     <lb/>possibly this breaking up of interests might 
     <lb/>have led to mutual distrust and to a feel<lb break="no"/>ing on the part of each that the other 
     <lb/>was only waiting an opportunity to do him 
     <lb/>an injury. But feelings like this should not 
     <lb/>exist ; and therefore, I hold that the public 
     <lb/>school is the place in which to bring the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of the rising generation together. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve that when boys are brought up in the 
     <lb/>public school together they become acquaint<lb break="no"/>ed with one another and there is a warm 
     <lb/>friendliness and sociability such as ought to 
     <lb/>exist between them. And so, when they 
     <lb/>meet each other on the country road there 
     <lb/>is a warm grasp of the hand and a ' John 
     <lb/>how do you do ? ' And an answering hand 
     <lb/>clasp with the warm greeting. ' Charley, I 
     <lb/>I am glad to meet you.' I hold that the 
     <lb/>separate school creates discord and irritation 
     <lb/>and unfriendliness, and that it strikes a 
     <lb/>blow at the very foundation of the public 
     <lb/>school which has for its object the uniting 
     <lb/>together of the rising generation. The pub<lb break="no"/>lic school seems to harmonize, to a certain 
     <lb/>extent, the minds of the rising generation. 
     <lb/>and rubs off the rough edges of all classes, 
     <lb/>races and creeds. Attending the same 
     <lb/>school, they feel that they know one 
     <lb/>another, and they march along together, 
     <lb/>as it were, a united body of men, 
     <lb/>each perhaps having his own views 
     <lb/>with regard to religion,—which is rlght 
     <lb/>enough—but of one mind in doing the best 
     <lb/>they can for themselves and for the build<lb break="no"/>ing up of Canada as a great nation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="5103" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5103.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">5103</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> 

            <p>Therefore, I hold that the public school is the<lb/>right school for this country. However, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Speaker. I believe that every school, as far 
     <lb/>
     as religious instruction is concerned, should 
     <lb/>
     open with the Lord's prayer. Further than 
     <lb/>
     that I feel that the instruction should be 
     <lb/>
     continued to secular teaching. The home, 
     <lb/>
     the Sunday school and the church are the 
     <lb/>
     proper places for moral and religious in<lb break="no"/>struction. When children go to Sunday 
     <lb/>
    school or church, their minds are more 
     <lb/>in accord with the object that they 
     <lb/>are trying to attain, they are more 
     <lb/>ready to accept religious instruction 
     <lb/>than they would be in a public or a 
     <lb/>separate school from which they are 
     <lb/>anxious to get away home just as fast as 
     <lb/>they can. So I say that religious instruc<lb break="no"/>tion should very largely be confined to the 
     <lb/>home, the Sunday school and the church. 
     <lb/>of course, as I said before. Opening the 
     <lb/>school with the Lord's prayer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>Now, Mr. Speaker, when the right hon. 
     <lb/>
     first Minister (Sir Wilfrid Laurier) intro<lb break="no"/>duced this very important measure on the 
     <lb/>
     21st February, he did so in a very able 
     <lb/>
     speech. It was a speech that attracted the 
     <lb/>
     attention of every person within hearing 
     <lb/>
     distance and more than that, judging from 
     <lb/>
     the vast number of petitions which have 
     <lb/>
     come in from all parts of the country against 
     <lb/>
     certain clauses in the Autonomy Bill, it was 
     <lb/>
     a speech that attracted the attention of all 
     <lb/>
     readers of newspapers in all parts of the 
     <lb/>
     country. When the right hon. First Min<lb break="no"/>ister spoke on the land question it struck 
     <lb/>
     me that perhaps it was not right that the 
     <lb/>
     federal government should withhold the 
     <lb/>
     land from the provinces and give them in 
     <lb/>
     lieu a certain sum of money. I felt that 
     <lb/>
     way, and after my hon. friend from Jacques 
     <lb/>
     Cartier (Mr. Monk) had delivered his speech, 
     <lb/>
     which was certainly a most able and argu<lb break="no"/>mentative speech on the land question, and 
     <lb/>
     after he had brought forward some excellent 
     <lb/>
     precedents to show that when provinces are 
     <lb/>
     created out of these Territories the land 
     <lb/>
     should pass within the control of those 
     <lb/>
     provinces, I felt more firmly convinced that 
     <lb/>
     the land ought to go to the provinces and 
     <lb/>
     be placed under their particular control. 
     <lb/>
     When the right hon. First Minister spoke 
     <lb/>
     on the educational clauses of the Bill, I 
     <lb/>
     noticed that he based his argument very 
     <lb/>
     largely upon the utterances of the late Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Geo. Brown. He said that Hon. Geo. Brown 
     <lb/>
     had said that once separate schools were 
     <lb/>
     introduced into the Territories then sepa<lb break="no"/>rate schools for the future ; once separate 
     <lb/>
     schools were introduced then separate 
     <lb/>
     schools for all time. Well, no doubt, the 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Geo. Brown said that, but Hon. Geo. 
     <lb/>
     Brown on the other hand fought very 
     <lb/>
     strongly for many years against the estab<lb break="no"/>lishment of separate schools. He did his 
     <lb/>
     very best against separate schools, but when 
     <lb/>
     it came down to the time of confederation 
     <lb/>
     he ceased his agitation against them. Why 
     <lb/>
     did he do that ? It was in order that he 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5104</fw>
            
     might do his part to bring about the 
     <lb/>
    great scheme of confederation. He felt 
     <lb/>that it was his duty to cease his 
     <lb/>agitation against separate schools for 
     <lb/>the sake of confederation, but at the 
     <lb/>same time his parting shot when he 
     <lb/>ceased his agitation was that he was still 
     <lb/>opposed to separate schools and that he 
     <lb/>would always be opposed to separate 
     <lb/>schools. Mr. Brown more than once said, 
     <lb/>in presenting his arguments, that separate 
     <lb/>schools had a tendency to separate the 
     <lb/>people, that they created a dual system of 
     <lb/>schools which was very expensive indeed 
     <lb/>to the people especially in rural school sec<lb break="no"/>tions and taking it all round—no doubt his 
     <lb/>arguments are quite familiar to the house-<lb/>
he was entirely opposed to the separate 
     <lb/>school system. I think when the right 
     <lb/>hon. reader of the government placed so 
     <lb/>much confidence in the assertion of Hon. 
     <lb/>Geo. Brown when he said once separate 
     <lb/>schools always separate schools. certainly 
     <lb/>he ought to have kept in mind the assertion 
     <lb/>of Mr. Brown when he said he was opposed 
     <lb/>to separate schools on the ground that they 
     <lb/>would be an injury to the country and that 
     <lb/>they were not equal to the public school 
     <lb/>system. Therefore, if the right hon. leader 
     <lb/>of the government believed Hon. Geo. 
     <lb/>Brown in both of these utterances. the only 
     <lb/>thing he could do was to leave the matter 
     <lb/>to the new provinces to deal with. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>The late Hon. Geo. Brown also said that 
     <lb/>
     if the Roman Catholics were allowed sepa<lb break="no"/>rate schools all other Protestant bodies 
     <lb/>
     would have the right to separate schools, 
     <lb/>
     the Methodists, Presbyterians, Anglicans, 
     <lb/>
     Baptists and all other sects, and he argued 
     <lb/>
     very strongly upon the fact that all others 
     <lb/>
     would have the right to separate schools 
     <lb/>
     and of course tangle up the country in a 
     <lb/>
     way that would be very bad for it. That 
     <lb/>
     would include a great many other sects, for 
     <lb/>
     instance the Galicians, Doukhohors, Men<lb break="no"/>nonites, Mormons and many others. Now, 
     <lb/>
     we will just deal with the Mormons for a 
     <lb/>
     moment. I will endeavour to show that 
     <lb/>
     there is likely to be a very great influx of 
     <lb/>
     the Mormon people into the Northwest Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories and I will then endeavour to show 
     <lb/>
     that the separate school clauses in the 
     <lb/>
     Autonomy Bill would be an advantage to 
     <lb/>
     the Mormon people which is something that 
     <lb/>
     I think ought not to be given. We take 
     <lb/>
     from a very reliable paper that is published 
     <lb/>
     in Ontario the following : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>The report which comes from Toronto that 
     <lb/>
     the Cochrane ranch in Alberta has been sold to 
     <lb/>
     President Smith of the Mormon church in Utah 
     <lb/>
     will not be received with surprise by Canadians 
     <lb/>
     generally, but it is apt to create a feeling of 
     <lb/>
     concern as to whether the embarrassing ques<lb break="no"/>tion with which the American people are wrest<lb break="no"/>ling is to be transferred to the Dominion. The 
     <lb/>
     Cochrane ranch comprises 66,500 acres in one 
     <lb/>
     great block, and would admit the settlement 
     <lb/>
     upon it of four hundred and fifteen families, 
     <lb/>
     giving to each family a homestead of a hundred 
     <lb/>
     and sixty acres. This would mean a population 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="5105" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5105.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">5105</fw>  <fw type="dateline">APRIL 28, 1905</fw> 
          
     of from two thousand to two thousand five hun<lb break="no"/>dred souls or more, settled upon some of the 
     <lb/>
     best land in western Canada and so powerfully 
     <lb/>
     entrenched by reason of their numbers and pos<lb break="no"/>sessions that they could to all intents and pur<lb break="no"/>poses practice what customs they chose and 
     <lb/>
     could propagate with impunity their opinions 
     <lb/>
     among their neighbours. That is what a large 
     <lb/>
     and compact colony of any people, distinctive 
     <lb/>
     in their customs and habits, means in the Can<lb break="no"/>adian Northwest, and that is what such a 
     <lb/>
     settlement of the Mormons means. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>That the Mormon people are thrifty, indus<lb break="no"/>trious, and, from their own point of view, 
     <lb/>
     moral, it would be impossible to deny. They 
     <lb/>
     are intelligent, and, with the exception that 
     <lb/>
     they venture on active proselytizing, they at<lb break="no"/>tend to their own affairs, and do not interfere 
     <lb/>
     with their neighbours. That they would quickly 
     <lb/>
     make any district in which they settled, in the 
     <lb/>
     west, one of the most prosperous in the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion, may be taken for granted. The question, 
     <lb/>
     however, remains whether the people of this 
     <lb/>
     country are prepared to accept the Mormons 
     <lb/>
     on their own guarantee that they will abstain 
     <lb/>
     from the practice of polygamy and other cus<lb break="no"/>toms which have attracted hostility in the 
     <lb/>
     United States and which are regarded with 
     <lb/>
     equal abhorrence in this country. It is a 
     <lb/>
     question which demands consideration whether 
     <lb/>
     the frugality, the industry and the general in<lb break="no"/>telligence of the Mormons, should they come to 
     <lb/>
     this country, would in the opinion of Canadians, 
     <lb/>
     counterbalance any unlawful customs to which 
     <lb/>
     they are addicted or any opinions which are 
     <lb/>
     not in accord with the views of the people 
     <lb/>
     at large. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>


            <p>Now, we take up the Toronto 'Globe' of 
     <lb/>
     April 3, which also alludes to something of 
     <lb/>
     the same kind: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     Mormons in Alberta. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Joseph Smith purchases tract of land there. 
     <lb/>
     Will divide it into small farms and colonize it 
     <lb/>
    with chosen people from Utah—Latter Day 
     <lb/>Saints' movement to Illinois. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     (Associated Press Despatch.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Butte, Montana, April 2.—Joseph Smith, head 
     <lb/>
     of the Mormon church, has bought 67,000 acres 
     <lb/>
     of land in Alberta and proposes to establish a 
     <lb/>
    colony of Mormons. The price paid was about 
     <lb/>$400,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>The plan is to divide the tract into small 
     <lb/>
     farms to be settled upon by Mormon colonists 
     <lb/>
     from Utah and elsewhere. Although the deal 
     <lb/>
     has been closed, the Mormons are not expected 
     <lb/>
     to take possession until late this fall or early 
     <lb/>
     next year. They will raise crops this season 
     <lb/>
     at their old homes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>I quote the following from a reliable 
     <lb/>
     paper of long standing published in New 
     <lb/>
     York : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     The Mormon Revival. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>The question of secular or parochial schools 
     <lb/>
     is not the only religious difficulty confronting 
     <lb/>
     the new provinces of the Canadian Northwest. 
     <lb/>
     That region, like the United States and Mexico, 
     <lb/>
     has its Mormon problem. Within the past five 
     <lb/>
     years thousands of Mormons have migrated to 
     <lb/>
     Alberta from the United States and Europe, and 
     <lb/>
     one-third of them are said to be polygamists. 
     <lb/>
     Prosecutions have been begun against a number 
     <lb/>
     of these people at Raymond, with the avowed 
     <lb/>
     intention of making them give up polygamy or 
     <lb/>
     leave the country. The Mormon element is so 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5106</fw>
          
     numerous that it is expected to control two 
     <lb/>
     seats in the Alberta legislature, and the ex<lb break="no"/>perience of Idaho shows what may be expected 
     <lb/>
     when the saints once get into politics. In Utah 
     <lb/>
     the church is displaying an arrogance that re<lb break="no"/>calls the days of Brigham Young. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>There is evidence that there is likely to 
     <lb/>
     be a very large influx of Mormons into our 
     <lb/>
     Canadian Northwest, and it is my purpose 
     <lb/>
     to show that the separate school clauses of 
     <lb/>
     the present Autonomy Bill would give them 
     <lb/>
     a privilege which I feel they ought not 
     <lb/>
     to have. We have no objection to the Mor<lb break="no"/>mon people personally, but we do object 
     <lb/>
     to some features of their religious belief, 
     <lb/>
     and we ought to guard against the privilege 
     <lb/>
     they would have under this Bill of incul<lb break="no"/>cating that religious belief in the minds of 
     <lb/>
     children in our schools. We will suppose 
     <lb/>
     that there is a rural school section in the 
     <lb/>
     west, in which the majority is composed 
     <lb/>
     of Roman Catholics who ask for and ob<lb break="no"/>tain a separate school. Then there is a 
     <lb/>
     Protestant minority, the greater number of 
     <lb/>
     whom are of the Mormon persuasion, and 
     <lb/>
     who for school purposes would come under 
     <lb/>
     the head of Protestants. Suppose there 
     <lb/>
     are ten families of Mormons in that school 
     <lb/>
     section, one family of Anglicans, one family 
     <lb/>
     of Presbyterians, one family of Methodists 
     <lb/>
     and one family of Baptists ; the Mormons 
     <lb/>
     will be in the majority and they will elect 
     <lb/>
     as a board three trustees of their own re<lb break="no"/>ligious belief who in turn will engage a 
     <lb/>
     Mormon teacher. The school opens in the 
     <lb/>
     morning at nine o'clock, let us hope with 
     <lb/>
     the reading of the Lord's Prayer, and the 
     <lb/>
     teaching goes on to half-past three when 
     <lb/>
     the religious instruction privilege comes in. 
     <lb/>
     Now Mr. Speaker, I would ask you what 
     <lb/>
     kind of religious instruction is likely to 
     <lb/>
     be given in that school which is controlled 
     <lb/>
     by a Mormon board. We find by the or<lb break="no"/>dinances of the Northwest Territories that: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     The board means the board of trustees of any 
     <lb/>
     district. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>And in section 137 we find: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     No religious instruction except as hereinafter 
     <lb/>
     provided shall be permitted in the school of any 
     <lb/>
     district from the opening of such school until 
     <lb/>
     half an hour previous to its closing in the 
     <lb/>
     afternoon ; after which time any such instruc<lb break="no"/>tion permitted or desired by the board may be 
     <lb/>
     given. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>I ask hon. gentlemen to mark these 
     <lb/>
     words. I contend that the board would 
     <lb/>
     have the power to decide what kind of re<lb break="no"/>ligious instruction should be given, and in 
     <lb/>
     the case I mention that board would be 
     <lb/>
     composed of Mormons. I believe they 
     <lb/>
     would not be open and above board in the 
     <lb/>
     matter as the Roman Catholics or Protes<lb break="no"/>tants would be, but you know how the 
     <lb/>
     Mormons make their proselytes or con<lb break="no"/>verts and that they do so in a quiet, 
     <lb/>
     subtle, under cover kind of way- There 
     <lb/>
    is not the slightest doubt that the 
     <lb/>teacher in such a school, backed up 
     <lb/>
         
            <pb n="5107" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5107.jpg"/>
          
     by the trustees and by the Mormon 
     <lb/>
     majority would have a very great per<lb break="no"/>sonal influence in inculcating in the 
     <lb/>
     minds of the children the religious tenets 
     <lb/>
     of the Mormon people. It may be said: 
     <lb/>
     What of it ? They could not practice poly<lb break="no"/>gamy under our Dominion laws. True 
     <lb/>
     enough, and we are glad they cannot, but 
     <lb/>
     they might influence a Protestant boy or 
     <lb/>
     two, a Methodist boy or two, a Presbyterian 
     <lb/>
     boy or two, an Anglican boy or two, a 
     <lb/>
     Baptist boy or two, to begin to believe in 
     <lb/>
     the precepts of the Mormon doctrine, and 
     <lb/>
     although they could not practise polygamy 
     <lb/>
     in the Dominion of Canada they could go 
     <lb/>
    to Utah, or Salt Lake City, and there 
     <lb/>become followers of the late Brigham 
     <lb/>Young and Joe Smith. I am sure 
     <lb/>that the members of this House would not 
     <lb/>be inclined to allow anything of that kind, 
     <lb/>and that being so we should have the 
     <lb/>school clauses so carefully framed that 
     <lb/>the Mormons would not be able to avail 
     <lb/>of them for their own ends. It would be 
     <lb/>no credit to us as Canadians if we should 
     <lb/>raise up young men here to go off as re<lb break="no"/>cruits to that Mormon population in the 
     <lb/>United States which has caused so much 
     <lb/>trouble, and which has actually become so 
     <lb/>strong as to send a representative to the 
     <lb/>House of Congress. I am glad to say that 
     <lb/>the members of congress, as would no 
     <lb/>doubt the members of this House under 
     <lb/>similar circumstances, did not feel comfor<lb break="no"/>table in having such a member sitting with 
     <lb/>them, and excluded him from that body. 
     <lb/>But, it behooves us to be careful in Canada 
     <lb/>because already we find that one of these 
     <lb/>newspapers has said that the Mormons are 
     <lb/>likely to control two seats in the legisla<lb break="no"/>tive assembly of Alberta, and it may not 
     <lb/>be many years before they might send a 
     <lb/>representative to the Canadian House of 
     <lb/>Commons. I feel that there should be no 
     <lb/>privilege given to the Mormons under the 
     <lb/>school laws which would tend to strengthen 
     <lb/>them in these practises which are so re<lb break="no"/>pulsive to the vast majority of the people 
     <lb/>of this country. I feel that any Canadian 
     <lb/>government, whether Conservative or Re<lb break="no"/>form, would blush to think that they 
     <lb/>would even turn the key that would open 
     <lb/>the door that would permit the Mormons 
     <lb/>to teach their doctiine in separate schools. 
     <lb/>I believe that every hon. gentleman on the 
     <lb/>government side of the House and on the 
     <lb/>opposition side of the House too; I believe 
     <lb/>that the First Minister and the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen who sit with him on the treasury 
     <lb/>benches will agree with me when I say: 
     <lb/>It is a glorious thing for any man to have 
     <lb/>one good helpmate through life, and that 
     <lb/>one good helpmate is quite sufficient to take 
     <lb/>the best possible care of any one respec<lb break="no"/>table man in the Dominion of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Some hon. MEMBERS. Hear, hear. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KENN1">Mr. KENNEDY</persName>. The hon. gentleman <lb/>(Mr. Elston) has read one
                  clause from the <lb/>
                  <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5106</fw> school ordinance, but I would ask him to <lb/> read the succeeding clause
                  which qualifies <lb/> it. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:ELSO1">Mr. ELSON</persName>. A great deal has been said <lb/> in this debate
                  with regard to standing on <lb/> the rock of the constitution, I believe in <lb/>
                  that. I believe it is right to stand on the <lb/> rock of the constitution in this
                  Autonomy <lb/> Bill, but there seems to be some uncer<lb break="no"/>tainty as to
                  the power that the federal gov<lb break="no"/>ernment has under the constitution.
                  Some <lb/> members have suggested that it would be <lb/> well to submit this
                  measure to the Privy <lb/> Council in England so that we might learn <lb/> just
                  what powers we have in granting this <lb/> Autonomy, and I believe myself that
                  would <lb/> be a wise course for us to take. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>I think it was the hon. Postmaster Gene<lb break="no"/>ral (Sir William Mulock) who said that we 
     <lb/>
     should look at the spirit of the constitution 
     <lb/>
     rather than the letter of the constitution. I 
     <lb/>
     have noticed, in my limited experience, that 
     <lb/>
     when men get into difficulty and become en<lb break="no"/>tangled in the law, they find before they get 
     <lb/>
     out of it that the law is carried out to the 
     <lb/>
     very letter rather than in the spirit, especial<lb break="no"/>ly when their treasury is considerably de<lb break="no"/>pleted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Now, Mr. Speaker, so far as I am con<lb break="no"/>cerned, I stand as firm as a rock against 
     <lb/>
     separate schools. I hold that the public 
     <lb/>
     school, the national school, is the right 
     <lb/>
     school for this country. Of course, as the 
     <lb/>
     separate school is established in the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces of Ontario and Quebec, we must be 
     <lb/>
     satisfied with it ; I am not complaining of 
     <lb/>
     that. But I feel that it is the duty of both 
     <lb/>
     Protestants and Roman Catholics to be 
     <lb/>
     united as much as possible in friendly inter<lb break="no"/>course, each enjoying his own religious be<lb break="no"/>liefs, and moving on together with the one 
     <lb/>
     great object of building up a great nation 
     <lb/>
     in the Dominion of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>In conclusion, I am in favour of giving the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest autonomy. If the right hon. the 
     <lb/>
     First Minister will not delay this measure 
     <lb/>
     until we can obtain the information, which 
     <lb/>
     I am sure many members on the govern<lb break="no"/>ment side of the House, as well as many on 
     <lb/>
     the opposition side, would like to have from 
     <lb/>
     the highest authority, then we shall have to 
     <lb/>
     vote on the Bill when the proper time comes. 
     <lb/>
     In giving autonomy to the people of the 
     <lb/>
     Territories, I believe in giving them full 
     <lb/>
     autonomy. Let them have self-government, 
     <lb/>
     not only in the matter of their municipal 
     <lb/>
     affairs, but in the management of their pub<lb break="no"/>lic lands and in the control and management 
     <lb/>
     of their educational system. It is my inten<lb break="no"/>tion to support the amendment put forward 
     <lb/>
     by the hon. leader of the opposition. I feel 
     <lb/>
     strong on the question of provincial rights. 
     <lb/>
     I believe in equal rights to all and special 
     <lb/>
     favours to none. I want to thank you, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Speaker, for so kindly using your influence 
     <lb/>
     in keeping such splendid order in the House, 
     <lb/>
     and, through you, I want to thank the hon. 
     <lb/>
     members of the House for the kind attention 
     <lb/>
     they have given to my remarks. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="5109" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5109.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">5109</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 28, 1905</fw> 
           
 <p><persName ref="pers:BLAC4">Mr. J. B. BLACK</persName> (Hants). Mr. Speaker, <lb/> I had intended to
                  give a silent vote on this <lb/> question ; but I have found that outside of <lb/>
                  this parliament there are existent and ram<lb break="no"/>pant such erroneous and
                  false ideas regard<lb break="no"/>ing the school clause and the class of schools
                  <lb/> now in the Territories, that I find it binding <lb/> on me to state the
                  facts as I find them, both <lb/> in regard to the class of schools now in the
                  <lb/> Territories, which the school clause of the <lb/> Autonomy Bill proposes to
                  endorse and con<lb break="no"/>tinue, and in regard to the attitude of the <lb/>
                  people in the Territories touching this legis <lb/> iation; and I further deem it
                  my duty to <lb/> publicly declare why I heartily support the <lb/> amended clause
                  relating to schools in the <lb/> Autonomy Bill. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>In 1896 I took an active part, in my own 
     <lb/>
     county, in opposing any interference with 
     <lb/>
     the public schools of Manitoba as establish<lb break="no"/>ed by the Greenway government of that pro<lb break="no"/>vince. The same principles of fair play to 
     <lb/>
     wards the people—equal rights for all and 
     <lb/>
     special legislation for no class or church—as 
     <lb/>
     actuated me then actuate me now in giving 
     <lb/>
     this Bill my unqualified support. When this 
     <lb/>
     legislation came before the House I confess 
     <lb/>
    I was as ignorant of the conditions of the so- 
     <lb break="yes"/>called separate schools in the Territories as 
     <lb/>are some whom I have found outside of 
     <lb/>parliament publicly teaching the people on 
     <lb/>this question. With regard to the schools in 
     <lb/>the Territories with which this Bill deals, I 
     <lb/>find that they are housed in 1,100 school<lb break="no"/>houses. Of these less than a dozen—to be 
     <lb/>exact, eleven—are occupied by the separate 
     <lb/>schools. Of these, again, two are so-called 
     <lb/>Protestant and nine are so-called Roman 
     <lb/>Catholic. I find that these 1,100 are using 
     <lb/>exactly the same textbooks ; are taught, 
     <lb/>every one, by normal school graduates from 
     <lb/>the government normal school ; are all ex<lb break="no"/>amined by the same government inspectors ; 
     <lb/>in fact, in every way are public government 
     <lb/>schools, wholly under the government care, 
     <lb/>inspection and regulation. and none are un<lb break="no"/>der the control of any church or denomina<lb break="no"/>tion. One difiierence only exists, and it is 
     <lb/>this: I find that in the two so-called Pro<lb break="no"/>testant separate schools, if a majority of 
     <lb/>parents desire it, a clergyman—Baptist, 
     <lb/>Methodist, Presbyterian, Anglican, or what<lb break="no"/>ever other denomination—may come after 
     <lb/>school hours are done, after 3.30 o'clock, and 
     <lb/>may for thirty minutes give religious instruc<lb break="no"/>tion. I find that in the nine so-called Catho<lb break="no"/>lic separate schools, if a majority of parents 
     <lb/>desire it, a clergyman of that faith may have 
     <lb/>the same privilege, at the same hour, and 
     <lb/>for the same length of time ; and I further 
     <lb/>find that no child is obliged to remain whose 
     <lb/>parents object. This provision is in exact 
     <lb/>accord with our public school system in 
     <lb/>Nova Scotia, which we have been accustom<lb break="no"/>ed for many years, and justly so, to boast 
     <lb/>of as the best school system in America. 
     <lb/>With regard to religious instruction, the 
     <lb/>school law of Nova Scotia provides : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     It is ordered, That in case where the parents 
     <lb/>
     or guardians of children in actual attendance 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5110</fw>
          
     on any public school or department signify in 
     <lb/>
     writing to the trustees their conscientious ob<lb break="no"/>jection to any portion of such devotional exer<lb break="no"/>cises as may be conducted therein under the 
     <lb/>
     sanction of the trustees, such devotional exer<lb break="no"/>cises shall either be so modified as not to offend 
     <lb/>
     the religious feelings of those so objecting, or 
     <lb/>
     shall be held immediately before the time fixed 
     <lb/>
     for rthe opening, or after the time fixed for the 
     <lb/>
     close of the daily work of the school ; and no 
     <lb/>
     children. whose parents or guardians signify 
     <lb/>
     conscientious objections thereto, shall be re<lb break="no"/>quired to be present during such devotional 
     <lb/>
     exercises. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>I find by comparison that the schools of 
     <lb/>
     the Territories and the schools of Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia are practically the same. If these 
     <lb/>
     schools in the Territories are not free 
     <lb/>
     public schools, if there is not here 
     <lb/>
     civil and religious liberty, if there are 
     <lb/>
     not here equal rights for all, then I have 
     <lb/>
     failed in my conception of these terms. 
     <lb/>
     These are the kind and quality of public 
     <lb/>
     schools which with slight variation have 
     <lb/>
     been in these Territories for about thirty 
     <lb/>
     years. These are the kind and quality of 
     <lb/>
     schools which the amended clause of the 
     <lb/>
     Autonomy Bill seeks to perpetuate—seeks 
     <lb/>
     this and this only—seeks this and nothing 
     <lb/>
     more and nothing less. These are the kind 
     <lb/>
     and quality of schools which the Catholic 
     <lb/>
     clergy are uttering their complaint against, 
     <lb/>
     because they are not sectarian. These are 
     <lb/>
     the schools against which many Protestant 
     <lb/>
     preachers are hurling their anathemas, be<lb break="no"/>cause they claim that these schools are 
     <lb/>
     altogether Catholic and French. Some of 
     <lb/>
     these tirades against the school clauses of 
     <lb/>
     the Autonomy Bill are, I believe, said in 
     <lb/>
     honesty, but in profound ignorance of the 
     <lb/>
     public school system of the Territories, 
     <lb/>
     which this Bill seeks to establish and per<lb break="no"/>petuate. These are the schools of which Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Haultain, the Conservative premier of the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest Territories said a few weeks ago: 
     <lb/>
     ' If I were a dictator I would not change the 
     <lb/>
     school system of the Territories.' These are 
     <lb/>
     the schools of which Mr. Greenway said<lb break="no"/>and mark it well—'If Manitoba had had 
     <lb/>
     such a system as is in existence in the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories there never would have 
     <lb/>
     been any Manitoba school question.' 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Who that remembers the long and bitter 
     <lb/>
     fight led by Mr. Greenway for the free 
     <lb/>
     public schools in Manitoba, will not give 
     <lb/>
     weight to these words of his, and earnest 
     <lb/>
     heed and thought to his wise advice on 
     <lb/>
     the question of the Northwest Territories' 
     <lb/>
     public schools. Would you hear Arch<lb break="no"/>bishop Langevin's sad refrain over the non- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Catholic control of these schools? In a 
     <lb/>
     circular to his clergy, he said : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Just as we are committing to press this cir<lb break="no"/>cular, we learn with unspeakable sorrow that 
     <lb/>
     the educational clause destined to be inserted 
     <lb/>
     in the Autonomy Bill of the two new provinces 
     <lb/>
     of Alberta and Saskatchewan will not restore 
     <lb/>
     us to the position we held in 1875, when the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest Territories were organized in virtue 
     <lb/>
     of the British North America Act, but that this 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="5111" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5111.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">5111</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> 

     clause will conserve the spoilation of our school 
     <lb/>
     rights by the ordinance of 1892 and will sanc<lb break="no"/>tion all ordinances passed up to 1901. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>This is for us a cruel disappointment and a 
     <lb/>
     source of great sadness and grave anxiety for 
     <lb/>
     the future. The spoilation of 1892 will thus be 
     <lb/>
     definitely confirmed and conserved, and we lose 
     <lb/>
     all hope of recovering our rights, we who ex<lb break="no"/>pected this act of justice and high wisdom, as 
     <lb/>
     well as of true patriotism, from our rulers at 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>In 1873 we had the same school rights as the 
     <lb/>
     Protestant minority of Quebec and the Catholic 
     <lb/>
     minority of Ontario, and these rights, shame<lb break="no"/>fully violated in spite of the constitution, as 
     <lb/>
     the lamented Archbishop Taché so well proved 
     <lb/>
     in his memorial of 1894, will not be recognized 
     <lb/>
     and restored to us, as we had reason to expect, 
     <lb/>
     by parliament which had power to do so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Catholics who express satisfaction at such a 
     <lb/>
     state of things betray not only unpardonable 
     <lb/>
     ignorance of Catholic educational principles, 
     <lb/>
     but also a lack of understanding of the painful 
     <lb/>
     position in which we are placed since 1892, 
     <lb/>
     ostracized, as we truly are in the Territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Wherefore, reverend and dear brethren, we 
     <lb/>
     deem it our duty to lift up our voice in protest 
     <lb/>
     against this ignoring of school rights, which the 
     <lb/>
     constitution of our country gives us. Our rights 
     <lb/>
     are as sacred and as certain to-day as they 
     <lb/>
     were in 1875. And, if some opportunists were 
     <lb/>
     tempted to ask us to be silent for the sake of 
     <lb/>
     peace, or because it is impossible now to re<lb break="no"/>cover our right, we would answer : ' There can 
     <lb/>
     be no peace except with justice.' There can be 
     <lb/>
     no prescription against right. No question of 
     <lb/>
     principle is truly settled except when it is 
     <lb/>
     settled according to justice and equity. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Our cause is that of justice and peace, be<lb break="no"/>cause it is the cause of conscience and truth ; 
     <lb/>
     <choice> <sic>asd</sic> <corr>as</corr> </choice> truth, like God, never dies. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>I have yet to hear of a single Protestant 
     <lb/>
     clergyman in the Territories preaching or 
     <lb/>
     speaking against the school question there. 
     <lb/>
     Of the satisfaction shown by western Or<lb break="no"/>angemen, we have had convincing evidence 
     <lb/>
     on the floor of this House. The hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for Portage la Prairie (Mr. Crawford) an 
     <lb/>
     ardent orangeman a few days ago expressed 
     <lb/>
     himself, not only as favourable to the Bill, 
     <lb/>
     but as intending to vote for it on the ground 
     <lb/>
     that it was just and righteous to all classes 
     <lb/>
     of people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Besides the eminently satisfactory status 
     <lb/>
     of the Territorial school system which the 
     <lb/>
     school clause endorses and perpetuates, I 
     <lb/>
     support it because it will prevent further 
     <lb/>
     future fighting in the local legislature over 
     <lb/>
     the vexed question of Catholic separate 
     <lb/>
     schools in the Territories, and forbids the 
     <lb/>
     necessity of a repetition of that bitter war<lb break="no"/>fare which took place in Manitoba for free 
     <lb/>
     public schools. I support this Bill because 
     <lb/>
     the people of the Territories have unmistak<lb break="no"/>ably declared that they are wholly satisfied 
     <lb/>
     with their school system and desire no med<lb break="no"/>dling interference from Tory Toronto or 
     <lb/>
     ultramontane Quebec. I support it be<lb break="no"/>cause the almost unanimous voice of the 
     <lb/>
     representatives in parliament of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories are in its favour. I say 
     <lb/>
     almost, because there are some members of 
     <lb/>
     the opposition who would vote against a 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5112</fw>
         
     passport to Paradise if it were offered by 
     <lb/>
     this government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>As regards the constitutional and legal 
     <lb/>
     aspect of this school clause, I have heard 
     <lb/>
     learned and eminent legal gentlemen in this 
     <lb/>
     House declare that the federal government 
     <lb/>
     had no right to interfere in this question ; 
     <lb/>
     that it was an invasion of 'provincial 
     <lb/>
     rights,' and I have heard them quote emi<lb break="no"/>nent authorities on both sides of the Atlan<lb break="no"/>tic to support their contention. I have also 
     <lb/>
     heard learned and eminent lawyers in this 
     <lb/>
     House declare that the federal authority 
     <lb/>
     had the right to deal with this question 
     <lb/>
     and quote eminent jurists in Great Britain 
     <lb/>
     to support their case. Now while these 
     <lb/>
     legal lights are engaged in the gentle art 
     <lb/>
     and exercise of splitting hairs, I deem it 
     <lb/>
     my privilege, nay, my bounden duty, as 
     <lb/>
     the representative of a liberty loving con<lb break="no"/>stituency, to support a Bill which gives 
     <lb/>
     the new provinces a system of schools 
     <lb/>
     which they desire, and which they have 
     <lb/>
     had for thirty years, and approve of the 
     <lb/>
     system which gives free public schools, cal<lb break="no"/>culated for the enlightenment, and making 
     <lb/>
     for the intelligence of the young people who 
     <lb/>
     are teeming into this great west, as well 
     <lb/>
     as for those unborn, in these new pro<lb break="no"/>vinces—a system which by this Bill can 
     <lb/>
     never be controlled by any one church or 
     <lb/>
     sect or denomination, and will remain un<lb break="no"/>trammelled by religious dogma and uncon<lb break="no"/>trolled by religious bigotry or fanatical 
     <lb/>
     zeal. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>I readily find in the examination of this 
     <lb/>
     measure, as it is presented by the leader 
     <lb/>
     of the government, and also by the leader 
     <lb/>
     of the opposition, that he who votes on it at 
     <lb/>
     all must vote for separate schools, as they 
     <lb/>
     are and must continue to be in the new pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. If he vote with the government, 
     <lb/>
     he must endorse separate schools; and the 
     <lb/>
     leader of the opposition in the amendment 
     <lb/>
     he has offered, certainly does not propose 
     <lb/>
     to remove or interfere in any way with the 
     <lb/>
     territorial school system. The voting pro<lb break="no"/>blem as I see it is this: Vote with the 
     <lb/>
     government and in favour of the present 
     <lb/>
     school system in the Territories—or vote 
     <lb/>
     with the opposition, who do not propose to 
     <lb/>
     remove or interfere with these schools, but 
     <lb/>
     an opposition which when in power put 
     <lb/>
     themselves on record as in favour of sep<lb break="no"/>arate schools, controlled by the Catholic 
     <lb/>
     church in Manitoba; and went to wreck 
     <lb/>
     and ruin on this question, and who never 
     <lb/>
     have shown even a death bed repentance. 
     <lb/>
     Or if the member do not vote at all, he 
     <lb/>
     shows himself an arrant coward pandering 
     <lb/>
     to the ignorance or bigotry of a few fana<lb break="no"/>tics. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>I understand that the member for East 
     <lb/>
     Grey (Mr. Sproule) has sent to the Orange<lb break="no"/>men of Nova Scotia a telegram giving his 
     <lb/>
     advice and opinion in regard to this Bill. 
     <lb/>
     In that organization in Nova Scotia there 
     <lb/>
     are many grand men, and noble supporters 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="5113" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5113.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">5113</fw> <fw type="dateline">APRIL 28, 1905</fw> 
           
     of this government; and had they known 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member's party subservience, 
     <lb/>
     his hide bound, slavish adherence to 
     <lb/>
     everything Tory whether right or wrong, 
     <lb/>
     they would long have hesitated to ask or 
     <lb/>
     receive his advice. I have no objection to 
     <lb/>
     this gentleman washing his political gar<lb break="no"/>ments in Boyne Water, but I do object to 
     <lb/>
     his afterwards taking them out of the cess<lb break="no"/>pool of party prejudice and Conservative 
     <lb/>
     misrepresentation and sending them down 
     <lb/>
     to Nova Scotia as the pure robes of a 
     <lb/>
     patriot. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>As well might our Orange supporters 
     <lb/>
     there have asked of beelzebub—his opinion 
     <lb/>
     of the supreme delights and divine glories 
     <lb/>
     of the heavenly world. For the hour he 
     <lb/>
     may deceive a few of these Liberals, but 
     <lb/>
     only for the hour. Every intelligent Orange<lb break="no"/>man, every intelligent Catholic, every intel<lb break="no"/>ligent citizen, who is not a narrow party 
     <lb/>
     slave, if he seek the facts in regard to the 
     <lb/>
     school system in the Northwest Territories, 
     <lb/>
     will see in that system, righteous justice 
     <lb/>
     which panders to none and shows a broad- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     mindness which well becomes this broad 
     <lb/>
     and great country which by justice and 
     <lb/>
     right, we are trying to build into a great 
     <lb/>
     nation, broad, tolerant, self-respecting and 
     <lb/>
     self-governing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>At six o'clock, House took recess. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     After Recess. 
     <lb/></head>

<p>House resumed at eight o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PRIVATE BILLS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">CONSIDERED IN COMMITTEE THIRD 
<lb/>
     READING.</head>
   
            <p>Bill (No. 97) respecting the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     Central Railway Company—Mr. Harty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     DOMINION ATLANTIC RAILWAY COMPANY. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>House in committee on Bill (No. 106), 
     <lb/>
     respecting the Dominion Atlantic Railway 
     <lb/>
     Company—Mr. Black. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>On section 2, <lb/>
                  <persName ref="pers:LAUR1">Mr. LAURENCE</persName> moved: <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     That section 2 be amended by adding thereto 
     <lb/>
     the following words : And the said Midland 
     <lb/>
     division is hereby declared to be a work for the 
     <lb/>
     general advantage of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Bill reported, read the third time, and 
     <lb/>
     passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PROVINCIAL AUTONOMY IN THE 
     <lb/>
     NORTHWEST. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>House resumed consideration of the pro<lb break="no"/>posed motion of Sir Wilfrid Laurier for 
     <lb/>
     the second reading of Bill (No. 69) to es<lb break="no"/>tablish and provide for the government of 
     <lb/>
     the province of Alberta, and the amend<lb break="no"/>ment of Mr. R. L. Borden thereto. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5114</fw>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ADAM2">Mr. A. J. ADAMSON</persName> (Humbolt). Mr. <lb/> Speaker, the Bill
                  which is now before the <lb/> House is one of great importance to Can<lb break="no"/>ada and particularly to the Northwest Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories
                  which are about to be created into <lb/> provinces. As I have the honour to re<lb break="no"/>present a constituency which forms a part <lb/> of these great
                  Territories I consider it my <lb/> duty to give some reasons why I intend to <lb/>
                  support the Bill which is before the House <lb/> as I certamly will do. I have
                  listened <lb/> with a great deal of attention to the views <lb/> expressed by hon.
                  members on both sides <lb/> of the House and I have endeavoured to <lb/> realize
                  their point of view. I was particu<lb break="no"/>larly struck with the simile
                  used by the <lb/> hon. member for East Grey (Mr. Sproule) <lb/> when he
                  congratulated my right hon. friend <lb/> the Prime Minister (Sir Wilfrid Laurier)
                  on <lb/> the introduction of this Bill. He likened <lb/> the provinces which are
                  being created to <lb/> a pair of twins which had just arrived on <lb/> the scene.
                  At the time I thought the com<lb break="no"/>parison was a very happy one, but
                  further <lb/> consideration struck me that it perhaps did <lb/> not quite fit the
                  occasion. I thought it <lb/> would have been fairer to have compared <lb/> the two
                  young provinces to a couple of <lb/> youths who have been under probation, <lb/>
                  who have completed their education and <lb/> are about to enter into their estate.
                  The <lb/> Dominion government have been the trus<lb break="no"/>tees who have been
                  looking after their <lb/> interests until they came of age and until <lb/> they
                  were fit to be entrusted with their <lb/> own attairs. I thought the simile was
                  <lb/> very well taken by the hon. member for <lb/> East Grey, but at the same time
                  I thought <lb/> possibly his professional pride was piqued <lb/> at not being
                  called in as consulting physi<lb break="no"/>cian on the auspicious occasion.
                  These <lb/> provinces, having attained man's estate, are <lb/> about to become
                  independent to a certain <lb/> extent ; that is as independent as any per<lb break="no"/>son can be in these days, or as any pro<lb break="no"/>vince can be
                  that is a member of this great <lb/> confederacy. No province can be perfectly
                  <lb/> independent any more than any individual <lb/> who is a member of a
                  community can be <lb/> perfectly independent. There must be <lb/> some restraints
                  to guard against en<lb break="no"/>trenching upon the rights, privileges and <lb/>
                  property of the different provinces, but <lb/> so long as they keep within their
                  rights <lb/> and privileges they are free. It is so <lb/> with these new
                  provinces. They are <lb/> now the centre of observations and the <lb/> methods
                  adopted by them at this present <lb/> juncture and their ability to cope with the
                  <lb/> problems with which they must deal will <lb/> have a most powerful effect in
                  the future <lb/> of these provinces. If at the commence<lb break="no"/>ment of
                  their career they deal recklessly, <lb/> weakly, or carelessly with the questions
                  <lb/> which will be presented to them their fut<lb break="no"/>ure career will be
                  most injuriously affected <lb/> and all that affects them will certainly <lb/>
                  affect the rest of Canada to an extent that <lb/>
                  <pb n="5115" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5115.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">5115</fw>
                  <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
                   very few people can at present realize. <lb/> Fortunately
                  the territorial government has <lb/> been so far most satisfactory and we must
                  <lb/> be careful now not to undo any of the <lb/> good work that has been done in
                  the past. <lb/> The first provision of this Bill which I <lb/> want to discuss
                  relates to the financial terms <lb/> arranged for the new provinces. They, of
                  <lb/> course, are the most important ones, at <lb/> least they are very important
                  to the well- <lb break="yes"/> being of the provinces, and looking at them <lb/>
                  as a whole I may say that the representa<lb break="no"/>tives of the Territories
                  are satisfied with <lb/> the provision which has been made. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve that the income which has been pro<lb break="no"/>vided for them will
                  enable them to conduct <lb/> their internal affairs in a satisfactory man<lb break="no"/>ner. They are not in the position of re<lb break="no"/>mittance
                  men. They have had a fair set<lb break="no"/>tlement and they can go on and
                  develop the <lb/> country in a perfectly independent manner. <lb/> Each province
                  will have over a million dol<lb break="no"/>lars to start with and as their
                  population <lb/> increases so will their income, and thus <lb/> they will have
                  increasing means with the <lb/> increasing demands which will be made <lb/> upon
                  them for the support and establish<lb break="no"/>ment of schools, roads and
                  different public <lb/> improvements of one kind or another. If <lb/> the lands
                  were handed over to the provinces <lb/> they have to be used immediately as a
                  <lb/> source of income. We would have to get <lb/> revenue out of them. The
                  present policy <lb/> of the Dominion government is to settle the <lb/> lands and
                  not to make them a revenue- <lb break="yes"/> producing property. Every settler
                  that <lb/> goes into the Northwest is a valuable asset <lb/> to the Dominion of
                  Canada. He contributes <lb/> to the general revenue so that it is a great <lb/>
                  benefit to the Dominion, and looking at it <lb/> from the purely financial point
                  of view it <lb/> is proper that the government should get <lb/> as many settlers
                  into the country as pos<lb break="no"/>sible, but as these settlers necessitate
                     ex<lb break="no"/>penditure on the part of the provinces it is <lb/> also
                  necessary that their income should in<lb break="no"/>crease wlth the advent of new
                  people. If <lb/> the lands had been handed over to the new <lb/> provinces it
                  would be a most difficult mat<lb break="no"/>ter to determine the interests of
                  each. A <lb/> large amount of land in the Territories has <lb/> already been
                  disposed of and it will be al<lb break="no"/>most impossible to say how much was
                  <lb/> taken from one or the other and to adjust <lb/> matters between them. Under
                  the proposi<lb break="no"/>tion as adopted all trouble of this kind is <lb/>
                  avoided and there is no material for dispute <lb/> between the provinces. Beth are
                  satisfied <lb/> with the liberality of the terms and feel <lb/> that they have
                  been fairly dealt with. <lb/> Many possible complications have been dis<lb break="no"/>posed of by this settlement and there is no <lb/> room for further
                  discussion in the matter. <lb/> In regard to the boundary question, I <lb/>
                  believe that the division of the Territories <lb/> has been a most ideal one.
                  There was at <lb/> one time some difference of opinion as to <lb/> where the line
                  should be. Many people con<lb break="no"/><cb/>
     <fw type="num">5116</fw>sidered that the north country,
                  bounded by <lb/> the North Saskatchewan river, should be <lb/> made into one
                  province and that the south <lb/> country should be made into another pro<lb break="no"/>vince. I myself at one time held that <lb/> opinion, but on further
                  considering the mat<lb break="no"/>ter and hearing the views of others express<lb break="no"/>ed, I can easily see that this is an equally <lb/> good division,
                  and we are all satisfied with <lb/> it. Only one objection, and one only, has
                  <lb/> been raised against the dividing line de<lb break="no"/>cided on, and on
                  examination that objection <lb/> proves to have very little force. The hon. <lb/>
                  member for Calgary (Mr. M. S. McCarthy) <lb/> states that the 104th meridian will
                  divide <lb/> the ranching country and that confusion is <lb/> likely to arise
                  between the different cattle <lb/> brands in the new provinces. If this objec<lb break="no"/>tion were a valid one, it would entail taking <lb/> the boundary
                  east to the western boundary <lb/> of Manitoba, which would be out of the <lb/>
                  question. There are cattle brands extending <lb/> all over that country, and
                  therefore the <lb/> adoption of another boundary would not re<lb break="no"/>move
                  what he regards as a serious objection. <lb/> It would entail making this whole
                  territory <lb/> into one province. I consider then that the <lb/> present dividing
                  line is as nearly ideal as is <lb/> possible, and that the two provinces will be
                  <lb/> closely equal in their present population, in <lb/> their prospects of
                  increased population, in <lb/> their natural resources and in the income <lb/>
                  which is at their disposal. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>There has been much discussion on the 
     <lb/>
     subject of the extension of the Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     boundaries to the west. On this question I 
     <lb/>
     am fully in accord with the sentiments of 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for East Assiniboia (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Turriff) and the hon. member for Saskatche<lb break="no"/>wan (Mr. Lamont). To quote the words of 
     <lb/>
     the latter gentleman, I believe that if such 
     <lb/>
     an extension were seriously contemplated 
     <lb/>
     it would raise such a storm in the west that 
     <lb/>
     our friends of the opposition who talk so 
     <lb/>
     persistently of the agitation of public 
     <lb/>
     opinion, of conflagrations and storms, would 
     <lb/>
     really see what a Northwest hurricane does 
     <lb/>
     mean. In this case they would not have to 
     <lb/>
     whistle for a breeze. The storm would be 
     <lb/>
     on them in very short order. There is no 
     <lb/>
     question, Mr. Speaker, as to the temper of 
     <lb/>
     the west on this subject. Public opinion is 
     <lb/>
     crystallized, and they have very clear-cut 
     <lb/>
     ideas on the subject. That opinion is grow<lb break="no"/>ing every day. There was a time when union 
     <lb/>
     with Manitoba might have been accepted, 
     <lb/>
     but dating from the day of that meeting held 
     <lb/>
     at Indian Head, a joint meeting which Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Haultain and Mr. Roblin, premier of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba, attended, and at which meeting Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Roblin actually threatened to hold up the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest Territories if they did not accede 
     <lb/>
     to his desires in this matter, there has been 
     <lb/>
     a change of sentiment. From the moment 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Roblin attempted to tell these peo<lb break="no"/>ple that if they did not consent to join with 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba, if they did not fall in with his 
     <lb/>
     views at that time expressed, he would 
     <lb/>
     make certain reprisals upon them, a feeling 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="5117" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5117.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">5117</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">APRIL 28, 1905</fw> 
          
     of antagonism to the idea of union has 
     <lb/>
     grown up. It is impossible that people who 
     <lb/>
     have any self-respect should submit to these 
     <lb/>
     threats or should give way to pressure of 
     <lb/>
     this kind. That feeling has been growing, 
     <lb/>
     and there is, further, a strong and rooted 
     <lb/>
     Objection to throwing in their fortune with 
     <lb/>
     a province which has so many heavy and 
     <lb/>
     serious liabilities at this time. A union 
     <lb/>
     with Manitoba would be entirely out of the 
     <lb/>
     question. This feeling is universal, and a 
     <lb/>
     determination exists, and has existed for 
     <lb/>
     some time, to oppose by every possible 
     <lb/>
     means the adding to Manitoba of one foot 
     <lb/>
     of territory to the west. I venture to say 
     <lb/>
     that if a vote were taken on this question 
     <lb/>
     95 per cent of the people would vote in this 
     <lb/>
     way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>The school clauses of the Bill have been 
     <lb/>
     the subject of much criticism and much 
     <lb/>
     discussion, and their consideration has 
     <lb/>
     taken up most of the time of the House. 
     <lb/>
     I am not a lawyer and I cannot discuss the 
     <lb/>
     matter from a constitutional point of view, 
     <lb/>
     but I have heard the opinions of constitu<lb break="no"/>tional lawyers on both sides of the House, 
     <lb/>
     and I must say that the different conclu<lb break="no"/>sions at which they have arrived have con<lb break="no"/>fused rather than enlightened those who 
     <lb/>
     listened to them. I will speak on the school 
     <lb/>
     question from a point of view different from 
     <lb/>
     that taken by any other gentleman who has 
     <lb/>
     spoken on the subject. I have been living 
     <lb/>
     in the Northwest for many years. I have 
     <lb/>
     reared a family there. and I am going to 
     <lb/>
     speak on the subject from the point of 
     <lb/>
     view of the father of a family whose chil<lb break="no"/>dren have attended those schools which are 
     <lb/>
     under diseussion. I have availed myself 
     <lb/>
     of the opportunity to somewhat carefully 
     <lb/>
     study our school system since I went into 
     <lb/>
     that country, because I have always con<lb break="no"/>sidered the education of a family to be a 
     <lb/>
     very serious matter. I can say this, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Speaker, and I can say it frankly and 
     <lb/>
     plainly, that in the Northwest Territories 
     <lb/>
     we have as good a school system as exists 
     <lb/>
     anywhere in Canada. The people who use 
     <lb/>
     these schools are satisfied with them. We 
     <lb/>
     can turn to our friends from Quebec and we 
     <lb/>
     can say to them: Your compatriots and 
     <lb/>
     your co-religionists in the Northwest Terri<lb break="no"/>tories are satisfied with those schools ; and 
     <lb/>
     we can say to our friends from Ontario or 
     <lb/>
     any of the other Protestant provinces: We, 
     <lb/>
     the Protestants of the Northwest are satis<lb break="no"/>fied with our school system which has 
     <lb/>
     worked well and is satisfactory to every 
     <lb/>
     one concerned. Let me say, Sir, that from 
     <lb/>
     the constituency which I have the honour 
     <lb/>
     to represent I have had not a single peti<lb break="no"/>tion asking me to do anything else than to 
     <lb/>
     support the system of schools which is at 
     <lb/>
     present established in that country. I would 
     <lb/>
     like to say one thing further, Mr. Speaker, 
     <lb/>
     and that is, that after listening to the 
     <lb/>
     speeches made from the opposition side of 
     <lb/>
     the House, I do not think that any one 
     <lb/>
     of them described the actual state of affairs. 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5118</fw>
          
     I do not think you will find in one of these 
     <lb/>
     speeches that the real state of affairs in re<lb break="no"/>gard to education now existing in the North<lb break="no"/>west is plainly set forth before the people. 
     <lb/>
     You hear from these gentlemen opposite a 
     <lb/>
     great deal about shackling the new pro<lb break="no"/>vinces and tying up the people of the North<lb break="no"/>west, but all that kind of talk is an entire 
     <lb/>
     mystery to the people of the west them<lb break="no"/>selves. I have just arrived from the west 
     <lb/>
     to-day, and I can say that in the hotels, 
     <lb/>
     travelling on trains, passing through 
     <lb/>
     the country and meeting people of all 
     <lb/>
     kinds, I failed to find a single man 
     <lb/>
     who really understood the exact state of 
     <lb/>
     affairs and who was not satisfied to see the 
     <lb/>
     school clauses of this Bill become law. The 
     <lb/>
     fact of the matter is that to find any agita<lb break="no"/>tion on the subject you have to get away 
     <lb/>
     from the Northwest Territories. The hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman who addressed the House this 
     <lb/>
     afternoon was able to give us some very 
     <lb/>
     valuable information on the subject, and I 
     <lb/>
     intended to deal at length with it but it 
     <lb/>
     has been gone over so often that it is hardly 
     <lb/>
     worth while to do so at this stage of the 
     <lb/>
     debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>Some hon. MEMBERS. Go on. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:ADAM2">Mr. ADAMSON</persName>. There are at least eleven <lb/> hundred schools
                  now in operation in the <lb/> Northwest Territories. Any of the school <lb/>
                  districts have the power, if they choose to <lb/> exercise it, to call into
                  operation the sepa<lb break="no"/>rate school clauses of the Act, but we find
                  <lb/> that less than one per cent of them have <lb/> done so, and that one per
                  cent is hardly <lb/> noticed although both Protestant and Catho<lb break="no"/>lic
                  children do attend these separate schools. <lb/> I lived within twelve miles of
                  one of these <lb/> separate schools for a long time without <lb/> knowing that
                  there was a separate school <lb/> there. I think every member of this House <lb/>
                  who seriously considers the question will <lb/> acknowledge that this is just as
                  close as we <lb/> possibly can get to having a national school <lb/> system. We
                  had a very pleasant picture <lb/> drawn by the member for Middlesex (Mr. <lb/>
                  Bison) of a condition of afiairs which he <lb/> considered to be ideal, in which
                  children <lb/> grew up together knowing one another well, <lb/> and becoming
                  closer in friendship and more <lb/> united in ideas. We all agree with that. <lb/>
                  The ideal state of afiairs possibly would be <lb/> that, and I contend that in the
                  Northwest <lb/> Territories we have attained as near as is <lb/> humanly possible
                  to that ideal. Now, I do not <lb/> say that religious instruction in the schools
                  is <lb/> good, nor do I say it is bad ; but, acting on <lb/> the assumption that
                  national schools are <lb/> actual perfection, and seeing that the ex<lb break="no"/>treme limit of religious instruction which <lb/> can be given in these schools
                  amounts to <lb/> one-half hour each day, then in the North<lb break="no"/>west
                  Territories we have it, that as one- <lb break="yes"/> twelfth of the time only
                  can be devoted to <lb/> religious instruction, and that only one per <lb/> cent of
                  the schools exercise that right, <lb/> We, therefore, come within one—twelfth of a <lb/>
                  <pb n="5119" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5119.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">5119</fw>
                  <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
                   one-hundreth part of perfection, as perfec<lb break="no"/>tion is described by the gentlemen who op<lb break="no"/>pose this Bill. I
                  think, Sir, that no one will <lb/> deny that this is just about as close to
                     perfec<lb break="no"/>tion as can be attained. If a man, no mat<lb break="no"/>ter whether he be a lawyer, a physician, or <lb/> a member of the House of
                  Commons, gets <lb/> within one-twelfth of a hundredth part of <lb/> perfection in
                  doing his duty he is very <lb/> close to the real thing. I can tell you, Sir,
                  <lb/> that it would be weak in us and it would <lb/> be shirking our
                  responsibility, if the parlia<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada when passing these
                     Auton<lb break="no"/>omy Bills did not settle the school question <lb/> for now
                  and for all time. We would not <lb/> be doing our duty here if we were to throw
                  <lb/> it as an apple of discord into the midst of <lb/> the new provinces. The
                  future of Canada <lb/> hinges very largely on the prosperity and <lb/> the
                  settlement of this new territory of ours. <lb/> It will be found on examination
                  that <lb/> the expansion of trade in eastern Can<lb break="no"/>ada is just about
                  commensurate with the <lb/> development of the west. It is the duty of <lb/> every
                  Canadiana to do what he can to <lb/> develop his country, and if we can people
                  <lb/> the west with an industrious and enter<lb break="no"/>prising population,
                  then we will be helping <lb/> every province in this Dominion. We have <lb/> heard
                  discussions in this House as to whe<lb break="no"/>ther there should be two story
                  sheds or one <lb/> story sheds built on the wharfs of Mon<lb break="no"/>treal ;
                  we have heard discussions as to <lb/> the improvement of harbours and canals,
                  <lb/> but, when you come to consider the solid <lb/> facts of the case you will
                  see that in the <lb/> final analysis the prosperity of all these <lb/> great
                  undertakings must depend upon the <lb/> development of the west. If the wheat
                  <lb/> lands of the west are not cultivated and <lb/> brought under the hands of
                  the tiller of the <lb/>soil there is no use developing the harbours <lb/>of the
                  cities of the east. I would strongly <lb/>impress upon the House that the
                  attention <lb/>of the people of the west should not be <lb/>diverted from the
                  great work which they <lb/>have in hand to develop the fertility of the <lb/>soil.
                  I was one of those who for seven <lb/>  years took part in the fight about the
                  school <lb/>question in Manitoba. We fought there for <lb/>just such a system of
                  schools as we have <lb/>now in operation in the Northwest Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, and I know how that agitation tore <lb/>the people apart, how it
                  exhausted their <lb/>energies, and how it diverted them from <lb/>the work they
                  might otherwise be profitably <lb/>employed in. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>It is a serious matter to involve people 
     <lb/>in a strife of this kind with one another ; 
     <lb/>and, as we have the matter practically set<lb break="no"/>tled amongst ourselves, it would be a last<lb break="no"/>ing shame on this government if it did not 
     <lb/>continue the system of schools which has 
     <lb/>proved so effective. We hear much decla<lb break="no"/>mation about the imposing of conditions on 
     <lb/>the new provinces ; but how can there be 
     <lb/>imposition where all the parties concerned 
     <lb/>are willing and anxious that the measure 
     <lb/>should be adopted ? There can be no shack<lb break="no"/><cb/>
     <fw type="num">5120</fw>ling where the bonds do not bind ; and, as 
     <lb/>
     the Territories say distinctly that they want 
     <lb/>
     the present school system, where is the 
     <lb/>
     point of the opposition in this discussion ? 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Haultain, the premier of the Northwest 
     <lb/>
     Territories, has declared that if he were 
     <lb/>
     dictator to-morrow, he would not change 
     <lb/>
     the school law, and he is certainly right 
     <lb/>
     in so expressing himself. That law is a 
     <lb/>
     good and satisfactory one, and I consider 
     <lb/>
     that it is in line with the record of this 
     <lb/>
     Liberal government that knowing the wishes 
     <lb/>
     of the people on this point, they should 
     <lb/>
     make it a part of the constitution of the 
     <lb/>
     new provinces.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>I notice that the Conservative press of 
     <lb/>
     to-day claims that a great victory on the 
     <lb/>
     school question has been won by the Con<lb break="no"/>servative party in Manitoba, in the division 
     <lb/>
     of Mountain, where a supporter of the 
     <lb/>
     Roblin government has been elected. I 
     <lb/>
     would like, however, to draw the attention 
     <lb/>
     of the House to the fact that the Prime 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Manitoba distinctly stated in 
     <lb/>
     opening the campaign, that the school ques<lb break="no"/>tion was not an issue in that election. He 
     <lb/>
     made that very clear and distinct, and his 
     <lb/>
     utterance on that point is quoted in to<lb break="no"/>day's press. He has made a stand on what 
     <lb/>
     he calls the rights of Manitoba in the matter 
     <lb/>
     of the enlargement of its boundaries. If 
     <lb/>
     our friends of the opposition wish to put to 
     <lb/>
     the test how the people of the Northwest 
     <lb/>
     stand on this question, there is a very good 
     <lb/>
     opportunity for them. There happen to be 
     <lb/>
     at present seven vacancies in the North<lb break="no"/>west legislature, and I believe it would be 
     <lb/>
     the consistent and the proper course for 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Haultain to submit this question to 
     <lb/>
     the electors in those vacant constitutncies. 
     <lb/>
     He would then get his answer with no 
     <lb/>
     uncertain sound ; and then, by calling the 
     <lb/>
     legislature together, he would be in a posi<lb break="no"/>tion to obtain a declaration from that body 
     <lb/>
     on the subject. I venture to prophesy that 
     <lb/>
     he would find himself in the very unpleasant 
     <lb/>
     position of being voted down by the North<lb break="no"/>west legislature. The school Act of the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest Territories makes it very clear 
     <lb/>
     what the powers of the provinces are. The 
     <lb/>
     school system is under the control of a sup<lb break="no"/>erintendent ; that superintendent is respons<lb break="no"/>ible to the government : he has his advisory 
     <lb/>
     board, he licenses the teachers, provides 
     <lb/>
     their curriculum, selects the text-books of 
     <lb/>
     the schools, provides for their inspection, 
     <lb/>
     and has complete control over them. There 
     <lb/>
     is but one system, not a dual system, and, 
     <lb/>
     as I said before, it is perfectly satisfactory 
     <lb/>
     to the people of the Territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>These are briefly my reasons, Mr. Speaker, 
     <lb/>
     for supporting the Bill, and I can say con<lb break="no"/>fidently that it is acceptable to the people 
     <lb/>
     of the Northwest Territories, and that any 
     <lb/>
     portion of those Territories will confirm the 
     <lb/>
     action that is now being taken. We have 
     <lb/>
     had an illustration of the feeling or the 
     <lb/>
     people in what has taken place in the con<lb break="no"/>stituency of the present Minister of the 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="5121" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5121.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">5121</fw> <fw type="dateline">APRIL 28, 1905</fw> 
     
    Interior, the Hon. Mr. Oliver. The Con<lb break="no"/>servative association there passed a resolu<lb break="no"/>tion to the effect that it would be useless 
     <lb/>or impolitic to oppose him ; his late op<lb break="no"/>ponent, Mr. Secord, endorsed his candi<lb break="no"/>dature ; and he has been returned by ac<lb break="no"/>clamation. If he had been opposed, he 
     <lb/>certainly would have been returned by a 
     <lb/>larger majority than he had before. The 
     <lb/>Board of Trade of Edmonton, which cer<lb break="no"/>tainly cannot be called a sectarian body, 
     <lb/>which is neither Galician nor Doukhobor, 
     <lb/>but strictly Canadian, passed a resolution 
     <lb/>endorsing his candidature. I think that is 
     <lb/>a fairly good answer to our critics on the 
     <lb/>other side of the House, and I am confident 
     <lb/>that any other constituency in the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories, I care not which it is, 
     <lb/>would give exactly the same answer. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve that the people of the Northwest are 
     <lb/>at one on this subject. These are the rea<lb break="no"/>sons, Mr. Speaker, why I intend to support 
     <lb/>this Bill, and I am sure that everybody in 
     <lb/>the House will join in the wish of the hon. 
     <lb/>member for Middlesex that peace and happi<lb break="no"/>ness may be the lot of these now provinces 
     <lb/>which are now about to join the great 
     <lb/>federacy of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SINC1">Mr. J. H. SINCLAIR</persName> (Guysborough). Mr. <lb/>Speaker, allow me to
                  congratulate my hon. <lb/>friend from Humbolt (Mr. Adamson) on <lb/>the splendid
                  speech to which we have just <lb/>listened. It has been one of the most inter<lb break="no"/>esting contributions that has been made <lb/>to the present debate.
                  It would have been <lb/>more in accord with the etiquette of debate <lb/>for some
                  hon. gentleman from the other <lb/>side of the House to undertake to answer
                  <lb/>my hon. friend ; but one thing that has <lb/>struck me very forcibly during
                  the last few <lb/>days has been the great calm which has <lb/>come over the
                  opposition benches. Three <lb/>or four weeks ago it was different. One <lb/>would
                  have imagined, from the speeches of <lb/>hon. gentlemen opposite, and from the
                     arti<lb break="no"/>cles in the newspapers which support their <lb/>party, that
                  there was a great agitation in <lb/>this country, that the heather was on fire
                  <lb/>all over Canada. The Toronto ' World ' and <lb/>the Toronto ' News ' came out
                  day after day <lb/>with extravagant headlines ; the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber
                  for North Toronto (Mr. Foster) deluged <lb/>us with sarcasm ; the hon. member for
                  <lb/>South York (Mr. Maclean) went about with <lb/>a chip on his shoulder
                  challenging us all <lb/>to resign ; and the hon. member for East <lb/>Grey (Mr.
                  Sproule), in his own mild and <lb/>gentle manner, said some pretty hard things
                  <lb/>about us. But, Sir, the Easter holidays <lb/>came and have passed away, the
                  ice has <lb/>melted from the river, the grass has <lb/>begun to grow, the tulips
                  have begun to <lb/>appear, and we have all been struck with <lb/>the quietness of
                  this chamber. We cannot <lb/>but ask ourselves: Has there really been <lb/>an
                  agitation in this country? And those <lb/>who remember that there was an agitation
                  <lb/>are beginning to inquire what it was all <lb/>about. <lb/>
               </p>
   
          <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5122</fw>
   
            <p>We are told that this is a struggle for 
     <lb/>
     provincial rights. Hon. gentlemen opposite 
     <lb/>
     claim to be the divinely constituted cham<lb break="no"/>pions of these rights considering their past 
     <lb/>
     record. It is rather satisfactory to find 
     <lb/>
     them in that frame of mind. We are 
     <lb/>
     rather gratified to perceive this change of 
     <lb/>
     heart among so many of our hon. friends 
     <lb/>
     opposite on this important question. But 
     <lb/>
     in my opinion provincial rights are not 
     <lb/>
     at all assailed in this measure, and our hon. 
     <lb/>
     frends opposite, in rushing to the rescue, 
     <lb/>
     are simply seeking to combat a phantom 
     <lb/>
     of their own imagination. If we look 
     <lb/>
     into the facts, we will find that there is no 
     <lb/>
     such thing in this country as strict pro<lb break="no"/>vincial rights on the question of educa<lb break="no"/>tion. That is a thing unknown in our con<lb break="no"/>stitution. It might be a good thing and I 
     <lb/>
     am not at present disposed to say it would 
     <lb/>
     not ; and if hon. gentlemen opposite wish to 
     <lb/>
     start a crusade to change the constitution 
     <lb/>
     and place the question of education on a 
     <lb/>
     different basis, that would be a fair ques<lb break="no"/>tion to discuss in public and on which to 
     <lb/>
     get the sense of the people. And if hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen opposite were to start any such 
     <lb/>
     crusade, possibly many of us would feel 
     <lb/>
     like having the question of education made 
     <lb/>
     a purely provincial one. I need hardly re<lb break="no"/>fer to the fact, since every hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     here knows it, that section 91 of the Bri<lb break="no"/>tish North America Act enumerates certain 
     <lb/>
     subjects as coming under Dominion con<lb break="no"/>trol, such as the public debt, postal ser<lb break="no"/>vice, fisheries, the criminal law and many 
     <lb/>
     others, and that section 92 enumerates the 
     <lb/>
     subjects which fall under the control of the 
     <lb/>
     provincial legislature, such as direct tax<lb break="no"/>ation, the maintenance of hospitals and asy<lb break="no"/>lums, property, and civil rights. Then 
     <lb/>
     we come to section 93, which deals with 
     <lb/>
     the question of education, and that question 
     <lb/>
     is dealt with in a different way from any 
     <lb/>
     of the others. We do not find it mentioned 
     <lb/>
     at all in sections 91 and 92, but we have 
     <lb/>
     it specially mentioned in section 93, and 
     <lb/>
     that section places it under a divided juris<lb break="no"/>diction. Provision is made for separate 
     <lb/>
     schools in the old provinces of Quebec and 
     <lb/>
     Ontario, and there is also a provision that 
     <lb/>
     the minority in the other provinces will 
     <lb/>
     have the right to appeal to the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     parliament against any injustice done them 
     <lb/>
     by a provincial legislature. It seems to 
     <lb/>
     me therefore plain that in the matter of 
     <lb/>
     education there is no such thing, strictly 
     <lb/>
     speaking, as provincial rights under our 
     <lb/>
     constitution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>But what are the real merits of the agi<lb break="no"/>tation when it is sifted down? The school 
     <lb/>
     system of the Northwest Territories is ad<lb break="no"/>mittedly a good one. The hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     who spoke last has described what an ex<lb break="no"/>cellent one it is ; and none of the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen opposite who have been addressing 
     <lb/>
     us for the past month has ventured to say 
     <lb/>
     a word against it. What they do say is 
     <lb/>
     simply this, that while in itself it is an 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="5123" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5123.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">5123</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> 


     excellent system, it would be a bad thing 
     <lb/>
     to perpetuate it, because that is a matter 
     <lb/>
     which should come purely under provincial 
     <lb/>
     control. Premier Haultaln himself has 
     <lb/>
     said that it cannot be improved, and that 
     <lb/>
     if he should be declared dictator to-morrow 
     <lb/>
     he would not change it. He, however, is 
     <lb/>
     not willing that this parliament should 
     <lb/>
     take from him the power to do a thing 
     <lb/>
     which he says he never would do if left 
     <lb/>
     to himself. In that respect he reminds 
     <lb/>
     me of the small boy who would not let 
     <lb/>
     the other little fellow play in his back yard, 
     <lb/>
     and refused to allow him the privilege of 
     <lb/>
     hollering down the empty water barrel. 
     <lb/>
     And for what reason forsooth? Simply 
     <lb/>
     because it was his barrel, and he insisted 
     <lb/>
     on doing all the hollering himself. If that 
     <lb/>
     be not a case of tweedledum and tweedledee, 
     <lb/>
     I have never known of such a case in all 
     <lb/>
     my life. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>There is one feature, however, of the 
     <lb/>
     agitation which is extremely regrettable 
     <lb/>
     and that is the extremely inflammatory 
     <lb/>
     course which has been adopted by certain 
     <lb/>
     newspapers in this country. What justifi<lb break="no"/>cation, for instance, can be given for 
     <lb/>
     articles such as these. Let me read you 
     <lb/>
     an extract from an article in the Toronto 
     <lb/>
     'World' from some correspondent in Mani<lb break="no"/>toba and which is given all the notoriety of 
     <lb/>
     capital letters : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     You may give it for what it is worth, but 
     <lb/>
     my individual opinion is that Sir Wilfrid 
     <lb/>
     Laurier was informed immediately by Mon<lb break="no"/>seigneur Sbarretti of the failure of his advances, 
     <lb/>
     and that the invitation to the other provinces 
     <lb/>
     to put forward their claims was made expressly 
     <lb/>
     in Sir Wilfrid's speech on the following day 
     <lb/>
     from personal motives of pique, because the 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba delegates had not listened to reason. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>

            <p>That is a statement made in the Toronto 
     <lb/>
     ' World,' and made in spite of the fact that 
     <lb/>
     the speech was not at all made the follow<lb break="no"/>ing day. The dates were falsified obviously 
     <lb/>
     for the purpose of creating in the public 
     <lb/>
     mind the impression that Sir Wilfrid Lau<lb break="no"/>rier had brought the delegates from Mani<lb break="no"/>toba here in order to expose them to the 
     <lb/>
     blandishments of the Papal delegate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Sir Wilfrid Laurier's speech was made on 
     <lb/>
     the 21st February and the meeting of Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Campbell with the Papal delegate—mind 
     <lb/>
     you, Mr. Speaker, Mr. Rogers never met 
     <lb/>
     the Papal delegate at all—was (on the 23rd 
     <lb/>
     February, two days after the public an<lb break="no"/>nouncement was made of the policy of the 
     <lb/>
     government regarding the boundaries of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba. That falsehood was not only 
     <lb/>
     stated in the Toronto 'World' on that oc<lb break="no"/>casion but has been repeated time and 
     <lb/>
     again both in that newspaper and the To<lb break="no"/>ronto 'News.' I have gone through the 
     <lb/>
     columns of the 'News' carefully to see if 
     <lb/>
     the writers on that paper ever corrected 
     <lb/>
     that false impression. They might have 
     <lb/>
     been misled in the first instance by the 
     <lb/>
     impression given by Mr. Rogers in the in<lb break="no"/>terview he published in the city or Winni<lb break="no"/><cb/>
     <fw type="num">5124</fw>peg, but did they attempt to set the public 
     <lb/>
     right subsequently? Not at all. I have 
     <lb/>
     carefully gone through the editorials of 
     <lb/>
     that paper, and find that not the slightest 
     <lb/>
     attempt was made to correct the false im<lb break="no"/>pression to which it gave circulation re<lb break="no"/>garding the First Minister. Then I find 
     <lb/>
     another editorial, such as the following: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     Was there an understanding ? That Sir Wil<lb break="no"/>frid Laurier and Monseigneur Sbarretti would 
     <lb/>
     deny formal co-operation in the attempt to 
     <lb/>
     coerce the province of Manitoba into the adop<lb break="no"/>tion of such a separate school system as they 
     <lb/>
     both desire, was only to be expected. Negotia<lb break="no"/>tions of this kind under circumstances involv<lb break="no"/>ing inflammatory and dangerous questions are 
     <lb/>
     not carried on by an astute politician, and an 
     <lb/>
     equally astute diplom'atist in such a way as 
     <lb/>
     will leave any visible trail. Nevertheless, 
     <lb/>
     enough has been disclosed to render it in the 
     <lb/>
     highest degree probable that a tacit but very 
     <lb/>
     clear understanding existed between them. It 
     <lb/>
     is not necessary to suppose that a formal con<lb break="no"/>ference took place at which the Papal delegate 
     <lb/>
     was authorized to give the Manitoba delegates. 
     <lb/>
     the very distinct intimation that he did give. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>These are extracts from the 'World.' I 
     <lb/>
     shall give you now one or two from the 
     <lb/>
     'News.' Here is an editorial from that 
     <lb/>
     paper : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>On February 13th, Mr. Rogers and his col<lb break="no"/>league, Mr. Campbell, received a telegram from 
     <lb/>
     Sir Wilfnid Laurier asking them to visit Ot<lb break="no"/>tawa on the 17th. They saw Sir Wilfrid and 
     <lb/>
     presented the claims of the province for an ex<lb break="no"/>tension, and were asked to wait three or four 
     <lb/>
     days for an answer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>0n the 20th they received a letter, not from 
     <lb/>
     Sir Wilfrid, but from the Papal delegate, asking 
     <lb/>
     for a conference. When they saw the delegate, 
     <lb/>
     he told them that the settlement of the boundary 
     <lb/>
     question would be greatly facilitated if the 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba government would consent to certain 
     <lb/>
     amendments in the school law, which he sub<lb break="no"/>mitted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>The same criticism applies to that. They 
     <lb/>
     received no invitation from the premier, 
     <lb/>
     on the contrary they asked for the inter<lb break="no"/>view themselves. The date there, of course, 
     <lb/>
     is also changed. On the 17th they saw 
     <lb/>
     Sir Wilfrid Laurier, and presented the 
     <lb/>
     claims, and they were asked to wait three 
     <lb/>
     or four days. This has been denied by 
     <lb/>
     Sir Wilfrid Laurier, whose statement is 
     <lb/>
     corroborated by the Postmaster General (Sir 
     <lb/>
     William Mulock), and those newspapers 
     <lb/>
     which have circulated these falsehoods 
     <lb/>
     throughout the country have not apologized 
     <lb/>
     or tried to correct them. Another item 
     <lb/>
     from the Toronto ' News ' is headed : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     The Grit apostasy. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>This item was published in the Halifax 
     <lb/>
     'Herald,' which describes the Toronto 
     <lb/>
     'News ' as an independent Liberal paper. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     It is doubtful if a single member of the House 
     <lb/>
     of Commons, either to the right or left of the 
     <lb/>
     Speaker. is deceived by the specious argument 
     <lb/>
     that the government is constitutionally obliged 
     <lb/>
     to create a separate school system for the new 
     <lb/>
     western provinces. The truth is that the Bills 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="5125" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5125.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">5125</fw> <fw type="dateline">APRIL 28, 1905</fw> 

     now before parliament represent a bargain be<lb break="no"/>tween certain ministers and the Roman Catholic 
     <lb/>
     hierarchy, and, in consequence of this secret 
     <lb/>
     compact, we must accept an interpretation of 
     <lb/>
     the Canadian constitution, not by the Supreme 
     <lb/>
     Court of Canada or the Privy Council of the 
     <lb/>
     empire, but by the Court of Rome. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>There is not the slightest foundation for 
     <lb/>
     any of those statements. There is now 
     <lb/>
     abundant proof that they are absolutely un<lb break="no"/>true. I could give a large number of other 
     <lb/>
     extracts from such leading pournals as the 
     <lb/>
     Toronto "Mail ' and from a paper called the 
     <lb/>
     ' Sun,' published in Toronto, but I shall not 
     <lb/>
     weary the House by reading them. The 
     <lb/>
     object of these items is to convey a false 
     <lb/>
     impression to the people Of this country; 
     <lb/>
     and, to say the least of it, is it not disgrace<lb break="no"/>ful and reprehensible on the part of these 
     <lb/>
     newspapers? I am not in the habit of 
     <lb/>
     using strong language, but I question if the 
     <lb/>
     usage of parliament would permit language 
     <lb/>
     strong enough to characterize the conduct 
     <lb/>
     of those newspapers in connection with this 
     <lb/>
     matter. Everybody in Canada knows that 
     <lb/>
     these repeated and persistent attacks in con<lb break="no"/>nection with the Papal delegate would not 
     <lb/>
     have been made if the right hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     who leads this House was not a member 
     <lb/>
     of the Roman Catholic communion. It is 
     <lb/>
     repeated day after day that there is a power 
     <lb/>
     behind the throne. that this legislation is 
     <lb/>
     introduced and is being carried through at 
     <lb/>
     the instigation of the Roman Catholic hier<lb break="no"/>archy, that the premier of Canada has abro<lb break="no"/>gated his functions altogether, and has be<lb break="no"/>trayed the trust which this country has 
     <lb/>
     placed in him. We are invited to witness 
     <lb/>
     the noble spectacle of men standing patri<lb break="no"/>otically for a great principle. But what do 
     <lb/>
     we see ? Why, Sir, instead of that, we 
     <lb/>
     see men attempting to besmirch and in<lb break="no"/>jure the reputation of a great statesman 
     <lb/>
     by an utter disregard for the truth ; that 
     <lb/>
     is the spectacle we see. Let hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen look at this measure, calmly ex<lb break="no"/>amine the charges against the premier, 
     <lb/>
     and then judge for themselves. Why, 
     <lb/>
     Sir, there is not a sentence in those edu<lb break="no"/>cational clauses, not a single line that the 
     <lb/>
     veriest baby in public life would attri<lb break="no"/>bute to the pen of a prelate of the Roman 
     <lb/>
     Catholic church. Does any man imagine 
     <lb/>
     that if a prelate of the Roman Catholic 
     <lb/>
     church had an opportunity of moulding a 
     <lb/>
     school system for the Northwest, he would 
     <lb/>
     provide for national schools, for schools 
     <lb/>
     taught by duly licensed teachers, in which 
     <lb/>
     only authorized school books were used, 
     <lb/>
     schools subject to strict public inspection and 
     <lb/>
     controlled altogether by the local legislature, 
     <lb/>
     schools in which the only concession made to 
     <lb/>
     his views is that both Protestants and Cath<lb break="no"/>olics have the same opportunity or teaching 
     <lb/>
     religion for one-half hour at the close of 
     <lb/>
     each day ? I appeal to hon. gentlemen op<lb break="no"/>posite, what is their opinion ? Do they 
     <lb/>
     think that the educational provisions of 
     <lb/>
     this Bill show internal evidence that they 
     <lb/>
     were inspired by a priest of the Roman 
     <lb/>
       
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5126</fw>
         
     Catholic church ? I know that the press of 
     <lb/>
     both political parties on occasions of ex<lb break="no"/>citement say extravagant things, but there 
     <lb/>
     should be some bound even to newspaper 
     <lb/>
     discussion. I have watched the course of 
     <lb/>
     public discussion in this country for the 
     <lb/>
     past twenty years, but this is the first occa<lb break="no"/>sion on which I have known the press of a 
     <lb/>
     great political party, such as the party re<lb break="no"/>presented by hon. gentlemen opposite, to 
     <lb/>
     abandon all fair dealing and all decency 
     <lb/>
     and fair-play, and to revel in falsehood and 
     <lb/>
     misrepresentation, as they have done during 
     <lb/>
     the course of this discussion. I do not now 
     <lb/>
     refer to all the Conservative papers in Can<lb break="no"/>ada. The Conservative papers of Montreal, 
     <lb/>
     such as the Montreal 'Star' and the Mont<lb break="no"/>real 'Gazette,' have throughout maintained 
     <lb/>
     a sober and dignified course ; the news<lb break="no"/>papers which have lost all sense of decency 
     <lb/>
     and fairness are certain Toronto newspapers, 
     <lb/>
     and among the lowest and most despicable 
     <lb/>
     of the yellow journals of the city of Toron<lb break="no"/>to, representing the Conservative party, are 
     <lb/>
     the Toronto 'News' and the Toronto 
     <lb/>
     'World.' I am very sorry to say it, because 
     <lb/>
     we are all proud of Toronto as a great city, 
     <lb/>
     but Toronto seems to have won for itself 
     <lb/>
     the unenviable reputation of being the hot<lb break="no"/>bed of bigotry and intolerance in this coun<lb break="no"/>try. This is not my opinion alone; I shall 
     <lb/>
     give you the opinion of one of the leading 
     <lb/>
     newspapers in the city of Montreal. the 
     <lb/>
     Montreal 'Gazette.' The Montreal ' Ga<lb break="no"/>zette (Conservative) sums up the Toronto- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     made 'situation' in the following concise 
     <lb/>
     and effective manner : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     The Toronto 'Globe' of Saturday speaks of 
     <lb/>
     the situation at Ottawa as a crisis. The 'Globe ' 
     <lb/>
     is being too much excited by its own surround<lb break="no"/>ings. In a good many parts of the country 
     <lb/>
     there is a belief that if telegraph and mail 
     <lb/>
     communication with Toronto were shut off in 
     <lb/>
     some way for a few days, the people generally 
     <lb/>
     would forget that parliament was doing any<lb break="no"/>thing more serious than voting money for non<lb break="no"/>paying enterprises. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>That, Sir, is the opinion of the Montreal 
     <lb/>
     ' Gazette,' that if we could cut the telegraph 
     <lb/>
     and mail connections between Toronto and 
     <lb/>
     the rest of Canada, that this agitation would 
     <lb/>
     stop in a few days, and, Sir, I think the 
     <lb/>
     'Gazette' is right. There must be some 
     <lb/>
     compromise on a question of this kind. It 
     <lb/>
     has always been the case in the history of 
     <lb/>
     Canada that we have had to compromise 
     <lb/>
     delicate questions like this. You cannot 
     <lb/>
     override the views of a minority of the 
     <lb/>
     people that after all comprise nearly half 
     <lb/>
     our population, you cannot crush them and 
     <lb/>
     say they must do just what you say and 
     <lb/>
     what you think. Every student of Canadian 
     <lb/>
     history must know that no political leader 
     <lb/>
     in this country ever yet succeeded in doing 
     <lb/>
     that. The coterie that surrounded the old 
     <lb/>
     'Family Compact' tried to do it and no 
     <lb/>
     political combination in this country ever 
     <lb/>
     had so good an opportunity to succeed in 
     <lb/>
     that attempt and they failed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="5127" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5127.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">5127</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> 

            <p>What was the result? The people of 
     <lb/>
     Quebec led by Lafontaine and joined by 
     <lb/>
     Baldwin rallied the broad-minded and toler<lb break="no"/>ant men of Canada to their standard and 
     <lb/>
     routed old Toryism in this country for ever. 
     <lb/>
     Then George Brown emerged from the Bald<lb break="no"/>win party and began an agitation to unite 
     <lb/>
     the Protestants of Upper and Lower Canada 
     <lb/>
     against the Roman Catholic minority with 
     <lb/>
     the result that he kept Sir John Macdonald 
     <lb/>
     in power for a generation. Then our over<lb break="no"/>zealous fellow-countrymen in Ontario led on 
     <lb/>
     by the 'Mail and Empire' started a similar 
     <lb/>
     propaganda in more recent times with the 
     <lb/>
     result that the Liberal party led by Sir 
     <lb/>
     Oliver Mowat held power in Ontario for a 
     <lb/>
     quarter of a century. And, Sir, in view of 
     <lb/>
     our past history and the circumstances that 
     <lb/>
     surround us at present it is plain to every 
     <lb/>
     thinking man, and the leader of the oppo<lb break="no"/>sition himself must have realized it by 
     <lb/>
     this time, that the course adopted by him 
     <lb/>
     today in regard to this measure will have 
     <lb/>
     the effect of cementing the ranks of the 
     <lb/>
     Liberal party from the Atlantic to the Paci<lb break="no"/>fic and perpetuating Liberal rule in this 
     <lb/>
     country for the next twenty years. I know 
     <lb/>
     very well that the leader of the opposition 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. R. L. Borden) does not like the posi<lb break="no"/>tion that he is in, does not like the task that 
     <lb/>
     some of his over-zealous friends have im<lb break="no"/>posed on him on this occasion. I have 
     <lb/>
     always felt sorry that he was placed in 
     <lb/>
     that position as he is an eminent fellow- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     countryman of my own. And I firmly be<lb break="no"/>lieve that if he had a good, large follow<lb break="no"/>ing from the province of Nova Scotia, and if 
     <lb/>
     he continued to represent the good old coun<lb break="no"/>ty of Halifax, where race and religious 
     <lb/>
     disputes are unknown, he would find it 
     <lb/>
     easier to make his way through this tangle 
     <lb/>
     than he has found it under existing cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>The two provinces that profess to have 
     <lb/>
     this question most at heart are the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces of Ontario and Manitoba. It is from 
     <lb/>
     the Tory press and the Tory politicians 
     <lb/>
     of these provinces that the wild, hysterical 
     <lb/>
     appeals have come to which we have been 
     <lb/>
     compelled to listen during the course of 
     <lb/>
     this agitation. What is the past record of 
     <lb/>
     the Conservative party in these provinces 
     <lb/>
     on this question? Is it such that we are 
     <lb/>
     bound to give them credit for sincerity now? 
     <lb/>
     What did the Conservatives in these pro<lb break="no"/>vinces do in 1896? Did they stand by Sir 
     <lb/>
     Wilfrid Laurier, or did they vote for their 
     <lb/>
     own party, which, at that time, was attempt<lb break="no"/>ing to force separate schools of a clerical 
     <lb/>
     type on the province of Manitoba? On that 
     <lb/>
     occasion, which was the only occasion in 
     <lb/>
     the history of this country when the people 
     <lb/>
     lead an opportunity to vote upon this ques<lb break="no"/>tion Ontario gave Sir Wilfrid Laurier 44 
     <lb/>
     supporters out of 92 representatives elected, 
     <lb/>
     and Manitoba elected four Conservatives, 
     <lb/>
     two Liberals and one independent. Such is 
     <lb/>
     the record of these hysterical gentlemen on 
     <lb/>
     the only occasion in all their lives when they 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5128</fw>
           
     had an opportunity of showing that they 
     <lb/>
     had genuine and sincere convictions on this 
     <lb/>
     question ; and that is a record that entitles 
     <lb/>
     every thoughtful man in Canada to regard 
     <lb/>
     their present agitation as a thoroughly poli<lb break="no"/>tical agitation carried on, not for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of establishing free schools in the 
     <lb/>
     west, but for the sole purpose of getting 
     <lb/>
     votes for the Conservative party. What are 
     <lb/>
     the facts ? We all know that the course 
     <lb/>
     of the Toronto 'Globe' has not been friendly 
     <lb/>
     to the Liberal party on this question, and 
     <lb/>
     perhaps I cannot do better than to read to 
     <lb/>
     you a short extract from the Toronto 'Globe' 
     <lb/>
     describing the system of schools we are 
     <lb/>
     establishing in the west. We all want to 
     <lb/>
     place that before our friends in the country, 
     <lb/>
     because, that is, after all the vital question. 
     <lb/>
     I want to show What kind of schools we 
     <lb/>
     are giving to the new provinces, and this 
     <lb/>
     article from the Toronto 'Globe ' explains 
     <lb/>
     that point : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Stick to the facts. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>No good can come of misrepresenting the 
     <lb/>
     facts in the controversy respecting the schools 
     <lb/>
     in the new provinces. It is a gross misrepre<lb break="no"/>sentation to pretend that what is called a sepa<lb break="no"/>rate school in the Territories is the same thing 
     <lb/>
     as a separate school in Ontario. By no stretch 
     <lb/>
     of language could the separate school in the 
     <lb/>
     west be designated as a church school. From 
     <lb/>
     9 o'clock in the morning till 3.30 in the after<lb break="no"/>noon the schools of the Catholic or Protestant 
     <lb/>
     minority are conducted precisely as the public 
     <lb/>
     schools are conducted. The scholars are taught 
     <lb/>
     by a teacher certificated and authorized by the 
     <lb/>
     Department of Education of the Territories ; he 
     <lb/>
     teaches from the same text—hooks as are used 
     <lb/>
     in the public schools; he follows the same 
     <lb/>
     programme as is followed in the public schools: 
     <lb/>
     his school is regularly inspected by the inspec<lb break="no"/>tor that inspects the public schools, and if the 
     <lb/>
     teaching were unsatisfactory the government 
     <lb/>
     could withhold the public grants. So thoroughly 
     <lb/>
     undenominational is the teaching that Protest<lb break="no"/>ant children attend separate schools when these 
     <lb/>
     are more convenient than public schools. The 
     <lb/>
     only privilege that the Catholic minority obtain 
     <lb/>
     is that the teacher is a Catholic, and after halt~ 
     <lb/>
     past three may impart religious instruction ac<lb break="no"/>cording to the tenets of the Catholic church to 
     <lb/>
     the children who choose to remain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>These are the facts, and those who are hon<lb break="no"/>estly seeking a permanent and satisfactory 
     <lb/>
     solution of the vexed questions which arise un<lb break="no"/>der the Autonomy Bill's can afford to admit 
     <lb/>
     them. Those who are merely desirous of for<lb break="no"/>warding their political designs by appeals to 
     <lb/>
     passion are unfortunately seeking to mislead 
     <lb/>
     people and distort the facts of the case. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>


            <p>This is the description of the facts given 
     <lb/>
     by the Toronto 'Globe' and it is a very 
     <lb/>
     fair description. Now, Sir, it comes down 
     <lb/>
     to this, that we are. by the educational 
     <lb/>
     clauses of this Bill, establishing a national 
     <lb/>
     system of public schools for the west with 
     <lb/>
     the right to give one-half hour's religious 
     <lb/>
     instruction to the pupils at the close of each 
     <lb/>
     day. This is not a new idea by any means. 
     <lb/>
     We have the same in the province of Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia, and we have had it for a great many 
     <lb/>
     years. This was brought to the attention 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="5129" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5129.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">5129</fw> <fw type="dateline">APRIL 28, 1905</fw> 
           
     of the House this afternoon by my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend from Hants (Mr. Black). However, 
     <lb/>
     as he did not read the whole clause I would 
     <lb/>
     like to place it on record. I quote from 
     <lb/>
     the school regulations made by the Council 
     <lb/>
     of Public Instruction and now in force in 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia. This is the regulation: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Whereas, it has been represented to the 
     <lb/>
     council that trustees of public schools have, in 
     <lb/>
     certain cases, required pupils, on pain of for<lb break="no"/>feiting school privileges, to be present during 
     <lb/>
     devotional exercises not approved of by their 
     <lb/>
     parents ; and whereas, such proceeding is con<lb break="no"/>trary to the principles of the school law, the 
     <lb/>
     following regulation is made for the direction 
     <lb/>
     of trustees, the better to ensure the carrying 
     <lb/>
     out of the spirit of the law in this behalf: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>It is ordered that in cases where the parents 
     <lb/>
     or guardians of children in actual attendance 
     <lb/>
     on any public school or department signify in 
     <lb/>
     writing to the trustees their conscientious ob<lb break="no"/>jection to any portion of such devotional exer<lb break="no"/>cises as may be conducted therein under the 
     <lb/>
     sanction of the trustees, such devotional exer<lb break="no"/>cises shall either be so modfied as not to offend 
     <lb/>
     the religious feelings of those so objecting, or 
     <lb/>
     shall be held immediately before the time fixed 
     <lb/>
     for the opening, or after the time fixed for the 
     <lb/>
     close of the daily work of the school ; and no 
     <lb/>
     children whose parents or guardians signify 
     <lb/>
     conscientious objections thereto, shall be re<lb break="no"/>quired to be present during such devotional ex<lb break="no"/>ercises. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>It seems to be taken for granted by the 
     <lb/>
     council of public instruction of Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>
     that there will be devotional exercises in 
     <lb/>
     the schools, and this is a provision to 
     <lb/>
     regulate these exercises. Now, this system 
     <lb/>
     has worked well in Nova Scotia for a good 
     <lb/>
     many years. There is no person there who 
     <lb/>
     has turned pale or become hysterical over 
     <lb/>
     it. Everything has gone well; and I have 
     <lb/>
     no doubt that when we adopt this system 
     <lb/>
     in the west, it will work well there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>I do not wish to weary the House with 
     <lb/>
     a speech of any length. Like my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend from Hunts (Mr. Black) I simply 
     <lb/>
     intended, when I rose to give a few reasons 
     <lb/>
     why I intend to support the measure now 
     <lb/>
     before the House. While other clauses of 
     <lb/>
     the Bill are of equal importance, I have not 
     <lb/>
     attempted to deal with anything except 
     <lb/>
     the educational clauses. The reasons why 
     <lb/>
     I intend to support this Bill and to vote 
     <lb/>
     against the amendment of the leader of the 
     <lb/>
     opposition, I desire to state briefly as fol<lb break="no"/>lows : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>First. Because it is an honourable and 
     <lb/>
     fair compromise of a very difficult and deli<lb break="no"/>cate question, and, while it satisfies to some 
     <lb/>
     extent the religious convictions of forty- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     one per cent of the people of Can<lb break="no"/>ada, it contains nothing that should be 
     <lb/>
     in any sense offensive to the religious views 
     <lb/>
     of the remaining forty-nine per cent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Second. Because the school system that 
     <lb/>
     we are now perpetuating is a school system 
     <lb/>
     that was adopted about thirteen years ago 
     <lb/>
     by the people of the Territories themselves ; 
     <lb/>
     that system has worked satisfactorily ever 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
     <fw type="num">5130</fw>
         
     since; and it may be fairly said to be an 
     <lb/>
     expression of the will of the people of the 
     <lb/>
     Territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Third. I am opposed to the amendment 
     <lb/>
     of the leader of the opposition because the 
     <lb/>
     effect of it is to leave the whole matter in 
     <lb/>
     a state of uncertainty, to give rise to dis<lb break="no"/>putes and litigation, and to destroy the 
     <lb/>
     peace and retard the progress of the new 
     <lb/>
     provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Fourth. I am opposed to the amendment 
     <lb/>
     of the leader of the opposition because it 
     <lb/>
     is a sheer evasion of the question at issue. 
     <lb/>
     If the words 'at the union' are to be held 
     <lb/>
     to mean 1905, then, by passing this amend<lb break="no"/>ment we should be fastening on the new 
     <lb/>
     provinces the system of clerical schools 
     <lb/>
     that the people abolished in 1892, a system 
     <lb/>
     to which I am determinedly opposed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Fifth. I am in favour of the educational 
     <lb/>
     clauses of this Bill because they give an 
     <lb/>
     opportunity to both Protestants and Catho<lb break="no"/>lics who hold religious convictions on this 
     <lb/>
     question to give religious instruction to 
     <lb/>
     their children for half an hour at the close 
     <lb/>
     of each school day without interfering with 
     <lb/>
     the national character of the school. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Sixth. I support the Bill because it defi<lb break="no"/>nitely settles this question once for all, and 
     <lb/>
     prevents the introduction into these western 
     <lb/>
     provinces of those painful racial and re<lb break="no"/>ligious quarrels that have disturbed the 
     <lb/>
     peace of the older provinces of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Seventh. I support the Bill because the 
     <lb/>
     schools to be established under this regula<lb break="no"/>tion must of necessity be free public schools, 
     <lb/>
     using only the authorized text-books, taught 
     <lb/>
     by regularly licensed teachers, inspected by 
     <lb/>
     the public school inspector, and in every 
     <lb/>
     respect under complete public control. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Eighth. I support the Bill because it pre<lb break="no"/>serves existing rights and prevents any feel<lb break="no"/>ing of injustice on the part of those who 
     <lb/>
     enjoyed this system for the past thirty 
     <lb/>
     years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Ninth. I support the Bill because the 
     <lb/>
     policy of the Liberal party to-day is con<lb break="no"/>sistent with the policy of the party in 1896. 
     <lb/>
     In 1896 the Liberal party stood for schools 
     <lb/>
     established by the people of Manitoba, and 
     <lb/>
     to-day they stand for schools established by 
     <lb/>
     the people of the Northwest. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Tenth. Because we ought to have the 
     <lb/>
     courage of our convictions on a question of 
     <lb/>
     this kind, and not, like the hon. leader of 
     <lb/>
     the opposition (Mr. R. L. Borden), take 
     <lb/>
     refuge behind legal technicalities. What do 
     <lb/>
     you think of the spectacle of the leader of a 
     <lb/>
     great party declaring that he has nothing 
     <lb/>
     to say in favour of separate schools, that he 
     <lb/>
     has nothing to say against separate schools, 
     <lb/>
     who confesses that he has absolutely no 
     <lb/>
     more opinion than a baby on a great ques<lb break="no"/>tion of this kind, and who contents himself 
     <lb/>
     With moving a resolution that bewilders 
     <lb/>
     everybody, and that he has not yet ventured 
     <lb/>
     to explain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Eleventh. I am in favour of this measure 
     <lb/>
     because it secures to every child in Alberta 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="5131" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-04-28_Page_5131.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">5131</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> 

     and Saskatchewan for all time to come a 
     <lb/>
     good common school education. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Twelfth. Because every other province 
     <lb/>
     that has come into confederation has carried 
     <lb/>
     in with it the educational system that ex<lb break="no"/>isted in the province at the time it came in. 
     <lb/>
     and there is no good reason why any differ<lb break="no"/>ent course should be adopted in the case of 
     <lb/>
     Saskatchewan and Alberta. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Now, Sir, I believe that we ought to get 
     <lb/>
     past these racial and religious quarrels. 
     <lb/>
     We are too near grown-up people to go on 
     <lb/>
     in the way that the old provinces went many 
     <lb/>
     years ago. I think the time is past for 
     <lb/>
     these things. I am of opinion, Sir, 
     <lb/>
     that Canada is destined to expand and 
     <lb/>
     grow, that there is a great future 
     <lb/>
     before this country during the century up<lb break="no"/>on which we have now entered, and that 
     <lb/>
     it is the duty of every patriotic Cana<lb break="no"/>dian to cease quarrelling one with another 
     <lb/>
     and to endeavour to develop the great re<lb break="no"/>sources that have been given to us. We 
     <lb/>
     have a great work to do, and we cannot 
     <lb/>
     afford, as the hon. member who last had the 
     <lb/>
     floor (Mr. Adamson) said, to spend our ener<lb break="no"/>gies in tearing one another in pieces. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve it is the duty of every patriotic Cana<lb break="no"/>dian to stand shoulder to shoulder to help 
     <lb/>
     build up on the northern half of this conti<lb break="no"/>nent a state worthy of ourselves, worthy of 
     <lb/>
     the great heritage that has been left to us, 
     <lb/>
     worthy of the splendid stock from which 
     <lb/>
     we have sprung, a state in which there will 
     <lb/>
     be justice for all, free scope for all, tolerance 
     <lb/>
     for all, and a fair reward for labour, and 
     <lb/>
     a new home from freedom. If this, 
     <lb/>
     Sir, is our destiny, as I believe it is, we 
     <lb/>
     cannot achieve it by internal strife and dis<lb break="no"/>cord, or by mutual hatred and distrust. Let 
     <lb/>
     us trample both under our feet, and let us 
     <lb/>
     stand by the right hon. gentleman who 
     <lb/>
     leads this House in the great task that he 
     <lb/>
     has set for himself of bringing order out 
     <lb/>
     of confusion and peace out of discord. break 
     <lb/>
     ing down the barriers that separate the 
     <lb/>
     various races that compose the people of 
     <lb/>
     this country and welding them together into 
     <lb/>
     one happy, prosperous and united people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MART1">Mr. A. MARTIN</persName> moved the adjournment <lb/> of the debate.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p>Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>On motion of Mr. Fielding. House adjourn<lb break="no"/>ed at 9.20 p.m. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
    </div>     </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>