<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1903-10-19"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1903-10-19">19 October 1903</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Ninth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
          <date when="1903"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
          <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="14287" to="14289"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-19_Page_14287.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-19_Page_14289.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-05">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-19_Page_14287">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-19_Page_14287.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-19_Page_14289">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-19_Page_14289.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="14287" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-19_Page_14287.jpg"/>
          
          <fw type="num">14287</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">14288</fw>
          
          
          
          
            <head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES ACT.</head>
            
            
            <p>House again in committee on Bill (No.<lb/>259) to amend the North-west Territories<lb/>Act.—The Minister of Justice.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SCOT2">Mr. SCOTT</persName> moved to add the following<lb/>clause to the Bill :<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Notwithstanding anything in the North-west<lb/>Territories Act, or any Act in amendment there<lb break="no"/>to, the legislative assembly may, by ordinance,<lb/>repeal the provisions of sections 49, 51, 53, 55,<lb/>64, 88, 89 and 90 of the said North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories Act as amended and re-enacted the said<lb/>provisions or substitute other provisions in lieu<lb/>thereof, but nothing in this section contained<lb/>shall be construed as giving to the legislative<lb/>assembly power to pass ordinances for the con<lb break="no"/>
    
    
            <cb/>
        
        
     stitution, organization or maintenance of 
     <lb/>courts of criminal jurisdiction, or respecting pro<lb break="no"/>cedure in criminal matters.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
            
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName>. The effect<lb/>would be to confer on the North-west assem<lb break="no"/>bly power to regulate all matters connected<lb/>with the civil jurisdiction of the province.<lb/>That is to say, they may determine the sit<lb break="no"/>tings of the court, the places where the<lb/>court is to sit, how often it is to sit : they<lb/>may provide for the sittings of the court in<lb/>banc or with a single judge; provide for the<lb/>division of the territory into judicial dis<lb break="no"/>tricts ; define the territorial jurisdiction of<lb/>the judges, and so on—all matters relating<lb/>to the civil organization of the court. I<lb/>think it is a step in the right direction.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Amendment agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SCOT2">Mr. SCOTT</persName> moved to add the following<lb/>clause to the Bill :<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Notwithstanding anything in the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories Act, or any Act in amendment<lb/>thereof, the legislative assembly may, by or<lb break="no"/>dinance, repeal the provisions of sections 7, 8,<lb/>9, 11, and 12 of chapter 19 of the statutes of<lb/>1888, and section 18 of chapter 17 of the sta<lb break="no"/>tutes of 1894, as that section is enacted by sec<lb break="no"/>tion 9 of chapter 28 of the statutes of 1897, and<lb/>re-enact the said provisions or substitute other<lb/>provisions in lieu thereof.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
            
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILL4">Mr. GOURLEY</persName>. This amendment seems<lb/>objectionable, not necessarily in the sub<lb break="no"/>ject matter, but in that it gives a local legis<lb break="no"/>lature power to repeal sections of a statute<lb/>passed by this parliament. There must sure<lb break="no"/>ly be some more logical way to get it than<lb/>that. It would hardly be dignified for us<lb/>to confer that power.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName>. I would<lb/>draw to the attention of my hon. friend (Mr.<lb/>Gourley) the fact that paragraph 4, now<lb/>under consideration, has reference to the<lb/>organization of the North-west council it<lb break="no"/>self, as the other paragraph we have been<lb/>discussing has reference to the organization<lb/>of the courts. Now, if we repeal the pro<lb break="no"/>visions and merely give authority to the<lb/>North-west council to make others, we leave<lb/>an interregnum during which some embar<lb break="no"/>rassing conditions might arise. By this<lb/>amendment we, in effect, say that in all<lb/>matters affecting the North-west assembly,<lb/>that body shall have the right either to<lb/>adopt what we have done or to repeal the<lb/>enactments which we have passed, and sub<lb break="no"/>stitute others. My hon. friend will see the<lb/>difficulty of adopting any other course.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILL4">Mr. GOURLEY</persName>. I see, but still it seems<lb/>that there ought to be some other way than<lb/>to give power to the local legislature to re<lb break="no"/>peal our enactments.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName>. It is a<lb/>little off the line, but my hon, friend will<lb/>see that it is not unconstitutional.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILL4">Mr. GOURLEY</persName>. I take it for granted<lb/>that we have the power to delegate our<lb/>authority. It is not so much the thing itself<lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="14289" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-19_Page_14289.jpg"/>
         
         
         <fw type="num">14289</fw> <fw type="dateline">OCTOBER 19, 1903</fw>
         
         
         as the mode of doing it that I call attention<lb/>to-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName>. The diffi<lb break="no"/>culty that my hon. friend suggests occurred<lb/>to my mind also, but it seems there is no<lb/>relief. Suppose that these provisions were<lb/>repealed. The North-west council may not<lb/>sit for months yet. Should a by-election<lb/>occur in the meantime, how is it to be pro<lb break="no"/>vided for ? It seemed to me better to main<lb break="no"/>tain the statute in these matters and simply<lb/>give the legislature power to provide for the<lb/>changes necessary.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILL4">Mr. GOURLEY</persName>. Has the hon. minister's<lb/>department considered this and come to the<lb/>conclusion that this is the only way in<lb/>which it can be done ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName>. That is<lb/>our view - this is the only way to avoid<lb/>a hiatus.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Amendment agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Bill, as amended, reported: read the third<lb/>time and passed.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>