<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1889-04-24"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1889-04-24">24 April 1889</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1889"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="1498" to="1498"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-04-24_Page_01498.html"/> 
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-04-24_Page_01498">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-04-24_Page_01498.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1498" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1889-04-24_Page_01498.jpg"/>
            
            
           <fw type="num">1498</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES.</fw> <fw type="dateline">APRIL 24,</fw>
           
   
          
     <head rendition="simple:centre">N. W. T ACT AMENDMENT.</head> 
    
   
            <p>
     On the order for second reading of Bill (No 136) to con<lb break="no"/>solidate and amend the Act respecting the North-West 
     <lb/>
     Territories, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. When I introduced this Bill for the 
     <lb/>
     special purpose of consolidating the three Acts now in ex<lb break="no"/>istence, my principal reason was that last Session the 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Assembly consolidated the North-West Ordin<lb break="no"/>ances, and I thought it would be very convenient to have 
     <lb/>
     the North-West Territories Act also consolidated. How<lb break="no"/>ever, some hon. gentlemen opposite thought it was too late 
     <lb/>
     in the Session to put through this Bill; but I thought, sub<lb break="no"/>sequently, that if they would agree to raise no question on 
     <lb/>
     the clauses not amended, we might possibly be able to put 
     <lb/>
     through the amendment. Since that, several hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men have informed me, that probably there would be con<lb break="no"/>siderable discussion on some of the old clauses of the Bill 
     <lb/>
     which I do not propose to amend, and, as the amendments 
     <lb/>
     I did propose are not of a serious character, and several hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen on both sides have expressed a wish that, if pos<lb break="no"/>sible, I might allow the measure to remain over for another 
     <lb/>
     Session, I beg to move that the order be discharged. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, order discharged, and Bill withdrawn. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>