<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1892-05-30" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1892-05-30">30 May 1892</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, Second Session</title>.
<date when="1892"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="3062" to="3088"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03061.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03063.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03065.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03067.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03069.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03071.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03073.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03075.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03077.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03079.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03081.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03083.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03085.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03087.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-23">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03061"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03061.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03063"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03063.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03065"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03065.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03067"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03067.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03069"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03069.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03071"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03071.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03073"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03073.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03075"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03075.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03077"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03077.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03079"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03079.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03081"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03081.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03083"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03083.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03085"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03085.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03087"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03087.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="3061" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03061.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">3061</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 30, 1892.]</fw> <fw type="num">3062</fw> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">EDUCATION AND LANGUAGES IN THE <lb/>
NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES.</head> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ARMS3">Mr. ARMSTRONG</persName> moved: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>That it is expedient that power be given to the Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive Assembly of the North-West Territories, after the <lb/>
next general election of members of said Assembly, to <lb/>
deal with all matters pertaining to education and the use <lb/>
of dual languages in the courts and in the proceedings of <lb/>
the said Assembly: providing, however, that no school <lb/>
section, as at present constituted, shall be interfered with <lb/>
without the consent of the parties composing such section. <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>He said: Mr. Speaker, in moving this resolution, <lb/>
I wish to say that I am not moving it for any party <lb/>
or any set of men. I consulted no one in preparing <lb/>
the resolution, and I have not been asked by any <lb/>
member of this House to move it. I have taken <lb/>
this action altogether upon my own responsibility. <lb/>
It may be asked: Why not let the matter rest? <lb/>
Sir, the matter will not rest. It is one of those <lb/>
questions that, like Banquo's ghost, will not down, <lb/>
and session after session we have to meet it, and it <lb/>
is neither the part of good statesmanship nor of <lb/>
sound public policy to leave the question in abey<lb break="no"/>ance. I do think that there is surely some way <lb/>
in which the question can be satisfactorily settled <lb/>
and set at rest forever. In moving this resolution <lb/>
I may say that I am not tied down to its terms, <lb/>
because any just and honourable and fair means of <lb/>
settling the difficulty by whomsoever moved will <lb/>
have my hearty support. In the resolution it will <lb/>

<pb n="3063" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03063.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3063</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3064</fw> 

be seen that I take the ground that the matter <lb/>
should be left altogether to the people themselves to <lb/>
settle. That is the ground that I have always taken, <lb/>
and I am confirmed in this view of the case by <lb/>
the opinion of my hon. friend the member for <lb/>
Assiniboia (Mr. Davin). Two years ago, when <lb/>
the question of the dual languages was before the <lb/>
House, that hon. gentleman moved an amendment <lb/>
to the Bill to leave the matter entirely in the hands <lb/>
of the people of the North-West Territories. I <lb/>
approved of his amendment and I intended to vote <lb/>
for it if it had been reached; and, Sir, what was <lb/>
good in the case of the dual languages, I believe <lb/>
would be equality good in the case of separate <lb/>
Schools, and that the only sound policy is to leave <lb/>
the matter for the people of the North-West to <lb/>
deal with. There is another matter introduced in <lb/>
this resolution, and that is that the school sec<lb break="no"/>tions of the North-West as at present constituted <lb/>
shall not be interfered with without the consent <lb/>
of the parties composing the section. The reason <lb/>
that I was induced to admit that clause in the <lb/>
resolution was because a friend of mine pleaded <lb/>
that certain parties had established school sections <lb/>
there on the strength of the law as it at present <lb/>
stands, that in that way a sort of vested right had <lb/>
accrued, and that it was unfair to interfere with <lb/>
these rights. I agreed with him in that, and I <lb/>
consented to allow that clause to be inserted in <lb/>
the resolution. I know that there are some emin<lb break="no"/>ent men in this House and out of it who do not <lb/>
hold the doctrine of provincial rights. I remem<lb break="no"/>ber that two years ago the hon. member for North <lb/>
Simcoe (Mr. Mccarthy), speaking in the city of <lb/>
Montreal, made use of the following language:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"We are told that the Liberal party has always taken <lb/>
for their motto, that no matter what the Local Legisla<lb break="no"/>tures may do, so long as they act strictly within their <lb/>
power, the Dominion authorities would not exercise any <lb/>
interference. In other words, we have forced upon us by <lb/>
the introduction of such a policy, the pernicious doctrine <lb/>
of States Rights: a principle which has been crushed out <lb/>
in the United States by the most gigantic war which the <lb/>
country has ever witnessed." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>Now, Sir, knowing the intelligence of the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman and his knowledge of constitutional history, <lb/>
it is hard to believe that he was perfectly sincere <lb/>
when he made that assertion. What are the facts? <lb/>
In the rebellion there was only one single question <lb/>
of state rights at issue. It had been held from very <lb/>
early times by eminent jurists in the United States, <lb/>
and amongst others by Jefferson and Calhoun, that <lb/>
as the states had come into the federation as <lb/>
independent states, they retained to themselves <lb/>
the right to Secede for cause if they saw fit; The <lb/>
great question at issue, then, was whether one <lb/>
or more states had the right to secede. The south<lb break="no"/>ern States contended that they had the right and <lb/>
acted upon it; the northern States contended that <lb/>
they had not the right, and determined to prevent <lb/>
them acting upon it; and the question was <lb/>
settled, not by an appeal to reason, law or <lb/>
equity, but simply by the largest battalions <lb/>
and the heaviest artillery; and the question of <lb/>
right or wrong remains unsettled to the present <lb/>
day. But what I want to insist upon is this, that <lb/>
not another single state right was ever called in <lb/>
question; and if there is one part of public policy <lb/>
more than another which the people of the United <lb/>
States are united in supporting, it is the doctrine <lb/>
of state rights. If those rights were to be infring<lb break="no"/>ed, north and south alike would be determined to <lb/>

<cb/>

maintain them, and would fight to the death <lb/>
rather than allow them to be sacrificed. And, Sir, <lb/>
they are wise in doing so. Extended over a large <lb/>
area of country, with different interests and with <lb/>
different questions coming before them, they can <lb/>
only hope to maintain the union by a strict adher<lb break="no"/>ence to the doctrine of state rights. And, Sir, is <lb/>
this principle less important in the country in which <lb/>
we dwell? We occupy an enormous extent of terri<lb break="no"/>tory; our country is peopled by different races, <lb/>
with different feelings, religions and interests: and <lb/>
if we are going to be a united and prosper<lb break="no"/>ous people, I believe we can only be so by a <lb/>
strict adherence to the doctrine of provincial <lb/>
rights. Now, Sir, I wish at the outset to <lb/>
point out that I do not ask that either the lan<lb break="no"/>guage or the schools of the people in the North-West <lb/>
shall be in any way interfered with. When we <lb/>
speak about separate schools, we are apt to think <lb/>
of schools established by people of the Catholic <lb/>
faith; but if you look at the Act under which <lb/>
those schools were established, you will find that <lb/>
the same provision is made for every religious de<lb break="no"/>nomination; and is it not a fact that we have <lb/>
schools for at least four different religions denomi<lb break="no"/>nations in the North-West, each one of which re<lb break="no"/>ceives public support? Again, I say I have no in<lb break="no"/>tention whatever of interfering with either the <lb/>
separate schools or the language. All I ask is that <lb/>
the people of the North-West shall have the power <lb/>
to settle that matter, which rightfully belongs to <lb/>
them, for themselves. I may here say, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, that I was one of those who opposed the <lb/>
establishment of separate schools in the Province <lb/>
of Ontario when that was first agitated, and I did <lb/>
it because I was in favour of a uniform public <lb/>
school system. I believe that it was for the ad<lb break="no"/>vantage of the country that such a system should <lb/>
be established and maintained. However, when <lb/>
once the law gave permission for the establishment <lb/>
of separate schools, and when once they were es<lb break="no"/>tablished by law, from that day to this I <lb/>
have done, in my own humble way, every<lb break="no"/>thing that lay in my power to make those <lb/>
schools as efficient as possible. If they had <lb/>
to exist it was the part of good policy, <lb/>
the part of justice and right, to make them <lb/>
just as efficient as they could possibly be made. I <lb/>
am free to confess that the law has not worked the <lb/>
great harm in Ontario that was anticipated from <lb/>
it. I believe that in towns and cities it has done <lb/>
no harm at all; in the rural districts the only harm <lb/>
it has done has been that it has compelled the <lb/>
people to maintain two weak schools instead of one <lb/>
strong one; and in the public schools of, Ontario, so <lb/>
far from the rights of any religious body being <lb/>
interfered with, those rights have been strictly <lb/>
respected, with the result that the majority of the <lb/>
children of Catholic parents in the Province of <lb/>
Ontario attend the public schools to-day. I know <lb/>
that it is objected that some religious denomina<lb break="no"/>tions wish to have religious teaching in the public <lb/>
schools, and maintain that that can only be had <lb/>
from denominational school sections. Perhaps, Sir, <lb/>
I am not able sufficiently to appreciate that objec<lb break="no"/>tion. Many members in this House know that I <lb/>
gain one of those who do not believe that it is the <lb/>
duty of the state to teach religion at all—that that <lb/>
duty devolves upon the churches. Now, what <lb/>
I want to point out is that the public schools <lb/>
of our country are from the foundation to the <lb/>

<pb n="3065" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03065.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3065</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 30, 1892.]</fw> <fw type="num">3066</fw>

topmost stone altogether state institutions. The <lb/>
school section is formed under laws enacted <lb/>
by the state; the school-house is built by men <lb/>
amenable to the state; the money to pay for the <lb/>
building is collected by the state, and is paid over <lb/>
to the contractors by the state. The teachers in <lb/>
our public schools are men and women examined <lb/>
with regard to their fitness for the position by <lb/>
men appointed by the state, under rules prescribed <lb/>
by the state: they are appointed to their positions <lb/>
by the state, and their salaries are paid out of <lb/>
money collected by the state, under pains and pen<lb break="no"/>alties imposed by the state. So that from the top <lb/>
to the bottom our public schools are simply and <lb/>
solely state institutions; and holding, as I do, that <lb/>
it is not the duty of the state to teach religion, I <lb/>
am opposed to establishing a public school for that <lb/>
purpose by the state. Some may be inclined to <lb/>
ask if I am opposed to religious teaching altogether <lb/>
in the. schools. Well, there is one form of it that <lb/>
you cannot prevent. I happen to have had oppor<lb break="no"/>tunities of becoming acquainted with a great many <lb/>
of the teachers, both male and female, in our own <lb/>
Province of Ontario, and I say deliberately that I <lb/>
do not believe that a better class of men and women <lb/>
exists in the country; and if any one, man or woman, <lb/>
who accepts the position of public school teacher is <lb/>
under the influence of true religion, they will teach <lb/>
that religion whether they are compelled by the <lb/>
law to do it or not. They will teach it, not in <lb/>
dogmas or in set lessons given to the scholars, but <lb/>
they will teach it by giving good advice, by restrain<lb break="no"/>ing the evil they see and encouraging the good, and, <lb/>
most strongly and most powerfully of all, by the <lb/>
example they will set to the scholars. Unfortu<lb break="no"/>nately, our teachers are not all of that class or <lb/>
character: and I ask hon. gentlemen here who have <lb/>
children, if there is a teacher in their section who <lb/>
scoffs or laughs at religion, whether they want such <lb/>
a teacher to teach religion to their children? If they <lb/>
do, I can only say for myself, Heaven save my child<lb break="no"/>ren from such religious teaching. I have another <lb/>
objection to separate schools, and it has always been <lb/>
a very strong one, although you may, if you wish, <lb/>
call it a sentimental objection. I happen to have a <lb/>
few people of the Roman Catholic faith in my riding, <lb/>
and they happen to live in my own township and <lb/>
to be my own neighbours; and I say that no better <lb/>
neighbours any man need wish few—good, honest, <lb/>
upright people, ready to perform all the duties of <lb/>
neighbourhood and citizenship. I say again no <lb/>
better class of people could a man wish to live <lb/>
amongst. But the point I want to make is this. Their <lb/>
children are just as good as mine, and I hope mine are <lb/>
as good as theirs, and I do not want to see a wall of <lb/>
separation built up between them. I do not want <lb/>
the implication to exist that there is some disabil<lb break="no"/>ity, either on the one side or the other, or some <lb/>
reason why they should not associate together. I <lb/>
do not want it to be inferred that one side is, in <lb/>
some way or other, not the equal of the other, and <lb/>
that they cannot be allowed to grow up and be <lb/>
educated together. No; I want them to grow up <lb/>
together, to become acquainted with one another, <lb/>
to understand each other's feelings and aspirations, <lb/>
to be prepared, when they go out, to take their <lb/>
place in governing the country, to be able to see <lb/>
eye to eye, and to live together in harmony for the <lb/>
well-being of their common country. That is the <lb/>
strongest. objection I have to separate schools. And <lb/>
now with regard to the question of dual languages. <lb/>

<cb/>

I wish to say at the outset that I have not the <lb/>
slightest sympathy with, but, on the contrary, hold <lb/>
in utter abomination the idea that it is the duty of <lb/>
the majority of this country to stamp out the <lb/>
language of the minority. That, I believe, would <lb/>
be neither good policy nor good statesmanship. <lb/>
Nor do I believe that mixed races are any <lb/>
source of weakness to the country. On the <lb/>
contrary, I consider them a source of strength. <lb/>
I need only point to the mother country, to <lb/>
Great Britain; and where, I ask, is there a <lb/>
country in which the people are of more mixed <lb/>
blood? Had the attempt been made which it <lb/>
was sought to make two or three years ago here, <lb/>
to stamp out in England the language and institu<lb break="no"/>tions of the conquered, would the English people <lb/>
occupy the place they do to-day? Suppose that <lb/>
Norman William, when he conquered the Anglo-<lb break="yes"/>Saxons, determined, as some very advanced legisla<lb break="no"/>tors of the present day want to determine, that it <lb/>
was expedient, in the interests of the national <lb/>
unity of the country, that there should be unity of <lb/>
language among the people, and endeavoured to <lb/>
stamp out the Anglo-Saxon, do you think he would <lb/>
have succeeded? Norman William was not such a <lb/>
fool as to try it. He knew these things were under <lb/>
the operation of natural laws more potent than <lb/>
any human laws, and was perfectly willing to leave <lb/>
these laws to their own operation. And what is <lb/>
the result today? Why, the very language we <lb/>
use in this House and in which the majority of us <lb/>
express our views is not the language of any one <lb/>
people in the British Isles. As a learned philologist <lb/>
said, while the Anglo-Saxon may be considered as <lb/>
the foundation and the mortar that connects the <lb/>
fabric together, yet the fabric itself is built up of <lb/>
contributions from almost every language, ancient <lb/>
and modern; and if the attempt had been made to <lb/>
make any one of these languages permanent, do <lb/>
you think for a moment that Britain would have <lb/>
been the country she is to-day? I remember, <lb/>
two years ago, when my hon. friend from North <lb/>
Bruce (Mr. McNeill) was speaking on this question, <lb/>
that he instanced the people in the north of Scot<lb break="no"/>land as an example of the necessity for unity of <lb/>
language; and I may say here, and I think the <lb/>
House will agree with me, the great vigour, intel<lb break="no"/>lectual activity and the push and perseverance of <lb/>
the people of Great Britain to-day is largely due to <lb/>
the fact that they are a people of mixed blood. <lb/>
Any one who has studied the laws of heredity <lb/>
knows that the kingly men and queenly women <lb/>
have in all days been the result of the union of <lb/>
different but cognate races. We find it has had <lb/>
that effect in Great Britain and wherever else such <lb/>
a state of things has existed. The hon. member <lb/>
for North Bruce instanced the case of the high<lb break="no"/>landers of Scotland and the feuds which existed <lb/>
between them and the people of the lowlands, and <lb/>
he said if they had all spoken the one tongue these <lb/>
feuds would not have existed. Now, I have always <lb/>
a great respect for my hon. friend, because I know <lb/>
he is thoroughly honest, but I must take the liberty <lb/>
of differing from him in the conclusion he drew. <lb/>
I am very doubtful if any such result would have <lb/>
followed the speaking of the same language. Why, <lb/>
at that time when the bitterest feuds existed and <lb/>
the hottest fighting was going on between the two <lb/>
peoples, the very same thing was taking place be<lb break="no"/>tween the south of Scotland and the north of Eng<lb break="no"/>land, where the people spoke the same tongue. But <lb/>

<pb n="3067" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03067.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3067</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3068</fw> 

suppose we grant for a moment that it would have <lb/>
been better had the people in the north of Scot<lb break="no"/>land spoken the same language as the people in the <lb/>
lowlands, in the south of Scotland, could you <lb/>
have compelled them to do so? Suppose we had <lb/>
had then some very wise legislators, men of <lb/>
advanced liberal opinions,who thought it was ex<lb break="no"/>pedient, in the interests of the national unity of <lb/>
the country, that there should be community of <lb/>
language among the people of Scotland, and sup<lb break="no"/>pose they had tried to compel these people in the <lb/>
north of Scotland to speak the language of the <lb/>
south, do you think for a moment they would <lb/>
have succeeded? I know something of these people, <lb/>
having lived amongst them all my days on most <lb/>
intimate terms with them, and I know that had <lb/>
you attempted anything of the sort, you would <lb/>
never have been successful. You might have cut <lb/>
them to pieces, inch by inch, you might have made <lb/>
a desert and called it peace, but you never could <lb/>
have compelled them to give up their language. <lb/>
And why should such an attempt ever be made <lb/>
with any people? Sir, it is a God-given birthright, <lb/>
the language a man or a woman speaks, the lan<lb break="no"/>guage they learned at their mother's knee; and no <lb/>
state or no man has the right to attempt to stamp <lb/>
it out. Are you to suppose for a moment that our <lb/>
French-speaking neighbours of the Province of <lb/>
Quebec and other parts of the Dominion <lb/>
are less tenacious of their national rights <lb/>
than the people of the north of Scotland? <lb/>
No, I believe that they feel as strongly the rights <lb/>
which they enjoy, that they have the same senti<lb break="no"/>ments these people have, and will resist to the <lb/>
death every attempt to suppress their language. I <lb/>
believe it would be the most foolish, the most <lb/>
suicidal thing for the country, the most arbitrary <lb/>
thing any country ever attempted, to try to stamp <lb/>
out their language. I do not wish to detain the <lb/>
House any longer. I say again I believe it is the <lb/>
part of good statesmanship and sound policy to try <lb/>
and find a solution of this question, and I say that, <lb/>
if we are honestly desirous to do it, we can <lb/>
succeed. We have rather a difficult country here <lb/>
to govern, separated one part from the other by <lb/>
thousands of miles, with different interests to <lb/>
conciliate, different races to work with, different <lb/>
languages amongst us—all these things are, perhaps, <lb/>
hinderances in the way of governing the country, <lb/>
but I believe, when we meet these in an enlight<lb break="no"/>ened, honest and intelligent spirit, there is no <lb/>
danger that we shall not succeed. If we apply to <lb/>
others the golden rule to do to them what we wish <lb/>
to be done to ourselves, to put ourselves in their <lb/>
places, and to try to see how it would be if we <lb/>
looked at it from their standpoint, and to deal <lb/>
with them accordingly, it will make us a contented <lb/>
and a prosperous country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:WALL1">Mr. WALLACE</persName>. I am sorry the hon. member <lb/>
for Middlesex (Mr. Armstrong), when making this <lb/>
motion, has limited it as he has done. If the <lb/>
principles he has avowed in his speech are correct, <lb/>
is resolution does not bear out that speech, but is <lb/>
rather contradictory. I think that this clause in <lb/>
his resolution: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Providing, however, that no school section, as at <lb/>
present constituted shall be interfered with without the <lb/>
    consent of the parties composing such section"— <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>is one which will lead to difficulties of very many <lb/>
kinds, that will cause legislation to be very difficult <lb/>
enact and will defeat the very object be pro<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

poses in the speech we have just listened to. I <lb/>
think the time has come in the North-West when <lb/>
they may safely be given all those powers which <lb/>
have been given to the Legislatures of the other <lb/>
provinces, and more especially with reference to <lb/>
this question of education. We have in those <lb/>
Territories a people who are certainly not inferior <lb/>
to their brethren in the other provinces of the <lb/>
Dominion. They are largely the pick of the older <lb/>
provinces, the enterprising young men who have <lb/>
gone from the other provinces, have built up homes <lb/>
there, intend to reside there, and during the <lb/>
few years they have been there have given <lb/>
exhibitions of energy and intelligence which are <lb/>
the pride and admiration of Canadians of every <lb/>
part of this Dominion. It is not right to limit the <lb/>
power of these men to regulate their local affairs, <lb/>
and the matters relating to education which every <lb/>
province in the Dominion exercises fully, barring <lb/>
those restrictions which have been placed upon <lb/>
those matters in Ontario and Quebec, restrictions <lb/>
which many of us in Ontario, not only Protestants, <lb/>
but many members of the Roman Catholic church, <lb/>
regret, that these separate schools have been <lb/>
established and confirmed in our province. The <lb/>
right to deal with education is one that the Con<lb break="no"/>federation Act specifically gives to the various <lb/>
Local Legislatures. They are now laying the foun<lb break="no"/>dation of their educational system in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West. Powers that may be properly exercised <lb/>
some years hence may be a good deal more safely <lb/>
and properly given, I believe, to those Territories <lb/>
to-day. They are laying the foundations of their <lb/>
educational system, but if certain restrictions are <lb/>
placed upon their powers, then, after a larger <lb/>
population has gone in there and they have perhaps <lb/>
been established in separate provinces or given the <lb/>
complete powers of Local Legislatures, this question <lb/>
which might now be settled without diffi<lb break="no"/>culty, will cause discord and disunion as it <lb/>
is causing to-day in the Province of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba. I think this Parliament at this time   <lb/>
will be doing a wise act in handing over the <lb/>
complete powers in regard to education to the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Assembly. We need have no fear that the <lb/>
North-West Assembly will not legislate wisely and <lb/>
well. They are interested. We cannot say that <lb/>
we only have the interest of the North-West at <lb/>
heart. The men who are living there, who are <lb/>
devising schemes for the opening up of that country, <lb/>
have a deeper and more intelligent interest and a <lb/>
wider knowledge of these matters than we have <lb/>
here, representing every portion of the Dominion. <lb/>
We will therefore be doing our duty, we will have <lb/>
the blessings of people yet unborn, if we give the <lb/>
full powers in regard to educational matters to the <lb/>
Legislature of the North-West Territories. Then, <lb/>
with reference to the question of the language, two <lb/>
years ago we passed a resolution which was con<lb break="no"/>sidered a compromise measure, but was endorsed <lb/>
very heartily by members of this House. That was <lb/>
brought into force by legislation during the last <lb/>
session. I think that legislation, though not going <lb/>
as far as I would wish to go myself, was in the right <lb/>
direction, and, as it was a compromise measure <lb/>
largely meeting the views of those who think as I <lb/>
do, it received no opposition from us. I think per<lb break="no"/>haps that clause might have been left as it <lb/>
was. It was a compromise, it was answering the <lb/>
purpose, because I think the question of the lan<lb break="no"/>guage under the recent legislation will solve <lb/>

<pb n="3069" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03069.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3069</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 30, 1892.]</fw> <fw type="num">3070</fw>

itself. If it is the interest of the people that it <lb/>
should survive, it will survive; if it is their inter<lb break="no"/>est in the North-West that it should die out and <lb/>
become obsolete, it will become obsolete, and I <lb/>
think that might have been allowed to stand on <lb/>
the Statute-book as it is now. But, in regard to <lb/>
the other matter, I feel more strongly than ever <lb/>
that we will be making a great mistake if we re<lb break="no"/>fuse now, when the opportunity occurs, to enact <lb/>
legislation in regard to education in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories, which will settle difficulties <lb/>
which will otherwise inevitably arise, which will <lb/>
cause heart-burnings, trouble and disagreement in <lb/>
the North-West, and I, therefore, move that all the <lb/>
words after "That" in the motion be omitted and <lb/>
the following inserted:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>In the opinion of this House, the Legislative Assem<lb break="no"/>bly of the North-West Territories should be empowered <lb/>
to deal with all matters relating to education in the said <lb/>
Territories. <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. McMULLEN</persName>. I desire to say a few words <lb/>
upon this very important question. It has been <lb/>
several times before Parliament; on several oc<lb break="no"/>casions we have discussed the whole question with <lb/>
regard to the dual language in the North-West, <lb/>
and also in regard to separate schools. Now, for <lb/>
many years back the question of separate schools, <lb/>
not only in the North-West but in some of the <lb/>
Maritime Provinces, has caused a great deal of <lb/>
strife and bitterness, and has given considerable <lb/>
trouble to the Government, and to members of <lb/>
Parliament generally in dealing with it. For my <lb/>
part, had I been in the House at the time the <lb/>
North-West Act was passed, I do not think I <lb/>
would have given my sanction to a full-fledged <lb/>
system of separate schools being established, in <lb/>
that country. My impression is that under the <lb/>
circumstances it was imprudent. At the same <lb/>
time, we know well that in Ontario where <lb/>
separate schools have been in existence for many <lb/>
years, the Catholic population of that province, as <lb/>
was stated by the hon. gentleman who moved this <lb/>
motion, have not taken advantage of that system <lb/>
in many cases, and we find that they are sending <lb/>
their children in increased numbers to the common <lb/>
schools. Now, I do not think that it is an easy mat<lb break="no"/>ter to wipe out by law anything that was looked <lb/>
upon as a privilege by a certain class of the commun<lb break="no"/>ity; I have never read, in fact, where such a privi<lb break="no"/>lege has been abolished by arbitrary enactment of this <lb/>
kind. People belonging to the Catholic faith have <lb/>
certain conscientious convictions of their own; they <lb/>
claim that it is their right and their duty to give <lb/>
their children a certain amount of religious educa<lb break="no"/>tion in connection with secular education. I do <lb/>
not wish for a moment to challenge their convic<lb break="no"/>tions upon that point. The fact of the matter <lb/>
is, in my humble opinion, we are going too far at <lb/>
the present day, in our educational institutions, in <lb/>
the direction of secularism. I differ from my hon. <lb/>
friend who made this motion, in that I believe that <lb/>
if we had a little more religious instruction in our <lb/>
common schools, it would be better for our rising <lb/>
population. Now, with regard to those schools in <lb/>
the North-West, as I said before, it may possibly <lb/>
have been an error to encourage their establish<lb break="no"/>ment; at the same time, they are there. While I <lb/>
am willing to consent to the full exercise of all <lb/>
powers by any province that are duly exercised by <lb/>
other provinces, at the same time there is no rule <lb/>
without its exception, and if any exception at all <lb/>

<cb/>

should be made to this rule, it should be to protect <lb/>
the conscientious convictions of a minority. Now, <lb/>
these schools have been established there, and while <lb/>
I would have preferred to see a partly common school <lb/>
system established, I would rather a thousand times <lb/>
have separate schools than to drive out religious <lb/>
teaching altogether from these schools. I would <lb/>
favour such a curriculum in our common schools as <lb/>
would allow every class to take advantage of them. <lb/>
If our Catholic people object to their children <lb/>
attending such a school, I would rather a thousand <lb/>
times consent to separate schools than to abolish <lb/>
religious teaching altogether. That is my view <lb/>
with regard to separate schools. Now, I am quite <lb/>
willing, as I said before, to coax our Catholic <lb/>
friends out of the use of these schools, and to in<lb break="no"/>duce them to come in with the rest of the com<lb break="no"/>munity and educate their children along with ours. <lb/>
If they are not willing, however, to do so, if they <lb/>
claim, as they have a right to do, the privilege of <lb/>
educating their children in their own schools and <lb/>
teaching them certain dogmas of their own church, <lb/>
I do not wish for a moment to deprive them of that <lb/>
right. I would claim that right myself, and am <lb/>
willing to accord it to them. Now, let us look at <lb/>
the condition of things in some of the states that <lb/>
have been referred to by my hon. friend. I think <lb/>
the school population of the State of New York is <lb/>
about 80,000 between the ages of five and sixteen. <lb/>
I have heard it stated on good authority that 200,<lb break="no"/>000 of these children never attend a Sabbath school, <lb/>
never receive any religious instruction in the <lb/>
family, and, perhaps, never hear the word God <lb/>
mentioned unless in profanity. Now, these parents <lb/>
have no desire to send their children to a Sabbath <lb/>
school or to any place where they would get <lb/>
religious instruction. Would it not be a <lb/>
hundred times better if these children got a <lb/>
sprinkling of religious instruction in the common <lb/>
school rather than none at all? What a magnifi<lb break="no"/>cent regiment for his Satanic Majesty to have <lb/>
such a large number of children in one state from <lb/>
among whom to get recruits for murderers, for <lb/>
thieves, for robbers and for suicides—for that is <lb/>
the result of a secular education, if we are to trust <lb/>
the public prints of the United States. I think it <lb/>
is better, in my opinion, that we should even <lb/>
consent to a separate school system than that <lb/>
we should have no religion taught in the schools at <lb/>
all. We have in the Province of Ontario, a model <lb/>
school system, which is lauded throughout the <lb/>
British Empire, and has been referred to in other <lb/>
countries as well. These, even, who have differed <lb/>
with the men who established that system, have <lb/>
taken the opportunity on several occasions to <lb/>
praise our school system in Ontario. We have in <lb/>
that province separate schools; they are under <lb/>
the same inspection as our common schools. The <lb/>
teachers in those schools must receive their certifi<lb break="no"/>cates at the hands of the same examiners as those <lb/>
who teach in the Protestant schools. They have <lb/>
got to conduct the schools much in the same way <lb/>
as the other schools are conducted; but, they are <lb/>
allowed certain privileges in the teaching of the <lb/>
Catholic catechism, I presume, and other things that <lb/>
are recognized as necessary by the Catholic Church. <lb/>
That is about the only difference between the <lb/>
separate schools and the common schools, so far as <lb/>
I can learn. Now, we are getting along in the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Ontario without any particular friction. I <lb/>
know that in the town in which I live myself, there <lb/>
    
<pb n="3071" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03071.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3071</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3072</fw> 

was sometime ago a separate school, but there is <lb/>
none today. The reason is that the Catholic people <lb/>
in that section decided that their children would, <lb/>
perhaps, get a better education in our common <lb/>
schools; at least they decided to take advantage of <lb/>
the privileges that were offered them, and they have <lb/>
virtually dropped their separate schools and are <lb/>
now sending their children to our common schools, <lb/>
and I hear of no complaint. Now, I have not the <lb/>
slightest doubt that if an agitation had been got up <lb/>
in the Province of Ontario to take from these people <lb/>
the right to have separate schools, the probabilities <lb/>
are that we would have a separate school in my <lb/>
town to-day. Wherever you force by legislation <lb/>
people to part with a privilege, then you generally <lb/>
find they resent that action. I understand that <lb/>
in the Province of Nova Scotia there is no separate <lb/>
school system. I should like to know if separate <lb/>
schools are not established there? I am informed <lb/>
that such is the case. I raise no objection to giving <lb/>
the people that privilege if they want it. I think the <lb/>
people of Nova Scotia are acting wisely in given <lb/>
the Catholics that privilege if they ask for it as <lb/>
their conscientious right, because it is not right to <lb/>
trample on the concientions convictions of any <lb/>
class. A few words with respect to the dual <lb/>
language. My reason for voting for the Bill intro<lb break="no"/>duced by the hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. <lb/>
McCarthy) was in order to reach the question of <lb/>
the dual language. I do not wish for one moment <lb/>
to interfere with the right of any man to use any <lb/>
language that is his birthright, that has been used <lb/>
by him from infancy, I do not think the remarks <lb/>
of the hon. member were at all in point on this <lb/>
question. I do not think it was the intention of the <lb/>
hon. member fer North Simcoe in his Bill to declare <lb/>
that no man should be allowed to speak French; I <lb/>
think the only intention was to prevent the neces<lb break="no"/>sity of having all proceedings published in French <lb/>
and English. I have been led to understand that <lb/>
this is the law now. For example, if a subpoena <lb/>
was issued to a man, under the present terms of <lb/>
the North-West Act he would have the right to <lb/>
demand that it be served on him printed in English <lb/>
and French. I do not think that is necessary. <lb/>
There are only 1,500 people in the North-West <lb/>
whose language is French. For the sake of that <lb/>
number, I do not think it is right that we should <lb/>
be put to the expense of printing the entire pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings of the North-West Council and all legal <lb/>
documents both in English and French. Moreover, <lb/>
very great difficulty might arise sometimes. If <lb/>
we permit the proceedings in court to be con<lb break="no"/>ducted in either language, I can easily imagine <lb/>
that a lawyer might commence to address <lb/>
an English jury in the French language, <lb/>
and it would be very awkward if they did not <lb/>
understand what he said. I do not think it is <lb/>
necessary that we should continue that system. <lb/>
While I am willing to allow the people in the <lb/>
North-West the right to use their own language <lb/>
in their own families, and the right to have inter<lb break="no"/>preters in court if they cannot speak English, it is <lb/>
absurd to continue the present condition of things <lb/>
and publish all proceedings in the North-West <lb/>
Council in both languages when there is such a <lb/>
very limited French population there. When the <lb/>
North-West Act was passed it was perhaps thought <lb/>
that there might be a very large influx of popula<lb break="no"/>tion from the Province of Quebec or from France <lb/>
itself, but this has not proved to be the case, and <lb/>

<cb/>

in fact a great many of the people from Quebec go <lb/>
across to the United States instead of to our Cana<lb break="no"/>dian North-Wst. If the French-Canadians poured <lb/>
in in very large numbers and claimed the right to <lb/>
use their language in the courts and in general pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings, I would not deny it to them, but to go to <lb/>
this expense for the sake of 1,500 people is absurd. <lb/>
For this reason, I am willing to vote to eliminate <lb/>
the French language, and at the same time I am <lb/>
ready to grant the North-West every provincial <lb/>
right to which the people are fairly entitled. <lb/>
But in regard to the proposal to abolish schools <lb/>
which have been established there, and main<lb break="no"/>tained by people who may have one there for the <lb/>
purpose of taking advantage of them, I cannot <lb/>
consent to wipe out these schools by a ma<lb break="no"/>jority vote unless the people were disposed to <lb/>
part with the privilege they now enjoy. Of course <lb/>
we have Protestant schools of several denomina<lb break="no"/>tions there. I believe there are Methodist schools, <lb/>
and I understand a deputation came down here <lb/>
and waited on the Government for the purpose of <lb/>
obtaining a grant for a school, perhaps for an In<lb break="no"/>dian school. There are also Presbyterian and <lb/>
Baptist Schools. It is not necessary that all these <lb/>
different schools should exist. There is no con<lb break="no"/>scientious Conviction on the part of the Presby<lb break="no"/>terian which forbids him sending his child to either <lb/>
Methodist or Baptist schools. I think all the Pro<lb break="no"/>testant denominations can well unite on the common <lb/>
school system in the North-West. I am satisfied <lb/>
we can do that as well there as in the Province of <lb/>
Ontario. I would endeavour to make the system <lb/>
as acceptable as possible to our Catholic friends, in <lb/>
the hope that they will take advantage of it instead <lb/>
of persisting in opening separate schools; but to <lb/>
pass legislation to give the majority power to com<lb break="no"/>pel the Catholics to avail themselves of this system <lb/>
is not a proper mode of reaching the desired end, <lb/>
and I do not think the end desired by the hon. <lb/>
member for West York (Mr. Wallace) will be <lb/>
gained in this way. These are my views with <lb/>
respect to separate schools, and also with respect to <lb/>
the dual language. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. I have listened, with consider<lb break="no"/>able amazement, to the doctrine which has been <lb/>
given to the House by the hon. gentleman who has <lb/>
just resumed his seat. To be perfectly candid, I <lb/>
must say that I could notunderstand altogether <lb/>
what the hon. gentleman stated. He spoke on the <lb/>
question of education in the North-West, and he <lb/>
gave his own views. But the hon. gentleman does <lb/>
not seem to understand that this, in the Catholic <lb/>
faith, is a matter of principle. The hon. member <lb/>
for West Middlesex introduced a motion and said <lb/>
at the beginning of his remarks that he did not <lb/>
want to interfere with the French language or the <lb/>
separate school system in the North-West. As he <lb/>
warmed up and proceeded with the subject he soon <lb/>
did away with the separate school system there. <lb/>
He said that there had been opposition also to the <lb/>
system of separate schools being introduced into <lb/>
the Province of Ontario. I ask the hon. gentleman <lb/>
how, having had an experience of the system of <lb/>
separate schools in Ontario, he has any more reason <lb/>
than his fellow-citizens of that province to feel dis<lb break="no"/>satisfied with the result of the experience of these <lb/>
schools? Only a few years ago a battle was waged <lb/>
in Ontario on the lines of this question, and <lb/>
we well remember the cries then, put for<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="3073" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03073.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3073</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 30, 1892.]</fw> <fw type="num">3074</fw>

ward. We well remember the arguments used <lb/>
in order to defeat what to-day is a benefit in this <lb/>
province, as well as in the Province of Quebec, the <lb/>
separate school system, and no doubt the hon. <lb/>
gentleman on that occasion was obliged to confess <lb/>
that the separate school system in Ontario was a <lb/>
success. At all events, if he did not by his speech <lb/>
and vote make that confession, I am happy to say <lb/>
that the Protestant population of the greatest <lb/>
province of this Dominion declared that the separ<lb break="no"/>ate school system of Ontario was a success. The <lb/>
hon. gentleman wants no religious teaching in <lb/>
the schools. What does he want? Does he invite <lb/>
the godless school? He has to choose between the <lb/>
religious school and the godless school. If he wants <lb/>
the religious school, believing in his own views, he <lb/>
will want the Protestant school. If he does not <lb/>
want the religious school, he is confronted with the <lb/>
godless school; and as this is a religious country <lb/>
and we have to deal with christian people, I think <lb/>
they will not have the godless school. We know <lb/>
what has been the experience of the godless school <lb/>
in more than one country. We know that the god<lb break="no"/>less school and godless philosophy did about as <lb/>
much mischief during the last century in the old <lb/>
world as war, pestilence and famine. It must be <lb/>
understood that with us as Catholics it is <lb/>
a principle that we must have our Catholic <lb/>
schools. We are face to face with that problem. <lb/>
If the hon. gentleman wants the religious school <lb/>
and the Protestant school, we have no objections <lb/>
to offer. The Protestant is proud of his faith. <lb/>
He is ready to defend it against all attacks, he is <lb/>
ready on all occasions to stand up for it, and he <lb/>
would scorn us, and justly too, if we were to inter<lb break="no"/>fere with his rights. Why not let it be done to us <lb/>
as we are willing it should be done to them? Do <lb/>
we interfere with their rights? Look at things as <lb/>
they exist in the Province of Quebec. There, Sir, <lb/>
and proud I feel to say it, the minority is treated <lb/>
with justice, and is treated more liberally than <lb/>
even the minority in the Province of Ontario, since <lb/>
grants are made in Quebec for the cause of superior <lb/>
education which are not made in the Province of <lb/>
Ontario. Will the hon. gentleman, after the ex<lb break="no"/>perience we have had in the Province of Quebec of <lb/>
these separate schools, say that the system is a <lb/>
failure? The late Hon. Thomas White, if I <lb/>
remember well, himself admitted that the minority <lb/>
was treated with exceptional fairness, and Sir <lb/>
William Dawson, President of McGill University, <lb/>
who was at least as good a champion of Protestant<lb break="no"/>ism, and at least as sturdy and solid an exponent <lb/>
of Protestant thought as the hon. member for South <lb/>
Middlesex (Mr. Armstrong), or as the hon. member <lb/>
for York (Mr. Wallace), or as the hon. member for <lb/>
North Wellington (Mr. McMullen), was also ready <lb/>
to confess that the Protestants of the Province of <lb/>
Quebec had nothing to complain of, and had in fact <lb/>
received the fullest measure of justice from their <lb/>
Catholic fellow-countrymen. We have already <lb/>
since the beginning of this session voted large sums <lb/>
of money to open up the North-West Territories. <lb/>
What does the hon. member for Middlesex (Mr. <lb/>
Armstrong) propose by his motion, and what does <lb/>
the hon. member for West York (Mr. Wallace) <lb/>
propose by his amendment? The latter proposes <lb/>
to tell the Catholic people of the Province of Que<lb break="no"/>bec that to the North-West they must not go. <lb/>
That is his proposal. <lb/></p> 

<cb/>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. McMULLEN</persName>. No, no. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. The hon. member for Welling<lb break="no"/>ton says "no, no." What does he understand in <lb/>
the matter? The proposal of this motion, and of <lb/>
this amendment is to tell Catholics, that in the <lb/>
North-West Territories the same law will be <lb/>
invoked in a year or two as was applied by Mr. <lb/>
Greenway in the Province of Manitoba, and will it <lb/>
be contended for a moment that that act of ad<lb break="no"/>ministration on the part of Mr. Greenway has <lb/>
promoted increase of population or increase of <lb/>
good feeling among the people of Manitoba? <lb/>
That law is yet before the courts. A decision has <lb/>
been rendered against it here in the Supreme Court, <lb/>
and I express the hope that that decision will be <lb/>
confirmed by the Privy Council in England, and <lb/>
that fair-play will be extended to the Catholic <lb/>
population of Manitoba. Sir, adopt this motion <lb/>
be ore the House, pass a law denying to the Catholic <lb/>
population of the North-West the schools which <lb/>
they ask, and to which they are entitled, and you <lb/>
will tell the Catholic people in every province of <lb/>
this Dominion, that to the North-West they must <lb/>
not go, because steps have been taken to prevent <lb/>
them living there. You go across the ocean and you <lb/>
ask for your immigrants for this country. You expend <lb/>
large sums of money to bring them here: but, Sir, if <lb/>
you adopt this motion, you will refuse to our <lb/>
young men of the Province of Quebec the right of <lb/>
entering into these Territories. What right have <lb/>
we to do these things? To our Catholic people <lb/>
that great domain was given by Providence just as <lb/>
much as it was to any other portion of the popula<lb break="no"/>tion of Canada. I shall certainly vote against the <lb/>
proposal of the hon. member for South Mid<lb break="no"/>dlesex (Mr. Armstrong); I shall certainly with <lb/>
pride and happiness vote against the amendment <lb/>
proposed by the member for West York (Mr. <lb/>
Wallace), because I believe in conscience that <lb/>
because I am a Catholic I should no more be <lb/>
trampled upon than my rights should be no more <lb/>
sacrificed, and my privileges should be respected <lb/>
as much as those of any other man of any religion <lb/>
in this Dominion. I know, Sir, that there has been <lb/>
charged against me in connection with the motion <lb/>
I am about to make, that because the other day I <lb/>
voted against the Bill introduced by the member <lb/>
for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy), I am not in <lb/>
favour of Canadian Home, Rule. It is false. It is <lb/>
not the case. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. Order. The hon. gentleman <lb/>
cannot discuss a motion that is not before the <lb/>
House. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. I am not discussing it, Mr. Speaker. <lb/>
I am just putting myself right with regard to the <lb/>
statement that has been made against me in con<lb break="no"/>nection with my vote against the motion introduced <lb/>
the other day by the member for North Simcoe (Mr. <lb/>
McCarthy). Well, Sir, all I ask for my co-religi<lb break="no"/>onists in the North-West is the same treatment <lb/>
which is accorded to the Protestants of the Prov<lb break="no"/>ince of Quebec, and which the Catholics of the <lb/>
Province of Ontario enjoy. I believe that by voting <lb/>
down the motions which are presently before the <lb/>
House we will be acting in the interests of the <lb/>
honour and the peace of Canada, and I believe, <lb/>
furthermore, that by following out this course we <lb/>
will be laying the foundations of making the North-<lb break="yes"/>West contented, of making it the seat in future of <lb/>

<pb n="3075" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03075.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3075</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3076</fw> 

large cities and large centres of population, where <lb/>
the tiller of the soil may work peacefully, success<lb break="no"/>fully with honour and advantage to our common <lb/>
country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SCRI1">Mr. SCRIVER</persName>. Mr. Speaker, I desire to say <lb/>
first, Sir, that you were in error in naming me as <lb/>
the seconder of the motion now before the House. <lb/>
I did not consent to second the motion, but I did <lb/>
not dissent from your connecting my name with it <lb/>
because of my desire to be courteous to my neighbour, <lb/>
the hon. member for South Middlesex (Mr. Arm<lb break="no"/>strong). I am not in favour of this motion in all <lb/>
its details. So far as the part relating to the dual <lb/>
language is concerned it expresses my views; views <lb/>
which I took the liberty of giving to the House <lb/>
when the motion relating to that question was before <lb/>
us at a previous session of this House. I then <lb/>
expressed my sympathy with the motion of the <lb/>
hon. member for Assiniboia (Mr. Davin), which <lb/>
was to the effect that the question of languages <lb/>
should be left to the decision of the people of the <lb/>
Territories; but so far as the question of separate <lb/>
schools is concerned I take a somewhat different <lb/>
view. Allusion has been made by several hon. <lb/>
gentlemen to the position held by the Protestant <lb/>
minority in the Province of Quebec in relation to <lb/>
their school system. I am one of that Protestant <lb/>
minority, and I am here to express my concurrence <lb/>
in the statement already made, that the Protestant <lb/>
minority in that province has been treated since <lb/>
Confederation, with perfect fairness and with full <lb/>
liberality by the Roman Catholic majority. The <lb/>
Protestants of that province could not live there were <lb/>
they not accorded the privileges in regard to the edu<lb break="no"/>cation of their children which they now enjoy. Hold<lb break="no"/>ing the views which Roman Catholics do conscienti<lb break="no"/>ously hold, and they being largely in the majority, <lb/>
if we had a common school system there, and but <lb/>
one school where all religious tenets would be <lb/>
taught, the Protestants would not and could not <lb/>
possibly accept it. This being the case, and it <lb/>
being the fact that we have been, as I have said, <lb/>
treated with perfect fairness and perfect liberality <lb/>
in the Province of Quebec, I do not see how <lb/>
Protestants, taking a proper view of this question, <lb/>
can fail to consent to extend to their Roman <lb/>
Catholic fellow-citizens the same privileges which <lb/>
they enjoy themselves. I cannot give my support <lb/>
to a propositionwhich would deprive the Roman <lb/>
Catholic population of the North-West from the <lb/>
enjoyment of theprivileges which the Protestants <lb/>
of the Province of Quebec have enjoyed and do <lb/>
enjoy, and I believe will continue to enjoy in the <lb/>
future. I cannot consent to give my support to a <lb/>
motion which at sometime or other—if it would <lb/>
not have that immediate effect—would compel the <lb/>
Roman Catholics of the North-West to either <lb/>
allow their children to grow up in ignorance, or to <lb/>
send them to schools which it would be a violation <lb/>
of their religious convictions to send them to. <lb/>
Therefore, I am opposed to a portion of the motion <lb/>
of my hon. friehd from South Middlesex, and I am <lb/>
also opposed to the amendment moved by the hon. <lb/>
member for West York. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MACDONALD</persName> (Huron). I wish to say just <lb/>
one word upon this question. Two years ago, when <lb/>
the hon. member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy) <lb/>
introduced a Bill in regard to separate schools and <lb/>
the dual languages, my intention waste vote for <lb/>
the Bill:  Afterwards an amendment was adopted, <lb/>

<cb/>

which I called a compromising amendment, and <lb/>
against which I voted, and the Bill was not reached <lb/>
to vote on. I said then, as I say now, that this is a <lb/>
question which the Parliament of Canada must <lb/>
face, either to-day or some day in the near future, <lb/>
and we might as well look it fairly and squarely in <lb/>
the face, and decide now what is best to be done. <lb/>
The North-West Territories will soon be a province. <lb/>
They have now very largely the powers of a pro<lb break="no"/>vince. The people who live in the Territories have <lb/>
one there for the purpose of working out their <lb/>
future destiny, and making the very best they can <lb/>
of the circumstances in which they are placed; <lb/>
and I think we would be derelict in our duty if we <lb/>
did not give them control over their own affairs, <lb/>
and say to them: You can have separate schools if <lb/>
you please, or a national school system if you <lb/>
please, and you can have both languages if you <lb/>
please, or only one-decide for yourselves. That <lb/>
is a question which this Parliament must face; <lb/>
and I cannot, for the life of me, understand how <lb/>
those who have been for years talking of pro<lb break="no"/>vincial rights, and declaring that the provinces <lb/>
should have full and complete control over matters <lb/>
of a local character, can vote against giving the <lb/>
people of the North-West power to say what <lb/>
form of language or what kind of schools they <lb/>
will have. If their future is to be in their own <lb/>
hands, they must have power to work out that <lb/>
future; but if we place burdens upon them. I <lb/>
think there will be in the future a great deal more <lb/>
trouble excited by these questions than there is at <lb/>
the present time. Therefore the sooner we put the <lb/>
question right the better. At present the country <lb/>
is new, there are not a great many people there, <lb/>
and the majority will be disposed to be fair to the <lb/>
minority. They might consider it in their interest <lb/>
to continue the present condition of affairs; but if <lb/>
the majority should decide against separate schools <lb/>
or the dual languages, then the responsibility will <lb/>
rest upon that majority, and will be taken from <lb/>
our shoulders; and these sectarian questions, which <lb/>
cause so much irritation and unpleasant feeling, <lb/>
will be removed from this Parliament. I am <lb/>
satisfied that the Roman Catholics in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West will have nothing to complain of if we <lb/>
take this course, for I believe that the majority <lb/>
there will be just as favourable to giving them their <lb/>
rights as the majority in this Parliament. That is <lb/>
the reason which leads me to favour the amendment <lb/>
which has been moved: and while I support that <lb/>
amendment, I say to the people of the North-West: <lb/>
This is a question entirely of a local character which <lb/>
you have to settle; on your shoulders rests the re<lb break="no"/>sponsibility of working out your own destiny, and <lb/>
you have the right to say whether you will have <lb/>
separate schools and the dual languages or not. I <lb/>
hold that that is the fair way to dispose of this <lb/>
question, and I feel assured, though I am not a <lb/>
prophet nor the son of one, that the members of <lb/>
this House will have to come to that conclusion <lb/>
before they are five years older. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. Mr. Speaker, I would not <lb/>
be disposed to interpose at this stage of the debate <lb/>
but for the fact that, owing to the order passed on <lb/>
Friday last, this discussion must come to a vote <lb/>
before six o'clock to-day, as it cannot be resumed <lb/>
this session.  <lb/></p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. Oh, yes. </p>

<pb n="3077" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03077.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3077</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 30, 1892.]</fw> <fw type="num">3078</fw>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. I thought there was an <lb/>
intimation given by the hon. leader of the House <lb/>
that the remnant of this day which is left to us is <lb/>
to be taken from us. Well, Sir, I agree most <lb/>
heartily with the sentiment that has fallen from <lb/>
the hon. gentleman who has just resumed his seat, <lb/>
a sentiment which found utterance in the beginning <lb/>
of this debate, in the speech of the hon. gentleman <lb/>
who moved the resolution—that this matter must <lb/>
be faced, that it will not down; and it is in the <lb/>
interest of all of us, seeing how unfortunately the <lb/>
question excites both racial and religious feelings <lb/>
and prejudices, that at the earliest possible moment <lb/>
we should face it, deal with it, and determine it. <lb/>
Now, we have given to the North-West Assembly <lb/>
already very large powers. With the exception, <lb/>
perhaps, of the control of money, which I hope at <lb/>
an early day will also be granted to them, they <lb/>
have almost all the powers of a provincial assembly. <lb/>
That being so, those who in this House have <lb/>
declared that they are not to have the full power <lb/>
and control in the matter of education, have at least <lb/>
the responsibility resting upon them of showing <lb/>
why the authority of the North-West Assembly <lb/>
should be limited in that regard. We know per<lb break="no"/>fectly well that it is in accordance with the spirit <lb/>
of the federal system under which this Dominion is <lb/>
governed, that the subject of education is one of <lb/>
local concern; and while I do not go the length, and <lb/>
have never gone the length of saying that in no case, <lb/>
in the general interest of the Dominion, should this <lb/>
Parliament or this Government interfere in matters <lb/>
which in a narrow sense are of localconcern, I hold as <lb/>
strongly as any hon. member on the floor of this <lb/>
Parliament that in ordinary cases, within the scope <lb/>
of our legislation, local matters should be dealt <lb/>
a with by the local bodies and the local assemblies. <lb/>
Now, Sir, if that be accepted as a preliminary doc<lb break="no"/>trine, I want to know why it is that in the matter <lb/>
of education this Parliament undertakes to say <lb/>
that the North-west Assembly shall not have the <lb/>
full control? I want to know why it was that <lb/>
years and years ago, long before the North-West <lb/>
was settled, this House enacted as one of the organic <lb/>
laws regulatin to the North-West Territories <lb/>
that they should not have full, absolute and un<lb break="no"/>limited power in the matter of education? I have <lb/>
never heard any answer given to that question. I have <lb/>
never heard any suggestion offered why it was that <lb/>
the North-West should not have the same liberty <lb/>
that the other provinces have, all except the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Ontario and Province of Quebec; and we <lb/>
know the special reason which existed in the case <lb/>
of those provinces. I have heard it said, forsooth: <lb/>
Wait till we grant them full autonomy; wait till <lb/>
we create different provinces in the North-West; <lb/>
and when we create different provinces there, and <lb/>
endow them with full provincial powers, then it will <lb/>
be time enough to give them full authority to deal with <lb/>
education. Why should you deny them the right to <lb/>
consider and to deal with the question of education? <lb/>
I can perfectly well understand the feelin which <lb/>
actuate my Roman Catholic fellow-citizens. I respect <lb/>
their feelings and views; and if it were advisable in <lb/>
this country to give effect to their views, I should not <lb/>
be heard saying anything against them. But I am <lb/>
unable to see the fair-play on the part of Roman <lb/>
Catholics, who believe, and I respect their belief, <lb/>
that no education is complete unless accompanied <lb/>
by religious teaching, in denying to the other <lb/>

<cb/>

religious bodies, many of whom hold the same <lb/>
views, equal justice in that regard. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. We do not deny to Protestants <lb/>
the right to have separate schools. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. Practically you do. Take <lb/>
the Province of Ontario. There is a public school <lb/>
system there and a separate school system for the <lb/>
Roman Catholics. Now take the Protestants of my <lb/>
church, many of whom would desire to see their <lb/>
children taught in their schools thetenets of their <lb/>
faith as the Roman Catholicsare taught theirs in <lb/>
the separate schools; they are not given the privilege <lb/>
of having separate schools. However, I do not desire <lb/>
to enter into a discussion of that here, but, speaking <lb/>
for my own province, I must say I would like to <lb/>
see the power given that province to deal with the <lb/>
school question as other provinces deal with it; and <lb/>
should the majority in that province think it would <lb/>
be better that we should have a system of education <lb/>
free altogether from religious teaching, I should <lb/>
desire their view should prevail. I respect the <lb/>
views put forward by the hon. member for North <lb/>
Wellington (Mr. McMallen), and realize that there <lb/>
is a great deal in what he has said with regard <lb/>
to secular education, but I hold that the provinces <lb/>
should be allowed to work out this matter for <lb/>
themselves. They are the parties most competent <lb/>
to deal with it; and I would like to know why it <lb/>
is this Parliament undertakes to say to the people <lb/>
of the North-West that in any ordinance they may <lb/>
make regarding education, they must always enact <lb/>
there may be a separate school in every locality in <lb/>
that country. I think the burden of proof is upon <lb/>
those who desire to control the power of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of the North-West in that direction, and I am <lb/>
prepared to listen with every attention to any argu<lb break="no"/>ment in support of that restriction and limitation. <lb/>
Therefore am in favour of the motion the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman has brought forward, that power should be <lb/>
given the Legislative Assembly of the North-West <lb/>
Territories to deal with all matters pertaining to <lb/>
education, but am not in favour of his limitation <lb/>
that no school section shall be interfered with <lb/>
without the consent of the parties composing it. It <lb/>
is an insult to the North-West to say to them: <lb/>
You must keep perpetually these schools, scattered <lb/>
here and there, as separate schools unless the par<lb break="no"/>ticular locality consents to the legislative body <lb/>
dealing with the matter. Let us trust them, let <lb/>
us give them full power to deal with the matter <lb/>
themselves. If the hon. gentleman is sincere in his <lb/>
views of provincial rights, he will not have any <lb/>
reason for regretting the trust he will repose in <lb/>
the people of the North-West in this or any <lb/>
other respect. I did not move in this matter when <lb/>
I brought forward the question of dual language <lb/>
two years ago, and the reason I did not was <lb/>
this: I have not altered my opinions in the slightest <lb/>
respecting it, but I felt we ought to have an appeal <lb/>
from the people of the North- West, I felt that we <lb/>
ought to have a representation from their Assembly <lb/>
before interfering in a matter which I believe to <lb/>
be so absolutely of local concern. If they were <lb/>
satisfied with the law as it exists, it would be un<lb break="no"/>necessary and mischievous to bring forward any <lb/>
motion in this Parliament respecting it. But we <lb/>
know that they have petitioned this House to <lb/>
free them from the restrictions imposed, and give <lb/>
them power to deal with the School system as they <lb/>

<pb n="3079" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03079.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3079</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3080</fw> 

think proper. This has been twice represented <lb/>
here, once in the form of a petition and again in <lb/>
the form of a resolution by which the people of the <lb/>
North-West desires to remind the Parliament of <lb/>
Canada that they already asked for interference in <lb/>
that regard. When we reflect that the people of <lb/>
the North-West are rapidly attaining the position, <lb/>
as regard population, of some of our smaller <lb/>
provinces, I ask the members from Prince Edward <lb/>
Island: On what grounds do you venture to <lb/>
say to the people of the North-West that they <lb/>
are not as competent to deal with this school <lb/>
question as you are? I ask my hon. friends from <lb/>
British Columbia why they are not willing to al<lb break="no"/>low the people of the North-West to deal with <lb/>
their own schools. In all probability, in the next <lb/>
ten years, the people of the North-West will out<lb break="no"/>number both the provinces of British Colum<lb break="no"/>bia and Prince Edward Island, which, I do not <lb/>
suppose, would be willing to part with their power as <lb/>
regards education, or consider any interference with <lb/>
it by this Parliament as other than a gross outrage on <lb/>
their liberties and rights, yet they are unwilling <lb/>
that the North-West Territories should have the <lb/>
same right. It is not necessary for me to discuss <lb/>
the question in any other respect. I do not pre<lb break="no"/>sume to say what the people of the North-West <lb/>
will do, but all I ask for them is liberty to do what <lb/>
they consider is proper and right. I do not enter <lb/>
into the discussion as to whether there ought or <lb/>
ought not to be separate schools. I think, to say <lb/>
the least, it would be injudicious to bring on the <lb/>
floor of Parliament a discussion as to the merits of <lb/>
either system; but I want the House to under<lb break="no"/>stand that as long as that enactment remains on the <lb/>
Statute-book, so long do we compel the North-West <lb/>
to have separate schools. I want every member to <lb/>
realize the responsibility that he is taking in that <lb/>
regard. In his own province he may be content <lb/>
there should be no separate schools; but when <lb/>
dealing with the North-West, where there is no <lb/>
large population, and from which there is no large <lb/>
representation here, he considers this question as a <lb/>
matter of no consequence. But he is responsible <lb/>
to the whole people for saying there should be sep<lb break="no"/>arate schools there, although he must admit this is <lb/>
a matter with which it would be far better to leave <lb/>
the local authorities to deal. Now, as to the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of dual language, I do not accept the advice <lb/>
put forward by any of the hon. gentlemen who so <lb/>
far have addressed us. I trust I have grown wiser <lb/>
a little since my last effort, and I do not desire to <lb/>
excite, in this discussion, the same feelings that <lb/>
were aroused on a former occasion. Not that I do <lb/>
not hold as strongly to the views I held then, not <lb/>
that I do not think it would be in the interests of <lb/>
all the people of this Dominion if we spoke the one <lb/>
language and believed in the one theory of govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and so on. I do not at all retract my opinion <lb/>
in that regard; but I quite realize this, that my <lb/>
hon. friends from Quebec took the motion I made, <lb/>
which did not name the Province of Quebec but <lb/>
only affected the North-West Territories, as an <lb/>
attack upon what they regard as an institution <lb/>
they pride themselves upon possessing in that <lb/>
province. We are dealing now with the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, with that great country which, before many <lb/>
years, will overshadow the eastern partof the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion, with this territory which, before many years, will <lb/>
be the heart of the Dominion of Canada, and we are <lb/>
laying the foundations there of several great states. <lb/>

<cb/>

Now, is there an hon. gentleman in Parliament <lb/>
who believes that, if he had to formulate a constitu<lb break="no"/>tion for that country, he would lay down as a part <lb/>
of its laws, as the foundation of its existence, that <lb/>
the people should speak two separate tongues? <lb/>
That is the problem we have to deal with there. <lb/>
It is not the question of the Province of Quebec. <lb/>
It is not the rights that have grown up in regard <lb/>
to the Province of Quebec, but we are now dealing <lb/>
with another part of the great Dominion of Canada, <lb/>
and what I want to know is, is it wise or prudent <lb/>
or statesmanlike that we should, in establishing <lb/>
the North-West Territories, at once say there are <lb/>
to be two races holding an equality before the law <lb/>
and that we desire not their assimilation, not their <lb/>
amalgamation, but their perpetuation as two dis<lb break="no"/>tinctive races, just as they are unfortunately in the <lb/>
Province of Quebec at the present moment. I am <lb/>
not dealing at all with the loyalty of the French <lb/>
Canadian. I am not dealing from that point of <lb/>
view, but I am simply dealing with the wisdom or <lb/>
prudence of our saying that, in a country where it <lb/>
is the interest of all that we should be united and <lb/>
should form one nationality, we should lay down <lb/>
the rule that there shall be two languages and <lb/>
consequently the two racial distinctions and the <lb/>
cleavage which has existed unhappily in other parts <lb/>
of this Dominion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. Unhappily? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. Yes, I say to my hon. friend, <lb/>
unhappily. I think he will agree with me, not least <lb/>
amongst the hon. gentlemen who share his views, <lb/>
that it would be better for all of us if we all spoke <lb/>
English or if we all spoke French. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. Let all speak French. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAP4">Mr. CHAPLEAU</persName>. En Français. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. My hon. friend has me at a <lb/>
disadvantage there. I think my hon. friends, if <lb/>
they thought this matter out for themselves, if they <lb/>
did not allow themslves to be swayed by their pas<lb break="no"/>sions, would think as I do. The proposition which <lb/>
I intend to submit to the House as an amendment <lb/>
to the resolution is in accordance with the view <lb/>
that we here should deal with this question of lan<lb break="no"/>guage. It is not a matter of local concern that <lb/>
Germans, for instance, should go into our provinces <lb/>
and decide that the German tongue should hold <lb/>
sway. Surely no one will say that a matter of that <lb/>
kind partakes of local concern. I repeat what I <lb/>
have said on other occasions that, if there is any<lb break="no"/>thing more important than another in the formation <lb/>
of national character, it is the question of language, <lb/>
and that is a question for this Parliament, having <lb/>
assumed the position of the mother of several <lb/>
states. We are establishing states in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, and in that sense we are an imperial <lb/>
power, and it is for us to say, and we have in fact <lb/>
said, that, with the exception of the Province of <lb/>
Quebec, when we got our charter, the English <lb/>
language was to be the language of the people of <lb/>
this country. We have said in the Province of <lb/>
Quebec both languages might prevail. We said <lb/>
in this Parliament, at that time largely represented <lb/>
by a large proportion relatively of the French <lb/>
Canadian race, that the two languages should hold <lb/>
equal rank, but with regard to the other Provinces, <lb/>
New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, British Columbia <lb/>
when she afterwards came in, and Prince Edward <lb/>
Island, there is no such rule existing, and as the <lb/>

<pb n="3081" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03081.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3081</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 30, 1892.]</fw> <fw type="num">3082</fw>

foundation of our system we have it that the <lb/>
English tongue is to prevail. Then why have the <lb/>
two languages in the North-West, and least of <lb/>
all why have them in the way in which they are <lb/>
left by the so-called compromise amendment? <lb/>
Formerly it was permitted to the people in their <lb/>
Legislative Assembly to speak in both languages. <lb/>
It was enacted that the records of that Assembly <lb/>
should be recorded in both languages, that the <lb/>
proceedings of the court should be in both languages, <lb/>
and that the laws should be published in both <lb/>
languages. A so-called compromise was made, but <lb/>
whom was the compromise made between? Perhaps <lb/>
my hon. friend the leader of the Opposition could <lb/>
tell, perhaps my hon, friends on this side could <lb/>
tell also; but did any person making that com<lb break="no"/>promise represent or profess to represent the <lb/>
North-West There is my hon. friend, for in<lb break="no"/>stance, from Assiniboia (Mr. Davin). Is that part <lb/>
of the bargain he made on behalf of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West? The political leaders on either side of the <lb/>
House, anxious to get rid of a difficult question, <lb/>
politically speaking, thought this was a compro<lb break="no"/>mise which might be agreed upon, but I should <lb/>
like to know who were the parties who made that <lb/>
compromise, and why it should be regarded as <lb/>
sacred? What does it effect? What benefit has <lb/>
been derived from the compromise? We gave the <lb/>
people of the North-West power to say they <lb/>
should not speak both languages in the Legislative <lb/>
Assembly? What do they do? Like practical <lb/>
men they said: You can speak in any language you <lb/>
please, and, if one or two gentlemen there who <lb/>
speak French are fools enough to address in that <lb/>
language the great body who speak English, they <lb/>
will soon drop that, finding that they would take <lb/>
nothing by their eloquence. As to their proceed<lb break="no"/>ings, however, they are only to be recorded in one <lb/>
language. There again as practical men—and it <lb/>
shows what practical men will do—they say the <lb/>
mischief is not in the language in which the people <lb/>
speak, because no one pretends that there should <lb/>
be any interference with the sacred right of speak<lb break="no"/>ing in any language a man chooses, but in <lb/>
pursuing in our system a duality of language, if <lb/>
we believe, as I believe, that it is against the best <lb/>
interests of our political system. Then they dealt <lb/>
with it as practical men and said the proceedings <lb/>
of the Assembly should only be recorded in one <lb/>
tongue, and that is English. But we did not <lb/>
settle the question. The mischief to be got rid of, <lb/>
the difficulty to be obviated is not because a few <lb/>
people there speak French, but because we are en<lb break="no"/>couraging in the North-Warst system of duality <lb/>
of race by holding out the two languages as taking <lb/>
equal rank and holding equal sway in all proceed<lb break="no"/>ings. Then take the courts. One of the hon. <lb/>
gentlemen pointed out the practical mischief which <lb/>
arose from having the two languages in the courts, <lb/>
and there is a great deal to be said as to the practical <lb/>
view of the matter. But I am dealing with it on <lb/>
higher grounds. I am not dealing with this from <lb/>
any antipathy to any race in this Dominion, but <lb/>
on the higher ground that it is to the interest of <lb/>
us all to prevent any question of that kind arisin <lb/>
in the future, and to have it perfectly understood <lb/>
at the outset that the English tongue is the lan<lb break="no"/>guage of the people of this Dominion. It is better <lb/>
for all parties to realize that at the earliest moment. <lb/>
Why should the subject be remitted to the people of <lb/>
the North-West? If I merely looked at this from the <lb/>

<cb/>

practical point of view, it would not make the <lb/>
slightest difference If we give the North-West <lb/>
Assembly the power suggested by this resolution, <lb/>
they will decidedly exercise that power and repeal <lb/>
that law, but why should we hand that over to <lb/>
them? We are responsible here for imposing that <lb/>
law; surely we are the proper parties here if we <lb/>
believe it is not right, to remove it. Why should <lb/>
we cast that as a bone of contention among the <lb/>
people of the North-West? Why should not this <lb/>
Parliament, treating it as a matter of imperial im<lb break="no"/>portance, in the sense in which I use that term, <lb/>
remove from the Statute-book that law which this <lb/>
Parliament so unnecessarily put upon it, and do <lb/>
away with the distinction which exists in regard to <lb/>
the North-West and not in regard to any of the <lb/>
rest of the Dominion, that there are to be the two <lb/>
languages there? Without occupying the time of <lb/>
the House upon a subject in regard to which my <lb/>
views are pretty well known, I desire to move an <lb/>
amendment in order to put my views on record in <lb/>
a formal way. I accept what my hon. friend from <lb/>
West York (Mr. Wallace) has moved as far as the <lb/>
schools are concerned. I do not accept either the <lb/>
motion or the amendment, so far as the language <lb/>
is concerned. I say that here is the proper place <lb/>
for us to settle this question of language, and there<lb break="no"/>fore I move:— <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>That all after the word "That," in the original motion <lb/>
and the proposed amendment, be erased, and that the <lb/>
following be substituted instead therefor:— <lb/></p> 

<p>"It is expedient that the limitation and restriction upon <lb/>
the authority of the Assembly of the North-West Territo<lb break="no"/>ries in the matter of education, and the enactments <lb/>
respecting the use of the French language in the courts <lb/>
mm the compulsory publication of its ordinances in that <lb/>
tongue, should be repealed." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>It will be seen that I move simply that the restric<lb break="no"/>tion should be repealed, leaving with them the <lb/>
power which they have now on the subject of <lb/>
education, as it stands to-day, but that on the <lb/>
subject of language, that enactment shall he elimi<lb break="no"/>nated from our Statute-book. <lb/></p> 


<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). It is not my purpose <lb/>
to support any one of the motions in your hands. I <lb/>
shall endeavour to address myself to the observa<lb break="no"/>tions with which the hon. member for North Sim<lb break="no"/>one (Mr. McCarthy) closed his speech. The hon. <lb/>
gentleman has ex ressed himself as holding the <lb/>
doctrine enunciated by him two years ago in this <lb/>
House. Sir, I entertain to-day the same views I <lb/>
expressed then, and for the same reasons that I <lb/>
opposed this proposition then, I oppose the pro<lb break="no"/>position which he now submits. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man has said that the question of the dual language <lb/>
in the North-West Territories is a national ques<lb break="no"/>tion, whereas the establishment of public schools <lb/>
is purely a local matter; and he is in favour of <lb/>
what he calls the principle of Local Government in <lb/>
the Territories, but he is in favour at the same time <lb/>
of disregarding that principle so far as the use of <lb/>
the French language in the Territories is concerned. <lb/>
Now, Sir, we may learn something from what has <lb/>
transpired elsewhere where the people are of <lb/>
different nationalities. The hon. gentleman is of <lb/>
the opinion that it is highly desirable there should <lb/>
be no language spoken in this countrybut one, and <lb/>
in his opinion it would be best if that language were <lb/>
the English language; but it would be better that <lb/>
we should all speak French than that some <lb/>
of us should speak Freneh and some English. I <lb/>
do not hold to that view at all. I am dis<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="3083" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03083.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3083</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3084</fw> 

posed to maintain my rights to speak the English <lb/>
tongue, whether in Parliament or out of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, and I am disposed to concede to my French <lb/>
fellow-countrymen the same privilege that I claim <lb/>
for myself, of expressing themselves in that lan<lb break="no"/>guage which they believe will best serve the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of conveying their thoughts and presenting <lb/>
their views on all questions, whether those ques<lb break="no"/>tions be public or private. The hon. gentleman <lb/>
ought to remember that we have in Canada up<lb break="no"/>wards of one million people who speak the French <lb/>
language. They have in Great Britain upwards of <lb/>
one million people who speak the Welsh; and they <lb/>
have been in contact with an English-speaking <lb/>
population out of all proportion larger than the <lb/>
English population as compared with the French <lb/>
in Canada; yet utter a period of several hundred <lb/>
years, the people within the limits of Wales still <lb/>
speak the Welsh language, and the Welsh language <lb/>
is used in all local matters, whether they relate to <lb/>
political or social affairs, in a more marked degree <lb/>
than it was used a hundred years ago. If we look <lb/>
at our neighbours across the border we find that <lb/>
when Louisiana was acquired by the United <lb/>
States, the French language was spoken, and the <lb/>
Government so far from interfering with the use of <lb/>
the French, allowed the people to speak either, was <lb/>
they saw proper, and it is only some 12 or 15 years <lb/>
ago that the French language ceased to be used as <lb/>
a public language in the State of Louisiana. If we <lb/>
look, again, at the territory that was acquired from <lb/>
Mexico in 1844, and a portion of which was convert<lb break="no"/>ed into the State of California, we find that the <lb/>
Spanish language was spoken in the southern part <lb/>
of the state and used as an official language amongst <lb/>
that section of the population that could only speak <lb/>
Spanish, until, I think, 1876. And when you go <lb/>
into some of the northern states to-day, where <lb/>
the population is largely Norwegian, I believe that <lb/>
the Norwegian language is spoken in the schools, <lb/>
that Norwegian teachers are employed, and that <lb/>
Norwegian books are used, simply because the <lb/>
children have but a short period of time to spend <lb/>
in the public schools, and unless they are permitted <lb/>
to do that, the recent comers from the northern <lb/>
portion of Europe would be unable to give their <lb/>
children an effective education at all. Now, the <lb/>
people of the United States have so far proceeded <lb/>
upon the assumption that the question of the <lb/>
unification of the population and their use of their <lb/>
own language, or of the English language, is a <lb/>
matter which I will regulate itself if it is let alone. <lb/>
I have no doubt that that will be the case with re<lb break="no"/>gard to the North-West Territories. If there is a large <lb/>
influx of French population there from the Province <lb/>
of Quebec, they will carry the French language with <lb/>
them, and it will be perpetuated for an indefinite <lb/>
period. If but a small number go, and if they dif<lb break="no"/>fuse themselves among the other portions of the <lb/>
population, then they will, in the course of a few <lb/>
years, cease to speak French, because the use of a <lb/>
language is a matter of convenience, and whether <lb/>
the people use the one or the other, will depend <lb/>
entirely upon the solution that convenience gives to <lb/>
the question. I should think that Canada has <lb/>
difficulties enough without undertaking to put for<lb break="no"/>ward any active exertion, as it seems to me is being <lb/>
done here, for the purpose of creatin new, or of <lb/>
reviving old difficulties. So far as the North-West <lb/>
Territories are concerned, if you were to provoke <lb/>
a contest between two-fifths of the population <lb/>

<cb/>

and the other three-fifths over the subject of <lb/>
language, I do not think you would do much to <lb/>
promote immigration into the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories; on the contrary every effort put forward in <lb/>
that direction would lead to strife, am to the division <lb/>
of the country on the basis of race, and serious <lb/>
mischiefs would ensue, because you would neutral<lb break="no"/>ize the energies of the population by directing <lb/>
them into abnormal and perverted channels. <lb/>
I am not going to say more on the subject of <lb/>
language. I do not think it is a matter calling for <lb/>
very much discussion. I believe the experience of <lb/>
civilized men everywhere has been the same, that this <lb/>
is a question with which no Government can effectu<lb break="no"/>ally deal, and every attempt to deal with it will <lb/>
only effect serious injury on the population. I <lb/>
should like to know what has been held out to <lb/>
every person where civilization exists to-day as one <lb/>
of the strongest evidences of the despotism, of the <lb/>
barbarism of Russia, but her treatment of Poland, <lb/>
her attempt to force the Russian language on the <lb/>
Polish people. And when England a few years <lb/>
ago entered into a discussion with Denmark to pre<lb break="no"/>vent a conflict between Denmark on the one side <lb/>
and Austria and Prussia on the other, she pressed <lb/>
on the Government of Denmark not to attempt to <lb/>
force the use of the Danish language on those pro<lb break="no"/>vinces in which the German language was spoken, <lb/>
and they pointed out in that correspondence what <lb/>
an unfavourable impression on the public mind of <lb/>
the world Denmark would make if she undertook <lb/>
to deal with her subjects in Schleswig-Holstein in <lb/>
the way she had attempted. That is not simply <lb/>
the opinion of Great Britain alone. It is the <lb/>
opinion on which civilized men and statesmen have <lb/>
acted everywhere except where despotic government <lb/>
exists, as that which exists in Russia. But I pass <lb/>
away from this subject of language, because there <lb/>
are a number of hon. gentlemen who are interested <lb/>
in the question, and I have no doubt it will be dis<lb break="no"/>cussed by them, and I turn my attention, and I <lb/>
invite the attention of the House, to the view <lb/>
which has been expressed on sovereign rights, the <lb/>
rights of self-government, by the hon. member for <lb/>
North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy), as applying to the <lb/>
people of the North-West Territories. Let us look <lb/>
for a moment at the subject of the British North <lb/>
America Act. Those people as a community have <lb/>
had no voice in the distribution of power, no saying <lb/>
as to what powers should be allotted to the Federal <lb/>
Government or what powers should be allotted to <lb/>
the Governments of the different provinces. That <lb/>
is a question which was settled not by them, but a <lb/>
question that was settled for them. It was the <lb/>
public men who took part in the formation of the <lb/>
constitution who determined that question, not <lb/>
merely for the provinces which as corporations <lb/>
under the British North America Act were united, <lb/>
but for all those political corporations that became <lb/>
provinces under the Act for all time to come. I do <lb/>
not understand this doctrine of sovereign rights, of <lb/>
local self-government as it has been put forward by the <lb/>
hon. gentleman. I understand that where a central <lb/>
Government holds a large extent of territory on <lb/>
its own account over which it exercised sovereign <lb/>
jurisdiction, it determines not merely what shall be <lb/>
the extent of its own authority, but it determines <lb/>
all questions of general policy in the constitution of <lb/>
the union between itself and the provinces. Let us <lb/>
look, for instance, at the question as shown in the, <lb/>
history of the United States. For instance, the <lb/>

<pb n="3085" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03085.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3085</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 30, 1892.]</fw> <fw type="num">3086</fw>
    
constitution of the United States was not framed <lb/>
by 40 states; it was framed by 13. All the states <lb/>
that came in subsequently had no voice in deter<lb break="no"/>mining the extent of their local authority; they <lb/>
had it determined for them. It was determined by <lb/>
those who first instituted the Government. If you <lb/>
adopt the other view, that put forward by the hon. <lb/>
member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy), you <lb/>
would have no such thin as a permanent govern<lb break="no"/>ment at all. Why should the people who are rot<lb break="no"/>ting in the churchyards of the Province of Ontario <lb/>
am in the Province of Quebec, who framed the <lb/>
constitution 30 years ago, determine for us what <lb/>
these constitutions shall be? There is such a <lb/>
thing as continuity in government, and the people <lb/>
who go into a territory go there with the under<lb break="no"/>standing that the character of the Local Government, <lb/>
subject to the provisions of the constitution, shall <lb/>
be such as the central Government, that exercises <lb/>
the sovereign authority in the first instance, <lb/>
shall determine for it. That is as I understand <lb/>
the constitution. That is the doctrine recognized <lb/>
in the constitution of the neighbouring republic. <lb/>
What does that constitution say? It says that <lb/>
each state shall have a republican form of gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. Can the state determine that the <lb/>
government shall be some other form? Can the <lb/>
state determine to adopt a form of government <lb/>
incompatible with the constitution? No. The <lb/>
powers of the state depend on the constitution <lb/>
given by the original thirteen states. They made <lb/>
the constitution in the first instance, and the other <lb/>
states that have come in subsequently took that <lb/>
constitution in accordance with those provisions, <lb/>
subject to be altered only in the way the constitu<lb break="no"/>tion, as framed by the original thirteen states or <lb/>
by the people of those states, provides. I hold in <lb/>
my hand Mr. Cooley's book on "The American <lb/>
Constitution," and I wish to read a paragraph from <lb/>
that work with respect to the jurisdiction of the <lb/>
United States over the government of the terri<lb break="no"/>tories, and hon. gentlemen will see that this doc<lb break="no"/>trine of squatter's sovereignty which has been put <lb/>
forward here to-day has never found a place in the <lb/>
government of the territories of the United. States <lb/>
—or at all events it found aplace but for a moment <lb/>
of time, which led to a civil war, and which was <lb/>
superseded by the results of that war. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the United States have power to make all <lb/>
needful rules and regulations respecting the <lb/>
territories. That is the power we possess. That <lb/>
is the power which we used when we formed the <lb/>
North-West Territories. How far we should re<lb break="no"/>tain the government in our hands, how far we <lb/>
should entrust the government to the people of the <lb/>
territories was a matter of expediency, a matter to <lb/>
be determined by experience and by local circum<lb break="no"/>stances. If this doctrine is to be applied to a <lb/>
territory, it is equally applicable to a municipality, <lb/>
and yet we do not recognize it with respect to any <lb/>
municipality. In a province, is a city, or township, <lb/>
or town permitted to determine the extent of its <lb/>
own power or the character of its municipal insti<lb break="no"/>tutions for itself? Can we determine for each city, <lb/>
town or township these powers? Let us see what <lb/>
is said on this matter by Mr. Cooley. He says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"It is no doubt most consistent with the general theory <lb/>
of republican institutions that the people everywhere <lb/>
should be allowed self-government: but it has never been <lb/>
deemed a matter of right that a local community should <lb/>
be adhered to lay the foundation of institutions, and erect <lb/>
a structure of government thereon, without the guidance <lb/>

<cb/>

and restraint of a superior authority. Even in the older <lb/>
states, where society is most homogeneous and has fewest <lb/>
of the elements of is quiet and disorder, the state reserves <lb/>
to itself the right to shape municipal institutions; and <lb/>
towns and cities are only formed under its direction, and <lb/>
    towns and cities are only formed under its direction, and
according to the rules, and within the limits the state pre<lb break="no"/>scribes. With still less reason could the settlers in new <lb/>
territories be suffered to exercise sovereign owers. <lb/>
The practice of the Government, originating before the <lb/>
adoption of the constitution has been for Congress to <lb/>
establish governments for the territories; and whether <lb/>
the Jurisdiction over the district has been acquired from <lb/>
the states or by treaty with a foreign power, Congress <lb/>
has unquestionably full power to govern it, and the <lb/>
people, execpt as Congress shall provide therefor, are not <lb/>
of right entitled to participate in political authority, until <lb/>
the territory becomes a state. Meanwhile they are in a <lb/>
condition of temporary pupilage and dependence: and <lb/>
while Congress will be expected to recognize the principle <lb/>
of self-government to such extent as may seem wise, its <lb/>
discretion alone can constitute the measure by which the <lb/>
participation of the peeplc can be determined." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
    
<p>That is the American rule. It is the rule which <lb/>
experience points out to be necessary. These hon. <lb/>
gentlemen insist that before the territory pos<lb break="no"/>sesses any of these organic elements which are <lb/>
necessary to the constitution of a province and a <lb/>
successful working oi parliamentary government, <lb/>
that it shall have all the rights and powers of a <lb/>
province. Experience in the neighbouring republic <lb/>
has not induced them to possess that view. Their <lb/>
experience has been much longer than ours, and I <lb/>
think it would be a great mistake on our part. to <lb/>
adopt any view like that. Some hon. gentlemen <lb/>
have said here that this is a question of state <lb/>
rights, and they have referred to the question of <lb/>
state rights that was settled by the civil war in <lb/>
the neighbouring republic. Why, Sir, there is no <lb/>
question of state rights here, and there is no party <lb/>
advocating anything approaching the doctrine of <lb/>
state rights in Canada. The doctrine of state <lb/>
rights in the United States was that each state is <lb/>
sovereign; not sovereign simply as to the extent <lb/>
of its authority, but absolutely sovereign over all <lb/>
the powers vested in either Congress or the state. <lb/>
It was said that Congress was simply an assembly <lb/>
of ambassadors acting under instructions from the <lb/>
sovereign state, and that the state being sovereign <lb/>
had a right to insist upon withdrawal, just the <lb/>
same as it the great sovereign powers of Europe <lb/>
were represented in a congressof ambassadors, <lb/>
and were not satisfied with what was being <lb/>
done, they could instruct their representatives to <lb/>
withdraw and to repudiate the whole arrangement. <lb/>
That is a doctrine that has never found support in <lb/>
the courts of the United States, or by a majority <lb/>
in the Congress of the United States; and the <lb/>
men anxious for the perpetuation of slavery were <lb/>
in favour of such a doctrine. I wonld like to <lb/>
know whether any hon. gentleman would say <lb/>
that the Territories should have the right, in the <lb/>
exercise of self-government, to establish slavery? <lb/>
Would a territory in the exercise of its right of <lb/>
self-government have a right to admit the Mormon <lb/>
population from Utah? Suppose you had a majority <lb/>
of people coming to a territory from the State of <lb/>
Utah, who insisted upon legalizing polygamy, <lb/>
would you permit them to exercise that power and <lb/>
to legislate with regard to domestic matters of that <lb/>
kind? Of course you would not. You would repud<lb break="no"/>iate such a claim at once, and you would say that <lb/>
such a power would be beyond the limits of the local <lb/>
constitution. You would not listen for a moment <lb/>
to the proposition, that these people, not having <lb/>
been parties to the original compact, were not bounr <lb/>
by it, and before they came in they had a right to <lb/>

<pb n="3087" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1892-05-30_Page_03087.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">3087</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">3088</fw> 

discuss the question how much of the British North <lb/>
America Act they would recognize as binding upon <lb/>
them. The people of this Dominion sitting here, as a <lb/>
matter of public policy will determine how far they <lb/>
will recognize the principle of separate schools and <lb/>
how far they will not, in the establishment of gov<lb break="no"/>ernments in the Territories. A few years ago they <lb/>
thought it was expedient, looking at what tran<lb break="no"/>spired in Ontario and Quebec, as these were the <lb/>
larger provinces of the Dominion and represented <lb/>
the greater portion of the population, to give effect <lb/>
in the Territories to the terms of settlement that <lb/>
has been arrived at as a solution of the educational <lb/>
question in these provinces. Whether wise or <lb/>
unwise, that was done. What reason is there at <lb/>
this moment for altering it? Has there been any <lb/>
great grievance sprung up? Has any practical mis<lb break="no"/>chief grown out of it? I do not think so, and I <lb/>
think, looking at how extremely sensitive a large <lb/>
portion of the population of this country is upon <lb/>
this question, that instead of it being a wise course <lb/>
to undertake to force upon the attention of this <lb/>
House the consideration of this question at the <lb/>
present time; it is an extremely mischievous <lb/>
course. It is one not in the public interest and one <lb/>
that certainly cannot promote harmony and the <lb/>
well-being of the population of the Territories. Sir, <lb/>
the hon. gentleman, if he will take the trouble of <lb/>
examining into the solution of this question and the <lb/>
results elsewhere, will find that the course taken in <lb/>
the Province of Ontario on the whole produced the <lb/>
most satisfactory results on this continent on the <lb/>
educational question. I do not think that he should <lb/>
come here simply as a political theorist to advocate <lb/>
views of abstract political philosophy and under<lb break="no"/>take to shape them into law. We ought to look at <lb/>
practical results, we ought to look at the character <lb/>
of our population, we ought to look not merely on <lb/>
what we believe would in the abstract be best for <lb/>
every person, but we ought to look to the prejudices <lb/>
of the people as well as to their principles in so far <lb/>
as we can avoid every ground of friction and of <lb/>
irritation. So far as Ontario is concerned she has <lb/>
recognized the principle of separate schools. She <lb/>
has given to the Protestant minority and to the <lb/>
Roman Catholic population where they demand it, <lb/>
the privilege of establishing a separate school. <lb/>
That has not been done in the various states of the <lb/>
Union; and I wish to call the attention of the House <lb/>
to the fact that to-day in the Province of Ontario <lb/>
there is a smaller percentage of the Catholic <lb/>
population in the separate schools than there is <lb/>
in the State of New York in the parish schools <lb/>
where there is no provision made for a separate <lb/>
system. There is a smaller percentage of the Roman <lb/>
Catholic population in Ontario in the separate <lb/>
schools than there is in the parish schools of the <lb/>
State of Michigan where they have no separate <lb/>
school system. What is the practical working <lb/>
out of the Michigan system? It is this: When the <lb/>
Roman Catholic community is dissatisfied, or strong <lb/>
enough, they organize themselves voluntarily into <lb/>
a parish school. They employ their own teacher, <lb/>
and there is no public supervision over that teacher. <lb/>
If the people are poor the chances are that the <lb/>
teacher will be a person of rather inferior educa<lb break="no"/>tion, and the instruction given in these parish <lb/>
schools is altogether inferior to that given in the <lb/>
separate schools of the Province of Ontario. In <lb/>
Ontario you have today practically the same class <lb/>
of teachers, possessing the same qualifications in <lb/>

<cb/>

the separate schools that you have in the public <lb/>
schools. They undergo a public examination, they <lb/>
receive certificates in the same way, and since the <lb/>
Catholic population has been given representation <lb/>
on the High School Boards, at large number of the <lb/>
children are attending these High Schools. They <lb/>
are receiving their education, they are being em<lb break="no"/>ployed as teachers, and in many cases they are not <lb/>
giving encouragement to the establishment of sepa<lb break="no"/>rate schools where the public schools give to the <lb/>
Roman Catholic population adequate protection. <lb/>
I say, Sir, there is no public school system on this <lb/>
continent producing more satisfactory results, and <lb/>
being worked out with less friction than the school <lb/>
system of the Province of Ontario. <lb/></p> 

<p>It being six o'clock, the Speaker left the Chair. <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>