<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1875-03-12"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1875-03-12">12 March 1875</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Third Parliament, Second Session</title>.
               
               
               <date when="1875"/>.  
               
               
               <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>C.W. Mitchell, "Free Press", Elgin Street</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="654" to="662"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00654.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00655.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00656.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00657.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00658.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00659.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00660.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00661.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00662.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-07">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00654">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00654.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00655">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00655.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00656">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00656.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00657">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00657.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00658">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00658.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00659">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00659.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00660">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00660.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00661">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00661.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00662">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00662.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="654" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00654.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="num">654</fw> <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</fw>   
    
            <p>[...]aries of Manitoba in the east. The present 
     <lb/>Bill would be applicable to the territory 
     <lb/>of the Dominion east of Manitoba as well 
     <lb/>as to that to the west and north. He 
     <lb/>might mention that application had been 
     <lb/>made on behalf of the Government of 
     <lb/>Manitoba for an enlargement of their terri<lb break="no"/>tory. They proposed, in fact, to have it 
     <lb/>made something like nine or ten times 
     <lb/>larger than it was at present. But there 
     <lb/>were other proposals of that Government 
     <lb/>in connection with this matter which ren<lb break="no"/>dered necessary the postponement of action 
     <lb/>for the present until a conference, can be 
     <lb/>had with the Local Government. It was 
     <lb/>proposed by this Bill to have a Lieutenant- 
     <lb break="yes"/>Governor of the North-West territories 
     <lb/>who would be assisted by a Council. That 
     <lb/>Council would consist of five members ap<lb break="no"/>pointed by the GOVERNOR GENERAL in Coun<lb break="no"/>cil; three stipendiary magistrates or judges, 
     <lb/>to be appointed in a similar manner who 
               <lb/>would be members of the Council <hi rendition="simple:italic">ex-ofiicio</hi>— 
     <lb/>and two others, perhaps the principal In<lb break="no"/>dian Agent and some other person whose 
     <lb/>place of residence and occupation made it 
     <lb/>convenient for them to perform the duties 
     <lb/>that would be required of them. The first 
     <lb/>section of this Bill simply provided that 
     <lb/>the territories formerly known as "Ruperts 
     <lb/>Land, and the North-West territories," 
     <lb/>should continue to be styled and known as 
     <lb/>the North-West territories, and that there 
     <lb/>shall be a Lieutenant Governor appoint<lb break="no"/>ed who shall hold office during the pleasure 
     <lb/>of the GOVERNOR GENERAL and receive in<lb break="no"/>structions in the same way as Lieutenant 
     <lb/>Governors in the Provinces. The third 
     <lb/>section provides for the establishment of the 
     <lb/>Council, and the fourth that the seat of 
     <lb/>Government may from time to time be 
     <lb/>changed by the GOVERNOR GENERAL in 
     <lb/>Council. In the meantime the seat of 
     <lb/>Local Government for the territories shall 
     <lb/>be established at Fort Pelly, that being a 
     <lb/>convenient place to reach the Sascatchewan 
     <lb/>River and Fort Ellis, and other parts of 
     <lb/>the territories, and not beyond reach of the 
     <lb/>telegraph system about being established. 
     <lb/>The Government last season constructed 
     <lb/>buildings there for the North-West 
     <lb/>police force, sufficient to accommodate two 
     <lb/>hundred men, a commandant house, an 
     <lb/>hospital and other buildings ; and these 
     <lb/>buildings could accommodate the officers 
     <lb/>connected with the North West Govern<lb break="no"/>ment without any serious expense. Last 
     <lb/>year there was expended on these build<lb break="no"/>
           
    
            <cb/>
          
     ings something like $30,000. By section 
     <lb/>
     five it was proposed to pay the Lieut. 
     <lb/>
     Governor a salary not exceeding $7,000, 
     <lb/>
     and each Stipendary Magistrate or Judge 
     <lb/>
     a salary not exceedng $3,000, and the 
     <lb/>
     other two members of the Council a salary 
     <lb/>
     not exceeding $1,000; and to the Clerk 
     <lb/>
     of the Council who shall act as Secretary 
     <lb/>
     to the Lieut. Governor a salary not ex<lb break="no"/>ceeding $1,800. Sections six seven and 
     <lb/>
     eight simply provide for the consolidation 
     <lb/>
     of the laws and ordnances now in force in 
     <lb/>
     those territories, and the ninth section 
     <lb/>
     that no ordnance shall be passed by the 
     <lb/>
     Governor in Council or the Lieut. Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor inconsistant with any Act of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Parliament. This section re<lb break="no"/>stricts the jurisdiction of the Council prac<lb break="no"/>tically to that now enjoyed by the Lieut. 
     <lb/>
     Governor of Manitoba acting as Governor 
     <lb/>
     of the North— West Territories, and his 
     <lb/>
     Council. The next few sections provide 
     <lb/>
     for popular Government so far as it could 
     <lb/>
     be established under the circumstances of 
     <lb/>
     the country. The eleventh section pro<lb break="no"/>vides that so soon as the Lieut. Governor 
     <lb/>
     is satisfied by such proof as he may re<lb break="no"/>quire that any portion Of the territory not 
     <lb/>
     exceeding an area of one thousand square 
     <lb/>
     miles contains a population of not 
     <lb/>
     less than one thousand inhabitants 
     <lb/>
     such district may be erected into  
     <lb/>
     an electoral district which shall be 
     <lb/>
     entitled to elect a member of the Council 
     <lb/>
     or as it may be of the Legislative Assembly. 
     <lb/>
     The sub-sections provide the machinery for 
     <lb/>
     holding the elections. The fifth sub—sec<lb break="no"/>tion provides that as soon as the Lieut. 
     <lb/>
     Governor is satisfied that any electoral 
     <lb/>
     district contains a population of two 
     <lb/>
     thousand, exclusive of aliens and unen<lb break="no"/>franchised Indians, he shall issue a writ 
     <lb/>
     for the election of a second member. The 
     <lb/>
     sixth sub-section provides that when the 
     <lb/>
     number of elective members amounts to 
     <lb/>
     twenty-one the council hereinbefore 
     <lb/>
     appointed shall cease  be determined, 
     <lb/>
     and the members so elected shall be con<lb break="no"/>stituted and designated as the Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Assembly of the North—West Territory, 
     <lb/>
     and the powers by this Act vested in the 
     <lb/>
     council shall thenceforth be vested and 
     <lb/>
     exercisable by such Legislative Assembly. 
     <lb/>
     One of the sub—sections provides that every 
     <lb/>
     bona fide resident and householder who 
     <lb/>
     shall have been in the district for twelve 
     <lb/>
     months may vote, and any person entitled 
     <lb/>
     to vote shall be eligible for election. 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="655" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00655.jpg"/>
            
               
               
     <fw type="dateline">MARCH 12, 1875.</fw> <fw type="num">655</fw> 
     
            
          
     Sections twelve to thirty inclusive contain 
     <lb/>
     provisions for the holding of real estate, 
     <lb/>
     and the administration of estates, the law 
     <lb/>
     that prevails in Ontario with regard to 
     <lb/>
    property being introduced. Sections 36, 
     <lb/>to 44 inclusive make provisions for wills 
     <lb/>and their registration; and from 45 to 50 
     <lb/>provisions regarding married women defin<lb break="no"/>ing their rights as to property. Section 
     <lb/>54 provides that the Governor may appoint 
     <lb/>a registrar of deeds in and for the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories and the remunera<lb break="no"/>tion to be paid. Section 52 pro<lb break="no"/>vides for the appointment of a 
     <lb/>Sheriff who shall reside in the 
     <lb/>territory ; and the Lieutenant Governor 
     <lb/>is authorized by the 53d section to have 
     <lb/>local disposition of the police force in and 
     <lb/>for the North—West Territories established 
     <lb/>under the Act respecting the administra<lb break="no"/>tion of justice in those territories. For 
     <lb/>the administration of justice the Lieuten<lb break="no"/>ant Governor is authorized by section 54 
     <lb/>to appoint Justices of the Peace; and the 
     <lb/>Governor in Council may, by ordinances, 
     <lb/>subject to the provisions of this Act, set 
     <lb/>apart any portion of said territories as 
     <lb/>and for a judicial district, and may from 
     <lb/>time to time alter the limits and extent of 
     <lb/>any such district. Section 56 provides 
     <lb/>that a court or courts of civil and crimi<lb break="no"/>nal jurisdiction, shall be held in said ter<lb break="no"/>ritories in every judicial district, and at 
     <lb/>such periods and places as the Lieutenant 
     <lb/>Governor may from time to time alter. 
     <lb/>Section 55 provides authority for the 
     <lb/>appointment of a stipendary magistrate, 
     <lb/>and magistrates within the territories. 
     <lb/>Section 59, and following sections, provide 
     <lb/>the jurisdiction of each stipendary magis<lb break="no"/>trate, and the mode of holding the courts 
     <lb/>for the trial of criminal offences. Section 
     <lb/>68, and following sections, provide for the 
     <lb/>administration of justice in civil cases. 
     <lb/>Section 71, and the sub-sections one to six 
     <lb/>inclusive, contain provisions for excluding 
     <lb/>all intoxicating liquors, prohibiting their 
     <lb/>introduction and their sale in the territor<lb break="no"/>ies. This would give the Dominion a fair 
     <lb/>opportunity to commence with a clean 
     <lb/>slate in this enormous territory, and test 
     <lb/>practically the operation of a prohibitory 
     <lb/>liquor law where there has been no law on 
     <lb/>that or any other subject before. If we 
     <lb/>were able to accomplish prohibition in 
     <lb/>that territory it would enable us the bet<lb break="no"/>ter to accomplish the object that so many 
     <lb/>were petitioning for as regards the whole 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
          
     Dominion. He might say in connection 
     <lb/>
     with this part of the Bill that the officers 
     <lb/>
     of the police force now in the territory 
     <lb/>
     have very stringent instructions about the 
     <lb/>
     destruction of intoxicating liquors, and 
     <lb/>
     Col. McLeod, the officer in command at 
     <lb/>
     Belly river, at the flank of the Rocky 
     <lb/>
     Mountains, had seized a large quantity of 
     <lb/>
     liquor, and on one occasion knocked in 
     <lb/>
    the head of forty-four barrels of 
     <lb/>whiskey. The exclusion of intoxicating 
     <lb/>liquor had already been very beneficial, 
     <lb/>so far at least as regards the condition of 
     <lb/>the Indian tribes, and we had reason to 
     <lb/>believe that it had given the utmost satis<lb break="no"/>faction. The police force would also act 
     <lb/>as revenue officers, assisting the preven<lb break="no"/>tion of smuggling. They collected some 
     <lb/>$1,000 or $5,000 of duties levied upon 
     <lb/>merchandise, in the legitimate course of 
     <lb/>trade, in the months of December and 
     <lb/>January, the duties previous to that time 
     <lb/>not having been levied. The other sec<lb break="no"/>tions of the Act, 72, 73 and 74, simply 
     <lb/>provided for the repeal of the various Acts 
     <lb/>now in force and in order to avoid all con<lb break="no"/>fusion, a schedule was given of the Acts 
     <lb/>now in force, and which would be repealed 
     <lb/>by the enactment of this law. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CAUC1">Hon.Mr. CAUCHUN</persName> asked if the 
     <lb/>place of residence of the Lieut. Governor 
     <lb/>was fixed.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said the 
     <lb/>
     Government had at Fort Pelly all the 
     <lb/>
     buildings necessary to fulfill all the con<lb break="no"/>ditions of a Governor's residence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Right <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir JOHN MACDON<lb break="no"/>ALD</persName> said this wasa Bill of so great import<lb break="no"/>ance that every hon. member of this 
     <lb/>
     House would feel it his duty to consider 
     <lb/>
     it fully, and it might occupy a good deal 
     <lb/>
     of time. However, they must address 
     <lb/>
     themselves to the task. With reference 
     <lb/>
     to the proposed settlement of the bound<lb break="no"/>ary lines, he was sorry to learn that the 
     <lb/>
    suggestions of the late Government 
     <lb/>were not carried cut, and that the 
     <lb/>matter was not referred to the judi<lb break="no"/>cial committee of the Privy Council for an 
     <lb/>authoritative decision. He would like to 
     <lb/>know whether it was the duty, of these 
     <lb/>arbitrators (who would be acceptable, he 
     <lb/>was satisfied, to the country as they were 
     <lb/>to himself) to decide where the line is to 
     <lb/>run, or simply to decide upon aline which 
     <lb/>they would recommend to be adopted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> replied that 
     <lb/>the exact instructions he not yet been<lb/> 
     
            <pb n="656" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00656.jpg"/>
           
            <fw type="num">656</fw> <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</fw>
          
     communicated to the Arbitrator for the 
     <lb/>
       Dominion, but he might say he felt that 
     <lb/>
     the Arbitrators should be left to define 
     <lb/>
     where the line should be, though not 
     <lb/>
     strictly according to the interpretation of 
     <lb/>
     the law, if there should be any doubt on 
     <lb/>
     that score. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN MACDONALD</persName> asked 
     <lb/>
     whether concessions were to be made by 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba or by the Dominion. Accord<lb break="no"/>ing to one contention the head of Lake 
     <lb/>
     Superior belongs to the North-West;  
     <lb/>
      according to the other contention (and he 
     <lb/>thought that would be supported by the 
     <lb/>hon, member for Bothwell) the Province 
     <lb/>of Ontario runs to the Lake of the Woods 
     <lb/>or perhaps further. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName>—Very much further. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN MACDONALD</persName> contended 
     <lb/>
     that this question should be settled. The 
     <lb/>
     Dominion had purchased the whole of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West, and it belonged to Canada, 
     <lb/>
     and therefore the whole Dominion should 
     <lb/>
     know exactly what their property was, 
     <lb/>
     how far it extended, and what was the 
     <lb/>
     boundary of their farm in the first place. 
     <lb/>
     That being once ascertained it might be 
     <lb/>
     well, at all events it would be expedient, 
     <lb/>
     that wherever the line was to be fixed 
     <lb/>
     according to this arbitration, there should 
     <lb/>
     be a boundary defined as the legal bound<lb break="no"/>ary between the North-West and Mani<lb break="no"/>toba. He hoped the award of the arbi<lb break="no"/>trators, whatever it might be, would not 
     <lb/>
     be final, but would be subject to the rati<lb break="no"/>fication of the Government and be sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to Parliament. He wished to know  
     <lb/>whether the award was to be the unani<lb break="no"/>mous decision of the arbitrators or of a 
     <lb/>majority of them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName>—The award 
     <lb/>
     of two will be considered sufficient to set<lb break="no"/>tle the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>   
     <lb/>
     pressed strongly upon the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment that the arbitrators should 
     <lb/>
    be asked to find, first, where the western boun<lb break="no"/>dary line of Ontario was by law, and second, 
     <lb/>the eastern boundary of Manitoba. Then 
     <lb/>they might also be authorized to report a con<lb break="no"/>ventional line, other than the line they might 
     <lb/>say was the legal boundary, as being a 
     <lb/>convenient one considering all the circum<lb break="no"/>stances of the case. With regard to the 
     <lb/>appointment of Lieutenant Governor, the 
     <lb/>hon. gentleman should show some necessity 
     <lb/>for it since the Lieutenant Governor of 
     <lb/>Manitoba was paid, in addition to his 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
       salary, a sum for governing the North- <lb break="yes"/>West Territory as well. That was to 
     <lb/>
     say, he had two commissions ; one as 
     <lb/>
     Lieut. Governor of Manitaba, with a regu<lb break="no"/>lar Ministry, and the other as Lieutenant 
     <lb/>
    Governor of the North-West, which 
     <lb/>might be considered in the light 
     <lb/>of a colony. The hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>should be prepared to show in the second 
     <lb/>reading that there was a necessity for ap<lb break="no"/>pointing an additional Governor just now. 
     <lb/>Manitoba was a very small Province in 
     <lb/>itself, with a very small population, and 
     <lb/>if one Lieutenant Governor was suffiient 
     <lb/>for the Government of Ontario, surely 
     <lb/>one ought to be enough for Manitoba and 
     <lb/>the North-West for some time to come at 
     <lb/>all events. All the country lying west of 
     <lb/>Lake Superior and east of Manitoba was 
     <lb/>considered part of the North-West, and 
     <lb/>could not be governed as well from Fort 
     <lb/>Pelly as from Fort Garry. He approved 
     <lb/>of the provision relating to Stipendiary 
     <lb/>Magistrates, but thought there was no 
     <lb/>necessity for the clause introducing the 
     <lb/>popular element. It seemed to him that 
     <lb/>the Government should not clog them<lb break="no"/>selves with such a provision. At the 
     <lb/>right time they could pass an Act 
     <lb/>introducing the popular element into the 
     <lb/>Government of the North-West. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said the 
     <lb/>
     North-West Council was in existence, and 
     <lb/>
     could be increased to 21 members. Though 
     <lb/>
     several vacancies had occurred in it, the 
     <lb/>
    Government made no appointments. 
     <lb/>Every one of those gentlemen 
     <lb/>was styled honorable until hon<lb break="no"/>orables became very plentiful in 
     <lb/>in Manitoba. The Government found 
     <lb/>them a little Parliament acting for the 
     <lb/>North-West, though they resided in the 
     <lb/>Province, and some of them were never in 
     <lb/>the territories. The Government had 
     <lb/>repeated demands from them during the 
     <lb/>last year for large sums of money. They 
     <lb/>made a requisition once for $10,000, and 
     <lb/>actually cost the country during the last 
     <lb/>part of the year $3,000. It was evident 
     <lb/>that the council would cost the country 
     <lb/>as much as a Government in the territory, 
     <lb/>without being as efficient. In some places 
     <lb/>within the territories there is already a 
     <lb/>very considerable population. At Fort 
     <lb/>Albert there are 500 people other than 
     <lb/>  Indians who have settled there, and that 
     <lb/>  population would soon be increased to 
     <lb/>three or four times the number. There 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="657" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00657.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="dateline">MARCH 12, 1875.</fw> <fw type="num">657</fw> 
     
            
           
     is a very considerable settlement where 
     <lb/>
     the North-West Police was stationed, on 
     <lb/>
     the Belly River, on the flank of the 
     <lb/>
     Rocky Mountains, and as this district is 
     <lb/>
     one of the finest portions of the territory, 
     <lb/>
    it would be rapidly settled. It seemed to 
     <lb/>be exceedingly desirable, at the earliest 
     <lb/>point of time, that there should be a firm 
     <lb/>Government established within the terri<lb break="no"/>tories and that the Governor should reside 
     <lb/>several hundred miles west of the present 
     <lb/>point of authority, in order to exercisea pro<lb break="no"/>per influence for the maintenance of peace, 
     <lb/>or overlooking Indian affairs, and generally 
     <lb/>helping the Government to establish law 
     <lb/>and order throughout the territories. 
     <lb/>The Government had ascertained, from 
     <lb/>the most authentic source, that within 
     <lb/>the last eighteen months there were very 
     <lb/>nearly 150 murders committed in the 
     <lb/>North-West territories, and no person had 
     <lb/>been brought to trial. No doubt those 
     <lb/>were mostly slain in Indian fights with 
     <lb/>traders from Missouri and Montana, of a 
     <lb/>most reckless character, who introduced 
     <lb/>the vilest passions of human nature into 
     <lb/>the territories and slaughtered the poor 
     <lb/>people with their improved fire-arms and 
     <lb/>dealing death and destruction by their 
     <lb/>vile intoxicating liquors. It seemed very 
     <lb/>clear that there was an absolute necessity 
     <lb/>for the establishment of a firm Govern<lb break="no"/>ment within the boundaries of the territor<lb break="no"/>ies, and that provisions should be made for 
     <lb/>a popular Government, for the establish<lb break="no"/>ment of schools and of some municipal 
     <lb/>system which would enable the people to 
     <lb/>mantain roads, bridges, and other local 
     <lb/>works. That connot be done under the 
     <lb/>old laws, for although they were suitable 
     <lb/>for a short period of time, it was now evi<lb break="no"/>dent that the country required an impro<lb break="no"/>ved system. The Government were, 
     <lb/>therefore, quite justified in submitting this 
     <lb/>measure to Parliament, and no doubt 
     <lb/>whenever the Bill went into operation it 
     <lb/>would immensely promote the settlement 
     <lb/>of the country, for nothing was so essen<lb break="no"/>tial to the settlement of the country as the 
     <lb/>maintenance of law and order within its 
     <lb/>bounds. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!--Unsure about Mitchell perName-->
    <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MITC3">Hon. Mr. MITCHELL</persName> thought it was 
     <lb/>
     very desirable that the commissioners 
     <lb/>
     should be appointed as proposed. The 
     <lb/>
     Government having decided that they 
     <lb/>
     would not follow the course suggested by 
     <lb/>
     the late Government of having the Privy 
     <lb/>
     Council decide what were the local rights 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
           
     of the Dominion of Canada, but would 
     <lb/>
     refer the matter to the arbitrament of two 
     <lb/>
     commissioners, it was equally desirable 
     <lb/>
     that they should not only decide where it 
     <lb/>
     was desirable to define the boundaries of 
     <lb/>
     Ontario, but also to decide what were the 
     <lb/>
     legal and proper boundaries between On<lb break="no"/>tario and the North-West territories. 
     <lb/>
     The late Government had always recog<lb break="no"/>nized that the western boundary line of 
     <lb/>
     Ontario was two miles east of Fort Wil<lb break="no"/>liam. During the existence of the On<lb break="no"/>tario Government, of which the hon. 
     <lb/>
     First Minister was a member, they 
     <lb/>
     claimed and exercised jurisdiction over a 
     <lb/>
     district west of Fort William. As a 
     <lb/>
     representative of one of the smaller Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, he feared that Ontario possesses 
     <lb/>
     at the present time too much power, and 
     <lb/>
     that the great power which it exercised 
     <lb/>
     might act to the injury of the smaller 
     <lb/>
     Provinces, which had equal rights with 
     <lb/>
     Ontario in the North-West territory. In 
     <lb/>
     place of extending the boundaries of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba westward, it might be desirable 
     <lb/>
     to extend them eastward and northward 
     <lb/>
     toward Ontario, so as to give the Province 
     <lb/>
     of Manitoba water communication with 
     <lb/>
     the great lakes. He suggested to 
     <lb/>
     the Government the desirability when 
     <lb/>
     giving instructions to the commissioners 
     <lb/>
     of having them clearly defined, and the 
     <lb/>
     conclusion arrived at by the commission<lb break="no"/>ers should not be final, but subject to the 
     <lb/>
     approval of the Dominion Parliament. 
     <lb/>
    </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Hon. Mr. BLAKE</persName> said the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Northumberland had referred to 
     <lb/>
     the pre-eminent power of Ontario in this 
     <lb/>
     House, and was apprehensive that the 
     <lb/>
     results of that arbitration would be 
     <lb/>
     affected by that power. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man knew the character and reputation 
     <lb/>
     of the public men of his own Province 
     <lb/>
     better than he (Mr. BLAKE) could tell 
     <lb/>
     him ; but such an insinuation had never 
     <lb/>
     been cast on a public man as cast by the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member on the Ex-Governor WIL<lb break="no"/>MOT of his own Province, who was one of 
     <lb/>
     the commissioners.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MITC3">Hon. Mr. MITCHELL</persName> said he did not 
     <lb/>
     intend to cast any imputation on the 
     <lb/>
     character of the commissioners. He had 
     <lb/>
     confidence in both Judge RICHARDS and 
     <lb/>
     Judge WILMOT, but he knew the pre<lb break="no"/>eminent power which a great power like 
     <lb/>
     Ontario exercised over men's minds. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Hon. Mr. BLAKE</persName>—Has the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman been swayed ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="658" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00658.jpg"/>
            
           <fw type="num">658</fw> <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</fw> 
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:MITC3">Hon. Mr. MITCHELL</persName>—Very often. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Hon. Mr. BLAKE</persName> said he had no 
     <lb/>doubt whatever, that the arbitrators would 
     <lb/>discharge their duty to the best of their 
     <lb/>ability. Under the Imperial Act it was 
     <lb/>only by the joint legislative action 
     <lb/>of the Provinces affected, and of the 
     <lb/>Dominion that the boundaries, whatever 
     <lb/>they were, could be altered ; therefore, it 
     <lb/>was only an authoritative exposition of 
     <lb/>the law itself that would be obtained, and 
     <lb/>anything else would be merely suggestive. 
     <lb/>The task which the Ministry had set for 
     <lb/>itself was the most important it was pos<lb break="no"/>sible to conceive. To found primary 
     <lb/>institutions under which we hope to see 
     <lb/>hundreds of thousands, and the more san<lb break="no"/>guine among us think millions of men and 
     <lb/>families settled and flourishing, was one of 
     <lb/>the noblest undertakings that could be 
     <lb/>entered upon by any legislative body, and 
     <lb/>it was no small indication of the power 
     <lb/>and true position of this Dominion that 
     <lb/>Parliament should be engaged to-day in 
     <lb/>that important task. He agreed with the 
     <lb/>hon. member for Kingston that the task 
     <lb/>was one that required time, consider<lb break="no"/>ation and deliberation, and they must take 
     <lb/>care that no false steps were made in such 
     <lb/>a work. He did not agree with that 
     <lb/>right hon. gentleman that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment ought to repeal his errors. The 
     <lb/>right hon. gentleman had tried the insti<lb break="no"/>tutions for the North-West territories 
     <lb/>which he now asked the House to frame, 
     <lb/>and for the same reason as he had given 
     <lb/>to-day—that it would be better for the 
     <lb/>Dominion Government to keep matters in 
     <lb/>their own hands and decide what was best 
     <lb/>for the future. He (Mr. BLAKE) believed 
     <lb/>that it was essential to our obtaining a 
     <lb/>large immigration to the North-West that 
     <lb/>we should tell the people beforehand 
     <lb/>what those rights were to be in the coun<lb break="no"/>try in which we invited them to settle. 
     <lb/>It was interesting to the people to know 
     <lb/>that at the very earliest moment there 
     <lb/>was a sufficient aggregate of population 
     <lb/>within a reasonable distance, that aggrega<lb break="no"/>tion would have a voice in the self-govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the territories, and he believed 
     <lb/>the Dominion Government was wise, 
     <lb/>(although the measure might be brought 
     <lb/>down very late this session and 
     <lb/>it might be found impossible to 
     <lb/>give it due consideration) in determin<lb break="no"/>ing in advance of settlement what the 
     <lb/>character of the institutions of the country 
     <lb/>
         

            
            <cb/>
           
     should be in which we invite people to 
     <lb/>
     settle. He did not agree with the policy 
     <lb/>
     of asking people to settle in that western 
     <lb/>
     country, and tell them that a paternal 
     <lb/>
     Government would look after them, and 
     <lb/>
     would give them such institutions as the 
     <lb/>
     Government thought suitable. We had 
     <lb/>
     better let the people know their fate 
     <lb/>
     politically and otherwise before they set<lb break="no"/>tled there. The task to be discharged 
     <lb/>
     now, or at some future time, was one of 
     <lb/>
     considerable importance. And amongst 
     <lb/>
     the difficulties was the determining of 
     <lb/>
     what the range of power of the Council 
     <lb/>
     would be in the first place, assuming that 
     <lb/>
     its character would be that of a mixed 
     <lb/>
     nominative and elective council, as he un<lb break="no"/>derstood it would be of the First Minis<lb break="no"/>ter; the Council, at a subsequent period 
     <lb/>
     assuming the position of a Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Assembly when the population was suffi<lb break="no"/>cient to entitle it to assume that position. 
     <lb/>
     He did not hear from the hon. First Min<lb break="no"/>ister any distinct enunciation of the 
     <lb/>
     powers committed to the Council and 
     <lb/>
     afterwards to the Assembly. Looking 
     <lb/>
     over the Bill hastily it seemed that the 
     <lb/>
     powers were too general, that the powers 
     <lb/>
     were those of the British North Ameri<lb break="no"/>can Act with respect to peace, order and 
     <lb/>
     good government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN MACDONALD</persName>—Too wide. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Hon. Mr. BLAKE</persName>—It gave the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil all the powers practically enjoyed by 
     <lb/>
     this Parliament and the Local Legislatures 
     <lb/>
     together; and it would be proper to re<lb break="no"/>strict and define their powers in all mat<lb break="no"/>ters connected with Municipal Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and provision should be made at the 
     <lb/>
     earliest possible moment for municipal 
     <lb/>
     institutions, local taxation and improve<lb break="no"/>ments. He regarded it as essential under 
     <lb/>
     the circumstances of the country, and in 
     <lb/>
     view of the deliberation during the last 
     <lb/>
    few days that a general principle 
     <lb/>should be laid down in the Bill 
     <lb/>with respect to public instruction. 
     <lb/>He did believe that we ought not to intro<lb break="no"/>duce into that territory the heart burnings 
     <lb/>and difficulties with which certain other 
     <lb/>portions of this Dominion and other 
     <lb/>countries had been affected. It seemed to 
     <lb/>him, having regard to the fact that, as far 
     <lb/>as we could expect at present, the general 
     <lb/>character of that population would be 
     <lb/>somewhat analogous to the population of 
     <lb/>Ontario, that there should be some pro<lb break="no"/>vision in the constitution by which they 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="659" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00659.jpg"/>
           
           <fw type="dateline">MARCH 12, 1875.</fw> <fw type="num">659</fw>
           
           
     should have conferred upon them the same 
     <lb/>
     rights and privileges in regard to religious 
     <lb/>
     instruction as those possessed by the people 
     <lb/>
     of the Province of Ontario. The principles 
     <lb/>
     of local self-government and the settling of 
     <lb/>
     the question of public instruction seemed 
     <lb/>
     to him ought to be the cardinal principles 
     <lb/>
     of the measure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said the 
     <lb/>
     words "Governor-in-Council" in the 8th 
     <lb/>
     clause of the Bill meant not the Lieutenant 
     <lb/>
     Governor but the GOVERNOR GENERAL. 
     <lb/>
     Practically the legislation of the territory 
     <lb/>
     would be in the hands of the Government 
     <lb/>
     here at Ottawa. The Lieutenant Governor 
     <lb/>
     in Council would have power to make 
     <lb/>
     only such laws and ordinances as the Bill 
     <lb/>
     provided for, and it would be for Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, when the population had increased 
     <lb/>
     sufficiently, to confer upon them more 
     <lb/>
     extensive powers than it was proposed to 
     <lb/>
     give them under the present measure. As 
     <lb/>
    not in the first place attract his attention, 
     <lb/>but when he came to the subject of local 
     <lb/>taxation he was reminded of it. Not 
     <lb/>having had time before to insert a clause 
     <lb/>on the subject, he proposed to do so when 
     <lb/>the Bill was in committee. The clause 
     <lb/>provided that the Lieutenant Governor, 
     <lb/>by and with the consent of his Council or 
     <lb/>Assembly, as the case might be, should 
     <lb/>pass all necessary ordinances in respect of 
     <lb/>education, but it would be specially pro 
     <lb/>vided that the majority of the rate-payers 
     <lb/>might establish such schools and impose 
     <lb/>such necessary assessment as they might 
     <lb/>think fit; and that the minority of the 
     <lb/>rate-payers, whether Protestant or Roman 
     <lb/>Catholic, might establish separate schools: 
     <lb/>and such rate-payers would be liable only 
     <lb/>to such educational assessments as they 
     <lb/>might impose upon themselves. This, he 
     <lb/>hoped would meet the objection offered by 
     <lb/>the hon. member for South Bruce. There 
     <lb/>might be some amendments found neces<lb break="no"/>sary in the Bill, but he thought it would 
     <lb/>be found generally speaking to meet the 
     <lb/>requirements of the country. However, 
     <lb/>the Government would be very glad to 
     <lb/>avail themselves as far as possible of such 
     <lb/>suggestions as might be made to them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT3">Mr. D. A. SMITH</persName> thought the pro<lb break="no"/>visions of the Bill before the House were on 
     <lb/>the whole calculated to do good service in 
     <lb/>the North-West if honestly and properly 
     <lb/>carried out. A very great deal depended 
     <lb/>
           
   
           
            <cb/>
           
     upon the administration of the law and upon 
     <lb/>
     the character of those who were appointed to 
     <lb/>
     carry it out. In this respect they had suf<lb break="no"/>fered much in Manitoba. It was well 
     <lb/>
     known that sufficient care had not been 
     <lb/>
     taken in that respect. He did not say this 
     <lb/>
     as a reproach to the right hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Kingston, who, he believed, had under the 
     <lb/>
     circumstances done the best he could. At 
     <lb/>
     the time there was very little knowledge 
     <lb/>
     of the country in Canada, and perhaps even 
     <lb/>
     now there was not as much as could be 
     <lb/>
     desired. He believed the right hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man sent to the country those whom he 
     <lb/>
     thought best fitted to perform the duties. 
     <lb/>
     Much had been done within the past year 
     <lb/>
     towards introducing law and good order in 
     <lb/>
     that country by sending out an efficient 
     <lb/>
     body of police. He said this with the 
     <lb/>
     greater pleasure because in the first in<lb break="no"/>stance he was afraid they were not very effi<lb break="no"/>cient, and so much had been said to the 
     <lb/>
     discredit of the force in the early part of 
     <lb/>
     the season that they were received with a 
     <lb/>
     little distrust ; but he had in his possession 
     <lb/>
     a letter from a person who had been out 
     <lb/>
     just where Major McLEOD was, and which 
     <lb/>
     stated that officer was doing his duty ex<lb break="no"/>cellently. He had cleared the country of 
     <lb/>
     the whiskey traders, and it was now peace 
     <lb/>
     and quiet where last year it was dangerous 
     <lb/>
     for any one to be. He (Mr. SMITH) 
     <lb/>
     thought this spoke a great deal for the 
     <lb/>
     efficiency of the Mounted Police, and was 
     <lb/>
     a strong commentary upon what had al<lb break="no"/>ready been done for the Government of 
     <lb/>
     the country. The means for preserving 
     <lb/>
     the peace were formerly quite insufficient. 
     <lb/>
     He thought the provisions of the Bill now 
     <lb/>
     brought in were calculated to serve the 
     <lb/>
     purpose for which the measure was intend<lb break="no"/>ed for many years to come. At present 
     <lb/>
     the Council of the North-West was pro<lb break="no"/>bably not just exactly such a body as it 
     <lb/>
     ought to be. They were under the 
     <lb/>
     very great disadvantage of being 
     <lb/>
     far removed from such portions 
     <lb/>
     of the territory as were at all settled. The 
     <lb/>
     principal settlements were 500 or 600 
     <lb/>
     miles from Manitoba, which was quite 
     <lb/>
    equal to 3,000 or 4,000 miles in this 
     <lb/>eastern country, because the means of 
     <lb/>communication were very bad. He felt 
     <lb/>that under the circumstances of that 
     <lb/>country it would be a great 
     <lb/>benefit to have a Governor and 
     <lb/>Council within the territory. He did not 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="660" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00660.jpg"/>
               
            <fw type="num">660</fw>
            <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</fw>
           
     doubt that the Council would be an effi<lb break="no"/>cient one, or at any rate he hoped that it 
     <lb/>
     would be, since so much depended upon 
     <lb/>
     the character of those appointed to it. He 
     <lb/>
     thought it was a wise provision not to at 
     <lb/>
     once extend legislative powers to the new 
     <lb/>
     territory. In the chief settlement, Prince 
     <lb/>
     Albert,there were not at present more than 
     <lb/>
     500 inhabitants, but when they increased to 
     <lb/>
     1,000 or more, and the other settlements had 
     <lb/>
     increased in the same ratio, he thought it 
     <lb/>
     would be right to give them local legisla<lb break="no"/>tive powers. His objection to the North- <lb break="yes"/>West Council as at present constituted 
     <lb/>
     was that many of its members knew 
     <lb/>
     nothing more of the country than gentle<lb break="no"/>men on the floor of this House who had 
     <lb/>
     simply heard of the North-West as they 
     <lb/>
     had of other far distant countries. How<lb break="no"/>ever, there were atleast six of them who knew 
     <lb/>
     it intimately, but it would be a most invi<lb break="no"/>dious thing for these gentlemen to get up 
     <lb/>
     and tell their fellow-councillors that they 
     <lb/>
     knew nothing at all about it. It would be 
     <lb/>
     admitted that very frequently those who 
     <lb/>
     were the least acquainted with a subject 
     <lb/>
     were the most ready to give advice. He 
     <lb/>
     thought on the whole it was very much 
     <lb/>
     better that they should have the Council 
     <lb/>
     proposed in this Bill, and that those who 
     <lb/>
     formed the new Council should have an 
     <lb/>
     intimate local knowledge of the country, 
     <lb/>
     and be connected with its interests. The 
     <lb/>
     right hon. member for Kingston seemed to 
     <lb/>
     think that it would be an objection to 
     <lb/>
    have the Council at Fort Pelly, having in 
     <lb/>view the interests of the country eastward 
     <lb/>of Fort Garry. He was himself of opinion 
     <lb/>that the interests of that country for 
     <lb/>some time would be of such small im<lb break="no"/>portance that the location of the Council 
     <lb/>would not be a matter of such great con<lb break="no"/>sequence. With regard to the disputed 
     <lb/>boundary between Manitoba and Ontario, 
     <lb/>the people there would be very glad to 
     <lb/>find that a port on Lake Superior belonged 
     <lb/>to them by right, but he hoped that 
     <lb/>whether it did or not the people of Ontario 
     <lb/>would give it to them as a matter of grace. 
     <lb/>The point brought up by the hon. member 
     <lb/>for South Ontario was an important one, 
     <lb/>and he was glad to find that the First 
     <lb/>Minister intended to introduce a provision 
     <lb/>in Committee, dealing with the subject. 
     <lb/>He had not noticed from the explanations 
     <lb/>given that there was any intention to give 
     <lb/>a representative to the North-West at 
     <lb/>Ottawa. Without some such provision he 
     <lb/>
           
   
          
            <cb/>
           
     did not see how the North-West could 
     <lb/>
     have a voice in the legislation of this 
     <lb/>
     Dominion, and he strongly contended that 
     <lb/>
     there should be at least one member to 
     <lb/>
     represent its interests here. It would give 
     <lb/>
     a great deal of satisfaction in this country, 
     <lb/>
     and he thought it would be at least 
     <lb/>
     a matter of justice to the North-West. 
     <lb/>
     He hoped stringent measures would be 
     <lb/>
     taken to prevent the introduction of goods. 
     <lb/>
     without payment of duty, as such practice 
     <lb/>
     was injurious to the honest merchants 
     <lb/>
     who paid the duties. At present the 
     <lb/>
     revenue laws were evaded by bringing in 
     <lb/>
     goods by way of British Columbia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SCHU1">Mr. SCHULTZ</persName> said that those who 
     <lb/>were acquainted with the North-West 
     <lb/>Territory would agree with him that it 
     <lb/>was a most difficult matter to establish a 
     <lb/>proper and efficient system of Government 
     <lb/>there. He was very much pleased with 
     <lb/>the general features of the Bill. He dis<lb break="no"/>sented from the view of the hon. member 
     <lb/>for Kingston that the Lieut. Governor of 
     <lb/>Manitoba could efficiently administer the 
     <lb/>Government of the territories. That sys<lb break="no"/>tem had proved a failure, and though he 
     <lb/>was a member of the council he must 
     <lb/>frankly admit that it was impossible for 
     <lb/>them under the circumstances to efficiently 
     <lb/>carry out the laws in the territory. He 
     <lb/>believed with the member for South Bruce 
     <lb/>that we must have a strong Government 
     <lb/>in that territory. There was a moral 
     <lb/>power in the cocked hat of a Governor, 
     <lb/>and in the coat of a policeman. Large 
     <lb/>powers should be given to the proposed 
     <lb/>new council. It was not advisable in his 
     <lb/>opinion to give representative institutions 
     <lb/>to that territory just now. However, he 
     <lb/>would discuss the details of the measure 
     <lb/>at a future stage, and he hoped the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment would receive in a kindly spirit 
     <lb/>the suggestions of those who were familar 
     <lb/>with the condition and wants of that 
     <lb/>country. With regard to the mounted 
     <lb/>police, he must say that under its present 
     <lb/>able commander it had proved a very 
     <lb/>efficient force. He regretted that the 
     <lb/>Government decided upon Fort Pelly as 
     <lb/>the seat of Government for the North. 
     <lb/>West, as in his opinion it possessed no 
     <lb/>recommendation except the fact that it 
     <lb/>would have telegraph communication. 
     <lb/>However, as there was a provision in the 
     <lb/>Bill for a change in the seat of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, if it was deemed advisable he would 
     <lb/>raise no objection on that head. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
            <pb n="661" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00661.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="dateline">MARCH 12, 1875</fw> <fw type="num">661</fw>
           
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> said there were several 
     <lb/>
     important features in this Bill which 
     <lb/>
     would require special attention. One was 
     <lb/>
     that relating to the powers given to 
     <lb/>
     the Lieut. Governor in Council. The 
     <lb/>
     Premier spoke of their having power to 
     <lb/>
     establish schools, build roads and bridges 
     <lb/>
     and do other works of a municipal character. 
     <lb/>
     It was extremely doubtful whether the 
     <lb/>
    Governor in Council could have any of 
     <lb/>these powers. It was proposed to furnish 
     <lb/>the money for these objects out of the 
     <lb/>Dominion Treasury then it might be done, 
     <lb/>but the Crown itself had no power to im<lb break="no"/>pose taxes upon any portion of the com<lb break="no"/>munity, and of course could not delegate 
     <lb/>to any Lieut. Governor in Council powers 
     <lb/>which it did not itself possess. It could 
     <lb/>not authorize a Governor in Council to 
     <lb/>establish a municipal system and provide 
     <lb/>for the taxation of the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>—It 
     <lb/>
     can be done by statute. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName>—That is another matter. If 
     <lb/>
     it was intended, therefore, that these things 
     <lb/>
     should be done, it seemed to him provision 
     <lb/>
     must be made in the Bill for their being 
     <lb/>
     done by Parliament. There was another 
     <lb/>
     matter it seemed to him ought not to be 
     <lb/>
     disregarded; and that was the terms and 
     <lb/>
     conditions under which these people would 
     <lb/>
     ultimately be formed into a Province. It 
     <lb/>
     would be better that the people who settle 
     <lb/>
     that territory should know beforehand the 
     <lb/>
     terms and conditions under which they 
     <lb/>
     would become an organized part of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. He saw no objection, when the 
     <lb/>
     population became sufficiently large, to al<lb break="no"/>lowing that territory to be represented in the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Parliament before it was organized 
     <lb/>
     into a Province. By and by we would 
     <lb/>
     be called upon, when Provinces came to 
     <lb/>
     be organized in that territory, to state 
     <lb/>
     what liabilities the Dominion should 
     <lb/>
     assume, and what revenues should be 
     <lb/>
     given to the Local Government, and it 
     <lb/>
     seemed to him it was just as well that 
     <lb/>
     this should be done at the beginning so 
     <lb/>
     that there would be no room for dispute 
     <lb/>
     or difficulty in the future. If some defi<lb break="no"/>nite plan was adopted, the people would 
     <lb/>
     become accustomed to it, and no embar<lb break="no"/>rassment or trouble would arise when it 
     <lb/>
     came to be carried into effect. Those who 
     <lb/>
     observed the American territorial system 
     <lb/>
     of government would notice that from the 
     <lb/>
     tune the first government was organized 
     <lb/>
    under the ordinance enacted by Congress 
     <lb/>
           
           
            <cb/>
           
     in 1787, till the establishment of the last 
     <lb/>
     territorial government, there was scarcely 
     <lb/>
     any difference in the plan of government, 
     <lb/>
     and they had never found it necessary to 
     <lb/>
    depart from the general principle laid 
     <lb/>down in the ordinance of 1787. It 
     <lb/>seemed to him we ought not to refuse to 
     <lb/>profit by the experience of others under 
     <lb/>similar circumstances to our own. In 
     <lb/>order to accomplish the object he had sug<lb break="no"/>gested, the Government should know what 
     <lb/>moneys they had expended on public 
     <lb/>buildings and works in these territories, 
     <lb/>which might afterwards become the pro<lb break="no"/>perty of the Local Government, and in 
     <lb/>that case it would only be fair that when 
     <lb/>the time came for the admission of the terri<lb break="no"/>tory into the Union the money so expended 
     <lb/>could be charged to it as a public debt. 
     <lb/>He saw no difficulty in this being done, 
     <lb/>but thought it should be embraced in the 
     <lb/>fundamental law. The hon. member for 
     <lb/>Northumberland had stated that Mani<lb break="no"/>toba should have a sea-port town and its 
     <lb/>boundary ought to be extended to the 
     <lb/>shores of Lake Superior. If the hon. 
     <lb/>gentleman would look into the question, 
     <lb/>he wonld find Ontario had something to 
     <lb/>say on that matter, and he had no hesita<lb break="no"/>tion in saying seeing that it was to be 
     <lb/>decided on judicial principles he did not 
     <lb/>think it was competent for the Dominion 
     <lb/>Government to decide it otherwise than 
     <lb/>was proposed. Under the Quebec Act of 
     <lb/>1774, the western limit of what now 
     <lb/>remained to us as the old Province of 
     <lb/>Quebec was fixed at the forks of the Sask<lb break="no"/>atchewan, and the head waters of the 
     <lb/>Mississippi. By an Order in Council that 
     <lb/>was adopted ln 1791, it was declared that 
     <lb/>the western limit of the western portion 
     <lb/>of Quebec, erected into Upper Canada, 
     <lb/>shall extend to what is known as the 
     <lb/>western limit of Canada under the French. 
     <lb/>That, he apprehended, would extend to 
     <lb/>the Rocky Mountains. That country Was 
     <lb/>taken possession of by the French. They 
     <lb/>established forts at several points in the 
     <lb/>Red River territory and the most west<lb break="no"/>ern fort was at the forks of the Saskatch<lb break="no"/>ewan. They had appointed Captain 
     <lb/>LA CORNE to govern the territory under a 
     <lb/>license from Quebec. The whole coun<lb break="no"/>try was occupied by the French Govern<lb break="no"/>ment as part of Canada, and was made by 
     <lb/>the Order in Council of 1791, part of the 
     <lb/>present Province of Ontario. The late 
     <lb/>Government had organized the Province of 
     <lb/>
         
    
            <pb n="662" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-03-12_Page_00662.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">662</fw> <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</fw>
            
           Manitoba within those limits but he<lb/>apprehended if a judicial decision should<lb/>be sought from this arbitration instead of<lb/>extending the boundary of Manitoba to<lb/>the shores of Lake Superior, this Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment would be called upon to compen<lb break="no"/>sate Ontario for a very considerable por<lb break="no"/>tion they had acquired from that Pro<lb break="no"/>vince.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Bill was read a first time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>