<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1875-04-02"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1875-04-02">2 April 1875</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Third Parliament, Second Session</title>.
               
               
               <date when="1875"/>.  
               
               
               <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>C.W. Mitchell, "Free Press", Elgin Street</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="1048" to="1049"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-02_Page_01048.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-02_Page_01049.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-11">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-02_Page_01048">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-02_Page_01048.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-02_Page_01049">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-02_Page_01049.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1048" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-02_Page_01048.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="num">1048</fw> <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</fw>
            
           <head rendition="simple:centre">THE NORTH-WEST GOVERNMENT.</head>
            
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr MACKENZIE</persName> moved the 
     <lb/>third reading of Bill to amend and consoli<lb break="no"/>date the laws respecting the North-West<lb/>Territories.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN MACDONALD</persName> said he did <lb/>not object to the third reading and passage<lb/>of this Bill, but he would again impress upon<lb/>the leader of the Government the expe<lb break="no"/>diency, from an economical point of view,<lb/>of governing the North-West Territories<lb/>from Fort Garry. A commission could be <lb/>issued to the Lieut. Governor of Manitoba<lb/>to act for the present as Lieut. Governor<lb/>of the North-West. He had plenty of<lb/>time on his hands, and there was no reason<lb/>in the world why he should not direct his<lb/>attention to the government of the whole<lb/>of the North-West for the present. The <lb/>objection of the hon. Premier that the <lb/>North-West Council had proved a failure,<lb/>because none of its members residing west<lb/>of Manitoba was fully answered by the <lb/>hon. member for Selkirk who stated that<lb/>
          
            <pb n="1049" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-02_Page_01049.jpg"/>
          
          <fw type="dateline">APRIL 2, 1875.</fw> <fw type="num">1049</fw>
           
     at least six of these gentlemen were 
     <lb/>scattered through the territory and knew<lb/>all about it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> received the<lb/>suggestion of the hon. member, in the <lb/>spirit in which it was offered, but could<lb/>not adopt it. If he had not regarded this<lb/>measure as a necessity he would not have<lb/>introduced it. The Lieut. Governor, as <lb/>one of the commissioners who accom<lb break="no"/>panied the Minister of the Interior to<lb/>negotiate a treaty with the Indians,<lb/>although only absent three weeks from<lb/>Manitoba and distant about 250 miles<lb/>from that Province was obligated to issue a<lb/>commission to the Chief Justice to act as <lb/>Lieut. Governor of Manitoba in his<lb/>absence. That was, to say the least, incon<lb break="no"/>venient, and the inconvenience would be <lb/>increased, of course, in proportion to the <lb/>length of absence required in administrat<lb break="no"/>ing the affairs in the North-West. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was read a third time and<lb/>passed.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>