<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-03-06"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-03-06">6 March 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
  
                    

          <date when="1905"/>.   
          

           <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="2043" to="2048"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-06_Page_2043.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-06_Page_2045.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-06_Page_2047.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-01-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-01-17">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-06_Page_2043">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-06_Page_2043.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-06_Page_2045">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-06_Page_2045.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-06_Page_2047">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-06_Page_2047.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="2043" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-06_Page_2043.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">2043</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">2044</fw>

<!-- GL, 2017-01-17, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day --> 
            <!--<p>
     have no doubt that the sad event will be<lb/>appropriately referred to on Monday next, I<lb/>beg to move that the House do now adjourn.<lb/> 
               <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and House adjourned 
     <lb/>at 8:20 p.m.<lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head>
     HOUSE OF COMMONS.  
     </head>
   
            <p>
     MONDAY, MARCH 6, 1905. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>The SPEAKER took the Chair at Three<lb/>o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>FIRST READING.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p>Bill (No. 98) to incorporate the Imperial<lb/>Guarantee and Accident Insurance Company<lb/>of Canada.-Mr. Belcourt. <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>PROVINCIAL GOVERNMENT IN THE<lb/>NORTHWEST—PERSONAL EX<lb break="no"/>PLANATION.<lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Mr. R. L. BORDEN (Carleton, Ont.). Be<lb break="no"/>fore the Orders of the Day are called, I<lb/>wish to inquire of the government whether<lb/>or not there are to be any changes made in<lb/>the Bills that have been introduced by <lb/>the Prime Minister for the establishment of new<lb/>provinces in the Northwest Territories ? I<lb/>venture to mention this because I see in<lb/>newspapers that are supposed to be in the <lb/>confidence of the government, rumours-nay<lb/>more than rumours, direct statements-that<lb/>there are to be certain changes made in <lb/>provisions of these Bills. In connection<lb/>with this matter, it seems to me that the<lb/>practice followed by the Prime Minister with<lb/>regard to these Bills, and also the Grand<lb/>Trunk Pacific Bill of two years ago, is not a<lb/>practice supported by any competent authori<lb break="no"/>ty. I refer to the practice of introducing a<lb/>Bill with which the House is not at all<lb/>familiar, and proceeding to debate it in a <lb/>manner which is usual only upon the second<lb/>reading. I am aware, of course, that it is<lb/>not only perfectly proper, but that it is<lb/>,usual to make a succinct statement explana<lb break="no"/>tory of the provisions of a Bill upon its<lb/>first reading, but I do not find any authori<lb break="no"/>ty for proceeding to debate a Bull upon its<lb/>first reading, before the measures is laid be<lb break="no"/>fore the House in printed form and before<lb/>the House has had an opportunity of becom<lb break="no"/>ing familiar with its provisions. I am well<lb/>aware that it was the intention of the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to have favoured me personally<lb/>with a copy of the Bill some little time in<lb/>advance of its introduction ; but, unfor<lb break="no"/>tunately, for reasons which were no doubt <lb/>beyond the control of the government, that<lb/>intention was not carried out, and I received<lb/>the Bill only about the time the Prime Min<lb break="no"/>ister rose to introduce it. But even if I<lb/>had received the Bull say twenty-four hours<lb/>in advance, as might perhaps have been very<lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     proper under the circumstances, that would 
     <lb/>not have afforded an opportunity to other<lb/>members of the House who are equally in<lb break="no"/>terested with myself in discussion the mea<lb break="no"/>sure, if it was to be discussed at that stage, <lb/>to make themselves thoroughly acquainted <lb/>with the scope and meaning of the provi<lb break="no"/>sions of the Bill before proceeding to dis<lb break="no"/>cuss it. I mention this because it seems to<lb/>me that if this practice is to be followed by<lb/>the government in the future in regard to<lb/>important measures pf this kind, it would<lb/>be well to have each Bill printed two or<lb/>three days in advance of its introduction,<lb/>so that, if there is to be a discussion on the<lb/>first reading, the House can proceed in<lb break="no"/>telligently with that discussion, and can<lb/>have an opportunity beforehand of giving<lb/>the Bill that consideration which, of course,<lb/>is absolutely necessary to a measure of this<lb/>kind.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Now, I have asked as to changes in the<lb/> Bill. If they have not come to any conclu<lb break="no"/>sion with regard to changes in the Bill ; if<lb/>they have not come to any conclusions up <lb/>to the present time, I would very respect<lb break="no"/>fully suggest to the Prime Minister that, <lb/>if any changes of importance are to be made<lb/>in the provisions of this Bill before the<lb/>second reading is reached, it would<lb/> be highly in the interest of the country as<lb/>
               <lb/>a whole, that the Prime Minister should<lb/> acquaint the House with the nature of<lb/>those changes a reasonable time before<lb/>the second reading is brought on. I have<lb/> no doubt that the right hon. gentleman will<lb/>assent to this as a reasonable request, and<lb/>that it will be complied with. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Let me add just one world of personal ex<lb break="no"/>planation with regard to myself. I do not<lb/>usually trouble the House with very much <lb/>personal explanation about statements with<lb/>regard to myself in the public press ; but<lb/>there have been a number of suggestions or <lb/>statements made as to my recent absence <lb/>from the House which I think must proceed<lb/>upon an entire misunderstanding. I quote<lb/>only one of these, which is not couched<lb/>perhaps in a very offensive form, but which<lb/>conveys a suggestion which is absolutely<lb/>untrue :<lb/>
            </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">That the constant factors in our politics are<lb/>not wholly unknown to some of our Conservative<lb/>friends the tactful absence of Mr. Borden from<lb/>Ottawa at this juncture abundantly illustrates.<lb/>
            </quote>

            <p>And so in other journals, some of the<lb/>suggestions being couched in a somewhat<lb/>more impertinent form than that which I<lb/>have just read. I had no intention of ab<lb break="no"/>senting myself from the city of Ottawa up<lb/>to four o'clock of the afternoon of last<lb/>Wednesday week, when I received a tele<lb break="no"/>gram announcing the sudden death of a<lb/>very near and dear relative under very dis<lb break="no"/>tressing circumstances. On the following<lb/>
       
            <pb n="2045" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-06_Page_2045.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">2045</fw> <fw type="dateline">MARCH 6, 1905</fw> <fw type="num">2046</fw>
         
     morning I left for my home in Halifax for 
     <lb/>
     that reason and that reason alone, expecting 
     <lb/>
     to return to Ottawa by noon of the follow<lb break="no"/>ing Tuesday. As I have already mentioned 
     <lb/>
     in this House, I did not reach Halifax on 
     <lb/>
     Friday evening owing to the snow blockade, 
     <lb/>
     but I reached there on Monday evening, 
     <lb/>
     more than seventy-two hours late. I left 
     <lb/>
     Halifax on Wednesday morning and arrived 
     <lb/>
     at Ottawa on Thursday evening. I think it 
     <lb/>
     is due to myself to make this explanation, 
     <lb/>
     because I do not think that in my public 
     <lb/>
     life I have usually been found wanting in 
     <lb/>
     my attendance on parliament ; nor do I 
     <lb/>
     think that anything has been displayed in 
     <lb/>
     my public career which would lead any 
     <lb/>
     journalist of even the most suspicious type 
     <lb/>
     to suppose that 1 would have gone to Hali<lb break="no"/>fax on this particular occasion if it had not 
     <lb/>
     been absolutely necessary, in my judgment, 
     <lb/>
     that I should do so. I apologize to you, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Speaker, and to the House for having been 
     <lb/>
     compelled in self defence to inﬂict this state<lb break="no"/>ment of private and personal affairs upon 
     <lb/>
     the House. and I know that under the cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances the House will pardon me for 
     <lb/>
     doing so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There is one other matter which I forgot 
     <lb/>
     to mention. On the introduction of this Bill 
     <lb/>
     I brought to the attention of the government 
     <lb/>
     the fact that a number of returns which had 
     <lb/>
     been moved for had not yet been brought 
     <lb/>
     down. I also pointed out that there was 
     <lb/>
     certain information which I thought would 
     <lb/>
     be necessary for the intelligent discussion 
     <lb/>
     of the questions that are to be considered in 
     <lb/>
     the House, and that it should be brought 
     <lb/>
     down in a shape to be readily available to 
     <lb/>
     every member of the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Sir WILFRID LAURIER. Mr. Speaker, 
     <lb/>
     1 think I voice the feeling of the House 
     <lb/>
     when I say to my hon. friend that no 
     <lb/>
     apology was needed from him as to his 
     <lb/>
     absence from the House. Unfortunately, we 
     <lb/>
     are all victims of the press, and if we were 
     <lb/>
     to take very seriously everything that is 
     <lb/>
     said of us, our repose would be considerably 
     <lb/>
     affected. But I think we can make allow<lb break="no"/>ance for the newspaper men in their desire 
     <lb/>
     to give the latest news. Everybody knows 
     <lb/>
     the painful circumstances under which my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend had to leave this House, and no 
     <lb/>
     one, I can assure him, speaking for this 
     <lb/>
     side, had any suspicion that his absence was 
     <lb/>
     due to any other cause than domestic afflic<lb break="no"/>tion. With regard to the main question 
     <lb/>
     which my hon. friend has put to me, I do 
     <lb/>
     not agree with him as to the constitutional 
     <lb/>
     practice. I admit that in Canada the dis<lb break="no"/>cussion generally takes place on the second 
     <lb/>
     reading of a Bill. This is so in England 
     <lb/>
     also ; but my hon. friend is aware that in 
     <lb/>
     England every important measure, I do not 
     <lb/>
     say invariably, but as a rule, is explained 
     <lb/>
     by the minister in charge of the Bill upon 
     <lb/>
     its presentation for the ﬁrst reading. There<lb break="no"/>upon the matter is left for some time for 
     <lb/>
     the deliberation of the House and the 
     <lb/>
     
            <cb/>
            
     country. This practice I have followed on 
     <lb/>
     this occasion, and I believe yet that it is 
     <lb/>
     the best method. The government have ex<lb break="no"/>plained their policy, and have left it to the 
     <lb/>
     judgment of the House and the country. 
     <lb/>
     If the Bill were to be presented without any 
     <lb/>
     explanation, the country would be without 
     <lb/>
     the real reasons which prompted the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment in introducing it. If the ﬁrst read<lb break="no"/>ing were to be followed immediately by a 
     <lb/>
     discussion, I think the House, especially the 
     <lb/>
     opposition, would be taken at a disadvant<lb break="no"/>age, and the government might be charged 
     <lb/>
     with sharp practice ; but if the Bill is left 
     <lb/>
     for a reasonable time after being introduc<lb break="no"/>ed, the opposition have an opportunity to 
     <lb/>
     prepare and explain their views upon it. I 
     <lb/>
     still think this is the best policy that can be 
     <lb/>
     followed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     My hon. friend has asked me if it was 
     <lb/>
     the intention of the government to introduce 
     <lb/>
     changes into this Bill. I have only to reply 
     <lb/>
     that it is open to the party who introduces 
     <lb/>
     a Bill to change it at all times. I have seen 
     <lb/>
     few Bills introduced into this House or any 
     <lb/>
     deliberative assembly which have gone 
     <lb/>
     through the third reading without being 
     <lb/>
     considerably amended, and the more im<lb break="no"/>portant the Bill the more likely is it to be 
     <lb/>
     amended. Even Bills of a very minor im<lb break="no"/>portance are very often amended so as to 
     <lb/>
     be hardly recognizable when they leave the 
     <lb/>
     committee. Whether or not any changes 
     <lb/>
     shall be made will be known as the Bill 
     <lb/>
     goes through its various stages ; and if 
     <lb/>
     any should be made, they shall be made in 
     <lb/>
     the ordinary course. With regard to the 
     <lb/>
     information asked for by my hon. friend, I 
     <lb/>
     shall endeavour to comply with his request. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. FOSTER. It seems to me that in ad 
     <lb/>
     dition to the information already asked, 
     <lb/>
     it would be advisable that a deﬁnite sum<lb break="no"/>mary be furnished of the different changes, 
     <lb/>
     dating from confederation, in the ﬁnancial 
     <lb/>
     terms which have taken place to the bene<lb break="no"/>ﬁt of the provinces. There has been legis<lb break="no"/>lation in various years, adding to the pro<lb break="no"/>vincial subsidies. If a concise memo. could 
     <lb/>
     be made of all these changes with reference 
     <lb/>
     to each of the provinces, showing the addi<lb break="no"/>tions that each one has received to its sub<lb break="no"/>sidy and matters of that kind, that would 
     <lb/>
     help us very much when we come to discuss 
     <lb/>
     the ﬁnancial clauses of this measure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. FIELDING. I agree with my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend that a memo. of that character would 
     <lb/>
     be useful, and shall endeavour to have it 
     <lb/>
     produced before the second reading of the 
     <lb/>
     Bill is proceeded with. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. PETER WHITE. It would be de<lb break="no"/>sirable that in the case of a long speech such 
     <lb/>
     as that which was delivered by the right 
     <lb/>
     hon. the leader of the government when intro<lb break="no"/>ducing this Bill, a copy of the Bill should be 
     <lb/>
     also at the time, before the House. It would 
     <lb/>
     be well hereafter that members of the 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="2047" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-06_Page_2047.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">2047</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">2048</fw>
       
     House, should be given the opportunity of 
     <lb/>
     becoming conversant with the contents of 
     <lb/>
     the measures introduced, when the speech 
     <lb/>
     explained that measure on its introduction is 
     <lb/>
     delivered. Let me quote from Sir John 
     <lb/>
     Bourinot : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     It is usual on the introduction of a Bill—on 
     <lb/>
     the motion for leave—to explain clearly and 
     <lb/>
     succinctly its main provisions ; but it is not 
     <lb/>
     the practice to debate it at length at that stage, 
     <lb/>
     such discussion being more properly and con<lb break="no"/>veniently deferred to the second reading when 
     <lb/>
     the Bill is printed and the House in a position 
     <lb/>
     to discuss its principle. Sometimes, however, 
     <lb/>
     a short discussion may arise on some features 
     <lb/>
     of the Bill on the motion for its introduction, 
     <lb/>
     as there is no rule to prevent a debate. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>
     That is quite true, but, when on an im<lb break="no"/>portant Bill, such as that creating new pro<lb break="no"/>vinces in the Northwest Territories, the main 
     <lb/>
     speech of its introducer is made on the mo<lb break="no"/>tion for leave to introduce, I think the Bill 
     <lb/>
     itself should then be in the hands of hon. 
     <lb/>
     members, so that they might be seized of 
     <lb/>
     its contents before it is introduced. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Sir WILFRID LAURIER. So far as my 
     <lb/>
     information goes, and I think it is accurate, 
     <lb/>
     this is not the English practice. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. WHITE. I do not know what the 
     <lb/>
     English practice is. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Sir WILFRID LAURIER. In this coun<lb break="no"/>try we have been accustomed to explain 
     <lb/>
     Bills on their second reading, but in Eng<lb break="no"/>land all important measures are fully ex<lb break="no"/>posed and explained on their ﬁrst reading 
     <lb/>
     by the minister in charge. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. R. L. BORDEN. I do not think there 
     <lb/>
     is much difference between the right hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman and myself regarding the prac<lb break="no"/>tice, but the question is whether the prac<lb break="no"/>tice is carried out, and the only difference 
     <lb/>
     between us is as to the practice which was 
     <lb/>
     pursued in this case. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">

            <head>PRIVATE BILLS.</head>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>NORTHWEST TELEPHONE COMPANY.</head>
            
<p>
     House in committee on Bill (No. 28) to 
     <lb/>
    incorporate the Northwest Telephone Com<lb break="no"/>pany.—Mr. Turriff. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. BOLE. The point I desire to raise 
     <lb/>
     is whether it is advisable we should endorse 
     <lb/>
     the principle of incorporating more tele<lb break="no"/>phones. A Bill somewhat similar to this 
     <lb/>
     was introduced in the Manitoba Legislature 
     <lb/>
     a few weeks ago and was opposed by the 
     <lb/>
     council of the city of Winnipeg, which I 
     <lb/>
     have the honour to represent in this House. 
     <lb/>
     They opposed it chiefly on the ground that 
     <lb/>
     as the policy of taking over the business of 
     <lb/>
     telephone companies by the government was 
     <lb/>
     in the air, it would not be advisable to incor<lb break="no"/>porate any more companies, and the Bill 
     <lb/>
     was sent back to the committee in order that 
     <lb/>
           
   
            <!--<p>
     Mr. WHITE. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

            <cb/>
          
     they might carefully inquire into the whole 
     <lb/>
     question of having telephone business con<lb break="no"/>ducted by the government. When the Bill 
     <lb/>
     before us was introduced into this House, I 
     <lb/>
     regret very much that I was not present and 
     <lb/>
     therefore unable to put on record my object<lb break="no"/>ion ; and I deem it now my duty to reﬂect 
     <lb/>
     the opinion expressed by the city of Winni<lb break="no"/>peg, an opinion with which I am in full 
     <lb/>
     sympathy and accord. I have in my hands 
     <lb/>
     a resolution passed by the city council of 
     <lb/>
     Winnipeg on February 20, last, which is as 
     <lb/>
     follows : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     That as this council have a reasonable hope 
     <lb/>
     that the telephone system may in the near 
     <lb/>
     future be under government control, they would 
     <lb/>
     look with disfavour on the granting of any new 
     <lb/>
     telephone charters as complicating the situation, 
     <lb/>
     and hereby instruct our solicitors to oppose 
     <lb/>
     any such legislation now contemplated at Ot<lb break="no"/>tawa. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>
     With the spirit of that resolution I am 
     <lb/>
     fully in harmony. A telephone business, 
     <lb/>
     being essentially a monopoly and an im<lb break="no"/>portant public utility, it is dangerous to have 
     <lb/>
     it in the hands of a private corporation. A 
     <lb/>
     great many cities throughout the United 
     <lb/>
     States, and I think in Canada also, have 
     <lb/>
     made thorough inquiries into this subject. 
     <lb/>
     The city of San Francisco had an application 
     <lb/>
     before it for a charter for a local exchange, 
     <lb/>
     but representations were made to the council 
     <lb/>
     that the telephone business was essentially 
     <lb/>
     a monopoly, and therefore no new telephone 
     <lb/>
     company should be chartered and the appli<lb break="no"/>cation was not granted. Instead, the city of 
     <lb/>
     San Francisco appointed a commission to 
     <lb/>
     inquire into the whole subject, and the com<lb break="no"/>mission reported. This is the last clause 
     <lb/>
     of its report, as published in the bulletin of 
     <lb/>
     the League of American Municipalities in 
     <lb/>
     November, 1904 : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     Inasmuch as a telephone was essentially a 
     <lb/>
     monopoly, that” it would simply increase the 
     <lb/>
     burden on the citizens when they increased the 
     <lb/>
     number of telephone companies. There is no 
     <lb/>
     other public utility with which we come in con<lb break="no"/>tact where there are so many objections to com<lb break="no"/>petition. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>
     That is the mandate of a commission 
     <lb/>
     which has made extensive inquiries, which 
     <lb/>
     visited all the important cities on the Paciﬁc 
     <lb/>
     coast and examined into the conditions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. R. L. BORDEN. Will the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman tell us exactly what commission 
     <lb/>
     that was, I did not quite hear him. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. BOLE. A commission was appointed 
     <lb/>
     by the city of San Francisco to inquire into 
     <lb/>
     the whole question of the telephone busi<lb break="no"/>ness. An application was made by certain 
     <lb/>
     promoters to the city of San Francisco for 
     <lb/>
     permission to construct and operate a rival 
     <lb/>
     telephone business in San Francisco. Re<lb break="no"/>presentations were made to the city council 
     <lb/>
     that to multiply telephone lines would be 
     <lb/>
     a nuisance, and the city council therefore [...] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>