<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1897-05-25"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1897-05-25">25 May 1897</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Eighth Parliament, Second Session</title>.
          <date when="1897"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="2797" to="2798"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-05-25_Page_02797.html"/>
               </item>
     
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-05">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-05-25_Page_02797">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-05-25_Page_02797.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="2797" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-05-25_Page_02797.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2797</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 25, 1897]</fw> <fw type="num">2798</fw>
            
            
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES ACT.</head>
        
        
        
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName> (Mr.   
     <lb/>
     Sifton) moved for leave to introduce Bill 
     <lb/>
     (No. 114) to amend the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories Act. He said : The provisions of this 
     <lb/>
     Bill are somewhat miscellaneous in their 
     <lb/>
     character. I need not explain them at, 
     <lb/>
     length now, because they will hardly be. 
     <lb/>
     understood until the printed Bill is in the 
     <lb/>
     hands of hon. members. I may say, how<lb break="no"/>ever, generally speaking, that the main 
     <lb/>
     provision of the Bill is to change the con<lb break="no"/>stitution of the government of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories in this respect, that whereas 
     <lb/>
     they have what is called an executive com<lb break="no"/>mittee, a committee that was entirely a 
     <lb/>
     statutory body and I fancy without prece<lb break="no"/>dents in our constitutional system—under 
     <lb/>
     the proposed Bill they will have an execu<lb break="no"/>tive council which will, to the extent of the 
     <lb/>
     statutory powers conferred upon the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the North-west Territories by the 
     <lb/>
     Act, exercise such powers in the same way 
     <lb/>
     as the executive council of a province. The 
     <lb/>
     effect will be rather as to the methods in 
     <lb/>
     which the Government is carried on than 
     <lb/>
     as to any extension of the powers of the 
     <lb/>
     Government itself. The natural effect of 
     <lb/>
     this provision will be that the system of 
     <lb/>
     responsible government in the North-west 
     <lb/>
     Territories will be more clearly defined and 
     <lb/>
     established than it has been heretofore. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Various clauses of the Bill are amend<lb break="no"/>ments for the purpose of bringing the Act 
     <lb/>into conformity with this provision. The 
     <lb/>other amendments which are not mere 
     <lb/>verbal changes. are in the first place. a pro<lb break="no"/>vision which places it within the power of 
     <lb/>the legislative assembly of the Territories: 
     <lb/>to deal with the qualifications of justices 
     <lb/>of the peace. that being a purely local mat<lb break="no"/>ter which may be better disposed of by 
     <lb/>themselves than by the Parliament of Can-. 
     <lb/>ada. The appointment of clerks of the 
     <lb/>courts in the Territories is also given to the 
     <lb/>executive government of the Territorie. 
     <lb/>The sheriffs and clerks of the court have 
     <lb/>heretofore been appointed by the Federal 
     <lb/>Government. The sheriffs will continue to 
     <lb/>be appointed by the Federal Government, 
     <lb/>but by this Bill, if it receives the assent 
     <lb/>of the House. the clerks, who are paid en<lb break="no"/>tirely by fees, will be appointed by the 
     <lb/>Territorial Government. Another clause 
     <lb/>refers to the qualifications of police magis<lb break="no"/>trates. Another clause gives the Territorial 
     <lb/>assembly power to pass ordinances respect<lb break="no"/>ing the road allowances. I may say that 
     <lb/>the fact that the Department of the Interior 
     <lb/>has been compelled to deal with every local 
     <lb/>application respecting road allowance in the 
     <lb/>Territories, has been a source of great an<lb break="no"/>noyance and difficulty to the people there, 
     <lb/>and also of considerable annoyance to the 
     <lb/>department itself. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I am very glad the hon. 
     <lb/>
     Minister (Mr. Sifton) is introducing this Bill. 
     <lb/>
     I should like to ask him one question. He 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <cb/>
 
 
     used the expression " Executive Council of. 
     <lb/>
    the province." Does he intend to change 
     <lb/>the name from " Executive Council of the 
     <lb/>North-west Territories ?" 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. No; 
     <lb/>
     the word "province" is not used in the 
     <lb/>
     Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. The hon. Minister used that 
     <lb/>
     word in his speech. So far as I can see, 
     <lb/>
     the Bill is designed to bring in reforms which 
     <lb/>
     I have contended for year after year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LARI1">Mr. LaRIVIERE</persName>. Are there any changes 
     <lb/>
     with regard to the limitation of the legisla<lb break="no"/>tive powers of the legislature ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. It 
     <lb/>
     just occurs to me—I may say in answer to 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman's question—that I omit<lb break="no"/>ted to state one feature of the Bill. It 
     <lb/>
     gives the Territorial Assembly power to deal 
     <lb/>
     with questions of insurance, the incorpora<lb break="no"/>tion of local insurance companies, and other 
     <lb/>
     necessary insurance business. This is a 
     <lb/>
     power possessed by the provincial legisla<lb break="no"/>tures, but heretofore not possessed by the 
     <lb/>
     Territorial Assembly. Difficulties have arisen 
     <lb/>
     through the lack of local regulations, and it 
     <lb/>
     is to meet these difficulties that this change 
     <lb/>
     has been made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>