<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1895-04-25"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1895-04-25">25 April 1895</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, Fifth Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1895"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="197" to="198"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1895-04-25_Page_00197.html"/>
               </item>

            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-10">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-10">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1895-04-25_Page_00197">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1895-04-25_Page_00197.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="197" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1895-04-25_Page_00197.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">197</fw> <fw type="dateline">[APRIL 24, 1895]</fw> <fw type="num">198</fw>
            <p>
               
               
     [...] only to persons having contracts with the 
     <lb/>
     Government. I propose to make the penal<lb break="no"/>ties apply to directors and otlicers of rail<lb break="no"/>way companies who have subsidies, or loans,  
     <lb/>
     or advances, or bonuses, from the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada. And I think, Sir, that this 
     <lb/>
     will meet the view of the House and of the 
     <lb/>
     public. I hope at a later stage to discuss 
     <lb/>
     the matter more fully. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
            <div type="section">
               
               
               
               
            <head rendition="simple:centre">DOMINION NOTES ACT.<lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART3">Sir RICHARD CARTWRIGHT</persName>. Excuse 
     <lb/>
     me ; I suppose that the object of the Bill 
     <lb/>
     to amend the Dominion Notes Act is to put 
     <lb/>
     in the proviso which, in a most extraordin<lb break="no"/>ary fashion, was dropped from the measure 
     <lb/>
     last year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. Precisely that.</p>
            
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
               
               <head rendition="simple:centre">DOMINION ELECTIONS ACT.</head>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OBRI1">Mr. O'BRIEN</persName> (for Mr. McCarthy) moved 
     <lb/>
     for leave to introduce Bill No. 16 to amend  
     <lb/>
     the Dominion Elections Act. He said : The 
     <lb/>
     object of this Bill, Mr. Speaker, may be 
     <lb/>
     very briefly stated. Of its provisions—one 
     <lb/>
     is a most important one—to make railway 
     <lb/>
     companies that carry voters to or from the 
     <lb/>
     polls free of charge, guilty of a cor<lb break="no"/>rupt practice, and also to make any per<lb break="no"/>sons who abet the railway companies in 
     <lb/>
     doing so guilty of a corrupt practice. In fact, 
     <lb/>
     the object is to put a stop to the practice 
     <lb/>
     which is well known to prevail, especially 
     <lb/>
     as shown during recent elections, of rail<lb break="no"/>way companies making themselves election 
     <lb/>
     agents and carrying voters free from one end  
     <lb/>
     of the Dominion to the other to please the 
     <lb/>
     Government of the day. The other portion 
     <lb/>
     of the Bill relates to acts of personation. 
     <lb/>
      We have on our statute a clause referring to 
     <lb/>
     this offence. The Ontario Legislature has 
     <lb/>
     passed an Act which provides for summary 
     <lb/>
     process in cases of personation. Any one 
     <lb/>
     can easily understand that cases of persona<lb break="no"/>tion will frequently arise, especially in the 
     <lb/>
     more remote districts of the country, where 
     <lb/>
     the population is sparse, and where strangers  
     <lb/>
    can come in and poll votes on behalf of 
     <lb/>persons who are not present. This Bill en<lb break="no"/>acts, as an amendment to the existing law, 
     <lb/>a similar provision to that of the provincial 
     <lb/>Act, which provides for summary process 
     <lb/>in regard to personation. These are the 
     <lb/>main provisions of the Bill. I therefore beg 
     <lb/>leave to move, seconded by Mr. Bryson, 
     <lb/>for leave to introduce this Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES-DUAL 
     <lb/>
     LANGUAGE,  ETC. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:OBRI1">Mr. O'BRIEN</persName> (for Mr. McCarthy) moved 
     <lb/>
     for leave to introduce Bill (No. 17) to amend  
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories Act. He said : 
     <lb/>
     On behalf of Mr. McCarthy, I beg to intro<lb break="no"/>duce this Bill, which has been introduced 
     <lb/>
     on several previous occasions in this House 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <cb/>
        
        
     and which has not yet met with the sup<lb break="no"/>port which its advocates hoped it would<lb/>meet with and which they believe it will <lb/>ultimately meet with. I need say but little <lb/>with regard to the provisions of the Bill,<lb/>for they are well known. The object is to<lb/>give the North-west Territories power to<lb/>deal with the subject of education and to<lb/>abolish the use of the French language as<lb/>official in these Territories. I have said,<lb/>Mr. Speaker, that this Bill has not met with<lb/>the support in this House which we think it<lb/>
    ought to meet with, it has met with a very 
     <lb/>large support throughout the country, ex<lb break="no"/>cept in the province of Quebec. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. Hear, hear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:OBRI1">Mr. O'BRIEN</persName>. Which the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     who interrupts me so ably represents ; and, 
     <lb/>
     Sir, the public have come to the conclusion 
     <lb/>
     that they are not the demagogues who strive 
     <lb/>by every means in their power to do away 
     <lb/>with these distinctions of race and religion 
     <lb/>which are the cause of nearly all our trou<lb break="no"/>bles ; they are the real demagogues who fat<lb break="no"/>ten and batten and grow into political power 
     <lb/>and influence by means of these distinctions. 
     <lb/> Sir, it is within the knowledge of this House 
     <lb/> that gentlemen who are hardly qualified to 
     <lb/>fill the position of third class clerks have 
     <lb/>been put in high office in the Cabinet, and 
     <lb/>have been retained there from year to year, 
     <lb/>from one administration to another. Kept 
     <lb/>there, and kept there why ? Not on account 
     <lb/> of their merits, because nature never gave 
     <lb/>them any such qualifications as to entitle 
     <lb/>them to fill these positions, but simply and 
     <lb/>solely because they represented a certain 
     <lb/>race and a certain religion. And, Sir, the 
     <lb/>hon. Minister of Marine and Fisheries is a 
     <lb/>case in point. The. hon. gentleman illus<lb break="no"/>trated his position most admirably on a re<lb break="no"/>cent occasion. The hon. gentleman referred 
     <lb/> —or perhaps it would be more parliamentary 
     <lb/>to say reference was made—to the power 
     <lb/>which the late Sir John Macdonald had of 
     <lb/>judging character and choosing men, very 
     <lb/> seldom making mistakes in that respect. 
     <lb/> Well Sir, Sir John Macdonald made no mis<lb break="no"/>take in the case of the Minister of Marine 
     <lb/> and Fisheries. He made no mistake because 
     <lb/> he never thought that with all his powers 
     <lb/> it was possible to make a statesman of the 
     <lb/>hon. gentleman, but he did believe—and that 
     <lb/> belief has been justified by events—that the 
     <lb/>hon. gentleman would make a most admir<lb break="no"/>able placeman. A most admirable placeman 
     <lb/>he has been, a most admirable placeman he 
     <lb/>still continues to be. I do not propose to 
     <lb/> say anything further with reference to this 
     <lb/> Bill, but I beg to move, second by Mr. 
     <lb/>Denison, for leave to introduce the Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            </div>
            
            <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     FIRST READING.</head> 
  
  <p>
     Bill (No. 18) to prevent the importation and 
     <lb/>
     immigration of foreigners and aliens under [...]
     <lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>