<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1876-03-07"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1876-03-07">7 March 1876</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Third Parliament, Third Session</title>.
          <date when="1976"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
          <publisher>Maclean, Roger &amp; Co., Wellington Street</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="461" to="462"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-07_Page_00461.html"/> 
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-07_Page_00462.html"/> 
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-11">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-07_Page_00461">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-07_Page_00461.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-07_Page_00462">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-07_Page_00462.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="461" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-07_Page_00461.jpg"/>
            
            
            <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">The North-West Territories.</hi></fw> <fw type="dateline">[MARCH 7, 1876.]</fw> <fw type="num">461</fw> 
    
   
     <head>THE NORTH WEST TERRITORIES.</head> 
     
            <p>
     On the motion of the <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. Mac<lb break="no"/>kenzie</persName>, the House went into Com<lb break="no"/>mittee, Mr. Mills in the chair, on the<lb/>Act respecting the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> stated that 
     <lb/>in order to meet the views of his hon.<lb/>friend opposite, he proposed to intro<lb break="no"/>duce a preamable as follows:—Whereas<lb/>it is expedient, pending the settlement<lb/>of the North-West Territories, to create<lb/>a separate territory of the eastern por<lb break="no"/>tion of the North-West Territories,<lb/>therefore Her Majesty, &amp;c.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     With regard to the proposition made 
     <lb/>by his hon. friend from British Colum<lb break="no"/>bia, that the territory north of<lb/>British Columbia and the 60th parallel<lb/>should be provided for in this Bill,<lb/>he would reply that having examined<lb/>the map carefully he found that this<lb/>would not be as remote from the seat of<lb/>Government of British Columbia, as<lb/>from the seat of Government of the<lb/>North-West Territories. They proposed<lb/>in order to prevent any possible tem<lb break="no"/>porary inconvenience, to give British<lb/>Columbia magistrates current jurisdic<lb break="no"/>tion in that part of the territory lying<lb/>north of the Columbia and west of the<lb/>Mackenzie River, and the 120th<lb/>parallel. This country would be placed<lb/>
               
            <cb/>
          
     under the authority of existing laws. 
     <lb/>He proposed to fill the blank in the 1st<lb/>section by inserting after the word<lb/>" district," the title Keewatin, which<lb/>would be the name of the new territory,<lb/>signifying the North Land; also to<lb/>fill up blanks in the 4th section, by<lb/>inserting the words " not exceeding<lb/>ten, and not less than five."<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KIRK3">Mr. KIRKPATRICK</persName> took objection 
     <lb/>to the 6th clause on the ground that<lb/>too much power would be given to the<lb/>Lieutenant Governor in Council—the<lb/>power of amending or repealing any of<lb/>the laws passed by the Parliament of<lb/>Canada. In the 11th section it was<lb/>declared that certain laws should be<lb/>applicable to the District—criminal<lb/>laws for instance, so peculiarly under<lb/>Federal jurisdiction. The power in ques<lb break="no"/>tion was greater than that conferred<lb/>upon Local Legislatures. He suggested<lb/>in consequence that the last part of the<lb/>6th clause should be struck out, as a<lb/>year's delay respecting such legislation<lb/>could do no harm.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Hon. Mr. BLAKE</persName> said there was no   
               <lb/>no doubt a good deal to be said in<lb/>favour of what the hon. gentleman re<lb break="no"/>marked, but there had been some ex<lb break="no"/>perience of this kind of legislation be<lb break="no"/>fore, and there was no reason to sup<lb break="no"/>pose from it that there was anything<lb/>improper in this clause. No ordinance<lb/>of the North-West Council would have<lb/>force unless marked "urgent," and<lb/>even then it would be subject to dis<lb break="no"/>allowance. The proposition was simply<lb/>to keep the <hi rendition="simple:italic">status quo</hi> in this terri<lb break="no"/>tory until it was either annexed to<lb/>Manitoba or otherwise dealt with so<lb/>as to be in possession of provincial<lb/>rights and privileges.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The clause, and the two following, 
     <lb/>were adopted.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On clause nine, 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MOUSSEAU</persName> said this clause 
     <lb/>
     seemed to empower the Government 
     <lb/>of the New Province to repeal clause<lb/>11 of the Act of last Session securing<lb/>separate schools to the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories. He wished to know<lb/>if this was the case.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Hon. Mr. BLAKE</persName> said the 11th 
     <lb/>clause of the North-West Territories<lb/>Act was not yet in force, and would<lb/>not apply to any of these territories<lb/>until the Act was proclaimed. It was<lb/>
           
            <pb n="462" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1876-03-07_Page_00462.jpg"/>
            
               
               <fw type="num">462</fw> <fw type="running"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Law Relating to Violence, Threats and Molestations.</hi></fw> <fw type="running">[COMMONS.]</fw>
           
   
          
     a clause which could only come into 
     <lb/>force practically in connection with a<lb/>system of taxation, no provision for<lb/>which was made in this portion of the<lb/>territories so long as it remained under<lb/>this form of Government. The future<lb/>of these territories would be either<lb/>one of two things — they would be<lb/>annexed to Manitoba, or they would<lb/>be detached from Keewatin and re-<lb break="yes"/>annexed to the North-West. In either<lb/>case the rights of the minority<lb/>would be protected. There was no in<lb break="no"/>tention on the part of the Government<lb/>to depart from the general principle of<lb/>the 11th clause. If the territories were<lb/>attached to Manitoba they would be<lb/>subject to the laws of that Province; if<lb/>to the North-West, they would come<lb/>under the 11th clause of the Act of<lb/>last Session.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName> — If I 
     <lb/>understand it, by simply proclaiming<lb/>the Act of 1875 this 11th clause will<lb/>come into force.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName>—Certainly.     
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The clause and the following one   
     <lb/>were adopted.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On clause 11, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. BUNSTER</persName> moved to strike out 
     <lb/>the provision prohibiting the sale of<lb/>intoxicating liquors in the territory.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The motion lost and the clause<lb/>was adopted.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The remaining clauses of the Bill<lb/>were adopted without discussion.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On the motion to adopt the preamble.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SCHU1">Mr. SCHULTZ</persName> said a more euphon<lb break="no"/>ious name than Keewatin might have<lb/>been selection, and he would take occa<lb break="no"/>sion to suggest one before the third<lb/>reading of the Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The preamble was adopted and the<lb/>Committee rose and reported the Bill<lb/>as amended.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The amendments having been con<lb break="no"/>curred in the Bill was read the third<lb/>time and passed.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>