<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1897-06-15"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1897-06-15">15 June 1897</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Eighth Parliament, Second Session</title>.
          <date when="1897"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="4109" to="4118"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04109.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04111.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04113.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04115.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04117.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-05">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04109">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04109.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04111">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04111.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04113">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04113.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04115">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04115.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04117">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04117.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="4109" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04109.jpg"/>
         
            <fw type="dateline">[JUNE 15, 1897]</fw> <fw type="num">4110</fw>
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES.</head>
            
            
            <p>
     Bill (No. 114) further to amend the Acts 
     <lb/>
     respecting the North-west, was read the 
     <lb/>
     second time, and the House resolved itself 
     <lb/>
     into committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     (In the Committee.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On section 2, 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     2. The paragraph lettered (c.) of section 2 of the 
     <lb/>
     said Act is hereby repealed and the following 
     <lb/>
     substituted therefor :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "c. The expression ' Lieutenant-Governor in 
     <lb/>
     Council' means the Lieutenant-Governor of the 
     <lb/>
     Territories, by and with the advice and consent 
     <lb/>
     of the Executive Council of the Territories, or in 
     <lb/>
     conjunction with the Executive Council of the 
     <lb/>
     Territories, as the case may be." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. 'What is the difference ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName> 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Sifton). We are simply bringing the 
     <lb/>
     definition of Lieutenant-Governor in Council 
     <lb/>
     in the Territories into line with the defini<lb break="no"/>tion of Lieutenant-Governor in Council in 
     <lb/>
     the provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Sir CHARLES TUPPER. You are taking 
     <lb/>
     away the personal action of the Lieutenant- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Governor and making him act with his 
     <lb/>
     Council. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="4111" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04111.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">4111</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">4112</fw>
            
            
            <p>
     On section 8, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     8. Subsection one of section six of chapter 
     <lb/>
     twenty-two of the statutes of 1891 is hereby 
     <lb/>
    amended by striking out the words " at any time 
     <lb/>in force in " in the fifth line thereof, and substi<lb break="no"/>tuting in lieu thereof the words " declared to be 
     <lb/>applicable to." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
    

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     I move in amendment to strike out 
     <lb/>
     the words " subsection 1 of " so that 
     <lb/>
     the clause will read " section 6 of chap. 22 
     <lb/>
     of the statutes of 1891." At the time the 
     <lb/>
     Bill was introduced I explained that one of 
     <lb/>
     the provisions was we should strike out the 
     <lb/>
     limitation in the Act relating to the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories, preventing the legislative 
     <lb/>
     assembly legislating with regard to insur<lb break="no"/>ance companies. The clause was acciden<lb break="no"/>tally omitted to have that effect, and I beg 
     <lb/>
     to move the amendment which will effect 
     <lb/>
     the intention explained at the time the Bill 
     <lb/>
     was introduced. The Act at present in 
     <lb/>
     force gives the legislative assembly author<lb break="no"/>ity on certain subjects, among which are 
     <lb/>
     the following :—The incorporation of com<lb break="no"/>panies with territorial objects with the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing exceptions "—and among the excep<lb break="no"/>tions are " insurance companies." The 
     <lb/>
     amendment that I move would strike out 
     <lb/>
     this exception of insurance companies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Amendment agreed to, and section as 
     <lb/>
     amended agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On section 9, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     9. Section eighteen of chapter seventeen of the 
     <lb/>
     statutes of 1894 is hereby repealed and the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing substituted therefor :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " 18. No person holding any office, commission 
     <lb/>
     or employment to which an annual salary from 
     <lb/>
     the Crown is attached, shall be eligible as a 
     <lb/>
     member of the Legislative Assembly, or shall 
     <lb/>
     sit or vote therein, during the time he holds such 
     <lb/>
     office, commission or employment; but nothing 
     <lb/>
     herein contained shall render ineligible any mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the Executive Council of the Territories, 
     <lb/>
     by reason of any salary, fee, allowance, emolu<lb break="no"/>ment or profit of any kind or amount attaching 
     <lb/>
    to such membership, from being a member of 
     <lb/>the Assembly, or shall disqualify him from sitting 
     <lb/>or voting therein : Provided he is elected while 
     <lb/>holding such office, and is not otherwise disquali<lb break="no"/>fied." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I think that the old section 
     <lb/>
     No. 18. passed in 1894, was quite right under 
     <lb/>
     the circumstances, of that time : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     No member of the Executive Committee of the 
     <lb/>
     Territories shall, by reason or any salary, fee, 
     <lb/>
     allowance, emolumen't or profit of any kind or 
     <lb/>
     amount attaching to such membership, be dis<lb break="no"/>qualified from sitting or voting in the Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Assembly. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     As I understand the new clause it simply 
     <lb/>
    provides that when a member of the As<lb break="no"/>sembly accepts office he will have to go back 
     <lb/>for re-election. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     Yes. that is the usual clause ; it provides 
     <lb/>
     that members accepting office shall go back 
     <lb/>
     to the people for re-election. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
        
        
            <cb/>
            <p>
     On section 10, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     Section forty-nine of the said Act is hereby 
     <lb/>
     repealed and the following substituted there<lb break="no"/>for :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " 49. The court shall sit in banc at such times 
     <lb/>
     and places as the Lieutenant-Governor in Coun<lb break="no"/>cil appoints ; the senior judge present shall pre<lb break="no"/>side, and three judges of the court shall consti<lb break="no"/>tute a quorum." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. I 
     <lb/>
     understand that there is some objection to 
     <lb/>
     that section and I am prepared to move that 
     <lb/>
     it be struck out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Amendment agreed to. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>On section 11, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     11. Subsection one of section fifty-six of the 
     <lb/>
     said Act, as amended by section eight of chapter 
     <lb/>
     twenty-two of the statutes of 1891, is hereby re<lb break="no"/>pealed, and the following substituted therefor :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" 56. For each judicial district the Governor in 
     <lb/>Council may appoint a sheriff and the Lieutenant- 
     <lb break="yes"/>Governor in Council may appoint a clerk of the 
     <lb/>court and may respectively name the place at 
     <lb/>which such sheriff and clerk shall reside and 
     <lb/>keep an oflice ; and the clerk of the district with<lb break="no"/>in which the seat of Government of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories is situate, shall be registrar of the court 
     <lb/>sitting in banc." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. Who appoints the sheriff ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. The 
     <lb/>
     law now is that the Governor General in 
     <lb/>
     Council appoints both the sheriff and the 
     <lb/>
     clerk of the court. Under the proposed ar<lb break="no"/>rangement the Governor General in Council 
     <lb/>
     will still appoint the sheriff while the local 
     <lb/>
     Government shall appoint the clerk of the 
     <lb/>
     court. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On section 12. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     12. Subsection one of the section substituted 
     <lb/>
     for section sixty-four of the said Act by section 
     <lb/>
     seven of chapter seventeen of the statutes of 
     <lb/>
     1894 is hereby repealed and the following substi<lb break="no"/>tuted therefor :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " 64. The Lieutenant-Governor may appoint 
     <lb/>
     justices of the peace for the Territories, who shall 
     <lb/>
     have jurisdiction as such throughout the same; 
     <lb/>
     but, until the Legislative Assembly otherwise pro<lb break="no"/>vides, no person shall be appointed a justice of 
     <lb/>
     the peace for the Territories, or shall act as 
     <lb/>
     such, who is not the owner in fee simple for his 
     <lb/>
     own use and benefit of lands lying and being in 
     <lb/>
    the Territories of and above the value of three 
     <lb/>hundred dollars over and above what will sat<lb break="no"/>isfy and discharge all incumbrances affecting the 
     <lb/>same, and over and above all rents and charges 
     <lb/>payable out of or affecting the same, and who 
     <lb/>has not resided in the Territories for a period of 
     <lb/>at least three years." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
            
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. He may not be able to 
     <lb/>read and write. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     The only change is that the words " until 
     <lb/>
    the Legislative Assembly otherwise pro<lb break="no"/>vides," are inserted in the 12th and 13th 
     <lb/>lines. The effect is that the qualifications 
     <lb/>of justices of the peace remains as it was, 
     <lb/>so far as this Parliament is! concerned, but 
     <lb/>we give the Legislative Assemblies power to 
     <lb/>
       
       
            <pb n="4113" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04113.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">4113</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JUNE 15, 1897]</fw> <fw type="num">4114</fw>
         
         
     legislate in regard to the qualification of 
     <lb/>
     justices of the peace. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On section 14, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     14. Subsection four of the section substituted 
     <lb/>
     for section sixty-four of the said Act by section 
     <lb/>
     seven of chapter seventeen of the statutes of 1894 
     <lb/>
     is hereby amended by striking out all the words 
     <lb/>
     after " years " in the fourth line thereof. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     This has to do with the qualifications of the 
     <lb/>
     police magistrates. The law as it is now 
     <lb/>
     provides that no person shall be appointed 
     <lb/>
     a police magistrate unless he is admitted and 
     <lb/>
     has practiced as an advocate, barrister, or 
     <lb/>
     solicitor in one of the provinces of Canada 
     <lb/>
     for a period of not less than three years, or 
     <lb/>
     is a magistrate of not less than three years 
     <lb/>
     of standing in Canada. This has the effect 
     <lb/>
     of striking out the latter portion of that 
     <lb/>
     clause, because it is believed a man should 
     <lb/>
     not be a police magistrate unless he has 
     <lb/>
     been a practicing barrister for at least three 
     <lb/>
     years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On section 15, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     15. Subsection one of section eighty-eight of 
     <lb/>
     the said Act is hereby amended by striking out 
     <lb/>
     the words " Lieutenant-Governor" in the third 
     <lb/>
     line thereof, and substituting the words " Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Assembly" in lieu thereof. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. In 
     <lb/>
     this section I desire to move an amendment 
     <lb/>
     which has been suggested by Mr. Justice 
     <lb/>
     Wetmore, of the North-west Court, and con<lb break="no"/>curred in by the Department of Justice re<lb break="no"/>specting the definition of larceny. By sec<lb break="no"/>tion 66 of the North-west Territories Act, 
     <lb/>
     the jurisdiction of the judges of the Supreme 
     <lb/>
     Court of the Territories is defined, and 
     <lb/>
     under subsection "A" of this section au<lb break="no"/>thority is given to the judges to try any 
     <lb/>
     person charged with having committed or 
     <lb/>
     attempted to commit larceny, embezzlement, 
     <lb/>
    or obtaining money or property by false pre<lb break="no"/>tenses or feloniously receiving stolen pro<lb break="no"/>perty in any case in which the value or the 
     <lb/>whole property so stolen, &amp;c., does not, 
     <lb/>in the opinion of the said judge, exceed 
     <lb/>the sum of $200. The Criminal Act has ab<lb break="no"/>olished the use of the term larceny and the 
     <lb/>technical distinction formerly known to the 
     <lb/>Criminal Law by which stealing was de<lb break="no"/>nominated larceny and certain technical 
     <lb/>words used to describe the offence. The 
     <lb/>definition is a simple one, the act being de<lb break="no"/>fined as theft or stealing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The distinction between a misdemeanour 
     <lb/>
    and a felony was founded on the old rules 
     <lb/>of the criminal law, and as the law exists 
     <lb/>at present a question might arise as to whe<lb break="no"/>ther the judges of the Northwest Territor<lb break="no"/>ies had jurisdiction to try for theft. In 
     <lb/>accordance with the suggestion or Judge 
     <lb/>Wetmore. I move in amendment that the 
     <lb/>word " larceny " in the sections I have read, 
     <lb/>be changed to " theft " and that the word 
     <lb/>" felonious " be struck out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     On section 16. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     The eifect of this is to abolish the omce of 
     <lb/>
     clerk of the Lieutenant-Governor in Coun<lb break="no"/>cil, and put the office under the jurisdiction 
     <lb/>
     of the legislative assembly. We have a 
     <lb/>
     clerk there whom we pay $2,000 a year, and 
     <lb/>
     I do not see any reason why we should 
     <lb/>
     have such an officer there when the legisla<lb break="no"/>tive assembly can employ their own clerk 
     <lb/>
     for a much less sum. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I think we ought to put in 
     <lb/>
     something to save the officer. The present 
     <lb/>
     occupant of that office is a Dominion officer. 
     <lb/>
     and he has been a most effective officer. I 
     <lb/>
     can safely say that at the time he became 
     <lb/>
     an officer of the Government, his qualities 
     <lb/>
     and talents were of the greatest advantage 
     <lb/>
     to the North-west Territories. I may say as 
     <lb/>
     regards the politics of this gentleman, Mr. R. 
     <lb/>
     B. Gordon, that I believe his politics are of 
     <lb/>
     the neutral tint; however, if he had any, 
     <lb/>
     he never manifested them. But I think 
     <lb/>
     that when we have had a man there in our 
     <lb/>
     employ, giving him $2,000 a year, and when 
     <lb/>
     we are about to amend an Act which will 
     <lb/>
     give another body power of either retaining 
     <lb/>
     that man or dismissing him, I think we 
     <lb/>
     ought to limit the power of appointing a 
     <lb/>
     clerk to the time when, either by death or 
     <lb/>
     by retirement, Mr. Gordon ceases to be 
     <lb/>
     clerk. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Sir CHARLES TUPPER</persName>. I think that is 
     <lb/>
     a matter that may be left safely to the par<lb break="no"/>ties who are to be clothed with power to 
     <lb/>
     deal with it. I am afraid that the sugges<lb break="no"/>tion of my hon. friend is not practicable. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     Gentlemen who have been doing official 
     <lb/>
     business with this officer for years past, I 
     <lb/>
     understand, are on perfectly good terms 
     <lb/>
     with him. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Quite so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     I wish to move: 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     That after the word " territory " in subsection 
     <lb/>
    one there be added the following words -<lb/>" Subject to any right which may have been 
     <lb/>acquired under letters patent issued previous to 
     <lb/>such transfer." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     The object of that amendment is, to avoid 
     <lb/>
     the Government being compelled to trans<lb break="no"/>fer a trail, without having regard to the 
     <lb/>fact, that a patent might have been issued 
     <lb/>before for a certain part of the trail. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Amendment agreed rto. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On section 20,   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Why is it that the Minister 
     <lb/>
     is getting rid of subsection 2 of section 21 ? 
     <lb/>
     Is it no longer necessary ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     It applies to any transaction. and it is neces<lb break="no"/>sary, it will be there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. 'But under this section you 
     <lb/>
     would repeal it ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <pb n="4115" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04115.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">4115</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS|</fw> <fw type="num">4116</fw>
           
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     There may be something in the point raised 
     <lb/>
     by the hon. gentleman (Mr. Davin), and I 
     <lb/>
     will amend the section to meet his views. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BERG1">Mr. BERGERON</persName>. Do I understand that 
     <lb/>
     the intention of this Bill is, to give the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories autonomous government like the old<lb break="no"/>er provinces ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     The Bill will give the people of the 
     <lb/>
     Territories a government which shall not 
     <lb/>
     have the full powers of a provincial 
     <lb/>
     government, but in so far as they have 
     <lb/>
     power to deal with subjects, they shall do 
     <lb/>
     it in the same way as the other provinces. 
     <lb/>
     They will have Ministers who are responsi<lb break="no"/>ble to the legislature, and the rules and pre<lb break="no"/>cedents that apply to the provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ments will apply to the government of the 
     <lb/>
     Territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BERG1">Mr. BERGERON</persName>. Then the Territories 
     <lb/>
     will be constituted under one legislature, 
     <lb/>
     and I presume this Government will have 
     <lb/>
     to pay them the necessary expenses. Will 
     <lb/>
     this Bill increase the present expenses ?, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     De facto, they have this kind of 
     <lb/>
     government now. They have an execu<lb break="no"/>tive committee of the assembly who are the 
     <lb/>
     responsible advisers of the Lieutenant-Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor. It is a practice which has grown up, 
     <lb/>
     but the constitution does not provide for it 
     <lb/>
     in the proper form. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BERG1">Mr. BERGERON</persName>. I do not see that there 
     <lb/>
     is much object in this Bill. I believe that 
     <lb/>
     as soon as we can, we should constitute 
     <lb/>
     the North-west Territories into a province, 
     <lb/>
     and give them responsible government in a 
     <lb/>
     complete form. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     That is what we are doing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BERG1">Mr. BERGERON</persName>. Not at all. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>The Bill goes in that direction. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BERG1">Mr. BERGERON</persName>. This Bill will make 
     <lb/>very little difierence to them, except that I 
     <lb/>believe it will increase the expenses to us. 
     <lb/>Let the Territories have their own govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and pay for their own expenses, and 
     <lb/>let us get rid of them as soon as possible 
     <lb/>in that way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     The objection of the hon. gentleman (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Bergeron) is that we are not going far 
     <lb/>
     enough. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Sir CHARLES TUPPER</persName>. I must say a 
     <lb/>
     single word in qualification of what my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend (Mr. Bergeron) has stated. I am sure 
     <lb/>
    that no one wants to get rid of our friends 
     <lb/>in the Territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BERG1">Mr. BERGERON</persName>. I meant in the way of 
     <lb/>getting rid of paying their expenses. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Sir CHARLES TUPPER</persName>. On the con<lb break="no"/>
           
           
         
            <cb/>
       
       
     trary, we want to steadily do what I think 
     <lb/>
     this Act does, and the time has come when 
     <lb/>
     such an Act was required. It gives them 
     <lb/>
     power to deal with the local business of the 
     <lb/>
     North-west Territories to a greater extent 
     <lb/>
     than they were able to do before; but I do 
     <lb/>
     not think it is calculated to increase the ex<lb break="no"/>penditure. It rather increases their legis<lb break="no"/>lative power in accordance with the wishes 
     <lb/>
     of the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     It would undoubtedly increase the efficiency 
     <lb/>
     of their administration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. Hear hear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     The principle upon which I acted is this. I 
     <lb/>
     met the representatives of the territorial 
     <lb/>
     government, and they explained to me—as 
     <lb/>
     of course I knew before—that there has been 
     <lb/>
     in the Territories for some years, an agita<lb break="no"/>tion in favour of what they called provin<lb break="no"/>cial autonomy. Now, it is a subject with 
     <lb/>
     which it would be extremely inconvenient 
     <lb/>
     to deal until it takes some shape in the pub<lb break="no"/>lic mind. I fancy that any Government 
     <lb/>
     that undertook to form an organization 
     <lb/>
     there, without something more defined to go 
     <lb/>
     by than we have at the present time, 
     <lb/>
     would find very considerable difficulty. 
     <lb/>
     But I said that if they wanted something of 
     <lb/>
     a practical character which would assist 
     <lb/>
     them in carrying on their business, no doubt 
     <lb/>
     their wishes in that respect could be met. 
     <lb/>
     They suggested, therefore, that a Bill such 
     <lb/>
     as I have presented to the House would, for 
     <lb/>
     the present, meet the views of the people ; 
     <lb/>
     and I have not thought it advisable to go 
     <lb/>
     further at the present time. but to allow 
     <lb/>
     matters to develop. At a future time the 
     <lb/>
     House may be called on to deal with the 
     <lb/>
     question of the organization of a provincial 
     <lb/>
     constitution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BERG1">Mr. BERGERON</persName>. I am sorry that the 
     <lb/>
     hon. leader of the Opposition did, not under<lb break="no"/>stand me. I know that for some years it 
     <lb/>
     has :been the ambition of the people of the 
     <lb/>
     North-west to have provincial autonomy, 
     <lb/>
     and I think upon that depends largely the 
     <lb/>
     hope of the future prosperity of the coun<lb break="no"/>try<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Sir CHARLES HIBBERT TUPPER</persName>. 
     <lb/>
     Who will now enact the school ordinances? 
     <lb/>
     Are they in the power of the Governor in 
     <lb/>
     Council or of the legislative assembly ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName>. 
     <lb/>
    There is no change in that respect. The leg<lb break="no"/>islative assembly in conjunction with the 
     <lb/>Lieutenant-Governor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Bill reported, as amended. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName> 
     <lb/>moved that the Bill be now read, the third 
     <lb/>time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I want to say a few words 
     <lb/>
     which I did not sayjbefore. lest I might de<lb break="no"/>lay the Bill. I am exceedingly glad to see 
     <lb/>
     this Bill go through. In 1888, when the 
     <lb/>
         
         
            <pb n="4117" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1897-06-15_Page_04117.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">4117</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JUNE 15, 1897]</fw> <fw type="num">4118</fw>
     
     
     Right Honourable Sir John Macdonald sat 
     <lb/>
     where the Minister of Trade and 
     <lb/>
     Commerce now sits, he brought down 
     <lb/>
     a Bill to amend the North-west Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories Act, and I gave notice of 
     <lb/>
     an amendment to that Bill that would have 
     <lb/>
     introduced then precisely the change which 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend the Minister of the Interior 
     <lb/>
     has now happily introduced, and I congratu<lb break="no"/>late him. I may, as a little piece of history, 
     <lb/>
     say what occurred. The leader of the then 
     <lb/>
     Government (Sir John Macdonald) resented 
     <lb/>
     my action, and withdrew his Bill, and 
     <lb/>
     brought down another Bill, with a clause 
     <lb/>
     in it which will be found in the Act of 
     <lb/>
     1888. by which he introduced into our gov<lb break="no"/>ernment what was called the Advisory 
     <lb/>
     Council. I would not then speak on the 
     <lb/>
     Bill, as there was no use trying to pass my 
     <lb/>
     amendment, and my respect for my great 
     <lb/>
     leader would not allow me to comment on 
     <lb/>
     that clause and pour on it the ridicule it 
     <lb/>
     deserved ; but I said to a friend of 
     <lb/>
     mine, when he asked me why I did 
     <lb/>
     not comment on it, " It is a mere 
     <lb/>
     toy," as it turned out to be. In 
     <lb/>
     consequence of pressure brought by myself 
     <lb/>
     on the Government, we had a few years 
     <lb/>
     afterwards an amendment, which introduced 
     <lb/>
     a different state of things—which introduced 
     <lb/>
     a committee of four to aid the governor ; 
     <lb/>
     but that committee of four is a very incon<lb break="no"/>venient piece of machinery, as the hon. gen 
     <lb/>
     tleman knows, because, instead of being 
     <lb/>
     chosen by the Government, it was chosen 
     <lb/>
     by the legislative assembly. My hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     here (Mr. Bergeron) and, to some extent, my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend the Minister of the Interior, are. 
     <lb/>
     under a complete mistake in supposing that 
     <lb/>
     there has been any agitation amongst the 
     <lb/>
     people of the North-west for responsible 
     <lb/>
     government. There is not. In this House, 
     <lb/>
     whenever I advocated it, I found the mem<lb break="no"/>bers from the North-west Territories oppos<lb break="no"/>ing me. If the debates of 1888 are looked 
     <lb/>
     at. it will be found that Mr. Macdowail, 
     <lb/>
     and others, got up in the House and 
     <lb/>
     said that the Territories did not want re<lb break="no"/>sponsible government; and in Regina, at 
     <lb/>
     the instance of a certain individual, a meet<lb break="no"/>ing was held at which resolutions were pass<lb break="no"/>ed to prevent my action in this House being 
     <lb/>
     successful. I can say that the most 
     <lb/>
     thoughtful people in the Territories have al<lb break="no"/>ways held the views that I have held ; but 
     <lb/>
     at the same time there has been no agitation 
     <lb/>
     and I have battled for this thing single- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     handed. I believe it would have been a 
     <lb/>
     good thing for the Territories if we had 
     <lb/>
     had this legislation in 1888 : and subsequent<lb break="no"/>ly, in 1891, when another change was made, 
     <lb/>it would have been much better for the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories if this change had been made; so 
     <lb/>that, instead of having a nondescript gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, hampered in many ways, and with 
     <lb/>more power than a government should have, 
     <lb/>more irresponsible than this Government, 
     <lb/>which we now create will be, we should 
     <lb/>have had at once a stronger and more re<lb break="no"/>
         
         
            <cb/>
       
       sponsible government, and my belief is that 
     <lb/>
     we should have made more progress than 
     <lb/>
     we have done. I am very glad to see this 
     <lb/>
     Bill launched to the third reading, and to 
     <lb/>
     see that we are going to have responsible 
     <lb/>
     government in the (Territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the third 
     <lb/>
     time and passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>