<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-03-01"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-03-01">1 March 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          
          
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1905"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1851" to="1868"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1851.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1853.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1855.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1857.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1859.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1861.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1863.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1865.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1867.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1851">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1851.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1853">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1853.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1855">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1855.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1857">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1857.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1859">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1859.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1861">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1861.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1863">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1863.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1865">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1865.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1867">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1867.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1851" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1851.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1851</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">1852</fw>
           
<div type="section"> 
            <head>
               RESIGNATION OF THE HON. CLIFFORD <lb/>SIFTON. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Rt. Hon. Sir WILFRID LAURIER (Prime 
                  <lb/>
               Minister). I have to inform the House that 
                  <lb/>
               my colleague, Hon. Mr. Sifton, has resigned 
                  <lb/>
               his position in the government, and as Min<lb break="no"/>ister of the Interior. Mr. Sifton finds him<lb break="no"/>self unable to agree with the terms of the 
                  <lb/>
               Bill which has lately been introduced for 
                  <lb/>
               the admission into the Dominion of the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces of Alberta and Saskatchewan, his 
                  <lb/>
               disagreement being confined altogether to 
                  <lb/>
               the educational clause. After a conference 
                  <lb/>
               with him, the following correspondence has 
                  <lb/>
               been exchanged between him and myself : 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
              <p> Ottawa, February 27, 1905. 
                  <lb/>
               Dear Sir Wilfrid,—After giving my best con<lb break="no"/>sideration to the matters which we discussed 
                  <lb/>
               last evening, I have arrived at the conclusion 
                  <lb/>
               that it is impossible for me to continue in 
                  <lb/>
               office under present circumstances, and that it 
                  <lb/>
               is better for all concerned that I should act at 
                  <lb/>
               once. I therefore beg to tender my resignation 
                  <lb/>
               as a member of the government. I trust that 
                  <lb/>
               the unhappy necessity which has arisen will not 
                  <lb/>
               in the least impair the friendship with which 
                  <lb/>
               you have been kind enough to honour me. 
                  <lb/>
               Believe me, 
                  <lb/>
               Yours most faithfully, 
                  <lb/>
               CLIFFORD SIFTON. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Right Hon. Sir Wilfrid Laurier, G.C.M.G., 
                  <lb/>
               Ottawa. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            </quote>
         
            
            <p>
               To this I answered yesterday in the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing terms : 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
        <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
               Ottawa. February 28, 1905. 
                  <lb/>
               My dear Sifton,—I received yesterday your 
                  <lb/>
               letter of same date, whereby you tender me 
                  <lb/>
               your resignation as a member of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment. 
                  <lb/></p>

            
            <p>There is no alternative to me, but to accept<lb/>
it, and with much regret, it will be my duty to<lb/>
             
               place it in the hands of His Excellency. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
      
            <p>
               After our conversation of the other day, I 
                  <lb/>
               had left you with the impression that the differ<lb break="no"/>ences between us were more of words than of 
                  <lb/>
               substance, and until I received your letter, I 
                  <lb/>
               had cherished the hope that it would be pos<lb break="no"/>sible ere this to find a comparatively easy solu<lb break="no"/>tion. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Whilst I feel more regret than I can express 
                  <lb/>
               at this termination of our oflicial relations, let 
                  <lb/>
               me assure you that should our old friendship 
                  <lb/>
               be ever impaired, the fault will not be mine. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Yours very sincerely, 
                  <lb/>
               WILFRID LAURIER. 
                  <lb/></p>
<p>
               The Hon. Clifford Sifton, Ottawa. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
        </quote>
            
            <p>
               The resignation has been placed in the 
                  <lb/>
               hands of His Excellency, who has been 
                  <lb/>
               pleased to accept it. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. CLIFFORD SIFTON. The state<lb break="no"/>ment made by the right hon. the Prime Min<lb break="no"/>ister (Sir Wilfrid Laurier) necessitates a 
                  <lb/>
               very short explanation to the House on my 
                  <lb/>
               part. When it was determined that during 
                  <lb/>
               this session of parliament legislation should 
                  <lb/>
               be introduced creating new provinces out of 
                  <lb/>
               a portion of the Northwest Territories, I 
                  <lb/>
               felt called upon. in view of the history of 
                  <lb/>
    
            
            
        <!--    <p>
               Mr. HYMAN. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>-->
            
         <cb/>
               the educational question in Canada, to give 
                  <lb/>
               very serious consideration to the position 
                  <lb/>
               which I should take with regard to the legis<lb break="no"/>lative power to be conferred upon the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces in regard to the subject of education. 
                  <lb/>
               It was necessary that conferences should 
                  <lb/>
               take place with members of parliament 
                  <lb/>
               representing the Northwest Territories and 
                  <lb/>
               with the representatives of the Territorial 
                  <lb/>
               government, upon the subject of education 
                  <lb/>
               and other subjects involved in the Bill. 
                  <lb/>
               These conferences were unavoidably post<lb break="no"/>poned until after the beginning of the new 
                  <lb/>
               year, by reason of the absence of the Prime 
                  <lb/>
               Minister, who, after the general election, 
                  <lb/>
               was compelled to take a short rest, and was 
                  <lb/>
               therefore absent from the country. Shortly 
                  <lb/>
               before the time fixed for holding these con<lb break="no"/>ferences I was compelled by my own state 
                  <lb/>
               of health to leave Ottawa, and was there<lb break="no"/>fore unable to be present at the discussions 
                  <lb/>
               which took place. Before leaving I dis<lb break="no"/>cussed with the Prime Minister most of the 
                  <lb/>
               subjects that necessarily required to be 
                  <lb/>
               dealt with in the Bill which was to be in<lb break="no"/>troduced, and so far as I was able to do so 
                  <lb/>
               at that time, I communicated my views to 
                  <lb/>
               him upon the various subjects. I may say 
                  <lb/>
               that when I went away I did not anticipate 
                  <lb/>
               that it would be considered necessary to 
                  <lb/>
               introduce the Bill for creating the new pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, before I returned. As members of 
                  <lb/>
               the House are aware, I returned to the 
                  <lb/>
               capital on Thursday afternoon. I immedi<lb break="no"/>ately took occasion to read carefully the 
                  <lb/>
               speech which the right hon. the Prime Min<lb break="no"/>ister (Sir Wilfrid Laurier) had delivered in 
                  <lb/>
               introducing the Bill. I regretted that in the 
                  <lb/>
               right hon. gentleman's address I found some 
                  <lb/>
               principles enunciated with which I am un<lb break="no"/>able to agree. On Friday, the next day 
                  <lb/>
               after I returned, at the earliest possible 
                  <lb/>
               moment, I procured a copy of the education<lb break="no"/>al clause of the Bill which my leader had 
                  <lb/>
               introduced. That clause is as follows : 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
               16. The provisions of section 93 of the British 
                  <lb/>
               North America Act, 1867, shall apply to the 
                  <lb/>
               said provinces as if, at the date upon which 
                  <lb/>
               this Act comes into force, the territory com<lb break="no"/>prised therein were already a province, the ex<lb break="no"/>pression 'the union' in the said section being 
                  <lb/>
               taken to mean the said date. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               2. Subject to the provisions of the said sec<lb break="no"/>tion 93, and in continuance of the principles 
                  <lb/>
               heretofore sanctioned under the Northwest Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories Act, it is enacted that the legislature 
                  <lb/>
               of the said province shall pass all necessary 
                  <lb/>
               laws in respect of education, and that it shall 
                  <lb/>
               therein always be provided (a) that a majority 
                  <lb/>
               of the ratepayers of any district or portion of 
                  <lb/>
               the said province or of any less portion or sub<lb break="no"/>division thereof, by whatever name it is known 
                  <lb/>
               may establish such schools therein as they 
                  <lb/>
               think fit, and make the necessary assessments 
                  <lb/>
               and collection of rates therefor, and (b) that 
                  <lb/>
               the minority of the ratepayers therein whether 
                  <lb/>
               Protestant or Roman Catholic, may establish 
                  <lb/>
               separate schools therein, and make the neces<lb break="no"/>sary assessment and collection of rates there<lb break="no"/>for, and (c) that in such case the ratepayers 
                  <lb/>
               establishing such Protestant or Roman Catholic 
                  <lb/>
               separate schools shall be liable only to assess<lb break="no"/><pb n="1853" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1853.jpg"/><fw type="num">1853</fw> <fw type="dateline">MARCH 1, 1905</fw>     <fw type="num">1854</fw>ment of such rates as they impose upon them<lb break="no"/>selves with respect thereto. 
                  <lb/>
               3. In the appropriation of public moneys by<lb/>the legislature in aid of education, and in the<lb/>distribution of any moneys paid to the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the said province arising from the 
                  <lb/>
               school fund established by the Dominion Lands 
                  <lb/>
               Act, there shall be no discrimination between 
                  <lb/>
               the public schools and the separate schools, 
                  <lb/>
               and such moneys shall be applied to the sup<lb break="no"/>port of public and separate schools in equitable 
                  <lb/>
               shares or proportion. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            </quote>
      
            <p>
               That is the clause which is contained in 
                  <lb/>
               the Bill which was introduced by the leader 
                  <lb/>
               of the government. Between Friday, when <lb/> I procured a copy of the clause, and Mon<lb break="no"/>day morning I gave the subject my best con<lb break="no"/>sideration, and I had the privilege in the<lb/>meantime of having an interview with the<lb/>Prime Minister on the subject.  As the re<lb break="no"/>sult of such consideration I determined that<lb/>I could not endorse or support the principle <lb/>of the educational clauses.  Under these<lb/>circumstances, Mr. Speaker, my duty be<lb break="no"/>came perfectly clear, and on Monday morn<lb break="no"/>ing I wrote to the Prime Minister tendering<lb/>my resignation as a member of the cabinet.<lb/>Subsequently, I expressed the desire that<lb/>my resignation should be acted up on at<lb/>once and to that wish the Prime Minister<lb/>has now assented.
            
         </p>
            
            <p>
               In conclusion, Mr. Speaker, not intending 
                  <lb/>
               and not considering it proper at this time to 
                  <lb/>
               enter into a discussion of the merits of the 
                  <lb/>
               matter which has caused the difference be<lb break="no"/>tween myself and my leader, I have only 
                  <lb/>
               to add my regret that circumstances have 
                  <lb/>
               compelled the severance of my official rela<lb break="no"/>tions with my leader and with my col<lb break="no"/>leagues with whom my relations have al<lb break="no"/>ways been of the most harmonious and plea<lb break="no"/>sant character, and with whom upon other 
                  <lb/>
               questions I am in entire accord. The cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances, however, in my judgment, 
                  <lb/>
               make my duty perfectly clear, and it does 
                  <lb/>
               not seem possible for me to properly con<lb break="no"/>sider anything except the principles which 
                  <lb/>
               are involved.<lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <lb/> Hon. GEO. E. FOSTER (North Toronto). 
                  <lb/>
               Mr. Speaker, I quite agree with the hon. 
                  <lb/>
               gentleman, the retiring minister (Hon. Mr. 
                  <lb/>
               Sifton) that this is not the time to under<lb break="no"/>take the discussion of the principles in<lb break="no"/>volved in the Bill. But, with the two state<lb break="no"/>ments which have been read and with the 
                  <lb/>
               reading of the statements and the causes 
                  <lb/>
               which make the reading of the statements 
                  <lb/>
               necessary this afternoon, we alone have to 
                  <lb/>
               deal and with these I shall deal for a mo<lb break="no"/>ment with your kindly permission. It did 
                  <lb/>
               not come as a matter of surprise to this 
                  <lb/>
               side of the House that the Minister of the 
                  <lb/>
               Interior should at some early period read 
                  <lb/>
               his letter of resignation, or give his rea<lb break="no"/>sons for resigning to this House, nor do I 
                  <lb/>
               think it came as a matter of surprise to hon. 
                  <lb/>
               gentlemen who are within the secrets of 
                  <lb/>
               the party on the other side of the House. 
                  <lb/>
               We all remember the peculiar circumstances 
                  <lb/>
               under which this Bill appears to have been<lb/>
               
      <cb/>

               framed and to have been rushed before the<lb/>
House.  It did seem an odd and almost un<lb break="no"/>explainable thing that a Bill of such impor<lb break="no"/>tance should be framed in the absence of<lb/>
two of the most responsible ministers in<lb/>
the House as regards the country and the<lb/>
scope of territory in which that Bill was to<lb/>
be operative, and having respect to the de<lb break="no"/>claration of policy which I think a year or <lb/>
two ago was made in this House when, <lb/>
with some new idea of a division of<lb/>
ministerial responsibility, it was announced<lb/>
that certain ministers were to be held more<lb/>
or less accountable for the particular pro<lb break="no"/>vinces or sections from which they came.<lb/>
This was exemplied in the case of the hon.<lb/>
Minister of agriculture (Mr. Fisher) in his<lb/>
intermeddling with the militia matters of<lb/>
this country.  During the last few weeks<lb/>
this important Bill has been framed and<lb/>
has been laid before the House in the ab<lb break="no"/>sence of the hon. Minister of the Interior,<lb/>
who was especially charged with the super<lb break="no"/>vision of and the responsibility for the<lb/>
              Northwest Territories and the west gen<lb break="no"/>erally.  We were led to think that possibly 
                  <lb/>
               the second chapter of what took place on 
                  <lb/>
               an almost similar line a year or two ago 
                  <lb/>
               was being prepared for the House and the 
                  <lb/>
               country. It is well known that at that 
                  <lb/>
               time a most important railway Bill was 
                  <lb/>
               conceived and formed and was almost, if not 
                  <lb/>
               quite, presented to this House behind the 
                  <lb/>
               back of the responsible Minister of Rail<lb break="no"/>ways and Canals, whose office it should 
                  <lb/>
               have been to have aided in the consider<lb break="no"/>ation and preparation of that Bill. We 
                  <lb/>
               were of late led still more to suppose this 
                  <lb/>
               from a remark which fell casually, but 
                  <lb/>
               rather acridly, from the lips of the right hon. 
                  <lb/>
               Prime Minister (Sir Wilfrid Laurier) him<lb break="no"/>self, who, when, not long ago, asked about 
                  <lb/>
               the time when we might expect the intro<lb break="no"/>duction of the Bill, gave as his answer that 
                  <lb/>
               it would probably be introduced at a cer<lb break="no"/>tain time, and when some inquiring mind of 
                  <lb/>
               the many inquiring minds on this side of the 
                  <lb/>
               House put the question to the right hon. 
                  <lb/>
               Prime Minister as to whether the hon. the 
                  <lb/>
               Minister of the Interior would be back by 
                  <lb/>
               that time, the right hon. Prime Minister, as 
                  <lb/>
               I say, rather sharply retorted that he did 
                  <lb/>
               not know whether he would or not, but that 
                  <lb/>
               he, the Prime Minister, would be here. Tak<lb break="no"/>ing all this with the history of this Bill into 
                  <lb/>
               consideration it did not come as a surprise 
                  <lb/>
               to this part of the House, and I doubt very 
                  <lb/>
               much if it fell as much of a surprise upon 
                  <lb/>
               hon. gentlemen on the other side of the 
                  <lb/>
               House. But, it is a still stranger thing that 
                  <lb/>
               the hon. Minister of the Interior, a most 
                  <lb/>
               important member of the cabinet at any 
                  <lb/>
               time and a specially important member of 
                  <lb/>
               the cabinet as regards the conception and 
                  <lb/>
               arrangement of this Bill, did not actually 
                  <lb/>
               know, although it is supposed that tele<lb break="no"/>graph wires stretch from here to almost all 
                  <lb/>
               parts of the United States of America in 
                  <lb/>
               some particular portion of which the hon. 
                  <lb/>
               
          
            <pb n="1855" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1855.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1855</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
            <fw type="num">1856</fw>
            
        
               Minister of the Interior has been for the 
                  <lb/>
               past number of weeks, of the educational 
                  <lb/>
               clauses of this Bill until after he had re<lb break="no"/>turned to this city and to this House when 
                  <lb/>
               he obtained a copy of the clause. One 
                  <lb/>
               would have thought that on the general 
                  <lb/>
               theory of responsible government, of a 
                  <lb/>
               cabinet acting unitedly, of a cabinet acting 
                  <lb/>
               wisely. consulting with every unit of the 
                  <lb/>
               cabinet, as, I think it is in duty bound to 
                  <lb/>
               do, in order to secure the united wisdom 
                  <lb/>
               of the whole of the cabinet, that the hon. 
                  <lb/>
               Minister of the Interior would have been 
                  <lb/>
               consulted with, not even by telegraph or 
                  <lb/>
               letter does it seem that the hon. Minster of 
                  <lb/>
               the Interior was apprised of the one pro<lb break="no"/>minent clause in the Bill in which it would 
                  <lb/>
               be supposed naturally that he would be very 
                  <lb/>
               much interested. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The excuse, the reason, is given to-day-<lb/>
and we are bound to take the reason in a 
                  <lb/>
               parliamentary sense—that the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man is retiring because he could not find it 
                  <lb/>
               consistent with his principles to accede to 
                  <lb/>
               that particular clause in the Autonomy Bill, 
                  <lb/>
               but from what I have stated and from what 
                  <lb/>
               we have seen, it would be easily inferred, I 
                  <lb/>
               think, by any member of this House that 
                  <lb/>
               there is a reasonable doubt as to whether or 
                  <lb/>
               not that was the cause of the resignation, as 
                  <lb/>
               to whether the deliberate actions of the 
                  <lb/>
               Prime Minister and the rest of the Cabinet 
                  <lb/>
               heretofore have not made it quite abundant<lb break="no"/>ly apparent that it was the intention to get 
                  <lb/>
               rid of the hon. gentleman whether he got 
                  <lb/>
               out on this particular clause of the Bill or 
                  <lb/>
               on some other. The Prime Minister has not 
                  <lb/>
               quite satisfied the curiosity of the House. 
                  <lb/>
               Outside of the information which was con<lb break="no"/>veyed to us by the bulletin boards there are 
                  <lb/>
               other rumours which are abroad in the cor<lb break="no"/>ridors of this House, abroad on the streets 
                  <lb/>
               of the city and, I dare say, are tingling 
                  <lb/>
               the wires, which stretch from Ottawa to dif<lb break="no"/>ferent parts of this country even now while 
                  <lb/>
               we are speaking. And why? It is stated 
                  <lb/>
               that another important minister, another 
                  <lb/>
               important member of the cabinet of the right 
                  <lb/>
               hon. gentleman, is deliberating as to whether 
                  <lb/>
               he shall not follow in the tracks—no, I would 
                  <lb/>
               not put it that way—but follow, at least, the 
                  <lb/>
               example of the hon. the Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior who has retired, in also expressing his 
                  <lb/>
               formal and unqualified dissent from this 
                  <lb/>
               Bill. There might be some reasons which 
                  <lb/>
               would impose on us the idea that there is 
                  <lb/>
               truth in that. I could hardly reconcile to 
                  <lb/>
               my own mind the idea of a Prime Minister 
                  <lb/>
               and a cabinet undertaking to frame and to 
                  <lb/>
               put before the country so important a Bill 
                  <lb/>
               as this, involving no trivial and unimportant 
                  <lb/>
               financial burdens, but involving very oner<lb break="no"/>ous and continuous and growing financial 
                  <lb/>
               burdens upon this country, I cannot, I say, 
                  <lb/>
               understand how a Bill of that kind could 
                  <lb/>
               be conceived, put into form and introduced 
                  <lb/>
               into this House in the absence of the, Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Finance, who is responsible, if any 
                  <lb/>
               man in the cabinet is responsible, for the 
                  <lb/>
       
            
         
            
         <!--   <p>
               Mr. FOSTER. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>-->
            
         <cb/>
         
               financial interests of this country. Was he 
                  <lb/>
               also altogether and entirely in the dark 
                  <lb/>
               with reference to this Bill? Did he know 
                  <lb/>
               the clauses, financial or otherwise, before 
                  <lb/>
               he came back to Ottawa and ascertained 
                  <lb/>
               what they were by asking for a copy of the 
                  <lb/>
               Bill? Was there such an urgent necessity 
                  <lb/>
               for the introduction of the Bill that a delay 
                  <lb/>
               of at least two or three days could not have 
                  <lb/>
               been given until both the Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior and the Minister of Finance should 
                  <lb/>
               have had opportunity to meet their col<lb break="no"/>leagues in Council and by word of mouth 
                  <lb/>
               and interchange of ideas, see if an amicable 
                  <lb/>
               and united conclusion could not be had? 
                  <lb/>
               Now, we would be very loath to lose the 
                  <lb/>
               Minister of Finance. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Some hon. MEMBERS. Hear, hear. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. FOSTER. His pleasant countenance 
                  <lb/>
               is always an inspiration to us—when it is 
                  <lb/>
               not the opposite, and it is not often it is the 
                  <lb/>
               opposite. But we would like to have this 
                  <lb/>
               set at rest and to hear the Prime Minister 
                  <lb/>
               state whether there is any truth in the ru<lb break="no"/>mour which is persistent that the Minister of 
                  <lb/>
               Finance, not having been consulted, is not al<lb break="no"/>together at one with the rest of the cabinet 
                  <lb/>
               in relation to this Bill. We must bid adieu 
                  <lb/>
               to the Minister of the Interior with varying 
                  <lb/>
               feelings. We do it some with sympathy ; 
                  <lb/>
               some will say he has fought the fight and 
                  <lb/>
               finished the course—I am not going to say 
                  <lb/>
               how good a course it was—and he has en<lb break="no"/>tered into his reward. Probably he has had 
                  <lb/>
               his reward before; possibly, like the late 
                  <lb/>
               Minister of Railways and Canals, there is 
                  <lb/>
               some glorious future awaiting him in some 
                  <lb/>
               of the large official charges of this country. 
                  <lb/>
               Anyway, if he leaves us as Minister of the 
                  <lb/>
               Interior, he has not stated that he is going to 
                  <lb/>
               leave us as member and we will still have 
                  <lb/>
               him with us to remonstrate with and to 
                  <lb/>
               counsel and as far as we can abiding in 
                  <lb/>
               good will and friendship. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Mr. W. F. MACLEAN (South York). Mr. 
                  <lb/>
               Speaker, partly as a question of privilege I 
                  <lb/>
               desire to refer now to the question before 
                  <lb/>
               the House, and I would ask the right hon. 
                  <lb/>
               gentleman, who lives in the ramshackle 
                  <lb/>
               house now, and who is the Samson who has 
                  <lb/>
               pushed down the pillars and has the roof 
                  <lb/>
               upon him and his co-ministers in the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment? The other day the right hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman said I was quixotic. Well, there is 
                  <lb/>
               this at least to be said about Don Quixote, 
                  <lb/>
               that he was a country gentleman, a man of 
                  <lb/>
               high honour and that he died with good 
                  <lb/>
               Christian burial. If I must search for a his<lb break="no"/>torical reference to the hon. gentleman after 
                  <lb/>
               what has happened here to-day, I could think 
                  <lb/>
               of no one else than one of these autocratic 
                  <lb/>
               Russian grand dukes of whom we hear at the 
                  <lb/>
               present time. He has confessed here and the 
                  <lb/>
               late Minister of the Interior has confessed 
                  <lb/>
               here that in this House on Monday of this 
                  <lb/>
               week when I asked where was the Minister 
                  <lb/>
               of the Interior and the right hon. gentleman 
                  <lb/>
               said it was for me to have him here, that he 
                  <lb/>
         
            <pb n="1857" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1857.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1857</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               MARCH 1, 1905 
                 </fw>
            <fw type="num">1858</fw>
        
          
               knew then, as the House knows now, that 
                  <lb/>
               he was not in his cabinet and was not in his 
                  <lb/>
               administration. What is the reason of all 
                  <lb/>
               this ? This autocratic Prime Minister that 
                  <lb/>
               we have in this country eight years ago 
                  <lb/>
               using the words of Bismarck said: We 
                  <lb/>
               shall not go to Canossa. The right hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman has been to Three Rivers; he has 
                  <lb/>
               made the treaty of Three Rivers, and in pur<lb break="no"/>suance of that treaty he has chosen in his 
                  <lb/>
               autocratic way to bring down a Bill dealing 
                  <lb/>
               with the great questions now at issue 
                  <lb/>
               without consulting his colleagues. It is said 
                  <lb/>
               that in the preparation of this Bill he con<lb break="no"/>sulted only three of his ministers, of whom 
                  <lb/>
               two came from his own province of Quebec. 
                  <lb/>
               I do not propose to discuss the Bill, but I 
                  <lb/>
               know now why the Minister of the Interior 
                  <lb/>
               has left the government; it is now known 
                  <lb/>
               that it is on the school question and it is 
                  <lb/>
               on the land question as I said on Monday<lb break="no"/>but it is more. The right hon. gentleman 
                  <lb/>
               in introducing a certain measure in this 
                  <lb/>
               House argued on three grounds, the con<lb break="no"/>stitutional ground, the ground of policy, and 
                  <lb/>
               he argued for separate schools per se and 
                  <lb/>
               it is because the proposition is for separate 
                  <lb/>
               schools per se that the late Minister of the 
                  <lb/>
               Interior has had to leave the administration. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. SPEAKER. I presume the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman (Mr. W. F. Maclean) intends to con<lb break="no"/>clude with a motion) 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr W. F. MACLEAN. Yes, I have cer<lb break="no"/>tainly the right to speak somewhat from the 
                  <lb/>
               standpoint of privilege, but I intend to con<lb break="no"/>clude with a motion. There is another 
                  <lb/>
               thing in regard to this question. There is 
                  <lb/>
               a good old verse in the Bible which says 
                  <lb/>
               that all they who take to the sword shall 
                  <lb/>
               perish by the sword; and I say that all 
                  <lb/>
               those who take to provincial rights and 
                  <lb/>
               school questions will die by provincial rights 
                  <lb/>
               and school questions. The handwriting is 
                  <lb/>
               on the wall. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Some hon. MEMBERS. Oh, oh. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. W. F. MACLEAN. Yes, and the right 
                  <lb/>
               hon. gentleman has lost not only his Minister 
                  <lb/>
               of the Interior, the Napoleon of the West, 
                  <lb/>
               but that panegyrist of his, who set the right 
                  <lb/>
               hon. gentleman up as the greatest states<lb break="no"/>man we have ever had in this country, 
                  <lb/>
               and who glorified the late Minister of the 
                  <lb/>
               Interior as the Napoleon of the West. The 
                  <lb/>
               two of them are now joined together 
                  <lb/>
               against the right hon. gentleman. He has 
                  <lb/>
               lost his chief organ, the Toronto 'Globe,' 
                  <lb/>
               or this question ; he has lost the Montreal 
                  <lb/>
               ' Witness,' another of his organs ; and 
                  <lb/>
               I am afraid that he is now about to repudiate 
                  <lb/>
               the last organ he appears to have left, ' Le 
                  <lb/>
               Soleil,' that organ which, in its pontifical 
                  <lb/>
               way, said the other day : 'We are the 
                  <lb/>
               organ of Sir Wilfrid, and every one must 
                  <lb/>
               take note of it and govern themselves ac<lb break="no"/>cordingly.' 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I now come to the question of the school 
                  <lb/>
               lands and the way little Manitoba is treat<lb break="no"/>
           
            <!--<p>59 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>--><cb/>ed; and again I call the attention of the 
                  <lb/>
               hon. member for Lisgar (Mr. Greenway), 
                  <lb/>
               who is now in his place, to this declaration 
                  <lb/>
               of the leading organ of the right hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman, that it was the intention to pun<lb break="no"/>ish Manitoba because she had vindicated 
                  <lb/>
               provincial rights in connection with edu<lb break="no"/>cational matters. The province of Manitoba 
                  <lb/>
               has an area of only 74,000 square miles, 
                  <lb/>
               while the proposed provinces are to have 
                  <lb/>
               an area of nearly 300,000 square miles 
                  <lb/>
               each. But the province of Manitoba hap<lb break="no"/>pens to be in favour of public education, 
                  <lb/>
               and she is to be punished ; and now the 
                  <lb/>
               House and the country will be able to 
                  <lb/>
               see how all this came about. If you ex<lb break="no"/>tended the limits of the province of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba to the west, the result would be that 
                  <lb/>
               the portion of territory to the east would 
                  <lb/>
               have the right to regulate its own educat<lb break="no"/>ional affairs, while the other portion of the 
                  <lb/>
               same territory would be shackled. That is 
                  <lb/>
               the reason why Manitoba is being punished. 
                  <lb/>
               And so it turns out, after all the taunts 
                  <lb/>
               that I was met with here on Monday, that 
                  <lb/>
               I was right when I said that Manitoba was 
                  <lb/>
               being punished, and that the Dominion Lands 
                  <lb/>
               Act would have to be changed in order to 
                  <lb/>
               carry out the proposal made in the Bill. I 
                  <lb/>
               was given what was called a categorical 
                  <lb/>
               denial ; but to-day I have received a cate<lb break="no"/>gorical affirmation from the late Minister of 
                  <lb/>
               the Interior, I warn the right hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man that he is engaged in a quixotic career 
                  <lb/>
               if he fancies that he and his party, which 
                  <lb/>
               claims to be the party of provincial rights, 
                  <lb/>
               can shackle the two new provinces of the 
                  <lb/>
               west and impose a separate school system 
                  <lb/>
               upon them without consulting the people. 
                  <lb/>
               He does not consult his own ministers-<lb/>
the confession is made to-day. And what 
                  <lb/>
               is to be the fate of that minister who to<lb break="no"/>day declares that he has not been consulted? 
                  <lb/>
               He is to be Tartified and Blairified, like the 
                  <lb/>
               other ministers who have resigned ; and 
                  <lb/>
               the same fate awaits any one else who 
                  <lb/>
               chooses not to come under this new czardom 
                  <lb/>
               which we have in this country, under which 
                  <lb/>
               not even a cabinet minister is to be con<lb break="no"/>sulted in regard to public policy; under 
                  <lb/>
               which that great free west, which feels 
                  <lb/>
               more keenly on these great public questions 
                  <lb/>
               than we do in the east, is not to be con<lb break="no"/>sulted through its recognized minister, but 
                  <lb/>
               this hasty and ill-advised proposal is to 
                  <lb/>
               be introduced into this House in his ab<lb break="no"/>sence. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I congratulate the late Minister of the 
                  <lb/>
               Interior upon having the courage to come 
                  <lb/>
               out. I can say this at least of him, that 
                  <lb/>
               he has justified to-day that mission which 
                  <lb/>
               he made several years ago into my own 
                  <lb/>
               province, into the county of Haldimand, 
                  <lb/>
               to say that he came to the province of On<lb break="no"/>tario to ask for our sympathy because 
                  <lb/>
               it was proposed to put shackles upon his 
                  <lb/>
               province ; because, he said, if the province 
                  <lb/>
               of Manitoba is shackled to-day, the time 
                  <lb/>
               will come when the greater provinces to 
                  <lb/>
         
            
           <!-- <p>
               REVISED EDITION 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>-->
            
      
            <pb n="1859" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1859.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1859</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">1860</fw>
            
                          the west will be treated in the same way. 
                  <lb/>
               It turns out now that this treatment is 
                  <lb/>
               being meted out by the czar of the Liberal 
                  <lb/>
               party without consulting his colleagues. And 
                  <lb/>
               this man of autocratic tendencies gets up 
                  <lb/>
               in this House and reads us a lecture and 
                  <lb/>
               calls us all kinds of names; and yet, 
                  <lb/>
               within less than forty-eight hours of his 
                  <lb/>
               lecture to me, everything I said has been 
                  <lb/>
               justified and proved true. The right hon. 
                  <lb/>
               gentleman to-day stands discredited in this 
                  <lb/>
               House. He stands discredited of his own <lb/>
colleagues ; he stands discredited in the 
                  <lb/>
               different provinces, especially in the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Ontario, and by his own newspaper, 
                  <lb/>
               the 'Globe.' The right hon. gentleman quot<lb break="no"/>ed George Brown. The right hon. gentleman 
                  <lb/>
               actually read into the constitution the ut<lb break="no"/>terances of George Brown's newspaper and 
                  <lb/>
               George Brown's speeches, in justification of 
                  <lb/>
               this proposal of his to shackle these great 
                  <lb/>
               new provinces of the west. The right hon. 
                  <lb/>
               gentleman has failed. He has no justifica<lb break="no"/>tion for his proposal except as a matter of 
                  <lb/>
               policy. But he has not made it a question of 
                  <lb/>
               policy. He made a bogus constitutional 
                  <lb/>
               argument, and then he made a moral argu<lb break="no"/>ment, and that moral argument was what ? 
                  <lb/>
               Many a time in this House the right hon. 
                  <lb/>
               gentleman has read us a lesson about res<lb break="no"/>pect for our neighbours ; but there never 
                  <lb/>
               was a more insulting statement made to 
                  <lb/>
               the people of the United States than that 
                  <lb/>
               statement of his that they were immoral, that 
                  <lb/>
               divorces, lynchings and murders prevailed 
                  <lb/>
               in their country, and that the reason of 
                  <lb/>
               Canada's superiority in this respect was 
                  <lb/>
               that dogma was taught in our public schools. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Some hon. MEMBERS. Order. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. W. F. MACLEAN. What the people <lb/>of Canada believe in is the separation of 
                  <lb/>
               state and church. With regard to what is 
                  <lb/>
               embodied in the constitution, so far as On<lb break="no"/>tario and Quebec are concerned, we say all 
                  <lb/>
               right, we accept the situation. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               An hon. MEMBER. Thank you. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. W. F. MACLEAN. Nay, more ; I 
                  <lb/>
               go further and say, I for one would not 
                  <lb/>
               lift my hand to prevent the people of these 
                  <lb/>
               western provinces having separate schools 
                  <lb/>
               if they desire them. But my plea is that 
                  <lb/>
               the question must be left to them—that we 
                  <lb/>
               must not impose these schools upon them. 
                  <lb/>
               I am ready to declare here or anywhere else 
                  <lb/>
               ——shall I say as a radical or a democrat ?-<lb/>
for the principle of the entire separation of 
                  <lb/>
               church and state, so far as our constitution 
                  <lb/>
               will permit it. The right hon. gentleman 
                  <lb/>
               is in this House to-day as the champion of 
                  <lb/>
               a new alliance between church and state, 
                  <lb/>
               Again I warn him that he is on dangerous 
                  <lb/>
               ground. Again I tell him that he who 
                  <lb/>
               takes to the sword shall perish by the 
                  <lb/>
               sword. He who apparently, a few weeks 
                  <lb/>
               ago, entered on a long career of office, is to<lb break="no"/>day face to face with the handwriting on 
                  <lb/>
               the wall. I would like to see the right hon. 
                  <lb/>
               
 
           <!-- <p>
               Mr. W. F. MACLEAN. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>-->
            
         
        <cb/>

               gentleman introduce great measures into 
                  <lb/>
               this House, and not bring up questions of 
                  <lb/>
               this kind. I do not want to say anything 
                  <lb/>
               against my hon. friend who has retired from 
                  <lb/>
               office to-day ; but if there is one thing he 
                  <lb/>
               can recall, it is this : He came in on that 
                  <lb/>
               wave ; he goes out on that wave ; whi<lb break="no"/>ther it will carry him I leave him to find 
                  <lb/>
               out in his own experience. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. LEIGHTON G. McCARTHY (North 
                  <lb/>
               Simcoe). Mr. Speaker. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. SPEAKER. There is still no ques<lb break="no"/>tion before the House. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. W. F. MACLEAN. I move the ad<lb break="no"/>journment of the House. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. LEIGHTON G. McCARTHY. The 
                  <lb/>
               hon. member for South York (Mr. W. F. 
                  <lb/>
               Maclean) has referred to matters which, 
                  <lb/>
               perhaps should not have been referred to 
                  <lb/>
               in discussing the question before the House. 
                  <lb/>
               But, lest my silence should be misconstrued, 
                  <lb/>
               l desire to make a short statement. I oc<lb break="no"/>cupy, on this question, a much different 
                  <lb/>
               position from that occupied, probably, by 
                  <lb/>
               any other member in this House.  My hon. 
                  <lb/>
               friend from South York refers to the cam<lb break="no"/>paign of some ten years ago in the county 
                  <lb/>
               of Haldimand. The fact was referred to 
                  <lb/>
               that, on that occasion, the ex-Minister of the 
                  <lb/>
               Interior (Mr. Sifton) and myself stood on 
                  <lb/>
               the same platform when we were fighting 
                  <lb/>
               the men who are now calling in question 
                  <lb/>
               the actions which have taken place and have 
                  <lb/>
               caused that hon. gentleman's (Mr. Sifton's) 
                  <lb/>
               retirement. Therefore, for the last ten 
                  <lb/>
               years, my position on the school question 
                  <lb/>
               has been defined. I also fought on the 
                  <lb/>
               school question in 1895 in Cardwell, and 
                  <lb/>
               again in June 1896 was the school question 
                  <lb/>
               fought out in my riding. From that day 
                  <lb/>
               to this, I have remained firm and free, so 
                  <lb/>
               far as my constituency was concerned, upon 
                  <lb/>
               this question, and I have been thrice en<lb break="no"/>dorsed upon it. Therefore, I simply rise to 
                  <lb/>
               announce to this House as I announced the 
                  <lb/>
               first time I spoke in the House and as I 
                  <lb/>
               have previously announced to individual 
                  <lb/>
               members, that I am, like the ex-Minister of 
                  <lb/>
               the Interior, absolutely opposed to the 
                  <lb/>
               education clauses as submitted in the Auto<lb break="no"/>nomy Bills ; that I will oppose them and 
                  <lb/>
               oppose them unalterably. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. T. S. SPROULE (East Grey). I do 
                  <lb/>
               not rise to anticipate the discussion on the 
                  <lb/>
               Bill that will shortly be before us or to 
                  <lb/>
               explain to the House where I stand on 
                  <lb/>
               the question—I think my position is pretty 
                  <lb/>
               well known. But I rise merely to say that, 
                  <lb/>
               so far as the Prime Minister has given this 
                  <lb/>
               House his confidence, and so far as he has 
                  <lb/>
               explained the position, all is well. But 
                  <lb/>
               some of us thought he might well have 
                  <lb/>
               gone a little further. Perhaps to expect 
                  <lb/>
               that would be to ask him to anticipate 
                  <lb/>
               events. He did not indicate in any way 
                  <lb/>
               who is to be the incumbent of the office 
                  <lb/>
               
          
            <pb n="1861" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1861.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1861</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               MARCH 1, 1905 
            </fw>
            <fw type="num">1862<lb/></fw>
            
          
               which has just been made vacant. How<lb break="no"/>ever, that is something that concerns him 
                  <lb/>
               more than it does us on this side of the 
                  <lb/>
               House. But, in view of the loss from the 
                  <lb/>
               cabinet of the representative of Manitoba 
                  <lb/>
               and the Northwest,—and a man regarded 
                  <lb/>
               by many as one of the ablest members of 
                  <lb/>
               the cabinet to which he belonged, I wish to 
                  <lb/>
               ask the Prime Minister if he does not think 
                  <lb/>
               that it would be well to tell this House 
                  <lb/>
               that he is prepared to drop that clause of 
                  <lb/>
               the Bill ? I wish also to congratulate the 
                  <lb/>
               hon. member for Brandon (Mr. Sifton) who 
                  <lb/>
               has just resigned, and to congratulate our<lb break="no"/>selves who are opposed to this feature of 
                  <lb/>
               the Bill, upon the acquisition by our ranks 
                  <lb/>
               of that hon. gentleman and also of the hon. 
                  <lb/>
               member for North Simcoe (Mr. L. G. Mc<lb break="no"/>Carthy). 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Mr. L. G. MCCARTHY. Don't call the 
                  <lb/>
               hon. member for North Simcoe an acquisi<lb break="no"/>tion. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. SPROULE. I hope that many others 
                  <lb/>
               on that side will find that open confession 
                  <lb/>
               is good for the soul, and will rise and do 
                  <lb/>
               as these hon. gentlemen have done. While 
                  <lb/>
               I am on my feet I would like to say a word 
                  <lb/>
               with regard to the number of copies of 
                  <lb/>
               the Bill distributed so far. Eight days ago 
                  <lb/>
               the Bill was introduced. Up to to-day each 
                  <lb/>
               of us could only get one copy of the Bill. 
                  <lb/>
               Yesterday, the Prime Minister said that 
                  <lb/>
               there was no objection to having a large 
                  <lb/>
               number struck off. It would only take two 
                  <lb/>
               or three hours to strike off a couple of 
                  <lb/>
               thousand copies of the Bill. It seems 
                  <lb/>
               strange to us, therefore, that up to the 
                  <lb/>
               present, we have been able to get only four 
                  <lb/>
               or five copies each. I made inquiry of the 
                  <lb/>
               Printing Bureau and they told me : We 
                  <lb/>
               were instructed to give no information as 
                  <lb/>
               to the number of copies of the Bill to be 
                  <lb/>
               printed. It seems strange that there should 
                  <lb/>
               be such secrecy. I would ask the Prime 
                  <lb/>
               Minister if he knows any good reason why 
                  <lb/>
               we should not get more copies of the Bill, 
                  <lb/>
               and whether he will give instructions that 
                  <lb/>
               a much larger number be printed, because 
                  <lb/>
               there is an urgent demand for them from 
                  <lb/>
               many parts of the country. I myself have 
                  <lb/>
               applications for at least a hundred copies 
                  <lb/>
               of the Bill. Yet, though it is eight days 
                  <lb/>
               since the Bill was introduced, I am able 
                  <lb/>
               to supply only five. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. SAM. HUGHES (Victoria and Hali<lb break="no"/>burton). It is not my intention to speak on 
                  <lb/>
               this matter, further than to congratulate 
                  <lb/>
               the late Minister of the Interior (Mr. Sifton) 
                  <lb/>
               on the action he has taken in withdrawing 
                  <lb/>
               from the present government. I take this 
                  <lb/>
               opportunity of stating that, as soon as the 
                  <lb/>
               Bill was introduced, knowing the action 
                  <lb/>
               that the late Minister of the Interior had 
                  <lb/>
               taken in 1895 and 1896, when the Manitoba 
                  <lb/>
               school question was under discussion, though 
                  <lb/>
               I had no consultation with the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man, I had absolute faith that he would 
                  <lb/>
               take the course he has taken to-day.  In 
                  <lb/>
         
            
          <!--  <p>
                
                  <lb/>
               591/2 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>-->
            
        <cb/>

               justice to that hon. gentleman I may say 
                  <lb/>
               îhat I am in a position to state positively, 
                  <lb/>
               knowing whereof I speak, that it was his 
                  <lb/>
               desire that the Manitoba school question 
                  <lb/>
               should be kept out of the arena of Domi<lb break="no"/>nion politics and be settled in a satisfactory 
                  <lb/>
               manner by the province. That was the wish 
                  <lb/>
               also of many hon. gentlemen on the Lib<lb break="no"/>eral-Conservative side of this House. But 
                  <lb/>
               the wishes of those gentlemen and of the 
                  <lb/>
               late Minister of the Interior were not gra<lb break="no"/>tified. I felt that there was no other hon<lb break="no"/>ourable course open to the late Minister of 
                  <lb/>
               the Interior, than that which he has taken, 
                  <lb/>
               and I had the most perfect confidence in his 
                  <lb/>
               strength of purpose and knew that he 
                  <lb/>
               would not tolerate the infliction upon the 
                  <lb/>
               Northwest of the clause in this Bill relat<lb break="no"/>ing to education. I ask the Prime Minister; 
                  <lb/>
               I appeal to his patriotism—and he pretends 
                  <lb/>
               to be patriotic—in view of the fact that 
                  <lb/>
               the Minister of the Interior has retired and 
                  <lb/>
               that other ministers hang their heads when 
                  <lb/>
               this Bill is mentioned ; in view of the fact 
                  <lb/>
               that many hon. members behind him will 
                  <lb/>
               not and dare not support him ; in the in<lb break="no"/>terest of the west and of the financial and 
                  <lb/>
               commercial institutions that depend upon 
                  <lb/>
               the development and progress of that great 
                  <lb/>
               country, I appeal to him to pause in press<lb break="no"/>ing this Bill. He cannot but know that the 
                  <lb/>
               great tide of immigration now flowing to<lb break="no"/>ward that country, once checked will not 
                  <lb/>
               easily resume its course. I predict, if he 
                  <lb/>
               goes on with this Bill—and I am not the 
                  <lb/>
               only one who predicts—dire disaster to this 
                  <lb/>
               country.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 
                  <lb/>
               An hon. MEMBER. War. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. SAM. HUGHES. War ? Sir, if be<lb break="no"/>cause a few half-breeds on the banks of 
                  <lb/>
               the Saskatchewan refused to accept the 
                  <lb/>
               new and reasonable method of survey in<lb break="no"/>stead of the old one to which they were 
                  <lb/>
               accustomed, the First Minister would have 
                  <lb/>
               been justified in shouldering his musket in 
                  <lb/>
               their support, as he declared in 1885 he 
                  <lb/>
               would have done, then far more would the 
                  <lb/>
               boys in the Northwest—it will not need 
                  <lb/>
               the boys from Ontario—be justified in 
                  <lb/>
               shouldering their muskets in resistance to 
                  <lb/>
               the tyranny the Prime Minister proposes in 
                  <lb/>
               this Bill. His action, if he persists in it, 
                  <lb/>
               will check the tide of immigration into that 
                  <lb/>
               country and will produce a crisis in the 
                  <lb/>
               financial and business affairs of the Dom<lb break="no"/>inion. I ask the First Minister to give his 
                  <lb/>
               most careful attention to this idea. He 
                  <lb/>
               can turn a corner as quickly as anybody 
                  <lb/>
               can. It is not too late for him yet. Let 
                  <lb/>
               him withdraw these clauses of his Bill. 
                  <lb/>
               and leave it to the Northwest to settle this 
                  <lb/>
               matter. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. GEORGE TAYLOR (Leeds). I do 
                  <lb/>
               not rise to discuss the Bill which has led 
                  <lb/>
               to the resignation of the Minister of the 
                  <lb/>
               Interior (Mr. Sifton) but only to congratu<lb break="no"/>late my hon. friend from North Simcoe (Mr. 
                  <lb/>
               L. G. McCarthy) on having already de<lb break="no"/><pb n="1863" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1863.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1863</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">1864</fw>lared his attitude. He is not a member of 
                  <lb/>
               the cabinet ; but I presume that he was a 
                  <lb/>
               prospective minister. I have been waiting 
                  <lb/>
               to hear from another gentleman who sits 
                  <lb/>
               close to that hon. member. I refer to the 
                  <lb/>
               hon. member for North Ontario (Mr. Grant). 
                  <lb/>
               At a by-election in that constituency, I had 
                  <lb/>
               the honour to go there to say a word on 
                  <lb/>
               behalf of the hon. member for North Tor<lb break="no"/>onto (Mr. Foster) who was then a candidate 
                  <lb/>
               in North Ontario. And one of the principal 
                  <lb/>
               things brought against the hon. member 
                  <lb/>
               for North Toronto in that campaign, was 
                  <lb/>
               that he had supported the Remedial Bill, 
                  <lb/>
               and if elected would advocate the granting 
                  <lb/>
               of separate schools in the Northwest. That 
                  <lb/>
               was the principal argument used in that 
                  <lb/>
               by-election to further the election of the hon. 
                  <lb/>
               member for North Ontario, and I now expect 
                  <lb/>
               to hear from him that he will follow the hon. 
                  <lb/>
               member for North Simcoe and declare the 
                  <lb/>
               position he purposes taking when the Bill 
                  <lb/>
               comes up. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. HUGH GUTHRIE (South Wellington) 
                  <lb/>
               On the motion to adjourn, moved by the 
                  <lb/>
               hon. member for South York (Mr. W. F. 
                  <lb/>
               Maclean) and on which several members 
                  <lb/>
               have spoken, some of whom have said that 
                  <lb/>
               they are unalterably opposed to clause 16 
                  <lb/>
               of the Bills creating two new provinces in 
                  <lb/>
               the Northwest Territories, I would say on 
                  <lb/>
               my own behalf, speaking for myself only, 
                  <lb/>
               that I am unalterably in favour of that 
                  <lb/>
               clause 16 in the two Bills shortly to come 
                  <lb/>
               up for a second reading. So far as I have 
                  <lb/>
               been able to gather, the only point urged 
                  <lb/>
               today is that made by the hon. member 
                  <lb/>
               for North Toronto (Mr. Foster) who says 
                  <lb/>
               that the Bills are hurried ones. Surely he 
                  <lb/>
               does not mean that these are new Bills. I 
                  <lb/>
               remember last session hearing this matter 
                  <lb/>
               discussed, if not in the House at all events 
                  <lb/>
               around the House, and likewise the session 
                  <lb/>
               before that. They are, I submit, two of 
                  <lb/>
               the best considered Bills that have ever 
                  <lb/>
               been brought forward; and although they 
                  <lb/>
               may not have been as fully discussed with 
                  <lb/>
               some members of the government as they 
                  <lb/>
               might have been, still I venture to say that 
                  <lb/>
               during the past five or ten years no ques<lb break="no"/>tion has received greater consideration. If 
                  <lb/>
               I read parliamentary practise aright, if I 
                  <lb/>
               understand Todd's parliamentary procedure 
                  <lb/>
               and May's usages of parliament, I believe I 
                  <lb/>
               am correct in saying that it is the Prime 
                  <lb/>
               Minister who should introduce measures of 
                  <lb/>
               the kind we are now discussing; and if any 
                  <lb/>
               of the members of his cabinet are not in 
                  <lb/>
               accord with him, they have one duty to 
                  <lb/>
               perform and that is to resign. If the ex- 
                  <lb break="yes"/>
               Minster of the Interior (Mr. Sifton) found 
                  <lb/>
               he could not support the government in this 
                  <lb/>
               matter, he has taken the proper course; but 
                  <lb/>
               as I understand the question, so far as it 
                  <lb/>
               has now gone, there is a distinct desire on 
                  <lb/>
               the part of hon. members opposite, evinced 
                  <lb/>
               both in their speeches and their newspapers, 
                  <lb/>
               to create some inflammatory condition in this 
                  <lb/>
       
            
           <!-- <p>
               Mr. TAYLOR. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>-->
            
      <cb/>
               country which there is nothing in the Bills 
                  <lb/>
               introduced to warrant. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Some hon. MEMBERS. What about the 
                  <lb/>
               Globe ? 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. GUTHRIE. I have read the edi<lb break="no"/>torials in the ' Globe,' in which that news<lb break="no"/>paper takes issue with the government re<lb break="no"/>garding the educational policy laid down in 
                  <lb/>
               the Bills presented to this House. I am 
                  <lb/>
               sorry that the ' Globe' cannot see as the 
                  <lb/>
               government do on this question, but the 
                  <lb/>
               ' Globe ' is only one newspaper, and we are 
                  <lb/>
               legislating for the whole Dominion. If the 
                  <lb/>
               ' Globe ' cannot see eye to eye with us, that 
                  <lb/>
               is no reason whatever why we should turn 
                  <lb/>
               back from what we believe to be our duty. 
                  <lb/>
               The majority of this House and the coun<lb break="no"/>try, I am convinced, are of the opinion that 
                  <lb/>
               the measure submitted to us is right 
                  <lb/>
               and just; and in that belief I think we 
                  <lb/>
               should go forward notwithstanding the To<lb break="no"/>ronto ' Globe ' and the organ of the hon. 
                  <lb/>
               member for South York (Mr. W. F. Mac- 
                  <lb break="yes"/>
               lean) and those other organs which are 
                  <lb/>
               criticising these Bills very adversely at pre<lb break="no"/>sent. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. FOSTER. I do not want the right 
                  <lb/>
               hon. the First Minister to forget the second 
                  <lb/>
               question that I ventured to put to him so 
                  <lb/>
               that he may settle, if it is in his power to 
                  <lb/>
               do so, these disquieting rumours which have 
                  <lb/>
               been given currency with reference to the 
                  <lb/>
               attitude of some others of his ministers on 
                  <lb/>
               this Bill. We have had a most important 
                  <lb/>
               piece of information from the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man who has just spoken. He has just 
                  <lb/>
               told us that this Bill has been discussed 
                  <lb/>
               for two sessions, and he has informed the 
                  <lb/>
               House with all becoming gravity that it is 
                  <lb/>
               still being discussed. Where ? Is there 
                  <lb/>
               an inner circle somewhere ? 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. GUTHRIE. I said around the House. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. FOSTER. Is there a circle within a 
                  <lb/>
               circle in the party headed by my right hon. 
                  <lb/>
               friend, and at the head of which is pro<lb break="no"/>bably the right hon. gentleman who leads 
                  <lb/>
               the government? Is there an inner circle 
                  <lb/>
               which takes up these things in advance and 
                  <lb/>
               discusses and settles them and brings them 
                  <lb/>
               to a point where they are in the position of 
                  <lb/>
               not being new matters but things well dis<lb break="no"/>cussed and settled during these two years? 
                  <lb/>
               Last year my hon. friend the Minister of 
                  <lb/>
               the Interior (Mr. Sifton) was, I believe, pre<lb break="no"/>sent in this House and in his wonted 
                  <lb/>
               health. He was also present the year be<lb break="no"/>fore last in equally good condition. During 
                  <lb/>
               all that time, as we have just been in<lb break="no"/>formed. the principles of this Bill were be<lb break="no"/>ing discussed, and surely if any one of them 
                  <lb/>
               was discussed it must have been that one 
                  <lb/>
               dealing with the school question. But evi<lb break="no"/>dently the Minister of the Interior was not 
                  <lb/>
               in that warm current. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. SPEAKER. Is the hon. gentleman 
                  <lb/>
               bringing up some new matters? I would 
                  <lb/>
               
           
            <pb n="1865" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1865.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1865</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
               MARCH 1, 1905 
            </fw>
            <fw type="num">1866</fw>
            
     
               remind him that he has already spoken 
                  <lb/>
               once. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. FOSTER. I spoke not on the adjourn<lb break="no"/>ment but on the ministerial explanation, 
                  <lb/>
               and I am now calling the attention of the 
                  <lb/>
               First Minister to the question I have just 
                  <lb/>
               put. I also want to call his attention to 
                  <lb/>
               something else. It is in the interests of the 
                  <lb/>
               country that we should know whether two 
                  <lb/>
               or three days ago, after conferring with 
                  <lb/>
               the Minister of the Interior, my right hon. 
                  <lb/>
               friend still had hopes that the Minister of the 
                  <lb/>
               Interior would accede to what was evidently 
                  <lb/>
               a proposition put to him, possibly in modi<lb break="no"/>fication of this clause of the Bill, and that 
                  <lb/>
               his resignation at the last moment came as 
                  <lb/>
               a disappointment. It would be interesting to 
                  <lb/>
               the House to know whether the right hon. 
                  <lb/>
               gentleman made any advance towards a 
                  <lb/>
               compromise in the Bill as presented, in or<lb break="no"/>der to retain his colleague in the cabinet. I 
                  <lb/>
               want to call to the attention of my right 
                  <lb/>
               hon. friend two other matters, which I may 
                  <lb/>
               as well bring before him now, as otherwise 
                  <lb/>
               I should have to call his attention to them 
                  <lb/>
               later. I find that in the printed Bill there 
                  <lb/>
               are material alterations as compared with the 
                  <lb/>
               Bill laid on the table, when introduced by 
                  <lb/>
               the right hon. gentleman.  What is the 
                  <lb/>
               cause for these modifications? Have some 
                  <lb/>
               modifications been made between the time 
                  <lb/>
               this Bill was introduced and the time when 
                  <lb/>
               it was sent to the printer, with a view 
                  <lb/>
               of retaining in the government the Minister 
                  <lb/>
               of the Interior or any other aggrieved min<lb break="no"/>ister? When my hon. friend here to my 
                  <lb/>
               right asked for the printing of a larger num<lb break="no"/>ber of copies of the Bill, it struck me that 
                  <lb/>
               perhaps there was method in not printing 
                  <lb/>
               too many copies, because, before the next 
                  <lb/>
               printing takes place, it may possibly be that 
                  <lb/>
               some other clauses will be modified in or<lb break="no"/>der to retain members who are at present re<lb break="no"/>calcitrant, or to gain the favour of those 
                  <lb/>
               who are opposed to the Bill as it stands. 
                  <lb/>
               But I call my right hon. friend's attention 
                  <lb/>
               to this peculiarity, that some of the clauses 
                  <lb/>
               of the Bill which he put in Mr. Speaker's 
                  <lb/>
               hands do not appear in these Bills, the swamp 
                  <lb/>
               lands clause for instance. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir WILFRID LAURIER. I think the <lb/>hon. gentleman is mistaken.<lb/>
               <lb/> 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. FOSTER.  I think not.  I had a<lb/>copy of the Bill and read it, and I am sure 
                  <lb/>
               that was not in the Bill. I merely mention 
                  <lb/>
               the matter so that the right hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man may notice it. There is one other 
                  <lb/>
               thing I would like to speak of. We have 
                  <lb/>
               had placed in our hands what purports to 
                  <lb/>
               be a history from oflicial sources of the 
                  <lb/>
               legislation of the united provinces of the 
                  <lb/>
               Dominion since confederation. I do not 
                  <lb/>
               know to whose courtesy we are indebted<lb/>for this. It is useful in its way, so far as 
                  <lb/>
               it goes. But it has been stated in the 
                  <lb/>
               public press that it was arranged<lb/>and collated by the Secretary of State, 
                  <lb/>
        <cb/>

               and publicity has been given to that state<lb break="no"/>ment, and it is believed by a great many 
                  <lb/>
               people. I do not know whether that is 
                  <lb/>
               the case or not. I have no objection to the 
                  <lb/>
               government giving us all and the fullest 
                  <lb/>
               information with reference to the subject, 
                  <lb/>
               but I do object to the government putting 
                  <lb/>
               anything in circulation as official informa<lb break="no"/>tion if it has been done under the auspices 
                  <lb/>
               I have mentioned, and as has been reported 
                  <lb/>
               in the press, because the information is 
                  <lb/>
               more than a statement of facts, and is shap<lb break="no"/>ed into an argument from the beginning to 
                  <lb/>
               snpport the contention of the government. 
                  <lb/>
               I hope my right hon. friend will be able to 
                  <lb/>
               say that this has not been prepared by the 
                  <lb/>
               government or any member of the govern<lb break="no"/>ment, or officials connected with the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. It seems to bear the impress of 
                  <lb/>
               being printed in the Government Printing 
                  <lb/>
               Bureau, though that may not be the case. 
                  <lb/>
               However, as that has been current, I bring 
                  <lb/>
               it to the attention of my right hon. friend 
                  <lb/>
               so that he may mention it, if he will be 
                  <lb/>
               kind enough to do so, in connection with 
                  <lb/>
               the other points I have raised. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Hon. JOHN HAGGART (South Lanark). 
                  <lb/>
               In order to emphasize some of the remarks 
                  <lb/>
               of the hon. member for North Toronto (Mr. 
                  <lb/>
               Foster) I wish to draw the attention of the 
                  <lb/>
               premier to a statement he made in the min<lb break="no"/>isterial correspondence which he read as 
                  <lb/>
               having taken place between him and his 
                  <lb/>
               late colleague. It is to my mind a very cur<lb break="no"/>ious statement. He said that in consulta<lb break="no"/>tion with his colleague he hoped he would 
                  <lb/>
               be able to yield somewhat to his views so 
                  <lb/>
               as to retain him in the cabinet. Now what 
                  <lb/>
               the House wants is a clear cut statement 
                  <lb/>
               from the premier whether he is wedded to 
                  <lb/>
               that particular clause of the Bill regarding 
                  <lb/>
               separate schools, or whether he is prepared 
                  <lb/>
               to do what his colleague wishes him to do 
                  <lb/>
               in order to retain him in the cabinet, and 
                  <lb/>
               in order to meet the wishes of a great num<lb break="no"/>ber of his supporters in the House in that 
                  <lb/>
               direction. The difficulties may be all re<lb break="no"/>moved, there may be such an alteration in 
                  <lb/>
               that clause as that it may receive the sup<lb break="no"/>port of the whole House. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir WILFRID LAURIER. I have no ob<lb break="no"/>servation of any kind to offer to the House 
                  <lb/>
               on this occasion, because the occasion does 
                  <lb/>
               not call for any observation from me beyond 
                  <lb/>
               the statement which has been made by my<lb break="no"/>self and by my late colleague, the present 
                  <lb/>
               member for Brandon (Mr. Sifton). The hon. 
                  <lb/>
               member for South York (Mr. Maclean) knows 
                  <lb/>
               better than anybody that on such an oc<lb break="no"/>casion ministerial explanations are to be 
                  <lb/>
               given when a gentleman withdraws from 
                  <lb/>
               the administration, and it is left to the 
                  <lb/>
               prime minister and to the minister with<lb break="no"/>drawing to make such explanations as they 
                  <lb/>
               deem fit. I rise simply to answer one ques<lb break="no"/>tion, though it is not at all pertinent to 
                  <lb/>
               the issue, because everything that has been 
                  <lb/>
               said here on this occasion beyond that which 
                  <lb/>
               
      
            <pb n="1867" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-01_Page_1867.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">1867</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">1868</fw>
            
           
               refers to the withdrawal from the cabinet, 
                  <lb/>
               is aside altogether from the issue. But the 
                  <lb/>
               hon. gentleman has questioned me with re<lb break="no"/>gard to a pamphlet which has been issued 
                  <lb/>
               purporting to be certain collations from the 
                  <lb/>
               debates of this House on a former occasion 
                  <lb/>
               on the question of separate schools. I was 
                  <lb/>
               not aware until this moment that this pam<lb break="no"/>phlet had been distributed, and I shall make 
                  <lb/>
               inquiry and ascertain who is responsible 
                  <lb/>
               for it. I do not mean any discourtesy to 
                  <lb/>
               the House, on the contrary ; the House is 
                  <lb/>
               entitled to the amplest information, and 
                  <lb/>
               that it shall have at all times, and I hope 
                  <lb/>
               before this matter is settled. But many of 
                  <lb/>
               the matters which have been introduced to<lb break="no"/>day are absolutely foreign to the question 
                  <lb/>
               which I was forced to bring before the 
                  <lb/>
               House, that is to say the resignation of my 
                  <lb/>
               hon. friend from Brandon. The other ques<lb break="no"/>tions will come up at a later date. Some 
                  <lb/>
               remarks have been made, for instance, by 
                  <lb/>
               the hon. member for South Wellington (Mr. 
                  <lb/>
               Guthrie) when he said that this Bill had 
                  <lb/>
               been before the House for two sessions. 
                  <lb/>
               That was evidently a slip of the tongue, 
                  <lb/>
               and was easily answered. My hon. friend 
                  <lb/>
               meant only to say that the question of au<lb break="no"/>tonomy had been discussed for two sessions. 
                  <lb/>
               Everybody knows, especially the members 
                  <lb/>
               who were in the old parliament, that for 
                  <lb/>
               the last two sessions the question of auton<lb break="no"/>omy for the Territories has been under dis<lb break="no"/>cussion ; I presume that is what my hon. 
                  <lb/>
               friend had in his mind when he spoke on 
                  <lb/>
               this Bill. But the only object I had in ris<lb break="no"/>ing was to refer to a statement—not a state<lb break="no"/>ment but an insinuation, made, I think, by 
                  <lb/>
               the hon. member for South York. The hon. 
                  <lb/>
               gentleman insinuated that in bringing for<lb break="no"/>ward this measure there was an intention 
                  <lb/>
               on my part in some way to get rid of the 
                  <lb/>
               Minister of the Interior. I simply notice 
                  <lb/>
               the statement to give it the most emphatic 
                  <lb/>
               denial that I can. Whatever may be the 
                  <lb/>
               differences of opinion between myself and 
                  <lb/>
               my late colleague, I am sure he will acquit 
                  <lb/>
               me of having had any idea of acting deceit<lb break="no"/>fully towards him. I am sure that no one 
                  <lb/>
               knows better than himself that it is with 
                  <lb/>
               extreme regret that I have to lose his valu<lb break="no"/>able services, and if I could have retained 
                  <lb/>
               them 1 would have done so with great 
                  <lb/>
               pleasure. When the hon. member for South<lb/>York insinuates that I was conspiring<lb/>in some way to get rid of my hon. friend 
                  <lb/>
               from Brandon he makes an insinuation 
                  <lb/>
               which is absolutely eithout the shadow of 
                  <lb/>
               foundation. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Mr. SPROULE. We are entitled to some 
                  <lb/>
               information showing why we cannot get 
                  <lb/>
               more copies of the Bill. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Sir WILFRID LAURIER. My hon. friend 
                  <lb/>
               is very persistent in his question. I may 
                  <lb/>
               say at once that this matter of printing is 
                  <lb/>
               not in my department, it is in the hands 
                  <lb/>
               of the Secretary of State. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man will not be surprised perhaps to learn 
                  <lb/>
          
            
        <!--    <p>
               Sir WILFRID LAURIER. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>-->
            <cb/>
         
       
               that I have many things to attend to these 
                  <lb/>
               days, but I will not forget the subject and 
                  <lb/>
               will communicate directly with the Secretary 
                  <lb/>
               or' State. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               Motion (Mr. W. F. Maclean) to adjourn, 
                  <lb/>
               negatived. 
                  <lb/> </p>  
               
           <!-- GL, 2016-12-20, The rest of this text was not included, as it is not related to Confederation, I assume that this erasure was intentional -->
            
                 
            
    </div>     </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>