<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1903-10-01"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1903-10-01">1 October 1903</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Ninth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
          <date when="1903"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
          <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="12843" to="12846"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-01_Page_12843.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-01_Page_12845.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-26">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-09-26">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-01_Page_12843">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-01_Page_12843.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-01_Page_12845">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-01_Page_12845.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="12843" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-01_Page_12843.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12843</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">12844</fw>
            
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">GOVERNMENT OF THE NORTH-WEST<lb/>TERRITORIES—FINANCIAL AID.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p>Bill (No. 256) to provide for advances to<lb/>the government of the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, read the second time, and the House<lb/>went into committee thereon.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName> (Hon. W.<lb/>S. Fielding). This Bill is in the precise<lb/>terms of the resolution which has already<lb/>been fully discussed in Committee.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). Is this intended<lb/>as an advance for any paricular period of<lb/>time, say for the fiscal year, or is it simply<lb/>an indefinite advance to be paid to the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of the North-west Territories at<lb/>any time in the future, as the government<lb/>may see fit ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. It is an<lb/>advance without limit. It stands to the<lb/>credit of the government of the North-west<lb/>Territories, to be used or not to be used,<lb/>as in their discretion may seem to be neces<lb break="no"/>sary.<lb/>
            </p>
     
     
            <cb/>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). Has the corres<lb break="no"/>pondence brought down in connection with<lb/>this matter been printed ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. I am<lb/>not aware whether the correspondence has<lb/>been printed or not.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). My recollection<lb/>of the correspondence brought down in con<lb break="no"/>nection with this matter is that the Prime<lb/>Minister of the North-west Territories ob<lb break="no"/>jected to the creation of a debt accout be<lb break="no"/>tween the North-west Territories and the<lb/>government of Canada at the present time,<lb/>and pointed out that what the North-west<lb/>Territories really desire is that the annual<lb/>subside to the North-west Territories should<lb/>be increased to such an amount as would be<lb/>adequate for the works which they have to<lb/>undertake in the administration of that<lb/>country. He also expressed the opinion that<lb/>it was not in the interest of the North-west<lb/>Territories that any debt should be incurred<lb/>by them at the present time, before the<lb/>territories have received that provincial<lb/>status which has been demanded by its<lb/>legislature for some considerable time past.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. I do not<lb/>think that the government of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories objected to this advance<lb/>being made to them. The special point of<lb/>their objection was to a proposition which<lb/>was made at one stage of the negotiations<lb/>that the cost of two large bridges, for the<lb/>construction of which we were arranging<lb/>with them, should be made a charge against<lb/>an advance. However, I am sure the gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of the North-west Territories would<lb/>prefer to have any sums which are available<lb/>for them given in the way of an annual<lb/>grant and perhaps my hon. friend may be<lb/>right in saying they objected to this. There<lb/>is however, nothing compulsory about this ;<lb/>it is an option which we give to the govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the North-west Territories and if<lb/>they do not see fit to exercise it no harm<lb/>will be done. The allowance made in the<lb/>meantime was fully discussed in the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee. I then pointed out the rapid in<lb break="no"/>crease made by this government in the al<lb break="no"/>lowance to the North-west Territories and<lb/>I think the Committee were generally satis<lb break="no"/>fied that the allowances we now make, ir<lb break="no"/>respective of this grant, are quite liberal<lb/>and take due account of the rapid growth<lb/>and greater needs of that section of our<lb/>country.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). What increase<lb/>is made in the allowance for the present<lb/>year ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. I gave<lb/>the figures in the previous debate. The ap<lb break="no"/>propriation for 1902 was $407,979. I am<lb/>speaking now entirely of what I may call<lb/>the general vote for the North-west Terri<lb break="no"/>tories which would correspond to the pro<lb break="no"/>vincial subsidy. There are other grants<lb/>for other purposes, and my observations are<lb/>
       
       
            <pb n="12845" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-10-01_Page_12845.jpg"/>
       
       <fw type="num">12845</fw>
     <fw type="dateline">OCTOBER 1, 1903</fw> 
   
   
          
          confined entirely to that general vote which<lb/>appears in the estimates as a grant for<lb/>school and other purposes. For 1903, includ<lb break="no"/>ing the supplementary estimates passed in<lb/>the latter part of the year, the grant was<lb/>$707,989 and for the current year we are<lb/>proposing to pay them including a special<lb/>grant for two large bridges which at one<lb/>time it was suggested should be charged to<lb/>capital account, but which we ultimately<lb/>decided to provide for in the way of grant<lb/>—$1,046,979, irrespective of this advance<lb/>of which the government of the North-west<lb/>Territories may or may not avail them<lb break="no"/>selves.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Bill reported, read the third time and<lb/>passed.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>