<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1875-04-01"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1875-04-01">1 April 1875</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1975"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="1033" to="1035"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-01_Page_01033.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-01_Page_01034.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-01_Page_01035.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-11">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-01_Page_01033">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-01_Page_01033.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-01_Page_01034">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-01_Page_01034.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-01_Page_01035">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-01_Page_01035.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1033" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-01_Page_01033.jpg"/>
            
            
          <fw type="dateline">April 1, 1875</fw> <fw type="num">1033</fw>
            
            <head>NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES.</head>
            
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> moved the  
     <lb/>second reading of the Bill to amend and<lb/>consolidate the laws respecting the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories. He explained certain<lb/>changes he proposed to make in the Bill<lb/>in committee. It would be observed that<lb/>the 7th, 8th and 9th sections, contained<lb/>provisions respecting certain ordinances for<lb/>the administration of the laws of the<lb/>North-West Territories. These sections<lb/>were simply a recapitulation of the exist<lb break="no"/>ing laws and practically simply continued <lb/>the power vested in the Lieutenant Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor and Council of the North-West by<lb/>the present law. He proposed, however,<lb/>to remove some objections taken on the <lb/>introduction of this Bill by some hon.<lb/>members to the effect that we had no<lb/>right to generally delegate subjects of<lb/>legislation to another body in the way<lb/>
          
            <pb n="1034" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-01_Page_01034.jpg"/>
               
               
           <fw type="num">1034</fw> <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</fw>
           
           
     it was done by the existing law. He 
     <lb/>
     did not himself see much force in that ob<lb break="no"/>jection, as the Territories were practically 
     <lb/>
     constituted a Crown colony under our 
     <lb/>
     own immediate surveillance instead of 
     <lb/>
     under the Crown. He proposed to sub<lb break="no"/>stitute for the seventh and eighth sections 
     <lb/>
     the following :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "The Lieutenant Governor by and with 
     <lb/>
     the consent of the Council of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories may make, ordain and 
     <lb/>
     establish ordinances as to matters coming 
     <lb/>
     within the subjects next hereinafter 
     <lb/>
     enumerated, that is to say : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     l. Taxation for local and municipal 
     <lb/>
     purposes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. Property and civil rights in the 
     <lb/>
     Territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. The administration of justice in the 
     <lb/>
     Territories, including the maintenance 
     <lb/>
     and organization of courts, of civil and 
     <lb/>
     criminal jurisdiction and including pro<lb break="no"/>cedure in civil matters in these courts. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. Public health, the licensing of inns 
     <lb/>
     and places of refreshment, landmarks and 
     <lb/>
     foundaries, cruelty to animals, game and 
     <lb/>
     the care and protection thereof, injuries to 
     <lb/>
     public morals, nuisances, roads and 
     <lb/>
     bridges, the protection of timber, jails, 
     <lb/>
     lock—ups, and generally all matters of a 
     <lb/>
     merely local and private nature. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5. The imposition of and punishment by 
     <lb/>
     fine or penalty or imprisonment for the 
     <lb/>
     violation of any ordinance of the territory 
     <lb/>
     made in relation to any matter coming 
     <lb/>
     within any class of subjects herein enum<lb break="no"/>erated. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6. Provided that no ordinance so to be 
     <lb/>
     made by the Lieutenant Governor with 
     <lb/>
     the advice and consent of the Council of 
     <lb/>
     the said Territories, shall be inconsistent 
     <lb/>
     with, or alter or repeal any provision of 
     <lb/>
     any Act of the Parliament of Canada, or 
     <lb/>
     schedule of this Act or any Act of the 
     <lb/>
     Parliament of Canada which may now or 
     <lb/>
     at any time hereafter expressly refer to the 
     <lb/>
     said Territories, or which may be, at any 
     <lb/>
     time made by the GOVERNOR in Council, 
     <lb/>
     applicable to and in force in the said 
     <lb/>
     North-West Territories, or impose any fine 
     <lb/>
     or penalty exceeding $100. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     7. And provided that a copy of every 
     <lb/>
     such ordinance made by the Lieut. Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor in Council shall be mailed for trans<lb break="no"/>mission to the GOVERNOR GENERAL within 
     <lb/>
     ten days after its passage, and may be dis<lb break="no"/>allowed by him at any time within two 
     <lb/>
     years after its passage, and all such Orders 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
          
     in Council and all ordinances so made as 
     <lb/>
     aforesaid shall be laid before both Houses of 
     <lb/>
     Parliament as soon as convenient after their 
     <lb/>
     passage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     8. The GOVERNOR in Council may by 
     <lb/>
     proclamations made from time to time, 
     <lb/>
     direct that any Act of the Parliament of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, or any part or parts thereof shall 
     <lb/>
     be in force in the North—West Territories 
     <lb/>
     or in any part or parts thereof." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>
     The 9th section he proposed to amend to 
     <lb/>
     read as follows :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "Provided further that when and so soon 
     <lb/>
     as any electoral district shall be established 
     <lb/>
     as hereinafter provided the Lieut. Governor 
     <lb/>
     by and with the consent of the Council or 
     <lb/>
     the Assembly as the case may be, shall 
     <lb/>
     have power to pass ordinances for raising 
     <lb/>
     within such district by direct taxation or 
     <lb/>
     by shop, saloon, tavern, or any other such 
     <lb/>
     licences a revenue for local and municipal 
     <lb/>
     purposes for such district and for the collec<lb break="no"/>tion and appropriation of the same." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</quote>

            <p>
     The tenth section he proposed should 
     <lb/>
     read as follows :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " Whenever any electoral district shall 
     <lb/>
     be found to contain not less than 
     <lb/>
     inhabitants, the Lieut. Governor by and 
     <lb/>
     with the consent of the Council or 
     <lb/>
     Assembly, as the case may be, pass ordin<lb break="no"/>ances creating municipal corporations, and 
     <lb/>
     thenceforth the power of the Lieut. Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor in Council in respect of taxation for 
     <lb/>
     municipal purposes shall cease, and every 
     <lb/>
     such municipal corporation shall thence<lb break="no"/>forth have the right to pass by—laws for 
     <lb/>
     raising within such municipality by tax<lb break="no"/>ation a revenue for municipal purposes, 
     <lb/>
     and for the collection and appropriation of 
     <lb/>
     the same. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>
     11. When and so soon as any system 
     <lb/>
     of taxation shall be adopted in any district 
     <lb/>
     or portion of the North-West Territories 
     <lb/>
     the Lieut. Governor and Council or 
     <lb/>
     Assembly, as the case may be, shall 
     <lb/>
     pass all necessary ordinances in 
     <lb/>
     respect of education, and it shall 
     <lb/>
     therein be always provided that a majority 
     <lb/>
     of rate-payers in any district may estab<lb break="no"/>lish such schools therein as they may 
     <lb/>
     think fit and make the necessary assess<lb break="no"/>ment and rates therefor, and further that the 
     <lb/>
     minority of rate-payers therein whether Pro<lb break="no"/>testants or Roman Catholics may estab<lb break="no"/>lish separate schools therein. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The only other important amendment 
     <lb/>
     that he proposed was to make the provi<lb break="no"/>sion for the prohibition of the sale of in<lb break="no"/>
            
            <pb n="1035" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-01_Page_01035.jpg"/>
          <fw type="dateline">April 1, 1875.</fw> <fw type="num">1035</fw>
            
           
     toxicating liquors in the territory more 
     <lb/>stringent.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was read a second time, and <lb/>the House went into Committee on it<lb/>forthwith (Mr. Moss in the chair.)<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>It being six o'clock the committee rose.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>