<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1890-01-22" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1890-01-22">22 January 1890</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
<date when="1890"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="37" to="56"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00037.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00039.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00041.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00043.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00045.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00047.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00049.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00051.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00053.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00055.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-03">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-03">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00037"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00037.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00039"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00039.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00041"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00041.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00043"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00043.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00045"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00045.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00047"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00047.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00049"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00049.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00051"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00051.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00053"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00053.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00055"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00055.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="37" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00037.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">37</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 22, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">38</fw>

<table>
    <row><cell>Holton,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Weldon (Albert),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Ives,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Weldon (St. John),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Jamieson,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Welsh,</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Joncas,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">White (Cardwell),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Jones (Halifax),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">White (Renfrew),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Kenny,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wilson (Argenteuil)</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Kirk,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wood (Westmoreland),</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Kirkpatrick,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wright, and</cell></row>
    <row><cell>Landerkin,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Yeo.—110.</cell></row>
</table>

<p>And that the Quorum of the said Committee do <lb/>
consist of Nine Members. <lb/></p> 
</div>
<div type="debate">
<head rendition="simple:centre">ON AGRICULTURE AND COLONISATION.</head>

<head rendition="simple:centre">Messieurs</head>
    
    <table>
        <row><cell>Armstrong,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Guay,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Audet,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Guillet,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Bain (Soulanges),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Hesson,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Bain (Wentworth),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Innes,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Béchard,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Joncas,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Bell,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Jones (Digby),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Bernier,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Kirk,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Boisvert,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Labrosse,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Bourassa,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Landry,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Bowman,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Lang,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Brien,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Laurie (Lieut.-Gen.),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Bryson,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Lépine,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Burdett,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Livingston,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Burns,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Macdonald (Huron),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Cameron,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McCulla,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Carling,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McMillan (Huron),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Carpenter,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McMillan (Vaudreuil),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Chapleau,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">McNeill,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Chisholm,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Mara,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Choquette,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Marshall,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Cimon,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Masson,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Cochrane,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Mitchell,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Coughlin,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Montplaisir,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Coulombe,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Neveu,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Couture,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Paterson (Brant),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Daly,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Perley,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Daoust,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Perry,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Davin,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Platt,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Davis,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Pope,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Dawson,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Putnam,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Desaulniers,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Robertson,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Dessaint,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Rooms,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Dewdney,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Ross,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Dickinson,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Rowand,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Doyon,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Ste. Marie,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Earle,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Semple,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Edwards,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Smith (Ontario),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Eisenhauer,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Sproule,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Ferguson (Leeds &amp; Gren. ),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Stevenson,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Ferguson (Renfrew),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Sutherland,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Ferguson (Welland),</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Taylor,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Fiset,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Trow,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Fisher,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Tyrwhitt,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Flynn,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Watson,</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Gauthier,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">White (Renfrew),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Gigault,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wilson (Elgin),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Godbout,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wilson (Lennox),</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Gordon,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Wright, and</cell></row>
        <row><cell>Grandbois,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">Yeo.—98.</cell></row>
        
        
        
    </table>


<p>And that the Quorum of the said Committee do <lb/>
consist of Nine Members. <lb/></p>
    <p>
Motion agreed to. <lb/></p> 
</div>
<div type="debate">

<head rendition="simple:centre">ADULTERATION ACT AMENDMENT.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. COSTIGAN</persName> moved for leave to introduce <lb/>
Bill (No. 9) to amend the Adulteration Act, <lb/>
Chap. 107, Revised Statutes. He said: The first <lb/>
Object of this Bill is to change the present law <lb/>
so that if food or drugs be found in the possession <lb/>
of any person which on analysis be found to be <lb/>
adulterated, the cost of such analysis shall be <lb/>

<cb/>

charged to the owner of such adulterated article. <lb/>
This Bill when passed will be no tax whatever upon <lb/>
the honest trader and it proposes merely to make <lb/>
the vendor of adulterated articles pay the cost of <lb/>
the analysis. The other amendments are princi<lb break="no"/>pally with the object of strengthening the hands of <lb/>
the department in prosecuting under this Act. <lb/>
On account of the wording of one section of the <lb/>
Act, we find a difficulty in proceeding in certain <lb/>
matters, and to remove that difficulty, the amend<lb break="no"/>ment is proposed. <lb/></p>
    <p>
Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first time. <lb/></p> 
</div>
<div type="debate">

<head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH-VVEST TERRITORIES ACT—THE <lb/>
DUAL LANGUAGE.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName> moved for leave to introduce <lb/>
Bill (No. 10) to amend the North-West Territories <lb/>
Act. He said: In introducing this Bill I think <lb/>
that perhaps it might be as well that I should <lb/>
offer some explanation, though I do not think that <lb/>
any defence or apology is called for on my part in <lb/>
bringing this matter before the House. It is, how<lb break="no"/>ever, necessary that there should be some expla<lb break="no"/>nation, because it must occur to us all that it is <lb/>
most extraordinary that in the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, and so long ago as 1877 an Act should have <lb/>
been passed in this Parliament whereby the dual <lb/>
language was imposed upon the Territories; of <lb/>
course without any consent of theirs, because at <lb/>
that time there was practically no people in the <lb/>
Territories to assent, or consent, or dissent from the <lb/>
proposition. I think it is also requiring of expla<lb break="no"/>nation, not, as I say, to move for a repeal of this <lb/>
clause, but to give some account of how and why it <lb/>
is we find this clause in the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories Act. Now, the history of the matter, as I <lb/>
understand it, is this: I think it was a year or <lb/>
two, or perhaps three or four years, before the Act <lb/>
was passed to which I am about to refer more in <lb/>
detail, that the North-West Territories were con<lb break="no"/>stituted, or, at all events, brought under some kind <lb/>
or form of government—during the time my hon. <lb/>
friend the Prime Minister who now leads the <lb/>
Government and the House was also in the position <lb/>
he occupies to-day. In 1877, however, when my <lb/>
hon. friend from Bothwell (Mr. Mills) was Minister <lb/>
of the Interior in the Administration of the hon. <lb/>
member for East York (Mr. Mackenzie), he brought <lb/>
in a Bill to amend the North-West Territories Act, <lb/>
but that Bill as it was introduced into this House <lb/>
did not contain the clause with regard to the <lb/>
dual language which I now propose that <lb/>
the House should expunge. The Bill went <lb/>
in due course to the Senate, and in the Senate <lb/>
it was amended by the introduction of this clause; <lb/>
and, so far as I have been able to ascertain, there <lb/>
appears to have been no objection made in that <lb/>
body to the clause, which was introduced, as I am <lb/>
told, by an hon. Senator at the instance of the <lb/>
then leader of the Government in that House, the <lb/>
Hon. Mr. Scott. I do not pretend to vouch for <lb/>
that, but I am so credibly informed. I rather <lb/>
think that that cannot be true, however, because <lb/>
when the Bill reached this House with these <lb/>
amendments, and concurrence in them was called <lb/>
for, my hon. friend from Bothwell (Mr. Mills) <lb/>
seemed to be surprised at the introduction of <lb/>
this articular clause, and expressed his regret at <lb/>
    it. have extracted from <hi rendition="simple:italic">Hansard</hi> what said <lb/>
on that subject, and I can hardly imagine that his <lb/>

<pb n="39" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00039.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">39</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">40</fw> 

surprise was feigned, or that his astonishment was <lb/>
not expressed in perfect good faith. Speaking of <lb/>
the amendment, the hon. member for Bothwell is <lb/>
reported to have said: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"One of them, he stated, provided for the publication <lb/>
of the proceedings of the North-West Council in English <lb/>
and French, and for the use of both languages in the <lb/>
courts. They had thought that this was a matter which <lb/>
had better be left to the Council in question. He regret<lb break="no"/>ted that the amendment had been made, but it would be <lb/>
impossible to get the measure through at this late period <lb/>
in the Session, unless the amendments were accepted. <lb/>
The action taken by the Senate would add very consider<lb break="no"/>ably to the expense. Almost every one in that art of <lb/>
the country spoke Cree, though some spoke, in addition, <lb/>
English or French, and, if the proceedings were to <lb/>
published in the most prevalent language, Cree should be <lb/>
chosen for the purpose." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>With these observations the amendments were <lb/>
concurred in without any objections being made, <lb/>
so far as I have been able to see, by any hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber on the floor of this House; and I was either <lb/>
present or ought to have been present, and I there<lb break="no"/>fore share in the blame attachable to the proceed<lb break="no"/>ings on that occasion. Then, I think it was in the <lb/>
year 1880, this North-West Territories Act was <lb/>
again dealt with, and again we find this clause, <lb/>
which I venture to call an objectionable clause; <lb/>
and I believe that on that occasion also it was <lb/>
passed through both Houses of Parliament without <lb/>
objection being made by any hon. member on either <lb/>
side of the House. And finally last Session, in <lb/>
the proposition submitted to us by the Government <lb/>
in the Bill then brought down, the same clause is <lb/>
to be found; and although the Bill did not advance <lb/>
very far, so far as it did go, no objection appears <lb/>
to have been made to the clause. Now, Sir, all <lb/>
this may appear, perhaps, to form some good <lb/>
reason against the proposition I have now the <lb/>
honor to make. I venture to think, however, that <lb/>
that is not so. The enactment in question is as <lb/>
follows:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Either the English or the French language maybe <lb/>
used by any person in the debates of the said Council, and <lb/>
in the proceedings before the courts, and both those lan<lb break="no"/>guages shall be used in the records and journals of the <lb/>
said Council, and the ordinances of the said Council shall <lb/>
be printed in both those languages." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>Now, I venture to say that if a constitution were <lb/>
framed for a new country, it would never occur to <lb/>
any person to do so foolish a thing as to stipulate <lb/>
for two official languages. I venture to think that, <lb/>
with the knowledge which there is on the subject <lb/>
at this time, it never would occur to any person <lb/>
that it was a proper thing to create or perpetuate, <lb/>
as the case might be, two official languages; and <lb/>
yet practically that was what was done in that <lb/>
North-West Act. What is the explanation, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, of this extraordinary piece of legislation, <lb/>
which appears to have been assented to by the <lb/>
House on three or four different occasions without <lb/>
objection on the part of any one? It is not to be <lb/>
found in the Treaty of Cession, although a very <lb/>
large number of persons seem to be under the <lb/>
impression that by the treaty negotiated at the <lb/>
time this country was ceded to the British Crown, <lb/>
the right of the nguage was guaranteed to the <lb/>
French. As I say—and the fact cannot be too <lb/>
widely known or too often repeated—that is not <lb/>
so. The mistake is one which very generally pre<lb break="no"/>vails; and on looking at articles on this subject— <lb/>
articles by very learned men—I have been sur<lb break="no"/>prised that this statement has been very generally <lb/>
made and very generally accepted. But there is <lb/>

<cb/>

not a word to be found in the treaty or in the <lb/>
Articles of Cession anywhere by which the <lb/>
language was guaranteed to the conquered French. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. Not conquered—ceded. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. Ceded, my hon. friend says, <lb/>
although I venture to think the other expression <lb/>
is the more correct. But there is not a word to be <lb/>
found either at the time of the cession or conquest, <lb/>
or whatever it may be called, which gives any <lb/>
ground for the statement that the language was <lb/>
guaranteed to the French inhabitants of this coun<lb break="no"/>try. Nor is it to be found in the Act known as <lb/>
the Quebec Act. That Act went a good deal <lb/>
further than the treaty, as we all know. The treaty <lb/>
guaranteed to the French people their religion, and <lb/>
that so far as the laws of Great Britain permitted; <lb/>
but the Quebec Act went much further. It re<lb break="no"/>stored to them their laws—the civil laws to which <lb/>
they had been accustomed; and it restored to their <lb/>
church certain rights and privileges which are enjoy<lb break="no"/>ed to this day; but it dealt not with this question <lb/>
of language. Well, the next stage would be per<lb break="no"/>haps in 1791, when the Province of Lower Canada <lb/>
was constituted; and at the time of the constitu<lb break="no"/>tion of that Province the language was not dealt <lb/>
with either; though very shortly afterwards, it is <lb/>
perfectly true as an historical fact, the French <lb/>
members of the Assembly then constituted did <lb/>
claim the right, and enforced the right, to use their <lb/>
language; and I believe the proceedings were car<lb break="no"/>ried on in both languages in that Assembly—how<lb break="no"/>ever, not by any statute law, or by anything more <lb/>
than a resolution of the Assembly, which had a <lb/>
perfect right to so resolve and so act. Well, we <lb/>
come down to the time of the Rebellion and the <lb/>
Real Union of the Provinces in 1840 by the Act of <lb/>
that date; and there, so far from the lang<lb break="no"/>uage being allowed to the French, as we all <lb/>
know, consequent on the report of Lord Durham, <lb/>
who was sent out here to investigate the causes of <lb/>
the Rebellion—a report which was recognised on <lb/>
all hands as a most statesmanlike document—that <lb/>
in Lower Canada, at any rate, it was more a <lb/>
trouble of race than that of alleged misgovern<lb break="no"/>ment, a clause was introduced into the Union Act <lb/>
of 1841 by which the use of the French languagewas <lb/>
absolutely prohibited instead of being permitted. <lb/>
So that the first piece of legislation we have on the <lb/>
subject is a clause prohibiting the use of the <lb/>
French language. That was followed in the Par<lb break="no"/>liament of the United Provinces by an Address <lb/>
to the Crown, passed unanimously, I think, in <lb/>
1844, asking for the repeal of that clause, and ac<lb break="no"/>cordingly, in 1848, that clause in the Union Act <lb/>
was repealed. Now, Sir, I come down to 1867, to <lb/>
the time of the British North America. Act, and <lb/>
there we find that the dual languages are for the <lb/>
first time permitted by legislative enactment; but <lb/>
the permission is restricted to this Parliament and <lb/>
to the Assembly and Legislative Council of the <lb/>
Province of Quebec. It is not at all intended by <lb/>
that Act, from anything to be gathered from it, <lb/>
that the use of the dual languages is to be per<lb break="no"/>mitted in any of the other Provinces, much less in  <lb/>
any Province which did not even then belong to <lb/>
Canada, and which were acquired afterward; when <lb/>
the Hudson Bay Company sold us their, territory <lb/>
of Rupert's Land, by which that great country <lb/>
passed under the Dominion of Canada. There<lb break="no"/>fore, there was no legislative warrant for the use <lb/>

<pb n="41" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00041.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">41</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANULRY 22, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">42</fw>
    
of the French language in that territory in any <lb/>
sense, and it is based and founded, if founded <lb/>
at all, simply on the will of Parliament, <lb/>
and it ought, therefore, to be based on <lb/>
some good and sufficient reason. Now, is it, <lb/>
or is it not, a matter of importance that the <lb/>
dual language or the additional French language <lb/>
should be permitted—I will not say permitted <lb/>
—should be encouraged and fostered throughout <lb/>
the Dominion of Canada? If it is a matter of <lb/>
no importance—and so, perhaps, it was consi<lb break="no"/>dered at the time—of course the motion I am <lb/>
making to Parliament, the Bill I have had the <lb/>
honor to ask leave to introduce, is an unnecessary <lb/>
measure, and will no doubt be so received and <lb/>
dealt with by this House. But in my judgment it <lb/>
is by no means an unimportant matter. On the <lb/>
contrary, I think, and I assert here in my place in <lb/>
Parliament, that there is no more important mat<lb break="no"/>ter in the formation of the character of a people <lb/>
than the language that they speak, and, after all <lb/>
said and done, I think it will be found that nations <lb/>
and races are distinguished and are distinctive <lb/>
more by reason of the language they speak than by <lb/>
the blood which is common to or supposed to be <lb/>
common to them all. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Switzerland. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. I think it would be found <lb/>
upon an investigation of the subject, and I will <lb/>
appeal to the very closest investigation upon the <lb/>
subject, that this is the well-known and accepted <lb/>
truth. My hon. friend from Bothwell (Mr. Mills) <lb/>
refers to Switzerland or to the Swiss. When the <lb/>
proper time comes for the discussion of this Bill, <lb/>
that will certainly be a proper illustration to be dealt <lb/>
with; but I think my hon. friend would not, even <lb/>
if his view were correct, adopt the rule from the <lb/>
exception. Everyone knows that the use of sev<lb break="no"/>eral languages in Switzerland is an exception to <lb/>
the general rule, and should not be adopted as the <lb/>
general rule. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DESJ3">Mr. DESJARDINS</persName>. Well, well. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. My hon. friends laugh, and <lb/>
I hope, when the proper time comes, they will <lb/>
justify their laughter by something more than <lb/>
sneers. Before I sit down I will fortify my state<lb break="no"/>ment by an authority whose opinions I believe will <lb/>
be accepted, and certainly cannot be gainsaid. If, <lb/>
then, as I assert, it is an important matter in the <lb/>
great question of national life, I would ask my <lb/>
hon. friends in this House what we are assembled <lb/>
here for if not for the purpose of promoting <lb/>
national unity and building up a great country in <lb/>
the enormous territory we have under our control? <lb/>
Is not that the grandest and greatest object that <lb/>
has been entrusted to us as the representatives <lb/>
of a people; and towards that great object are we <lb/>
dealing truly if we are sowin the seeds of dissen<lb break="no"/>sions and of future trouble by legislation of this <lb/>
kind. <lb/></p> 

<p>Some hon. MEMBERS. Hear, hear. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. My hon. friends perhaps will <lb/>
allow me to proceed quietly because there will be <lb/>
a full opportunity of debating this subject, and <lb/>
then I hope there will be a fair hearing given to <lb/>
all opinions in this House. I have a right to my <lb/>
opinion and I intend to maintain it, notwithstand<lb break="no"/>ing what my hon. friends may say. In my opinion <lb/>

<cb/>

it is of the greatest importance to endeavor to <lb/>
make this great country united in fact as we are en<lb break="no"/>deavoring to unite it in substance. We are spend<lb break="no"/>ing our means, we have spent enormous sums of <lb/>
money, we have united the Atlantic to the Pacific <lb/>
we have spent enormous sums, I say, on the Inter<lb break="no"/>colonial Railway to unite the Maritime Provinces <lb/>
with the heart of the Dominion, but what profits it <lb/>
if, at the same time, we are passing measures and <lb/>
promoting legislation which separates and divides <lb/>
the people into two separate races, or which is per<lb break="no"/>petuating that division; which is not only permit<lb break="no"/>ting it in the Province of Quebec, but in the new <lb/>
territories belonging to the Dominion. As a matter of <lb/>
dollars and cents, as a matter of mere money, the <lb/>
acquisition of the North-West, looked upon as a spec<lb break="no"/>ulation, has been a loss, and, except for the purpose <lb/>
of building up a great nation, which we are willing <lb/>
to do, there can be no justification for the ex<lb break="no"/>penditure, not only in the acquisition of that great <lb/>
country, but in the building of those great railways <lb/>
at enormous expenditure, bringing into the market, <lb/>
to compete with our farmers, vast quantities of <lb/>
land, which must diminish the value of the land of <lb/>
the farmers in the older Provinces, while they are <lb/>
actually spending their money in the acquisition <lb/>
of the land which accomplishes this result. The <lb/>
only object we have had in all this has been to <lb/>
create on the northern part of this continent a <lb/>
great nationality, to build up a great country, one <lb/>
that our descendants would be proud to occupy <lb/>
and proud to belong to; and that is the only <lb/>
justification of the procedure which has been <lb/>
adopted from first to last since the passing of the <lb/>
Confederation Act. As I stated before, I will read <lb/>
from a document which I do not think hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen will say does not convey a fair statement <lb/>
of this question of language. I will read from an <lb/>
article written by Professor Freeman, in which he <lb/>
deals with this question in the following words:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"And now, having ruled that races and nations,though <lb/>
largely formed by the working of an artificial law, are <lb/>
still real and living things, groups in which the idea of <lb/>
kindred is the idea around which everything has grown, <lb/>
how are we to define cur races and our nations? How <lb/>
are we to mark them off one from the other? Bearing <lb/>
in mind the cautions and qualifications which have been <lb/>
already given, bearing in mind large classes of excep<lb break="no"/>tions which will presently be spoken of, I say unhesitat<lb break="no"/>ingly that for practical purposes there is one test, and one <lb/>
only, and that test is language. We may at least apply <lb/>
the test negatively. It might be unsafe to rule that all <lb/>
speakers of the same language have a common nation<lb break="no"/>ality, but we may safely say that, where there is not <lb/>
community of language, there is no common nationality <lb/>
in the big est sense. As in the teeth of community of <lb/>
language there may be what for all political purposes are <lb/>
separate nations, so without community of language <lb/>
there may be an artificial nationality, a nationality <lb/>
which may be good for all political purposes, and which <lb/>
may engender a common national feeling, still, this is <lb/>
not quite the same thing as that fuller national unity <lb/>
whic is felt where there is community of language. In <lb/>
fact, mankind instinctively takes language as the badge <lb/>
of nationality. We so far take it as the badge that we <lb/>
instinctively assume community of language as a nation <lb/>
as the rule, and we set down anything t at departs from <lb/>
that rule as an exception. The first idea suggested by <lb/>
the word Frenchman, or German, or any other national <lb/>
name, is that he is a man who speaks French pr German <lb/>
as his mother tongue. We take for granted, in the ab<lb break="no"/>sence of anything to make us think otherwise, that a <lb/>
Frenchman is a Speaker of French, and that a Speaker of <lb/>
French is a Frenchman." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>I think that will not be denied as a correct <lb/>
doctrine, but I will further trouble the House with <lb/>
a'reference from a man very distinguished in this <lb/>
branch of science, Professor Muller, who, in his <lb/>

<pb n="43" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00043.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">43</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">44</fw> 

lectures delivered before at the Oxford University <lb/>
Extension meeting, says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"It is said that blood is thicker than water, but it may <lb/>
be said with even greater truth that language is thicker <lb/>
than blood. If, in the interior of Africa, surrounded by <lb/>
black men, whose utterances are utterly unintelligible, <lb/>
we suddenly met with a man who could speak English, <lb/>
we should care very little whether he was English, or <lb/>
Irish, or American. We should understand him and be <lb/>
able to exchange our thoughts with him. That brings <lb/>
us together far more closely than if we met a Welshman <lb/>
speaking nothing but Welsh, or a Scotchman speaking <lb/>
nothing but Gaelic; or for all that, an Englishman who, <lb/>
having been brought up in China, could speak nothing <lb/>
Chinese. A common language is a common bond of in<lb break="no"/>tellectual brotherhood, far stronger than any supposed <lb/>
or real community of blood. Common blood without a <lb/>
common language leaves us as perfect strangers. <lb/>
common language, even without common blood, makes <lb/>
the whole world feel akin." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>Again, speaking of the other question, the question <lb/>
of race, a subject of very great interest, a subject <lb/>
which has been pursued by scientific men up to a <lb/>
recent period, this seems to be the result. The Pro<lb break="no"/>fessor quotes in his lecture from the Director of <lb/>
the American Bureau of Ethnology, who says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"There is a science of anthropology composed of sub<lb break="no"/>sidiary sciences. There is a science of sociology, which <lb/>
includes all the institutions of mankind. There is a sci<lb break="no"/>ence of philology, which includes the languages of man<lb break="no"/>kind. And there is a science, philosophy, which includes <lb/>
the opinions of mankind. But there is no science of <lb/>
ethnology, for the attempt to classify mankind in groups <lb/>
has failed on every hand." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>There is no such thing as a Celtic skull any <lb/>
more than a Saxon skull; no such thing as Celtic <lb/>
hair any more than Saxon hair. It is only by <lb/>
language and by the community of language, that <lb/>
men are formed into nations. Finally, speaking of <lb/>
the whole subject of the science of language, the <lb/>
professor says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"These may seem but idle dreams, of little interest to <lb/>
the practical politician. All I can say is that I wish that <lb/>
it were so. But my memory reaches back far enough to <lb/>
make me see the real and lasting mischief for which I <lb/>
feel the science of language has been responsible for the <lb/>
last fifty years. The ideas of race and nationality found<lb break="no"/>ed on language have taken such complete possession of <lb/>
the fancy, both of the young and the old, that all other <lb/>
arguments seem of no avail. Why was Italy united? <lb/>
Because the Italian language embodied Italian nation<lb break="no"/>ality. Why was Germany united? Because of Arndt's <lb/>
song, 'What is the German's Fatherland?' and the answer <lb/>
given, 'As far as sounds the German tongue.' Why is <lb/>
Russia so powerful a centre of attraction for the Slavonic <lb/>
inhabitants of Turkey and Germany? Because the Rus<lb break="no"/>sian language, even though it is hardly understood by <lb/>
Servians, Croatians and the Bulgarians, is known to <lb/>
most closely allied. Even from the mere cinders of <lb/>
ancient dialects, such as Welsh, Gaelic and Erse, eloquent <lb/>
agitators know how to fan a new, sometimes a dangerous, <lb/>
fire. <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>I would just add to that an extract from the re<lb break="no"/>port of Lord Durham who dealt with the matter, <lb/>
not solely from a scientific, but from a prac<lb break="no"/>tical point of view. When he was sent here, <lb/>
as we all know, he was a Liberal of the Lib<lb break="no"/>erals, and he was sent here by Lord Melbourne's <lb/>
Government for the purpose of investigating <lb/>
the difficulties and ascertaining what caused the <lb/>
rebellion in both Upper and Lower Canada. I have <lb/>
nothing to do at the moment with his report with <lb/>
regard to the Upper Province, but in his report on <lb/>
the Lower Province, he found the rebellion to be <lb/>
caused mainly, if not altogether, by race difficul<lb break="no"/>ties. Whatever else there was, whatever other pre<lb break="no"/>judices there were, whatever other causes there <lb/>
might be, the trouble, when probed to the bottom, <lb/>
was found to be caused by race difficulties. Now, <lb/>
it may be said that has nothing to do with language, <lb/>

<cb/>

but when hon. gentlemen take the trouble to pursue <lb/>
the subject further they will find that when speak<lb break="no"/>ing of race, they mean a community speaking the <lb/>
same language. When you talk of a race you will <lb/>
find, when you investigate the subject, that the <lb/>
race is made up, not of men of one blood, <lb/>
but of men who have been adopted into the <lb/>
race, and there are instances of that in the <lb/>
Province of Quebec. I would like to know whether <lb/>
the Highland soldiers Who were disbanded after the <lb/>
cession have not been received and adopted by <lb/>
the French Canadians, and are not now considered as <lb/>
much French Canadians as those who came from <lb/>
France a hundred years before that time? That <lb/>
process is going on constantly. Can you distin<lb break="no"/>guish an Englishman who came over at the time of <lb/>
the Conquest from an Englishman of three or four <lb/>
centuries earlier? Or, to come back to more recent <lb/>
times, is the Frenchman who came over to England <lb/>
during the time of the troubles, and owing to the <lb/>
troubles in France, and after a generation or two <lb/>
changed his name to an English name; is he to be <lb/>
distinguished from those who have descended from <lb/>
a long line of English ancestry? It is plain, that <lb/>
what makes the nation is language; and, there<lb break="no"/>fore, when one speaks of race, as these distin<lb break="no"/>guished writers have done, they meant a com<lb break="no"/>munity speaking the same language. But at the <lb/>
moment I am not dealing so much with that <lb/>
question, which I will come to by-and-bye, as with <lb/>
the particular matter of the difficulties in the <lb/>
Lower Province, and I will quote again from Lord <lb/>
Durham's report about this difference of language: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The difference of language in this respect produces <lb/>
effects quite apart from those which it has on the mere in<lb break="no"/>tercourse of the two races. Those who have reflected on the <lb/>
powerful influence of language on thought, will perceive <lb/>
in how different a manner peeple who speak in different <lb/>
languages are apt to think; and those who are familiar <lb/>
with the literature of France, know that the same opinion <lb/>
will be expressed by an English and French writer of the <lb/>
present day, not merely in different words, but in style so <lb/>
different as to make utterly different habits of thought. <lb/>
This difference is very striking in Lower Canada; it exists, <lb/>
not merely in the books of most influence and repute, <lb/>
which are, of course, those of the great writers of France <lb/>
and England, and by which the minds of the respective <lb/>
races are formed, but it is observable in the writings <lb/>
which new issue from the Colonial press. The articles in <lb/>
the newspapers of each race are written in style as widely <lb/>
different as those of France and England at present, and <lb/>
the arguments which convince the one are calculated to <lb/>
appear utterly unintelligible to the other. The difference <lb/>
of language produces misconceptions yet more fatal even <lb/>
than those which it occasions with respect to opinions; it <lb/>
aggravates the national animosities, by representing all <lb/>
the events of the day in utterly different light." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>Now, I venture to think, I have, at all events to <lb/>
some extent, made good the proposition which I am <lb/>
dealing with, that is, that language is of great im<lb break="no"/>portance, that it is of vital consequence to a nation <lb/>
that the language spoken by its people should be <lb/>
common to them all, that they should not, at all <lb/>
events, he encouraged and trained in speaking <lb/>
different languages. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Alsace and Lorraine seem <lb/>
to be exceptions to the rule. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I am glad to see that my <lb/>
hon. friend, at one time Minister of the Interior, has <lb/>
changed his views. He regretted the introduction <lb/>
of the French language in the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories at the time he consented to that amendment, <lb/>
and I give him credit for good faith in that regret. <lb/>
Certainly circumstances since have not altered in <lb/>
favor of the policy which my hon. friend seems now <lb/>

<pb n="45" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00045.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">45</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 22, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">46</fw>

to have adopted. But I am glad to see that he <lb/>
stands firmly by the Bill which he fathered. At <lb/>
all events, on his part there can be no going back, <lb/>
and he is not accustomed to change any opinion he <lb/>
has once entertained. Now, I say, what has been <lb/>
the result in this country? Let hon. gentlemen <lb/>
remember that when this country was ceded to the <lb/>
British Crown there was not more than 60,000 or <lb/>
65,000 French Canadians—I think that number in<lb break="no"/>cludes, though I am not quite certain, those who <lb/>
dwelt on the banks of the Illinois, and who did not <lb/>
form a part of what is now the Dominion of Canada. <lb/>
However that may be, instead of encouraging them in <lb/>
the use of their language, had a policy been pursued <lb/>
of inducing them—not by any harsh means at all, <lb/>
not by any aggravating measures—to speak the <lb/>
English tongue, I want to know whether to-day, <lb/>
instead of the difference, the cleavage of race, <lb/>
which we see going on, and which is <lb/>
becoming more and more pronounced, and <lb/>
which is calculated to rend this Dominion in twain, <lb/>
if some stop is not put to it—I would like to know <lb/>
whether we would see the spectacle that we see <lb/>
today? I think it is perfectly plain that we <lb/>
would not see it. I think no injustice would have <lb/>
been done, and that in one generation, or in two <lb/>
at most, my hon. friends that now represent the <lb/>
Province of Quebec, or their ancestors, would have <lb/>
been speaking English, and would have been <lb/>
English in fact, English in sentiment, just as much <lb/>
as those who have gone to the other side of the line, <lb/>
no matter what country they come from, whether <lb/>
from Austria, from Italy, from Germany, or any <lb/>
other country in Europe, have now become assimi<lb break="no"/>lated and form part of the American people, not <lb/>
merely in name but in truth and in fact. Well, <lb/>
it is said that this is a matter of no consequence. <lb/>
Now, I venture to state that Lord Durham did find <lb/>
it to be a matter of consequence, and as I am <lb/>
desirous of convincing my hon. friends, if I <lb/>
possibly can, I want to give authority for what I <lb/>
say. I see there is a good deal of feeling on the <lb/>
subject, more than I should have expected, but I <lb/>
assume that my hon. friends are open to reason, <lb/>
and willing to listen to argument. Now, Lord <lb/>
Durham says in his report again: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"I expected to find a contest between a government <lb/>
and a people; I found two nations warring in the bosom <lb/>
of a single state; I found a struggle, not of principle, but <lb/>
of race: and I perceived that it would be idle to attempt <lb/>
any amelioration of laws or institutions, until we could <lb/>
first succeed in terminating the deadly animosity that now <lb/>
separates the inhabitants of Lower Canada into the hos<lb break="no"/>tile divisions of French and English." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>Further down: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"We are ready to believe that the real motive of the <lb/>
quarrel is something else, and that the difference of <lb/>
race has slightly and occasionally aggravated dissensions, <lb/>
which we attribute to some more usual cause. Experi<lb break="no"/>ence of a state of society, so unhappily divided as that of <lb/>
Lower Canada, leads to an exactly contrary opinion. <lb/>
The national feud forces itself on the very sense, irresisti<lb break="no"/>bly and palpably, as the origin or the essence of every <lb/>
dispute which divides the community; we discover that <lb/>
dissensions, which appear to have another origin, are but <lb/>
forms of this constant and all-pervading quarrel, and <lb/>
every contest is one of French and English in the outset, <lb/>
or becomes so ere it has run its course." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>Now, I think that, as regards that time, at all <lb/>
events, Lord Durham's statement may be taken as <lb/>
good evidence—and no one would question his <lb/>
perfect impartiality—of what he saw on the spot <lb/>
ere and reported to his Government. I hear the <lb/>
First Minister remark that Lord Durham did not <lb/>
write the report himself. That may be perfectly <lb/>

<cb/>

true; but a man as competent as Lord Durham <lb/>
was here—Mr. Buller—who is credited with hav<lb break="no"/>ing written the report, and so, whether it is called <lb/>
Lord Durham's or Mr. Buller's report, does not <lb/>
alter the fact, if fact it was, that such was the re<lb break="no"/>sult of their investigation on the spot. But is it <lb/>
true or not that these things have changed, is all <lb/>
this matter of language a matter of no moment, <lb/>
a matter which does not call for investigation in <lb/>
this House or inquiry by the representatives of the <lb/>
people? Why, we have had statements made by <lb/>
the Premier of the Province of Quebec, who leads <lb/>
a great majority of his fellow countrymen in that <lb/>
Province, and there is no use denying, and I say it <lb/>
in the presence of the right hon. gentleman and the <lb/>
Government that I have hitherto followed, that <lb/>
there can be no question whatever that Mr. Mer<lb break="no"/>cier is to-day the true representative of the French <lb/>
Canadians of the Province of Quebec. Has he <lb/>
given any uncertain sound upon this question of <lb/>
Nationalism? What means it when he forms a <lb/>
party and calls it the National party? We have <lb/>
our National Policy. That was not a policy con<lb break="no"/>fined to one Province or one part of the Dominion, <lb/>
but a policy intended to apply and embrace the <lb/>
whole Dominion. We know, however, that the <lb/>
Nationalist party in the Province of Quebec is in<lb break="no"/>tended to embrace and consolidate one of the <lb/>
races, divided by the language— <lb/></p> 

<p>Some <persName ref="pers:ANON1">hon. MEMBERS</persName>. No, no. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>—and that it has successfully <lb/>
done so. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. No such thing. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I cannot accept the hon. <lb/>
gentleman's disclaimer. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LANGELIER</persName> (Quebec). We cannot accept <lb/>
your assertion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I may be asked what evidence <lb/>
I produce. I ask what is the meaning of the word <lb/>
"Nationalist?" <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:AMYO1">Mr. AMYOT</persName>. I will tell you later on. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I shall be glad to have an <lb/>
explanation, but I must accept the definition of <lb/>
the word as I find it. Nationalism means French <lb/>
nationality in that sense. What did Mr. Mercier <lb/>
say, speaking in the presence of the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man leading the Opposition in this House, if I am <lb/>
not misformed—at all events, the hon. gentleman <lb/>
spoke very shortly after him. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. I spoke for myself. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I said Mr. Mercier spoke in <lb/>
your presence. I am only stating what Mr. <lb/>
Mercier said. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. You do not expect me to ac<lb break="no"/>cept your statement. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I am going to do justice to <lb/>
the hon. gentleman, and say that he disclaimed it. <lb/>
Now, what did Mr. Mercier say? <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"To-day the reuse and the blue should give place to <lb/>
the tri-color. They must be united if they wish to make <lb/>
their nationality powerful." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>Mark the words—"their nationality." Perhaps <lb/>
these words do not mean what they appear to say: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"It was a triumph for the National cause." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>It does not need an explanation from the hon. <lb/>
gentleman, who, I believe, is a warm supporter <lb/>
of Mr. Mercier in provincial affairs. <lb/></p>

<pb n="47" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00047.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">47</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">48</fw> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"For the sake of their nationality, for the sake of <lb/>
their religion, they must be united." <lb/></p>
    <p>
Who must be united? <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The strength of the French Canadian people lay in <lb/>
the union of the people with the clergy. By coupling <lb/>
the name with Jesuit hero, Breboeuf, with the immortal <lb/>
Jacques Cartier they said to their insulters, it is useless <lb/>
to imagine that we will ever cease to be French and <lb/>
Catholic. This monument declares that after a century <lb/>
of separation from our ancient mother we are still <lb/>
French; more than that, we will remain French and <lb/>
Catholic." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>Is there any doubt about these words? What <lb/>
is meant by "National?" These words were said <lb/>
in the presence of the hon. gentleman who <lb/>
leads the Opposition in this House, as he does not <lb/>
deny, and he allowed them to pass without rebuke. <lb/>
I quite admit that when the hon. gentleman spoke <lb/>
he made no such declaration of policy in his own <lb/>
behalf, and when he delivered himself afterwards in <lb/>
Toronto—perhaps it would have been better if he <lb/>
had said it in Quebec—he stated that he for one was <lb/>
not in favor of French nationality. There is no <lb/>
doubt, at all events, as to what was meant by the <lb/>
hon. gentleman who leads the Local Government <lb/>
in the statement which called forth in Toronto a <lb/>
disclaimer from the leader of the Opposition in <lb/>
this House. But the hon. gentleman will remember <lb/>
that when he went back to his Province he was not <lb/>
warmly greeted for this frank and rather liberal <lb/>
declaration which he made in the Pavilion at <lb/>
Toronto. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. Do not pander to party pre<lb break="no"/>judice. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. When the hon. gentleman re<lb break="no"/>turned he threw himself into an election then <lb/>
pending, and the result (I should like the hon. <lb/>
gentleman to explain, if the result was due to any <lb/>
other cause,) was that the majority of the candi<lb break="no"/>date for the seat of the late Capt. Labelle was <lb/>
very much increased, the position not being appre<lb break="no"/>ciably changed except by this declaration, which <lb/>
was not received with favor by the press of Quebec, <lb/>
or a portion of the press of that Province. Is it not <lb/>
perfectly true also, that a large section of that <lb/>
press, more or less influential, having, I believe, an <lb/>
influence quite as great perhaps as any newspapers <lb/>
are supposed to possess, spoke out on this subject <lb/>
with no uncertain sound. Let me read to the <lb/>
    House, what is perfectly well known to the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Province of Quebec, what <hi rendition="simple:italic">La Vérité</hi> <lb/>
said on more than one occasion. We gather <lb/>
the signs of the times from newspaper articles and <lb/>
from the declarations of public men. I may per<lb break="no"/>haps be belittling Mr. Mercier by reading news<lb break="no"/>paper extracts in attempting to bolster up that <lb/>
hon. gentleman, but that newspaper makes such a <lb/>
declaration that I cannot pass it without remark. <lb/>
That journal says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"But such was not is not, never will be, the desire of <lb/>
French Canadians. For us, Confederation was and is the <lb/>
means to an end. It is a means of enabling us to dwell <lb/>
in peace with our English neighbors, whilst safe guard<lb break="no"/>ing our rights, developing our resources, strengthening <lb/>
us, and making us ready for our national future. Let us <lb/>
say it boldly—the ideal of the French Canadian people is <lb/>
not the ideal of the other races which to-day inhabit the <lb/>
land our fathers subdued for Christian civilisation. Our <lb/>
ideal is the formation here, in this corner of the earth, <lb/>
watered by the blood of our heroes, of a nation which <lb/>
shall perform on this continent the part France has <lb/>
played so long in Europe. Our aspiration is to found a <lb/>
nation which, socially, shall profess the Catholic faith <lb/>
and speak the French language. That is not, and cannot <lb/>
be, the aspiration of the other races. To say, then, that <lb/>
all the groups which constitute the Confederation are <lb/>

<cb/>

animated by one and the same aspiration, is to utter a <lb/>
sounding phrase without political or historical meaning. <lb/>
For us the present form of government is not and cannot <lb/>
be, the last word of our national existence. It is merely <lb/>
a road towards the goal which we have in view, that is <lb/>
all. Let us never lose sight of our own national destiny. <lb/>
Rather let us constantly pre are ourselves to fulfil it <lb/>
worthily at the hour decreed by Providence, which cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances shall reveal to us. Our whole history proves <lb/>
that it is not to be a vain dream, a mere Utopia, but the <lb/>
end which the God of nations has marked out for us. We <lb/>
have not been snatched from death a score of times; we <lb/>
have not multiplied with a rapidity truly prodigious; we <lb/>
have not wrought harvests of resistance and of peaceful <lb/>
conquest in the eastern townships and in the border <lb/>
counties of Ontario; we have not absorbed many of the <lb/>
English and Scotch settlements planted among us in <lb/>
order to break up our homogenity; we have not put forth <lb/>
all these efforts, and seen them crowned with success, to <lb/>
go and perish miserably in any all-Canadian arrange<lb break="no"/>ment." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    <p>I could multiply quotations of this kind; but per<lb break="no"/>haps <hi rendition="simple:italic">La Presse</hi> is a paper which may be said to <lb/>
speak with more authority, and I may give a <lb/>
quotation from it. I find, however, that I have not <lb/>
a quotation from that paper here. My hon. friend <lb/>
will perhaps remember it sneeringly alluded to the <lb/>
fact that the people were astonished at his observ<lb break="no"/>ation, they could not accept it, they could not <lb/>
credit it, and instead of cheering it they merely <lb/>
said "hear, hear," being induced to do so by aston<lb break="no"/>ishment, but such was not the views or the policy <lb/>
of the French Canadian people. Now I have en<lb break="no"/>deavored to show to the House so far, that this is not <lb/>
merely a sentimental matter but that it is a matter <lb/>
of practical politics and a matter which must be dealt <lb/>
with. I have endeavored to show that as early as <lb/>
the years 1837—38 it was then recognised as being <lb/>
the great cause of trouble in the Province of Que<lb break="no"/>bec. I think I have also successfully shown (I <lb/>
do not think, in fact, I needed to have shown it, <lb/>
because it is familiar to us all) that these difficulties <lb/>
exist at present, and that now that the French <lb/>
race, or those who speak the French language, <lb/>
to be more accurate, have attained to a consider<lb break="no"/>able numerical strength, their ambition is rising <lb/>
in proportion, and the difficulties which ought to <lb/>
have been foreseen long ago are now upon us and <lb/>
must be dealt with, at all events, as far as our <lb/>
new Territories are concerned, and that we must <lb/>
not allow the same difficulties to arise in that part <lb/>
of the Dominion. But if I have given the views of <lb/>
those within the Dominion, let me draw attention <lb/>
also to the views which are also entertained on <lb/>
this question outside of the Dominion by impartial <lb/>
spectators. I am not going to read from any <lb/>
journals that are hostile to the French Canadians, <lb/>
because I know that my quoting them as authority <lb/>
would produce no effect upon those whom I am <lb/>
very anxious indeed should very seriously consider <lb/>
this question. There ought to be no such differences <lb/>
between the English and French Canadian mem<lb break="no"/>bers of this House. There ought to be no differences <lb/>
on the subject between those who come from the <lb/>
Province of Quebec and speak in the French <lb/>
language, their mother tongue, and those who <lb/>
come from the other Provinces of the Dominion, <lb/>
and who speak the English language. If, in truth <lb/>
and fact it is in the interests of this Dominion, <lb/>
that there should be one race, one nationality and <lb/>
one national life, it is the duty of all of us to strive <lb/>
to bring about that result. I am now about to quote <lb/>
from a paper, from a Catholic journal, which was <lb/>
introduced to this House last Session by my hon. <lb/>
friend the Minister of Justice. I confess I did not <lb/>
hear of it before, but no doubt it has now become <lb/>

<pb n="49" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00049.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">49</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 22, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">50</fw>

historical. It is called The Month. Dealing <lb/>
with this difficulty with the French language in <lb/>
Canada in the year 1885, the writer speaks as <lb/>
follows:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"While freely admitting that the French Canadian is <lb/>
behind his English-speaking neighbor not only in farm<lb break="no"/>ing, but in commerce, trade and all kindred branches, <lb/>
we must not take for granted everything that this same <lb/>
English-speaking neighbor says of him. One of the <lb/>
most striking and curious things in the social life of <lb/>
Lower Canada is the latent hate which the French and <lb/>
English-speaking races have for each other. It is a sad <lb/>
thing to say, but truth requires that it should be said, <lb/>
that English-speaking people, no matter whether they <lb/>
are English Irish or Scotch, have rarely a good word for <lb/>
their French neighbors; and it is still sadder and more <lb/>
unaccountable that of all those English-speaking people, <lb/>
the Irish are those between whom and the French there <lb/>
    seems to be the least <hi rendition="simple:italic">rapport</hi> and the greatest enmity. <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>An <persName ref="pers:ANON1">hon. MEMBER</persName>. Do you believe that? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. This journal was accepted <lb/>
as a good authority last Session. I am reading <lb/>
from the same authority as my hon. friend the <lb/>
Minister of Justice quoted last Session. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. That was twelve <lb/>
months ago. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. The article goes on to say: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"If the French Canadians were not Catholics, if they <lb/>
were not the people of all others whom the Irish are sup<lb break="no"/>posed to love, one might not be so puzzled over this <lb/>
social enigma." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>It goes on to give reasons or to account in some <lb/>
way for this cause of the hatred being greater be<lb break="no"/>tween the Irish and the French, than between the <lb/>
French and any other nationality, and says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The preservation of the French language in Canada <lb/>
seems to be the most absorbing subiect at present, not <lb/>
only in that country, but in France, and public opinion <lb/>
in both countries seems somewhat divided about it. All <lb/>
Frenchmen, and most Canadians of French extraction, <lb/>
are as one as to the absolute necessity of preserving <lb/>
their language in America; but how is it to be done? <lb/>
The best way would, of course be to annex Canada to <lb/>
France; but that is not to be thought of. One thing is <lb/>
certain, and that is that in spite of the wonderful <lb/>
tenacity with which the French have stuck to their <lb/>
language in Canada, there are signs that it is losing <lb/>
ground." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. I do not see that. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. Neither do I; but that is <lb/>
the opinion of this writer. Finally, the writer in <lb/>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic">The Month</hi> says: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"It would appear as if the French Government has <lb/>
become fully aware that the French language in Canada <lb/>
is in danger, and that steps have been taken to bring <lb/>
about a more cordial and general intercourse between <lb/>
the French-speaking people on both sides of the Atlantic. <lb/>
This can done in many ways, but in no way more <lb/>
effectually than by close commercial relations." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>In another article it gives my hon. friend the Sec<lb break="no"/>retary of State credit for the endeavor he has made <lb/>
to bring about that good feeling between France <lb/>
and the people of the Province of Quebec, which <lb/>
    good feeling up to that time was not to be discov<lb break="no"/>ered. I have read these extracts from <hi rendition="simple:italic">The <lb/>
Month</hi>, which I thought would be accepted as <lb/>
undoubted authority, having been quoted before in <lb/>
this House by the Minister of Justice, and I now <lb/>
    propose to read from the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Catholic World</hi>, published <lb/>
in New York, and from its publication in the year <lb/>
1885 I make the following extracts:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"The growing power and importance of the French in <lb/>
Canada is the cause of the annexation feeling now taking <lb/>
root in Ontario and Nova Scotia. It is felt by all sections <lb/>
of Canadians that the connection with England must be <lb/>
severed, but the dread the French entertain towards <lb/>
annexation and the English towards independence pre<lb break="no"/>vents the sundering of the fragile tie." <lb/></p>
</quote>
    
<cb/>

<p><persName ref="pers:ANON1">An hon. MEMBER</persName>. You don't believe that. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I hear my hon. friend say <lb/>
that I do not believe that. Sir, I have heard that <lb/>
argued over and over again, and it is not very long <lb/>
ago since I heard a gentleman, who was a distin<lb break="no"/>guished member of this House, say it was the only <lb/>
remedy for the existing condition of things—that <lb/>
gentleman said that the only remedy was to swamp <lb/>
my hon. friends from the Province of Quebec in the <lb/>
great American Confederacy. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. Are you then an Annexation<lb break="no"/>ist? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. Not by any means. I do not <lb/>
at all concur in that, Mr. Speaker. I think that <lb/>
within the lines of the Constitution and in this <lb/>
Dominion of Canada this question can, will and <lb/>
must be settled, but I think that if that question <lb/>
is not settled considerable difficulties, as I have <lb/>
said, must arise. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). It is settled. <lb/></p> 

    <p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. The article in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Catholic <lb/>
World</hi>, to which I refer, commences by this: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"We are Englishmen speaking the French language," <lb/>
said the late Sir George Cartier, the colleague and close <lb/>
personal friend of Sir John A. Macdonald." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>And the article goes on to explain that the result <lb/>
of that statement made by that distinguished <lb/>
Canadian statesman was: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Before this he was the undisputed leader of the <lb/>
French Canadian element in Canada; three years later <lb/>
he was unmercifully beaten at the polls for Montreal East <lb/>
by an obscure young lawyer by the name of Jetté. The <lb/>
crushing defeat was the French Canadlan way of punish<lb break="no"/>ing Sir George for his ultra-loyal speech and the misre<lb break="no"/>presentation it embodied. Not that French Canadians <lb/>
are not well affected to the Empire as things go; only it <lb/>
must be understood they are well affected as French <lb/>
Canadians." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>I would just ask the House to allow me to trouble <lb/>
them with another extract. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BERG1">Mr. BERGERON</persName>. Is it another religious <lb/>
book? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I will not further trouble <lb/>
the House with quotations. I have endeavored at <lb/>
all events to make good my statements, that both <lb/>
from within and from without the general opinion <lb/>
prevails that this question has come to the point <lb/>
where it is likely to cause further differences, as it <lb/>
has already caused differences in the Dominion. I <lb/>
come back now, Sir, to the North-West Territories. <lb/>
I am not attempting here, and hon. gentlemen <lb/>
know that, at all events in this form of motion, I <lb/>
could not attempt in any way to interfere with <lb/>
any rights under the British North America Act <lb/>
which are guaranteed to the French Canadians of <lb/>
the Province of Quebec, and to the French Cana<lb break="no"/>dians in this Parliament. I am treating, Sir, of <lb/>
what this Parliament is competent to deal with. <lb/>
I am treating of the question of the dual language <lb/>
of the North-West Territories. I hold in my <lb/>
hand, though it has not been yet presented to the <lb/>
House, a petition from the Legislative Assembly of <lb/>
the North-West Territories. Where that petition <lb/>
is I cannot say: whether it is in the hands of the <lb/>
Government, whether it is to be brought before <lb/>
the House, whether it has been sent to Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, or where the petition is I cannot <lb/>
say; but, that the Legislative Assembly of the <lb/>
North-West Territories did, at their last ses<lb break="no"/>sion discuss this question and pass the following <lb/>
resolution on the subject, by what was practically <lb/>

<pb n="51" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00051.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">51</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">52</fw> 

an unanimous vote, there can be no doubt. That <lb/>
petition of the Legislative Assembly of the North-<lb break="yes"/>West is as follows:— <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Address to the Honorable the House of Commons of <lb/>
Canada, in Parliament Assembled, adopted by the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly of the North-West Territories, <lb/>
on Monday, 28th October, 1889. <lb/></p> 

<p>"The petition of the Legislative Assembly of the <lb/>
North-West Territories in Session assembled, humbly <lb/>
sheweth:— <lb/></p> 

<p>"That, whereas by Section one hundred and ten of <lb/>
'The North-West Territories Act' it is enacted that <lb/>
'Either the English or the French language may be used <lb/>
by any person in the debates of the Legislative As<lb break="no"/>sembly of the Territories and in the proceedings before <lb/>
the Courts; and both these languages shall be used in <lb/>
the records and journals of the Assembly, and all Ordi<lb break="no"/>nances made under this Act shall be printed in both <lb/>
these languages.' <lb/></p> 

<p>"And, whereas this Assembly is of the opinion that the <lb/>
sentiment of the people of the North-West Territories is <lb/>
against the continuance of the section recited, on the <lb/>
grounds that the needs of the Territories do not demand <lb/>
the official recognition of a dual language in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West or the expenditure necessitated by the same. <lb/></p> 

<p>"And, whereas this Assembly is also of the opinion <lb/>
that sound pubhc policy demands the discontinuance of <lb/>
two official languages in the North-West; <lb/></p> 

<p>"Wherefore your petitioners humbly pray: <lb/></p> 

<p>"That your Honorable House may be pleased to pass <lb/>
an Act repealing said section one hundred and ten of <lb/>
said Act.   <lb/></p> 

<p>"And as in duty bound your petitioners will ever <lb/>
pray." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
    
<p>Not only, Sir, was this petition thus with almost <lb/>
practical unanimity resolved upon, but I am <lb/>
informed, and I believe the fact to be, although I <lb/>
have not examined it, that every newspaper pub<lb break="no"/>lished in the North-West has declared in favor of <lb/>
the abolition of the dual languages—every paper <lb/>
which has referred to the subject, I mean. One <lb/>
    distinguished paper, the Regina <hi rendition="simple:italic">Leader</hi>, I believe, <lb/>
has not yet thought it a subject worthy of notice; <lb/>
but almost every other paper has pronounced in <lb/>
favor of abolition. So that we have practically <lb/>
the unanimous opinion of the people of that terri<lb break="no"/>tory. Now, are we going to perpetuate this sys<lb break="no"/>tem of things? Are we going to permit it to grow <lb/>
into what might be called a vested right, so that <lb/>
by-and-bye a French Canadian can urge, and with <lb/>
some degree of truth, "I have left my own home <lb/>
in the Province of Quebec and have gone and <lb/>
settled in the North-West Territories, relying on <lb/>
the faith of an Act of Parliament by which it was <lb/>
said I should be allowed to have my language." Is <lb/>
it, or is it not, a matter which we ought to deal <lb/>
with, and deal with promptly? Sir, I have nothing <lb/>
further to add on the general question. I will only <lb/>
say, in conclusion, that while I have thought it <lb/>
right at this early stage to make a statement of <lb/>
the reasons which have actuated the course I am <lb/>
taking, I desire here, as I have done elsewhere, to <lb/>
disclaim any feeling of hostility of any kind against <lb/>
the French Canadian race or their representatives in <lb/>
this House. I desire to say that I have no such <lb/>
feeling. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BERG1">Mr. BERGERON</persName>. Thank you. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. My only desire is to pro<lb break="no"/>mote the welfare of us all, and I think our truest <lb/>
interest will be found in trying to create and build <lb/>
up in this country one race with one national life, <lb/>
and with a language common to us all. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LARIVIERE</persName>. (Translation) I have listened <lb/>
to, with more curiosity than interest, Mr. Speaker, <lb/>
the speech which has just been made by the hon. <lb/>
member for Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy). I must con<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

fess that I have been astonished, and that in no <lb/>
slight degree, at seeing an Ontario member arro<lb break="no"/>gate to himself the right of coming here, into this <lb/>
House, and asking for amendments to the Act <lb/>
erecting the North-West Territories. It is thought <lb/>
good to make an attack upon a right which is very <lb/>
dear to us, to all of us French Canadians — a <lb/>
right which we possess under the British made <lb/>
constitution which governs us. And what aston<lb break="no"/>ishes us still more, connected with the means em<lb break="no"/>ployed to-day, is that they begin by attacking a <lb/>
handful of Métis scattered throughout the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories, with the object of crushing them <lb/>
out. I think this is a cowardly act, an act of cow<lb break="no"/>ardice which we must oppose with all our powers. <lb/>
To what end is all this exertion made? Why— <lb/>
if sincerity exists,—if this French language ought <lb/>
no longer to be spoken in Canada,—why do they <lb/>
not attack its use throughout the whole Dominion <lb/>
of Canada; why do they not endeavor to prohibit <lb/>
its use universally, instead of proceeding to attack, <lb/>
as I have just said, a handful of French Canadians, <lb/>
away off yonder, who cannot defend themselves; <lb/>
but who count upon us to be their defenders? I do <lb/>
    not intend, Mr. Speaker, to follow the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber throughout the speech which he has just <lb/>
delivered; I shall only animadvert upon certain <lb/>
passages. He stated, among other things, that the <lb/>
language of a people is the foundation of its nation<lb break="no"/>ality. I ask myself, if this idea is correct, how <lb/>
does it happen that in the Islands of Jersey and <lb/>
Guernsey, which have been English possessions for <lb/>
more than two hundred years, they have preserved <lb/>
the French language,—that the French language <lb/>
only is spoken,—and that that language is the only <lb/>
one recognised officially? How comes it that in <lb/>
the Island of Saint Lucie and the other islands in <lb/>
the Antilles which happen to be British possessions, <lb/>
the French language is spoken? Is this merely a <lb/>
privilege which the peoples of these places have ar<lb break="no"/>rogated to themselves; or is it not rather a privi<lb break="no"/>lege granted by the British Crown, by the laws, <lb/>
and by the constitution of these countries that the <lb/>
mother tongue of the inhabitants is allowed them. <lb/>
So that the power which we possess, we French <lb/>
Canadians, of using our mother tongue is no unpre<lb break="no"/>cedented concession; it is not a right possessed ex<lb break="no"/>clusively by the French Canadian subject, but it is, <lb/>
a right which belongs to subjects in other colonies <lb/>
of the Empire. The hon. member has observed <lb/>
that it is only in Switzerland where the use of two <lb/>
    languages is permitted. I think that if he had <lb/>
studied history he would have found that in other <lb/>
countries likewise the use of two distinct and dif<lb break="no"/>ferent languages is sanctioned. In Belgium, among 
    <lb/>others, two languages are allowed; French is the <lb/>
official language, even though the public docu<lb break="no"/>ments and papers are printed and published in <lb/>
Flemish. So that Canada forms no peculiar ex<lb break="no"/>ception. The strongest position of the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Simcoe rests upon the celebrated report of <lb/>
Lord Durham, or supposed to be that of Lord <lb/>
Durham. All my fellow countrymen know what. <lb/>
this report is worth. It was not pro ared with <lb/>
the object of favoring the population of this coun<lb break="no"/>try; it was not drafted in the interests of those <lb/>
who then dwelt in Lower Canada; but it was pro<lb break="no"/>jected with the aim of Anglicising and of being able <lb/>
to persecute the population which then dwelt in <lb/>
the land, to the benefit of the immigration which <lb/>
had come out to possess it. Under such circum<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="53" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00053.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">53</fw> <fw type="dateline">[JANUARY 22, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">54</fw>

stances is it allowable to make use of this report <lb/>
in order to support the attempt which they are at <lb/>
this moment making adversely to our interests? <lb/>
Those who take advantage to-day of this report <lb/>
are worthy successors of him who prepared it. I <lb/>
must here remark, Mr. Speaker, that there exists <lb/>
a false impression about the history of this country. <lb/>
They wish to treat us as if we were a conquered <lb/>
people, whereas Canada was not conquered but was <lb/>
ceded to England under the terms of a treaty. In <lb/>
this treaty it is provided that our religion, our <lb/>
laws, and our customs as they existed at the time, <lb/>
should be protected, and I ask myself whether it <lb/>
cannot be affirmed to-day, that within these con<lb break="no"/>ditions and terms is included the conservation of <lb/>
our mother tongue, which we spoke at that time <lb/>
and which we still speak. From such reasoning <lb/>
it results that when the hon. member for Simcoe <lb/>
states that there was no such guarantee in the <lb/>
treaty,—that is to say the guarantee of the use of <lb/>
our language,—I can tell him his statement is <lb/>
false. The gravest insult that can be offered to us <lb/>
in the course of this discussion, which has hardly <lb/>
yet opened in this House; is that men should <lb/>
wish to have our enemies believe that because we <lb/>
do not use the English language habitually we are <lb/>
not loyal subjects of Her Majesty. They attack <lb/>
us on this line when taxing us with disloyalty. <lb/>
Well, when we see what our ancestors did when <lb/>
the time had come to defend the frontier, can it <lb/>
not be fairly said that they showed themselves <lb/>
quite as loyal if not more loyal than our fellow <lb/>
subjects of British origin? Can it be that people <lb/>
have forgotten the celebrated battles which we <lb/>
fought against our powerful neighbors the <lb/>
Americans? And if Canada still remains a British <lb/>
possession, to whom does England owe its retention <lb/>
if not to the French—but still loyal—population <lb/>
of the Province of Quebec. No, Mr. Speaker, in <lb/>
the present state of affairs they have thought it <lb/>
expedient to endeavor to exite prejudices in order <lb/>
perhaps to avenge the defeat which they suffered <lb/>
last year in another matter; but on this question, as <lb/>
on every other where our laws and our religion are <lb/>
attacked, I believe that we shall remain unmoved; <lb/>
and more particularly, that we shall defend in this <lb/>
House, as is but our duty, against the attacks this <lb/>
day attempted to be made against them, the few <lb/>
men of our own race who are scattered throughout <lb/>
the North-West country. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN A. MACDONALD</persName>. The Bill intro<lb break="no"/>duced is in terms of very great importance, and of <lb/>
course we can weigh it with reference to its effect <lb/>
on the North-West. But the line of argument my <lb/>
hon. friend has taken raises questions of such a <lb/>
nature, his whole line of argument is of such a <lb/>
kind, as to involve most serious and grave questions <lb/>
    —so grave that I think we must take full time to <lb/>
consider what his arguments are, what they tend <lb/>
to, in what direction they lead, and what conse<lb break="no"/>quences may follow if the measure is persisted in. <lb/>
I, therefore, Sir, would hope that the discussion <lb/>
would end here—that the Bill should be allowed to <lb/>
be read the first time, and that after we have an <lb/>
opportunity of reading the carefully prepared <lb/>
speech of my hon. friend, we may, on the second <lb/>
reading, have an opportunity of discussing this im<lb break="no"/>portant, this very grave question in all its bearings. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAP4">Mr. CHAPLEAU</persName>. May I be allowed, not to <lb/>
enter into a discussion of this question, but—as <lb/>

<cb/>

my hon. friend from Simcoe has quoted the author<lb break="no"/>ity of a great name, a great statesman and writer <lb/>
—only to cite one authority which I suppose will <lb/>
be accepted by himself and the whole House, as it <lb/>
has already been accepted by the whole country. <lb/>
A great statesman, at the time of the Union, wrote <lb/>
these words which have never been forgotten in <lb/>
this country: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"I must, moreover, confess that I for one am deeply <lb/>
convinced of the impolicy of all such attempts to dena<lb break="no"/>tionalise the French. Generally speaking they produce <lb/>
the opposite effect from that intended, causing the flame <lb/>
of national prejudice and animosity to burn more <lb/>
fiercely. But suppose them to be successful, what would <lb/>
be the result? You may perhaps Americanise, but, de<lb break="no"/>pend upon it, by methods of this description you will <lb/>
never Anglicise the French inhabitants of the Province. <lb/>
Let them feel on the other hand, that their religion, <lb/>
their habits, their prepossessions, their prejudices if you <lb/>
will, are more considered and respected here than in <lb/>
other portions of this vast continent, who will venture to <lb/>
say that the last hand which waves the British flag on <lb/>
American ground may not be that of a French Canadian." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
    
<p>These words were those of the noble Lord Elgin, <lb/>
and I ask my hon. friend to read them and to <lb/>
meditate upon them. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. I have read them. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Mr. LAURIER</persName>. I did not understand my hon. <lb/>
friend from Simcoe, in his opening remarks, to say <lb/>
that he expected that this question would be <lb/>
debated at this stage of his Bill. I understood, on <lb/>
the contrary, that he expected that it would be <lb/>
debated, as is usual in this House, only on the <lb/>
second reading. This is our customary practice, <lb/>
and, therefore, perhaps, the hon. gentleman will <lb/>
permit me to tell him that it would have been <lb/>
preferable if he had not introduced in his re<lb break="no"/>marks a good deal of controversial matter, which <lb/>
is quite debatable, no matter what stand is taken <lb/>
on the Bill. The hon. gentleman must allow that <lb/>
a man may be in favor of his Bill, and not agree with <lb/>
a good deal that he has said. For my own part, <lb/>
Sir, I do not propose at this stage to express an <lb/>
opinion on the Bill which he has presented. I <lb/>
reserve that for the second reading. I propose to <lb/>
follow in this instance the very safe practice <lb/>
which has always been followed in this House, <lb/>
of not expressing an opinion on a Bill, even if the <lb/>
tenor of it be well known in advance, until it has <lb/>
been placed in the hands of all members, and until <lb/>
they have read it and can form a mature judgment <lb/>
upon it. There is a good deal that I would per<lb break="no"/>sonally take exception to in the hon. gentleman's <lb/>
remarks. I will not do so to-day; but the hon. <lb/>
gentleman will permit me to give him a piece of <lb/>
information as to which he appears to be in <lb/>
obscurity. He wants to know what was the <lb/>
cause that the Liberal candidate was defeated in <lb/>
the County of Richelieu. So far as my informa<lb break="no"/>tion goes, I have always understood that the cause <lb/>
was the bank notes of the defunct Mechanics <lb/>
Bank. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA5">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. May I be permitted, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, to say that I am sorry if I have intro<lb break="no"/>duced what my hon. friend calls controversial <lb/>
matter. I deliberately adopted the course I have <lb/>
taken in making my statement, which I endeavored <lb/>
to make as impartial and fair as possible, on the <lb/>
introduction of the Bill. I understood it to be the <lb/>
English practice, and I think it is the fair practice. <lb/>
I have made my statement now and hon. gentlemen <lb/>
have an opportunity of considering it before the <lb/>
second reading, and then I shall have an oppor<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="55" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-01-22_Page_00055.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">55</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">56</fw> 

tunity of defending my position in answer to the <lb/>
objections that may then be made.   <lb/></p> 

<p>Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first time. <lb/></p> 
</div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">CUSTOMS DUTY ON MEAT.</head>
        
<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. MARSHALL</persName> asked, Is it the intention of <lb/>
the Government at the present time to increase the <lb/>
duty on mess pork or meat of any kind coming in<lb break="no"/>to Canada? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. This is. a question which it <lb/>
would be inadvisable to answer at the present time, <lb/>
as it is in regard to tariff matters. <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">INSPECTOR OF FISHERIES FOR PRINCE <lb/>
EDWARD ISLAND.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:PERR1">Mr. PERRY</persName> asked, Have the Government ap<lb break="no"/>pointed an Inspector of Fisheries for Prince <lb/>
  Edward Island in the stead of Col. John H. Duvar? <lb/>
If yes, who is he? What is the date of the ap<lb break="no"/>pointment? and at what salary? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TUPP2">Mr. TUPPER</persName>. Mr. Edward Hackett was ap<lb break="no"/>pointed, on the 1st July last, Inspector of Fisheries <lb/>
for Prince Edward Island, at a salary of $800 per <lb/>
annum. <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
        
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">IMPORTED FLOUR AND WHEAT.</head> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CAMP3">Mr. CAMPBELL</persName> asked, How many barrels of <lb/>
flour have been entered for consumption in Canada <lb/>
during the six months ending on 31st December <lb/>
last, with amount of duty paid on the same? Also, <lb/>
how many bushels of wheat were entered during <lb/>
the same time for consumption, and amount of <lb/>
duty paid on same? Also, number of barrels of <lb/>
cornmeal entered for consumption during the same <lb/>
period, and amount of duty collected on same? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BOWE1">Mr. BOWELL</persName>. The number of barrels of flour <lb/>
entered for consumption in Canada during the six <lb/>
months ending on the 31st December last, was <lb/>
108,408 barrels, and the duty collected on the same <lb/>
was $54,204. Those figures, however, do not include <lb/>
the return from British Columbia for the three <lb/>
months ending the 3lst December last, for the reason <lb/>
that they have not yet been received. The returns <lb/>
showing the different descriptions of grain are <lb/>
only received quarterly, and, as a number of the <lb/>
ports have not yet forwarded their reports for the <lb/>
last two quarters, answers to the last two questions <lb/>
cannot be accurately given now. <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">BAR AT THE MOUTH OF THE THAMES.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:CAMP3">Mr. CAMPBELL</persName> asked, Whether it is the in<lb break="no"/>tention of the Government to complete the work <lb/>
of removing the bar at the mouth of the River <lb/>
Thames, in the County of Kent, Ontario, as soon <lb/>
as the weather will permit in the spring? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:LANG1">Sir HECTOR LANGEVIN</persName>. The Government <lb/>
have not as yet considered this question. <lb/></p> 
    </div>
   <div type="debate">
   
<head rendition="simple:centre">NORTH SHORE RAILWAY.</head>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. LANGELIER</persName> (Quebec) moved for: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="simple:centre">
<p>Copies of all correspondence between the Government <lb/>
and the Canadian Pacific Railway Company, or between <lb/>
the Government and the Board of Trade of Quebec, or <lb/>
other public bodies or persons, as well as all other <lb/>
documents, respecting the debentures of the North Shore <lb/>
Railway Company. <lb/></p> 
</quote>
       
<p>He said: Every hon. member of this House knows <lb/>
that in the year 1875, the Government of the Pro<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

vince of Quebec undertook the construction of a rail<lb break="no"/>way from Quebec to Ottawa, which was then called <lb/>
the Quebec, Montreal, Ottawa and Occidental Rail<lb break="no"/>way. That railway was completed in 1879. In 1880, <lb/>
the Government of the Province took possession of <lb/>
the road, and undertook the management of the <lb/>
same. In 1882, when the Hon. the Secretary of State <lb/>
was Prime Minister of the Province of Quebec, the <lb/>
railway in question was sold—one portion, that <lb/>
between Ottawa and Montreal, to the Canadian <lb/>
Pacific Railway Company, and the other section, <lb/>
that between St. Martin's Junction, in the County <lb/>
of Laval, and the city of Quebec, to a company <lb/>
which was constituted by the same Act, which <lb/>
authorised the sale of the railway. By that Act, <lb/>
the company, which was known as the North Shore <lb/>
Railway Company, was empowered to issue de<lb break="no"/>bentures at the rate of $25,000 per mile over the <lb/>
whole length of the railway. Acting on the <lb/>
powers contained in that Act, the North Shore <lb/>
Railway Company issued debentures to the amount <lb/>
of about one and three quarter millions, in round <lb/>
numbers. I do not pretend to give the exact <lb/>
figures, but that was about he amount. I under<lb break="no"/>stand that a portion of these debentures was <lb/>
handed over to the Government of Quebec as col<lb break="no"/>lateral security for the obligation entered into by <lb/>
the company with the said Government of Quebec <lb/>
for the payment of the price of the railway. As I <lb/>
understand, half a million was paid cash, but the <lb/>
rest, three millions and a-half, is still due to the <lb/>
Government of Quebec. Of the total amount of de<lb break="no"/>bentures issued some $1,108,000 was given as <lb/>
collateral security by the company to the Bank of <lb/>
Montreal. At the time of the sale of the railway <lb/>
to the North Shore Railway Company, a great deal <lb/>
of opposition was shown to the scheme of the <lb/>
Government, not only by the members of the <lb/>
then Opposition, but also by a great many <lb/>
supporters of the Government of which my hon. <lb/>
friend the Secretary of State was then the head. <lb/>
That opposition from his own friends was stopped, <lb/>
in a large measure, by the. representations which <lb/>
were made—that that was the only way to prevent <lb/>
the railway from going into the hands of the Grand <lb/>
Trunk Railway Company. That sale took place in <lb/>
1882, and not later, I think, than February, 1883, <lb/>
the same railway was sold to the Grand Trunk <lb/>
Railway Company. I do not mean to say that the <lb/>
line of the railway was sold, but an agreement was <lb/>
entered into by the North Shore Railway Com<lb break="no"/>pany, which was then represented by the late <lb/>
Senator Senecal, and the Grand Trunk Railway <lb/>
Company, by which the stock of the former com<lb break="no"/>pany was transferred to certain parties represent<lb break="no"/>ing the interest of the Grand Trunk ailway <lb/>
Company. The Grand Trunk Railway Company <lb/>
then took possession of the railway, and what <lb/>
was the result? The city of Quebec had subscribed <lb/>
a large sum, a much larger sum than it could <lb/>
relatively afford, if we consider the needs of the <lb/>
city of Quebec. That subscription amounted to <lb/>
$1,000,000. In order to help the construction of <lb/>
the North Shore Railway the city of Quebec <lb/>
made this immense sacrifice, so as to secure a rival <lb/>
line between that city and Montreal. After the <lb/>
line was sold to the Grand Trunk Railway, that <lb/>
rivalry for which the city of Quebec had paid so <lb/>
much ceased altogether to exist. Not only that <lb/>
rivalry ceased to exist, but an arrangement was <lb/>
entered into by the Grand Trunk Railway and the[...] <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>