<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1903-09-29"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1903-09-29">29 September 1903</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Ninth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
          <date when="1903"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
          <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="12610" to="12611"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-29_Page_12610.html"/>
               </item>
   
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-26">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-09-26">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-29_Page_12610">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-29_Page_12610.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="12610" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-29_Page_12610.jpg"/>
      
      <fw type="num">12610</fw>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS</head>
            <head rendition="simple:right">Tuesday, September 29, 1903.</head>
            
            
            <p>
      The SPEAKER took the Chair at Eleven 
     <lb/>
     o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
            <div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES ACT 
     <lb/>AMENDMENT.<lb/>
     
     
     
            </head>

            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName> (Hon.  
     <lb/>Charles Fitzpatrick) moved for leave to in<lb break="no"/>troduce Bill (No. 259) to amend the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories Act.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. Explain.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName>. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Speaker, the Supreme Court of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories, as at present constituted, 
     <lb/>
      consists of four puisne judges and one judge 
     <lb/>
      of the Supreme Court. The intention is 
     <lb/>
     now to have a court consituted with five  
     <lb/>puisne judges and a chief justice. The<lb/>second section of the Bill provides for cases<lb/>reserved for considerations by the full court.<lb/>As the law now stands a judge reserving<lb/>a point for the consideration of the full<lb/>court cannot be a member of the court un<lb break="no"/>less his presence is necessary to constitute<lb/>a quorum. The intention is that when a<lb/>point is reserved in a criminal case the<lb/>judge sitting at the trial in the criminal<lb/>case who reserved the point may form part<lb/>of the court before which the last amend<lb break="no"/>ment is suggested by the judges of the <lb/>Supreme Court.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). Is there any de<lb break="no"/>mand from the bar or the people of the<lb/>
     
     
            <cb/>
    

   
     North-west Territories for an additional   
     <lb/>
     judge ? 
            </p>
            
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName>. Yes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). Where is he to 
     <lb/>
     be  stationed or to reside ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName>. There is<lb/>an almost unanimous request from the bar<lb/>of the North-west Territories for the ap<lb break="no"/>pointment of this additional judge, and I<lb/>may say that it is supported by the Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General of the North-west Territories.<lb/>No provision is made for residence at the<lb/>present time. There will necessarily have<lb/>to be a division made so as to make pro<lb break="no"/>vision for the district in which Macleod is<lb/>situated, but I am not sure at the present<lb/>time where the residence will be.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first<lb/>time.<lb/>
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>