<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1903-07-20"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1903-07-20">20 July 1903</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Ninth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
          <date when="1903"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
          <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="6891" to="6893"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-20_Page_06891.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-20_Page_06893.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-26">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-09-26">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-20_Page_06891">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-20_Page_06891.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-20_Page_06893">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-20_Page_06893.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="6891" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-20_Page_06891.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">6891</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">6892</fw>
      
      
      
            <head rendition="simple:centre">INQUIRIES FOR RETURNS.</head>
      
      
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). I would like 
     <lb/>to bring to the attention of the government<lb/>the fact that the documents which have been<lb/>printed, purporting to be a return to an<lb/>address of the House of Commons dated the<lb/>11th May, 1902, for copies of all Orders in<lb/>Council and other documents having refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the granting of provincial autonomy<lb/>to the North-west Territories, are extremely<lb/>defective. I had procured a number of<lb/>prints of these documents from Regina, and.<lb/>doing the work of a clerk this morning, I<lb/>compared them with the return which has<lb/>been brought down, and I found that a very<lb/>great number of the documents have not<lb/>been printed. In order to show my right<lb/>turn as printed, I will read a list of the<lb/>documents which have not been included in<lb/>it, some of which are of no great import<lb break="no"/>ance, but others of which are of the greatest<lb/>possible importance for the purpose of an<lb/>intelligent discussion of this question. I may<lb/>say that one or two of the documents which<lb/>I have included in the list, while not directly<lb/>referring to the question of provincial auto<lb break="no"/>nomy, are nevertheless in answer to cor<lb break="no"/>respondence which does touch that question<lb/>as well as the question of better financial<lb/>terms ; and these, I think, ought to be<lb/>brought down, because they are part of<lb/>the consecutive correspondence dealing with<lb/>these matters. The letters which have been<lb/>omitted, which I had to take from a num<lb break="no"/>ber of documents and therefore have got<lb/>them arranged in chronological order, are<lb/>as follows : January 31, 1903, Mr. Haul<lb break="no"/>tain to Mr. Sifton : February 11, 1903, Mr.<lb/>Haultain to Mr. Sifton : February 9, 1903,<lb/>Mr. McGee to Mr. Haultain : February 16,<lb/>1903, Mr. Keys to Mr. Haultain : March<lb/>19, 1903, Mr. Haultain to Mr. Sifton : March<lb/>21, 1903, Mr. Sifton to Mr. Haultain : April<lb/>15, 1903, Mr. Haultain to Mr. Sifton : De<lb break="no"/>cember 17, 1902, Mr. A. L. Sifton to Mr.<lb/>Clifford Sifton : February 5, 1903, Mr. Sif<lb break="no"/>ton to Mr. Haultain : February 11, 1903,<lb/>Mr. Haultain to Mr. Sifton : February 21,<lb/>1903, Mr. Haultain to Mr. Sifton : April<lb/>16, 1903, Mr. Fielding to Mr. Haultain :<lb/>April 17, 1903, Mr. Haultain to Mr. Field<lb break="no"/>ing : April 20, 1903, Sir Wilfrid Laur<lb break="no"/>ier to Mr. Haultain : April 20, 1903, Mr.<lb/>Haultain to Mr. Fielding : April 24, 1903,<lb/>Lieut.-Gov. Forget of the North-west<lb/>Territories to the Secretary of State, Inclos<lb break="no"/>ing an address : June 2, 19003, Mr. Haul<lb break="no"/>tain to Sir Wilfred Laurier : June 6, 1903,<lb/>Mr. Fielding to Mr. Haultain : June 15, 1903,<lb/>Mr. Pelletier. acting Under Secretary of<lb/>Mr. BORDEN (Halifax)<lb/>

<cb/>
    
    
    State to Lieut.-Gov. Forget ; January 30,<lb/>1901, Mr. Haultain to Mr. Sifton ; March<lb/>21, 1901, Mr. Sifton to Mr. Haultain ; March<lb/>30, 1901, Mr. Haultain to Mr. Sifton ; April<lb/>5, 1901, Mr. Sifton to Mr. Haultain : June<lb/>4, 1901, Mr. Haultain to Mr. Sifton : June<lb/>5, 1901, Mr. Sifton to Mr. Haultain : Aug<lb break="no"/>ust, 11, 1901, Mr. A. L. Sifton to Mr. Clifford<lb/>Sifton ; August 14, 1901, Mr. Clifford Sifton<lb/>to Mr. A. L. Sifton ; January 11, 1901, A.<lb/>L. Sifton to Sir Wilfred Laurier ; January<lb/>22, 1902, Sir Wilfred Laurier to Mr. A. L.<lb/>Sifton ; March 15, 1902, Mr. Haultain to<lb/>Sir Wilfred Laurier ; March 18, 1902, Sir<lb/>Wilfred Laurier to mr. Haultain ; March<lb/>27, 1902, Mr. Sifton to mr. Haultain ; April<lb/>2, 1902, Mr. Haultain to mr. Sifton ; April<lb/>29, 1903, Mr. Pelletier, acting Under Secre<lb break="no"/>tary of State, to Lieut.-Gov. Forget. I<lb/>thought it would be desirable to read this<lb/>long list in order to indicate to my right<lb/>hon, friend how very defective is the return<lb/>which has been brought down and printed.<lb/>I recollect that at the time the papers were<lb/>first brought down, the right hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man mentioned to the House that there<lb/>would be some other papers. Possibly these<lb/>have not yet been prepared ; but might I<lb/>be permitted to suggest that, in bringing<lb/>down correspondence of this kind, it would<lb/>great diminish the labour of members<lb/>who desire to deal with important subjects<lb/>of this character, if the documents could be<lb/>printed in chronological order, beginning<lb/>with the documents, of an earlier date. That<lb/>has not been done in this case, and if we have<lb/>another return printed, with the documents<lb/>that I have mentioned, I am afraid that the<lb/>matter will be in rather a confused condi<lb break="no"/>tion. Possibly it would be advisable to nave<lb/>these documents arranged in chronological<lb/>order, if it would not take too long, and<lb/>printed, so as to have them in an intelli<lb break="no"/>gible form before the House. The corres<lb break="no"/>pondence is quite voluminous, and it will<lb/>be difficult to gather its bearings unless we<lb/>have it in that form.</p>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName> (Hon. W.<lb/>S. Fielding). I think that some part of<lb/>the difficult arises from the fact that my<lb/>hon. friend's remarks dealt with two sub<lb break="no"/>jects, which probably the officials who pre<lb break="no"/>pared the return did not associate together,<lb/>although they do in some respects touch<lb/>each other. My hon. friend's remarks had<lb/>relation to the question of provincial au<lb break="no"/>tonomy, and he has mentioned some corres<lb break="no"/>pondence which took place between Mr.<lb/>Haultain and myself which has not been<lb/>brought down. I had no correspondence<lb/>whatever with Mr. Haultain on the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of provincial autonomy. I did have cor<lb break="no"/>respondence with him in respect to the<lb/>grants to the North-west Territories, and<lb/>I quite admit that the two questions tones<lb/>each other, and I think that may be the<lb/>explanation for he absence of these docu<lb break="no"/>ments.<lb/> <lb/>
            </p>
    
    
    
            <pb n="6893" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-07-20_Page_06893.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">6893</fw> <fw type="dateline">JULY 20, 1903</fw> 
    
    
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). That explains<lb/>two or three of these documents, but not<lb/>all. Two or three communications, prin<lb break="no"/>cipally telegrams, passed between Mr.<lb/>Haultain and the Minister of Finance. I<lb/>referred to those in mentioning that some of<lb/>the documents contained no reference to pro<lb break="no"/>vincial autonomy. But there are a great<lb/>many other documents not brought down<lb/>which refer to provincial autonomy, al<lb break="no"/>though they may refer principally to better<lb/>terms. some of those omitted relate entirely<lb/>to the question of provincial autonomy.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">The PRIME MINISTER</persName> (Rt. Hon. Sir<lb/>Wilfrid Laurier). When I brought down this<lb/>return I stated that something more would<lb/>have to come. I noted that some correspon<lb break="no"/>dence subsequent to the date of my hon.<lb/>friend motion is not included, but I will<lb/>have this brought down. Would my hon.<lb/>friend be kind enough to let me have the<lb/>list he has just read ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). I am afraid<lb/>that it is not legible to any one but myself,<lb/>but I will have a copy made.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">The MINISTER OF FINANCE</persName>. It will<lb/>be in 'Hansard,' and can be got there.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. BORDEN</persName> (Halifax). I would like to<lb/>bring to the attention of my hon. friend the<lb/>Minister of the Interior the fact that he pro<lb break="no"/>mised to bring down a return which had<lb/>been moved for by my hon. friend from<lb/>Marquette (Mr. Roche). I don not know<lb/>whether it has been brought down or not,<lb/>but I have not seen it. When we were pro<lb break="no"/>ceeding with the estimates a few days ago,<lb/>the hon. gentleman said that it would be<lb/>brought down the next day or the day fol<lb break="no"/>lowing. He said also that he would bring<lb/>down certain information with regard to the<lb/>lands still obtainable in the organized terri<lb break="no"/>tories for homestead entries.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SIFT1">The MINISTER OF THE INTERIOR</persName> <lb/>(Hon. Clifford Sifton). I have instructions<lb/>to have the return referred to by the hon.<lb/>gentleman brought down and expected to<lb/>have it this morning. It is, however, being<lb/>attended to. As to the lands, I have a state<lb break="no"/>ment, but my hon. friend was not here at<lb/>the time. You will find it in 'Hansard.'<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LANC1">Mr. LANCASTER</persName>. I desire to call the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the hon. the Minister of Marine<lb/>to a return ordered the 1st of June for cor<lb break="no"/>respondence with regards to fishing rights in<lb/>James Bay. When may we expect this re<lb break="no"/>turn ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:PREF1">The MINISTER OF MARINE AND<lb/>FISHERIES</persName>. It must be in the hands of<lb/>the Secretary of State, because I sent him<lb/>the papers a long time ago.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>