<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1894-03-20"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1894-03-20">20 March 1894</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
          
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
          
          
          <date when="1894"/>.  
          
          
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="144"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00137.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00139.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00141.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00143.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-23">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00137">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00137.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00139">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00139.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00141">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00141.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00143">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00143.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="137" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00137.jpg"/>
         
         
     
<fw type="dateline">[MARCH 20,1394]</fw> <fw type="num">138</fw> 


               <!-- GL, 2018-10-23, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day --> 
           <!-- <p>
     they are afraid to buy a bullock this year, and  
     <lb/>
     although I am largely interested in the trade,  
     <lb/>
     I will not buy this spring.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first 
     <lb/>
     time.  
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>DUTIES OF CUSTOMS —EXPORT DUTY 
     <lb/>ON LOGS.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Mr. CHARLTON moved for leave to intro<lb break="no"/>duce Bill (No. 9) further to amend the 
     <lb/>
     Acts respecting the duties of Customs. He 
     <lb/>
     said : The object of the Bill is to repeal 
     <lb/>
     certain clauses of the Customs Act relating 
     <lb/>
     to the imposition of export duties. The law  
     <lb/>
     imposing those duties was first enacted 
     <lb/>
     in chapter 33, section 6, of the Revised 
     <lb/>
     Statutes of Canada, and in schedule E 
     <lb/>
     of the same. Schedule E was subse<lb break="no"/>quently amended by section 3 of chapter 39 
     <lb/>
     of the Statutes of 1887, and in 1888, section  
     <lb/>
     1 of chapter 15 gave the Governor in 
     <lb/>
     Council power to increase those duties to 
     <lb/>
     $3, to reduce them, to repeal them, to re<lb break="no"/>impose them, and to keep the trade in a 
     <lb/>
     great state of uncertainty and fear as to 
     <lb/>
     the course that the Governor in Council 
     <lb/>
     might be pleased to take with respect to 
     <lb/>
     this very disturbing proceeding. From my 
     <lb/>
     own connection with the lumber trade, I am 
     <lb/>
     well aware that this power in the hands of 
     <lb/>
     the Governor in Council has had a depress<lb break="no"/>ing and unfavourable influence on the trade, 
     <lb/>
     and whatever may be the question as to the 
     <lb/>
     propriety of imposing export duties, the last 
     <lb/>
     section of this Bill, which says that no 
     <lb/>
     further action shall be taken by the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor in Council, with respect to export 
     <lb/>
     duties, without the consent of Parliament 
     <lb/>
      having first been obtained, is a section which  
     <lb/>
     must commend itself to the good judgment 
     <lb/>
     of every business man. If the export 
     <lb/>
     duties which have been removed under the 
     <lb/>
     statutory provision of the McKinley Act 
     <lb/>
     are to be reimposed, the matter should be 
     <lb/>
     fully discussed, and the House should 
     <lb/>
     be made aware of the reasons for the 
     <lb/>
     imposition of those duties. There was an 
     <lb/>
     occasion when the Government increased 
     <lb/>
     the duties from $2 to $3 per thousand. They  
     <lb/>
     speedily found they had taken a step that 
     <lb/>
     was an imprudent one, and they receded 
     <lb/>
     from the position they had taken, which was 
     <lb/>
     an illustration of the point I desire to make, 
     <lb/>
     that the consideration of this important 
     <lb/>
     question is one which should be had in open 
     <lb/>
     day, should be discussed here on the floor of 
     <lb/>
     this House, and the reasons for the 
     <lb/>
     imposition of those duties should be fully 
     <lb/>
     canvassed and considered before action was 
     <lb/>
     taken. For these reasons, the Bill proposes 
     <lb/>
     that the clause of the Customs Act authoriz<lb break="no"/>ing the imposition of export duties should 
     <lb/>
     be repealed, and that no action on this 
     <lb/>
     matter should in future be taken without 
     <lb/>
     the consent of Parliament having first been 
     <lb/>
     obtained. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first 
     <lb/>
     time.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>-->
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     N. W. T.—DUAL LANGUAGE.  
            </head>
               
               
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. McCARTHY</persName> moved for leave to intro<lb break="no"/>duce Bill (No. 10) further to amend the 
     <lb/>
     Act respecting the North-west Territories. 
     <lb/>
     He said : I may explain that this is the 
     <lb/>
     Bill which I introduced last year. It deals 
     <lb/>
     with two subjects. It proposes to repeal 
     <lb/>
     the clause in the North-west Territories Act 
     <lb/>
     by which separate schools are imposed upon 
     <lb/>
     the Territories, and by which no discretion 
     <lb/>
     is given to the Council of the North-west 
     <lb/>
      Territories respecting education, and in place 
     <lb/>of that clause to give the power to deal with 
     <lb/>the subject of education untrammelled and 
     <lb/>uncontrolled, and as the North-west Council 
     <lb/>may see fit. It also proposes to do away 
     <lb/>with the remnant of what is known as the 
     <lb/>dual language clause. It will be in the 
     <lb/>remembrance of members of this House 
     <lb/>who sat in the fast Parliament of 1890 that 
     <lb/>a discussion took place with respect to the 
     <lb/>repeal of the clause as it then stood, and 
     <lb/>the result of the discussion was a compro<lb break="no"/>mise, by which a portion of the clause was 
     <lb/>repealed, or rather power was given to the 
     <lb/>Council of the North-west Territories to repeal 
     <lb/>a portion of the clause, but the remaining 
     <lb/>portion stands as it was in the original Act. 
     <lb/>The original section inposed duality in lan<lb break="no"/>guage in four matters : first, with respect to 
     <lb/>publication of the laws ; second, with respect 
     <lb/>to proceedings in the courts ; third, with 
     <lb/>respect to proceedings in the Council ; 
     <lb/>and fourth, with respect to the printing and 
     <lb/>publishing of those proceedings. As to the 
     <lb/>proceedings in the Council, this power was 
     <lb/>given by the Act of 1891, in pursuance of 
     <lb/>the arrangement made across the floor in 
     <lb/>the preceding session ; provided, however, 
     <lb/>that after the next general election for the 
     <lb/>Legislative Assembly such Assembly may, 
     <lb/>by ordinance or otherwise, regulate its pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings in the matter of recording and 
     <lb/>publishing the same, and the said regula<lb break="no"/>tion shall be embodied in the proceedings 
     <lb/>which shall be forthwith published by the 
     <lb/>Lieutenant Governor, in conformity with the 
     <lb/>law, and shall afterward have full force and 
     <lb/>effect. The House will observe that the 
     <lb/>power given to the Legislative Assembly 
     <lb/>was merely with respect to its own pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings, and the other portion of the law 
     <lb/>still remained in force : first, that proceed<lb break="no"/>ings in the courts might be conducted in 
     <lb/>either language, and, second, that the ordin<lb break="no"/>ances, passed under this provision, shall be 
     <lb/>published in both languages. As I have 
     <lb/>often said before in making this motion, or 
     <lb/>in bringing in a bill to repeal this clause, I 
     <lb/>do not do it with any feeling of hostility to 
     <lb/>my French-Canadian fellow-subjects. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve, Sir, that the interests of this country 
     <lb/>will be best served, when the distinction be<lb break="no"/>tween these nationalities is done away with : 
     <lb/>at all events, that so far as the North-west 
     <lb/>is concerned, we certainly should not intro<lb break="no"/>duce a measure which is calculated and ap<lb break="no"/>
       
       
       
            <pb n="139" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00139.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">139</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">140</fw>
      
      
      
     parently designed, to perpetuate that race           
     <lb/>
     distinction which unhappily exists in one of       
     <lb/>
    the older provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. Which one ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. In the province of Que<lb break="no"/>bec. If the hon. gentleman wants to know, 
     <lb/>we have no difficulty in answering that 
     <lb/>question.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. We will tell you about the 
     <lb/>
     other one by and by. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. With regard to the sub<lb break="no"/>ject of education, I think that the House 
     <lb/>
     and the country must be satisfied just now, 
     <lb/>
     that an attempt to interfere with a pro<lb break="no"/>vince in the North-west, or the territories 
     <lb/>
     in the North- west on the subject of educa<lb break="no"/>tion, is calculated to cause a great deal of 
     <lb/>
     trouble. We have had the Manitoba School 
     <lb/>
     question up, by reason of an attempt that 
     <lb/>
     was made in the constitution of Manitoba, 
     <lb/>
     to fetter or control that province on the 
     <lb/>
     subject of education, and recently, I think 
     <lb/>
     the Government have found some little diffi<lb break="no"/>culty in dealing with a cognate question 
     <lb/>
     which came from the North-west Territories. 
     <lb/>
     The sooner we realize that the people of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba, as well as the people of the North<lb break="no"/>west, are perfectly competent to manage 
     <lb/>
     their educational affairs themselves, with<lb break="no"/>out any control from this Parliament, the 
     <lb/>
     better it will be for the peace and welfare 
     <lb/>
     of this country. I, therefore, have pleasure 
     <lb/>
     in introducing to the House a Bill which will 
     <lb/>
     take away that limitation which the Act 
     <lb/>
     intends to impose, which the Act does im<lb break="no"/>pose, with regard to education, and which 
     <lb/>
     will remove the last vestige of the dual lan<lb break="no"/>guage clause so far as the North-west is 
     <lb/>
     concerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. Mr. Speaker, I certainly did 
     <lb/>
     not expect to speak upon this question at 
     <lb/>
     the present time, but I wish to answer one 
     <lb/>
     statement which was made bv the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman who has just resumed his seat (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McCarthy). He says that the province of 
     <lb/>Quebec is responsible for the hard feeling<lb/>that to-day exists in the Dominion of Can<lb break="no"/>ada ; and I answer that by saying : He is<lb/>the one. He is the one who is responsible for<lb/>the hard feeling that exists in the Dominion<lb/>of Canada. We have had that hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man here year after year since 1887; with<lb/>what ? With a project of law, the inten<lb break="no"/>tion of which is to close the North-west<lb/>Territories and the province of Manitoba<lb/>against the Catholics of the province of<lb/>Quebec ; a project of law wich tells them<lb/>that if they wish to go to that province or<lb/>to those territories, they must remember<lb/>that there—if his views can be carried out<lb/>—their language will be prescribed, and their<lb/>rights will be trampled upon. Why, Mr. Speak<lb break="no"/>er, it was only last night that there was in<lb/>this city another effusion on this same sub<lb break="no"/>ject. I do not see the Controller of Cus<lb break="no"/>toms in his seat at this moment, and I<lb/>
   
   
            <cb/>
          
          
     regret that he is not. But we are beginning<lb/>to be accustomed to these insults coming<lb/>from those gentlemen whose only political 
     <lb/>
     stock is this one theme: their hatred of 
     <lb/>
     their Roman Catholic fellow-citizens. What 
     <lb/>
     does the hon. gentleman expect to gain by 
     <lb/>
     all this agitation ? Does he imagine for a 
     <lb/>
     moment that we from the province of Que<lb break="no"/>bec fear him? Does he imagine for one 
     <lb/>
     moment that the province of Quebec is 
     <lb/>
     going to submit to all his dictates ? His 
     <lb/>
     object, no doubt, is to attain to a position 
     <lb/>
     which, by reason of his alliance with the 
     <lb/>
     party with which he is so long connected, 
     <lb/>
     he could not attain. He wanted, no doubt, 
     <lb/>
     to enter the Cabinet. I beliele that was 
     <lb/>
     his object. Now, finding that he could not 
     <lb/>
     enter the Cabinet, finding that he would not 
     <lb/>
     be taken into the Cabinet, he is trying by 
     <lb/>
     this other means, to attain to the position 
     <lb/>
     of leader of the Govrenment in this country. 
     <lb/>
     He would like to form a solely Protestant 
     <lb/>
     population in this country. He would like 
     <lb/>
     to form solely, and to constitute solely, 
     <lb/>
     Protestant schools in this country. He would 
     <lb/>
     stand up in this House and tell a province 
     <lb/>
     which sends sixty-five representatives here, 
     <lb/>
     that they shall not speak the language which 
     <lb/>
     they learned from their parents. From the 
     <lb/>
     very beginning of the time in which this 
     <lb/>
     animosity took root in his heart, from that 
     <lb/>
     moment to this, every  political question of 
     <lb/>
     any importance to the country at large has 
     <lb/>
     been 1eft aside by him, simply that he might 
     <lb/>
     speak his hatred against the Catholics of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, and in palticular against the French- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Canadians of the province of Quebec. He 
     <lb/>
     has met with very little success so far. He 
     <lb/>
     speaks of the province of Quebec as one in 
     <lb/>
     which there is hatred. Let me tell him— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. McCARTHY</persName>. The hon. gentleman will 
     <lb/>
     allow me to interrupt him. I did not at all 
     <lb/>
     use the expression he thinks. I never re<lb break="no"/>ferred to the province of Quebec as having 
     <lb/>
     hatred. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. Would the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     tell us exactly what he did say ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCCA9">Mr. MCCARTHY</persName>. What I said was : That I 
     <lb/>
     trusted we were not going to perpetuate in 
     <lb/>
     the North-west the racial divisions which 
     <lb/>
     unhappily existed in the province of Quebec. 
     <lb/>
     I never said "hatred " at all. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. Very well, then. I will 
     <lb/>
     immediately give the hon. gentleman an 
     <lb/>
     instance of some of the divisions which exist 
     <lb/>
     in the province of Quebec. In the counties 
     <lb/>
     of that province which are largely Catholic 
     <lb/>
     in some of such counties the representative 
     <lb/>
     is Protestant. I will take the county which 
     <lb/>
     I represent in this House. The overwhelm<lb break="no"/>ing majority of that county is Roman Catho<lb break="no"/>lic, yet I am the first Catholic member that 
     <lb/>
     ever sat for Ottawa county in this House. 
     <lb/>
     A Protestant gentleman represented that 
     <lb/>
     county for thirty years. To give the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member (Mr. McCarthy) a further instance 
     <lb/>
     
     
            <pb n="141" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00141.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">141</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MARCH 20, 1894]</fw> <fw type="num">142</fw>
    
    
     of the same generosity, I may state that the 
     <lb/>
     county of Ottawa was represented in the 
     <lb/>
     Local House by a Protestant member for 
     <lb/>
     years. The warden of that county was a 
     <lb/>
     Protestant ; for years the Mayor of the most 
     <lb/>
     Catholic city in the whole province of Quebec 
     <lb/>
     -the city of Hull-was a Protestant, and so 
     <lb/>
     I could name a good many other counties 
     <lb/>
     with a similar record. I could name the 
     <lb/>
     county of Lotbinière, which is almost ex<lb break="no"/>clusively French-Canadian and Catholic, and 
     <lb/>
     that county sent a Protestant representative 
     <lb/>to this House. More than that, it sent to<lb/>the Quebec Parliament-a Catholic Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment-a Protestant gentleman to represent<lb/>it. I tell the hon. member that there is no<lb/>spirit of intolerance in the province of Que<lb break="no"/>bec ; there is no bigotry in the province of<lb/>Quebec. There is certainly a spirit of<lb/>disgust, but that disgust is entirely due to<lb/>the miserable attempt of the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man to fasten against them this charge<lb/>of bigotry. Does he claim that the<lb/>French-Canadian people have no rights in<lb/>this Dominion of Canada ? He tells us here<lb/>plainly that the object is to do away with<lb/>their language. Have they not as much<lb/>right to speak the French language as he has<lb/>to speak the English language? What is<lb/>the object of all his hostility against the<lb/>French language ? What is the object of all<lb/>his hostility against institutions which have<lb/>been established in this country, and which<lb/>have been found to work successfully here ?<lb/>Does he mean to say that a population of<lb/>nearly two millions shall have no right in<lb/>the Dominion of Canada ? Sir, I tell the<lb/>hon. member that every time he stands up<lb/>in this House to attack us as he has done to<lb break="no"/>day, there are nearly two millions of Roman<lb/>
    Catholics in this country who mock at him, 
     <lb/>who laugh at him, who treat him with con<lb break="no"/>tempt ; and here in this House what is his 
     <lb/>following ? One lone gentleman ; that is 
     <lb/>the following he has here, after all these 
     <lb/>years of agitation against the Catholics. I 
     <lb/>tell the hon. gentleman that the Catholic 
     <lb/>element in Canada has been truer, and a 
     <lb/>better friend of the Dominion than ever the 
     <lb/>hon. gentleman was. What has he done 
     <lb/>for the country ? Let us examine his career 
     <lb/>from the beginning to this moment. Let us 
     <lb/>examine what he was outside the House ; 
     <lb/>let us examine what he has been inside the 
     <lb/>House. What has he done after all these 
     <lb/>years to promote the prosperity of his 
     <lb/>country, or good feeling amongst our people ? 
     <lb/>Nothing, nothing, but a few mean, despicable 
     <lb/>attempts at imposing a peculiar kind 
     <lb/>of legislation on this country. He 
     <lb/>spoke of the Manitoba School Act ; he 
     <lb/>no doubt means to say it is a success. I 
     <lb/>would like to ask the hon. gentleman, does 
     <lb/>he mean to say that public schools or Pro<lb break="no"/>testant schools exist to-day in the province 
     <lb/>of Manitoba ? The hon. gentleman who in<lb break="no"/>troduced the School Act is in this House 
     <lb/>to-day, and he is able to speak for himself 
     <lb/>on the subject. The Protestants in the pro<lb break="no"/>
        
        
            <cb/>
          
          
          vince of Manitoba, who are in a majority,<lb/>abolished the Catholic schools under the pre<lb break="no"/>tense of establishing public schools. Are<lb/>public schools in existence in the province<lb/>of Manitoba to-day ? No, there are no pub<lb break="no"/>lic schools in the province of Manitoba. I<lb/>said so last session ; I said so the session<lb/>before. The schools which exist to-day in<lb/>the province of Manitoba, to which we Catho<lb break="no"/>lics are obliged to subscribe, are purely Pro<lb break="no"/>testant schools.  
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">An hon. MEMBER</persName>. No. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. I beg pardon, yes. The 
     <lb/>
     best authority on that subject is the gentle<lb break="no"/>man who introduced those schools, and I will<lb/>quote his own words. The hon. member for<lb/>Winnipeg (Mr. Martin), speaking a short<lb/>time ago, said:<lb/>
            </p>
   
   
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     He was himself not satisfied with the School 
     <lb/>
     Act and had never been so. He had made a strong 
     <lb/>
     effort to have the public schools controlled by the 
     <lb/>
     Government really made national schools, with 
     <lb/>
     religion obliterated. And he was now more con<lb break="no"/>vinced than ever that that was the only school 
     <lb/>
     which could be justified as constitutional. They 
     <lb/>
     said that the state had no right to interfere in the 
     <lb/>
     matter of religion, but he contended that they 
     <lb/>
     could not do the one without the other. It had 
     <lb/>
     been urged by satistied supporters of the Act that 
     <lb/>
     none could complain of the devotional element in<lb break="no"/>troduced, as it was of the broadest nature, but 
     <lb/>
     they found that the Roman Catholics had the very 
     <lb/>
     greatest objection to this provision of the Act, and 
     <lb/>
     is was dissatisfied himself and was glad many 
     <lb/>Protestants shared his objections. It had been<lb/>said that in the event of his opinions being adopted<lb/>

     our public schools would he Godless schools, but 
     <lb/>
     by many staunch sup orters of the School Act it 
     <lb/>
     had been privately  admitted to him that the reli<lb break="no"/>gious exercises practiced in the Schools at that time 
     <lb/>
     were without value * *. The Roman Catholics 
     <lb/>
     had honestly stated that in their belief the two 
     <lb/>
     forms of education should go together. The Pro<lb break="no"/>testants admitted, on the other hand. that 
     <lb/>
     it was impossible to have religious training in 
     <lb/>
     schools, and only asked that it be recognized, in<lb break="no"/>sisting, however, on imposing their views on others 
     <lb/>
     in that respect. Rather than that small amount 
     <lb/>
     of religious training should be done away with 
     <lb/>
     in the schools, the Protestants said they would 
     <lb/>
     prefer the old state of affairs. He would leave it 
     <lb/>
     to his audience to determine which was the more 
     <lb/>
     honest stand of the two. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     And, Sir, documents have recently been put 
     <lb/>
     into the possession of every reader in this 
     <lb/>country by the Venerable Archbishop of St.<lb/>
    Boniface—documents which we will quote 
     <lb/>further on in the debate on this Bill— show<lb break="no"/>ing conclusively that the schools which ex<lb break="no"/>ist to-day in Manitoba are not public schools, 
     <lb/>but simply and purely Protestant schools. 
     <lb/>I have quoted from the hon. gentleman who 
     <lb/>introduced this villainous School Act in the 
     <lb/>province of Manitoba to the effect that the 
     <lb/>schools there are Protestant schools. And 
     <lb/>this is your great generosity towards the 
     <lb/>Catholics of Manitoba. You wanted public 
     <lb/>schools, you said, on the broad grounds of 
     <lb/>
       
       
            <pb n="143" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1894-03-20_Page_00143.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">143</fw>
            <fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">144</fw>
      
      
     the young nationality growing up in that 
     <lb/>
     province. See the result : you have turned 
     <lb/>
     the strong Protestant element of that pro<lb break="no"/>vince against the poor, struggling Catholic 
     <lb/>
     minority. You have not succeeded even in 
     <lb/>
     establishing the public schools that you pre<lb break="no"/>tended by this Bill you were going to estab<lb break="no"/>lish. You have established Protestant 
     <lb/>
     schools ; you maintain them ; and you wish 
     <lb/>
     to do the same in the North-west. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Speaker, last night the hon. Controller of 
     <lb/>
     Customs—and I just quote this as evidence 
     <lb/>
     of the spirit of the Bill and the spirit of the 
     <lb/>
    hon. member who has introduced it—referred ' 
     <lb/>to our Church as the " Romish Church ": he 
     <lb/>spoke next. of its efforts to obtain state re<lb break="no"/>cognition in the North-west ; he next said 
     <lb/>that the Archbishop had been foiled in his 
     <lb/>attempt to secure ascendancy in the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Manitoba ; and. finally, he went on 
     <lb/>to speak of the loyalty of the Orangemen, 
     <lb/>leaving the inference to be drawn that the 
     <lb/>Catholics were not loyal. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man uttered three insults in that speech : 
     <lb/>first, against the Church, by speaking of it 
     <lb/>in an offensive way as the " Romish Church." 
     <lb/>In the second place, against the Archbishop 
     <lb/>of Manitoba in saying what was untrue, that 
     <lb/>the Archbishop tried to secure ascendancy. 
     <lb/>The Archbishop did nothing of the kind. He 
     <lb/>simply asked for the restoration of those 
     <lb/>rights which, up to 1890, the Catholics of 
     <lb/>Manitoba enjoyed. Finally, against the 
     <lb/>loyalty of the Orangemen, and of the 
     <lb/>lack of loyalty on the part of others, I will 
     <lb/>say that he speaks the truth if he refers to 
     <lb/>their loyalty to persecution from the begin<lb break="no"/>ning to the end of the history of the Order. 
     <lb/>These are some of the results due to the 
     <lb/>mean spirit of hostility manifested towards 
     <lb/>the Catholics of this country by the hon. 
     <lb/>member for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy), 
     <lb/>by the Controller of Customs, a gentleman 
     <lb/>paid by the Catholics— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. Order. I think the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman should not indulge in remarks of 
     <lb/>
     that kind. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. Perhaps I should not in<lb break="no"/>dulge in the truth, Mr. Speaker. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. I think the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     had better take the advice of the Chair, and 
     <lb/>
     not indulge in the language he is using— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. Against the Controller ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>—with regard to hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. I was merely quoting the 
     <lb/>
     Controller's language from an organ of the 
     <lb/>
     Government.' 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. The hon. gentleman. in 
     <lb/>
     saying that these hon. gentlemen, were 
     <lb/>
     actuated by a mean spirit, is indulging in 
     <lb/>
     language which he, as an old member of this 
     <lb/>
     House, will, I think, admit is not in accord<lb break="no"/>ance with parliamentary usage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    
    
            <cb/>
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DEVL1">Mr. DEVLIN</persName>. Very well, Mr. Speaker, 
     <lb/>
     when the question is up again, I will refer 
     <lb/>
     to the lovely spirit, the generous, broad 
     <lb/>
     spirit, actuating these gentlemen—the magni<lb break="no"/>ficent spirit which has for its object the 
     <lb/>
     destruction of a language and the depriva<lb break="no"/>tion of a people of its rights. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TART1">Mr. TARTE</persName>. (Translation.) Mr. Speaker, 
     <lb/>
     although we are not used, at the first reading 
     <lb/>
     of a Bill, to consider its worth and bearing, 
     <lb/>
     I cannot let this opportunity pass without 
     <lb/>
     registering my protest against this measure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Hon. MEMBERS</persName>. Oh ! oh! 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TART1">Mr. TARTE</persName>. By the noise made, it will 
     <lb/>
     appear as if there were on the other side of 
     <lb/>
     the House, hon. members who wish to abolish 
     <lb/>
     i the French language immediately. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TART1">Mr. TARTE</persName>. (Translation.) I have only 
     <lb/>
     two words to say, Mr. Speaker. and 
     <lb/>
     I am determined to say them in 
     <lb/>
     French. I was just stating, when I 
     <lb/>
     was interrupted, that, although it is not 
     <lb/>
     according to the practice followed in this 
     <lb/>
     House to consider at this stage the worth 
     <lb/>
     and bearing of a Bill, I nevertheless deem it 
     <lb/>
     my duty to avail myself of this opportunity 
     <lb/>
     to record my protest against this proposed 
     <lb/>
     legislation. The hon. member for North 
     <lb/>
     Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy), whom I consider one 
     <lb/>
     of the most intelligent and enlightened mem<lb break="no"/>bers of this House, might have used, and 
     <lb/>
     might use in the future, his abilities and 
     <lb/>
     the power of his mind in a much more useful 
     <lb/>
     way for the general interests of the country. 
     <lb/>
     We will consider, later on, the merit of the 
     <lb/>
     arguments with which he brought before this 
     <lb/>
     House the child which seems so dear to him. 
     <lb/>
     At present, I am inclined to let his measure 
     <lb/>
     be introduced by simply stating : " on divi<lb break="no"/>sion," for I think the country is enormously in<lb break="no"/>terested in that the stand taken by him should 
     <lb/>
     be well and clearly defined. If we are to 
     <lb/>
     continue to sit together, French and English 
     <lb/>
     members, in this House, it is well that we 
     <lb/>
     should know once for all on what ground 
     <lb/>
     we will stand in relation of one to another. 
     <lb/>
     If we are called upon to form a nation in 
     <lb/>
     this country, it is better for us to just now 
     <lb/>
     lay the grounds on which that nation will 
     <lb/>
     stand later on. Consequently, Mr. Speaker, 
     <lb/>
     I will resume my seat after recording my 
     <lb/>
     most solemn and energetic protest against 
     <lb/>
     the measure brought in by the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for North Simcoe (Mr. McCarthy). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first 
     <lb/>
     time (on a division). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
   
            <!-- GL, 2018-10-23, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day --> 
            <!--<p>
     MESSAGE FROM HIS EXCELLENCY— 
     <lb/>
     THE ESTIMATES. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. FOSTER presented a Message from 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency the Governor General. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName> read the Message, as fol<lb break="no"/>lows :<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <p>ABERDEEN. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Governor General transmits to the House of 
     <lb/>
     Commons, Estimates of sums required for the ser<lb break="no"/>
            </p>-->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>