<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1903-09-18"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
          <date when="1903-09-18">18 September 1903</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Ninth Parliament, Third Session</title>.
          <date when="1903"/>.
          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
          <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="11691" to="11692"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-18_Page_11691.html"/>
               </item>
         
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-26">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-09-26">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-18_Page_11691">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-18_Page_11691.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="11691" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1903-09-18_Page_11691.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">11691</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> <fw type="num">11692</fw>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS</head>
         
         
            <head rendition="simple:right">
     FRIDAY, September 18, 1903 
     <lb/>
            </head>
            <p>
     The SPEAKER took the Chair at Eleven 
     <lb/>o'clock<lb/>
            </p>
   
   <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     REPRESENTATION OF THE NORTH- 
     <lb break="yes"/>WEST TERRITORIES IN THE<lb/>SENATE.<lb/>
            </head>
      
      
            <p><persName ref="pers:FITZ1">The MINISTER OF JUSTICE</persName> (Hon.
<lb/>Charles Fitzpatrick) moved the first read<lb break="no"/>ing of the Bill (No. 253) to increase the repre<lb break="no"/>sentation of the North-west Territories in
<lb/>the Senate. He said: Hon. gentlemen are
<lb/>aware that, under the British North America
<lb/>Amendment Act of 1886, it is provided
<lb/>that the parliament of Canada may, from
<lb/>time to time, make provision for the re<lb break="no"/>presentation in the Senate and House of
<lb/>Commons of Canada, or either of them, of
<lb/>any territory for the time being formed in
<lb/>the Dominion of Canada, but not included
<lb/>in any of the provinces thereof. In the
<lb/>following year a Bill was introduced, which
<lb/>appears as chapter 3 of the statute of 1887,
<lb/>by which provision was made for the re-<lb break="yes"/>
          
          
       
            <cb/>
      
      
      presentation of the North-west Territories<lb/>in the Senate by two members. Since that<lb/>time the population has materially increas<lb break="no"/>ed. The population of the organized part,<lb/>Assinibola, Alberta and Saskatchewan,<lb/>which was only 25,515 in 1881, increased<lb/>the 66,799 in 1891, and to 159,940 in 1901.<lb/>Of course, since then there has been even<lb/>a greater proportion of increase. The in<lb break="no"/>crease in the unorganized territory was<lb/>from 30,931 in 1881 to 52,709 in 1901. Tak<lb break="no"/>ing there two together and allowing for in<lb break="no"/>crease since 1901, the proportion of repre<lb break="no"/>sentation of the territories in the Senate<lb/>will be about the same as it is in Ontario.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Motion agreed to, and Bill read the first<lb/>time.<lb/>
            </p>
   
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>