<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1890-05-02" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1890-05-02">2 May 1890</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Sixth Parliament, Fourth Session</title>.
<date when="1890"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="4373" to="4374"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-02_Page_04373.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-03">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-03">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-02_Page_04373"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-02_Page_04373.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="4373" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1890-05-02_Page_04373.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4373</fw> <fw type="dateline">[MAY 2, 1890.]</fw> <fw type="num">4374</fw>

<p>[...]would be brought within the purview of the dis<lb break="no"/>abling provisions provided for by this section. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLB1">Mr. COLBY</persName>. I wish hon. members, especially <lb/>
those from the Maritime Provinces, and particularly <lb/>
the ex-Minister of this Department, to understand <lb/>
that their opinions have, as they are entitled to <lb/>
have, great weight in this matter. We desire to <lb/>
make what progress we can, and I would be glad <lb/>
to have the clauses pass this stage, with the under<lb break="no"/>standing that we will leave the Bill still in Com<lb break="no"/>mittee, if they so desire. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MITC2">Mr. MITCHELL</persName>. That is reasonable, and I am <lb/>
satisfied that, when the Council reconsider the <lb/>
    arguments <hi rendition="simple:italic">pro</hi> and <hi rendition="simple:italic">con</hi>, they will make the change <lb/>
desired. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:COLB1">Mr. COLBY</persName>. We want to make it right. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) The examination on <lb/>
which a certificate is granted is not simply in regard <lb/>
to technical knowledge, but also as to habits of life <lb/>
and character. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. As a supporter of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, I am very glad to hear that the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man intends to have this reconsidered, because I <lb/>
was trying to find some reason for defending the <lb/>
clause as it stood, but it seems to me contrary to <lb/>
true business principles. <lb/></p> 

<p>Progress reported. <lb/></p> 
</div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">FIRST READING.</head>

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName> moved first reading of Bill <lb/>
(No. 146) to amend the Acts respecting the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Territories (from the Senate). <lb/></p> 
    </div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">BANKS AND BANKING.</head> 

<p>House again resolved itself into Committee on <lb/>
Bill (No. 127) respecting banks and banking. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">(In the Committee.) <lb/></p> 

<p>0n section 86, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. The only change in this clause <lb/>
is that "fifteen" is put in place of "twenty" in <lb/>
the fourth line. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:KIRK2">Mr. KIRKPATRICK</persName>. I would suggest that <lb/>
the number of days for the banks to make their <lb/>
returns should be left twenty as it was before. <lb/>
The law has worked satisfactorily and there is no <lb/>
reason for changing it. If anything caused a delay <lb/>
of a day or two, the bank would be subject to a <lb/>
heavy penalty. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. The only reason for making it <lb/>
twenty days was in regard to British Columbia <lb/>
before the railway was opened, and that has ceased <lb/>
to be a reason. Practically the banks can put in <lb/>
their returns within ten days from the furthest <lb/>
parts of the country, and fifteen days are quite <lb/>
sufficient. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) Must the return be in <lb/>
the Finance Minister's Department before the ex<lb break="no"/>piration of the fifteen days? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. It must be sent. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI2">Mr. DAVIES</persName> (P.E.I.) There might be some <lb/>
difficulty in getting the returns in from Prince <lb/>
Edward Island, when the steamboat is unable to <lb/>
run on account of the ice. Sometimes it takes <lb/>
eight or ten days to get a letter. If it is simply <lb/>

<cb/>

that the returns are to be dispatched within that <lb/>
time, it is another thing. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:KIRK2">Mr. KIRKPATRICK</persName>. The clause says that <lb/>
the returns are to be made and sent in within that <lb/>
time. That must mean, that they are to be re<lb break="no"/>ceived by the Finance Minister. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TISD1">Mr. TISDALE</persName>. If a bank has twenty or thirty <lb/>
agencies, it practically evades the law, because it is <lb/>
given to commence the returns sooner than it ought <lb/>
in order to send the report in promptly. If banks <lb/>
are established, as I hope they will be, in the min<lb break="no"/>ing regions in the North-West Territories, where <lb/>
they will not be able to send returns with the <lb/>
promptness they do now, there will be considerable <lb/>
difficulty, and very heavy penalties are imposed <lb/>
for a violation of the statute. <lb/></p> 

<p>On section 89, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. With reference to this clause <lb/>
and the sub-sections contained in it, I have a word <lb/>
to say which will, to some extent, modify what I <lb/>
stated upon the introduction of the Bill, and upon <lb/>
its second reading. There were two things included <lb/>
in section 89. The first part of the section, and a <lb/>
vital part, was that which provided for publicity <lb/>
being given to unclaimed dividends and balances <lb/>
in the bank. The second part was to provide that <lb/>
these unclaimed dividends and balances, or <lb/>
deposits, should, after a certain time, revert to <lb/>
the Government and be held by them for the <lb/>
public uses of the country. It will be remembered <lb/>
that I stated that we proposed to hold by this <lb/>
clause in its essence, but I foreshadowed at the <lb/>
time that certain amendments might be made. <lb/>
The change which I propose to ask the Committee <lb/>
to make in that is this: That we shall hold by the <lb/>
principle embodied in the first part of this <lb/>
section, and that we shall give up to a very <lb/>
large degree the principle that we contended <lb/>
for in the second part. With regard to the <lb/>
unclaimed dividends and balances in the hands <lb/>
of the bank after a certain period returns shall <lb/>
be made of them to the Minister of Finance <lb/>
and Receiver General; but these balances shall <lb/>
remain in the hands of the banks with the pub<lb break="no"/>licity given by the return enabling those who <lb/>
have a right to claim them to know that they are <lb/>
there, and to proceed to claim them and make <lb/>
what disposition they please with regard to them, <lb/>
saving that, with reference to banks which become <lb/>
insolvent, I shall have a clause to submit to the <lb/>
Committee which will provide that unclaimed <lb/>
dividends and balances in these respects shall re<lb break="no"/>vert to the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MITC2">Mr. MITCHELL</persName>. Revert to the Government <lb/>
for what purposes? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. For the very same purposes as we <lb/>
proposed that the whole of them should so revert, <lb/>
always subject, of course, to the claims of indivi<lb break="no"/>duals who may have a right to them. What I <lb/>
propose in the place of the 89th section, is this: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>1. The banks shall, within twenty days after the close <lb/>
of each calendar year, transmit or deliver to the Minister <lb/>
of Finance and Receiver General, to be laid by him <lb/>
before Parliament, a return of all dividends which have <lb/>
remained unpaid for more than five years, and also of <lb/>
all amounts or balances in respect of which no transac<lb break="no"/>tions have taken place, or upon which no interest has <lb/>
been paid during the five years prior to the date of such <lb/>
statement; provided always, that in cases of moneys <lb/>
deposited for a fixed period, the period of five years, <lb/>
above referred to, shall be reckoned from the date of the <lb/>
termination of such fixed period. <lb/></p>
</quote>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>