<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1905-03-10" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1905-03-10">10 March 1905</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:TAEK1">Sarah Taekema</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

         
          
         
         
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Tenth Parliament, First Session</title>.
                    
                  

           <date when="1905"/>.  
          

                   <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>S.E. Dawson, Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="2263" to="2278"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2263.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2265.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2267.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2269.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2271.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2273.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2275.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2277.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-02-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="sarahtaekema">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-08">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2263">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2263.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2265">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2265.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2267">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2267.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2269">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2269.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2271">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2271.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2273">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2273.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2275">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2275.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2277">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2277.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="2263" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2263.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">2263</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> 

            <p>[...] turn carried some time ago concerning Port 
     <lb/>
     Arthur and Fort William harbours, has not, 
     <lb/>
     to my knowledge, been laid on the table yet. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:HYMA1">Mr. HYMAN</persName>. When the motion for the <lb/> return reached the
               department, I gave in<lb break="no"/>structions to the officers to facilitate its
               <lb/> preparation in every way. I will make <lb/> special inquiry again. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. I would like to draw <lb/> the attention of
               the Minister of Marine and <lb/> Fisheries (Mr. Préfontaine) to the fact that <lb/>
               out of some twenty returns ordered from <lb/> his department—two of them having been
               <lb/> ordered very recently and the others on dif<lb break="no"/>ferent dates between
               the 25th of January <lb/> and the 27th of February—only seven have <lb/> been brought
               down, leaving eleven that I <lb/> think ought to have been brought down ere <lb/>
               this. It is desirable that we should have <lb/> them before the hon. gentleman's
               estimates <lb/> are more fully discussed. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:PREF1">Hon. RAYMOND PREFONTAINE</persName> (Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Marine and
               Fisheries). So many of <lb/> these returns were asked from the depart<lb break="no"/>ment that my officers, although they have <lb/> been working at them diligently,
               have not <lb/> yet been able to prepare them all ; but I will <lb/> bring them down
               as fast as I can get them <lb/> prepared. <lb/>
            </p>
   <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SUPPLY-PROVINCIAL GOVERNMENT 
     <lb/>
     IN THE NORTHWEST TERRITORIES. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FIEL1">Hon. W. S. FIELDING</persName> (Minister of Fin<lb break="no"/>ance)
                  moved that the House go into com<lb break="no"/>mittee of Supply. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName> (Carleton, Ont.). Mr. <lb/> Speaker, before
                  you leave the chair, I take <lb/> the opportunity of pressing once more upon <lb/>
                  the attention of the right hon. gentleman <lb/> (Sir Wilfrid Laurier) the matters
                  which I <lb/> took occasion to mention yesterday. What <lb/> he said in reply to
                  my inquiry at that time <lb/> was very excellent in its way. He cited <lb/>
                  constitutional authorities as to the course <lb/> which should be adopted upon the
                  formation <lb/> of a government and he read certain quota<lb break="no"/>tions
                  from a great authority on that ques<lb break="no"/>tion, but none of his remarks
                  touched at all <lb/> or were even relevant to the real ques<lb break="no"/>tion
                  which I asked. It seems to me that in <lb/> a matter of this kind the inquiry is
                  one <lb/> worthy of some attention by the right hon. <lb/> Prime Minister when it
                  is made in a respect<lb break="no"/>ful and serious way, as my inquiry was <lb/>
                  intended to be. The circumstances are very <lb/> unusual. A measure of the
                  greatest possible <lb/> importance not only to the Territories of the <lb/>
                  Northwest which are now being constituted <lb/> into provinces, but to the country
                  as a <lb/> whole, is brought to the attention of parlia<lb break="no"/>ment and
                  the right hon. Prime Minister <lb/> introduces that measure. When he places <lb/>
                  that measure before the House he says to <lb/> the House as emphatically as if he
                  had <lb/> declared it in express words that the mea<lb break="no"/>sure had been
                  submitted to, had been con<lb break="no"/><cb/>
     <fw rendition="simple:right" type="num">2264</fw>sidered by and had met with the
                  approval <lb/> of every one of his colleagues. That is <lb/> the situation as I
                  understand it. I have <lb/> yet to be corrected in that apprehension <lb/> of my
                  right hon. friend's conduct in intro<lb break="no"/>ducing this Bill. Well,
                  afterwards it trans<lb break="no"/>pires that at least one member of the ad<lb break="no"/>ministration had not considered, and more <lb/> than that, had not
                  even seen the measure <lb/> which was brought down by the Prime <lb/> Minister,
                  and it is an open secret that an<lb break="no"/>other member of the
                  administration, then on <lb/> his way from Europe and expected to arrive <lb/> in
                  Ottawa within a few days, was not made <lb/> acquainted with the provisions of the
                     mea<lb break="no"/>sure as far as we are aware. In making that <lb/> statement,
                  I am, of course, not making it <lb/> of my own personal knowledge, and if I <lb/>
                  am wrong in my conjecture in that regard <lb/> I shall be glad to be corrected.
                  But the <lb/> importance of the situation is this, that the <lb/> two hon.
                  gentlemen to whom I have refer<lb break="no"/>red were gentleman who had allied
                     them<lb break="no"/>selves with the right hon. gentleman in <lb/> 1895 and 1896
                  in regard to a very similar <lb/> question. The hon. ex-Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior (Mr. Sifton), in 1895 and in 1896, <lb/> used language in
                  regard to one, of the ques<lb break="no"/>tions embraced in this measure, lan<lb break="no"/>guage which I have under my hand, but <lb/> which I shall not read
                  to the House to-day <lb/> because the views of the hon. gentleman are <lb/> pretty
                  well known. His language was not <lb/> only of a pronounced. but, in some
                  respects, <lb/> even of a violent character and it would do <lb/> no good to place
                  it before the House to-day. <lb/> There is no dispute and there never has <lb/>
                  been any dispute as to the attitude of the <lb/> hon. ex-Minister of the Interior
                  in that re<lb break="no"/>gard. Yet, he is one of the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men who was not made acquainted with <lb/> the intentions of the government in
                     bring<lb break="no"/>ing down this measure. But, there is an<lb break="no"/>other hon. gentleman, the hon. Minister of <lb/> Finance, to whom I have already
                  referred, <lb/> and in so far as we can gauge the circum<lb break="no"/>stances
                  and in so far as we can learn from <lb/> the silence of the administration after
                  the <lb/> statement has been made across the floor of <lb/> the House, he was also
                  absolutely ignorant <lb/> of the provisions of the Bill which the right <lb/> hon.
                  Prime Minister introduced within two or <lb/> three days of the date when that
                  hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman expected to return. Now, I have <lb/> referred to
                  the opinions of the hon. ex- <lb break="yes"/> Minister of the Interior. I would
                  like to add <lb/> also that the opinions of the hon. Minister <lb/> of Finance,
                  acting as an ally, as the chief <lb/> of my right hon. friend in the campaign made
                  <lb/> in Nova Scotia in 1896, although not ex<lb break="no"/>pressed perhaps in so
                  violent a way as <lb/> those to which I have just referred of the <lb/> hon.
                  ex-Minister of the Interior, neverthe<lb break="no"/>less, are of a very
                  pronounced character. <lb/> My hon. friend the Minister of Finance con<lb break="no"/>ducted a very able campaign in support of <lb/> my right hon.
                  friend in 1896 in the province <lb/> of Nova Scotia. He was regarded as the <lb/>
                  leader of the Liberal ranks in that province <lb/>
               </p>
            <pb n="2265" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2265.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">2265</fw> <fw type="dateline">MARCH 10, 1905</fw> 
     <lb/>
            <p>at that time and the exertions which he then 
     <lb/>
     put forth met with their fitting reward in 
     <lb/>
     the tender to him of the position which he 
     <lb/>
     now holds. This hon. gentleman was acting 
     <lb/>
     as the ally and, I suppose. under the direc<lb break="no"/>tion of the right hon. gentleman in the east 
     <lb/>
     as was the hon. member for Brandon in 
     <lb/>
     the west of Canada. He pronounced him<lb break="no"/>self in no equivocal terms upon this ques<lb break="no"/>tion. It was thought by his friends in Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia that the speech which he delivered 
     <lb/>
     at Windsor in the county of Hants on the 
     <lb/>
     6th of March, I think it was, 1896, was the 
     <lb/>
     ablest deliverance made in that province in 
     <lb/>
     support of the policy of the Liberal 
     <lb/>
     party at that time, and was perhaps 
     <lb/>
     the best exposition of their policy that 
     <lb/>
     had been made by any man in Canada 
     <lb/>
     up to that time. I will quote a few words 
     <lb/>
     not for the purpose of criticising them, not 
     <lb/>
     for the purpose of assenting to them, but 
     <lb/>
     s'mply to support my position that my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend had very pronounced views to the 
     <lb/>
     knowledge of the Prime Minister on this 
     <lb/>
     question which makes it all the more strange 
     <lb/>
     that the provisions of this Bill should have 
     <lb/>
     been withheld from him, if, as a matter of 
     <lb/>
     fact, they were so withheld. Said the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman on that occasion to which I have 
     <lb/>
     referred : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Why should we not believe that Manitoba will 
     <lb/>
     be reasonable in this matter ? The Manitobans 
     <lb/>
     are not African savages. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>I will venture the statement that the true 
     <lb/>
     interests of the Roman Catholic citizens of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba will be better advanced by the policy 
     <lb/>
     of conciliation than by the policy of coercion. 
     <lb/>
     This Remedial Bill which the government are 
     <lb/>
     trying to enforce upon an unwilling parliament, 
     <lb/>
     even it it should pass, cannot settle the ques<lb break="no"/>tion. it would be an attack on provincial 
     <lb/>
     rights... If Roman Catholics are ever to 
     <lb/>
     obtain a solution of this question which is 
     <lb/>
     worth having they must obtain it through the 
     <lb/>
     good will of the majority of the people of the 
     <lb/>
     province to which they belong. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>Further on in the same speech he said : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>I ask the people of Hants county and the 
     <lb/>
     people of Nova Scotia to stand by the principle 
     <lb/>
     of free schools in the case of Manitoba just as 
     <lb/>
     they would stand by it in their own province. 
     <lb/>
     We in Nova Scotia know the value of 
     <lb/>
     a system of free public schools. We have 
     <lb/>
     shown in the past that while we may differ on 
     <lb/>
     many questions We are practically a unit in 
     <lb/>
     support of that system. If the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion authorities should attempt to interfere with 
     <lb/>
     our school system, if they should attempt to 
     <lb/>
     impose upon this province a system which they 
     <lb/>
     are trying to force upon Manitoba, we would 
     <lb/>
     expect to have the sympathy of the friends of 
     <lb/>
     free schools elsewhere, and we would ex<lb break="no"/>:pect the people of the western provinces to 
     <lb/>
     give us their sympathy and support in such a 
     <lb/>
     condition. Let us to-day give them our hearty 
     <lb/>
     sympathy and support in the struggle until we 
     <lb/>
     find that they are not amenable to reason. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>Further on after giving credit to Sir 
     <lb/>
     Charles Tupper for establishing public 
     <lb/>
     schools in Nova Scotia, he continues: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
            <cb/>
     <fw rendition="simple:right" type="num">2266</fw>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
     What can we say of the position of that gen<lb break="no"/>tleman to-day who instead of standing up as the 
     <lb/>
     champion of a free school system and resisting 
     <lb/>
     those who attack it scrambles into parliament 
     <lb/>
     through the unfair influence of the Roman 
     <lb/>
     Catholic pupils of the county of Cape Breton, 
     <lb/>
     and is now devoting the evening of his life to 
     <lb/>
     the work of destroying the free school system 
     <lb/>
     of Manitoba, and forcing upon that province a 
     <lb/>
     system which he would not dare to attempt to 
     <lb/>
     force upon the province of Nova Scotia. 
     <lb/>
            </quote>
   
            <p>Further on in a letter to the 'Casket' 
     <lb/>
     newspaper published in Antigonish he said : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>The uproar is upon us, already the blaze of 
     <lb/>
     religious strife has been kindled and is being 
     <lb/>
     vigorously fanned every day by the efforts to 
     <lb/>
     coerce the province of Manitoba. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>In the speech at Windsor to which I have 
     <lb/>
     just now referred he used this further 
     <lb/>
     language : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>For twenty years the Roman Catholic min<lb break="no"/>ority thus had the privilege of a separate 
     <lb/>
     school system. The result of that system proved 
     <lb/>
     exceedingly unsatisfactory to the people of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba. Ample evidence has been ad<lb break="no"/>duced to prove that the separate schools were 
     <lb/>
     not efficient schools. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>Then, one more passage from his speech 
     <lb/>
     which is of some importance at the present 
     <lb/>
     juncture as embodying his views: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>I believe that the people of Manitoba it let 
     <lb/>
     alone will settle this question for themselves. 
     <lb/>
     Why should we not believe this? We know 
     <lb/>
     from our own experience in the maritime pro<lb break="no"/>vinces that it has been found possible to main<lb break="no"/>tain a free school system and to administer it 
     <lb/>
     so as to make it acceptable to the people of 
     <lb/>
     every class and creed. We hear no complaint 
     <lb/>
     of the Nova Scotia School Law. The Manitoba 
     <lb/>
     school system is substantially the same as 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
            <p>My object in quoting this language of the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Finance is not to criticise or to 
     <lb/>
     discuss it; it is simply to Show that when 
     <lb/>
     the right hon. gentleman accepted the aid 
     <lb/>
     and support of the Minister of Finance 
     <lb/>
     tHon. Mr. Fielding) and when he invited 
     <lb/>
     him to enter his cabinet, he knew that the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman had used that language, and 
     <lb/>
     had made these speeches in Nova Scotia. 
     <lb/>
     Thus, the right hon. gentleman (Sir Wilfrid 
     <lb/>
     Laurier) had full knowledge of the views 
     <lb/>
     which the Minister of Finance entertained 
     <lb/>
     in regard to certain provisions similar to 
     <lb/>
     those in the Bill now before parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>I wish to once more call the attention of 
     <lb/>
     the right hon. gentleman (Sir Wilfrid 
     <lb/>
     Laurier) to the fact that upon the eve of 
     <lb/>
     the return to Ottawa of the ex-Minister of 
     <lb/>
     the Interior (Hon. Clifford Sifton) and of the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Finance (Hon. W. S. Fielding) 
     <lb/>
     he has seen fit to introduce to parlia<lb break="no"/>ment a Bill in such manner that parlia<lb break="no"/>ment had every reason to believe, was 
     <lb/>
     bound to believe, and indeed every one of us 
     <lb/>
     did believe, that the provisions of that 
     <lb/>
     Bill had received the assent of every member 
     <lb/>
     of the administration. Under the circum<lb break="no"/>stances, that was undoubtedly a grave de<lb break="no"/>parture from constitutional usage. I do not 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="2267" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2267.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2267</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS</fw> 
          
     know of any modern precedent for conduct 
     <lb/>
     of that kind with regard to a measure of 
     <lb/>
     any importance, and I think it my duty 
     <lb/>
     to once more inquire of the right hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman what was the overmastering reason 
     <lb/>
     which led him under these circumstances 
     <lb/>
     to introduce that Bill to this parliament 
     <lb/>
     without giving to the people of this coun<lb break="no"/>try, and especially to this House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons, the information that two members 
     <lb/>
     of the cabinet, members who above all 
     <lb/>
     others, it seems to me, should have been 
     <lb/>
     consulted with regard to the provisions of 
     <lb/>
     this measure, had not even had it submitted 
     <lb/>
     to them, were not even consulted with re<lb break="no"/>gard to it, had not even seen it or read it. 
     <lb/>
     There must be some explanation for so ex<lb break="no"/>traordinary an act. The right hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man (Sir Wilfrid Laurier) has not vouch<lb break="no"/>safed any. I do not want to make explan<lb break="no"/>ations for him. I do not want to suggest 
     <lb/>
     any explanations. Explanations are being 
     <lb/>
     suggested throughout the country, and I 
     <lb/>
     would think that it is not only due to this 
     <lb/>
     House and to the country, but due to the 
     <lb/>
     right hon. gentleman himself that he should. 
     <lb/>
     without any further delay, without any 
     <lb/>
     further attempt to avoid the issue, inform 
     <lb/>
     the House as to the real circumstances un<lb break="no"/>der which he took this step in defiance of 
     <lb/>
     all unconstitutional usage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>There is one more question which I would 
     <lb/>
     again like to ask the right hon. gentleman, 
     <lb/>
     and I think that in doing so I am not trans<lb break="no"/>gressing my duty. I ask it in the same 
     
     <lb/>
     respectful way and for the purpose of in<lb break="no"/>formation; it is this: The right hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman in his speech introducing this Bill 
     <lb/>
     referred to the aid in its preparation which 
     <lb/>
     the government had received from the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Executive Council of the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest Territories. What I would 
     <lb/>
     like to know is whether or not the 
     <lb/>
     educational clauses of this Bill were 
     <lb/>
     submitted to, were fully discussed with, 
     <lb/>
     and met with the appropriation of mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Executive Council of the North<lb break="no"/>west Territories. In the last place, I would 
     <lb/>
     like to ask the right hon. gentleman a ques<lb break="no"/>tion which I have not already asked but 
     <lb/>
     which seems to me to be very pertinent in 
     <lb/>
     view of his reply of yesterday.. How long 
     <lb/>
     does he propose to carry on the affairs 
     <lb/>
     of the country without filling the va<lb break="no"/>cant portfolio of the Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior? One would suppose that when a 
     <lb/>
     measure of the importance of that which 
     <lb/>
     has been proposed to parliament, a measure 
     <lb/>
     especially affecting the Northwest Terri<lb break="no"/>tories of Canada, has been introduced and 
     <lb/>
     is about to be discussed in parliament, that 
     <lb/>
     we should have the advantage of the ex<lb break="no"/>perience and knowledge of some gentleman 
     <lb/>
     of the Northwest Territories, occupying a 
     <lb/>
     position in the administration, or, at all 
     <lb/>
     events that we should have the benefit 
     <lb/>
     of the advice and experience and knowl<lb break="no"/>edge of some gentleman filling the 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
     <fw rendition="simple:right" type="num">2268</fw>
       
     portfolio of the Department of the 
     <lb/>
     Interior, appointed to that portfolio for 
     <lb/>
     the very reason that he is well qualified to 
     <lb/>
     fill it. These three questions I venture to 
     <lb/>
     again bring to the attention of my right 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend, and I trust that he will be 
     <lb/>
     pleased to give to the House, at my request, 
     <lb/>
     that full and sufficient information on the 
     <lb/>
     subject to which I think the House is en<lb break="no"/>titled. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Rt. Hon. Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName> (Prime <lb/> Minister). My hon.
                  friend (Mr. R. L. Bor<lb break="no"/>den) has to-day asked one question which
                  <lb/> he has not previously put and as to which <lb/> I am quite ready to give all
                  the information <lb/> I have at present. My hon. friend desires <lb/> to know how
                  long the vacancy in the port<lb break="no"/>folio of the Minister of the Interior
                  will be <lb/> left unfilled. I have only to submit to my <lb/> hon. friend and to
                  the House that there has <lb/> been no undue delay in filling it. The vacancy
                  <lb/> occurred only ten days ago, and I do not <lb/> think it could be expected
                  that in so short <lb/> a time as that the government could come <lb/> to a
                  conclusion as to whom they should <lb/> call to fill such an important office. I
                  hope <lb/> before long I shall be able to give to my <lb/> hon. friend the
                  opportunity to give his as<lb break="no"/>sent to the appointment we shall make. I
                  <lb/> do not know whether he will respond to the <lb/> invitation, but at all
                  events we shall cer<lb break="no"/>tainly afford it to him. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>With regard to the other two questions I 
     <lb/>
     do not think that I am warranted in giving 
     <lb/>
     more information to my hon. friend than I 
     <lb/>
     have already given. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. That is none. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. That is not <lb/> much; but I would
                  submit that strictly <lb/> speaking my hon. friend is entitled to none <lb/> at
                  all. The conferences which took place be<lb break="no"/>tween the government and
                  the representa<lb break="no"/>tives of the Northwest Territorial govern<lb break="no"/>ment were carried on confidentially, and I <lb/> do not know
                  whether I have any authority <lb/> to give any information about them to the <lb/>
                  House; no record has been kept of this in<lb break="no"/>formation; the
                  conferences have been ab<lb break="no"/>solutely confidential. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>With regard to the other question, which 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend has now put for the third 
     <lb/>
     time. I am sorry to say my mind has not 
     <lb/>
     changed. I think, with all due respect to 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend and to the position he oc<lb break="no"/>cupies, and to this House, that I have given 
     <lb/>
     all the information the House was entitled 
     <lb/>
     to. I can see plainly that my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     is shaping his course carefully; he is going 
     <lb/>
     ahead bit by bit, he is taking no plunge, 
     <lb/>
     but every day we can see a little more 
     <lb/>
     where we are finally to be led. Yesterday 
     <lb/>
     we could not see where he was to place 
     <lb/>
     his batteries, but today we can see 
     <lb/>
     where they are to be placed. He endea<lb break="no"/>voured to show that there is a difference 
     <lb/>
     between the position occupied by two mem<lb break="no"/><pb n="2269" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2269.jpg"/><fw type="num">2269</fw><fw type="dateline">MARCH 10, 1905</fw>bers of the Liberal party and by the Lib<lb break="no"/>eral party itself to-day and the position oc<lb break="no"/>cupied by that party in 1896. My hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend (Mr. R. L. Borden) did my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend the Minister of Finance (Hon. W. S. 
     <lb/>
     Fielding) the honour of quoting him. I am 
     <lb/>
     not at all jealous of that honour which he 
     <lb/>
     has paid to my hon. friend the Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Finance. I compliment the minister upon 
     <lb/>
     it; but he might have quoted some of my 
     <lb/>
     speeches on the same question. I took some 
     <lb/>
     part in that discussion. I intend to take 
     <lb/>
     some part in the present discussion. My 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend is re—echoing the attempts that 
     <lb/>
     have been made in the press to show that 
     <lb/>
     there has been a great change from the posi<lb break="no"/>tion taken by the Liberal party in 1896 in 
     <lb/>
     the position taken by them in 1905. Now 
     <lb/>
     we shall have an opportunity by and by of 
     <lb/>
     discussing that question; when we come to 
     <lb/>
     the second reading of the Bill I will en<lb break="no"/>deavour to discuss the question with my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend, and we shall discuss it on both 
     <lb/>
     sides of the House. I do not admit that 
     <lb/>
     there has been any departure at all in the 
     <lb/>
     conduct of the Liberal party between 1896 
     <lb/>
     and 1905; but I am sorry to say that hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen on the opposite side are always 
     <lb/>
     in the wrong. They never can interpret the 
     <lb/>
     constitution as it is. In 1896, the position 
     <lb/>
     which we took and maintained before the 
     <lb/>
     country was that it was not right for the 
     <lb/>
     federal parliament to try to impose on the 
     <lb/>
     province of Manitoba a system of schools 
     <lb/>
     which the province of Manitoba had re<lb break="no"/>jected, acting within the plenary exercise 
     <lb/>
     of its powers. If there had been a system 
     <lb/>
     of schools in the province of Manitoba in 
     <lb/>
     1870, when it was admitted to confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. then, Sir, the minority would have 
     <lb/>
     been entitled to those schools by the judg<lb break="no"/>ment of the courts; but the courts decided 
     <lb/>
     that there had been no such system of 
     <lb/>
     schools. and therefore the powers of the 
     <lb/>
     province of Manitoba were not in any way 
     <lb/>
     curtailed. There is a difference. therefore, 
     <lb/>
     in the position of Manitoba in 1870, as ex<lb break="no"/>posed in 1896, and the position which we 
     <lb/>
     are confronted with at the present time. 
     <lb/>
     But I will not discuss this question with 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend to-day—I do not think the 
     <lb/>
     time is opportune. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:BORD2">Mr. R. L. BORDEN</persName>. I did not discuss it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:LAUR5">Sir WILFRID LAURIER</persName>. In my estima<lb break="no"/>tion my hon.
                  friend came very near discuss<lb break="no"/>ing it. He was very guarded, but
                  introduced <lb/> it in a gentle way, just to create the impres<lb break="no"/>sion
                  that there was a great difference be<lb break="no"/>tween the position taken by
                  the Liberal <lb/> party in 1896 and its position in 1905. My <lb/> hon. friend
                  understands his business too <lb/> well to have introduced it so bluntly as to
                  <lb/> state it in that way, but he led to a conclu<lb break="no"/>sion which was
                  inevitable. I do not think <lb/> the present is the time to discuss that ques<lb break="no"/>tion. but I assure my hon. friend that we <lb/>
                  <cb/>
     <fw rendition="simple:right" type="num">2270</fw> shall take the opportunity of doing so at <lb/> the proper time and on the
                  proper occasion. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Hon. GEO. E. FOSTER</persName> (North Toronto). <lb/> Mr. Speaker, it
                  was a candid admission of <lb/> my right hon. friend when he confessed <lb/> that
                  he had not given much information to <lb/> the hon. leader of the opposition in
                  response <lb/> to his question of yesterday and of to-day. <lb/> It was a charming
                  bit of persiflage that the <lb/> right hon. gentleman made an exhibition <lb/> of
                  in those few words—airy, light, well- <lb break="yes"/> chosen, skimming all
                  around, but avoiding <lb/> carefully any expression which would go <lb/> to shed
                  light upon the grave and serious <lb/> questions which my hon. friend beside me
                  <lb/> had raised. Now, I do not intend to be <lb/> led away by this little
                  diversion into a dis<lb break="no"/>cussion of matters which are not at pres<lb break="no"/>ent before the House. I want to reiterate, <lb/> in the first
                  place, the position taken by the <lb/> hon. leader of the opposition. He quoted
                  <lb/> from statements that had been made by the <lb/> Minister of Finance, and
                  could have quoted <lb/> from statements which had been made by <lb/> the late
                  Minister of the Interior, to show to <lb/> the right hon. the premier that he knew
                  <lb/> thoroughly well, when these hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men were in his
                  cabinet, and when just <lb/> lately he introduced his Bill for discussion <lb/> in
                  his cabinet, that these hon. gentlemen <lb/> had well-known and pronounced views
                  with <lb/> reference to the question of education as it <lb/> would develop in
                  these new provinces. That <lb/> is the only purpose my hon. friend had in <lb/>
                  View. The quotations which he made drove <lb/> that fact fairly well home, so that
                  the right <lb/> hon. gentleman could not say that he did <lb/> not know, in the
                  absence of these two <lb/> gentlemen, that their opinions had been <lb/> firmly
                  formed and plainly expressed. The <lb/> startling thing about it was this—and it
                  was <lb/> not explained away by all the charming <lb/> discursiveness of my hon.
                  friend yesterday. <lb/> The question is: what is the constitutional <lb/> practice
                  when a Bill, having been discussed <lb/> in the cabinet and agreed to or supposed
                  <lb/> to be agreed to there, is launched upon the <lb/> House as the utterance of
                  the government <lb/> as a whole ? That is the question, and the <lb/> startling
                  thing about it is that the premier <lb/> introduced a Bill for discussion in his
                     cabi<lb break="no"/>net, knowing the views of these two gentle<lb break="no"/>men in their absence, and with a haste that <lb/> has not yet been explained.
                  Engaged as it <lb/> were, in a race for a goal with the Minister <lb/> of Finance
                  and the Minister of the Interior, <lb/> he beat them by about two days and twelve
                  <lb/> hours—he got in ahead, and he launched <lb/> his Bill. Now, the country and
                  this <lb/> House had no warrant for believing any<lb break="no"/>thing else than
                  that that Bill in its entirety <lb/> had been assented to and had the cordial
                  <lb/> agreement of every member of the cabinet. <lb/> That is the point the
                  country heeds. and <lb/> that is the point my hon. friend the leader <lb/> of the
                  opposition makes. What has happened <lb/> in this case is. I believe,
                  unprecedented in <lb/> the history of this parliament, and it is a <lb/>
                  <pb n="2271" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2271.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">2271</fw><fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
                  matter not of curiosity, but of right, that <lb/> both this House and the country
                  should <lb/> know why this was and what it meant. <lb/> Now, let me say a word or
                  two with refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the changed methods of my right <lb/> hon.
                  friend. Take, for instance, the British <lb/> North America Act. The clauses in it
                  with <lb/> reference to education were framed to do <lb/> what? To give legal
                  effect to an agreement <lb/> between thoroughly constituted bodies who <lb/> under
                  that agreement went into the pact of <lb/> confederation. Each had a House with
                  <lb/> elected representatives from the people en<lb break="no"/>joying all the
                  powers of a representative <lb/> assembly. Those provinces came together <lb/> as
                  independent constituents, and they (did <lb/> not attempt legislation until they
                  had made <lb/> their agreement and asked that it be em<lb break="no"/>bodied in an
                  enactment. Come to the case <lb/> of the Manitoba Act. In Manitoba there was <lb/>
                  no representative body such as an as<lb break="no"/>sembly ; but how carefully the
                  men of that <lb/> time were minded to consult the con<lb break="no"/>stituent
                  elements of that northwest coun<lb break="no"/>try. Delegates were sent ; the men
                  <lb/>were assembled; their views were got; <lb/>the views were sent here ; the
                  views <lb/>were communicated to the British govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and it was
                  upon that tacit agreement <lb/>or real agreement as to the wants and wishes
                  <lb/>of the constituent elements of Manitoba <lb/>that the legislation was based
                  which be<lb break="no"/>came fixed in law. How different has been <lb/>the action
                  of the right hon. gentleman in this <lb/>matter. Whom has he consulted? Why, I
                  <lb/>think it is stated in his own speech that <lb/>there were some reasons why he
                  should not <lb/>have granted autonomy two years ago or <lb/>one year ago, and what
                  are the reasons he <lb/>gave? <lb/>
               </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>That as we were on the eve of a general elec<lb break="no"/>tion, the time and occasion would be more pro<lb break="no"/>pitious and more fitting after the general elec<lb break="no"/>tion when the Territories would have the bene<lb break="no"/>fit on this floor of a larger representation. 
     <lb/>
     These views were generally accepted. The elec<lb break="no"/>tions have taken place and immediately after 
     <lb/>
     the elections, or as soon as was practicable 
     <lb/>
     thereafter, We invited the executive of the 
     <lb/>
     Northwest Territories to send delegates here 
     <lb/>
     to confer with us upon the measure which was 
     <lb/>
     to be introduced so as to admit them into the 
     <lb/>
     confederation. We have had the benefit of 
     <lb/>
     the presence of Mr. Haultain, the premier of 
     <lb/>
     the Northwest Territories, and Mr. Bulyea, one 
     <lb/>
     of his colleagues, and we have had the advant<lb break="no"/>age of several conferences with them. We have 
     <lb/>
     had the advantage also of the presence and ad<lb break="no"/>vice of several of the members from the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>Now, in profession, what does this mean? 
     <lb/>
     it means that before this Bill was agreed 
     <lb/>
     upon and given to the House, the right 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman wanted to have all the 
     <lb/>
     representative opinion he could possibly 
     <lb/>
     get from the west. Did he consult it? 
     <lb/>
     There are 500,000 people living in those 
     <lb/>
     two provinces. according to the state<lb break="no"/>ment of my right hon, friend. Isit on record 
     <lb/>

            <cb/>
     <fw rendition="simple:right" type="num">2272</fw>
      
     that he consulted those people before 
     <lb/>
     introducing this Bill? There were a 
     <lb/>
     certain number of old and new represent<lb break="no"/>atives from the Northwest present in this 
     <lb/>
     House. Did the right hon. gentleman con<lb break="no"/>sult them with reference to this clause ? If 
     <lb/>
     he did, did they approve of this clause ? If 
     <lb/>
     they did approve of it, why all this bother 
     <lb/>
     since ? Why has the right hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     been held up? The right hon. gentleman also 
     <lb/>
     had an accredited representative of That 
     <lb/>
     Northwest country in the person of the 
     <lb/>
     Minister of the Interior, a gentleman who 
     <lb/>
     had travelled the west, who knew the west, 
     <lb/>
     who, before and from his first entry into 
     <lb/>
     this parliament had taken a very deep in<lb break="no"/>terest in this very subject. Did my right 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend consult him ? If so. how comes 
     <lb/>
     it that in a race for time, after he had beat<lb break="no"/>en his Minister of the Interior by a few 
     <lb/>
     hours, that minister rose in his place in 
     <lb/>
     parliament and said to his chief: I never 
     <lb/>
     saw that clause until I read it after I came 
     <lb/>
     here ? Yet if there was any note in the 
     <lb/>
     right hon. gentleman's voice in 1895 and 
     <lb/>
     1896, it was this. He will find it embalmed 
     <lb/>
     in 'Hansard,' in the pages of his press, in 
     <lb/>
     the hearts of his admirers, in quotations 
     <lb/>
     everywhere. What was it? Translated in<lb break="no"/>to a few English words, it was this and 
     <lb/>
     nothing more : I want my people in Mani<lb break="no"/>toba to have separate schools, but I want 
     <lb/>
     them to have those schools by the voice of 
     <lb/>
     Manitoba itself. I desire to see these pri<lb break="no"/>vileges retained for them, but I desire still 
     <lb/>
     more not to violate provincial rights. That 
     <lb/>
     was his note. There was none more domi<lb break="no"/>nant. How has he changed ? Today he is 
     <lb/>
     an autocrat. To-day he rushes the Bill. To<lb break="no"/>day he rushes the members of his cabinet, 
     <lb/>
     the representatives from the Northwest, and 
     <lb/>
     the representative council from the North<lb break="no"/>west for he has not been able to state that 
     <lb/>
     he did confer with that council—a repre<lb break="no"/>sentative body if there ever was any—and 
     <lb/>
     that it ever gave its assent to this clause. 
     <lb/>
     In all these cases the old spirit has depart<lb break="no"/>ed, the old method has been laid aside, and 
     <lb/>
     today we have in their stead the work of 
     <lb/>
     the autocrat, caring nothing for his Minis<lb break="no"/>ter of the Interior, caring nothing for his 
     <lb/>
     Minister of Finance, caring nothing for the 
     <lb/>
     representatives from the west, caring noth<lb break="no"/>ing and consulting in no way the 500,000 
     <lb/>
     people for whom we are legislating. That 
     <lb/>
     is a change to which I call the attention of 
     <lb/>
     this House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>There is another peculiar circumstance in 
     <lb/>
     this connection. On the introduction of a 
     <lb/>
     Bill, the usual method followed is simply 
     <lb/>
     to explain it, but when my right hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     was taxed with going beyond an explana<lb break="no"/>tion, he defended himself by saying that he 
     <lb/>
     did give and only intended to give what was 
     <lb/>
     a full explanation of the Bill. What is the 
     <lb/>
     purpose of having a Bill explained, espe<lb break="no"/>cially an important Bill of this kind, on its 
     <lb/>
     introduction? It is that the House and 
     <lb/>
     the country may become seized with its sa<lb break="no"/><pb n="2273" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2273.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2273</fw> <fw type="dateline">MARCH 10, 1905</fw> ient points so that before they are called 
     <lb/>
     upon to make up their minds to it, they may 
     <lb/>
     have the information necessary. I submit 
     <lb/>
     that it was not a lucid explanation of the 
     <lb/>
    Bill which my right hon. friend gave but an 
     <lb/>impassioned argument in its behalf. On the 
     <lb/>one hand he professed the greatest concern 
     <lb/>that no old cries should be renewed, that 
     <lb/>no old issues should be called up, that the 
     <lb/>demon of discord, which had been laid in 
     <lb/>1896, should not be roused again at this 
     <lb/>time, but I submit that the argument he 
     <lb/>used when he came to that clause was one 
     <lb/>he should not have made had he desired to 
     <lb/>live up to his profession. On what ground 
     <lb/>did the right hon. gentleman advocate his 
     <lb/>Bill ? It was not explanation but an 
     <lb/>argument which he gave ? He advocated it 
     <lb/>on the ground that separate schools were 
     <lb/>superior to public free schools or secular 
     <lb/>schools. He raised an issue which there 
     <lb/>was no need of raising at all, an issue which, 
     <lb/>in the earlier part of his speech, my right 
     <lb/>hon. friend declared he did not intend to 
     <lb/>raise. But he forgot that intention and he 
     <lb/>raised the question of the respective merits 
     <lb/>of public free schools and separate schools, 
     <lb/>and gave the horrible example of the United 
     <lb/>States as an argument against public 
     <lb/>schools. There you have his argument and 
     <lb/>his illustration. He tortured the British 
     <lb/>North American Act of 1867 and the British 
     <lb/>North America Act of 1871 in order to get 
     <lb/>a legal ground—what for ? For an explana<lb break="no"/>tion of his Bill? No, but to make strong 
     <lb/>his argument for the passage of his Bill. 
     <lb/>He tortured the shades of George Brown of 
     <lb/>illustrious memory, until I could almost 
     <lb/>hear the squeaking ghost of that eminent 
     <lb/>statesman fitting through the passages here, 
     <lb/>tortured and injured by the violent wrench<lb break="no"/>ing and twisting which the right hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman gave it. And in all these ways, 
     <lb/>instead of making a lucid explanation of the 
     <lb/>main feature of his Bill, he entered into an 
     <lb/>impassioned argument in order that his Bill 
     <lb/>might gain the assent of this House and 
     <lb/>the country. Well, the right hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man has had to eat the fruits of his mis<lb break="no"/>take. Just then, under the glamour of his 
     <lb/>speech, under his successful avoidance of 
     <lb/>certain points, under his equally successful 
     <lb/>exclusion of certain other points in that 
     <lb/>Bill, every man behind him applauded to the 
     <lb/>echo ; and if a vote had been called for 
     <lb/>then, every man would have risen to his 
     <lb/>feet—perhaps with one exception—and have 
     <lb/>voted for the Bill. He rushed the House 
     <lb/>for the time being, but he failed to rush it 
     <lb/>permanently ; and the disorganization and 
     <lb/>confusion of these ten days is abundant 
     <lb/>proof that the right hon. gentleman went 
     <lb/>further than prudence and good statesman<lb break="no"/>ship justified. He taunted my hon. friend 
     <lb/>beside me (Mr. Borden) with deftly shaping 
     <lb/>his course. We11, I hope his course is more 
     <lb/>deftly shaped than that of my right hon. 
     <lb/>friend. He lightly told my hon. friend that 
     <lb/>he was seeking for hills of vantage and 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
     <fw rendition="simple:right" type="num">2274</fw>
          
     strategical points, forsooth. There are hills 
     <lb/>
     of vantage but there are also valleys of hu<lb break="no"/>miliation. And it would be interesting to 
     <lb/>
     know who will head the procession through 
     <lb/>
     the valley of humiliation. Will it be the 
     <lb/>
     sturdy young Napoleon of the west with 
     <lb/>
     downcast eyes and drooping colours ? Or 
     <lb/>
     will it be my right hon. friend who in 1895 
     <lb/>
     boasted that he possessed the courage which 
     <lb/>
     did not promise until he had made up his 
     <lb/>
     mind, but once his promise was made stood 
     <lb/>
     immovable as a rock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Now, all these are questions which we 
     <lb/>
     cannot but be interested in—questions rais<lb break="no"/>ed in this House and in the country. There 
     <lb/>
     is one other thing. Shall I speak of it ? 
     <lb/>
     Not content with rushing his Bill, not con<lb break="no"/>tent with throwing aside his colleagues to 
     <lb/>
     rush his Bill, not content with proceeding 
     <lb/>
     without taking care to ascertain the senti<lb break="no"/>ment of the west, not content with making 
     <lb/>
     his speech on the merits of the Bill and 
     <lb/>
     confounding it with a lucid explanation of 
     <lb/>
     the measure, the right hon. gentleman tried 
     <lb/>
     to rush the country as well. One of his 
     <lb/>
     colleagues in another place prepared a pam<lb break="no"/>phlet, a remarkable pamphlet in some ways. 
     <lb/>
     It purported to be a ' brief history, from 
     <lb/>
     official sources, of the legislation respecting 
     <lb/>
     the separate schools since the year 1863 in 
     <lb/>
     the united province of Canada, and in the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion since confederation.' Now, as I 
     <lb/>
     said before, I have no fault to find, nor has 
     <lb/>
     any one in this House with the publication 
     <lb/>
     by the government of official information 
     <lb/>
     that will shed light upon this question. 
     <lb/>
     But this pamphlet is a partisan pamphlet. 
     <lb/>
     It does give the facts taken from 'Hansard,' 
     <lb/>
     but it does also colour them, and it does 
     <lb/>
     also argue the points involved. How does 
     <lb/>
     it colour them ? I do not suppose, for in<lb break="no"/>stance, that Edward Blake or George Brown, 
     <lb/>
     or any of these old worthies, some of whom 
     <lb/>
     have passed away, others of whom are still 
     <lb/>
     with us, in making their speeches, italicized 
     <lb/>
     certain parts of them, or altered them in 
     <lb/>
     double-leaded columns, to make the argu<lb break="no"/>ments impressive. But in the quotations from 
     <lb/>
     the speeches of these gentlemen every sen<lb break="no"/>tence that favours the contention of the 
     <lb/>
     right hon. gentleman (Sir Wilfrid Laurier) 
     <lb/>
     is italicized or given emphasis which 
     <lb/>
     points the argument. It is not necessary 
     <lb/>
     for me to go into details. But when it 
     <lb/>
     comes to George Brown's momentous sen<lb break="no"/>tence, the maker of this pamphlet is not 
     <lb/>
     satisfied with italicizing it, but he puts it in 
     <lb/>
     bolder type, italicizes it and double—spaces 
     <lb/>
     it, in order that it may catch the eye and 
     <lb/>
     make the impression the compiler intended 
     <lb/>
     to make. And, when that is all done, here is 
     <lb/>
     the argument with which it ends—not a 
     <lb/>
     quotation from Blake or Brown, not an ab<lb break="no"/>stract from 'Hansard,' but an argument 
     <lb/>
     from the pen of the maker of this pamphlet : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Under the Territorial legislation, the rights 
     <lb/>
     of the minority have in the past been recog<lb break="no"/>nized. It would be a breach of faith and a vio<lb break="no"/>lation of the British North America Act to dis<lb break="no"/><pb n="2275" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2275.jpg"/><fw type="num">2275</fw><fw type="running">COMMONS</fw>
             turb now the rights and privileges granted by 
          
           
     <lb/>
     the parliament of Canada. thirty years ago and 
     <lb/>
     enjoyed by the minority up to this time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
            <p>Now, I say that this is not a very im<lb break="no"/>portant matter, but it is significant. I say 
     <lb/>
     that no government has a right—and it is 
     <lb/>
     poor politics, I think, for any government 
     <lb/>
     to assume that it has the right and act 
     <lb/>
     upon that assumption—in giving what pur<lb break="no"/>ports to be official information from the 
     <lb/>
     records, to endeavour, by the means I have 
     <lb/>
     explained, to point out the argument and 
     <lb/>
     lead to a partisan conclusion with regard 
     <lb/>
     to a measure that has been introduced. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Now, I have no more to say on this occa<lb break="no"/>sion. These are just some thoughts which 
     <lb/>
     occur to us. We wish them to sink into the 
     <lb/>
     minds of hon. gentlemen opposite. We have 
     <lb/>
     no wish to dictate their policy ; but we 
     <lb/>
     would fain give them something for reflec<lb break="no"/>tion, for calm and, if possible, fruitful medi~ 
     <lb/>
     tation. This is our contribution, made with 
     <lb/>
     the best of intention and in the best of 
     <lb/>
     spirit, and in the hope that it will contri<lb break="no"/>bute to the benefit of the hon. gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     opposite. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. T. S. SPROULE</persName> (East Grey). In my <lb/> judgment, we are
                  face to face with a most <lb/> extraordinary state of affairs in this parlia<lb break="no"/>ment to-day. We propose to put through an <lb/> important measure
                  affecting the destinies <lb/> of practically half a continent under the <lb/>
                  leadership of a government that has not a <lb/> representative of that half
                  continent among <lb/> its members. Under constitutional govern<lb break="no"/>ment, as we understand it, and as it has <lb/> been carried out, the cabinet is
                  composed of <lb/> heads who have received the endorsation of <lb/> the people
                  before they enter upon their work <lb/> in that cabinet. And these cabinet
                     minis<lb break="no"/>ters are chosen from the provinces accord<lb break="no"/>ing to the population or importance of those <lb/> provinces. For instance,
                  Ontario in the <lb/> past has nearly always had five members <lb/> in the cabinet,
                  Quebec four, the maritime <lb/> provinces at least three, one of whom was <lb/>
                  allowed for New Brunswick, another for <lb/> Nova Scotia and, until recent years,
                  one <lb/> for Prince Edward Island. Thus every part <lb/> of the Dominion was
                  represented in the <lb/> cabinet ; and when important questions <lb/> came up in
                  which any portion of the coun<lb break="no"/>try was particularly interested, its
                     repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives in the cabinet were supposed to <lb/> have
                  influence in swaying the government <lb/> in regard to that matter. That has
                  hitherto <lb/> been the case with regard to Ontario and <lb/> Quebec and either of
                  those provinces would <lb/> rebel to-day if an important measure affect<lb break="no"/>ing its interests were before parliament and <lb/> it were deprived
                  of its due proportion of re<lb break="no"/>presentation in the cabinet. But to-day
                  we <lb/> have practically half a continent without <lb/> representation in the
                  cabinet, notwithstand<lb break="no"/>ing that an important measure is going <lb/>
                  through that vitally affects the interests of <lb/> that half continent, and that
                  will seal its <lb/> fate for the future. The only representa<lb break="no"/>tive
                  in the cabinet of that part of the coun<lb break="no"/>try has become so
                  dissatisfied with the <lb/>
                  <cb/>
     <fw rendition="simple:right" type="num">2276</fw> measure that he has publicly declared that <lb/> it cannot receive his
                  support, and, rather <lb/> than remain in the cabinet and assume any <lb/>
                  responsibility for the measure, he has re<lb break="no"/>signed. The government
                  have not dared to <lb/> put themselves in touch with that great <lb/> section of
                  the country by appointing an<lb break="no"/>other member in his place. Is it
                  because of <lb/> the unpopularity of the measure or because <lb/> no one can be
                  found who will take the re<lb break="no"/>sponsibility of it, as an in-coming
                  member <lb/> of the cabinet would necessarily do ? Or is <lb/> it because of the
                  dearth of public men from <lb/> that country and the impossibility of finding
                  <lb/> any one in the ranks of the government <lb/> supporters sufficiently
                  intelligent to be a <lb/> cabinet minister ? It cannot be the latter, <lb/>
                  because the government has many support<lb break="no"/>ers from the Northwest,
                  some of whom <lb/> would be a credit to a cabinet. We are <lb/> driven, therefore,
                  to conclude that it is be<lb break="no"/>cause of the unpopularity of the measure,
                  <lb/> and because the government dare not ask <lb/> the Governor General to
                  appoint a new <lb/> minister and, by an electoral contest, allow <lb/> the people
                  of the Northwest to express their <lb/> opinion upon the measure. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>If they did so, in that election which must 
     <lb/>
     take place, this measure would undoubtedly 
     <lb/>
     be discussed, every phase of it would be dis<lb break="no"/>cussed before the people, and the people 
     <lb/>
     themselves would have an opportunity to ex<lb break="no"/>press an opinion on it. The government are 
     <lb/>
     in the humiliating position to-day—I am 
     <lb/>
     justified in saying so in view of what has 
     <lb/>
     transpired—that they dare not risk their re<lb break="no"/>putation by appointing a new Minister of 
     <lb/>
     the Interior and sending him back for re<lb break="no"/>election before this measure goes through. 
     <lb/>
     So that great country is not represented 
     <lb/>
     in this cabinet, that great country is without 
     <lb/>
     a representative to voice their views with 
     <lb/>
     regard to this important measure. Is that 
     <lb/>
     not constitutional government run mad ? Is 
     <lb/>
     that according to the principles of the British 
     <lb/>
     constitution that we have heretofore carried 
     <lb/>
     out in the Dominion of Canada ? I say it 
     <lb/>
     is the very reverse. The government are to<lb break="no"/>day in the humiliating position that they 
     <lb/>
     dare not put a minister into the cabinet 
     <lb/>
     and ask him to go to his constituents and 
     <lb/>
     get their endorsation of his appointment 
     <lb/>
     and of the measure that is before the House 
     <lb/>
     to-day. Now in view of this condition of 
     <lb/>
     affiairs what ought the government to do ? 
     <lb/>
     In my judgment they ought either at once 
     <lb/>
     to fill that position, and give the people an 
     <lb/>
     opportunity of endorsing the appointment, 
     <lb/>
     and let this measure be discussed by the 
     <lb/>
     people themselves, or they ought to with<lb break="no"/>draw the unpopular part of their measure ; 
     <lb/>
     because, if I know anything about the 
     <lb/>
     sentiment of this country, especially of 
     <lb/>
     that part of the country which this measure 
     <lb/>
     will affect more than any other, it is I might 
     <lb/>
     say almost unanimous against the Bill, or 
     <lb/>
     at least the school clauses contained in this 
     <lb/>
     Bill that the right hon. gentleman has sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="2277" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1905-03-10_Page_2277.jpg"/> <fw type="num">2277</fw>
            <p><fw type="dateline">MARCH 10, 1905</fw>  <fw type="num">2278</fw>  
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. I presume the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman does
                  not propose to discuss the Bill <lb/>at this present time. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. If you will first allow <lb/>me to commence the
                  discussion of the Bill, <lb/>I shall then be happy to be called to order. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName>. I judged that the hon. <lb/> gentleman was
                  coming very close to a dis<lb break="no"/>cussion of the Bill in the latter
                  remarks <lb/> he made. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPRO2">Mr. SPROULE</persName>. I mentioned the Bill <lb/> as several speakers
                  before me have done, <lb/> and I assume I have a perfect right to do so, <lb/>
                  without discussing the principles of the Bill. <lb/> I am merely referring to the
                  Bill as a rea<lb break="no"/>son why the government do not fill the <lb/> vacant
                  portfolio, and I am asking them to <lb/> fill it so that the people may have a
                  chance <lb/> to express their opinion of it. When that <lb/> is done we will say
                  that the government are <lb/> acting according to the principles of con<lb break="no"/>stitutional government. I need not say <lb/> anything with regard
                  to another portfolio <lb/> that has been practically vacant for a long <lb/> time
                  ; while we are voting large sums of <lb/> money for that department to spend we
                  are <lb/> not carrying out the principles of constitu<lb break="no"/>tional
                  government both during this session <lb/> and last session. Until the government
                  bring <lb/> themselves in accord with the principles <lb/> of constitutional
                  government as carried out <lb/> in Great Britain, we are justified in draw<lb break="no"/>ing their attention from time to time to their <lb/> failure to do
                  so, and in asking them to put <lb/> themselves in accord with these principles
                  <lb/> which they have always declared they are <lb/>desirous of upholding. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p>Motion agreed to, and House went into 
     <lb/>
     Committee of Supply.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>
<div type="section">
            <head>
     National Transcontinental Railway—surveys, 
     <lb/>
     construction and other expenses, $1,328,500. 
     <lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:EMME1">Hon. H. R. EMMERSON</persName> (Minister of <lb/> Railways and Canals).
                  I am asking for <lb/>this money to meet the necessary expenses <lb/>in connection
                  with the work of the National <lb/>Transcontinental Railway Commission. The
                  <lb/>details of that sum are as follows : For <lb/>salaries of commissioners and
                  headquarters <lb/>staff. $100,000 ; for headquarters rental, <lb/>$13,500 ; head
                  office, stationery, furniture, <lb/>light, telephone, telegrams, travelling,
                     inci<lb break="no"/>dental and unforeseen expenses, $25,000 ; <lb/>for wages of
                  men in connection with the <lb/>different survey parties, $600,000 ; head
                  <lb/>office, district and divisional engineers' sal<lb break="no"/>aries, $100,000
                  ; supplies and commissariat, <lb/>$425,000 ; outfit and instruments, $20,000 ;
                  <lb/>freight and travelling expenses of engineers <lb/>and transport of men,
                  $45,000. These sums <lb/>make up the total. <lb/>
               </p>

    
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:FOST1">Mr. FOSTER</persName>. Now suppose we raise <lb/> the question, first, a
                  very important one, <lb/> before any of this money is voted, as to <lb/> what
                  information this House is going to <lb/> get. We have tried on several occasions <lb/>
                  <cb/>
     <fw rendition="simple:right" type="num">2278</fw> to get it, but have not been able to. The<lb/>thing has been thrown
                  backwards and for<lb break="no"/>wards like a rubber ball. We have incurred <lb/>
                  a large expense, and we are now to face <lb/> a million and a third, and we have
                  not a <lb/> scintilla of information as to what this com<lb break="no"/>mission
                  has done, or the results of its <lb/> labours, if it has done anything. If it has
                  <lb/> not done anything it has not justified its <lb/> existence because the
                  expense heretofore has <lb/> been very great. If it has done anything <lb/> we
                  want a complete statement placed before <lb/> the House as to what it is that it
                  has done. <lb/> We have debated the question casually time <lb/> and again and it
                  has been called to the <lb/> attention of the right hon. Prime Minister <lb/> and
                  also the hon. Minister of Railways and <lb/> Canals as to the fact that
                  information does <lb/> get out, but it does not get out to the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the House of Commons and the coun<lb break="no"/>try, because there is
                  no medium of communi<lb break="no"/>cation between that commission and this <lb/>
                  House. We would like to have this mat<lb break="no"/>ter settled first before we
                  vote any money. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:EMME1">Mr. EMMERSON</persName>. The commission is <lb/> constituted under the
                  Act of this parliament <lb/> and it has certain work to do. It is to be <lb/>
                  presumed that it is attending to its duties. <lb/> Now, until it has accomplished
                  certain work, <lb/> until the work is completed, there can be <lb/> nothing to
                  report. For instance, the pre<lb break="no"/>sumption is that in the first
                  instance it will <lb/> have to look after the surveys. It is to <lb/> have a road
                  surveyed over the whole route. <lb/> It will be taken for granted that that will
                  <lb/> take a certain time, and it will be taken for <lb/> granted that there are
                  certain preliminary <lb/> surveys to be made. Now, until there is <lb/> something
                  to report, until it has the work <lb/> completed which will enable it to lay
                  before <lb/> the Governor in Council a statement of the <lb/> result, we could not
                  naturally expect that the <lb/> information would be placed before the <lb/>
                  members of this House. We must not an<lb break="no"/>ticipate too much. My hon.
                  friend, I think, <lb/> shows too much anxiety for this information. <lb/>The
                  information cannot be in existence. It <lb/>is true that the general statement may
                  be <lb/>published in the press that the surveyors <lb/>are meeting with success in
                  finding a route, <lb/>but until the finished work of the survey is <lb/>placed
                  before the Governor in Council it <lb/>would not naturally be placed on the table
                  <lb/>of the House. My hon. friend, I think, has <lb/>become somewhat involved as
                  to the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of the means of communication be<lb break="no"/>tween the commission and this House. <lb/>There is no question as to the medium
                  of <lb/>communication. There was a question how<lb break="no"/>ever as to the
                  medium of communication <lb/>between the Railway Commission, another <lb/>and an
                  entirely different commission, and <lb/>this House. The question was as to whether
                  <lb/>the Department of Railways and Canals <lb/>had any connection with that
                  commission <lb/>or any control over it. On this the terms <lb/>of the Act seem to
                  be silent. There is <lb/>an implication in certain of the sections as [...] <lb/>
               </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>