<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1875-04-05"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1875-04-05">5 April 1875</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
               
               <title>House of Commons Debates, Third Parliament, Second Session</title>.
               
               
               <date when="1875"/>.  
               
               
               <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>C.W. Mitchell, "Free Press", Elgin Street</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="1081" to="1082"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-05_Page_01081.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-05_Page_01082.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-09-11">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="ichudson" when="2018-09-11">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-05_Page_01081">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-05_Page_01081.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-05_Page_01082">
         <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-05_Page_01082.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1081" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-05_Page_01081.jpg"/>
            
            
            
     <fw type="dateline">APRIL 5, 1875.</fw> <fw type="num">1081</fw> 
  
        
         <head rendition="simple:centre">GOVERNMENT LANDS IN THE NORTH-WEST.</head> 
    
     
     <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ARCH2">Mr. ARCHIBALD</persName> hoped the House  
     <lb/>would permit him to ask a question,<lb/>although no notice had been given,<lb/>namely, whether any steps had been<lb/>taken to prevent speculations in land on<lb/>the line of the Pacific Railway in the<lb/>Province of Manitoba and the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, and also whether the Hudson Bay<lb/>Company had any lands along the route<lb/>of the railway.<lb/>
     </p>

            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName>—The only 
     <lb/>steps the Government have taken in con<lb break="no"/>nection with the Government lands is to<lb/>pass an Order in Council prohibiting the<lb/>sale or pre-emption of any lands on the<lb/>line of the railway until the Government<lb/>have time to consider the question of the<lb/>final disposal of those lands in connection<lb/>with the contracts; and that Order in<lb/>Council embraces the entire route from<lb/>Rat Portage westward to Fort Pelly.<lb/>The Government thought it desirable that<lb/>a very careful examination of the country<lb/>should be had in the first place in order to<lb/>ascertain where a town might be located,<lb/>
           
   
            <cb/>
           
     or where lands might be advantageously 
     <lb/>reserved, and to take such measures as<lb/>would effectually prevent any land specu<lb break="no"/>lators from taking advantage of the loca<lb break="no"/>tion of the railway to the detriment of the<lb/>public. With respect to the latter ques<lb break="no"/>tion, my hon. friend will find from the<lb/>language of the treaty with the Hudson<lb/>Bay Company that they have one-twentieth<lb/>of the land reserved to them, and that<lb/>they are entitled in the Saskatchewan<lb/>country to choose land on the north side<lb/>in preference to the south side in certain<lb/>places that they desire it. We have con<lb break="no"/>sidered the position they occupy relative<lb/>to the Government with their lands. It<lb/>is impossible that we can interfere with<lb/>the rights they have under the agreement<lb/>made and sanctioned by Parliament, but<lb/>the Government have been considering<lb/>and will consider further during the recess<lb/>whether it is not desirable in these<lb/>quarters, at least, to endeavor to extin<lb break="no"/>guish the rights of the company to any of<lb/>the lands.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:PLUM1">Mr. PLUMB</persName> was glad to hear from the<lb/>hon. the First Minister that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment proposed to withdraw their land<lb/>from sale, and that a full examination had<lb/>been made. He hoped that when such <lb/>examination had been completed the land<lb/>would be put up for competition of which<lb/>ample notice would be given—so that<lb/>every one would have an opportunity of<lb/>competing for the lands.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MITC3">Hon. Mr. MITCHELL</persName> asked for<lb/>explanations of the expression of the<lb/>hon. the Premier in regard to extinguish<lb break="no"/>ing the claims of the Hudson Bay Com<lb break="no"/>pany to the North-West lands.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName>—We cannot<lb/>of course force the land from the company ;<lb/>but I have already taken the ground that<lb/>it is extremely inconvenient to have a com<lb break="no"/>pany the proprietors of a very large extent<lb/>of land in the North-West, and if Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment could make an arrangement for<lb/>Canada to become the sole proprietors of<lb/>the soil in that country, it would be of<lb/>advantage. The question was one for<lb/>Parliament to consider.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN MACDONALD</persName> said that<lb/>while on the one hand, great dissatisfaction<lb/>had been expressed at companies owning<lb/>immense tracts of country, as was seen in<lb/>the case of the Canada Land Company ;<lb/>on the other hand, it should be remem<lb break="no"/>bered that the Hudson's Bay Company,<lb/>
           

    

    
            <pb n="1082" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1875-04-05_Page_01082.jpg"/>
    


            <fw type="num">1082</fw>  <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS.</fw>
          
           were a powerful body in England with<lb/>large political influence and might become<lb/>Emigration Agents for the settlement of<lb/>the country. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said that all<lb/>those points would have to be considered<lb/>by the Government, but the tendency of<lb/>public opinion in Canada was wholly<lb/>against land companies controlling very<lb/>large portions of the public domain. He<lb/>thought at the time the arrangement was<lb/>negotiated with the Hudson's Bay Com<lb break="no"/>pany, as he thought now, that it was not<lb/>desirable that such a state of affairs should<lb/>exist. It would be for the Government<lb/>to consider whether any such advantage as <lb/>the right hon. member for Kingston had<lb/>suggested would be likely to accrue from <lb/>the company owning large tracts of land<lb/>in the North-West, and the Government<lb/>would consider the propriety of submitting<lb/>a measure dealing with the subject to Par<lb break="no"/>liament at its next session. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir JOHN MACDONALD</persName> asked for 
     <lb/>explanations as to the arrangement with<lb/>the Hudson's Bay Company in regard to<lb/>the taxation of land.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName> said the com<lb break="no"/>pany were liable to taxation after they<lb/>had taken possession of the land. The<lb/>Government must first survey the land,<lb/>and then the company must take them up,<lb/>after which the land become subject to<lb/>taxation, but only to such taxation as<lb/>was imposed on lands owned by other pro<lb break="no"/>prietors.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT3">Mr. D. A. SMITH</persName> remarked that one<lb/>of the provisions of the deed of surrender<lb/>expressly set forth that the Hudson's Bay<lb/>Company's land should not be liable to<lb/>any exceptional taxation.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The question then dropped.<lb/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>