<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_AB_SK_1891-08-24" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>,
<date when="1891-08-24">24 August 1891</date>, Canadian Confederation with Alberta and Saskatchewan</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC">
<title>House of Commons Debates, Seventh Parliament, First Session</title>.
<date when="1891"/>.
<pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Brown Chamberlin, Printer to the Queen's Most Excellent Majesty</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="4297" to="4299"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-24_Page_04297.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-24_Page_04299.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-23">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-24_Page_04297"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-24_Page_04297.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-24_Page_04299"> <graphic url="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-24_Page_04299.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="4297" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-24_Page_04297.jpg"/> 

<fw type="num">4297</fw> <fw type="dateline">[AUGUST 24, 1891.]</fw> <fw type="num">4298</fw>

<head rendition="simple:centre">THE NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES.</head>

    <p>House again resolved itself into Committee on <lb/>
Bill (No. 129) to amend the Acts respecting the <lb/>
North-West Territories. <lb/></p>
</div>
    <div type="debate">
<cb/>

<head rendition="simple:centre">(In the Committee.)</head> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Mr. DEWDNEY</persName>. The second clause was <lb/>
allowed to stand for two purposes: one, in order <lb/>
that the schedule might be prepared, and also, I <lb/>
think, with reference to the application made by <lb/>
the hon. member for West-Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) <lb/>
regarding the police. Instead of repealing the whole <lb/>
of section 2, I would ask that only a portion be <lb/>
repealed. I propose to leave that portion which <lb/>
says that the members of the Assembly shall receive <lb/>
$500, as it is. With regard to the schedules, it is <lb/>
proposed to give the Assembly twenty-six members <lb/>
instead of, as heretofore, twenty-two members and <lb/>
three experts. That will carry out the proposition <lb/>
of the hon. member for Alberta (Mr. Davis) by <lb/>
adding two to Alberta, one to the Saskatchewan <lb/>
and one to Assiniboia, which will make the total <lb/>
number twenty-six. I have laid on the table a plan <lb/>
showing the division of districts proposed under <lb/>
this Bill; and as I informed the hon. member for <lb/>
Bothwell (Mr. Mills), we have to provide for <lb/>
an election which takes place in the course of a <lb/>
month or two, it will be for Parliament to say <lb/>
whether, in the future, the division of districts <lb/>
should be left to the Assembly. I think there <lb/>
would be no objection to that. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). I think in the future <lb/>
it ought to be left to the Assembly. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. We ought to decide <lb/>
the number of members. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). Why? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. The number may be <lb/>
indefinitely enlarged, and we have to pay them. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). If they had only a fixed <lb/>
amount of money appropriated, the more they <lb/>
multiplied the members, the less they would get. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. The Act says they <lb/>
shall get so much each. I think it right to allow <lb/>
them to alter the boundaries of the districts. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:OBRI1">Mr. O'BRIEN</persName>. Do I understand the Minister <lb/>
of Justice to say that the Assembly will be allowed <lb/>
to alter the boundaries at any time? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. That is what is pro<lb break="no"/>posed. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR2">Mr. CHARLTON</persName>. This Bill provides for a <lb/>
Legislature of 26 members. Is there any provision <lb/>
for a future increase? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM21">Sir JOHN THOMPSON</persName>. No; that is what we <lb/>
were discussing, and I was urging that, that should <lb/>
be kept in the hands of this Parliament to arrange <lb/>
from time to time, so that the number should be <lb/>
definite, but that we should give them power to <lb/>
alter the boundaries of the electoral districts. <lb/></p> 

<p>0n section 10, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). I am astonished that <lb/>
the hon. member for East Assiniboia (Mr. Davin) <lb/>
does not suggest some other name instead of Moose <lb/>
Jaw. That is the translation of an Indian name, <lb/>
and I am sure that it must grate harshly upon the <lb/>
exquisitely fine ear of the hon. gentleman. I will <lb/>
suggest that it he called Davin's Jaw. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. The name is taken from a stream <lb/>
called the Moose Jaw. I believe it is the transla<lb break="no"/>tion of an Indian word, but it is very appropriate, <lb/>
because the stream forms an outlet very like that <lb/>
of a moose jaw. But I object to Davin's Jaw for <lb/>
this reason— that we intend to have mills on the <lb/>

<pb n="4299" facs="final/images/AB_SK_H_of_C_1891-08-24_Page_04299.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">4299</fw>
<fw type="running">[COMMONS]</fw> <fw type="num">4300</fw> 

Moose Jaw, and if we have Davin's Jaw, probably <lb/>
some Mills would he afraid to go there. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. MILLS</persName> (Bothwell). I think the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man will he content as long as the mills go after they <lb/>
are there. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:DAVI8">Mr. DAVIN</persName>. I wish to call the attention of the <lb/>
Government to a matter I raised in committee the <lb/>
other day, and it is a subject I dealt with on a <lb/>
motion for the first reading of the Bill to amend <lb/>
the Dominion Lands Act. It has relation to the <lb/>
clause that limits section 13. The Bill reads: <lb/></p> 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"7. Section thirteen of the Act is hereby repealed, and <lb/>
the following is substituted therefor:— <lb/></p>
    <p>
"13. The Legislative Assembly shall, subject to the pro<lb break="no"/>visions of this Act, or any other Act of the Parliament <lb/>
of Canada in force in the Territories, have power to make <lb/>
ordinances for the Government of the Territories in rela<lb break="no"/>tion to the classes of subjects next hereinafter men<lb break="no"/>tioned." <lb/></p> 
</quote>
        
        
<p>Sub-section 6 has reference to the incorporation <lb/>
of companies for territorial objects, with the <lb/>
following exceptions: "railway, tramway, <lb/>
steamboat, canal, transportation, telegrpah, and <lb/>
telephone and irrigation companies." I called the <lb/>
attention of the Government to this, as I thought it <lb/>
was unwise to limit the power of the Legislative <lb/>
Assembly in regard to railway or tramway, and <lb/>
other such companies, and, if I may refer to what <lb/>
I said on the motion for the first reading of the <lb/>
Dominion Lands Act, I may say that I pointed out <lb/>
that the United States was accustomed to give <lb/>
grants of lands for railway purposes to these terri<lb break="no"/>tories and I instanced especially Minnesota. An <lb/>
hon. gentleman who is always well informed on <lb/>
railway matters, and who is especially well <lb/>
informed on matters connected with the United <lb/>
States, question the accuracy of the statement. <lb/>
Now, Sir, as a matter of fact the Territory of <lb/>
Minnesota obtained grants of lands from Congress <lb/>
to the extend of 4,051,140 acres for the purpose of <lb/>
giving lands to railways, and the advantage that <lb/>
has accrued to them is very great, because <lb/>
Minnesota derives a large revenue at the present <lb/>
time from a certain percentage which that State <lb/>
is entitled to on the net profit. I do not intend <lb/>
to move in this matter, but I call the attention of <lb/>
the Government to it, that perhaps we err on the <lb/>
side of not giving more power to the Legislative <lb/>
Assembly. I do not see that it would be any harm <lb/>
to give it the power to incorporate railways, tram<lb break="no"/>ways and irrigation companies. I call the attention <lb/>
of the Government to it because they have to <lb/>
deal with the territories at some future session and <lb/>
I think it would be well to consider whether the <lb/>
power to incorporate small railway companies <lb/>
should not be given to the Assembly; and whether <lb/>
it would not be well, also, to do what was done in <lb/>
the case of Minnesota, and place at their disposal <lb/>
a certain amount of land which they could give to <lb/>
    the railways.
  <lb/></p> 

<p>Bill reported, and read the third time and passed. <lb/></p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>