<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgPCLA_1865-02-03" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPCLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-02-03">3 February 1865</date>, Province of Canada, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPCLA">
          

          
          
         
               <title>Parliamentary Debates on the Subject of the Confederation of the British North American Provinces, 3rd Session, 8th Provincial Parliament of Canada</title>.
                      
                    

          <date when="1865"/>. 
          

          <pubPlace>Quebec</pubPlace>: <publisher>Hunter, Rose &amp; Co., Parliamentary Printers</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="20"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0013.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0014.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0015.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0016.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0017.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0018.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0019.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0020.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-01">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-01">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-11-21">Marked-up people</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0013">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0013.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0014">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0014.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0015">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0015.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0016">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0016.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0017">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0017.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0018">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0018.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0019">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0019.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0020">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0020.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="13" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0013.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">13</fw>
<!-- GL, 2016-12-01, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->             

<!--<p>
     General Government that you should be ap<lb break="no"/>pointed for life. If so, then let the people say 
     <lb/>
     whether such power should be conferred. 
     <lb/>
     Take the means to make sure that the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Assembly shall appeal to the 
     <lb/>
     country. In New Brunswick the question 
     <lb/>
     was about to be submitted to the people 
     <lb/>
     through a general election. To be sure, it 
     <lb/>
     was said that the term of Parliament there 
     <lb/>
     had expired ; but if the Ministers in New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick had understood they could force 
     <lb/>
     a vote, as was about to be done in Canada, 
     <lb/>
     he doubted whether the general election would 
     <lb/>
     have taken place immediately. He believed, 
     <lb/>
     too, that the Conference generally had re<lb break="no"/>garded this as the most proper mode. Then 
     <lb/>
     did not think that such a change should 
     <lb/>
     have been brought about under a Coalition 
     <lb/>
     Government. This was contrary to British 
     <lb/>
     usage, and he believed that if a petition was 
     <lb/>
    numerously signed, and forwarded to the 
     <lb/>Imperial Government, representing that this 
     <lb/>important change had been brought about by 
     <lb/>a coalition, the act would be declared uncon<lb break="no"/>stitutional. The scheme was practically 
     <lb/>unknown to the people. Under some pres<lb break="no"/>sure it had been sent confidentially, to the 
     <lb/>members, but what did the country under<lb break="no"/>stand of it ?—little or nothing. It had been 
     <lb/>said that if the scheme were not adopted now 
     <lb/>it would be in danger ; but would it not keep 
     <lb/>good for a little while ? Was it feared that 
     <lb/>the peeple would find out that it would 
     <lb/>occasion increased expense, and so refuse to 
     <lb/>have it ? If only for the reason that it was 
     <lb/>not known to the people, he would vote against 
     <lb/>it. When the details came to be discussed, 
     <lb/>he believed some of them would not be ap<lb break="no"/>proved ; and he also thought that the project 
     <lb/>not embrace all the provisions which it 
     <lb/>should embrace. Finally, he thought the 
     <lb/>Government should not set its face against 
     <lb/>some changes in the scheme, were it only in 
     <lb/>the matter of the election of members to the 
     <lb/>Legislative Council, and he hoped the House 
     <lb/>would lead them to consent to that alteration. 
     <lb/>When the resolutions came up, he would make 
     <lb/>it his duty to speak more positively to the 
     <lb/>particulars in question. The honorable mem<lb break="no"/>ber then sat down, saying he approved of the 
     <lb/>mode of discussion proposed. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. MR. CURRIE then moved that the 
     <lb/>debate be adjourned until Monday, which was 
     <lb/>carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>-->

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY.</head>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">FRIDAY, <hi rendition="simple:italic">February</hi> 3, 1865.</head>
           
 <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> said the 
     <lb/>
     Speaker having desired that he should not go 
     <lb/>
     on with the Address about the union of the 
     <lb/>
     colonies, he proposed not to take it up till 
     <lb/>
     Monday next, but as the matter was one of 
     <lb/>
     the utmost importance, he thought it would 
     <lb/>
     be well now to settle the mode of conducting 
     <lb/>
     the discussion. He would propose that after 
     <lb/>
     the discussion commenced, it should continue 
     <lb/>
     day after day, and that for the purpose of 
     <lb/>
     greater regularity the Speaker should remain 
     <lb/>
     in the chair. At the same time he would 
     <lb/>
     propose that the rule which prevented mem<lb break="no"/>bers speaking more than once when the Speak<lb break="no"/>er was in the chair should be suspended, in 
     <lb/>
     order that every member might have the same 
     <lb/>
     liberty of free discussion as he would have in 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD2">HON. J. S. MACDONALD</persName> said the Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General's proposition that discussion 
     <lb/>
     should continue day after day, was one which, 
     <lb/>
     in his opinion, ought not to be entertained by 
     <lb/>
     the House. This was a very grave question, 
     <lb/>
     and he thought the people of this country had 
     <lb/>
     a right to consider maturely the sentiments 
     <lb/>
     promulgated by their representatives with re<lb break="no"/>gard to it. He was sorry, therefore, to have 
     <lb/>
     heard it announced by the Attorney General 
     <lb/>
     that the Government were to hurry the mea<lb break="no"/>sure through, to the exclusion of all other 
     <lb/>
     matters. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> said he had 
     <lb/>
     not stated this. His idea was that after the 
     <lb/>
     debate commenced it should go on each day 
     <lb/>
     after half-past seven, leaving the afternoon sit<lb break="no"/>ting for other business. If the discussion was to 
     <lb/>
     be confined to government days, the debate of 
     <lb/>
     Tuesday would be forgotten by Friday, the 
     <lb/>
     same arguments would be gone over, and they 
     <lb/>
     would sit the whole year round to finish it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD2">HON. J. S. MACDONALD</persName> said other 
     <lb/>
     changes of no less importance than this, with 
     <lb/>
     reference to Clergy Reserves, Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cil, Seignorial Tenure, &amp;c., had been before 
     <lb/>
     the people for a quarter of a century, and fully 
     <lb/>
     discussed session after session before being 
     <lb/>
     finally disposed of. Public opinion in that 
     <lb/>
     way was fully matured on these questions, but 
     <lb/>
     here they were called on at a few days' notice 
     <lb/>
     to change entirely the Constitution we lived 
     <lb/>
     under, and time was not to be allowed for 
     <lb/>
     public opinion to be expressed on it. He ob<lb break="no"/>jected also to the suspension of the rules of 
     <lb/>Parliament, so as to make the discussion take 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="14" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0014.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">14</fw>
         
     place with the Speaker in the chair, instead of 
     <lb/>
     in Committee of the Whole. If there was any 
     <lb/>
     question on which the House should adhere to 
     <lb/>
     its forms, it was a question like this—when 
     <lb/>
     the Government was so strong, so outrageously 
     <lb/>
     strong—(laughter)—the minority should be 
     <lb/>
     protected by the rules of the House being 
     <lb/>
     fully maintained. He observed the President 
     <lb/>
     of the Council laugh. He had learned a good 
     <lb/>
     deal from that gentleman in standing up for 
     <lb/>
     the rules of the House. But now, forsooth, 
     <lb/>
     the lion and lamb were lying together, and the 
     <lb/>
     Government, knowing that they had it in their 
     <lb/>
     power, were now to carry the measure through 
     <lb/>
    by brute force—the force of the majority. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> said there 
     <lb/>
     was nothing irregular in his proposing that 
     <lb/>
     discussion should go on with the Speaker 
     <lb/>
     in the chair. The suspension of the rules he 
     <lb/>
     proposed was for the protection of the mino<lb break="no"/>rity, by allowing each member to speak and 
     <lb/>
     state his objections as often as he pleased. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAME2">HON. J. H. CAMERON</persName> approved of the 
     <lb/>
     proposition that discussion be conducted with 
     <lb/>
     the Speaker in the chair. With reference to 
     <lb/>
     the other proposition that it should go on from 
     <lb/>
     day to day, he suggested that after Attorney 
     <lb/>
     General MACDONALD had stated his views at 
     <lb/>
     length on Monday, the debate should be ad<lb break="no"/>journed for at least one week, that people in 
     <lb/>
     the country might have the views of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment fully before them, before the debate 
     <lb/>
     fairly commenced. After that it might go on 
     <lb/>
     day after day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">HON. MR. HOLTON</persName> said he had not 
     <lb/>
     regarded the Attorney General's proposition 
     <lb/>
     in exactly the same light as the member for 
     <lb/>
     Cornwall, but was willing to accept it as indi<lb break="no"/>cating a desire on the part of the Government 
     <lb/>
     to afford facilities for a full and free discussion. 
     <lb/>
     He thought, however, it would be advantage<lb break="no"/>ous if, after the general discussion took place 
     <lb/>
     with the Speaker in the chair, the House went 
     <lb/>
     into Committee of the Whole, to consider the 
     <lb/>
     details. He thought three days in the week 
     <lb/>
     sufficient for the discussion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BROW4">HON. MR. BROWN</persName> said the member for 
     <lb/>
     Chateauguay had rightly apprehended the 
     <lb/>
     object of the Attorney General when he treated 
     <lb/>
     his proposition as dictated by a desire to afford 
     <lb/>
     the fullest opportunity of discussing this great 
     <lb/>
     question. Nothing could be further from 
     <lb/>
     their intention than to hurry the measure 
     <lb/>
     through by brute force, as charged by the 
     <lb/>
     member for Cornwall. Although the Attorney 
     <lb/>
     General had proposed that the discussion 
     <lb/>
     should continue day after day, he had not 
     <lb/>
     suggested for a moment that the whole should 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
        
     
    be hurried on ; the debate at any period 
     <lb/>might be adjourned, if deemed necessary, to 
     <lb/>allow time for the expression of public opinion. 
     <lb/>There were 130 members, and almost every 
     <lb/>member would desire to speak on the question, 
     <lb/>and he thought clearly the proper course was 
     <lb/>to devote every day after half-past seven to 
     <lb/>the discussion, to allow all the members on 
     <lb/>both sides to state their views, that they might 
     <lb/>go to the country and be fully considered. 
     <lb/>He thought there was a good deal of force in 
     <lb/>the suggestion of the member for Peel, that 
     <lb/>after the views of the Government had been 
     <lb/>stated distinctly to the House the debate should 
     <lb/>be adjourned for a short time. Of course the 
     <lb/>Attorney General East, as well as the Attorney 
     <lb/>General West, would desire to explain the 
     <lb/>scheme from his point of view, so would the 
     <lb/>Minister of Finance ; and probably he also (Mr. 
     <lb/>BROWN) from his own particular stand point 
     <lb/>would like to say something about the scheme. 
     <lb/>After the views of the Government had thus 
     <lb/>been put before the House, there could be no 
     <lb/>difficulty about adjourning the debate for a 
     <lb/>time, that the country might distinctly under<lb break="no"/>stand what they were about. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

            <p>
     After some remarks by Hon. <persName ref="pers:CAUC1">Mr. CAU<lb break="no"/>CHON</persName> and <persName ref="pers:DUNK1">Mr. DUNKIN</persName>, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POWE2">Mr. POWELL</persName> asked whether the House 
     <lb/>
     was expected to adopt the scheme in its 
     <lb/>
     entirety, or would it be open to the House to 
     <lb/>
     adopt one portion of it and reject another 
     <lb/>
     portion of it ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">HON. MR. HOLTON</persName> —That is not a fair 
     <lb/>
     question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BROW4">HON. MR. BROWN</persName> —Perfectly fair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POWE2">MR. POWELL</persName> thought Mr. Holton's re<lb break="no"/>gard for fair play excessive, when it even im<lb break="no"/>pelled him to interfere on behalf of the Ad<lb break="no"/>ministration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">HON. MR. HOLTON</persName> —I think it would be 
     <lb/>
     unfair to answer such a question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> said he agreed 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Cameron's proposition was a reason<lb break="no"/>able one. The Government would, in the first 
     <lb/>
     place, lay their case before the House, and 
     <lb/>
     through the press before the country, and 
     <lb/>
     then allow a reasonable time for the country 
     <lb/>
     to judge of the case as presented by the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment. It would not, of course, be pre<lb break="no"/>sented by himself alone, as the President of 
     <lb/>
     the Council had said. The subject was so 
     <lb/>
     large in itself and comprehended so great a 
     <lb/>
     variety of details, that he fancied all the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Government would find it necessary 
     <lb/>
     to express their views on particular portions 
     <lb/>
     of this great scheme. In answer to the mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Carleton, the Government desired to 
     <lb/>
         
            <pb n="15" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0015.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">15</fw>
         
     say that they presented the scheme as a whole, 
     <lb/>
     and would exert all the influence they could 
     <lb/>
     bring to bear in the way of argument to in<lb break="no"/>duce the House to adopt the scheme without 
     <lb/>
     alteration, and for the simple reason that the 
     <lb/>
     scheme was not one framed by the Government 
     <lb/>
     of Canada, or by the Government of Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia, but was in the nature of a treaty set 
     <lb/>
     tled between the different colonies, each clause 
     <lb/>
     of which had been fully discussed, and which 
     <lb/>
     had been agreed to by a system of mutual 
     <lb/>
     compromise. Of course it was competent to 
     <lb/>
     the House to vote against the Address as a 
     <lb/>
     whole, or to adopt amendments to it, but if 
     <lb/>
     they did so, it would then be for the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to consider whether they would press the 
     <lb/>
     scheme further on the attention of the House. 
     <lb/>
     It was obvious that unless the scheme were 
     <lb/>
     adopted as it had been settled between the 
     <lb/>
     different provinces, if they prosecuted it fur<lb break="no"/>ther, they would have to commence <hi rendition="simple:italic">de novo</hi>, 
     <lb/>
     and he had no hesitation in expresing his be<lb break="no"/>lief that if the scheme was not now adopted in 
     <lb/>
     all its principal details, as presented to the 
     <lb/>
     House, we could not expect to get it passed 
     <lb/>
     this century. It had been only in conse<lb break="no"/>quence of a very happy concurrence of cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances, which might not easily arise 
     <lb/>
     again, that the different provinces had been 
     <lb/>
     enabled to arrive at the conclusion now 
     <lb/>
     presented, and he should exceedingly regret 
     <lb/>
     in the interests of Canada and of the future 
     <lb/>
     of British North America, if anything should 
     <lb/>
     delay beyond this year the completion and 
     <lb/>
     conclusion of this great scheme. The resolu<lb break="no"/>tions on their face bore evidence of compro<lb break="no"/>mise ; perhaps not one of the delegates from 
     <lb/>
     any of the provinces would have propounded 
     <lb/>
     this scheme as a whole, but being impressed 
     <lb/>
     with the conviction that it was highly desir<lb break="no"/>able with a view to the maintenance of British 
     <lb/>
     power on this continent that there should be 
     <lb/>
     Confederation and a junction of all the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, the consideration of the details was 
     <lb/>
     entered upon in a spirit of compromise. Not 
     <lb/>
     one member of the Canadian Government had 
     <lb/>
     his own views carried out in all the details, 
     <lb/>
     and it was the same with the other delegates. 
     <lb/>
     But after a full discussion of sixteen days, and 
     <lb/>
     after the various details had been voted on, 
     <lb/>
     the resolutions as a whole were agreed to by 
     <lb/>
     a unanimous vote ; every one of the delegates, 
     <lb/>
     whatever his view to any of the details, 
     <lb/>
      being satisfied to adopt the whole scheme as 
     <lb/>
     adopted by a majority for each individual re<lb break="no"/>solution, and to press it upon his own Legis<lb break="no"/>lature as the only practicable scheme that 
     <lb/>
     could be carried ; such being the case, he 
     <lb/>
        
            <cb/>
     
     trusted the Government would have the sup<lb break="no"/>port of a very large majority of the House in 
     <lb/>
     carrying the scheme just as it stood, mem<lb break="no"/>bers sacrificing their individual opinions as to 
     <lb/>
     particular details, if satisfied with the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment that the scheme as a whole was for the 
     <lb/>
     benefit and prosperity of the people of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">HON. MR. HOLTON</persName> would like to inquire 
     <lb/>
     whether, according to the course of proceed<lb break="no"/>ing proposed by the Attorney General, the 
     <lb/>
     several resolutions of the Conference would be 
     <lb/>
     submitted separately to the House as affirma<lb break="no"/>tive propositions ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> said " no." 
     <lb/>
     The proposition submitted to the House is 
     <lb/>
     that an Address be presented to Her Majesty, 
     <lb/>
     praying that a bill should be passed based on 
     <lb/>
     these resolutions. All amendments might be 
     <lb/>
     moved to that one resolution. It would be 
     <lb/>
     the same thing, in fact, as to move them upon 
     <lb/>
     each resolution separately. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">HON. MR. HOLTON</persName> held that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment ought to ask for an affirmative vote from 
     <lb/>
     the House on each of these resolutions. They 
     <lb/>
     had been prepared and passed by a self-consti<lb break="no"/>tuted body, without the House or the people 
     <lb/>
     ever having been consulted on the subject. 
     <lb/>
     Unless the House were a sham altogether, 
     <lb/>
     the least reference that could be paid to it 
     <lb/>
     would be to obtain a direct affirmation of each 
     <lb/>
     of the basis on which the projected Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion which was hereafter to govern us were 
     <lb/>
     to be founded. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAUC1">HON. MR. CAUCHON</persName> wished information 
     <lb/>
     as to whether the scheme was to be discussed 
     <lb/>
     as a whole, or whether there would be an op<lb break="no"/>portunity given to consider each part of it 
     <lb/>
     separately ? There were part of the resolu<lb break="no"/>tions about which there might be some mis<lb break="no"/>understanding and difference of opinion, as 
     <lb/>
     for example those clauses by one of which it 
     <lb/>
     was stated that the civil laws of the country 
     <lb/>
     were to be under the control of the local 
     <lb/>
     governments, and by the other of which the 
     <lb/>
     law of marriage was placed under the control 
     <lb/>
     of the General Government. The law of mar<lb break="no"/>riage pervaded the whole civil code, and he 
     <lb/>
     wanted to know how it could be placed under 
     <lb/>
     a different legislature from that which was to 
     <lb/>
     regulate the rest of the civil law. He did 
     <lb/>
     not, however, see why an affirmative vote on 
     <lb/>
     each resolution would enable the House to 
     <lb/>
     pronounce with more freedom on these details 
     <lb/>
     than the course proposed by the Attorney 
     <lb/>
     General. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DORI1">HON. A. A. DORION</persName> said the member for 
     <lb/>
     Montmorency misapprehended the scope of the 
     <lb/>
     objection made by the member for Chateau<lb break="no"/><pb n="16" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0016.jpg"/><fw type="num">16</fw>guay. That objection was that the freedom 
     <lb/>
     of Parliament would be better consulted, and 
     <lb/>
     more opportunity would be given to learn the 
     <lb/>
     sense of the House by the different clauses of 
     <lb/>
     the Address being moved <hi rendition="simple:italic">seriatim</hi>, in the same 
     <lb/>
     way as supplies were voted. This was the 
     <lb/>
     manner in which the Irish Union Act had 
     <lb/>
     been passed, as well as the bill to change the 
     <lb/>
     Government of India, the Canadian Union Act 
     <lb/>
     of 1840, Legislative Council Act, and other 
     <lb/>
     important measures. This was the uniform 
     <lb/>
     course of Parliament, and there was no pre<lb break="no"/>cedent to be found for an contrary mode of 
     <lb/>
     proceeding. He thought the course proposed 
     <lb/>
     on the Opposition side of the House the most 
     <lb/>
     reasonable—that there should be a general dis<lb break="no"/>cussion on the scheme, in which Members of 
     <lb/>
     the Government should state their views ; that 
     <lb/>
     then there should be an adjournment for a 
     <lb/>
     week to enable the public to consider these 
     <lb/>
     speeches, and that then the subject should be 
     <lb/>
     discussed three whole days each week till dis<lb break="no"/>posed of. This would, in fact, be devoting 
     <lb/>
     more time to it than the plan that was pro<lb break="no"/>posed by the President of the Council, and 
     <lb/>
     would secure more fair, open and full oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity for discussion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> could under<lb break="no"/>stand the object of the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Hochelaga. That hon. gentleman was op<lb break="no"/>posed to Confederation, and the course he pro<lb break="no"/>posed was just that which was calculated to 
     <lb/>
     throw the scheme to another Parliament and 
     <lb/>
     till another conference was held, so that Con<lb break="no"/>federation might not be effected till the day of 
     <lb/>
     judgment. These resolutions were in the na<lb break="no"/>ture of a treaty, and if not adopted in their 
     <lb/>
     entirety, the proceedings would have to be 
     <lb/>
     commenced <hi rendition="simple:italic">de novo</hi>. If each province under<lb break="no"/>took to change the details of the scheme, there 
     <lb/>
     would be no end to the discussions and the 
     <lb/>
     conferences which would have to be held.<lb break="no"/>Then, as to having a debate three days a week, 
     <lb/>
     it would extend the session beyond all bounds, 
     <lb/>
     especially as after the Confederation scheme 
     <lb/>
     was disposed of, there would be a measure for 
     <lb/>
     organizing the local governments under that 
     <lb/>
     scheme. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">HON. MR. HOLTON</persName> —Why not bring that 
     <lb/>
     measure down with this ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> said that they 
     <lb/>
     were two different propositions, and they could 
     <lb/>
     be only dealt with separately. If the House 
     <lb/>
     declared, by its vote, that Confederation was 
     <lb/>
    desirable, then it would be proper to consider 
     <lb/>the nature of the local governments ; but if it 
     <lb/>failed to accept the principle of Confederation, 
     <lb/>then it would be entirely useless to bring up 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
       
     the other measure. Besides, to bring down 
     <lb/>
     both measures at once would make confusion 
     <lb/>
     worse confounded, because members would, of 
     <lb/>
     necessity, introduce their views upon local 
     <lb/>
     governments into the consideration of the Con<lb break="no"/>ederation question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD2">HON. J. S. MACDONALD</persName> comment<lb break="no"/>ed upon the declaration that the resolu<lb break="no"/>tions of the Conference were tantamount to 
     <lb/>
     a treaty, and asked by what authority the 
     <lb/>
     Government had undertaken to negotiate a 
     <lb/>
     treaty. He contended that all forms of the 
     <lb/>
     House should be strictly observed, so that 
     <lb/>
     there should be no infringement upon the 
     <lb/>
     rights of the minority. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FERG2">MR. THOMAS FERGUSON</persName> asked whe<lb break="no"/>ther it was the intention of the Government to 
     <lb/>
     carry this measure into force without submit<lb break="no"/>ting it to the peopele ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> said he could 
     <lb/>
    answer his honorable friend at once. If this 
     <lb/>measure received the support of the House, 
     <lb/>there would be no necessity of going to the 
     <lb/>people. If, however, the measure were de<lb break="no"/>feated, it, would be for the Government to 
     <lb/>consider whether there should not be an ap<lb break="no"/>peal to the country. (Hear, hear, and laugh<lb break="no"/>ter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SCAT1">MR. SCATCHERD</persName> asked whether it was 
     <lb/>intended to make any amendments in the 
     <lb/>scheme to meet the suggestions contained. in 
     <lb/>the despatch of the Colonial Secretary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName>, in reply, 
     <lb/>
     said of course he could not answer what the 
     <lb/>
     policy of the Imperial Government might be ; 
     <lb/>
     all he could say was this, that the represen<lb break="no"/>tatives of the various colonial governments, 
     <lb/>
     after this treaty had been made, agreed to go 
     <lb/>
     home and press upon the legislatures of their 
     <lb/>
     respective provinces this measure as a whole, 
     <lb/>
     and to present in all the colonial legislatures 
     <lb/>
     addresses identical in their nature to Her 
     <lb/>
     Majest , asking Her to pass an Act based 
     <lb/>
     upon these resolutions, such address being an 
     <lb/>
     expression of the deliberate opinion of the 
     <lb/>
     colonies. It would then become the duty of 
     <lb/>
     the Imperial Government and Legislature to 
     <lb/>
     act as they pleased in the matter. He hoped 
     <lb/>
     and believed they would not make any altera<lb break="no"/>tions in the scheme adopted by the Confer<lb break="no"/>ence. He was quite satisfied that if the local 
     <lb/>
     legislatures asked them to pass the scheme as 
     <lb/>
     it stood, they would leave us to be the best 
     <lb/>
     judges of our own affairs and carry the mea<lb break="no"/>sure through. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">HON. MR. HOLTON</persName> said he had given 
     <lb/>
     notice the other day of three questions he in<lb break="no"/>tended to put to the Government before going 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="17" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0017.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">l7</fw>
         
     into Committee of Supply, but as the present 
     <lb/>
     was an equally favorable opportunity, he 
     <lb/>
     trusted there would be no objection to his put<lb break="no"/>ting them now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> —No, go on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">HON. MR. HOLTON</persName> said the first question 
     <lb/>had a reference to the subject to which the 
     <lb/>Attorney General had alluded in the course of 
     <lb/>his remarks just now. It was, whether it was 
     <lb/>the intention of the Government to bring down 
     <lb/>their projects for local constitutions for the 
     <lb/>two sections of Canada before inviting the 
     <lb/>House to proceed with the discussion of this 
     <lb/>question of Confederation. The honorable 
     <lb/>gentleman had already answered that question 
     <lb/>by saying it was not the intention of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to introduce this measure, and had 
     <lb/>given reasons for this course. Upon these 
     <lb/>reasons he (Hon. Mr. HOLTON) desired to say 
     <lb/>one word. He maintained that the question now 
     <lb/>before the House was, should they revolu<lb break="no"/>tionize the country, should they revolutionize 
     <lb/>the government of the country ? (Hear, 
     <lb/>hear.) That was undoubtedly the question, 
     <lb/>and he would like to know distinctly whether 
     <lb/>the form of the proposed new government, 
     <lb/>local as well as general, formed part of the 
     <lb/>same scheme ? He felt that the House could 
     <lb/>not be in a position to consider the proposed 
     <lb/>forms of the Constitution until they had before 
     <lb/>them, at least in a general way, the forms of 
     <lb/>government which were to obtain between the 
     <lb/>two sections of the province, of the union of 
     <lb/>which a dissolution was to be wrought by the 
     <lb/>measure before the House. Then another 
     <lb/>question which he had proposed to put had 
     <lb/>reference to the educational system of Lower 
     <lb/>Canada. The Minister of Finance, in a speech 
     <lb/>at Sherbrooke, had promised that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment would introduce a bill to amend the 
     <lb/>school laws of Lower Canada. The honorable 
     <lb/>gentleman must be aware that this was a 
     <lb/>question on which there was a great deal of 
     <lb/>feeling in this section of the province amongst 
     <lb/>the English-speaking, or the Protestant class, 
     <lb/>of the population. He did not like to introduce 
     <lb/>anything of a religious character into discus<lb break="no"/>sions of this House, but in debating the great 
     <lb/>changes which it was proposed to effect in our 
     <lb/>system of government, the effect of them upon 
     <lb/>that class to which he referred must be con<lb break="no"/>sidered. Among that class there was no phase 
     <lb/>or feature of these threatened changes which 
     <lb/>excited so much alarm as this very question of 
     <lb/>education. Well, the Minister of Finance 
     <lb/>had said, with great solemnity, as having the 
     <lb/>authority of his colleagues for it, that this 
     <lb/>session the Government would bring down 
     <lb/>
       
            <cb/>
        
     amendments to the school laws of Lower Can<lb break="no"/>ada, which they proposed enacting into law 
     <lb/>
     before a change of government should take 
     <lb/>
     place, and which would become a permanent 
     <lb/>
     settlement of that question. The question he 
     <lb/>
     then desired to put was whether they intended 
     <lb/>
     to submit these amendments before they asked 
     <lb/>
     the House to pass finally upon the other 
     <lb/>
     scheme of Confederation, and if so, to state 
     <lb/>
     when the House might look for that measure, 
     <lb/>
     as it would undoubtedly exercise very consid<lb break="no"/>erable influence upon the discussion of the 
     <lb/>
     Confederation scheme, and probably in the last 
     <lb/>
     resort from several members from Lower Can<lb break="no"/>ada. (Hear, hear.) Then the third question 
     <lb/>
     of which he had given notice had reference to 
     <lb/>
     the Intercolonial Railway. It was a novelty 
     <lb/>
     that, perhaps, might not be found in the con<lb break="no"/>stitution of any country, to introduce a pro<lb break="no"/>vision for the construction of a railroad, canals, 
     <lb/>
     turnpike roads or other public works. (Laugh<lb break="no"/>ter.) But the novelty existed in this case. 
     <lb/>
     and we are told that a part of the proposed 
     <lb/>
     Constitution was to build the Intercolonial 
     <lb/>
     Railway, as to the usefulness of which there 
     <lb/>
     had been a great difference of opinion amongst 
     <lb/>
     members of the House and in the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After the dinner recess, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">HON. MR. HOLTON</persName>, continuing his re<lb break="no"/>marks, said it appeared now to be proposed to 
     <lb/>
     make the construction of a railwa part of the 
     <lb/>
     Constitution of the country. The President 
     <lb/>
     of the Council, who had formerly strongly op<lb break="no"/>posed the Intercolonial Railway, had now be<lb break="no"/>come so enamoured of it and its adjuncts that 
     <lb/>
     he was reported to have declared in a speech 
     <lb/>
     at Toronto, that rather than not have those 
     <lb/>
     adjuncts, to wit, the union of all the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, which he had also previously opposed 
     <lb/>
     as vigorously as the railway itself, he would 
     <lb/>
     consent to building six intercolonial rail<lb break="no"/>ways. (Laughter.) He thought the House was 
     <lb/>
     entitled to know what was to be done with re<lb break="no"/>ference to that railway before they were asked 
     <lb/>
     to consider the great question of which it 
     <lb/>
     formed a part. He desired also some infor<lb break="no"/>mation as to the position of the North-West 
     <lb/>
     question on which the President of the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil had always taken strong grounds, main<lb break="no"/>taining that Canada had a territorial right 
     <lb/>
     extending over all that region. He took it 
     <lb/>
     for granted the President of the Council still 
     <lb/>
     maintained his position, but he wished to 
     <lb/>
     know from him authoritatively the manner 
     <lb/>
     in which the Government proposed to deal 
     <lb/>
     with the question. He desired, also, some 
     <lb/>
     information on the subject of the defences, 
     <lb/>
     and what was to be the measure of our con<lb break="no"/><pb n="18" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0018.jpg"/><fw type="num">18</fw>tributions under the proposed scheme for that 
     <lb/>
     important object. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> said the 
     <lb/>
     Government would cheerfully give an answer 
     <lb/>
     to Hon. Mr. HOLTON'S questions. As to the 
     <lb/>
     local constitutions of Upper and Lower Canada, 
     <lb/>
     when subordinate provinces of the Confedera<lb break="no"/>ation, Government proposed to submit to the 
     <lb/>
     House a scheme or schemes to be considered 
     <lb/>
     by members of Upper and Lower Canada, 
     <lb/>
     respecting the constitutions of their respective 
     <lb/>
     governments. But the action with regard to 
     <lb/>
     them must be the action of Parliament. That 
     <lb/>
     action would only be asked after the Con<lb break="no"/>federation scheme was adopted, for until it 
     <lb/>
     was settled that there was to be Confederation, 
     <lb/>
     it was idle to discuss what should be the con<lb break="no"/>stitutions of the several provinces. As to the 
     <lb/>
     school question, it had been announced by Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. GALT, at Sherbrooke, that before Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation took place, this Parliament would be asked 
     <lb/>
     to consider a measure which he hoped would be 
     <lb/>
     satisfactory to all classes of the community. 
     <lb/>
     There was a good deal of apprehension in 
     <lb/>
     Lower Canada on the part of the minority 
     <lb/>
     there as to the possible effect of Confederation 
     <lb/>
     on their rights on the subject of education, 
     <lb/>
     and it was the intention of the Government, if 
     <lb/>
     Parliament approved the scheme of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, to lay before the House this session, 
     <lb/>
     certain amendments to the school law, to 
     <lb/>
     operate as a sort of guarantee against any in<lb break="no"/>fringement by the majority of the rights of 
     <lb/>
     the minority in this matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DORI1">HON. A. A. DORION</persName> —Will it apply to 
     <lb/>
     both Upper and Lower Canada ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> said he be<lb break="no"/>lieved, as regarded Upper Canada, the matter 
     <lb/>
     would remain in <hi rendition="simple:italic">statu quo</hi>, as the present law 
     <lb/>
     there was quite satisfactory to the minority. 
     <lb/>
     As regarded the Intercolonial Railroad, the 
     <lb/>
     resolutions shewed precisely what was the in<lb break="no"/>tention of the Government in that matter. The 
     <lb/>
     railroad was not, as stated by Hon. Mr. HOLTON, 
     <lb/>
     a portion of the Constitution, but was one of 
     <lb/>
     the conditions on which the Lower Provinces 
     <lb/>
     agreed to enter into the constitutional agree<lb break="no"/>ment with us. The North-West question he 
     <lb/>
     would leave in the hands of the President of 
     <lb/>
     the Council, who understood it thoroughly, 
     <lb/>
     and could, no doubt, give Hon. Mr. HOLTON a 
     <lb/>
     satisfactory answer. With respect to the de<lb break="no"/>fences of the province, they were now the sub<lb break="no"/>ject of negotiations with the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and the fullest information would be 
     <lb/>
     given to the House on that subject. He might 
     <lb/>
     mention that the Maritime Provinces, recog<lb break="no"/>nising the peculiar position of Canada geogra<lb break="no"/><cb/>phically, and its danger in case of hostilities, 
     <lb/>
     had most cordially agreed that any sum this 
     <lb/>
     Parliament might vote for the defence of Ca<lb break="no"/>nada, the would undertake their share of. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WALL5">MR. WALLBRIDGE</persName> asked if he was to 
     <lb/>
     understand that a guarantee was to be given in 
     <lb/>
     the Constitution of the Federal Government to 
     <lb/>
     Roman Catholic separate schools ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> —I only said 
     <lb/>
     this, that before Confederation is adopted, the 
     <lb/>
     Government would bring down a measure to 
     <lb/>
     amend the school law of Lower Canada, pro<lb break="no"/>tecting the rights of the minority, and which, 
     <lb/>
     at the same time, I believe, would be satisfac<lb break="no"/>tory to the majority, who have always hitherto 
     <lb/>
     shown respect for the rights of the minority, 
     <lb/>
     and, no doubt, will continue to do so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BROW4">HON. MR. BROWN</persName> said Hon. Mr. HOLTON 
     <lb/>
     had done no injustice to him in supposing he 
     <lb/>
     held now precisely the same sentiments on the 
     <lb/>
     North-West question he formerly did. He be<lb break="no"/>lieved it of vast importance that that region 
     <lb/>
     should be brought within the limits of civiliza<lb break="no"/>tion, and vigorous measures had been taken to 
     <lb/>
     ascertain what could be done with that view. 
     <lb/>
     It was not long since he returned from Eng<lb break="no"/>land, where the matter was very fully discussed, 
     <lb/>
     and he had not as yet had an opportunity of 
     <lb/>
     submitting the thing so fully to the Council 
     <lb/>
     that a decision could be had upon it, but he 
     <lb/>
     had no doubt that in a very short time they 
     <lb/>
     would be able to communicate to the House 
     <lb/>
     ample information as to their intentions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The discussion was then made regular by 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Atty. Gen. MACDONALD</persName> formally proposing 
     <lb/>
     that an Address be presented to Her Majesty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">HON. MR. HOLTON</persName> said that the uni<lb break="no"/>versal law of Parliament with respect either 
     <lb/>
     to bills or addresses looking to the disposal of 
     <lb/>
     public property or funds, or additions to the 
     <lb/>
     burdens of the country, was that the measure 
     <lb/>
     must originate in Committee of the Whole. 
     <lb/>
     This Confederation scheme disposed of the 
     <lb/>
     whole assets of the country, and established 
     <lb/>
     burdens which were to be applied to the pur<lb break="no"/>poses of the provinces of New Brunswick 
     <lb/>
     and Newfoundland, besides paying eighty 
     <lb/>
     cents per head of population to all the various 
     <lb/>
     provinces. This appropriation of property 
     <lb/>
     indeed ran throughout the scheme. Not only 
     <lb/>
     so, but the usage on all similaroccasions was 
     <lb/>
     to introduce the measure in Committee of the 
     <lb/>
     Whole. The act of union between England 
     <lb/>
     and Ireland was originated in this way, and 
     <lb/>
     so was our own act of union in the legislature 
     <lb/>
     of Upper Canada under the management of 
     <lb/>
     Mr. POULET THOMPSON, who was well known 
     <lb/>
     to be an able English parliamentarian. The 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="19" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0019.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">19</fw>
       
     same course was taken on our own Reform 
     <lb/>
     Bill under the HINCKS Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> said that 
     <lb/>
     any measure appropriating  money must origi<lb break="no"/>nate in Committee of the Whole, but it was 
     <lb/>
     otherwise with an Address to the Crown, ask<lb break="no"/>ing to recommend a grant of money. This 
     <lb/>
     was an address asking the Crown to make a 
     <lb/>
     great constitutional change. Now, supposing 
     <lb/>
     that it was asking to have the Constitution 
     <lb/>
     done away with altogether, must such an ad<lb break="no"/>dress originate in committee ? Clearly not. 
     <lb/>
     The money to be appropriated was to be 
     <lb/>
     granted by legislatures which did not yet 
     <lb/>
     exist. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DORI1">HON. A. A. DORION</persName> —There is nothing 
     <lb/>
     more plain than that, according to the stand<lb break="no"/>ing order of the House of Commons, any 
     <lb/>
     measure appropriating money or any Address 
     <lb/>
     to the Crown asking for a grant of money, 
     <lb/>
     or that expenses may be incurred, must origi<lb break="no"/>nate in Committee of the Whole. Our own 
     <lb/>
     80th rule was in a similar sense, setting forth 
     <lb/>
     that motions tending to grant an aid or to 
     <lb/>
     make any charge upon the people must origi<lb break="no"/>nate in committee. Now, surely these reso<lb break="no"/>lutions tended to create a charge upon the 
     <lb/>
     people. Among other things they bound the 
     <lb/>
     country to make a railway. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> —That will 
     <lb/>
     be made by the Confederate Government, not 
     <lb/>
     by this Government. We are not granting 
     <lb/>
     any money. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DORI1">HON. A. A. DORION</persName> —Nor do you ever 
     <lb/>
     grant money when you ask the Crown to re<lb break="no"/>commend the grant, since the Crown may re<lb break="no"/>fuse ; surely if a matter involving $5 or $50 
     <lb/>
     must originate in committee, so large a mat<lb break="no"/>ter as this must do so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">ATTY. GEN. CARTIER</persName> spoke of Hon. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     DORION'S remarks as absurd, as not a farthing of 
     <lb/>
     money was being appropriated. It was quite true 
     <lb/>
     the rule of the Imperial Parliament might seem 
     <lb/>
     to go as far as Hon. Mr. DORION said, but we had 
     <lb/>
     no such rule. Ours was founded on the Union 
     <lb/>
     Act, which merely said that no appropriation 
     <lb/>
     could be made, except after a Message from 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency , which must be referred to a 
     <lb/>
     committee. The Union Act was our law, and 
     <lb/>
     to-morrow the British Parliament, with the 
     <lb/>
     sanction of the Queen, might abolish the Con<lb break="no"/>stitution.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DUNK1">MR. DUNKIN</persName> —The Attorney General was 
     <lb/>
     the very BAYARD of defenders of every little 
     <lb/>
    corporation which had received its charter 
     <lb/>from that legislature ; that was of every cor<lb break="no"/>poration or company which enjoyed his favor, 
     <lb/>from none of which he would take away the 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
           
     
    smallest part of the privileges ever conferred 
     <lb/>upon them, and yet he asserted that the whole 
     <lb/>privileges and rights of this great colony could 
     <lb/>be taken away to-morrow by the Imperial Par<lb break="no"/>liament. He (Mr. DUNKIN) denied that all 
     <lb/>our rights were held at pleasure, but, if they 
     <lb/>were, that had nothing to do with the matter. 
     <lb/>If we were precluded from giving away small 
     <lb/>sums of money, except in a particular way, 
     <lb/>surely we were debarred from giving away all 
     <lb/>our rights. The British Parliament could de<lb break="no"/>clare that a man is a woman, and he must 
     <lb/>thereafter legally be called a woman, but that 
     <lb/>did not make him one. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GALT1">HON. MR. GALT</persName> said clearly no charge 
     <lb/>
     was put on the people by this Address ; not a 
     <lb/>
     penny could be taken out of the public chest 
     <lb/>
     in consequence of it. He thought also the 
     <lb/>
     spirit of the rules was no more infringed than 
     <lb/>
     their letter, by taking the course proposed by 
     <lb/>
     the Attorney General West ; because, if the 
     <lb/>
     Address passed, the Imperial Act would refer 
     <lb/>
     again to the people the power of disposing of 
     <lb/>
     this property by their votes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName> decided as follows :-<lb/>
            </p>

            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">The honorable member for Chateauguay has 
     <lb/>
     submitted that the motion is not in order, " insa<lb break="no"/>much as the proposed Address prays the Crown 
     <lb/>
     to recommend to the Imperial Parliament the 
     <lb/>
     passage of an Act laying new burdens on the 
     <lb/>
     people of this Province, and making dispositions 
     <lb/>
     as to the public property and money of this 
     <lb/>
     Province, the law of Parliament requires that it 
     <lb/>
     should be founded on Resolutions originated in 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the whole House." Now, the 4th 
     <lb/>
     clause of the 14th section of the Consolidated 
     <lb/>
     Statutes of Canada, " The Legislative Assembly 
     <lb/>
     shall not originate or pass any Vote, Resolution 
     <lb/>
     or Bill for the appropriation of any part of the 
     <lb/>
     said Consolidated Revenue Fund, or of any other 
     <lb/>
     tax or impost, to any purpose which has not been 
     <lb/>
     first recommended by a Message of the Governor 
     <lb/>
     to the Legislative Assembly, during the Session 
     <lb/>
     in which such Vote, Resolution or Bill is passed ;" 
     <lb/>
     and the 88th Rule of this House, " If any motion 
     <lb/>
     be made in the House for any public aid or charge 
     <lb/>
     upon the people, the consideration and debate 
     <lb/>
     thereof may not be presently entered upon, but 
     <lb/>
     shall be adjourned till such further day as the 
     <lb/>
     House shall think fit to appoint ; and then it 
     <lb/>
     shall be referred to a Committee of the whole 
     <lb/>
     House before any Resolution or Vote of the 
     <lb/>
     House do pass thereupon," which seems to be 
     <lb/>
     based thereon, refer to Resolutions or to an 
     <lb/>
     Address upon which some future action of this 
     <lb/>
     House is to be based. I fail to see in this motion 
     <lb/>
     that the action of this House is to be involved 
     <lb/>
     any further after passing this Resolution. As 
     <lb/>
     this matter was discussed before I left the chair, 
     <lb/>
     at six o'clock, I took occasion to put in writing 
     <lb/>
     my opinion upon the subject. I will read : "The 
     <lb/>
     motion is for an Address to Her Majesty, in which 
     <lb/>
         
            <pb n="20" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LA_1865-02-03_Page_0020.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">20</fw>
          
     the Resolutions on Confederation of the Provinces 
     <lb/>
     are set out. How does this differ from an Address 
     <lb/>
     moved to His Excellency , which always comes 
     <lb/>
     on motion upon a two days' notice given as in 
     <lb/>
     this case ? I cannot see how, as a point of Order, 
     <lb/>
     I can treat the matter other than as in the ordinary 
     <lb/>
     case of an Address. The argument is that it will 
     <lb/>
     be inconvenient so to discuss it. That is not 
     <lb/>
     addressed to a question of Order, but to one of 
     <lb/>
     convenience. The case cited by the honorable 
     <lb/>
     member for Chateauguay of Resolutions upon 
     <lb/>
     the question of a Bill for the Government of 
     <lb/>
     India was not one of Resolutions for an Address, 
     <lb/>
     but of Resolutions simply , containing the pro<lb break="no"/>posed principles of the Bill intended to be intro<lb break="no"/>duced. It is not pretended here that this House 
     <lb/>
     has any right to pass such a Bill, or that it is 
     <lb/>
     intended to present one on that subject here. The 
     <lb/>
     reasons why it is convenient to discuss matters in 
     <lb/>
     the form of a Resolution on which a Bill is after<lb break="no"/>wards to be introduced, is that Resolutions more 
     <lb/>
     easily admit of alteration. The Government 
     <lb/>
     have expressed their determination not to admit 
     <lb/>
     of any alterations in these Resolutions. Thus it 
     <lb/>
     is obvious that the same reasons for going into 
     <lb/>
     Committee do not hold. The member who 
     <lb/>
     moves an Address can force the vote on his 
     <lb/>
     motion in the manner he has put it, unless the 
     <lb/>
     form of it be changed by amendment, and this 
     <lb/>
     appears to be the only course open here. In 
     <lb/>
     truth the word ' Resolutions' might very well 
     <lb/>
     have been omitted altogether from this motion. 
     <lb/>
     Whatever might have been the result on a mere 
     <lb/>
     question of convenience, it is certain that the 
     <lb/>
    Specker does not decide that matter. His duties 
     <lb/>are to preserve order and decorum, and to decide 
     <lb/>questions of Order." 
     <lb/>
            </quote>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> moved 
     <lb/>
     that the debate be adjourned and made 
     <lb/>
     the first order for Monday after half-past 
     <lb/>
     seven o'clock, P.M. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">HON. MR. HOLTON</persName> raised the objection 
     <lb/>
     that this motion could not be put without 
     <lb/>
     two days' notice 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD</persName> said if this 
     <lb/>
     was the sort of tactics to be pursued, and an 
     <lb/>
     attempt made to embarrass the Government 
     <lb/>
     at every step, he must withdraw the conces<lb break="no"/>sion made to the member for Peel, and would 
     <lb/>
     give notice that he would move on Tuesday , 
     <lb/>
     that the debate be continued from day to 
     <lb/>
     day until the Address was finally adopted or 
     <lb/>
     rejected by the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After some discussion, <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. HOLTON</persName> 
     <lb/>
     withdrew his objection, and <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Atty. Gen. 
     <lb/>
     MACDONALD</persName> his notice. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2016-12-01, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


            <!--<milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     MONDAY, February 6, 1865. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>HON. MR. CAMPBELL said that, with 
     <lb/>the permission of the honorable member who  
     <lb/>had the floor (Hon. Mr. CURRIE), he would 
     <lb/>offer a few remarks upon one portion of the 
     <lb/>scheme of Confederation, to which allusion 
     <lb/>had been specially made in the House, and 
     <lb/>which, to a limited extent, had occupied the  
     <lb/>attention of the country . He referred to the 
     <lb/>proposed constitution of the Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cil under that scheme ; and in offering the 
     <lb/>reasons which had led the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and the other members of the Confer<lb break="no"/>ence, which, as honorable members knew, was  
     <lb/>composed of the leading men in the legisla<lb break="no"/>tures of the several provinces — the leading 
     <lb/>men in opposition as well as the leading man in 
     <lb/>office—to decide as they had done, he begged 
     <lb/>the House to believe that the decision had 
     <lb/>not been arrived at hastily, but after prolonged 
     <lb/>and anxious discussion, and after a full and 
     <lb/>careful consideration of the subject. It was 
     <lb/>not to be supposed that the Government of<lb/>Canada had itself laid down the scheme of 
     <lb/>the constitution as embraced in the resolutions 
     <lb/>on the table of the House. Honorable gentle<lb break="no"/>men must not misunderstand him. He did 
     <lb/>not mean to say that the Government did not 
     <lb/>heartily concur in and adopt the scheme, but 
     <lb/>that it was not its work alone, but that of the 
     <lb/>delegates from the other provinces as well. 
     <lb/>It was the result of deliberation, accommo<lb break="no"/>dation and compromise. When it became 
     <lb/>necessary for the Government to press the 
     <lb/>resolutions, he trusted honorable members 
     <lb/>would not suppose that they did so out of 
     <lb/>that love which people have for the creation 
     <lb/>of their own intellect, but would remember 
     <lb/>they were the joint production of the gentle<lb break="no"/>men to whom he alluded, and that any per<lb break="no"/>tinacity on his part arose from a sense of the 
     <lb/>sacrifices they had made to secure an agree<lb break="no"/>ment, and the difficulties which any failure  
     <lb/>now would create. He felt it had been im<lb break="no"/>possible for the Conference to arrive at any 
     <lb/>other understanding, and he only wished that 
     <lb/>those who looked with disfavor upon their 
     <lb/>plan, could have witnessed the anxious debates 
     <lb/>held at Charlottetown and Quebec before it 
     <lb/>was finally settled. The result arrived at 
     <lb/>would, he hoped, promote the welfare of the 
     <lb/>provinces interested, and be remembered with 
     <lb/>gratitude by their inhabitants many long years 
     <lb/>hence. And supposing this Chamber and 
     <lb/>the other were to come to a different opinion 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

    </div>     </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>