<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPCLC_1865-02-10"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPCLCoun">Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1865-02-10">10 February 1865</date>, Province of Canada, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

   
          
         
               <title>Parliamentary Debates on the Subject of the Confederation of the British North American Provinces, 3rd Session, 8th Provincial Parliament of Canada</title>.
   

         <date when="1865"/>. 
          

          <pubPlace>Quebec</pubPlace>: <publisher>Hunter, Rose &amp; Co., Parliamentary Printers</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="149" to="161"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0149.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0150.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0151.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0152.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0153.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0154.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0155.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0156.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0157.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0158.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0159.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0160.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0161.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-05">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-14">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0149">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0149.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0150">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0150.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0151">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0151.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0152">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0152.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0153">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0153.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0154">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0154.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0155">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0155.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0156">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0156.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0157">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0157.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0158">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0158.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0159">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0159.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0160">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0160.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0161">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0161.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="149" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0149.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">149</fw>
   
       
            <fw type="running">LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL.</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
     FRIDAY, <hi rendition="simple:italic">February</hi> 10, 1865. 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            
<p>
     Hon. MR. MACPHERSON, continued 
     <lb/>
     his speech commenced yesterday, as fol<lb break="no"/>lows :—In the remarks I offered to this 
     <lb/>
     House yesterday, hon. gentlemen, I desired 
     <lb/>
     to state my reasons for voting against the 
     <lb/>
     amendment of my hon. friend from Welling<lb break="no"/>ton, and for the resolutions of Hon. Sir E. P. 
     <lb/>
     Taché. I stated that I believed the Con<lb break="no"/>federation scheme was desired by an over<lb break="no"/>whelming majority of the people of this 
     <lb/>
     country, certainly by a very large majority of 
     <lb/>
     my own constituents. I stated further that 
     <lb/>
     as the resolutions had been before the 
     <lb/>
     country for a long time—for a number of 
     <lb/>
     months—and as there was no evidence what<lb break="no"/>ever before us of their being disapproved 
     <lb/>
     of as a whole, or indeed any one of them, we 
     <lb/>
     had good reason to assume that the people 
     <lb/>
     were satisﬁed. The press had published 
     <lb/>
     them in full, and there was not one petition 
     <lb/>
     against the measure. We have every right to 
     <lb/>
     assume that the people are in favor of Con<lb break="no"/>federation. I went on further, and said that 
     <lb/>
     during last autumn, I was constantly and 
     <lb/>
     daily bringing the matter before a very large 
     <lb/>
     constituency, where it was always approved 
     <lb/>
     of. During a portion of that canvass, one of 
     <lb/>
     my opponents mooted what I may call the 
     <lb/>
     smaller Confederation—that is, the Confed<lb break="no"/>eration of the two parts of Canada, and the 
     <lb/>
     people rejected and scouted it, while approv<lb break="no"/>ing of the larger one. (Hear.) I went on 
     <lb/>
     to say, with respect to the proposed change 
     <lb/>
     in the constitution of this House, that I did 
     <lb/>
     not look upon it as a disfranchisement of the 
     <lb/>
     electors, although the nominative was to be 
     <lb/>
     substituted for the elective principle, because 
     <lb/>
     while the nomination was not to be made by 
     <lb/>
     the people directly, it was to be made on the 
     <lb/>
     recommendation of their representatives in 
     <lb/>
     the other House of Parliament,—in fact in a 
     <lb/>
     manner analogous to the mode adopted for 
     <lb/>
     selecting the Senate of the United States-<lb/>two senators being elected by the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture of each state. In our case the mon<lb break="no"/>archical principle was strictly preserved, 
     <lb/>
     and the Legislative Council was to be ap<lb break="no"/>pointed by the Crown, on the advice of the 
     <lb/>
     Government of the day. If I viewed it as a 
     <lb/>
     measure of disfranchisement, then, looking 
     <lb/>
     at my obligation to maintain the franchise of 
     <lb/>
     the peeple, I should have more hesitation in 
     <lb/>
     voting for it. An hon. gentleman has said 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     that the change, from the nominative to the 
     <lb/>
     elective plan, was made at the demand of 
     <lb/>
     the people. That assertion is not historical<lb break="no"/>ly correct; it is not correct as far as Upper 
     <lb/>
     Canada is concerned, and I think not with 
     <lb/>
     respect to Lower Canada either. There was, 
     <lb/>
     at one time, a desire in Lower Canada, for 
     <lb/>
     the election of its legislative councillors, 
     <lb/>
     but the public men who carried out the 
     <lb/>
     change, did so more out of respect to the 
     <lb/>
     traditions of the country than from any 
     <lb/>
     pressure that existed then. In Upper Can<lb break="no"/>ada, I am quite sure, that so far from the 
     <lb/>
     people desiring it, they were either lukewarm 
     <lb/>
     or opposed to it. The liberal and reform 
     <lb/>
     party of Upper Canada were all opposed to 
     <lb/>
     it. It is well known that the late Hon. 
     <lb/>
     ROBERT BALDWIN, so many years the leader 
     <lb/>
     of that party, was always opposed to the 
     <lb/>
     change. And it is also well known, that the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman who is and has been for years 
     <lb/>
     the leader of that party, and who now holds in 
     <lb/>
     the Government the position of the President 
     <lb/>
     of the Council (Hon. Mr. BROWN), opposed 
     <lb/>
     the change to the very last wherever his in<lb break="no"/>ﬂuence extended, in the press which he con<lb break="no"/>trolled, and in his place in Parliament I 
     <lb/>
     myself saw him stand up to vote against the 
     <lb/>
     third reading of the bill . It cannot, there<lb break="no"/>fore, be said that the alteration was made at 
     <lb/>
     the earnest desire of the people. (Hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear.) I went on further, and stated that I 
     <lb/>
     looked on the measure as one which did not 
     <lb/>
     admit of amendment, since if we were to 
     <lb/>
     amend it, there were nine other houses 
     <lb/>
     which might claim the right to do the same,   
     <lb/>
     and it could, perhaps, never be carried out. 
     <lb/>
     I then expressed approval of the ﬁnancial 
     <lb/>
     arrangements contemplated, and differed from 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend from Port Hope (Hon. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     SEYMOUR), who said the revenues of the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces in past times should have been made 
     <lb/>
     the basis on which they should bring their 
     <lb/>
     debts into the Confederation. Inasmuch as 
     <lb/>
     we are not to continue separate provinces, 
     <lb/>
     and not to contribute separate revenues to 
     <lb/>
     the treasury, but are to be subject to the 
     <lb/>
     same imposts and to have one tariff a 
     <lb/>
     capitation basis is the proper one, and not 
     <lb/>
     that desired by my hon. friend. (Hear.) I 
     <lb/>
     went on to say that the trifling amount to 
     <lb/>
     be paid to New Brunswick by the Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation, for ten years, was necessary under the 
     <lb/>
     circumstances, and ought not to be allowed 
     <lb/>
     to weigh for one moment against the beneﬁts 
     <lb/>
     to be derived from the proposed arrangement. 
     <lb/>
     The hon. gentleman from Niagara (Hon. 
     <lb/>
        
            <pb n="150" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0150.jpg"/>
          
     Mr. CURRIE) said our expenditure would 
     <lb/>
     be greatly increased. I said that would de<lb break="no"/>pend upon ourselves, for we should continue 
     <lb/>
     to have the management of our own affairs, 
     <lb/>
     and the economy with which they are con<lb break="no"/>ducted will depend upon those who admin<lb break="no"/>ister them. If great improvements are car<lb break="no"/>ried out—if the Intercolonial Railway is 
     <lb/>
     built, and our canals enlarged—if harbors are 
     <lb/>
     constructed on Lake Huron, as they must be-<lb/> and if further aid should be granted to ex<lb break="no"/>tend a railway to those harbors —if all this 
     <lb/>
     is done, it will be impossible to effect it and 
     <lb/>
     not increase our present expenditure—but 
     <lb/>
     these improvements will be amongst our<lb break="no"/>selves in Canada, and we shall enjoy the bene<lb break="no"/>ﬁts they will confer; and Canada, it should 
     <lb/>
     be remembered, will have a just voice in the 
     <lb/>
     Confederate Legislature. I myself hope 
     <lb/>
     these great improvements will be carried 
     <lb/>
     on in the west, simultaneously with the 
     <lb/>
     Intercolonial Railway, although this is the 
     <lb/>
     only one specifically referred to in the resolu<lb break="no"/>tions—the enlargement of the canals being 
     <lb/>
     only spoken of generally. The Intercolonial 
     <lb/>
     Railway, hon. gentlemen, must be construct<lb break="no"/>ed if we have Confederation ; but I hope 
     <lb/>
     western improvements will be carried on at 
     <lb/>
     the same time. (Hear, hear.) I think, 
     <lb/>
     honorable gentlemen, we should be governed 
     <lb/>
     in our votes by the consideration of the effect 
     <lb/>
     of this measure upon the prosperity of the 
     <lb/>
     provinces. If it is to do us good, we should 
     <lb/>
     adopt it without unnecessary delay. What 
     <lb/>
     is it that we expect? Have we not reason 
     <lb/>
     to believe that it will settle the sectional 
     <lb/>
     difficulties which have so long agitated and 
     <lb/>
     distracted the country? Will it not be the 
     <lb/>
     means of extending our influence over a 
     <lb/>
     large and most valuable territory? Will it 
     <lb/>
     not open the way for us to two of the finest 
     <lb/>
     harbors on the Atlantic—St. John and Hali<lb break="no"/>fax? Will it not give us access to the ocean 
     <lb/>
     at all seasons of the year? Will it not open 
     <lb/>
     to us the coal fields of the Lower Provinces? 
     <lb/>
     Will it not add nearly another million to our 
     <lb/>
     present population, and place under one gov<lb break="no"/>ernment our millions of souls? (Hear.) 
     <lb/>
     But if the measure fails, what will our posi<lb break="no"/>tion be? I believe that our position in Up<lb break="no"/>per Canada would be one of hopelessness, one 
     <lb/>bordering on despair—with none of the 
     <lb/>questions settled that have been agitating us, 
     <lb/>and which have checked the progress of the 
     <lb/>country; with representation by population 
     <lb/>not granted, and no prospect of it being 
     <lb/>granted for a long time to come, while the 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
          
     agitation for it could not possibly cease until 
     <lb/>
     it was granted. (Hear, hear.) Further<lb break="no"/>more, hon. gentlemen, you all know the in<lb break="no"/>fluence that the agreement arrived at in the 
     <lb/>
     Conference had upon our credit in England ; 
     <lb/>
     that it had the effect of raising the price 
     <lb/>
     of our securities 15 to 17 per cent. But 
     <lb/>
     if we fail to agree upon the measure here 
     <lb/>
     in Parliament, what will be the effect in 
     <lb/>
     Britain? Would there not be a feeling 
     <lb/>
     of disappointment—would not our friends 
     <lb/>
     there almost despair of our ever placing our<lb break="no"/>selves in a position to carry on our affairs 
     <lb/>
     with credit, and acting for ourselves in a 
     <lb/>
     statesmanlike way? Some hon. gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     speak of dreading to take the responsibility 
     <lb/>
     of a vote on a question which is to make a 
     <lb/>
     change in the constitution of this House, 
     <lb/>
     without consulting the people. Why! what 
     <lb/>
     are we here for if it is not to take responsi<lb break="no"/>bility? The people send us here for that 
     <lb/>
     purpose, to act as we think best upon all 
     <lb/>
     measures that may be presented to us. But 
     <lb/>
     under existing circumstances, I think the 
     <lb/>
     responsibility of postponing the adoption of 
     <lb/>
     the scheme, of putting Confederation off, is 
     <lb/>
     very much greater than the responsibility of 
     <lb/>
     sanctioning it. (Hear, hear.) I cannot help 
     <lb/>
     thinking that if we postpone the measure-<lb/> and to adopt any amendment would have 
     <lb/>
     the effect of postponing it, and perhaps, of 
     <lb/>
     losing Confederation for ever—our conduct 
     <lb/>
     will be considered extremely factious and 
     <lb/>
     unpatriotic. A good deal has been said 
     <lb/>
     about a possible dead-lock between this 
     <lb/>
     House and the other House, but there has 
     <lb/>
     been little of that in past times, and nothing 
     <lb/>
     of a serious nature. If, however, the amend<lb break="no"/>ment passes, I can imagine a dead-lock which 
     <lb/>
     might be extremely prejudicial to this House 
     <lb/>
     —prejudicial to its inﬂuence in the country; 
     <lb/>
     nay, almost destructive of it. Suppose these 
     <lb/>
     resolutions to be carried in the other House 
     <lb/>
     by a large majority, which I have little doubt 
     <lb/>
     will be the case, and we carry an amendment 
     <lb/>
     here—suppose all the legislatures of the 
     <lb/>
     Lower Provinces adopt the resolutions, and 
     <lb/>
     this House stands alone in rejecting them-<lb/> do you believe the British Parliament will 
     <lb/>
     be turned aside from what it believes to 
     <lb/>
     be the best interests of British America 
     <lb/>
     by the action of this House? I can 
     <lb/>
     imagine a dead-lock occurring then, and 
     <lb/>
     one in consequence of which the opin<lb break="no"/>ion of this House might be set aside 
     <lb/>
     and its vote disregarded. Until this mea<lb break="no"/>sure is carried out it is impossible the 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="151" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0151.jpg"/>
           

     defences of the country can be properly 
     <lb/>
    attended to, while all must admit it is most 
     <lb/>important they should be proceeded with. 
     <lb/>Is it patriotic, honorable gentlemen, in the 
     <lb/>presence of such a state of things, and in view 
     <lb/>of circumstances which all thinking men 
     <lb/>admit to be most serious, is it wise to delay 
     <lb/>unnecessarily the passing of these resolu<lb break="no"/>tions? Honorable gentlemen may feel that 
     <lb/>they do not meet the views of every one in 
     <lb/>all particulars, but they must see the beneﬁ<lb break="no"/>cial tendency of the whole, and they cannot 
     <lb/>fail to see the importance of getting them 
     <lb/>passed without delay, for if they are to 
     <lb/>receive the sanction of the Imperial Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment at its next session, there is no time to 
     <lb/>be lost (Hear, hear.) One honorable 
     <lb/>gentleman as said the people are not 
     <lb/>satisﬁed with the measure. I believe 
     <lb/>they are perfectly satisﬁed. It has been 
     <lb/>before them for a long time, and they are 
     <lb/>possessed of suﬂicient intelligence to have 
     <lb/>made their disapprobation known if it was 
     <lb/>felt. But, to shew the feeling in reference 
     <lb/>to the matter, I will read two or three extracts 
     <lb/>from a report which I received this morning 
     <lb/>of the proceedings of the Counties Council 
     <lb/>of York and Peel. These counties send four 
     <lb/>representatives to the other House of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, and they comprise portions of three of 
     <lb/>the divisions represented in this Chamber<lb break="no"/>Midland, Peel and York. Mr. GRAHAM, a 
     <lb/>member of the council, moved that a select 
     <lb/>committee be appointed to draft a petition to 
     <lb/>the Legislature as to the advisability of the 
     <lb/>people being consulted before the scheme of 
     <lb/>Confederation should be carried into effect. 
     <lb/>I will now read from the report :-<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Mr. GRAHAM, Vaughan, argued that he did not 
     <lb/>introduce the resolution with any such intention, 
     <lb/>for he did not regard it as political. The Admin<lb break="no"/>istration was composed of men of different shades 
     <lb/>of politics, and hence the question was not one of 
     <lb/>my particular party. The present Parliament 
     <lb/>was not elected to consider this question, and 
     <lb/>should therefore not pronounce on the scheme 
     <lb/>without ﬁrst consulting the people. On questions 
     <lb/>of far less interest they gone to the country, 
     <lb/>and he thought they should on this, as it involved 
     <lb/>large interests, and was of the greatest importance. 
     <lb/>The Attorney General had said, in his place in 
     <lb/>Parliament, that the scheme must be adopted 
     <lb/>without any amendmcnts, but he (Mr. GRAHAM) 
     <lb/>thought it needed amendment so far as the peeple 
     <lb/>of‘ Upper Canada were concerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

   

            <p>
     Hr. HARTLEY said the whole scheme was now 
     <lb/>
     before the country, and the people who were in<lb break="no"/>terested in the matter were aware of its provisions. 
     <lb/>
     In the very riding represented in part by the very 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
          
     mover of the resolution the people gave expres<lb break="no"/>sion in favor of Confederation by the election. of 
     <lb/>
     the Hon. W. P. HOWLAND ; and in fact at every 
     <lb/>
     election held since the scheme was proposed, the 
     <lb/>
     candidates elected have declared in its favor. 
     <lb/>
     He considered the Attorney General perfectly 
     <lb/>
     right in declaring that the resolutions must pass 
     <lb/>
     without amendment. The measure, as it stood, 
     <lb/>
     had received the sanction of all the delegates 
     <lb/>
     representing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. GRAHAM, Gore, stated that some ot the 
     <lb/>
     members looked upon the resolution as being of a 
     <lb/>
     political character. However, be that as it may, 
     <lb/>
     the resolution was now before the chair, and had 
     <lb/>
     to be disposed of. He thought  the question of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation was in the hands of the best judges, 
     <lb/>
     and they would decide whether it would be advan<lb break="no"/>tageous to Canada or not. These representatives 
     <lb/>
     of the people were all well posted up in the re<lb break="no"/>sources of the provinces, an how such could be 
     <lb/>
     best deveIoped and therefore he thought that the 
     <lb/>
    question should be left with them for decision. 
     <lb/>As to an appeal to the people, he could not see 
     <lb/>what good results would ﬂow from it. The reso<lb break="no"/>lutions passed at the Quebec Conference on Con<lb break="no"/>federation were before the people and their repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives, and it is for the latter to decide for or 
     <lb/>against them ; and they are undoubtedly in a 
     <lb/>good position to form correct conclusions concern<lb break="no"/>ing them. He could not see what reasons the 
     <lb/>statesmen of Canada would have in sacriﬁcing the 
     <lb/>interests of our country. They all had a common 
     <lb/>interest with ourselves, and hence would not be 
     <lb/>likely to do anything detrimental to the best in<lb break="no"/>terests of Canada. As regarded the submitting 
     <lb/>of the question to the people, Mr. GRAHAM thought 
     <lb/>that ample time had been given the representatives 
     <lb/>during the recess, to ascertain the feelings of the 
     <lb/>people on the subject, and that, therefore, they 
     <lb/>went to Quebec perfectly prepared to deal with 
     <lb/>the question without putting the country to the 
     <lb/>expense of a general election. An appeal to the 
     <lb/>peop1e would be a useless expenditure, and, 
     <lb/>therefore, he would oppose the resolution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On being put to the council, the motion was 
     <lb/>lost on the vote of 6 to 25. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
    
   
            <p>
     This, honorable gentlemen, is the opinion 
     <lb/>
     of the Municipal Council of York and Peel, 
     <lb/>
     and I hope this House will do as that coun<lb break="no"/>cil desire, and decide upon the measure 
     <lb/>
     without resorting to any course that can pro<lb break="no"/>duce any delay whatever. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
     So important is this scheme considered in 
     <lb/>
     England, as well as in our own country, that 
     <lb/>
     I believe the vote taken on it will be regarded 
     <lb/>
     as a test of our desire to remain in connection 
     <lb/>
     with the British Empire, to maintain our 
     <lb/>
     allegiance to our beloved Sovereign, or of 
     <lb/>
     our indifference to the prospect of being 
     <lb/>
     merged into another country. This might be 
     <lb/>
     an unjust conclusion to arrive at, but we 
     <lb/>
     have recent examples in our own history of 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="152" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0152.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">152</fw>
          
     the way such conclusions are formed abroad. 
     <lb/>
     I remember a vote which was misconstrued, 
     <lb/>
     much to the prejudice of this country—I 
     <lb/>
     refer to that on the Militia Bill rejected in 
     <lb/>
     1862. There is no doubt the rejection of 
     <lb/>
     that bill gave rise to the opinion which pre<lb break="no"/>vails in England—and you cannot convince 
     <lb/>
     the people there to the contrary—that Cana<lb break="no"/>dians are unwilling to defend themselves. 
     <lb/>
     Nothing could be more unjust to our people 
     <lb/>
     than to entertain such an idea, nothing 
     <lb/>
     more unjust even to the majority who voted 
     <lb/>
     against that bill ; but still that was the con<lb break="no"/>viction arrived at, which it took a long time 
     <lb/>
     to modify, and which is not entirely removed 
     <lb/>
     to this day. I believe that vote has cost the 
     <lb/>
     country a very large sum of money in various 
     <lb/>
     ways. (Hear, hear.) In conclusion, let me 
     <lb/>
     just say that we cannot remain any longer as 
     <lb/>
     we are; we have to advance in some direc<lb break="no"/>tion, and I believe we are going in the right 
     <lb/>
     direction when we proceed towards Confed<lb break="no"/>eration. I am very much disposed to agree 
     <lb/>
     with the honorable and gallant Premier, that 
     <lb/>
     we are on the top of an inclined plane, and 
     <lb/>
     that if we do not adopt Confederation, we 
     <lb/>
     shall very likely ﬁnd ourselves descending it 
     <lb/>
     against our wish, and plunged into a mal<lb break="no"/>strom of debt, democracy and demagogism. 
     <lb/>
     (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. BOULTON said he rejoiced to 
     <lb/>
     find, in the accession to the House of the hon<lb break="no"/>orable member who had just spoken, a gentle<lb break="no"/>man so well calculated to sustain its credit, 
     <lb/>
     and to assist by his enlightened and thoroughly 
     <lb/>
     patriotic views in the disposal of the many 
     <lb/>
     and important questions with which it had to 
     <lb/>
     deal, in a manner worthy of the House and 
     <lb/>
     beneﬁcial to the country. With respect to the 
     <lb/>
     measure in debate, he must state he was de<lb break="no"/>lighted at the principles it embodied. He 
     <lb/>
     was strongly in its favor, and so far from re<lb break="no"/>garding it as imperilling the interests of the 
     <lb/>
     province, thought it eminently adapted  to 
     <lb/>
     advance its prosperity and welfare. He was 
     <lb/>
     not a young man, having numbered more than 
     <lb/>
     half a century of years, during the greater 
     <lb/>
     part of which period he had ﬁlled a seat in 
     <lb/>
     either one or the other of the Houses of Par<lb break="no"/>liament, but he had never yet known a mea<lb break="no"/>sure of equal importance brought under dis<lb break="no"/>cussion. He might possibly not live to see it 
     <lb/>
     carried, but hoped and expected he would, and 
     <lb/>
     if it were, he had no doubt it would realize 
     <lb/>
     all the anticipations of its framers, and issue 
     <lb/>
     in the greatest advantages not to the colonies 
     <lb/>
     alone, but to the Mother Country likewise. 
     <lb/>
     During the time he had been in Parliament he 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     could safely say he had been guided by an 
     <lb/>
     earnest purpose to vote rightly, but yet he had 
     <lb/>
     two or three votes to regret, and that which 
     <lb/>
     he most regretted, was the one he gave against 
     <lb/>
     the union of Upper and Lower Canada. In 
     <lb/>
     this he felt now, as he had felt before, that he 
     <lb/>
     was wrong, but his consolation was that he 
     <lb/>
     had acted independently and conscientiously, 
     <lb/>
     not allowing himself to swerve from what he 
     <lb/>
     regarded as his duty even by the earnest en<lb break="no"/>treaties of one of his most valued friends, the 
     <lb/>
     then Attorney General for Upper Canada, who 
     <lb/>
     had taken a different view of the case. He 
     <lb/>
     now recognized the wisdom of the measure, 
     <lb/>
     and was glad his fears had been disappointed, 
     <lb/>
     and that great beneﬁts had resulted from it to 
     <lb/>
     both sections. He viewed the union now pro<lb break="no"/>posed as fraught with the largest advantages 
     <lb/>
     to all the British North American Provinces, 
     <lb/>
     and believed his anticipations would be rea<lb break="no"/>lised. He had often crossed the Atlantic and 
     <lb/>
     travelled extensively in England and the United 
     <lb/>
     States, but it was not until last summer, as he 
     <lb/>
     acknowledged with shame, that he had paid a 
     <lb/>
     visit to the Lower Provinces, now proposed to 
     <lb/>
     be united with Canada. This ignorance of sister 
     <lb/>
     colonies so near to our own country, he thought, 
     <lb/>
     was not creditable to any legislator, and he 
     <lb/>
     hoped other honorable members would feel it 
     <lb/>
     their duty to acquire for themselves informa<lb break="no"/>tion which was so necessary to their position. 
     <lb/>
     Well, he had been there last summer, and his 
     <lb/>
     opinions respecting those countries had imme<lb break="no"/>diately undergone a very sensible change. He 
     <lb/>
     had not expected to see such a beautiful city 
     <lb/>
     as St. John, N. B., or such a place as Hali<lb break="no"/>fax. He had conceived the people as poor 
     <lb/>
     and struggling for existence, but was delighted 
     <lb/>
     to ﬁnd merchants doing a great business, and 
     <lb/>
     exhibiting as high a standing and as much 
     <lb/>
     enterprise as any in Canada. Then, these 
     <lb/>
     provinces were distinguished by the most de<lb break="no"/>voted attachment to the British Empire and 
     <lb/>
     loyalty to the British Crown, sentiments which 
     <lb/>
     he was unfeignedly delighted to observe. He 
     <lb/>
     hoped these sentiments would continue to pre<lb break="no"/>vail and even be strengthened by the Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion now contemplated. (Hear, hear.) When 
     <lb/>
     he represented a constituency in Upper Can<lb break="no"/>ada and had to seek reëlection, he had always 
     <lb/>
     hung out his flag with “British supremacy” 
     <lb/>
     inscribed thereon — (hear, hear,) — and he 
     <lb/>
     hoped that the sentiment would continue to 
     <lb/>
     be cherished in the country so long as he 
     <lb/>
     lived. As to the allegations of some honorable 
     <lb/>
     members that the people were ignorant as to 
     <lb/>
     the merits of the measure proposed, he could 
     <lb/>
     say that, so far as the locality from which h 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="153" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0153.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">153</fw>
            
     came was concerned, it was a serious error. It 
     <lb/>
     had engaged the attention of the people more 
     <lb/>
     or less for many years, and especially of late. 
     <lb/>
     After alluding to the favorable consideration 
     <lb/>
     of a Confederation of the British North 
     <lb/>
     American Provinces by many distinguished  
     <lb/>
     British statesmen, such as the late Earl of 
     <lb/>
     DURHAM and the late Sir WILMONT HORTON, 
     <lb/>
     formerly Under Secretary of State, many 
     <lb/>
     years ago, the hon. gentleman spoke of the 
     <lb/>
     opinion of a particular friend of his own, a 
     <lb/>
     distinguished member of the other House, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     MORRIS, son of the late Hon. WM. MORRIS, 
     <lb/>
     with whom he (Honorable Mr. BOULTON) had 
     <lb/>
     had the pleasure of acting for many years in 
     <lb/>
     the House of Assembly of Upper Canada. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. MORRIS, the present member for South 
     <lb/>
     Lanark, in a pamphlet published by him, in 
     <lb/>
     1858, expressed himself clearly and distinctly 
     <lb/>
     in favor of the union of the British North 
     <lb/>
     American Provinces, and in that pamphlet 
     <lb/>
     quoted the views of the present American 
     <lb/>
     Secretary of State, Mr. SEWARD, and which he 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Mr. BOULTON) read as follows. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     MORRIS introduces those views thus :-<lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>That day may be and I trust is far distant, but 
     <lb/>
     sure I am that whatever, in the upheavings of the 
     <lb/>
     old world and the restless whirl of events may be<lb break="no"/>tide, yet the connection between our country and 
     <lb/>
     the parent state will not be rudely severed but 
     <lb/>
     fostered by the power and might of Britain, and, 
     <lb/>
     rising in strength and power, thousands of strong 
     <lb/>
    hands and bold hearts within our borders will 
     <lb/>cherish towards Britain sentiments of warm af<lb break="no"/>ffection and attached loyalty, and will be ready, if 
     <lb/>need be, in the contests for liberty that may 
     <lb/>arise, to stand side by side in the foremost rank 
     <lb/>with the armies of Britain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     There is, indeed, vast room for speculation as 
     <lb/>
     to the future of this great British Colonial Em<lb break="no"/>pire, and its consideration has engrossed and is 
     <lb/>
     engrossing the energies of many minds. Amongst 
     <lb/>
     others, hear what Senator SEWARD thinks of us : 
     <lb/>
     “ Hitherto, in common with most of my country<lb break="no"/>men, as I suppose, I have thought Canada, or, to 
     <lb/>
     speak more accurately, British America, to be a 
     <lb/>
     mere strip lying north of the United States, easily 
     <lb/>
     detachable from the parent state, but incapable 
     <lb/>
     of sustaining itself, and therefore ultimately, nay 
     <lb/>
     right soon, to be taken on by the Federal union 
     <lb/>
     without materially changing or affecting its own 
     <lb/>
     condition or development. I have dropped the 
     <lb/>
    opinion as a national conceit. I see in British 
     <lb/>North America, stretching as it does across the 
     <lb/>continent from the shores of Labrador and New 
     <lb/>foundland to the Paciﬁc, and occupying a consid<lb break="no"/>erable belt of the temperate zone, traversed 
     <lb/>equally with the United States by the lakes, and 
     <lb/>enjoying the magniﬁcent shores of the St. Law<lb break="no"/>rence, with its thousands of islands in the river 
     <lb/>and gulf, a region grand enough for the seat of a 
     <lb/>great empire. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</quote>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     Secretary SEWARD (who was known to be 
     <lb/>
     one of the principal men in the American 
     <lb/>
     Government) once regarded this country as a 
     <lb/>
     poor one, but it was clear he no longer thought 
     <lb/>
     so, but had formed a very high opinion of our 
     <lb/>
     resources and capabilities. There was no 
     <lb/>
     doubt that Canada was a great country and 
     <lb/>
     destined to be much greater still, and he held 
     <lb/>
     that if we were true to ourselves we could well 
     <lb/>
     sustain ourselves, especially as in the effort 
     <lb/>
     (if effort ever were needed) we were sure to 
     <lb/>
     enlist the sympathies, cooperation and sup<lb break="no"/>port of the Empire. (Hear, hear.) Then 
     <lb/>
     he was satisﬁed that as the project of Confed<lb break="no"/>eration was favorably received at home as 
     <lb/>
     calculated to strengthen our position, we might 
     <lb/>
     expect all the aid that we needed. He re<lb break="no"/>gretted not being prepared to support his 
     <lb/>
     views by statistical statements, but other hon<lb break="no"/>orable members who were much more compe<lb break="no"/>tent than himself, had done so, and no doubt 
     <lb/>
     others would follow. Of this, however, he was 
     <lb/>
     convinced, that we would lose nothing by the 
     <lb/>
     union, but would considerably improve our re<lb break="no"/>venue. The Lower Provinces possessed ad<lb break="no"/>vantages which we had not, and among them 
     <lb/>
     their coal and their gold ﬁelds might be re<lb break="no"/>garded as of great value. We would soon 
     <lb/>
     require a large and constant supply of coal, a 
     <lb/>
     mineral which, so far, had not been found in 
     <lb/>
     Canada. It was really melancholy that there 
     <lb/>
     should have been so little commercial inter<lb break="no"/>course between us and those provinces. They 
     <lb/>
     were constantly needing large supplies of pro<lb break="no"/>visions, which we had to sell, and it was a 
     <lb/>
     pity that the money expended in procuring 
     <lb/>
     them was not paid to us. He hoped that 
     <lb/>
     there would be a great revolution in the state 
     <lb/>
     of things before long, and that we would pro<lb break="no"/>ﬁt largely by it. In every point of view, he 
     <lb/>
     conceived this union to be most desirable, 
     <lb/>
     though he must confess he would not desire 
     <lb/>
     to see it carried out if he thought there was 
     <lb/>
     the remotest probability of its leading to a 
     <lb/>
     separation from the Empire. (Hear.) The 
     <lb/>
     Mother Country had done much for us; mis<lb break="no"/>takes had arisen, but, on the whole, we had 
     <lb/>
     been most kindly and generously treated by 
     <lb/>
     her; we had been materially assisted by loans 
     <lb/>
     on the guarantee of the Imperial Government, 
     <lb/>
     and that very fact had greatly enhanced our 
     <lb/>
     credit. In this way it was that our great and 
     <lb/>
     valuable public works had been constructed. 
     <lb/>
     It had often been a matter of surprise to him 
     <lb/>
     that we had shown so little care and anxiety 
     <lb/>
     with regard to our own defence, but the time 
     <lb/>
     had now come when we would be obliged to 
     <lb/>
    do something for ourselves in that direction. 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="154" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0154.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">154</fw>
          
     The people of England very truly said we had 
     <lb/>
     now grown up so as to be able, to some ex<lb break="no"/>tent at least, to protect ourselves, and while 
     <lb/>
     they did not expect us to maintain the whole 
     <lb/>
     struggle unaided, they yet demanded that we 
     <lb/>
     should do our part. This done, according to 
     <lb/>
     the measure of our ability, we would have 
     <lb/>
     nothing to fear, and the union would enable 
     <lb/>
     us to do better than we otherwise could. 
     <lb/>
     There might still be a feeling among a few of 
     <lb/>
     our people in favor of annexation to the 
     <lb/>
     United States, but it was limited to a very 
     <lb/>
     small number indeed, if it existed at all. 
     <lb/>
     (Hear, hear.) Some years back he thought 
     <lb/>
     the feeling prevailed to some extent, but the 
     <lb/>
     unhappy war in the adjoining country had 
     <lb/>
     led to a very great change in this respect. 
     <lb/>
     He deplored that dreadful war, and would 
     <lb/>
     deprecate the possibility of a rupture of our 
     <lb/>
     present peaceful relations with that country. 
     <lb/>
     He hoped we would still continue to live 
     <lb/>
     upon amicable terms, and was convinced 
     <lb/>
     that if war did arise, it would not be pro<lb break="no"/>voked by us. They were a great and a 
     <lb/>
     powerful people, and he hoped they would con<lb break="no"/>tinue in the future to treat us kindly as they 
     <lb/>
     had done in the past ; but it could not be 
     <lb/>
     denied that of late they had shewn a different 
     <lb/>
     disposition. They had passed a measure to 
     <lb/>
     repeal the Reciprocity Treaty, which had been 
     <lb/>
     of so much advantage to the two countries ; 
     <lb/>
     a repeal which, two or three years ago, they 
     <lb/>
     had no purpose whatever to bring about ; but 
     <lb/>
     he thought a change might yet take place, and 
     <lb/>
     that after all the treaty would not be abolished. 
     <lb/>
     At the same time, if it were abolished, he did 
     <lb/>
     not think we would be ruined altogether, but 
     <lb/>
     expected that intercourse with the Lower Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces would, in a great degree, make up the 
     <lb/>
     loss. It might be, however, that we could 
     <lb/>
     yet pass through the States, but if not, and 
     <lb/>
     we were restricted to our own channels of 
     <lb/>
     communication, we must do the best we can. 
     <lb/>
     He trusted the amendment of the honorable 
     <lb/>
     member for Sherbrooke (Hon. MR. SANBORN) 
     <lb/>
     would be voted down, and that the measure as 
     <lb/>
     it was would pass in its integrity. The Con<lb break="no"/>stitution of the Federal Legislature had been 
     <lb/>
     adopted in a council of our leading politicians, 
     <lb/>
     some of whom had all along been opposed to 
     <lb/>
     elective legislative councils, amongst others, 
     <lb/>
     the Honorable President of the Council, (Hon. 
     <lb/>
     GEORGE BROWN). And the people, he verily 
     <lb/>
     believed, did not wish to see the principle 
     <lb/>
     prevail. He had no doubt the Crown would 
     <lb/>
     make wise selections as it had generally done 
     <lb/>
     before, and though mistakes might in some 
     <lb/>
     cases have been made, for his part he was per<lb break="no"/><cb/>fectly willing to trust it. He was willing to 
     <lb/>
     give the people all the power they could 
     <lb/>
     reasonably ask, but it was a fact that the power 
     <lb/>
     granted had in many instances been abused. 
     <lb/>
     Many municipalities have been nearly ruined. 
     <lb/>
     They contracted loans, and instead of applying 
     <lb/>
     the money in a way to forward the public 
     <lb/>
     weal, a good deal of it had gone into the 
     <lb/>
     pockets of the borrowers. (Hear, hear.) He 
     <lb/>
     desired to prevent a recurrence of such things. 
     <lb/>
     When the Municipal Loan Fund Bill was 
     <lb/>
     passed, great advantages had been expected 
     <lb/>
     from it, and great improvements had been 
     <lb/>
     projected, some of which, he was free to say, 
     <lb/>
     had been carried out, but some of the munici<lb break="no"/>palities had misapplied and wasted the money, 
     <lb/>
     and now they were asking the Government 
     <lb/>
     for delay to enable them to pay the interest. 
     <lb/>
     In making these remarks he had no intention 
     <lb/>
     of saying aught that could be disagreeable, 
     <lb/>
     and if he had done so he prayed it might be 
     <lb/>
     overlooked. He had taken an active part in 
     <lb/>
     the legislature, especially in the other branch, 
     <lb/>
     in years gone by, and had always acted in<lb break="no"/>dependently, and he thought it was the duty 
     <lb/>
     of public men to follow the dictates of their 
     <lb/>
     own convictions in preference to the solicita<lb break="no"/>tions of friends. Having done so in the past, 
     <lb/>
     he would try to do so in the future. He would 
     <lb/>
     close by expressing the hope that the resolu<lb break="no"/>tions would pass by a large majority, as he had 
     <lb/>
     no doubt they would. (Cheers) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. AIKINS said :—I do not believe, 
     <lb/>
     honorable gentlemen, that what occurred in 
     <lb/>
     the Counties Council of York and Peel, to 
     <lb/>
     which the honorable member for the Saugeen 
     <lb/>
     Division referred, can bear the interpretation 
     <lb/>
     that honorable gentleman placed upon it. 
     <lb/>
     The honorable member stated that a large 
     <lb/>
     majority in that council had declared them<lb break="no"/>selves unfavorable to an appeal to the people 
     <lb/>
     on the subject now before the House—the 
     <lb/>
     Confederation of the Provinces. Now, I am 
     <lb/>
     personally acquainted with most of the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of that body, and think a fuller reading 
     <lb/>
     of the proceedings to which the honorable 
     <lb/>
     member referred will place the matter in a 
     <lb/>
     different light-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. MR. MACPHERSON—I read the 
     <lb/>
     whole of the report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. AIKINS—Well, I shall read 
     <lb/>
     it for myself and draw my own conclusions. 
     <lb/>
     [Here the honorable gentleman read the re<lb break="no"/>port again, remarking that there was nothing 
     <lb/>in the speeches of any of the members of the 
     <lb/>Counties Council to show that they were op<lb break="no"/>posed to an appeal to the people, and then 
     <lb/>proceeded] :— The members of the Counties 
     <lb/>
            

    
            <pb n="155" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0155.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">155</fw>
          
     Council were not elected on political grounds, 
     <lb/>
     but to administer the affairs of the munici<lb break="no"/>pality. Any expression of opinion that they 
     <lb/>
     may offer on political subjects is therefore but 
     <lb/>
     the expression of their own individual opinions, 
     <lb/>
     and however much it may be entitled to respect 
     <lb/>
     from the character of the gentlemen composing 
     <lb/>
     the council, it can in no way be regarded as 
     <lb/>
     the expression of their constituents‘ wishes on 
     <lb/>
     the subject. But I contend, moreover, that 
     <lb/>
     the vote in the council was not even an ex<lb break="no"/>pression of opinion on the part of the mem<lb break="no"/>bers ; for we find from the report that several 
     <lb/>
     members opposed the motion for an appeal to 
     <lb/>
     the people, simply on the ground that the 
     <lb/>
     question was one that ought not to have been 
     <lb/>
     brought before them, it being of a purely poli<lb break="no"/>tical character, and they rejected it without 
     <lb/>
     expressing any opinion upon its real merits. 
     <lb/>
     Then, combined with them were the gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     who really oppose the appeal to the people, 
     <lb/>
     and of these two classes was the majority com<lb break="no"/>posed, of which the honorable gentlemen spoke 
     <lb/>
     so exultingly. (Hear, hear.) But apart from 
     <lb/>
     the expression of opinion of the Counties 
     <lb/>
     Council referred to, in whatever light it may 
     <lb/>
     be regarded, I object to the resolutions being 
     <lb/>
     submitted to Parliament and pressed upon 
     <lb/>
     the consideration of this House in the same 
     <lb/>
     way as the Address in reply to the Speech 
     <lb/>
     from the Throne. They are said to be passed 
     <lb/>
     or rejected as a whole, without alteration 
     <lb/>
     or amendment, just as if the Government 
     <lb/>
     were bound to stand or fall by the decision. 
     <lb/>
     The Government, it appears, has pledged 
     <lb/>
     itself to the other governments to abide 
     <lb/>
     by these resolutions, and in that case it 
     <lb/>
     should have been a condition that they should 
     <lb/>
     stand or fall with them. Ministers are op<lb break="no"/>posed further to any expression of opinion on 
     <lb/>
     the contents of these resolutions, other than 
     <lb/>
     what may be stated in the speeches of honor<lb break="no"/>able members ; the resolutions cannot be 
     <lb/>
     changed, modified or amended in any particu<lb break="no"/>lar, and yet the chambers are asked to con<lb break="no"/>sider them ! What is the use of considering 
     <lb/>
     them if we cannot come to our own conclusions 
     <lb/>
     and give them effect in the shape of amend<lb break="no"/>ments ? I stand here as the representative 
     <lb/>
     of, if not one of the largest, at least one of 
     <lb/>
     the most intelligent constituencies in Upper 
     <lb/>
     Canada, and I have no hesitation in saying 
     <lb/>
     the people are generally in favor of the princi<lb break="no"/>ple of the resolutions ; in other words, of a 
     <lb/>
     Confederation of Canada and the Lower Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, but I do not believe they are in favor 
     <lb/>
     of all the details of the project. The Honor<lb break="no"/>able Premier, in moving the resolutions, said 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
           
     they would be productive of two special ad<lb break="no"/>vantages to Canada ;—they would give us 
     <lb/>
     strength and durability, and at the same time 
     <lb/>
     settle the difficulties under which the province 
     <lb/>
     has labored for some years. That honorable 
     <lb/>
     member also stated that if this union is not 
     <lb/>
     accomplished there will be a danger of our 
     <lb/>
     being forced by violence into the United 
     <lb/>
     States ; that, if not forced therein by violence, 
     <lb/>
     we will insensibly slide thither ; and that we 
     <lb/>
     are upon an inclined plane which must of 
     <lb/>
     necessity land us there, and whether by vio<lb break="no"/>lence or by sliding, we must reach that result. 
     <lb/>
     (Hear, hear.) If the Honorable Premier had 
     <lb/>
     shown that the proposed union would in reality 
     <lb/>
     give us strength, and place us in a position to 
     <lb/>
     improve our defences, then I would admit he 
     <lb/>
     had made a good case. I have anxiously 
     <lb/>
     waited to hear his reasons and explanations, 
     <lb/>
     for I wanted better reasons for adopting the 
     <lb/>
     resolutions than any I was acquainted with. 
     <lb/>
     I am anxious to have them carefully analyzed 
     <lb/>
     and scrutinized, and desire that they may be 
     <lb/>
     found in the interest of Canada. If the 
     <lb/>
     Government, in bringing them down, had 
     <lb/>
     stated that after a thorough canvass and ex<lb break="no"/>amination, if deemed desirable, they might 
     <lb/>
     be amended in some particulars, I would have 
     <lb/>
     accepted the declaration with satisfaction and 
     <lb/>
     hope ; but no, though allowed to debate them, 
     <lb/>
     we cannot proceed any further. They are 
     <lb/>
     submitted, as I have already said, like an 
     <lb/>
     opening Speech from the Throne, an amend<lb break="no"/>ment to which is treated as a motion of want 
     <lb/>
     of confidence, and I can see no great use in 
     <lb/>
     discussing them at all. I desire, however, 
     <lb/>
     prior to the taking of the vote, to know how 
     <lb/>
     much the Intercolonial Railway will cost. 
     <lb/>
     Only a short time ago public opinion in Upper 
     <lb/>
     Canada was adverse to this enterprise, but if 
     <lb/>
     new light has dawned upon the subject, I 
     <lb/>
     would be glad to share in it. I would like to 
     <lb/>
     know also what the route will be, and how 
     <lb/>
     many millions it will cost ; and if it should be 
     <lb/>
     shown that its construction will be a real 
     <lb/>
     advantage to the country, I will be prepared 
     <lb/>
     to go for it. There are other points upon 
     <lb/>
     which I desire information, and one is as to 
     <lb/>
     the proportion of the debt which Upper and 
     <lb/>
     Lower Canada will be called upon respectively 
     <lb/>
     to bear. If the sixty-two and a-half millions 
     <lb/>
     of debt the Confederation is to assume is to 
     <lb/>
     be divided according to the extent of the 
     <lb/>
     two populations, will Lower Canada, over and 
     <lb/>
     above its share, assume the amount paid for 
     <lb/>
     the abolition of the Seigniorial Tenure ? These 
     <lb/>
     questions, in my opinion, need answers before 
     <lb/>
     this scheme is carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="156" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0156.jpg"/>
            <p>
     HON. MR. CAMPBELL—There is no 
     <lb/>
     disposition on the part of the Government to 
     <lb/>
     withhold any information the House may 
     <lb/>
     desire to have ;—on the contrary, they are 
     <lb/>
     anxious to afford all in their power,—but the 
     <lb/>
     points suggested by the honorable member are 
     <lb/>
     not yet before the House for discussion. As 
     <lb/>
     to the Seigniorial Tenure debt it will be 
     <lb/>
     assumed entirely by Lower Canada. Then 
     <lb/>
     as to the five millions reserved for a certain 
     <lb/>
     part of the debt, the matter will be disposed 
     <lb/>
     of by a fair division between Upper and Lower 
     <lb/>
     Canada ; and I beg to add that Parliament 
     <lb/>
     will have the opportunity of fully considering 
     <lb/>
     the arrangement which the Government may 
     <lb/>
     propose for that division. An affirmative 
     <lb/>
     proposition will be laid before the House, upon 
     <lb/>
     which members will of course have the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of pronouncing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. AIKINS—I am very much 
     <lb/>
     pleased, indeed, to hear the statement of the 
     <lb/>
    Honorable Commissioner of Crown Lands ; 
     <lb/>but I must say I am at a loss to perceive how 
     <lb/>we shall have an opportunity of considering 
     <lb/>any of these resolutions if we now affirm the 
     <lb/>substantive proposition. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     HON. MR. CAMPBELL—The opportunity 
     <lb/>
     will be afforded when these five millions of 
     <lb/>
     debt come to be distributed between Upper 
     <lb/>
     and Lower Canada, and when bills or propo<lb break="no"/>sitions are brought before Parliament for that 
     <lb/>
    purpose. The intention of the Government 
     <lb/>is to offer propositions which it considers fair 
     <lb/>to both sections of the country, and it will be 
     <lb/>in the power of Parliament, of course, to 
     <lb/>speak and decide in regard to the scheme. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     HON. MR. AIKINS—I am quite willing 
     <lb/>
     to give the Government credit for sincerity on 
     <lb/>
     this question, but before I am called upon to 
     <lb/>
     vote for Confederation, I would like to know, 
     <lb/>
     and I am sure this House would like to know, 
     <lb/>
     not only how much the Intercolonial Railway 
     <lb/>
     is to cost, but how this amount of debt is to 
     <lb/>
     be diffused or distributed between Upper and 
     <lb/>
     Lower Canada. It does appear to me very 
     <lb/>
     important that we should have all these ex<lb break="no"/>planations prior to being called upon to vote 
     <lb/>
     these resolutions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. CAMPBELL—As to the In<lb break="no"/>tercolonial Railway, the honorable gentleman 
     <lb/>
     will see that it is a matter for the Government 
     <lb/>
     of the Confederation to deal with. The only 
     <lb/>
     question for this House to consider is as to 
     <lb/>
     how the five millions of debt is to be distribu<lb break="no"/>ted between the two sections, and as to that 
     <lb/>
     every member will have an opportunity of 
     <lb/>
     assenting  to or differing  from the proposition 
     <lb/>
     of the Government. The question of the rail<lb break="no"/><cb/>way stands on an entirely different footing, 
     <lb/>
     being for the consideration only of the Gene<lb break="no"/>ral Legislature of the union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. AIKINS—I am quite well 
     <lb/>
     aware that the Intercolonial Railway is to be 
     <lb/>
     constructed by the General Government, but 
     <lb/>
     I would like to know now how much it is to 
     <lb/>
     cost. It does appear to me that this is a very 
     <lb/>
     important question, and one that lies at the 
     <lb/>
     root of the whole matter in the minds of many 
     <lb/>
     honorable gentlemen. I know that it affects 
     <lb/>
     me very much. (Hear, hear.) Then, with 
     <lb/>
     regard to the Constitution of this Chamber, 
     <lb/>
     the honorable gentleman who has just taken 
     <lb/>
     his seat (Hon. Mr. BOULTON), and who 
     <lb/>
     comes from Cobourg, has indulged in a gene<lb break="no"/>ral attack upon the elective system, because, 
     <lb/>
     forsooth, several municipalities throughout the 
     <lb/>
     country have borrowed largely from the Loan 
     <lb/>
     Fund, and because the money they so borrowed 
     <lb/>
     has not been properly invested. He argues 
     <lb/>
     from this that the principle of election by the 
     <lb/>
     people should be done away with in this 
     <lb/>
     House. It does appear strange that any hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen should take the narrow and contract<lb break="no"/>ed ground that this Chamber should be appoint<lb break="no"/>ed by the Crown, because certain loans have not 
     <lb/>
     been properly distributed by municipal bodies 
     <lb/>
     —especially strange that an honorable gentle<lb break="no"/>man should take it who represents a munici<lb break="no"/>pality that is very heavily in arrears to the 
     <lb/>
    Loan Fund. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     HON. Ma. BOULTON—I did not allude 
     <lb/>
     to the town of Cobourg at all, but to other 
     <lb/>
     municipalities, where the councils squandered 
     <lb/>
     the money borrowed from the Loan Fund and 
     <lb/>
     put large sums of it into their own pockets. 
     <lb/>
     Cobourg expended the money properly in con<lb break="no"/>nection with a great public work, and acted 
     <lb/>
     honestly, uprightly and properly in the mat<lb break="no"/>ter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     HON. MR. AIKINS—Well, I do not see 
     <lb/>
     why a good thing should be put past the hon<lb break="no"/>orable gentleman himself ; and when he in<lb break="no"/>dulges in an attack upon the elective system, 
     <lb/>
     because certain municipalities have failed to 
     <lb/>
     meet their obligations, I do not see why I 
     <lb/>
     should not point out that Cobourg is a de<lb break="no"/>faulter to a large amount. The honorable 
     <lb/>
     member from the Saugeen Division argues 
     <lb/>
     that the appointment of members of this 
     <lb/>
     House by the Crown is not a disfranchise<lb break="no"/>ment of the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. MACPHERSON—The honor<lb break="no"/>able gentleman is mistaken. What I said was 
     <lb/>
     that, inasmuch as the appointments are to be 
     <lb/>
     made in the way that has been described-<lb/>that is, on the nomination of gentleman re<lb break="no"/><pb n="157" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0157.jpg"/>presenting the people in the other House—the 
     <lb/>
     change does not amount to a disfranchisement. 
     <lb/>
     (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. AIKINS—If the honorable gen<lb break="no"/>tleman had not been quite so sensitive, I would 
     <lb/>
     have saved him the trouble of making his 
     <lb/>
     explanation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. MACPHERSON—I did not 
     <lb/>
     wish to be misrepresented. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. AIKINS—It certainly is not 
     <lb/>
     my desire to misrepresent the honorable gen<lb break="no"/>tleman in any manner. I think the conclu<lb break="no"/>sion one would arrive at, after hearing his 
     <lb/>
     remarks upon the point, is that the people 
     <lb/>
     would still, after this proposed change in the 
     <lb/>
     Constitution, have the power to make ap<lb break="no"/>pointments to this House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. MACPHERSON —No, but 
     <lb/>
     through their representatives. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. AIKINS—The honorable gen<lb break="no"/>tleman says they will have the power, through 
     <lb/>
     their representatives, to make their appoint<lb break="no"/>ments. Well, after reading the fourteenth 
     <lb/>
     resolution, it does appear to me that, after the 
     <lb/>
     first election of the Chamber, the people will 
     <lb/>
     have nothing at all to do with it. (Hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear.) The honorable gentleman says, how<lb break="no"/>ever, that the representatives of the people 
     <lb/>
     will have the power of making these appoint<lb break="no"/>ments. Who are the representatives of the 
     <lb/>
     people he refers to ? The members of the 
     <lb/>
    Government, who will have this power ; or, in 
     <lb/>other words, the Crown will make the ap<lb break="no"/>pointments. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Hon. MR. MACPHERSON—With the 
     <lb/>
     advice of the representatives of the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. AIKINS—Yes, undoubtedly ; 
     <lb/>
     but the people, nevertheless, will have nothing 
     <lb/>
     at all to do with the matter ; we advert again, 
     <lb/>
     in fact, to the old principle when the Crown 
     <lb/>
     made all the appointments. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
     Now, with regard to this question, I feel my<lb break="no"/>self in this position, that although I may be 
     <lb/>
     in favor of the Crown making these appoint<lb break="no"/>ments—upon which principle I express no 
     <lb/>
     opinion at this moment—if I voted for these 
     <lb/>
     resolutions I would give a vote, and every 
     <lb/>
     member of this House would give a vote, by 
     <lb/>
     which they would give themselves seats in 
     <lb/>
     this House as long as Providence thought fit 
     <lb/>
     to let them remain. (Hear, hear.) I came 
     <lb/>
     here, honorable gentlemen, to conserve certain 
     <lb/>
     interests, to represent certain classes, and to 
     <lb/>
     reflect the views of those who sent me here so 
     <lb/>
     far as they accorded with my own judgment. 
     <lb/>
     But they did not send me here to change the 
     <lb/>
     Constitution under which I was appointed, 
     <lb/>
     and to sweep away at one dash the privileges 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
          
     they possess, one of which is, to give a seat in 
     <lb/>
     this House to him in whom they have confi<lb break="no"/>dence. It does not appear right to me that 
     <lb/>
     the members of this House should declare, 
     <lb/>
     by their own votes, that we shall remain here 
     <lb/>
     for all time to come. (Hear, hear.) The 
     <lb/>
     reasons given for the proposed change are 
     <lb/>
     various, and to some extent conflicting. We 
     <lb/>
     find one member of the Government telling us 
     <lb/>
     that it is because the Maritime Provinces are 
     <lb/>
     opposed to an elective Chamber, and hence we 
     <lb/>
     in Canada—the largest community and the 
     <lb/>
     most influential—give way to them, and set 
     <lb/>
     aside a principle that was solemnly adopted 
     <lb/>
     here, and so far has worked without prejudice 
     <lb/>
     to our interests. We find another gentleman, 
     <lb/>
     who, when the question came up years ago, 
     <lb/>
     strongly opposed the elective principle, quite 
     <lb/>
     as strongly opposes it now, because since then 
     <lb/>
     certain municipalities have borrowed more 
     <lb/>
     than they are able to pay ! These are some<lb break="no"/>what extraordinary reasons, and I trust the 
     <lb/>
     House will give them their due weight. I 
     <lb/>
     think, honorable gentlemen, that prior to the 
     <lb/>
     proposed change taking place, we ought not 
     <lb/>
     to declare by our own votes that we are en<lb break="no"/>titled to permanent seats in this House,- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     without, at any rate, knowing whether the 
     <lb/>
     people consent to it or not ; an I do not think 
     <lb/>
    I am wrong in using this line of argument, 
     <lb/>when we have reason to believe that, even if 
     <lb/>the Crown-appointed members remain here, a 
     <lb/>large number of the elected members will also 
     <lb/>remain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     HON. MR. ROSS—How would you act if 
     <lb/>
     you were satisﬁed that the whole public opinion 
     <lb/>
     was in favor of it ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. AIKINS—I can very easily 
     <lb/>
     answer the honorable gentleman. If did not 
     <lb/>
     and could not reflect the views of my con<lb break="no"/>stituents on such an important subject as this, 
     <lb/>
     there is one thing I could do, return to them 
     <lb/>
     the power they placed in my hands. (Hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear.) That is the course I should feel com<lb break="no"/>pelled to take under such circumstances. 
     <lb/>
     (Hear, hear.) With regard to this scheme 
     <lb/>
     altogether, I think that a very great deal 
     <lb/>
     depends upon the resolutions themselves. If 
     <lb/>
     we are to have framed a new Constitution  upon 
     <lb/>
     them as a basis, all of them, in my opinion, 
     <lb/>
     should be thoroughly canvassed and examined ; 
     <lb/>
     and this House, as well as the other branch of 
     <lb/>
     the Legislature, ought not to be prevented by 
     <lb/>
     the Government of the day from expressing 
     <lb/>
     its opinions with regard to their merits. 
     <lb/>
     (Hear.) It is said by many honorable gentle<lb break="no"/>men that the people are in favor of this scheme. 
     <lb/>
     I think the peope are in favor of a scheme 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="158" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0158.jpg"/>
         
     of Confederation, but I think it depends 
     <lb/>
     altogether upon the details of that scheme 
     <lb/>
     whether they will give it their approval or not. 
     <lb/>
     I have no hesitation in declaring what is the 
     <lb/>
     opinion of the people of my division. I meet 
     <lb/>
     and mingle with them almost daily, and have 
     <lb/>
     had ample opportunities of ascertaining their 
     <lb/>
     views and sentiments. I believe that a very 
     <lb/>
     large proportion of them have no fixed and 
     <lb/>
     definite opinions with regard to this scheme. 
     <lb/>
     They are in favor of Confederation, but they 
     <lb/>
     have no definite distinct ideas in regard to the 
     <lb/>
     details of the scheme proposed. If they knew 
     <lb/>
     that their taxation would be largely increased 
     <lb/>
     by it, and that it would add heavily to the 
     <lb/>
     public burdens, they would not support it. 
     <lb/>
     (Hear, hear.) I think, then, that we who are 
     <lb/>
     placed here to conserve and protect the in<lb break="no"/>terests of the public, should be extremely 
     <lb/>
     careful and analyse these resolutions thor<lb break="no"/>oughly, and ascertain, as nearly as possible, 
     <lb/>
     what their effect is likely to be, before we take 
     <lb/>
     the responsibility of voting for them. I have 
     <lb/>
     no hesitation in declaring that there never was 
     <lb/>
     a period in the history of Canada when the 
     <lb/>
     people suffered more than they do at present. 
     <lb/>
     (Hear, hear.) In consequence of the per<lb break="no"/>sonal, municipal and national indebtedness, 
     <lb/>
     the farmers of the country were never placed 
     <lb/>
     in a worse position than that which they now 
     <lb/>
     occupy. (Hear, hear.) When we find that 
     <lb/>
     property has depreciated in value within the 
     <lb/>
     last five years, twenty, thirty, forty, ay, and 
     <lb/>
     even sixty per cent. ; when we find that the 
     <lb/>
     crops of the country have been steadily de<lb break="no"/>creasing in quantity and value within that 
     <lb/>
     period ; when we find that the people are dis<lb break="no"/>satisfied with the manner in which the coun<lb break="no"/>try has been governed during the last eight or 
     <lb/>
     ten years ; when we find all this, we may be<lb break="no"/>lieve that they are prepared to accept almost 
     <lb/>
     any change that promises a relief from their 
     <lb/>
     present difficulties. But we were placed here 
     <lb/>
     to conserve their interests, to look after their 
     <lb/>
     welfare, and should not hastily adopt any 
     <lb/>
     scheme, proposed by any Government- <lb/> whether all of one party stripe or not-<lb/> without fully examining it and weighing the 
     <lb/>
     results likely to flow from it. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
     It is said that the public is well acquainted 
     <lb/>
     with the nature of the scheme. I demur to 
     <lb/>
     that statement <hi rendition="simple:italic">in toto</hi>. The public is not 
     <lb/>
     acquainted with it in all its bearings, and if 
     <lb/>
     there is one thing I regret, it is this, that it 
     <lb/>
     has not been made a party measure. (Hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear.) I regret this because, although perhaps 
     <lb/>
     no party could have carried it as a party 
     <lb/>
     measure through this Legislature, it would 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
           
     have been better if proposed as a party 
     <lb/>
     scheme, for then its merits would have been 
     <lb/>
     more thoroughly canvassed and its demerits 
     <lb/>
     more thoroughly exposed. Our public men 
     <lb/>
     would have ranged themselves on either side ; 
     <lb/>
     some would have favored it, and others would 
     <lb/>
     have opposed it ; they would have pointed out 
     <lb/>
     its defects as well as its good points ; the 
     <lb/>
     whole subject would have been fully venti<lb break="no"/>lated, and the result would have been that, 
     <lb/>
     if passed at all, the scheme would have been 
     <lb/>
     as perfect as it was possible to have made it. 
     <lb/>
     But what do you find now ? You scarcely 
     <lb/>
     see a newspaper from one end of the country 
     <lb/>
     to the other that is not full of laudations of 
     <lb/>
     the scheme. And why ? Because the leading 
     <lb/>
     public men of the country have thought proper 
     <lb/>
     to make a fusion ; the leading daily journals on 
     <lb/>
     both sides applaud the step and the scheme 
     <lb/>
     that followed, and the small papers through<lb break="no"/>out the province, as in duty bound, follow 
     <lb/>
     in their wake. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. CAMPBELL—They only ex<lb break="no"/>press public opinion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. AIKINS—Public opinion, the 
     <lb/>
     honorable gentleman says. I say that public 
     <lb/>
     opinion has not sufficiently weighed this scheme, 
     <lb/>
     and that we should be influenced here by our 
     <lb/>
     own matured opinion in regard to it. (Hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear.) As I have already stated, I am in 
     <lb/>
     favor of the confederation of these provinces, 
     <lb/>
     framed on a proper basis ; and all I desire is 
     <lb/>
     that we should have the opportunity of exam<lb break="no"/>ining all these resolutions, and if we object to 
     <lb/>
     any of them, finding them imperfect or un<lb break="no"/>suitable, that we should have power to amend 
     <lb/>
     them. (Hear, hear.) So far as the amend<lb break="no"/>ment that has been proposed is concerned, 
     <lb/>
     there are portions of it with which I cordially 
     <lb/>
     agree. After it has been thoroughly discussed 
     <lb/>
     I shall, like other honorable members, make 
     <lb/>
     up my mind as to what course I shall pursue 
     <lb/>
     in reference to it. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. REESOR—As no one has taken 
     <lb/>
     the floor to continue the debate, I beg to 
     <lb/>
     enquire of the Honorable Commissioner of 
     <lb/>
     Crown Lands why it is that certain export 
     <lb/>
     duties are allowed under this scheme to be 
     <lb/>
     collected by the local governments in New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick and Nova Scotia, but which in 
     <lb/>
     Canada are collected by the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment ? It is part of the forty-third resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, which reads:—“ The local legislatures 
     <lb/>
     shall have power to make laws respecting the 
     <lb/>
     following subjects : Direct taxation, and in 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick the imposition of duties on 
     <lb/>
     the export of timber, logs, masts, spars, deals 
     <lb/>
     and sawn lumber ; and in Nova Scotia, of 
     <lb/>
        
            <pb n="159" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0159.jpg"/>
        
     coal and other minerals.” That, it appears 
     <lb/>
     to me, is leaving very valuable material to be 
     <lb/>
     subject to taxation by these local governments, 
     <lb/>
     for they comprise a very large proportion of 
     <lb/>
     the exports of the country. This is giving a 
     <lb/>
     great preference to the eastern provinces in 
     <lb/>
     regard to powers of taxation. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
     Then, again, as stated by the President of the 
     <lb/>
     Council, in another place, the sum of $63,000 
     <lb/>
     a year is to be given as a sort of gratuity to 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick for a period of ten years. 
     <lb/>
     When these things are taken into considera<lb break="no"/>tion, certainly it seems that our public men 
     <lb/>
     representing Canada in the Conference have 
     <lb/>
     gone to work in a rather reckless manner. 
     <lb/>
    They have apparently been regardless of ex<lb break="no"/>pense on the part of Canada, while particularly 
     <lb/>careful to meet every objection to union on 
     <lb/>the part of the Lower Provinces. It would 
     <lb/>appear that because Canada is the largest 
     <lb/>colony, they were willing to grant everything 
     <lb/>that the other colonies asked. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>It seems extraordinary too that these gentle<lb break="no"/>men should have passed a scheme binding the 
     <lb/>Government to construct the Intercolonial 
     <lb/>Railway without any understanding or know<lb break="no"/>ledge as to what it will cost. (Hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     HON. MR. CAMPBELL—It will be some<lb break="no"/>what inconvenient for a member of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to answer at once the questions put 
     <lb/>
     by the honorable member, but I have no ob<lb break="no"/>jection to answer those which he has now 
     <lb/>
     asked. The House understands, of course, 
     <lb/>
     that the Crown lands of the provinces are 
     <lb/>
     retained under the Confederation scheme by 
     <lb/>
     each individual province. It was found ne<lb break="no"/>cessary that they should be retained in order 
     <lb/>
     to provide each province with the required 
     <lb/>
     funds to carry on the local government. In 
     <lb/>
     the province of New Brunswick the duties 
     <lb/>
     that are levied in Canada as “ stumpage dues” 
     <lb/>
     on cutting down timber, are not levied in the 
     <lb/>
     woods but collected at the ports as export 
     <lb/>
     duties, this being in that province a more con<lb break="no"/>venient and less expensive mode of obtaining 
     <lb/>
     revenue from the timber trade. Now, the 
     <lb/>
     honorable gentleman will see that if we do 
     <lb/>
     not allow the Local Government in New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick to collect these dues in this way, 
     <lb/>
     the revenue which is derived in Canada from 
     <lb/>
     “ stumpage dues,” would be lost to New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick. That is the reason why the ex<lb break="no"/>ception he refers to was made. In the same 
     <lb/>
     way, with reference to Nova Scotia, was al<lb break="no"/>lowed the royalty on coal, that is the percentage 
     <lb/>
     of the product of the mines reserved for the 
     <lb/>
     use of the Government, which is collected as a 
     <lb/>
     duty on the export of the article. There also 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
      
     the export duty is reserved as a source of 
     <lb/>
     revenue to the Local Government, it being 
     <lb/>
    necessary in both cases that they should have 
     <lb/>the advantage of their territorial revenue in 
     <lb/>the same way as the local governments in 
     <lb/>Canada, which will collect the same revenue 
     <lb/>in a different way. At the first glance it may 
     <lb/>seem that this clause gives especial advan<lb break="no"/>tages to the Lower Provinces not conferred 
     <lb/>upon the local governments here, but this is 
     <lb/>not the case. (Hear, hear.) Then, with re<lb break="no"/>gard to the subvention of $63,000 a year to 
     <lb/>New Brunswick for a period of ten years, it 
     <lb/>was found necessary because during that time 
     <lb/>it would be impossible for New Brunswick 
     <lb/>out of its local revenue to carry out the un<lb break="no"/>dertakings upon which the province had en<lb break="no"/>tered. The honorable gentleman said, and I 
     <lb/>regret to hear the statement, that the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of Canada must have been reckless, 
     <lb/>and that as the Lower Provinces made de<lb break="no"/>mands conditional upon entering the union, 
     <lb/>we had to submit with what grace we could. 
     <lb/>All I can say is that I wish very heartily that 
     <lb/>those gentlemen who thus find fault had been 
     <lb/>at the Conference, and then they would have 
     <lb/>had an opportunity of judging whether in<lb break="no"/>deed we were reckless or not ; and I must 
     <lb/>say to my honorable friend, whom I have had 
     <lb/>the pleasure of knowing for some years, that 
     <lb/>if he had truly known the representatives of 
     <lb/>Canada on that occasion, he would have 
     <lb/>spared us to-day the imputation made against 
     <lb/>them that they were reckless. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>The $63,000 were given to New Brunswick 
     <lb/>because it was found that with the local rev<lb break="no"/>enue allowed her it would have been impossi<lb break="no"/>ble for her to fulfil her engagements. It 
     <lb/>would of course have been idle to have gone 
     <lb/>into a confederation and find that the revenues 
     <lb/>of that colony had been so far ceded to us 
     <lb/>that she was unable to meet the obligations 
     <lb/>into which she had entered, and that the Con<lb break="no"/>federation would be responsible for the claims 
     <lb/>of her creditors. The engagements into which 
     <lb/>she had entered involved a subvention of the 
     <lb/>railways of the province. In New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick they thought it better, rather than take 
     <lb/>the shares or mortgages of a railway for the 
     <lb/>encouragement of railway enterprise, to give a 
     <lb/>certain sum at once for railway purposes. Any 
     <lb/>company constructing a railway became entitled 
     <lb/>to a certain sum per mile out of the public funds. 
     <lb/>Thus liabilities were incurred which of course 
     <lb/>it was necessary to redeem. Well, New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick having ceded all her ordinary revenues 
     <lb/>to the General Government, means had to be 
     <lb/>provided by it to enable her to meet these 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="160" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0160.jpg"/>
            
     liabilities. And I may say that these rail<lb break="no"/>ways, which are among the public works 
     <lb/>
    ceded to the General Government, are not 
     <lb/>valueless. They yield a revenue to the pub<lb break="no"/>lic exchequer. I do not remember the exact 
     <lb/>sum, but it is about $6,000 or $8,000 per 
     <lb/>annum. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. CURRIE—That is exactly 
     <lb/>
     three-eighths of one per cent. of their cost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. CAMPBELL—Well, I said 
     <lb/>
     they yielded a revenue—I did not say what 
     <lb/>
     proportion it bore to their cost—and when 
     <lb/>
     we give this sum we know, that we are 
     <lb/>
     not entirely without a return for it. Un<lb break="no"/>less we made some provision for this pay<lb break="no"/>ment we would have been unable to carry 
     <lb/>
     out the scheme, and there is a fair proba<lb break="no"/>bility of these works becoming more pro<lb break="no"/>ductive. Of course, some gentlemen may 
     <lb/>
     say that it was possible to have given the other 
     <lb/>
    provinces equivalents for this expenditure in 
     <lb/>New Brunswick, but we all know how un<lb break="no"/>favorable to our finances has been this system 
     <lb/>of equivalents. (Hear, hear.) A similar 
     <lb/>sum might have been granted to the other 
     <lb/>provinces, but that would have been nothing 
     <lb/>but extravagance, which, I am sure, the 
     <lb/>country would be slow to sanction, in view of 
     <lb/>the past experience in this province in the 
     <lb/>system of equivalents. (Hear, hear.) This, 
     <lb/>we all felt convinced, was the most economical 
     <lb/>and prudent course to have followed in order 
     <lb/>to obtain the end of Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     HON. MR. SIMPSON—I would like to ask 
     <lb/>
     the Commissioner of Crown Lands whether, 
     <lb/>
     supposing I sent a vessel from Montreal with 
     <lb/>
     flour to a lower port, and it returned with a 
     <lb/>
     cargo of coal, there would be an export duty 
     <lb/>
     upon it in Nova Scotia ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. CAMPBELL—I am not aware 
     <lb/>
     that there would be, but upon this point I 
     <lb/>
    speak under correction. That is a question 
     <lb/>which, if the honorable gentleman desires ex<lb break="no"/>plicit information, I would like to reserve for 
     <lb/>a future occasion. If questions are put, not 
     <lb/>to embarrass the passage of the scheme before 
     <lb/>the House, but to elicit information on par<lb break="no"/>ticular points, I shall prepare myself to answer 
     <lb/>them as fully as possible. (Hear, hear.) I 
     <lb/>am sure, however, no honorable gentleman 
     <lb/>would put questions with a view of embar<lb break="no"/>rassing the subject, but simply to obtain in<lb break="no"/>formation on certain points. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     HON. MR. SIMPSON—I have no desire to 
     <lb/>
     ask questions in order to create embarrass<lb break="no"/>ment, but this is a question forced upon me 
     <lb/>
     by the explanations that have been made, and 
     <lb/>
     while I am up I may ask another. I will not 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
          
     discuss how much Upper Canada gives to the 
     <lb/>
     General Government under this scheme, but 
     <lb/>
     it strikes me as singular that in making these 
     <lb/>
     compensations the Conference gave them all 
     <lb/>
     to the Lower Provinces. Why was not this 
     <lb/>
     money required by New Brunswick raised by 
     <lb/>
     direct taxation, and the colonies thus placed 
     <lb/>
     on an equal footing ? (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. ROSS—Because the income of 
     <lb/>
     these railways in New Brunswick accrues to 
     <lb/>
     the General Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. SIMPSON—But they pay 
     <lb/>
    nothing. 
     <lb/>HON. MR. ROSS—They do pay something 
     <lb/>now, and in future they will pay more. I, 
     <lb/>however, speak only from my own individual 
     <lb/>point of view, and not from any knowledge 
     <lb/>other than that in possession of the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     HON. MR. SIMPSON—And I speak from 
     <lb/>
     the same, and think the objection I have made 
     <lb/>
    good. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     HON. MR. ROSS—As to the export duty 
     <lb/>
     on coal from Nova Scotia, it appears from the 
     <lb/>
     resolutions that the equivalent given to Upper 
     <lb/>
     Canada for this revenue is the duty on Crown 
     <lb/>
     timber. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. SIMPSON—Well, what about 
     <lb/>
     the fishery dues given to the Lower Provinces ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. ROSS—We will have that by 
     <lb/>
     and by. I am only answering one question 
     <lb/>
     now. It is in lieu of the duty we levy on 
     <lb/>
     timber, and known as “ stumpage dues,” that 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia is allowed to levy an export duty 
     <lb/>
     on coal. The honorable gentleman shakes his 
     <lb/>
     head, but it is a fact. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. SIMPSON—It is not on the 
     <lb/>
     stump that we levy dues, but as the hewn 
     <lb/>
     timber passes through the slides. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. ROSS—Well, it is not an ex<lb break="no"/>port duty at any rate ; but in New Brunswick 
     <lb/>
     it pays a duty when exported, either as saw- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     logs or square timber. In both cases it pays 
     <lb/>
     a duty to the Local Government, and it only 
     <lb/>
     seems reasonable that Nova Scotia should en<lb break="no"/>joy a revenue from her coal wherever it goes 
     <lb/>
     (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. MOORE—If the coal were ex<lb break="no"/>ported to a foreign country, then I could un<lb break="no"/>derstand why a duty should be imposed, but 
     <lb/>
     when a ship is laden in one port of the Con<lb break="no"/>federation, with coal, for another port in the 
     <lb/>
     same country, it does not appear much like a 
     <lb/>
     free Confederation if an export duty is levied 
     <lb/>
     upon the cargo. (Hear, hear.) There would 
     <lb/>
     seem, then, to be a distinction—a preference 
     <lb/>
     for one portion over another—within the 
     <lb/>
     limits of the Confederation. If we are to have 
     <lb/>
     a union, I hope we shall have it in fact and 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="161" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-10_Page_0161.jpg"/>
          
     not in name alone. I should like to be fully 
     <lb/>
     informed as to whether an export duty is to 
     <lb/>
     be levied on coal in Nova Scotia, no matter 
     <lb/>
     whether it is intended for another part of the 
     <lb/>
     Confederation or for a foreign country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. CAMPBELL—The royalty col<lb break="no"/>lected on coal in Nova Scotia is similar to the 
     <lb/>
     stumpage duty on timber in Canada, which is 
     <lb/>
     paid no matter where the timber is exported 
     <lb/>
     to. It may well be, therefore, that when coal 
     <lb/>
     is exported from Nova Scotia to another pro<lb break="no"/>vince it will contribute to the revenues of the 
     <lb/>
     Local Government of Nova Scotia. (Hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. REESOR—There are several 
     <lb/>
     other provisions in the proposed Constitution 
     <lb/>
     which seem to be ambiguous in their meaning, 
     <lb/>
     and before discussion upon them it would be 
     <lb/>
     well to have them fully explained. In the 
     <lb/>
     eleventh clause of the twenty-ninth resolution, 
     <lb/>
     for instance, it is declared that the General 
     <lb/>
     Parliament shall have power to make laws 
     <lb/>
     respecting “ all such works as shall, although 
     <lb/>
     lying  wholly within any province, be specially 
     <lb/>
     declared by the acts authorizing them to be 
     <lb/>
     for the general advantage.” It would appear 
     <lb/>
     from this, that works like the Welland canal, 
     <lb/>
     which yield a very large revenue, will be given 
     <lb/>
     over to the General Government ; and this 
     <lb/>
     being the case, surely this is a sufficient set- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     off, five times over, for the railways given by 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick, without the annual subsidy 
     <lb/>
     proposed to be given to that province of 
     <lb/>
     $63,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. MACPHERSON—The cost of 
     <lb/>
     these works forms part of the public debt of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, which is to be borne in part by the 
     <lb/>
     Lower Provinces under the Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. CAMPBELL—The honorable 
     <lb/>
     gentleman will see that there are some works 
     <lb/>
     which, although local in their geographical 
     <lb/>
     position, are general in their character and 
     <lb/>
     results. Such works become the property 
     <lb/>
     of the General Government. The Welland  
     <lb/>
     canal is one of them, because, although it is 
     <lb/>
     local in its position, it is a work in which 
     <lb/>
     the whole country is interested, as the chief 
     <lb/>
     means of water communication between the 
     <lb/>
     western lakes and the sea. Other works, in 
     <lb/>
    the Lower Provinces, may be of the same 
     <lb/>character, and it is not safe to say that be<lb break="no"/>cause a certain work lies wholly in one pro<lb break="no"/>vince, it is not to belong to the General Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     HON. MR. REESOR—I do not object to 
     <lb/>
     the General Government having the control 
     <lb/>
     of these works. It is, I believe, a wise pro<lb break="no"/>vision to place them under such control. But 
     <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
           
     I do say that it is unfair that an express stip<lb break="no"/>ulation should be made to pay one province a 
     <lb/>
     large sum per annum for certain works, while, 
     <lb/>
     at the same time, we throw in our public 
     <lb/>
     works, such as the Welland and St. Lawrence 
     <lb/>
     canals, without any consideration whatever. 
     <lb/>
     This, I think, is paying quite too much for 
     <lb/>
     the whistle. Then the answer of the Com<lb break="no"/>missioner of Crown Lands about the export 
     <lb/>
     duty on minerals in Nova Scotia is not at all 
     <lb/>
     satisfactory. Whatever dues may be levied 
     <lb/>
     on minerals in Canada—and Canada, although 
     <lb/>
     it may contain no coal, is rich in gold, silver, 
     <lb/>
     copper, iron, and other ores—in the shape of 
     <lb/>
     a royalty or otherwise, go to the General 
     <lb/>
     Government, while in Nova Scotia they ac<lb break="no"/>crue for the benefit of the Local Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. ROSS—No, they will not go to 
     <lb/>
     the General Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. REESOR—Well, there is no<lb break="no"/>thing to the contrary in the resolutions, and 
     <lb/>
     you may depend upon it that whatever reve<lb break="no"/>nues the General Government may claim, 
     <lb/>
     under the proposed Constitution, will be fully 
     <lb/>
     insisted upon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. CAMPBELL—My honorable 
     <lb/>
     friend, referring a moment ago to the Welland 
     <lb/>
     and other canals, objected to certain works 
     <lb/>
     being considered as belonging to the General 
     <lb/>
     Government, because they are local in their 
     <lb/>
     geographical position. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. REESOR—I do not say that 
     <lb/>
     they should not go to the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, but what I do say is that they are a 
     <lb/>
     sufficient set-off for the works given by the 
     <lb/>
     Lower Provinces, without paying them a 
     <lb/>
     special sum from the general revenues of 
     <lb/>
     $63,000 per annum. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A Message from the Legislative Assembly 
     <lb/>
     interrupted further discussion upon the sub<lb break="no"/>ject, and the House afterwards adjourned 
     <lb/>
     without resuming it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<!-- GL, 2016-12-05, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
      
            <!--<p>
     MONDAY, February 13, 1865.    
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     HON. MR. REESOR—Honorable gentle<lb break="no"/>men, as the question now under considera<lb break="no"/>tion involves a change in the constitution, not 
     <lb/>
     only of this House but of the whole of the 
     <lb/>
     British American Provinces, I think that more 
     <lb/>
     time ought to be given to it ; and my object 
     <lb/>
     in now rising, is to urge upon this Honorable 
     <lb/>
     House the propriety of adjourning this de<lb break="no"/>bate—say for ten ays. (No! no!) Many 
     <lb/>
     new features have been developed since the 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>