<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgPCLC_1865-02-03" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPCLCoun">Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1865-02-03">3 February 1865</date>, Province of Canada, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          
          
         
               <title>Parliamentary Debates on the Subject of the Confederation of the British North American Provinces, 3rd Session, 8th Provincial Parliament of Canada</title>.
                    

                    

          <date when="1865"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Quebec</pubPlace>: <publisher>Hunter, Rose &amp; Co., Parliamentary Printers</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="13"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0001.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0002.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0003.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0004.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0005.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0006.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0007.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0008.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0009.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0010.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0011.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0012.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0013.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-01">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-01">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0001">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0002">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0002.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0003">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0003.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0004">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0004.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0005">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0005.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0006">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0006.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0007">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0007.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0008">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0008.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0009">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0009.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0010">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0010.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0011">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0011.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0012">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0012.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0013">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0013.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0001.jpg"/>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">PARLIAMENTARY DEBATES<lb/>
         
    ON THE 
     <lb/>
           
     SUBJECT OF THE CONFEDERATION OF THE BRITISH 
     <lb/>
     NORTH AMERICAN PROVINCES. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre"><hi rendition="simple:italic">Third Session, Eighth Provincial Parliament 0f Canada, in the 
     <lb/>
    Twenty-eighth year of the the Reign of Her Majesty</hi> Queen 
     <lb/>VICTORIA.</head>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL.</head>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">FRIDAY, <hi rendition="simple:italic">February</hi> 3, 1865.</head>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TACH1">Hon. Sir E. P. TACHÉ</persName> moved, "That 
     <lb/>
     an humble Address be presented to Her 
     <lb/>
     Maestyj , praying that She may be graciously 
     <lb/>
     pleased to cause a measure to be submitted to 
     <lb/>
     the Imperial Parliament for the purpose of 
     <lb/>
     uniting the Colonies of Canada, Nova Scotia, 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick, Newfoundland, and Prince 
     <lb/>
     Edward Island, in one Government, with pro<lb break="no"/>visions based on the following Resolutions, 
     <lb/>
     which were adopted at a Conference of Dele<lb break="no"/>gates from the said Colonies, held at the city 
     <lb/>
     of Quebec, on the 10th of October, 1864 :" 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>
     1. The best interests and present and future 
     <lb/>
     prosperity of British North America will be pro<lb break="no"/>moted by a Federal Union under the Crown of 
     <lb/>
     Great Britain, provided such Union can be effect<lb break="no"/>ed on principles just to the several Provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2. In the Federation of the British North 
     <lb/>
     American Provinces, the system of Government 
     <lb/>
     best adapted under existing circumstances to pro<lb break="no"/>tect the diversified interest of the several Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, and secure efficiency, harmony and per<lb break="no"/>manency in the working of the Union, would be 
     <lb/>
     a General Government, charged with matters of 
     <lb/>
     common interest to the w ole country ; and 
     <lb/>
     Local Governments for each of the Canadas, and 
     <lb/>
     for the Provinces of Nova Scotia, New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick and Prince Edward Island, charged with the 
     <lb/>
     control of local matters in their respective sec<lb break="no"/>tions. Provision being made for the admission 
     <lb/>
     into the Union, on equitable terms, of Newfound<lb break="no"/>land, the North—West Territory, British Columbia 
     <lb/>
     and Vancouver. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3. In framing a Constitution for the General 
     <lb/>
     Government, the Conference, with a view to the 
     <lb/>
     perpetuation of our connection with the Mother 
     <lb/>
    
            <cb/>
        
     Country, and the promotion of the best interests 
     <lb/>
     ot' the people of these Provinces, desire to follow 
     <lb/>
     the model of the British Constitution, so far as 
     <lb/>
     our circumstances will permit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4. The Executive Authority or Government 
     <lb/>
     shall be vested in the Sovereign of the United 
     <lb/>
     Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, and be 
     <lb/>
     administered according to the well-understood 
     <lb/>
    principles of the British Constitution, by the 
     <lb/>Sovereign personally, or by the Representative of 
     <lb/>the Sovereign duly authorized. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>5. The Sovereign or Representative of the 
     <lb/>Sovereign shall be Commander-in-Chief of the 
     <lb/>Land and Naval Militia Forces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     6. There shall be a General Legislature or 
     <lb/>
     Parliament for the Federated Provinces, com<lb break="no"/>posed of a Legislative Council and a House of 
     <lb/>
     Commons. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     7. For the purpose of forming the Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Council, the Federated Provinces shall be con<lb break="no"/>sidered as consisting of three divisions: lst, 
     <lb/>
     Upper Canada; 2nd, Lower Canada ; 3rd, Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia, New Brunswick and Prince Edward 
     <lb/>
     Island; each division with au equal representa<lb break="no"/>tion in the Legislative Council. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     8. Upper Canada shall be represented in the 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Council by 24 Members, Lower Cana<lb break="no"/>da by 24 Members, and the three Maritime Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces by 24 Members, of which Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>
     shall have 10 New Brunswick 10, and Prince 
     <lb/>
     Edward Island 4 Members. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     9. The Colony of Newfoundland shall be enti<lb break="no"/>tled to enter the proposed Union with a repre 
     <lb/>
     sentation in the Legislative Council of 4 Members. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     10. The North- West Territory, British Colum<lb break="no"/>bia and Vancouver shall be admitted into the 
     <lb/>
     Union on such terms and conditions as the Par<lb break="no"/>liament of the Federated Provinces shall deem 
     <lb/>
     equitable, and as shall receive the assent of Her 
     <lb/>
    Majesty; and in the case of the Province of Bri<lb break="no"/>tish Columbia or Vancouver, as shall be agreed 
     <lb/>to by the Legislature of such Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     11. The Members of the Legislative Council 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="2" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0002.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2</fw>
           
     shall be appointed by the Crown under the Great 
     <lb/>
     Seal of the General Government, and shall hold 
     <lb/>
     office during life: if any Legislative Councillor 
     <lb/>
     shall, for two consecutive sessions of Parliament, 
     <lb/>
     fail to give his attendance in the said Council, his 
     <lb/>
     seat shall thereby become vacant. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     12. The Members of the Legislative Council 
     <lb/>
     shall be British subjects by birth or naturaliza<lb break="no"/>tion, of the full age of thirty years, shall possess 
     <lb/>
     a continuous real property qualification of four 
     <lb/>
     thousand dollars over and above all incumbrances, 
     <lb/>
     and shall be and continue worth that sum over 
     <lb/>
     and above their debts and liabilities, but in the 
     <lb/>
     case of Newfoundland and Prince Edward Island, 
     <lb/>
     the property may be either real or personal. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     13. If any question shall arise as to the quali<lb break="no"/>fication of a Legislative Councillor, the same 
     <lb/>
     shall be determined by the Council. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     14. The first selection of the Members of the 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Council shall be made, except as re<lb break="no"/>gards Prince Edward Island, from the Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Councils of the various Provinces so far as a 
     <lb/>
     sufficient number be found qualified and willing 
     <lb/>
     toserve; such Members shall be appointed by 
     <lb/>
     the Crown at the recommendation of the General 
     <lb/>
     Executive Government. upon the nomination of 
     <lb/>
     the respective LocalGovcrnments, and in such 
     <lb/>
     nomination due regard shall he had to the claims 
     <lb/>
     of the Members of the Legislative Council of the 
     <lb/>
     Opposition in each Province, so that all political 
     <lb/>
     parties may, as near ly as possible, be fairly repre<lb break="no"/>sented. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     15. The Speaker of the Legislative Council 
     <lb/>
     (unless otherwise provided by Parliament), shall 
     <lb/>
     be appointed by the Crown from among the Mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Legislative Council, and shall hold 
     <lb/>
     office during pleasure, and shall only be entitled 
     <lb/>
     to a casting vote on an equality of votes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     16. Each of the twenty-four Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cillors representing Lower Canada in the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Council of the General Legislature shall be 
     <lb/>
     appointed to represent one of the twenty-four 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Electoral l ivisions mentioned in Schedule A of 
     <lb/>
     Chapter first of the Consolidated Statutes of Can<lb break="no"/>ada, and such Councillor shall reside or possess 
     <lb/>
     his qualification in the Division he is appointed 
     <lb/>
     to represent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     17. The basis of Representation in the House 
     <lb/>
     of Commons shall be Population, as determined 
     <lb/>
     by the Official Census every ten years ; and the 
     <lb/>
     number of Members at first shall be 194, distrib<lb break="no"/>ted as follows: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
     <table>
     <row><cell>Upper Canada ..................</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">82</cell> </row> 
     <row><cell>Lower Canada ...... . .........</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">65</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>Nova Scotia ...................</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">19</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>New Brunswick .................</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">15</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>Newfoundland ......... . ........</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">8</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>Prince Edward Island ............</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">5</cell> </row>
     </table>
   
            <p>
     18. Until the Official Census of 1871 has been 
     <lb/>
     made up, there shall be no change in the number 
     <lb/>
     of Representatives from the several sections. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     19. Immediately after the completion of the 
     <lb/>
     Census of 1871, and immediately after every de<lb break="no"/>cennial census thereafter, the Representation from 
     <lb/>
     each section in the House of Commons shall be 
     <lb/>
     readjusted on the basis of Population. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     20. For the purpose of such readjustments, 
     <lb/>
     Lower Canada shall always be assigned sixty-five 
     <lb/>
     Members, and each of the other sections shall, at 
     <lb/>
     each readjustment, receive, for the ten years 
     <lb/>
     then next succeeding, the number of Members to 
     <lb/>
     which it will be entitled on the same ratio of 
     <lb/>
     Representation to Population as Lower Canada 
     <lb/>
     will enjoy according to the Census last taken by 
     <lb/>
     having sixty-five Members. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     21. No reduction shall be made in the number 
     <lb/>
     of Members returned by any section, unless its 
     <lb/>
     population shall have decreased, relatively to the 
     <lb/>
     population of the whole Union, to the extent of 
     <lb/>
     five per centum. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     22. In computing at each decennial period the 
     <lb/>
     number of Members to which each section is en<lb break="no"/>titled, no fractional parts shall be considered, 
     <lb/>
     unless when exceeding one-half the number en<lb break="no"/>titling to a Member, in which case a Member 
     <lb/>
     shall be given for each such fractional part. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     23. The Legislature of each Province shall 
     <lb/>
     divide such Province into the proper number of 
     <lb/>
     constituencies, and define the boundaries of each 
     <lb/>
     of them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     24. The Local Legislature of each Province 
     <lb/>
     may, from time to time, alter the Electoral Dis<lb break="no"/>tricts for the purposes of Representation in such 
     <lb/>
     Local Legislature, and distribute the Represen<lb break="no"/>tatives to which the Province is entitled in such 
     <lb/>
     Local Legislature, in any manner such Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture may see fit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     25. The number of Members may at any time be 
     <lb/>
     increased by the General Parliament—regard be<lb break="no"/>ing had to the proportionate rights then existing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     26. Until provisions are made by the General 
     <lb/>
     Parliament, all the laws which, at that date of 
     <lb/>
     the Proclamation constituting the Union, are in 
     <lb/>
     force in the Provinces respectively, relating to 
     <lb/>
     the qualification and disqualification of any per<lb break="no"/>son to be elected, or to sit or vote as a Member 
     <lb/>
     of the Assembly in the said Provinces respective<lb break="no"/>ly ; and relating to the qualification or disqualifi<lb break="no"/>cation of voters and to the oaths to be taken by 
     <lb/>
     voters, and to Returning Officers and their pow<lb break="no"/>ers and duties,—and relating to the proceedings 
     <lb/>
     at Elections,—and to the period during which 
     <lb/>
     such elections may be continued—and relating 
     <lb/>
     to the Trial of Controverted Elections. and the 
     <lb/>
     proceedings incident thereto,—and relating to the 
     <lb/>
     vacating of seats of Members, and to the issuing 
     <lb/>
     and execution of new Writs, in case of any seat 
     <lb/>
     being vacated otherwise than by a dissolution<lb break="no"/>shall respectively apply to elections of Members 
     <lb/>
     to serve in the House of Commons, for places 
     <lb/>
     situate in those Provinces respectively. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     27. Every House of Commons shall continue 
     <lb/>
     for five years from the day of the return of the 
     <lb/>
     writs choosing the same, and no longer; subject, 
     <lb/>
     nevertheless, to be sooner prorogued or dissolved 
     <lb/>
     by the Governor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     28. There shall be a Session of the General 
     <lb/>
     Parliament once, at least, in every year, so that 
     <lb/>
     a period of twelve calendar months shall not in<lb break="no"/>tervene between the last sitting of the General 
     <lb/>
     Parliament in one Session, and the first sitting 
     <lb/>
     thereof in the neat Session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0003.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">3</fw>
            <p>
     29. The General Parliament shall have power 
     <lb/>
     to make Laws for the peace, welfare and good 
     <lb/>
     government of the Federated Provinces (saving 
     <lb/>
    the Sovereignty of England), and especially laws 
     <lb/>respecting the following subjects :-<lb/>
            </p>
<table>
            <row><cell>l. The Public Debt and Property. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>2. The regulation of Trade and Commerce.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>3. The imposition or regulation of Duties of 
     <lb/>
     Customs on Imports and Experts,<lb break="no"/>except on Exports of Timber, Logs, 
     <lb/>
     Masts, Spars, Deals and Sawn Lum<lb break="no"/>ber from New Brunswick, and of Coal 
     <lb/>
     and other minerals from Nova Scotia.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>4. The imposition or regulation of Excise 
     <lb/>Duties. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>5. The raising of money by all or any other 
     <lb/>
     modes or systems of Taxation. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>6. The borrowing of money on the Public 
     <lb/>
     Credit.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>7. Postal Service.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>8. Lines of Steam or other Ships, Railways, 
     <lb/>
     Canals and other works, connecting 
     <lb/>
     any two or more of the Provinces 
     <lb/>
     together, or extending beyond the 
     <lb/>
     limits of any Province.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>9 . Lines of Steamships between the Feder<lb break="no"/>ated Provinces and other Countries.</cell></row> 
    <row><cell>10. Telegraph Communication and the Incor<lb break="no"/>poration of Telegraph Companies. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>11. All such works as shall, although lying 
     <lb/>
     wholly within any Province, be spe<lb break="no"/>cially declared by the Acts authoriz<lb break="no"/>ing them to be for the general ad<lb break="no"/>vantage.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>12. The Census. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>l3. Militia—Military and Naval Service and 
     <lb/>
     Defence.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>l4. Beacons, Buoys and Light Houses.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>15. Navigation and Shipping. </cell></row> 
     <row><cell>16. Quarantine. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>17. Sea Coast and Inland Fisheries. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>18 Ferries between any Province and a For- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     sign country, or between any two 
     <lb/>
     Provinces.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>19. Currency and Coinage. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>20. Banking—Incorporation of Banks, and 
     <lb/>
     the issue of paper money.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>21. Savings Banks. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>22. Weights and Measures.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>23. Bills of Exchange and Promissory Notes.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>24. Interest.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>25. Legal Tender.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>26. Bankruptcy and Insolvency.</cell></row> 
    <row><cell>27. Patents of Invention and Discovery</cell></row>
     <row><cell>28. Copy Rights.</cell></row>  
     <row><cell>29. Indians and Lands reserved for the In<lb break="no"/>dians.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>30. Naturalization and Aliens </cell></row>
     <row><cell>31. Marriage and Divorce. </cell></row>
    <row><cell>32. The Criminal Law, excepting the Consti<lb break="no"/>tution of Courts of Criminal Jurisdic<lb break="no"/>tion, but including the procedure in 
     <lb/>
     Criinal matters.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>33. Rendering uniform all or any of the laws 
     <lb/>
     relative to property and civil rights 
     <lb/>
     in Upper Canada, Nova Scotia, New 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
       
     Brunswick, Newfoundland and Prince 
     <lb/>
     Edward sland, and rendering uniform 
     <lb/>
     the procedure of all or any of the 
     <lb/>
     Courts in these Provinces ; but any 
     <lb/>
     statute for this purpose shall have 
     <lb/>
     no force or authority in any Province 
     <lb/>
     until sanctioned by the Legislature 
     <lb/>
     thereof </cell></row>
   <row><cell>34. The establishment of a General Court of 
     <lb/>
     Appeal for the Federated Provinces.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>35. Immigration. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>36. Agriculture.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>37. And generally respecting all matters of 
     <lb/>
     a general character, not specially and 
     <lb/>
     exclusively reserved for the Local 
     <lb/>
     Governments and Legislatures.</cell></row>
</table> 

            <p>
     30 The General Government and Parliament 
     <lb/>
     shall have all powers necessary or proper for per<lb break="no"/>forming the obligations of the Federated Prov<lb break="no"/>inces, as part of the British Empire, to foreign 
     <lb/>
     countries arising under Treaties between Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain and such countries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     32. The General Parliament may also, from 
     <lb/>
     time to time, establish additional Courts, and the 
     <lb/>
     General Government may appoint Judges and 
     <lb/>
     officers thereof, when the same shall appear ne<lb break="no"/>cessary or for the public advantage, in order to 
     <lb/>
     the due execution of the laws of Parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     32. All Courts, Judges, and officers of the 
     <lb/>
     several Provinces shall aid, assist and obey the 
     <lb/>
     General Government in the exercise of its rights 
     <lb/>
     and powers, and for such purposes shall be held 
     <lb/>
     to be Courts, Judges and officers of the General 
     <lb/>
     Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     33. The General Government shall appoint 
     <lb/>
     and pay the Judges of the Superior Court in 
     <lb/>
     each Province, and of the County Courts in Up<lb break="no"/>per Canada, and Parliament shall fix their salaries. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     34. Until the Consolidation of the Laws of 
     <lb/>
     Upper Canada, New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland and Prince Edward Island, the 
     <lb/>
     Judges of these Provinces appointed br the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Government, shall be selected from their 
     <lb/>
     respective Bars. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     35. The Judges of the Courts of Lower Can<lb break="no"/>ada shall be selected from the Bar of Lower 
     <lb/>
     Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     36. The Judges of the Court of Admiralty 
     <lb/>
     now receiving salaries shall be paid by the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     37. The Judges of the Superior Courts shall 
     <lb/>
     hold their offices during good behaviour, and shall 
     <lb/>
     be removable only on the Address of both Houses 
     <lb/>
     of Parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     38. For each of the Provinces there shall be 
     <lb/>
     an Executive Officer, styled the Lieutenant Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor, who shall be appointed by the Governor- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     General in Council, under the Great Seal of the 
     <lb/>
     Federated Provinces, during pleasure : such pleas<lb break="no"/>ure not to be exercised before the expiration of 
     <lb/>
     the first five years, except for cause : such cause 
     <lb/>
     to be communicated in writing to the Lieutenant 
     <lb/>
     Governor immediately after the exercise of the 
     <lb/>
     pleasure as aforesaid, and also by Message to 
     <lb/>
     both Houses of Parliament within the first week 
     <lb/>
      of the first session afterwards. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="4" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0004.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">4</fw>
            <p>
     39. The Lieutenant Governor of each Prov<lb break="no"/>ince shall be paid by the General Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     40. In undertaking to pay the salaries of the 
     <lb/>
     Lieutenant Governors, the Conference does not 
     <lb/>
     desire to prejudice the claim of Prince Edward 
     <lb/>
     Island upon the Imperial Government for the 
     <lb/>
     amount now paid for the salary of the Lieutenant 
     <lb/>
     Governor thereof. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     41. The Local Government and Legislature of 
     <lb/>
     each Province shall be constructed in such man<lb break="no"/>ner as the existing Legislature of each such 
     <lb/>
     Province shall provide. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     42. The Local Legislature shall have power to 
     <lb/>
     alter or amend their constitution from time to 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     43. The Local Legislatures shall have power 
     <lb/>
     to make laws respecting the following subjects : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<table>
     <row><cell>1. Direct taxation, and in New Brunswick 
     <lb/>
     the imposition of Duties on the Ex<lb break="no"/>port of Timber, Logs, Masts, Spars, 
     <lb/>Deals, and Sawn Lumber ; and in 
     <lb/>Nova Scotia, of Coals and other min<lb break="no"/>erals.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>2. Borrowing money on the credit of the 
     <lb/>
     Province.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>3. The establishment and tenure of local 
     <lb/>
     offices, and the appointment and pay<lb break="no"/>ment of local officers.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>4. Agriculture.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>5. Immigration.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>6. Education ; saving the rights and privil<lb break="no"/>eges which the Protestant or Catholic 
     <lb/>
     minority in both Canadas may possess 
     <lb/>
     as to their Denominational Schools 
     <lb/>
     at the time when the Union goes into 
     <lb/>
     operation.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>7. The sale and management of Public Lands 
     <lb/>
     excepting Lands belonging to the 
     <lb/>
     General Government.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>8. Sea Coast and Inland Fisheries. </cell></row>
     <row> <cell>9. The establishment, maintenance and 
     <lb/>
     management of Penitentiaries, and 
     <lb/>
     Public and Reformatory Prisons.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>10. The establishment, maintenance and 
     <lb/>
     management of Hospitals, Asylums, 
     <lb/>
     Charities, and Eleemosynary Institu<lb break="no"/>tions.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>11. Municipal Institutions. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>12. Shop, Saloon, Tavern, Auctioneer and 
     <lb/>
     other Licenses.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>13. Local Works.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>14. The Incorporation of Private or Local 
     <lb/>
     Companies, except such as relate to 
     <lb/>
     matters assigned to the General Par<lb break="no"/>liament.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>15. Property and Civil Rights, excepting 
     <lb/>
     those portions thereof assigned to the 
     <lb/>
     General Parliament.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>16. Inflicting punishment by fine, penalties, 
     <lb/>
     imprisonment or otherwise, for the 
     <lb/>
     breach of laws passed in relation to 
     <lb/>
     any subject within their jurisdiction.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>17. The Administration of Justice, including 
     <lb/>
     the Constitution, maintenance and 
     <lb/>
    organization of the Courts,—both of 
     <lb/>Civil and Criminal Jurisdiction, and 
     <lb/>
 
            <cb/>
         
     including also the Procedure in Civil 
     <lb/>
    matters.</cell> </row>
   <row><cell>18. And generally all matters of a private or 
     <lb/>
     local nature, not assigned to the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Parliament.</cell> </row>
</table>

            <p>
     44. The power of respiting, reprieving, and 
     <lb/>
     pardoning Prisoners convicted of crimes, and of 
     <lb/>
     commuting and remitting of sentences in whole 
     <lb/>
     or in part, which belongs of right to the Crown, 
     <lb/>
     shall be administered by the Lieutenant Governor 
     <lb/>
     of each Province in Council, subject to any 
     <lb/>
     instructions he may, from time to time, receive 
     <lb/>
     from the General Government, and subject to 
     <lb/>
     any provisions that may be made in this behalf 
     <lb/>
     by the General Parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     45. In regard to all subjects over which juris<lb break="no"/>diction belongs to both the General and Local 
     <lb/>
     Legislatures, the laws of the General Parliament 
     <lb/>
     shall control and supersede those made by the 
     <lb/>
     Local Legislature, and the latter shall be void so 
     <lb/>
     far as they are repugnant to, or inconsistent with, 
     <lb/>
     the former. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     46. Both the English and French languages 
     <lb/>
     may be employed in the General Parliament and 
     <lb/>
     in its proceedings, and in the Local Legislature 
     <lb/>
     of Lower Canada, and also in the Federal Courts 
     <lb/>
     and in the Courts of Lower Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     47. No lands or property belonging to the 
     <lb/>
     General or Local Governments shall be liable to 
     <lb/>
     taxation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     48. All Bills for appropriating any part of the 
     <lb/>
     Public Revenue, or for imposing any new Tax or 
     <lb/>
     Impost, shall originate in the House of Commons 
     <lb/>
     or House of Assembly, as the case may be. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     49. The House of Commons or House of 
     <lb/>
     Assembly shall not originate or pass any Vote, 
     <lb/>
     Resolution, Address or Bill for the appropriation 
     <lb/>
     of any part of the Public Revenue. or of any 
     <lb/>
     Tax or Impost to any purpose, not first recom<lb break="no"/>mended by Message of the Governor General or 
     <lb/>
     the Lieutenant Governor, as the case may be, 
     <lb/>
     during the Session in which such Vote, Resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, Address or Bill is passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     50. Any Bill of the General Parliament may 
     <lb/>
     be reserved in the usual manner for Her Majesty's 
     <lb/>
     Assent, and any Bill of the Local Legislatures 
     <lb/>
     may, in like manner, be reserved for the con<lb break="no"/>sideration of the Governor General. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     51. Any Bill passed by the General Parliament 
     <lb/>
     shall be subject to disallowance by Her Majesty 
     <lb/>
     within two years, as in the case of Bills passed 
     <lb/>
     by the Legislatures of the said Provinces hither<lb break="no"/>to ; and, in like manner, any Bill passed by a 
     <lb/>
     Local Legislature shall be subject to disallowance 
     <lb/>
     by the Governor General within one year after 
     <lb/>
     the passing thereof. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     52. The Seat of Government of the Federated 
     <lb/>
     Provinces shall be Ottawa, subject to the Royal 
     <lb/>
     Prerogative. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     53. Subject to any future action of the respec<lb break="no"/>tive Local Governments, the Seat of the Local 
     <lb/>
     Government in Upper Canada shall be Toronto ; 
     <lb/>
     of Lower Canada. Quebec ; and the Seats of the 
     <lb/>
     Local Governments in the other Provinces shall 
     <lb/>
     be as at present. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     54. All Stocks, Cash, Bankers' Balances <choice>
  <sic>an</sic>
  <corr>and</corr>
</choice> 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="5" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0005.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">5</fw>
         

     Securities for mass belonging to each Province 
     <lb/>
     at the time of the Union, except as hereinafter 
     <lb/>
     mentioned, shall belong to the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     55. The following Public Works and Property 
     <lb/>
     of each Province shall belong to the General 
     <lb/>
     Government, to wit :-<lb/>
            </p>
<table>
            <row><cell>1. Canals.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>2. Public Harbours.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>3. Light Houses and Piers.</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>4. Steamboats, Dredges and Public Vessels.</cell></row> 
     <row><cell>5. River and Lake Improvements. </cell></row>
    <row><cell>6. Railway and Railway Stocks, Mortgages 
     <lb/>
     and other debts due by Railway Com<lb break="no"/>panies. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>7. Military Roads. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>8. Custom Homes, Post Offices and other 
     <lb/>
     Public Buildings, except such as may 
     <lb/>
     be set aside by the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment for the use of the Local Legis<lb break="no"/>latures and Governments. </cell></row>
    <row><cell>9. Property transferred by the Imperial 
     <lb/>
     Government and known as Ordnance 
     <lb/>
     Property. </cell></row>
     <row><cell>10. Armories, Drill Sheds, Military Clothing 
     <lb/>
     and Munitions of War, and</cell> </row>
     <row><cell>11. Lands set apart for public purposes.</cell></row> 
     </table>

            <p>
     56. All lands, mines, minerals and royalties 
     <lb/>
     vested in Her Majesty in the Provinces of Upper 
     <lb/>
     Canada, Lower Canada, Nova Scotia, New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick and Prince Edward Island, for the 
     <lb/>
     use of such Provinces, shall belong to the Local 
     <lb/>
     Government of the territory in which the same 
     <lb/>
     are so situate ; subject to any trusts that may 
     <lb/>
     exist in respect to any of such lands or to any 
     <lb/>
     interest of other persons in repect of the same. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     57. All sums due from purchasers or lessees of 
     <lb/>
     such lands, mines or minerals at the time of the 
     <lb/>
     Union, shall also belong to the Local Govern<lb break="no"/>ments. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     58. All assets connected with such portions 
     <lb/>
     of the public debt of any Province as are as<lb break="no"/>sumed by the Local Governments shall also 
     <lb/>
     belong to those Governments respectively. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     59. The several Provinces shall retain all 
     <lb/>
     other Public Property therein, subject to the 
     <lb/>
     right of the General Government to assume any 
     <lb/>
     Lands or Public Property required for Fortifica<lb break="no"/>tions or the Defence of the Country 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     60. The General Government shall assume all 
     <lb/>
     the Debts and Liabilities of each Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     61. The Debt of Canada, not specially as<lb break="no"/>sumed by Upper and Lower Canada respectively. 
     <lb/>
     shall not exceed, at the time of the Union, 
     <lb/>
     $62,500.000 ; Nova Scotia shall enter the Union 
     <lb/>
     with a debt not exceeding $8,000,000 ; and New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick with a debt not exceeding $7,000,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     62. In case Nova Scotia or New Brunswick do 
     <lb/>
     not incur liabilities beyond those for which their 
     <lb/>
     Governments are now bound, and which shall 
     <lb/>
     make their debts at the date of Union less than 
     <lb/>
    $8,000,000 and $7,000,000 respectively, they 
     <lb/>shall be entitled to interest at five per cent. on 
     <lb/>the amount not so incurred, in like manner as is 
     <lb/>hereinafter provided for Newfoundland and Prince 
     <lb/>Edward Island ; the foregoing resolution being 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     in no respect intended to limit the powers given 
     <lb/>
     to the respective Governments of those Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, by Legislative authority, but only to limit 
     <lb/>
     the maximum amount of charge to be assumed 
     <lb/>
     by the General Government ; provided always, 
     <lb/>
     that the powers so conferred by the respective 
     <lb/>
     Legislatures shall be exercised within five years 
     <lb/>
     from this date, or the same shall then lapse. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     63. Newfoundland and Prince Edward Island, 
     <lb/>
     not having incurred Debts equal to those of the 
     <lb/>
     other Provinces, shall be entitled to receive, by 
     <lb/>
     half-yearly payments, in advance, from the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Government, the Interest at five per cent on 
     <lb/>
     the difference between the actual amount of their 
     <lb/>
     respective Debts at the time of the Union, and 
     <lb/>
     the average amount of indebtedness per head of 
     <lb/>
     the Population of Canada, Nova Scotia and 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     64. In consideration of the transfer to the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Parliament of the powers of Taxation, an 
     <lb/>
     annual grant in aid of each Province shall be 
     <lb/>
     made, equal to eighty cents per head of the pop<lb break="no"/>ulation, as established by the census of 1861 ; the 
     <lb/>
     population of Newfoundland being estimated at 
     <lb/>
     130,000. Such aid shall be in full settlement of 
     <lb/>
     all future demands upon the General Government 
     <lb/>
     for local purposes, and shall be paid half-yearly 
     <lb/>
     in advance to each Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     65. The position of New Brunswick being such 
     <lb/>
     as to entail large immediate charges upon her 
     <lb/>
     local revenues, it is agreed that for the period of 
     <lb/>
     ten years, from the time when the Union takes 
     <lb/>
     effect, an additional allowance of $63.000 per 
     <lb/>
     annum shall be made to that Province. But that 
     <lb/>
     so long as the liability of that Province remains 
     <lb/>
     under $7,000,000 a deduction equal to the in<lb break="no"/>terest on such deficiency shall be made from the 
     <lb/>
     $63,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     66. In consideration of the surrender to the 
     <lb/>
     General Government by Newfoundland of all its 
     <lb/>
     rights in Mines and Minerals, and of all the un<lb break="no"/>granted and unoccupied Lands of the Crown, it 
     <lb/>
     is agreed that the sum of $150,000 shall each 
     <lb/>
     year be paid to that Province, by semi-annual 
     <lb/>
     payments ; provided that that Colony shall retain 
     <lb/>
     the right of opening, constructing and controlling 
     <lb/>
     Roads and Bridges through any of the said Lands 
     <lb/>
     subject to any Laws which the General Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment may pass in respect of the same. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     67. All engagements that may before the Un<lb break="no"/>ion be entered into with the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment for the defence of the Country. shall be as<lb break="no"/>sumed by the General Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     68. The General Government shall secure, 
     <lb/>
     without delay, the completion of the Intercolonial 
     <lb/>
     Railway from Rivière du Loup, through New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick. to Truro in Nova Scotia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     69. The communications with the North-West<lb break="no"/>ern Territory, and the improvements required 
     <lb/>
     for the development of the Trade of the Great 
     <lb/>
     West with the Seaboard, are regarded by this 
     <lb/>
     Conference as subjects of the highest importance 
     <lb/>
     to the Federated Provinces, and shall be prose<lb break="no"/>cuted at the earliest possible period that the state 
     <lb/>
     of the Finances will permit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     70. The sanction of the Imperial and Local 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="6" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0006.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">6<lb/></fw>
   

         

     Parliaments shall be sought for the Union of the 
     <lb/>
     Provinces, on the principles adopted by the Con<lb break="no"/>ference. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     71. That Her Majesty the Queen be solicited 
     <lb/>
     to determine the rank and name of the Federated 
     <lb/>
     Provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     72. The proceedings of the Conference shall 
     <lb/>
     be authenticated by the signatures of the Dele<lb break="no"/>gates, and submitted by each Delegation to its 
     <lb/>
     own Government, and the Chairman is author<lb break="no"/>ized to submit a copy to the Governor General 
     <lb/>
     for transmission to the Secretary of State for the 
     <lb/>
     Colonies. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Having read the motion, the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     commenced to speak in French, when Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Ross requested he should address the 
     <lb/>
     House in English. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LETE1">HON. MR. LETELLIER</persName> thought, as there 
     <lb/>
     were two members of the government in the 
     <lb/>
     House, one who spoke best in French (Sir E. 
     <lb/>
     P. TACHÉ), and one who did the same in Eng<lb break="no"/>lish, it would be better for the Hon. Premier 
     <lb/>
     to speak in French, and then his colleague 
     <lb/>
     could do the same in English; but <persName ref="pers:TACH1">Hon. Sir 
     <lb/>
     E. P. TACHÉ</persName> concluded that as there were 
     <lb/>
     English members who did not understand 
     <lb/>
     French at all, while the French members all 
     <lb/>
     understood English, it would be best for him 
     <lb/>
     to speak in the latter language, and proceed<lb break="no"/>ed to do so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TACH1">HON. SIR E. P. TACHÉ</persName> then said that in 
     <lb/>
     moving the resolution he felt it his duty first 
     <lb/>
     to make a few preliminary remarks, and to 
     <lb/>
    give fully and thoroughly the reasons which 
     <lb/>had induced him to assume the grave respon<lb break="no"/>sibility of laying this measure before the 
     <lb/>House and the country. The reasons were 
     <lb/>two-fold. They related first to the intrinsic 
     <lb/>merits of the scheme itself, divested of all 
     <lb/>other considerations, and next, to the settle<lb break="no"/>ment of the domestic difficulties which for 
     <lb/>some years had distracted the country, and 
     <lb/>the means we might and ought to employ to re<lb break="no"/>store good feeling, harmony and concord there<lb break="no"/>in. He would, then, first address himself to 
     <lb/>what he considered the intrinsic merits of the 
     <lb/>scheme of Confederation, and he would there<lb break="no"/>fore say that if were anxious to continue our 
     <lb/>connection with the British Empire, and to 
     <lb/>preserve intact our institutions, our laws, 
     <lb/>and even our remembrances of the past, we 
     <lb/>must sustain the measure. If the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity which now presented itself were allowed 
     <lb/>to pass by unimproved, whether we would or 
     <lb/>would not, we would be forced into the Ameri<lb break="no"/>can Union by violence, and if not by violence, 
     <lb/>would be placed upon an inclined plain which 
     <lb/>would carry us there insensibly. In either 
     <lb/>case the result would be the same. In our 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
         
     present condition we would not long continue 
     <lb/>
     to exist as a British colony. To sustain this 
     <lb/>
     position he thought it was only necessary to 
     <lb/>
     look at the present state of Canada, its extent, 
     <lb/>
     its agricultural and mineral resources, its in<lb break="no"/>ternal means of communication—natural and 
     <lb/>
     artificial,—its geographical position and its 
     <lb/>
     climate. The extent of the Canadian terri<lb break="no"/>tory was, perhaps, not defined, but it was suf<lb break="no"/>ficiently well known to enable him to state 
     <lb/>
     that it was as large as many empires in Eu<lb break="no"/>rope, larger than France or Austria. He 
     <lb/>
     knew that the portion cultivated was, in re<lb break="no"/>spect to its superficial area, only as to the sea<lb break="no"/>coast to the sea itself. We had vast forests 
     <lb/>
     not yet opened or occupied, and yet we had a 
     <lb/>
     population numbering over two and a half 
     <lb/>
     millions of souls. With such an extent of 
     <lb/>
     territory and so fertile a soil, he had no doubt 
     <lb/>
     whatever that in less than half a century Ca<lb break="no"/>nada would embrace a population equal to 
     <lb/>
     that of the large empires of the old world. 
     <lb/>
     Then with regard to our internal communica 
     <lb/>
     tions, natural and artificial, there was the 
     <lb/>
     noble St. Lawrence, which, with great pro<lb break="no"/>priety, might be called the father of rivers, 
     <lb/>
     for this stream, in point of navigable extent, 
     <lb/>
     was longer than any other river in the world. 
     <lb/>
     Some of its tributaries which would help to 
     <lb/>
     people the interior, were larger than the first- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     class rivers of Europe, and as to its lakes, 
     <lb/>
     none such are to be found elsewhere, especially 
     <lb/>
     in view of the facilities they afford to trade. 
     <lb/>
     Then the minerals of Canada, which were 
     <lb/>
     only now beginning to attract attention, were of 
     <lb/>
     the most valuable character, and as practical 
     <lb/>
     men asserted, much more valuable than the 
     <lb/>
     richest auriferous regions could be. The hon<lb break="no"/>orable member then referred to the artificial 
     <lb/>
     commucations of the country, viz., our Canals, 
     <lb/>
     which, he said, were on a scale unequalled in 
     <lb/>
     America, or, indeed, in the world. Our Rail<lb break="no"/>way system too, in proportion to our means 
     <lb/>
     and population, was as extensive as could be 
     <lb/>
     found anywhere else ; yet with all these ad<lb break="no"/>vantages, natural and acquired, he was bound 
     <lb/>
     to say we could not become a great nation. 
     <lb/>
     We labored under a drawback or disadvantage 
     <lb/>
     which would effectually prevent that, and he 
     <lb/>
     would defy any one to take a map of the world 
     <lb/>
     and point to any great nation which had not sea<lb break="no"/>ports of its own open at all times of the year. 
     <lb/>Canada did not possess those advantages, but 
     <lb/>was shut up in a prison, as it were, for five 
     <lb/>months of the year in fields of ice, which all 
     <lb/>the steam engineering apparatus of human 
     <lb/>ingenuity could not overcome, and so long as 
     <lb/>this state of things continued, we must con<lb break="no"/><pb n="7" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0007.jpg"/><fw type="num">7</fw>sent to be a small people, who could, at any 
     <lb/>
     moment, be assailed and invaded by a people 
     <lb/>
     better situated in that respect than we were. 
     <lb/>
     Canada was, in fact, just like a farmer who 
     <lb/>
     might stand upon an elevated spot on his 
     <lb/>
     property, from which he could look around 
     <lb/>
     upon fertile fields, meandering streams, wood 
     <lb/>
     and all else that was necessary to his domestic 
     <lb/>
     wants, but who had no outlet to the highway. 
     <lb/>
     To be sure he might have an easy, good-na<lb break="no"/>tured neighbor, who had such an outlet, and 
     <lb/>
     this neighbor might say to him, " Don't be 
     <lb/>
     uneasy about that, for I will allow you to pass 
     <lb/>
     on to the highway, through my cross road, and 
     <lb/>
     we shall both profit by the arrangement." So 
     <lb/>
     long as this obliging neighbor was in good 
     <lb/>
     humor everything would go on pleasantly, but 
     <lb/>
     the very best natured people would sometimes 
     <lb/>
     get out of temper, or grow capricious, or cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances might arise to cause irritation. And 
     <lb/>
     so it might come to pass that the excellent 
     <lb/>
     neighbor would get dissatisfied. For instance, 
     <lb/>
     he might be involved in a tedious and expen<lb break="no"/>sive law suit with some one else ; it might be 
     <lb/>
     a serious affair—in fact, an affair of life or 
     <lb/>
     death, and he might come to the isolated 
     <lb/>
     farmer and say to him, " I understand that 
     <lb/>
     you and your family are all sympathising with 
     <lb/>
     my adversary ; I don't like it at all, and I am 
     <lb/>
     determined you will find some other outlet to 
     <lb/>
     the highway than my cross road, for hence<lb break="no"/>forth my gate will be shut against you." In 
     <lb/>
     such a case what is the farmer to do ? There 
     <lb/>
     is the air left, but until the aerostatic science 
     <lb/>
     is more practically developed, he can hardly 
     <lb/>
     try ballooning without the risk of breaking 
     <lb/>
     his neck. (Laughter.) Well, that was pre<lb break="no"/>cisely our position in reference to the United 
     <lb/>
     States. Since the Atlantic and St. Lawrence 
     <lb/>
     Railway was opened we have had a very con<lb break="no"/>venient outlet to the sea, and he, with other 
     <lb/>
     hon. members now present, would remember 
     <lb/>
     the joyful jubilee which was held on the occa<lb break="no"/>sion of its opening at Boston in 1851 or '52. 
     <lb/>
     For one he was perfectly delighted, as being a 
     <lb/>
     man of a different origin, to mark how the two 
     <lb/>
     branches of the Anglo-Saxon race fraternised. 
     <lb/>
     How they did shake hands to be sure ! How 
     <lb/>
     they did compliment each other as possessing 
     <lb/>
    qualities superior to all other people. They 
     <lb/>were indeed very affectionate and almost swore 
     <lb/>eternal friendship and fidelity, and he (Sir 
     <lb/>E. P. TACHÉ) had no doubt whatever of 
     <lb/>their perfect sincerity at the time. The con<lb break="no"/>sequences of this great work had, no doubt, 
     <lb/>been highly advantageous to both sides, for 
     <lb/>their commercial relations had enlarged very 
     <lb/>much, so much indeed that now the transac<lb break="no"/><cb/>tions with the United States were, as he be<lb break="no"/>lieved, more extensive than those with Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain. If the advantages had been all on 
     <lb/>
     one side this increase would, of course, not 
     <lb/>
     have taken place. But how were we situated 
     <lb/>
     now? Difficultics had supervened, in which 
     <lb/>
     we were in no wise concerned, but which ori<lb break="no"/>ginated with themselves. It was North against 
     <lb/>
     South solely, yet these difficulties had affected 
     <lb/>
     the good feeling between them and this coun<lb break="no"/>try. To be sure there had been no misunder<lb break="no"/>standing at all between our respective Govern<lb break="no"/>ments, but the minds of the people on both 
     <lb/>
     sides had been considerably affected. The 
     <lb/>
     people of the Northern States believed that 
     <lb/>
     Canadians sympathized with the South much 
     <lb/>
     more than they really did, and the conse<lb break="no"/>quences of this misapprehension were : first, 
     <lb/>
     that we had been threatened with the abolition 
     <lb/>
     of the transit system ; then the Reciprocity 
     <lb/>
     Treaty was to be discontinued ; then a pass<lb break="no"/>port system was inaugurated, which was almost 
     <lb/>
     equivalent to a prohibition of intercourse, and 
     <lb/>
     the only thing which really remained to be 
     <lb/>
     done was to shut down the gate altogether and 
     <lb/>
     prevent passage through their territory. Would 
     <lb/>
     any one say that such a state of things was 
     <lb/>
     one desirable for Canada to be placed in ? Will 
     <lb/>
     a great people in embryo, as he believed we 
     <lb/>
     were, coolly and tranquilly cross their arms and 
     <lb/>
     wait for what might come next ? For his part 
     <lb/>
     he held that the time had now arrived when we 
     <lb/>
     should establish a union with the great Gulf 
     <lb/>
     Provinces. He called them great advisedly, 
     <lb/>
     for they had within themselves many of the 
     <lb/>
     elements which went to constitute greatness, 
     <lb/>
     and of some of which we were destitute.-<lb/>
Canada was unquestionably wanting in several 
     <lb/>
     of these important elements, and he had been 
     <lb/>
     very sorry a few days ago to hear an hon. 
     <lb/>
     member of this House make comparisons un<lb break="no"/>favorable to those countries. That hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber had said the Lower Provinces were poor 
     <lb/>
     and needy, and that like all other poor people 
     <lb/>
     they would no doubt be glad to connect them<lb break="no"/>selves with a wealthy partner. He had also 
     <lb/>
     said their product of wheat was very small, 
     <lb/>
     and that one of the inferior counties in Upper 
     <lb/>
     Canada yielded more than the whole of New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick. Well, the allegations in respect 
     <lb/>
     of the produce of wheat might be true ; but 
     <lb/>
     that did not necessarily constitute them poor 
     <lb/>
     provinces. Let the honorable member look 
     <lb/>
     at Massachusetts, Connecticut, Rhode Island 
     <lb/>
     and New Hampshire, which, in respect of 
     <lb/>
     agricultural produce, might be said to be poor, 
     <lb/>
     so poor that an American had once told him 
     <lb/>
     (Sir E. P. TACHÉ) that they did not even grow 
     <lb/>
        
            <pb n="8" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0008.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">8</fw>
      
     grass, and their inhabitants had to file the 
     <lb/>
     teeth of their sheep in summer to enable them 
     <lb/>
     to get a subsistence. (Laughter.) Yet were 
     <lb/>
     these states poor ? Had they no resources 
     <lb/>
     from their trade and manufactures ? If they 
     <lb/>
     did not produce wealth in one way they cer<lb break="no"/>tainly did in others, and so it was with New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick. If it did not produce wheat, it 
     <lb/>
     produced timber in immense quantities. It 
     <lb/>
     had a very extensive fishing coast which was 
     <lb/>
     a source of great wealth. Some honorable 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen would perhaps remember what an 
     <lb/>
     eminent man from Nova Scotia—the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     JOSEPH HOWE—had said at a dinner in this 
     <lb/>
     country in 1850, that he knew of a small 
     <lb/>
     granite rock upon which, at a single haul of 
     <lb/>
     the net, the fishermen had taken 500 barrels 
     <lb/>
     of mackerel. That was a great haul no 
     <lb/>
     doubt—(laughter)—but the honorable gentle<lb break="no"/>man had not given the size of the barrels. 
     <lb/>
     (Laughter.) Still no one could deny that the 
     <lb/>
    Gulf Provinces were of immense importance, 
     <lb/>if only in respect of their fisheries. Then 
     <lb/>they were rich in minerals. Their coal alone 
     <lb/>was an element of great wealth. It had been 
     <lb/>said that where coal was found the country was 
     <lb/>of more value than gold. Look at England, 
     <lb/>and what was the chief source of her 
     <lb/>wealth if not coal ? Deprived of coal, she 
     <lb/>would at once sink to the rank of a second or 
     <lb/>third rate power. But Canada had no coal, 
     <lb/>and notwithstanding all her other elements 
     <lb/>of greatness, she required that mineral in 
     <lb/>order to give her completeness. What 
     <lb/>she had not, the Lower Provinces had ; 
     <lb/>and what they had not, Canada had. 
     <lb/>Then as to ship-building, it was an industry 
     <lb/>prosecuted with great vigor and success in 
     <lb/>those provinces, especially in New Brunswick, 
     <lb/>and some of the finest vessels sailing under 
     <lb/>the British flag had been built in the port of 
     <lb/>St. John, which annually launched a consi<lb break="no"/>derable number of the largest class. They 
     <lb/>were not beggars, nor did they wish to come 
     <lb/>into the union as such ; but as independent 
     <lb/>provinces, able to keep up their credit, and 
     <lb/>provide for their own wants. They would 
     <lb/>bring into the common stock a fair share of 
     <lb/>revenue, of property, and of every kind of 
     <lb/>industry. As to their harbours, he (Sir E. P. 
     <lb/>TACHE) had had the good fortune to visit 
     <lb/>them personally, and would say they could 
     <lb/>not be surpassed anywhere ; in fact he believed 
     <lb/>they were unequalled in the world. He would 
     <lb/>especially refer to that of Halifax, and would 
     <lb/>ask honorable members to imagine an exten<lb break="no"/>sive roadstead, protected by several islands 
     <lb/>standing out in the sea, so as to break the 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
          
     waves and quiet the waters in the worst of 
     <lb/>
     storms. This most beautiful harbour could 
     <lb/>
     accommodate, in perfect safety, more than 100 
     <lb/>
     of the largest vessels ; but this was not all, 
     <lb/>
     for at the east end where it diminished into a 
     <lb/>
     gully, but with very deep water, you enter 
     <lb/>
     into a large natural basin, rounded as it were 
     <lb/>
     by the compass, and of an extent sufficient to 
     <lb/>
     take in all the navies of the world. The, 
     <lb/>
     entrance to this magnificent inner harbour was 
     <lb/>
     rendered inaccessible to any foe by the fortifi<lb break="no"/>cations erected at the mouth, and the entrance 
     <lb/>
     could, moreover, be so barred that no hostile 
     <lb/>
     fleet could ever get through. He did not 
     <lb/>
     suppose the fleets of England would ever need 
     <lb/>
     to take refuge there—(hear, hear)—although 
     <lb/>
     it had been loudly alleged that they could be 
     <lb/>
     blown out of the water in an incredibly short 
     <lb/>
     space of time—(laughter)—but it might afford 
     <lb/>
     shelter to isolated vessels, in case they were 
     <lb/>
     hard pushed by superior numbers. Well,  
     <lb/>
     under the union, Canada would become a 
     <lb/>
     partner in these advantages, and with the 
     <lb/>
     harbours of Halifax and Quebec, they might 
     <lb/>
     well feel proud of their country. On the  
     <lb/>
     whole, he thought that the Confederation of 
     <lb/>
     all the Provinces had become an absolute 
     <lb/>
     necessity, and that it was for us a question of 
     <lb/>
     to be or not to be. If we desired to remain 
     <lb/>
     British and monarchical, and if we desired to 
     <lb/>
     pass to our children these advantages, this 
     <lb/>
     measure, he repeated, was a necessity. But 
     <lb/>
     there were other motives and other reasons 
     <lb/>
     which should induce us to agree to the scheme. 
     <lb/>
     Every honorable gentleman in the House knew 
     <lb/>
     the political position of the country, and were 
     <lb/>
     acquainted with the feelings of irritation which 
     <lb/>
     have prevailed for many years. They knew it 
     <lb/>
     happily not by their experience in this House, 
     <lb/>
     but by the tone of the public press, and by the 
     <lb/>
     discussions in another place where taunts and 
     <lb/>
     menaces were freely flung across the floor by 
     <lb/>
     contending parties. They knew what human 
     <lb/>
     passions were, and how, when bitter feelings 
     <lb/>
     continued for a long time, the distance between 
     <lb/>
     exasperation and actual conflict was not very 
     <lb/>
     great. They had now before their own eyes 
     <lb/>
     an example of the effects of such disagreements. 
     <lb/>
     It was persistently believed by many that the 
     <lb/>
     rival interests would never come to a rupture, 
     <lb/>
     but for three years they had been waging a 
     <lb/>
     conflict which had desolated and ruined the 
     <lb/>
     fairest portion of the country, and in the course 
     <lb/>
     of which acts of barbarity had been committed 
     <lb/>
     which were only equalled by the darkest ages. 
     <lb/>
     We in Canada were not more perfect, and the 
     <lb/>
     time had arrived when, as he believed, all the 
     <lb/>
     patriotic men in the country ought to unite in 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="9" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0009.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">9</fw>
         
     providing a remedy for the troubles we had to 
     <lb/>
     contend with. It might be said that the 
     <lb/>
     remedy proposed was not required, but he 
     <lb/>
     would like to know what other could be pro<lb break="no"/>posed. Legislation in Canada for the last two 
     <lb/>
     years had come almost to a stand still, and if 
     <lb/>
     any one would refer to the Statute Book since 
     <lb/>
     1862, he would find that the only public 
     <lb/>
     measures there inscribed had been passed 
     <lb/>
     simply by the permission of the Opposition. 
     <lb/>
      This was the condition of things for two years, 
     <lb/>
      and if this were an evil there was another not 
     <lb/>
     less to be deplored ; he referred to the adminis<lb break="no"/>tration of public affairs during the same period. 
     <lb/>
      From the 21st May, 1862, to the end of June, 
     <lb/>
     1864, there had been no less than five different 
     <lb/>
      Governments in charge of the business of the 
     <lb/>
     country. The honorable member here gave a 
     <lb/>
     history of the several changes until the MAC<lb break="no"/>DONALD-DORION Administration died, as he 
     <lb/>
     stated, of absolute weakness, falling under the 
     <lb/>
     weight they were unable to carry. Their 
     <lb/>
      successors were not more successful, and 
     <lb/>
     being defeated were thinking of appealing to 
     <lb/>
     the country, which they might have done 
     <lb/>
     with more or less success, gaining a consti<lb break="no"/>tuency here, and perhaps losing another else<lb break="no"/>where.  They had assumed the charge of 
     <lb/>
      affairs with an understanding that they would 
     <lb/>
     have a right to this appeal, and while they 
     <lb/>
     were consulting about it they received an inti<lb break="no"/>mation from the real chief of the Opposition, 
     <lb/>
      through one of their own friends, to the effect 
     <lb/>
      that he was desirous of making overtures to 
     <lb/>
    them, with the view of seeking to accommo<lb break="no"/>date the difficulties.  The honorable gentleman 
     <lb/> and some of his friends then came into contact 
     <lb/> with the leaders of the Government, and it 
     <lb/> was agreed between them to try to devise a 
     <lb/>scheme which would put an end to the mis<lb break="no"/>understandings, and at the same time secure 
     <lb/>for Canada and the other provinces a position 
     <lb/> which would ensure their future safety and 
     <lb/>procure them the respect and confidence of 
     <lb/>other nations. They arranged a large scheme 
     <lb/>and a smaller one.  If the larger failed, then 
     <lb/>they were to fall back upon the minor, which 
     <lb/>provided for a federation of the two sections of 
     <lb/>the province.  At the time these measures 
     <lb/> were resolved upon the country was bordering 
     <lb/>on civil strife, and he would ask if it was not 
     <lb/>the duty of both sides to do all they could to 
     <lb/>prevent the unfortunate results which would 
     <lb/>have followed. An honorable member oppo<lb break="no"/>site (Hon. Mr. LETELLIER DE ST. JUST) had 
     <lb/>said, a few days ago, that it would have been 
     <lb/>easy to have prevented the necessity for a 
     <lb/>Confederation of all the provinces, by granting 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
           
     to Upper Canada the increased representation, 
     <lb/>
     or the demand of representation according to 
     <lb/>
     population, which they had been contending 
     <lb/>
     for.  
     <lb/>
    
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:LETE1">HON. MR. LETELLIER DE ST. JUST</persName> 
     <lb/>begged to say that the Hon. Premier must 
     <lb/>have misunderstood him. What he had said 
     <lb/>was that if the proposition had been made to 
     <lb/>the people whether they should have a Con<lb break="no"/>federation of all the provinces, or give Repre<lb break="no"/>sentation according to Population to Upper 
     <lb/>Canada, they would have chosen the latter ; 
     <lb/>and when he had alluded to some other mode 
     <lb/>of accommodating the difficulties, he meant 
     <lb/>that if the Government had applied to other 
     <lb/>parties in the Legislature than those they had 
     <lb/>had associated with themselves, they might 
     <lb/>have succeeded without having recourse to 
     <lb/>Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TACH1">HON. SIR. E. P. TACHÉ</persName> said that he had 
     <lb/>
     not been alone in interpreting the honorable 
     <lb/>
     member as he had done, for two city journals 
     <lb/>
     had taken the same view of his remarks. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:LETE1">HON. M. LETELLIER</persName> said he was aware 
     <lb/>
     of it, but the were mistaken for all that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TACH1">HON. SIR E. P. TACHÉ</persName>—Well, it did 
     <lb/>
     not much matter ; but the honorable member 
     <lb/>
     should recollect that Lower Canada had con<lb break="no"/>stantly refused the demand of Upper Canada 
     <lb/>
     for representation according to population, 
     <lb/>
     and for the good reason that, as the union 
     <lb/>
     between them was legislative, a preponderance 
     <lb/>
     to one of the sections would have placed the 
     <lb/>
     other at its mercy . It would not be so in a 
     <lb/>
     Federal Union, for all questions of a general 
     <lb/>
     nature would be reserved for the General 
     <lb/>
     Government, and those of a local character to 
     <lb/>
     the local governments, who would have the 
     <lb/>
     power to manage their domestic affairs as they  
     <lb/>
     deemed best. If a Federal Union were 
     <lb/>
     obtained it would be tantamount to a separa<lb break="no"/>tion of the provinces, and Lower Canada 
     <lb/>
     would thereby preserve its autonomy together 
     <lb/>
     with all the institutions it held so dear, and  
     <lb/>
     over which they could exercise the watchful<lb break="no"/>ness and surveillance necessary to preserve them 
     <lb/>
     unimpaired. [The honorable member re<lb break="no"/>peated this portion of his speech in French, 
     <lb/>for the express purpose of conveying his  
     <lb/>meaning in the clearest and most forcible  
     <lb/>manner to his follow-members for Lower  
     <lb/>Canada, who might not have apprehended so 
     <lb/>well the English.]  But there might be a 
     <lb/>portion of the inhabitants of Lower Canada  
     <lb/>who might at a first glance have greater reason  
     <lb/>to complain than the  French Roman Catholics, 
     <lb/>and these were the English Protestants. And 
     <lb/>why ? Because they were in a minority ; but 
     <lb/>
     

    
            <pb n="10" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0010.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">10</fw>
       
     he thought that if they took the trouble fully 
     <lb/>
     to consider the subject, they would be re<lb break="no"/>assured and satisfied with the scheme. First 
     <lb/>
     a great event had taken place ; the law of 
     <lb/>
     Lower Canada had been consolidated and the 
     <lb/>
     Englîsh-speaking people residing in that section 
     <lb/>
     had got reconciled to it ; in fact they were well 
     <lb/>
     satisfied therewith. In this respect, then, 
     <lb/>
     they were secure. But they might say that 
     <lb/>
     the majority in the Local Legislature might 
     <lb/>
     hereafter be unjust to them, but he thought 
     <lb/>
     that, on looking at the past, their fears might 
     <lb/>
     be allayed. Before the union of the provinces, 
     <lb/>
     when the large majority of members in the 
     <lb/>
     Legislature were French, the English inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants had never found cause of complaint 
     <lb/>
     against them. In no instance had injustice 
     <lb/>
       been attempted. The difficulty was that 
     <lb/>
     the minority wanted to rule and wanted to 
     <lb/>
       possess the whole power of the state in their 
     <lb/>
     hands. That the people of Lower Canada 
     <lb/>
     always acted towards the English with liber<lb break="no"/>ality was best exemplified by facts. Before 
     <lb/>
     the union wile the constituencies were almost 
     <lb/>
     exclusively French, English Protestant gentle<lb break="no"/>men were frequently returned to Parliament, 
     <lb/>
        and he had now opposite to him an honorable 
     <lb/>
     member who had for twenty years represented 
     <lb/>an entirely French and Roman Catholic county.<lb/>He doubted if in the course of those twenty<lb/>
     
     
     years that honorable member had ever been 
     <lb/>
     asked whether he were Scotch or Protestant. 
     <lb/>
     They took the man for his sterling worth. It 
     <lb/>
     was even a fact that the French had elected 
     <lb/>
     members with extraordinary names, and as 
     <lb/>
     everybody knew, there was sometimes a good 
     <lb/>
     dealin a name, (Hear, hear.) Now if there 
     <lb/>
     was one name which French Canadians dis<lb break="no"/>liked more than another, it was that of Luther 
     <lb/>
    (Hear, hear and laughter). Yet they had 
     <lb/>elected a gentleman bearing that significant 
     <lb/>appellation. He was glad they had, and he 
     <lb/>had no doubt he had been elected because of 
     <lb/>his personal worth ; but it unquestionably 
     <lb/>showed a great deal of liberal feeling on the 
     <lb/>part of the electors. (Hear, hear.). But if 
     <lb/>an English Protestant was bad in the eyes of   
     <lb/>a French Canadian, a French Protestant was 
     <lb/>infinitely worse, and yet the county of Lot<lb break="no"/>binière had elected a French Canadian Pro<lb break="no"/>testant without even questioning his religion. 
     <lb/>That gentleman was a most worthy, able  and 
     <lb/>well educated person, and every way well 
     <lb/>qualified for the important trust. But again, 
     <lb/>quite fately in a division in Lower Canada 
     <lb/>numbering over fifty thousand souls, of which 
     <lb/>only one thousand four hundred were English, 
     <lb/>an election of a member to this Chamber had 
     <lb/>
       
            <cb/>
       
     taken place, the candidates being a French: 
     <lb/>
     Roman Catholic gentlemen, long and well 
     <lb/>
     known, and an English Protestant—and with 
     <lb/>
     what result ? Why, that the English Protes<lb break="no"/>tant had beaten the French Canadian Roman 
     <lb/>
     Catholic by one thousand votes. (Hear.) 
     <lb/>
     Could any greater proof of a tolerant and 
     <lb/>
     liberal feeling be exhibited ? These examples  
     <lb/>
     should show, as he thought, that the Protest<lb break="no"/>tants of Lower Canada were sure to meet with 
     <lb/>
     not justice simply, but with the largest tolera<lb break="no"/>tion. It might perhaps be said that Mr. PRICE, 
     <lb/>
     who had been elected for the division of which 
     <lb/>
     he spoke, being a large merchant doing busi<lb break="no"/>ness in Chicoutimi, had used the influence 
     <lb/>
     which his position gave him over many electors  
     <lb/>
     who were in his debt to obtain success ; but 
     <lb/>
     whatever might be said of Chicoutimi, it 
     <lb/>
     could not be said of the county of Charlevoix, 
     <lb/>
     where he had no such business relations, and 
     <lb/>
     yet he obtained a majority there too. The 
     <lb/>
     fact was, the result might be considered not 
     <lb/>
     only as a mark of confidence in Mr. PRICE, the 
     <lb/>
     son elected, but as a token of respect and 
     <lb/>
     gratitude to Mr. PRICE, senior, who had by his 
     <lb/>
     energy and enterprise opened up the Saguenay 
     <lb/>
     country, and who, in a certain sense, might be 
     <lb/>
     said to be the father of that region. Much 
     <lb/>
     had been said on the war of races, but that 
     <lb/>
     war was extinguished on the day the British 
     <lb/>
     Government granted Canada Responsible Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, by which all its inhabitants, without 
     <lb/>
     distinction of race or creed, were placed on a 
     <lb/>
     footing of equality. (Hear, hear). The war 
     <lb/>
     of races found its grave in the resolutions of 
     <lb/>
     the 3rd September, 1841, and he hoped never 
     <lb/>
     to hear of it again. We were so situated that 
     <lb/>
     there must needs be mutual forbearance. This 
     <lb/>
     .life was one of compromise. Not only was for<lb break="no"/>bearance needed in public life, but in domestic 
     <lb/>
     life. If one member in a family insists upon 
     <lb/>
     having all his own way, there will be trouble, 
     <lb/>
    and so through all possible relations of 
     <lb/>humanity. He believed the French-Canadians 
     <lb/>would do all in their power to render justice 
     <lb/>to their fellow subjects of English origin, 
     <lb/>and it should not be forgotten that if the 
     <lb/>former were in a majority in Lower Canada, 
     <lb/>the English would be in majority in the 
     <lb/>General Government, and that no act of real 
     <lb/>injustice could take place, even if there were a 
     <lb/>disposition to perpetuate it, without its being 
     <lb/>reversed there. He had now given to the House    
     <lb/>the motives which had led him to take the 
     <lb/>responsibility of introducing this important 
     <lb/>measure, and he trusted they would be viewed 
     <lb/>as sufficient. When the proper time for the   
     <lb/>discussion of the details came, he would be 
     <lb/>
      
            <pb n="11" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0011.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">11</fw>
         
     prepared to give such explanations as might 
     <lb/>
     seem requisite, and as to the mode and time of 
     <lb/>
     the discussion he would leave that to the 
     <lb/>
     decision of the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAI2">Hon. Mr. FERGUSSON BLAIR</persName>—[Owing 
     <lb/>
     to some noise in the House, the reporter did 
     <lb/>
     not clearly understand the opening remarks of 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member, except so far as that he de<lb break="no"/>sired to convey the impression that what he 
     <lb/>
     was about to say was not to be regarded as 
     <lb/>
     committing any one but himself; that he did 
     <lb/>
     not speak for any party or as representing any 
     <lb/>
     party in the House. The hon. member was 
     <lb/>
     also understood to allege he did not think the 
     <lb/>
     political struggles and difficulties alluded to by 
     <lb/>
     the Hon. Premier could be taken as sufficient 
     <lb/>
     to justify the great constitutional change now 
     <lb/>
     proposed]. He thought that in the course of 
     <lb/>
     party struggles for supremacy, the Opposition 
     <lb/>
    had erred in seeking to oust the Ministry be<lb break="no"/>fore they themselves were prepared to assume 
     <lb/>the charge with a reasonable prospect of being 
     <lb/>able to carry on the Government with success. 
     <lb/>This was the British system, and an instance 
     <lb/>had lately occurred in the Imperial Parliament 
     <lb/>exemplifying it. On the Danish question Mr. 
     <lb/>D'Israeli could have defeated Ministry, 
     <lb/>but, being aware that he could not form a 
     <lb/>strong Administration, many of his party ab<lb break="no"/>stained from voting. Such a condition of 
     <lb/>things could happen just as well in an assem<lb break="no"/>bly of 300 as in one of 600, and he did not 
     <lb/>think the change proposed would guarantee 
     <lb/>immunity from future difficulties of the same 
     <lb/>kind, therefore they might happen in the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Government as we as in that of Canada 
     <lb/>alone. But looking at the scheme as pre<lb break="no"/>sented, and forgetting all past party disputes 
     <lb/>and the charges against the public men con<lb break="no"/>cerned, it came before the House in such a 
     <lb/>shape as to make it necessary to attempt or re<lb break="no"/>ject it. He must say he could act but attach 
     <lb/>great weight to a scheme prepared by men of 
     <lb/>differentt political opinions, by eminent men 
     <lb/>who had met together for the express purpose 
     <lb/>of, arranging it, and who had agreed upon its 
     <lb/>provisions. If it were obstructed by any seri<lb break="no"/>ous amendments, involving a prolonged delay, 
     <lb/>such delay might be fatal, and if it were to 
     <lb/>pass, he thought it should be allowed to do so 
     <lb/>at a sufficiently early period to permit of its 
     <lb/>being laid before the Imperial Parliament this 
     <lb/>year. (Hear, hear.) He could not shut his 
     <lb/>eyes to the fact that whether or not the union 
     <lb/>added strength to the provinces interested, it 
     <lb/>would unquestionably add to their respecta<lb break="no"/>bility and standing , both at home and abroad. 
     <lb/>(Hear.) The people of England were, evi<lb break="no"/><cb/>dently looking to the proposed change with 
     <lb/>
     confidence and hope, and as likely to perpet<lb break="no"/>uate the connection of the provinces with the 
     <lb/>
     empire for a long time to come. But it was 
     <lb/>
     well known that there was an anti-colonial 
     <lb/>
     party in England persistently urging that it 
     <lb/>
     would be an advantage to the nation to get rid 
     <lb/>
     of the colonies. The question of defending 
     <lb/>
     them was an embarrassing one, and unless 
     <lb/>
     some such scheme as this were adopted, it 
     <lb/>
     might present grave difficulties. If the scheme 
     <lb/>
     were rejected, the effect would be very injuri<lb break="no"/>ous upon our credit. (Hear) But if adopted, 
     <lb/>
     the reverse would be the case. Its acceptance 
     <lb/>
     would also improve our position in the eyes of 
     <lb/>
     our neighbors in France and other nations; 
     <lb/>
     indeed it would, in all probability, give us a 
     <lb/>
     national standing, without the necessity of 
     <lb/>
     separating from the mother country. For these 
     <lb/>
     reasons he had come to the conscientious con<lb break="no"/>clusion that it would be highly injurious to 
     <lb/>
     reject the scheme, and that it was our duty to 
     <lb/>
     pass it as soon as was consistent with a due 
     <lb/>
     consideration of what was due to so important 
     <lb/>
     a subject. He did not think it necessary to 
     <lb/>
     express, at greater length, his reasons for giv<lb break="no"/>ing the motion his support, but he again de<lb break="no"/>sired it to be well understood that he spoke 
     <lb/>
     only for himself, and not in concert with any 
     <lb/>
     one else. At the same time he might say, 
     <lb/>
     that from what he knew personally of the 
     <lb/>
     feeling of his section of the country, it was 
     <lb/>
     highly favorable to the measure. There might 
     <lb/>
     be some matters of detail upon which there 
     <lb/>
     was a difference of opinion, and when the reso<lb break="no"/>lutions came up in their order, he would indi<lb break="no"/>cate what they were. The proposed submis<lb break="no"/>sion of the scheme to the electors would in<lb break="no"/>volve a delay which could not be compensated 
     <lb/>
     for by any benefit proposed to be derived from 
     <lb/>
     such a course; but if there should hereafter be 
     <lb/>
     any' very important public movement and 
     <lb/>
     numerous petitions in favor of an appeal to 
     <lb/>
     the people, then the subject would present a 
     <lb/>
     different aspect. Or if the majority in favor 
     <lb/>
     of the scheme in the other branch of the Le<lb break="no"/>gislature should be very small, that might be 
     <lb/>
     deemed a sufficient reason for submitting it to 
     <lb/>
     the country. As to the course to be pursued in 
     <lb/>
    the decision on the merits, he did not know whe<lb break="no"/>ther it would be best to have it in Committee 
     <lb/>of the Whole or with the Speaker in the chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TACH1">Hon. Sir E. P. TACHÉ</persName> thought it would be 
     <lb/>
     better that the Speaker should continue in the 
     <lb/>
     chair, but with the understanding that every 
     <lb/>
     honorable member should be at liberty to 
     <lb/>
     speak freely and frequently as if the House were 
     <lb/>
     in committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0012.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12</fw>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAI2">HON. MR. FERGUSSON BLAIR</persName> assented. 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:LETE1">HON. MR. LETELLIER DE ST. JUST</persName> 
     <lb/>
     said, that if he were sufficiently master of 
     <lb/>
     English he would address the House in that 
     <lb/>
     language, but not being so would have to use 
     <lb/>
     the French. The difficulties to which allusion 
     <lb/>
     had been made were produced by two causes. 
     <lb/>
     They were not constitutional, however, but 
     <lb/>
     parliamentary, and, as he believed, could have 
     <lb/>
     been surmounted without recourse to the 
     <lb/>
     constitutional change which it was proposed 
     <lb/>
     to adopt without appeal to the country. It 
     <lb/>
     was true that difficulties had succeeded to 
     <lb/>
     difficulties, and that legislation was stopped, 
     <lb/>
     but if the leaders had sought in the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture itself for the means of removing them, he 
     <lb/>
     believed they would have been found. Who 
     <lb/>
     would guarantee the Government under the 
     <lb/>
     new Constitution from the recurrence of similar 
     <lb/>
     troubles ? There would of course be an Op<lb break="no"/>position as in the smaller House. If similar 
     <lb/>
     difficulties happened, would the Confederation 
     <lb/>
     seek relief in another change of Constitution. 
     <lb/>
     On the contrary, would not relief be sought 
     <lb/>
     in the means he had suggested. At any rate 
     <lb/>
     he did not think such a change as the union 
     <lb/>
     of all the British provinces was required. In 
     <lb/>
     1820, when a union of Upper and Lower 
     <lb/>
     Canada was proposed, it was objected that if 
     <lb/>
     it did not work a larger union would follow, 
     <lb/>
     and then, lastly, a legislative union of all the 
     <lb/>
     Provinces. Two of these steps had already 
     <lb/>
    been taken, and we were going on with rapid 
     <lb/>strides towards the last. In such a case it was 
     <lb/>not hard to conceive what would be the posi<lb break="no"/>tion of Lower Canada. It was a misfortune 
     <lb/>that we had to contend with national prejudices, 
     <lb/>but it was impossible to forget them. In the 
     <lb/>event of a legislative union would the guaran<lb break="no"/>tees proposed to Lower Canada under the 
     <lb/>federation system be found ? Would it not 
     <lb/>then be at the mercy of those they now feared ? 
     <lb/>He admitted we had a rich country as repre<lb break="no"/>sented ; we had wheat fields, mineral resources, 
     <lb/>forests, rivers and lakes, but to make them 
     <lb/>available did we require an increase of terri<lb break="no"/>tory ? We had territory enough, and an 
     <lb/>increase would be a source of weakness, not of 
     <lb/>strength. Would it not add to our already 
     <lb/>large frontier, and make us more vulnerable 
     <lb/>to invasions. The union would not increase 
     <lb/>the power of England to protect us, and 
     <lb/>England would have the same interest in 
     <lb/>protecting the colonies without as well as with 
     <lb/>the union. New Brunswick might be rich 
     <lb/>in coal, in wood and in fisheries, and do a large 
     <lb/>business in ship building, but these things 
     <lb/>would seek the best markets under any circum<lb break="no"/><cb/>stances, and he did not see that a union with 
     <lb/>
     us would increase their value, and if it did 
     <lb/>
     it would be no advantage. Then, as to Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia with its small population and fine 
     <lb/>
     harbour—where would be the advantage of 
     <lb/>
     connection with her ? Though not united, 
     <lb/>
     would not the harbour be equally available to 
     <lb/>
     our vessels ? He would now say he preferred 
     <lb/>
     to Confederation a legislative union of Upper 
     <lb/>
     and Lower Canada with inequality of repre<lb break="no"/>sentation in the Lower House and equality in 
     <lb/>
     the Upper. This would not add to the ex<lb break="no"/>penses of the province, and would be more 
     <lb/>
     consonant with our interests and the sentiments 
     <lb/>
     [ideas] of the people. Though there should 
     <lb/>
     be inequality in the Assembly , the equality in 
     <lb/>
     the Legislative Council would act as a coun<lb break="no"/>terpoise, and prevent one section from invading 
     <lb/>
     the interests of the other. Then did not Con<lb break="no"/>federation consecrate [establish] the principle 
     <lb/>
     of representation according to population ? 
     <lb/>
     It would give larger to one of the nationalities, 
     <lb/>
     and, as the General Government would be able 
     <lb/>
     to veto the acts of the Local Government, 
     <lb/>
     would there be no danger to Lower Canada ? 
     <lb/>
     If representation by population had been so 
     <lb/>
     much opposed in this part, it was doubtless 
     <lb/>
     because there was cause of fear, yet this very 
     <lb/>
     power was to be conferred upon the Federal 
     <lb/>
     Government. If it could not be given with 
     <lb/>
     safety under our present regime, how could it 
     <lb/>
     be safer to give it to the Confederation. The 
     <lb/>
     advantage of the plan to Upper Canada was 
     <lb/>
     well understood, for immediately after the 
     <lb/>
     coalition they all agreed to say they had 
     <lb/>
     gained what they had so long contended for. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TACH1">HON. SIR E. P. TACHÉ</persName>—Well, after all, 
     <lb/>
     they only got what the honorable member 
     <lb/>
     himself proposed to give them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LETE1">HON. MR. LETELLIER DE ST.JUST</persName> 
     <lb/>
     said he always preferred a short direct course 
     <lb/>
     to a long tortuous one. The friends of the 
     <lb/>
     new movement had tried to conceal the fact 
     <lb/>
     that representation according to population 
     <lb/>
     was to be conceded to Upper Canada, but they 
     <lb/>
     had failed, and the avowal had come out at 
     <lb/>
     last. The resolutions not being before the 
     <lb/>
     House, it would be improper to go into the 
     <lb/>
     merits of the details, but he could not avoid 
     <lb/>
     alluding to one point which was of profound 
     <lb/>
     interest. It was clear that the constituencies 
     <lb/>
     had not sent honorable members to this House 
     <lb/>
     for the purpose of electing themselves mem<lb break="no"/>bers for life, as they were invited to do. They 
     <lb/>
     were not sent here to change the Constitution, 
     <lb/>
     but to uphold it. (Hear.) You were, in 
     <lb/>
     fact, about to declare that the local govern<lb break="no"/>ments would have power to recommend to the 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="13" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-03_Page_0013.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">13</fw>
          
     General Government that you should be ap<lb break="no"/>pointed for life. If so, then let the people say 
     <lb/>
     whether such power should be conferred. 
     <lb/>
     Take the means to make sure that the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Assembly shall appeal to the 
     <lb/>
     country. In New Brunswick the question 
     <lb/>
     was about to be submitted to the people 
     <lb/>
     through a general election. To be sure, it 
     <lb/>
     was said that the term of Parliament there 
     <lb/>
     had expired ; but if the Ministers in New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick had understood they could force 
     <lb/>
     a vote, as was about to be done in Canada, 
     <lb/>
     he doubted whether the general election would 
     <lb/>
     have taken place immediately. He believed, 
     <lb/>
     too, that the Conference generally had re<lb break="no"/>garded this as the most proper mode. Then 
     <lb/>
     did not think that such a change should 
     <lb/>
     have been brought about under a Coalition 
     <lb/>
     Government. This was contrary to British 
     <lb/>
     usage, and he believed that if a petition was 
     <lb/>
    numerously signed, and forwarded to the 
     <lb/>Imperial Government, representing that this 
     <lb/>important change had been brought about by 
     <lb/>a coalition, the act would be declared uncon<lb break="no"/>stitutional. The scheme was practically 
     <lb/>unknown to the people. Under some pres<lb break="no"/>sure it had been sent confidentially, to the 
     <lb/>members, but what did the country under<lb break="no"/>stand of it ?—little or nothing. It had been 
     <lb/>said that if the scheme were not adopted now 
     <lb/>it would be in danger ; but would it not keep 
     <lb/>good for a little while ? Was it feared that 
     <lb/>the peeple would find out that it would 
     <lb/>occasion increased expense, and so refuse to 
     <lb/>have it ? If only for the reason that it was 
     <lb/>not known to the people, he would vote against 
     <lb/>it. When the details came to be discussed, 
     <lb/>he believed some of them would not be ap<lb break="no"/>proved ; and he also thought that the project 
     <lb/>not embrace all the provisions which it 
     <lb/>should embrace. Finally, he thought the 
     <lb/>Government should not set its face against 
     <lb/>some changes in the scheme, were it only in 
     <lb/>the matter of the election of members to the 
     <lb/>Legislative Council, and he hoped the House 
     <lb/>would lead them to consent to that alteration. 
     <lb/>When the resolutions came up, he would make 
     <lb/>it his duty to speak more positively to the 
     <lb/>particulars in question. The honorable mem<lb break="no"/>ber then sat down, saying he approved of the 
     <lb/>mode of discussion proposed. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName> then moved that the 
     <lb/>debate be adjourned until Monday, which was 
     <lb/>carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
 
 <!-- GL, 2016-12-01, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
          
<!--<milestone type="unknown"/>
            <fw type="num">LEGISLATIVE</fw>
            <fw type="running">ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
     FRIDAY, February 3, 1865. 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD said the 
     <lb/>
     Speaker having desired that he should not go 
     <lb/>
     on with the Address about the union of the 
     <lb/>
     colonies, he proposed not to take it up till 
     <lb/>
     Monday next, but as the matter was one of 
     <lb/>
     the utmost importance, he thought it would 
     <lb/>
     be well now to settle the mode of conducting 
     <lb/>
     the discussion. He would propose that after 
     <lb/>
     the discussion commenced, it should continue 
     <lb/>
     day after day, and that for the purpose of 
     <lb/>
     greater regularity the Speaker should remain 
     <lb/>
     in the chair. At the same time he would 
     <lb/>
     propose that the rule which prevented mem<lb break="no"/>bers speaking more than once when the Speak<lb break="no"/>er was in the chair should be suspended, in 
     <lb/>
     order that every member might have the same 
     <lb/>
     liberty of free discussion as he would have in 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. J. S. MACDONALD said the Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General's proposition that discussion 
     <lb/>
     should continue day after day, was one which, 
     <lb/>
     in his opinion, ought not to be entertained by 
     <lb/>
     the House. This was a very grave question, 
     <lb/>
     and he thought the people of this country had 
     <lb/>
     a right to consider maturely the sentiments 
     <lb/>
     promulgated by their representatives with re<lb break="no"/>gard to it. He was sorry, therefore, to have 
     <lb/>
     heard it announced by the Attorney General 
     <lb/>
     that the Government were to hurry the mea<lb break="no"/>sure through, to the exclusion of all other 
     <lb/>
     matters. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD said he had 
     <lb/>
     not stated this. His idea was that after the 
     <lb/>
     debate commenced it should go on each day 
     <lb/>
     after half-past seven, leaving the afternoon sit<lb break="no"/>ting for other business. If the discussion was to 
     <lb/>
     be confined to government days, the debate of 
     <lb/>
     Tuesday would be forgotten by Friday, the 
     <lb/>
     same arguments would be gone over, and they 
     <lb/>
     would sit the whole year round to finish it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. J. S. MACDONALD said other 
     <lb/>
     changes of no less importance than this, with 
     <lb/>
     reference to Clergy Reserves, Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cil, Seignorial Tenure, &amp;c., had been before 
     <lb/>
     the people for a quarter of a century, and fully 
     <lb/>
     discussed session after session before being 
     <lb/>
     finally disposed of. Public opinion in that 
     <lb/>
     way was fully matured on these questions, but 
     <lb/>
     here they were called on at a few days' notice 
     <lb/>
     to change entirely the Constitution we lived 
     <lb/>
     under, and time was not to be allowed for 
     <lb/>
     public opinion to be expressed on it. He ob<lb break="no"/>jected also to the suspension of the rules of 
     <lb/>Parliament, so as to make the discussion take 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
</div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>