<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgPCLC_1865-02-07" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPCLCoun">Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1865-02-07">7 February 1865</date>, Province of Canada, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgPCLC">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Parliamentary Debates on the Subject of the Confederation of the British North American Provinces, 3rd Session, 8th Provincial Parliament of Canada</title>.
 

         <date when="1865"/>.   
          

         <pubPlace>Quebec</pubPlace>: <publisher>Hunter, Rose &amp; Co., Parliamentary Printers</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="45" to="53"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0045.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0046.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0047.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0048.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0049.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0050.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0051.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0052.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0053.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0045">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0045.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0046">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0046.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0047">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0047.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0048">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0048.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0049">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0049.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0050">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0050.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0051">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0051.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0052">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0052.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0053">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0053.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="45" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0045.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">46</fw>

<!-- GL, 2016-12-12, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
            <!--<p> mode of securing the
well-being,—the present <lb/>
and future prosperity of British America.<lb break="no"/>(Cheers.)   It is our privilege and happiness <lb/>
to be in such a position, and we cannot be <lb/>
too grateful for the blessings thus conferred <lb/>
upon us.   (Hear, hear.)   I must apologize <lb/>
for having detained you so long— for having <lb/>
gone perhaps too much into tedious details <lb/>
with reference to the questions bearing on <lb/>
the Constitution now submitted to this <lb/>
House. —(Cries of " no, no" and " go
on.") <lb/>
—In conclusion, I would again implore the <lb/>
House not to let this opportunity to pass. <lb/>
It is an opportunity that may never recur. <lb/>
At the risk of repeating myself, I would say, <lb/>
it was only by a happy concurrence of cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances, that we were enabled to bring <lb/>
this great question to its present position. <lb/>
If we do not take advantage of the time, if we <lb/>
show ourselves unequal to the occasion, it <lb/>
may never return, and we shall hereafter <lb/>
bitterly and unavailingly regret having failed <lb/>
to embrace the happy opportunity now <lb/>
offered of founding a great nation under the <lb/>
fostering care of Great Britain, and our <lb/>
Sovereign Lady, Queen Victoria.   (Loud <lb/>
cheers, amidst which the honorable gentle<lb break="no"/>man resumed
his seat). <lb/>
The House, at eleven, P.M., adjourned. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> ___.0_____ <lb/>
            </p>-->
            
<div type="section">
<head>LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL.</head>

            <p> Tuesday, 7th <hi rendition="simple:italic">February</hi>, 1865. <lb/>
            </p>
           
 <p> <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName>
said that yester<lb break="no"/>day he had promised to give to the House <lb/>
to-day an explanation of the provision con<lb break="no"/>tained in the 14th resolution relating to the <lb/>
selection of members for the Legislative <lb/>
Council of the General Legislature. This <lb/>
resolution read as follows :-<lb/>
            </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>l4.  The
first selection of the Members of the <lb/>
Legislative Council shall be made, except as re<lb break="no"/>gards Prince Edward
Island, from the Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive Councils of the various Provinces, so far as <lb/>
a sufficient
number be found qualitied and wil<lb break="no"/>ling to serve ;
such Members shall be appointed <lb/>
by the Crown at the recommendation of the <lb/>
          General Executive Government, upon the
nomi<lb break="no"/>nation of the respective Local Governments, and<lb/>
in such nomination due regard shall be had to <lb/>
the claims of the Members of the Legislative <lb/>
Council of the Opposition in each Province, so <lb/>
that all political parties may
as nearly as
possible <lb/>
be fairly represented. <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p> And under it the
first recommendation
for <lb/>
the appointment
of Legislative Councillors <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
          from Canada would,
should the Confederation <lb/>
scheme be adopted, come from the existing <lb/>
Government of this province.   In making <lb/>
such recommendations, the spirit of the reso<lb break="no"/>lution would be carefully observed, and both <lb/>
sides in this House and as well life as elected <lb/>
members, be equally considered and fairly re<lb break="no"/>presented in the new Parliament. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:FLIN1">HON. MR.FLINT</persName> begged
to inquire whether <lb/>
the resolutions before House were in all <lb/>
respects the
same as those sent to the members. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName> said
they were not <lb/>
in one particular precisely as first printed, <lb/>
there being a clause in those before the House <lb/>
to allow New Brunswick to impose a duty on <lb/>
timber and logs, and Nova Scotia
on coal, <lb/>
which was not found in the first ; as for the <lb/>
other provinces, the imposition of such duties <lb/>
was reserved to the General Legislature. <lb/>
(Hear, hear, from Mr. CURRIE.) <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR.CAMPBELL</persName> said he
hoped that <lb/>
honorable members would rather aid in further<lb break="no"/>ing the scheme than take pleasure in detect<lb break="no"/>ing the supposed causes of opposition.  (Hear.) <lb/>
HON. MR. CURRIE asked
whether the dif<lb break="no"/>ference between the two sets of resolutions <lb/>
was merely a misprint. <lb/>
HON. MR.
CAMPBELL could not say <lb/>
whether it was owing to a misprint or to an <lb/>
error in the manuscript.
<lb/>
HON. MR. CURRIE again asked whether <lb/>
the members of the Conference had not signed <lb/>
the instrument containing its resolutions ? <lb/>
HON. MR. CAMPBELL could only say that <lb/>
the resolutions now before the House truly <lb/>
and expressly represented the conclusions the <lb/>
Conference had
arrived at.   (Hear, hear.) <lb/>
Those conclusions had not been changed. <lb/>
HON. MR. CURRIE then rose and said <lb/>
that the measure now before the House was <lb/>
the most important one ever submitted to a <lb/>
Colonial Legislature, and he hoped to be able <lb/>
to approach it with entire freedom from party  <lb/>
spirit, and without the purpose
of finding out <lb/>
unnecessary objections.   He hoped he would, <lb/>
at all times, be able to judge of the measures <lb/>
presented with the fairness and candour of a <lb/>
Canadian and a British subject.   At the out<lb break="no"/>set he would, however, say, that the project <lb/>
now before the House had taken the country <lb/>
by surprise.   The first time he had ever ad<lb break="no"/>dressed the House he
was reported to have <lb/>
spoken thus :-<lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>That by a course of
legislation alike moderate, <lb/>
prudent and upright, it will yet be the lot of some <lb/>
present to
live and see the day when Canada will<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>be the centre of a
noble British North American <lb/>
Confederecy extending from the Atlantic to the <lb/>
            
            <pb n="46" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0046.jpg"/>
            <fw>46 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
   
          
     Pacific—a Confederacy not born in war, or bap<lb break="no"/>tised in blood , but a Confederacy united by 
     <lb/>
     the bonds of riendship, held together by the 
     <lb/>
     strong ties of friendly commerce and mutual 
     <lb/>
     interests, and cemented by a common allegiance 
     <lb/>
     to the throne of Great Britain. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     From this quotation it would be seen that 
     <lb/>
     then he was in favor of a Confederation of the 
     <lb/>
     several British North American Provinces, but 
     <lb/>
     he little thought then that within two short 
     <lb/>
    years such. a scheme would be submitted to 
     <lb/>Parliament. He was still in favor of Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation—(hear)—but it must be a Confederation 
     <lb/>founded on a just and equitable basis, upon 
     <lb/>principles which would be alike advantageous 
     <lb/>to all and injurious to none. If any 
     <lb/>other kind of Confederation'were agreed upon, 
     <lb/>it would contain within itself the seeds of 
     <lb/>decay and dissolution. The project had been 
     <lb/>elaborately presented to the House by the gal<lb break="no"/>lant knight at the head of the Government, 
     <lb/>and by his able colleague, the Hon. Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner of Crown Lands, and what reasons had 
     <lb/>they alleged in favor of it? He confessed he 
     <lb/>had been quite surprised. at some of the argu<lb break="no"/>ments of the former. That hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>had stated that if the scheme were rejected, 
     <lb/>whether we would -or would not, Canada 
     <lb/>would be forced by violence into the Ameri<lb break="no"/>can Union, or placed upon an inclined plane 
     <lb/>which would carry us there. Now when men 
     <lb/>occupying high positions like the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber, assumed the responsibility of giving ut<lb break="no"/>terance to such startling opinions, they ought 
     <lb/>to be prepared to support them with very 
     <lb/>cogent reasons 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:TACH1">Hon. SIR E. P. TACHÉ</persName>—I am quite ready 
     <lb/>to give them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">Hon. Mr. CURRIE</persName>—If the case were as 
     <lb/>
     represented, it mnstbe because we are quite de<lb break="no"/>fenceless, and that except in union with the 
     <lb/>
     Lower Provinces we were at the mercy of the 
     <lb/>
     United States. But what did the honorable 
     <lb/>
     member mean by the inclined plane ? For his 
     <lb/>
     part, he had not heard of any desire on the part 
     <lb/>
     of the people of this province to change their 
     <lb/>
     political institutions and turn from the glorious 
     <lb/>
     flag under which many of them had fought 
     <lb/>
     and bled. Had anything been heard from 
     <lb/>
     abroad, to the efl'ect that unless we accepted 
     <lb/>
     this scheme, England would cast us off or let 
     <lb/>
     us slide down-the inclined plane ? (Laugher) 
     <lb/>
     Yet these were the sole, or at least the chief , 
     <lb/>
     reasons alleged by that honorable member. 
     <lb/>Let us then ask ourselves whether the scheme<lb/>provided a remedy for the threatened evils.<lb/>Would Canada indeed be so physically strength<lb break="no"/>ened sea-ward and land-ward by this alliance<lb/>
        
            <cb/>
          
     that in the event of aggression on the of 
     <lb/>
     the United States, we would be rende quite 
     <lb/>
     safe ? It was easy to say that union gave 
     <lb/>
     strength, but would this union really give us 
     <lb/>
     strength ? He could understand that union with 
     <lb/>
     a people contiguous would do so, but union 
     <lb/>
     with provinces 1,500 miles apart at the ex<lb break="no"/>treme points, was a very difi'erent thing, and 
     <lb/>
     more likely to be a source of weakness. In 
     <lb/>
     his mind it was like tying a small twine at 
     <lb/>
     the end of a large rope and saying it strength<lb break="no"/>ened the whole line. When the honorable 
     <lb/>
     member said that Canada would be supported 
     <lb/>
     by all the military power of the Lower Prov<lb break="no"/>inces, we should not run away with the idea 
     <lb/>
     that this meant anything. What were the 
     <lb/>
     facts ? Upon looking at the census of those 
     <lb/>
     provinces he found that the male population 
     <lb/>
     between the ages of 21 and 50—the extreme 
     <lb/>
     limits at which men bore arms—was 128,457, 
     <lb/>
     of which number 63,289 were chiefly employed 
     <lb/>
     on the water, that is, in the coasting trade and 
     <lb/>
     the fisheries, leaving 65,000 to assist in the de<lb break="no"/>fence of Canada. (Hear, hear.) Now, en 
     <lb/>
     pose a draft of one-third of these was made 
     <lb/>
    for military exigencies-—and one-third would 
     <lb/>be a large preportion—we would have less 
     <lb/>than 22,000 men available for the service. 
     <lb/>Why, that would not be enough to defend 
     <lb/>their own frontier from aggression. Without 
     <lb/>referring to the causes which had led to the 
     <lb/>formation of the present Government, or to 
     <lb/>the extraordinary conduct of some of the pub<lb break="no"/>lic men composing it, he must nevertheless 
     <lb/>allude to the express objects they professed to 
     <lb/>have in view in coming together. And the 
     <lb/>principal object was a scheme of federation, 
     <lb/>but not the scheme now offered to the House. 
     <lb/>If he understood the matter at all, the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment was organized on the basis of a Con<lb break="no"/>federation of Upper and Lower Canada first, _ 
     <lb/>in which Confederation the Lower Provinces 
     <lb/>might afterwards be admitted if they wished it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName>—Not so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">Hon. Mr. CURRIE</persName>—He was not surprised 
     <lb/>
     at the dissent of the Honorable Commissioner, 
     <lb/>
     of Crown Lands, for the leaders in both, 
     <lb/>
     Houses had placed the larger object, that is 
     <lb/>
     the organization of a general Confederation, 
     <lb/>
     as the primary one. But the basis of the 
     <lb/>
     organization had been reduced to writing, and 
     <lb/>
     he held in his hand the paper which recapitu<lb break="no"/>lated the conditions. They were as follows :— 
     <lb/>
     " The Government are prepared to pledge, 
     <lb/>
    themselves to bring in ameasure, next session, 
     <lb/>for the purpose of removing existing difficulties 
     <lb/>by. introducing the Federal principle into 
     <lb/>Canada, coupled with such provision as will 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="47" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0047.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">47</fw>
         
     permit the Maritime Provinces and the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     West Territory to be incorporated into the same 
     <lb/>
     system of Government." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName>—The resolutions 
     <lb/>
     on the table fulfilled that promise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>— Well, the honorable 
     <lb/>
     member's colleague, the Provincial Secretary, 
     <lb/>
     did not mention the Lower Provinces other<lb break="no"/>wise than incidentally at the great meeting in 
     <lb/>
     South Oxford, and the Intercolonial Railway 
     <lb/>
     not at all. If his position (Hon. Mr. CURRIE'S) 
     <lb/>
     was correct, that the Confederation of Canada 
     <lb/>
     alone was the basis of the coalition, then they 
     <lb/>
     had not carried out their pledge, and he pro<lb break="no"/>nounced the scheme now propounded as the 
     <lb/>authorised production of a number of self- 
     <lb break="yes"/>appointed delegates, and not the measure the 
     <lb/>country expected.  Then he had been sur<lb break="no"/>prised to find that in the Conference Canada 
     <lb/>had so small a representation. He very wil<lb break="no"/>lingly admitted that we had very able men 
     <lb/>there, but they were few compared with the 
     <lb/> whole number of the Conference, and did not 
     <lb/>fairly represent the population and wealth of 
     <lb/>the country. The Honorable Commissioner 
     <lb/>of Crown Lands had said, to be sure, that it did 
     <lb/>not make much difference as the votes were 
     <lb/>not taken by numbers but by the provinces ; 
     <lb/>in other words, that Prince Edward Island, 
     <lb/>with its population of 80,000 souls, had as 
     <lb/>much to say as Canada with its millions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName>—The two sec<lb break="no"/>tions of Canada voted separately. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>—That was not much 
     <lb/>
    better, for it made Prince Edward Island 
     <lb/>equal to Upper Canada, with nearly 1,500,000 
     <lb/>of population. But all this apart, He main<lb break="no"/>tained the country was not prepared to pass 
     <lb/>judgment upon this momentous question. It 
     <lb/>was the greatest matter that had ever been 
     <lb/> presented for its consideration, and it should 
     <lb/>be the aim of all to have it perfectly under<lb break="no"/>stood and approved of before it was adopted. 
     <lb/>We should seek to frame a Constitution which 
     <lb/>would last for ages. If any portion of the 
     <lb/>country were seriously opposed to the project, 
     <lb/>and it were carried through in spite of them, 
     <lb/>a wrong would be inflicted which would per<lb break="no"/>petuate itself in all coming time. If passed 
     <lb/>against the sense of a majority of Upper or 
     <lb/>Lower Canada, the act might lead to an agi<lb break="no"/>tation such as had never been witnessed, and 
     <lb/>which might be fraught with the most disas<lb break="no"/>terous  consequences. To prove that the coun<lb break="no"/>try was not prepared for this sudden change,     
     <lb/>he would ask how many public meetings had<lb/> been held in Upper  Canada for the purpose of 
     <lb/> discussing it? He had heard of but one, and 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
          
     
     that not very influential, where both sides of 
     <lb/>
     the question were discussed. The people had 
     <lb/>
     in fact been waiting for the progamme, and 
     <lb/>
     to this moment it had not been supplied—cer<lb break="no"/>tainly not in all its details. In a matter of 
     <lb/>
     this momentous importance, upon which the 
     <lb/>
     well-being of millions in the future might so 
     <lb/>
     much depend, he sincerely trusted the country 
     <lb/>
     would not be hurried, but that full time for 
     <lb/>
     discussion would be given to enable it to arrive 
     <lb/>
     at a safe verdict. (Hear.) It was said that 
     <lb/>
     all the Governments interested were in favor 
     <lb/>
     of the project, and it was well known that 
     <lb/>
     there was to be a dissolution of Parliament 
     <lb/>
     in one of the provinces ; if so, where was the 
     <lb/>
     necessity for haste in Canada, unless indeed 
     <lb/>
     it was for the purpose of unduly influencing 
     <lb/>
     the other provinces ? When the union 
     <lb/>
     between Upper and Lower Canada was 
     <lb/>
     effected, there had been no such impatience 
     <lb/>
     of delay. The Imperial Government had 
     <lb/>
     brought in a bill, copies of which were sent 
     <lb/>
     out, and submitted to the Parliament of Upper 
     <lb/>
     Canada—Lower Canada then had no Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment to consult, and in its case there was less 
     <lb/>
     need of delay than now—the bill was sent 
     <lb/>
     home again approved, though meetings  were 
     <lb/>
     held in Lower Canada strongly opposed to the 
     <lb/>
     measure, and to this day it is said it was 
     <lb/>
     forced upon an unwilling people.  (Hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear, from some of the French members.) 
     <lb/>
     If time was then allowed, why should not 
     <lb/>
     time be allowed now, when a much more im<lb break="no"/>portant union was in question ? (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
     Had the views of such eminent men as Lord 
     <lb/>
     Ellenborough and Lord Durham been duly 
     <lb/>
     appreciated in 1839, this Parliament would 
     <lb/>
     not now be met for the purpose of dissolving 
     <lb/>
     a union which had been unprofitable to one 
     <lb/>
     section, and unsatisfactory to the other. 
     <lb/>
     (Hear, hear, derisivcly.) He would now take 
     <lb/>
     the liberty to quote the views of Lord Dur<lb break="no"/>ham, to which he had just alluded. They 
     <lb/>
     were as follows : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>
     I am averse to  every plan that has been pro<lb break="no"/>posed for giving an equal number of members to 
     <lb/>
     the two Provinces, in order to obtain the tempor<lb break="no"/>ary end of out-numbering the French, because I 
     <lb/>
     think the same object will be obtained without any 
     <lb/>
     violation of the principles of representation, and 
     <lb/>
     without any such appearance of injustice in the 
     <lb/>
     scheme, as would set public opinion both in Eng<lb break="no"/>land and America strongly against it ; and 
     <lb/>
     because, when emigration shall have increased 
     <lb/>
    the English  population in the Upper  Province, the 
     <lb/>adoption of such a principle would operate to 
     <lb/>defeat this very purpose it is intended to serve. 
     <lb/>It appears to me that any such elective arrange<lb break="no"/>ment, founded on the present Provincial Divisions 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="48" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0048.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">48</fw>
           
     would tend to defeat the purpose of Union, and 
     <lb/>
     perpetrate the idea of disunion. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     He cited these pregnant  words to indicate 
     <lb/>
     the danger of resorting to temporary expe<lb break="no"/>dients for the purpose of overcoming  grave 
     <lb/>
     difficulties. If hon. members desired  to es<lb break="no"/>tablish a union under which the provinces 
     <lb/>
     would grow in wealth, power and importance, 
     <lb/>
     they must endeavor to make it as nearly infal<lb break="no"/>lible as fallible men could. He had already 
     <lb/>
     remarked that there had been but little dis<lb break="no"/>cussion in Upper Canada on this subject, and 
     <lb/>
     he felt it ill became him, representing, as he 
     <lb/>
     did, a large constituency, to vote approbation 
     <lb/>
     before the people understood what the vote 
     <lb/>
     involved. In the Lower Provinces the people 
     <lb/>
     and the press seemed alive to the subject, for 
     <lb/>
     the latter teemed with articles for and against, 
     <lb/>
     all tending to give information which our 
     <lb/>
     population had not received, But speaking 
     <lb/>
     of the Lower Provinces, he was really afraid 
     <lb/>
     that some public men down there were dis<lb break="no"/>posed to exaggerate the advantages of a union 
     <lb/>
     with Canada, just as some of ours seemed prone 
     <lb/>
     to magnify the riches of the Lower Provinces. 
     <lb/>
     If we were going into a partnership, which he 
     <lb/>
     hoped would last if entered into—(hear, hear,) 
     <lb/>
     —we should not attempt to deceive each other, 
     <lb/>
     for if the people found they had been deceived, 
     <lb/>
     the compact would be short-lived. To give 
     <lb/>
     honorable members some idea of the manner 
     <lb/>
     in which the subject was presented by leading 
     <lb/>
     men in the provinces, he would read them an 
     <lb/>
     extract from the speech of a Mr. LYNCH, at a 
     <lb/>
     large meeting in Halifax, as reproduced by 
     <lb/>
     one of the organs of the Government there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName>—What organ ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>—They had so many 
     <lb/>
     organs they did not seem to know them all. 
     <lb/>
     (Laughter.) He would now read from the 
     <lb/>
     speech in question :-<lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>But we are told by others that we had better 
     <lb/>
     have nothing to do with Canada, because she is 
     <lb/>
     bankrupt.  Canada  bankrupt ! I wish we were 
     <lb/>
     all such bankrupts. She is overflowing with 
     <lb/>
     wealth. This is now rapidly developing itself, 
     <lb/>
     and must eventually place her among the first 
     <lb/>
     nations of the earth. I have travelled over and 
     <lb/>
     examined that great country, and it would take 
     <lb/>
     more than all the time allotted to me to tell you 
     <lb/>
     of her wealth and resources. Her rivers are 
     <lb/>
     among the largest in the world, and her lakes 
     <lb/>
     are mighty inland oceans. I never had any idea 
     <lb/>
     of their extent until I stood on the shore of Lake 
     <lb/>
     Erie, saw before me a large square rigged ship, 
     <lb/>
     and was told that such was the class of vessels 
     <lb/>
     that navigated those waters. Why, sir, 7,000,000 
     <lb/>
     tons of shipping trade upon those mighty lakes. 
     <lb/>
     Again, look at the growth of the population.  
     <lb/>
     Sixty years ago it was 60,000, now it is 3,000,000. 
     <lb/>
            
            <cb/>
          
     Upper Canada doubled her population in ten 
     <lb/>
     years, and Toronto, in the beginning of this 
     <lb/>
     century the abode of the red man of the forest, is 
     <lb/>
     now one of the finest cities of British America, 
     <lb/>
     with a population of 40,000. The soil is of the 
     <lb/>
     richest description, indeed it is only too much so. 
     <lb/>
     In some places rich alluvial deposit is found to 
     <lb/>
     the depth of 50 feet, and in many instances lands 
     <lb/>
     have yielded their crops for years without the aid 
     <lb/>
     of a spadeful of manure. Canada has not only 
     <lb/>
     the greatest yield but the best wheat in America. 
     <lb/>
     It is a well-known fact that the people of the 
     <lb/>
     United States in exporting their best flour mix it 
     <lb/>
     to a large extent with Canadian wheat, and in 
     <lb/>
     order to give you an idea of the increased growth 
     <lb/>
     of it I would inform you that while in ten years 
     <lb/>
     the wheat crop increased in the States 50 per 
     <lb/>
     cent. (an immense increase), it in the same time 
     <lb/>
     in Canada increased 400 per cent. The average 
     <lb/>
     crop is equal to that of the best wheat growing 
     <lb/>
     countries in Europe, while some places have 
     <lb/>
     yielded the almost incredible quantity of 100 
     <lb/>
     bushels to the acre. The yield of last year was 
     <lb/>
     27,000.  
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     He only wished that this honorable gentle<lb break="no"/>man alone had been mistaken, but even the 
     <lb/>
     Hon.Mr. TILLEY, one of the most distinguished 
     <lb/>
     statesmen of New Brunswick, had made the 
     <lb/>
     statement that our tariff was in fact only an 
     <lb/>
     eleven per cent. tariff. But all the errors were 
     <lb/>
     not on that side, for they need but turn to a 
     <lb/>
     celebrated speech of one of our own leading 
     <lb/>
     men—a speech regarded almost as an important  
     <lb/>
     state paper—and there it was stated that  the 
     <lb/>
     United Provinces would become the third 
     <lb/>
     maritime power in the world. (Hear, Hear.) 
     <lb/>
     England, it said, was first, then the United 
     <lb/>
     States, and the speaker doubted if France 
     <lb/>
     could take the third rank before us. Our 
     <lb/>
     sea-going tonnage would be five millions, and 
     <lb/>
     our lake tonnage  seven millions. These were 
     <lb/>
     vast figures, and it almost bewildered the mind 
     <lb/>
     to conceive their magnificent proportions. 
     <lb/>
     (Laughter.) Now supposing all these vessels 
     <lb/>
     were 500 tons each, it would require 14,000 
     <lb/>
     to make up the sum, but unfortunately the 
     <lb/>
     census showed that we had but 808 sailors to 
     <lb/>
     navigate them—rather a small number it must 
     <lb/>
     be admitted for 14,000 ships.  (Great laugh<lb break="no"/>ter.) The way the mistake—to use the mildest 
     <lb/>
     expression—was made, was simple enough. 
     <lb/>
     The vessels were entered at the Custom 
     <lb/>
     Houses every time they came in and left port, 
     <lb/>
     and as some of them came into port 200 times 
     <lb/>
     in the year, as at Toronto for instance, their 
     <lb/>
     tonnage was counted 200 times. It was 
     <lb/>
     in this way to run up our inland marine to 
     <lb/>
     seven millions of tons. But then if the pro<lb break="no"/>ducts of Canada were as great as Mr. LYNCH 
     <lb/>
     represented, why of course we would require 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="49" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0049.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">49</fw>
         
     all those ships to carry away all that wheat 
     <lb/>
     (Hear, hear, and laughter.) He would be 
     <lb/>
     glad if he could tell as fine a story, but he 
     <lb/>
     could not do that and at the same time tell 
     <lb/>
     the truth. Then the Lower Provinces were 
     <lb/>
     told that our tariff averaged eleven per cent., 
     <lb/>
     but was it so ? [The honorable member was 
     <lb/>
     here quoting from a speech of Hon. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     TILLEY, to which he had before alluded] 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSS8">HON. MR. ROSS</persName>—Read on. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>, reading on, imme<lb break="no"/>diately came to a paragraph explaining the 11 
     <lb/>
     per cent. to mean the average of duties on the 
     <lb/>
     value of all imported goods, a large proportion 
     <lb/>
     of which were duty free. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. ROSS</persName>—The statement was cor<lb break="no"/>rect. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName> then proceeded to show 
     <lb/>
     the truth in regard to the duties on staples 
     <lb/>
     and articles in domestic use in Canada. He 
     <lb/>
     said if honorable gentlemen would turn to the 
     <lb/>
     Trade and Navigation returns for 1864, they 
     <lb/>
     would find that in the first half of that year 
     <lb/>
     we imported and paid the following duties on 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     eight kinds of commodities: 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>

<table>
<row><cell/><cell>Value.</cell><cell>Duty.</cell></row>
<row><cell>Cottons . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">$3,277,985</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">$644,381</cell> </row>
<row><cell>Woolens . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">2,537,669</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">499,084</cell> </row>
<row><cell>Tea, lbs., 3,048,567 . . . . . .</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">1,059,674</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">275,126</cell></row> 
<row><cell>Iron and hardware . . . . . . . </cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">776,225</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">151,422</cell> </row>
<row><cell>Linen . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </cell><cell rendition="simple:right">421,543</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">84,136 </cell></row>
<row><cell>Hats and Caps . . . . . . . . . . </cell><cell rendition="simple:right">281,197</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">55,546</cell> </row>
<row><cell>Sugar . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </cell><cell rendition="simple:right">779,907</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">376,189 </cell></row>
<row><cell>Sugar, refined . . . . . . . . . . . </cell><cell rendition="simple:right">9,980</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"> 6,260</cell> </row>
<row><cell>Coffee, green . . . . . . . . . . . .</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">89,016</hi></cell> <cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">20,449</hi> </cell></row>
<row><cell/><cell/><cell rendition="simple:right">$2,112,593 </cell></row>
</table>
   
            <p>
     Thus hon. gentlemen would see we pay 
     <lb/>
     more than fifty per cent. on our sugar, nearly 
     <lb/>
     twenty-three per cent. on coffee, while upon tea 
     <lb/>
     we pay about twenty-six per cent. He was 
     <lb/>
     afraid that if the present condition of Canada 
     <lb/>
     was calmly considered we would be found 
     <lb/>
    going into the union in a state far different 
     <lb/>from the glowing representations of Hon. Mr. 
     <lb/>LYNCH. Let hon. members look at the trade 
     <lb/>of Canada for half of the year 1864, and they 
     <lb/>would find that the balance against us was 
     <lb/>$9,999,000. Then there was the interest 
     <lb/>upon the public debt ; interest upon loans to 
     <lb/>private individuals ; bank dividends payable 
     <lb/>abroad, for much of the stock of our banks 
     <lb/>was held out of the province ; the interest to 
     <lb/>loan companies and others ; all to be added to 
     <lb/>the debit balance, and the picture of wealth 
     <lb/>conjured up would present a very different as<lb break="no"/>pect. Indeed, he wondered how, with all these 
     <lb/>the country had borne up so well.-<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>In the next place, he objected to the manner in 
     <lb/>
     which the scheme had been brought down. 
     <lb/>
     Why, if the Government desired the House to 
     <lb/>
     vote favorably, did they not act and speak 
     <lb/>
     understandingly ? Why did they not at once 
     <lb/>
     bring in the schemes for the local governments 
     <lb/>
     and the estimated cost of the Intercolonial 
     <lb/>
     Railway ? He (Hon. Mr. CURRIE) did not ob<lb break="no"/>ject to the principle of Confederation. (Hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear.) No, and he believed there would be 
     <lb/>
     the most perfect unanimity on the subject, as 
     <lb/>
     there was among the delegates as to the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of Confederation, but he asked to have, 
     <lb/>
     as part of the scheme, the cost of the railway , 
     <lb/>
     which seemed to be part and parcel of it. We 
     <lb/>
     knew little of this project, where it was to 
     <lb/>
     commence and where to end, or how many ends 
     <lb/>
     it was to have. We heard there was to be one 
     <lb/>
     branch from Truro to Pictou ; and then it was 
     <lb/>
     said again that the road must pass through the 
     <lb/>
     valley of the St. John, and end in that city. 
     <lb/>
     Were we to accept the project without inform<lb break="no"/>ation ? Were we to have a road to Halifax ? 
     <lb/>
     to purchase the Grand Trunk to Rivière du 
     <lb/>
     Loup and the link from Truro to Halifax, all 
     <lb/>
     of them to enter and form part of the national 
     <lb/>
     railway ? Notwithstanding the admitted talent 
     <lb/>
     of the delegates, he contended that a manifest 
     <lb/>
     injustice had been done to Canada, and espe<lb break="no"/>cially to Upper Canada, in the distribution of 
     <lb/>
     the subsidies to the local governments. Hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen must bear in mind that the subsidies 
     <lb/>
     change not with population, but remain fixed. 
     <lb/>
     They were as follows:-<lb/>
            </p>

<table>
<row><cell>Upper Canada . . . . . . . .</cell><cell> . . . . . </cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$1,116,873 00 </cell></row>
<row><cell>Lower Canada . . . . . . . .</cell><cell> . . . . . .</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">889,248 00</cell> </row>
<row><cell>Nova Scotia . . . . . . . . </cell><cell>. . . . . .</cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">264,000 00 </cell></row>
<row><cell>New Brunswick . . . . . . .</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"> $201,000 </cell><cell/></row>
<row><cell/><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">63,000</hi> </cell> <cell>264,000 00 </cell></row>
<row><cell>Prince Edward Island . . </cell><cell rendition="simple:right">64,035 </cell><cell/></row>
<row><cell/><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">89,043</hi></cell> <cell rendition="simple:right">153,728 00 </cell></row>
<row><cell>Newfoundland . . . . . . . . </cell><cell rendition="simple:right">98,110  </cell><cell/></row>
<row><cell/><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">270,890</hi></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">369,000 00</hi></cell> </row>
<row><cell/><cell/><cell rendition="simple:right">$3,656,849 00 </cell></row>
</table>

         
            <p>If a person was proposing to enter into a 
     <lb/>partnership he would naturally inquire into the 
     <lb/>assets of the other members of the intended 
     <lb/>firm. We knew what our assets were. We 
     <lb/>had the finest canals in the world, which had 
     <lb/>cost many millions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. ROSS</persName>—And they pay. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>—Place tolls on the 
     <lb/>
     St. Lawrence Canals and you will see what 
     <lb/>
     they pay. There was one canal that did pay, 
     <lb/>
     the Welland. In 1861 this work alone earned 
     <lb/>
     
            <pb n="50" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0050.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">50</fw>
          
     a net revenue of $184,289 50, over and above 
     <lb/>
     the costs of repair and management ; and if 
     <lb/>
     you add to that amount the tolls unwisely re<lb break="no"/>funded, $56,474 63, you have an amount 
     <lb/>
     equal to five per cent. on the total expendi<lb break="no"/>ture on the Welland Canal, as shown in the 
     <lb/>
     Report of the Commissioner of Public Works, 
     <lb/>
     up to the 1st January, 1862, and a margin 
     <lb/>
     of $7,436 to the credit of this work. Then 
     <lb/>
     we had the St. Lawrance Canals, and if they 
     <lb/>
     did not pay it was because of the extravagance 
     <lb/>
     of the management and the system of toll on 
     <lb/>
     those works. (Hear.) It was reported that 
     <lb/>
     some people believed if we could only get 
     <lb/>
     Confederation we would have enough to pay 
     <lb/>
     for both the general and local governments, 
     <lb/>
     and so much more to spare that we would not 
     <lb/>
     know what to do with our money. What 
     <lb/>
     would be the revenue of the Confederation ? 
     <lb/>
     Taking the year 1863 as the basis, we find 
     <lb/>
     the revenues of the proposed Confederation for 
     <lb/>
     that year, from customs and excise, to be as 
     <lb/>
     follows : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<table>
<row><cell>Canada . . . . . . . . . . . . </cell><cell>. . . . . . . . . . .</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"> $5,999,320 98 </cell></row>
<row><cell>Newfoundland. . . . . . . . . .</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$496,890</cell><cell/></row>
<row><cell>Prince Edward Island. . </cell><cell rendition="simple:right">153,520 </cell><cell/></row>
<row><cell>Nova Scotia . . . . . . . . . . . </cell><cell rendition="simple:right">861,989</cell> <cell/></row>
<row><cell>New Brunswick . . . . . . . . </cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">768,353</hi> </cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">2,280,752 00</hi> </cell></row>
<row><cell/><cell/><cell rendition="simple:right">$8,280,072 98 </cell></row>
</table>

            <p>
     We will now consider the burdens to be 
     <lb/>
     assumed by the Confederation. Interest on 
     <lb/>
     the debt of Canada, $3,812, 514 01 ; interest 
     <lb/>
     on the debts of New Brunswick and Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia, of $15,000,000, say $750,000 ; in<lb break="no"/>terest on the debt of Newfoundland, of 
     <lb/>
     $946,000, and the debt of Prince Edward 
     <lb/>
     Island, of $240,673—$59,333. Add to this 
     <lb/>
     the interest on the cost of constructing the 
     <lb/>
     Intercolonial Railway, not less than $1,000,000 
     <lb/>
     yearly, supposing it were to cost us but $20,<lb break="no"/>000,000, and the amount to be spent yearly 
     <lb/>
     for defensive purposes, $1,000,000. And 
     <lb/>
     assuming that civil government and the cost 
     <lb/>
     of legislation should be no more for the Con<lb break="no"/>federation than for Canada, which is certainly 
     <lb/>
     a reasonable view, we have for civil govern<lb break="no"/>ment, $430,572 47 ; for legislation, $627,<lb break="no"/>377 92 ; judges' salaries, Lower Canada, 
     <lb/>
     $115,755 55 ; judges' salaries, Upper Canada, 
     <lb/>
     $157,690 33 ; emigration and quarantine, 
     <lb/>
     $57,406 32 ; ocean and river service, $511,<lb break="no"/>356 40 ; lighthouses and coasts, $102,724 75 ; 
     <lb/>
     fisheries, $22,758 41 ; cost of collecting revenue 
     <lb/>
     and excise in Canada, $401,561 41 ; local 
     <lb/>
     subsidies to provinces, $3,056,849. Thus 
     <lb/>
     shewing a balance against revenue of $3,825,<lb break="no"/><cb/>781 89 ; and if the canals are to enlarged, 
     <lb/>
     as promised, an additional debt must be created 
     <lb/>
     of $12,000,000 for such purpose,—another 
     <lb/>
     annual charge of $600,000,—or a total balance 
     <lb/>
     against revenue of $4,425,781 89. These 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen from the east were going to give us 
     <lb/>
     the Intercolonial Railway and enlarge our 
     <lb/>
     canals, but if to enlarge the canals, why were 
     <lb/>
     not the canals put in the Constitution ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DICK2">HON. MR. DICKSON</persName>—They did not want 
     <lb/>
     to throw cold water upon it. (Laughter) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>— Why not give a 
     <lb/>
     guarantee for their enlargement ? He found 
     <lb/>
     that the desirable improvement would entail 
     <lb/>
     an expense of $12,000,000. As to the local 
     <lb/>
     subsidy, be regarded it as a farce, or as honey 
     <lb/>
     spread out to catch flies. As to the argument 
     <lb/>
     that the rejection of the scheme would injure 
     <lb/>
     our credit, he would ask whether the bond<lb break="no"/>holders would not much prefer our present 
     <lb/>
     financial condition to one of fifteen millions 
     <lb/>
     of increased indebtedness, with nothing of 
     <lb/>
     value to show for it. If the people of Eng<lb break="no"/>land knew that Confederation and the Inter- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     colonial Railway meant an increase of fifty 
     <lb/>
     per cent. on our tariff, they would not be so 
     <lb/>
     anxious for it. As to the representation in 
     <lb/>
     the Confederated Legislative Council, it was 
     <lb/>
     proposed to give Upper Canada and Lower 
     <lb/>
     Canada twenty-four members each, and to the 
     <lb/>
     Lower Provinces twenty-eight. That is, the 
     <lb/>
     780,000 souls in the Lower Provinces would 
     <lb/>
     have four members more than Upper Canada 
     <lb/>
     with its million and a half. This proved that 
     <lb/>
     though Canada had talented men in the Con<lb break="no"/>ference, they either forget our interests or 
     <lb/>
     sat there powerless. When the Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Council of Canada was made elective, his 
     <lb/>
     honorable friend near him (Hon. Mr. CHRIS<lb break="no"/>TIE) had stood up for the right of Upper 
     <lb/>
     Canada, as the Delegates should have done 
     <lb/>
     in the Conference. On the second reading of 
     <lb/>
     the bill to change the constitution of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Council, on the 14th March, 1856,-<lb/>
            </p>

           <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"> <p>Mr. BROWN moved, seconded by Mr. FOLEY, 
     <lb/>
     That it be an instruction to the Committee to 
     <lb/>
     amend the bill, by providing that the members of 
     <lb/>
     the Legislative Council shall be elected for four 
     <lb/>
     years, one-half retiring every second year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. GOULD moved, seconded by Mr. WRIGHT, 
     <lb/>
     That it be an instruction to the Committee to 
     <lb/>
     amend the bill by providing that the constituen<lb break="no"/>cies shall be arranged according to population, 
     <lb/>
     without regard to the division line between Upper 
     <lb/>
     and Lower Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     This amendment was supported by the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Messrs. AIKINS, BROWN, CAMERON, CHRIS<lb break="no"/>TIE FOLEY, FREEMAN, WILSON, and many 
     <lb/>
     leading reformers in Upper Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="51" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0051.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">51</fw>
            <p>
     And on the third reading of the bill on the 
     <lb/>
     27th March,-<lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Mr. HARTMAN moved, seconded by Mr. CHRIS<lb break="no"/>TIE, That the bill be recommitted to a Com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the whole House, with a view to ar<lb break="no"/>range the electoral divisions so as to embrace 
     <lb/>
     within each, as nearly as practicable, an equal 
     <lb/>
     population, and without regard to a division line 
     <lb/>
     between Upper and Lower Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     This amendment, although supported by 
     <lb/>
     Messrs. BROWN, CHRISTIE, and twenty other 
     <lb/>
     Upper Canada members, was not carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     If representation by population were right 
     <lb/>
     in 1856, was it not equally right in 1865 ? 
     <lb/>
     But it might be said that the union was to 
     <lb/>
     be a federal one, whereas it was no such thing. 
     <lb/>
     It was neither federal nor legislative, but a 
     <lb/>
     mongrel between both. If the representation 
     <lb/>
     had been properly arranged, there would have 
     <lb/>
     been no necessity for honorable members 
     <lb/>
     vacating their seats. In that case, Upper 
     <lb/>
     Canada would have had 30, Lower Canada 
     <lb/>
     24, and the Lower Provinces 18. Yesterday 
     <lb/>
     the Honorable Commissioner of Crown Lands 
     <lb/>
     had given reasons for abolishing the elective 
     <lb/>
     principle as applied to this House ; but not 
     <lb/>
     over a year ago he had lauded the system, and 
     <lb/>
     he (Hon. Mr. CURRIE) had not heard the life 
     <lb/>
     members say a word in opposition. The 
     <lb/>
    system had got a fair trial of eight years, and 
     <lb/>had proved satisfactory, and would a few self- 
     <lb break="yes"/>constituted delegates, with a dash of the pen, 
     <lb/>destroy that which had received the sanction 
     <lb/>of the country ? He was never sent to this 
     <lb/>House to vote away its constitution—(hear, 
     <lb/>hear)—and before endorsing any such propo<lb break="no"/>sition he would wish to go to his constituents, 
     <lb/>and if they said yes, he would not oppose<lb break="no"/>(hear, hear)—but without that permission, he 
     <lb/>was not going to give a vote which might 
     <lb/>have the effect of giving him his seat for life. 
     <lb/>(Hear, hear.) He had heard of Lower 
     <lb/>Canada domination, but if this was the first 
     <lb/>taste of eastern domination, he wished no 
     <lb/>more of it. (Hear, hear, and laughter.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName>—It was not a 
     <lb/>
     peculiarity of Canada, but the judgment of 
     <lb/>
     the whole Conference. (Hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>—He then presumed 
     <lb/>
     it was not the proposition of the honorable 
     <lb/>
     member that the seat the people had given 
     <lb/>
     him should be given to the Crown ; but it 
     <lb/>
     seemed he had passed under the domination 
     <lb/>
     of the Lower Provinces. (Laughter.) In 
     <lb/>
     1849, the Legislature had made provision for 
     <lb/>
     the support of common schools in Canada, 
     <lb/>
     and had set aside one million acres of the best 
     <lb/>
     lands for that noble purpose. The lands, all 
     <lb/>
         
            <cb/>
          
     situate in Upper Canada, had been sold, and 
     <lb/>
     a fund of a million and a quarter accumu<lb break="no"/>lated, but with another stroke of the pen this, 
     <lb/>
     too, was to be scored out. In 1862, the 
     <lb/>
     Government of the day had brought down a 
     <lb/>
     bill to amend the Separate School Act of 
     <lb/>
     Upper Canada, and without expressing an 
     <lb/>
     opinion as to its merits, he might say it had 
     <lb/>
     produced a very strong feeling of indignation, 
     <lb/>
     A mass meeting was held in Toronto to con<lb break="no"/>demn the bill, and the people were so exas<lb break="no"/>perated that they had called upon certain 
     <lb/>
     members of the Government to resign. Other 
     <lb/>
     meetings were held, viz. :-<lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Meeting at Harrington, North Oxford, 25th 
     <lb/>
     March, 1863: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>,—That the Hon. W. MACDOUGALL 
     <lb/>
     has betrayed the interests of his constituents for 
     <lb/>
     the sake of office. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Meeting at East Nissuuri, 6th April, 1863 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>,—That this meeting, while viewing 
     <lb/>
     the manner in which the Hon. Wm. MACDOUGALL 
     <lb/>
     has betrayed the interests of his constituents in 
     <lb/>
     supporting Mr. SCOTT's Separate School Bill, be- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     lives it to be his duty to resign his seat in the 
     <lb/>
     Provincial Parliament as member for the North 
     <lb/>
     Riding of Oxford. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     He had read these resolutions to show the 
     <lb/>
     feeling which then prevailed, and he might 
     <lb/>
     have quoted articles to prove that the measure 
     <lb/>
     was regarded as a most iniquitous one. He 
     <lb/>
     would give one or two from the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi> :-<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>We can hardly believe that a government 
     <lb/>
     based on the double majority, will permit an al<lb break="no"/>teration in our common school system in defiance 
     <lb/>
     of the vote of an Upper Canadian majority. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     March 20th.—The prospects of Mr. SCOTT's bill 
     <lb/>
     in the Upper House are not very bright. When it 
     <lb/>
     was brought up from the Assembly, nobody rose to 
     <lb/>
     move the first reading, and Sir ETIENNE TACHE, 
     <lb/>
     who, it will be remembered, introduced this last 
     <lb/>
     Upper Canada Separate School Bill, which passed 
     <lb/>
     into law, was about to assume this responsibility, 
     <lb/>
     when Mr. MCCREA, the newly elected Councillor 
     <lb/>
     for the Western Division, came to the rescue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The SPEAKER then very improperly suggested 
     <lb/>
     Mr. AIKINS as the seconder, an office which the 
     <lb/>
     member for the Home Division promptly declined. 
     <lb/>
     No one else appearing, Mr. LETELLIER, a French 
     <lb/>
     Canadian, seconded the motion. This is French 
     <lb/>
     domination with a vengeance. We are not as<lb break="no"/>tonished to find that there is a disposition to give 
     <lb/>
     the bill strong Opposition, regardless of the con<lb break="no"/>sequences to the government . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     April 11.—The bill passed the second reading 
     <lb/>
     in the Legislative Council, 11 to 13 from Upper 
     <lb/>
     Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In spite of every temptation, Upper Canada 
     <lb/>
     stands true to her school system. The bill may 
     <lb/>
     pass as other infamies have passed our Legisla<lb break="no"/><pb n="52" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0052.jpg"/><fw type="num">52</fw>ture before, but it will not be by Upper Canada 
     <lb/>
     votes. If our school system is destroyed, Lower 
     <lb/>
     Canada must bear the shame of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     April 21st.—Although the bill has passed 
     <lb/>
     both Houses, and no number of meetings can 
     <lb/>
     stay its progress, it is well for the people of Up<lb break="no"/>per Canada to pronounce upon its merits. They 
     <lb/>
     are deeply hurt and mortified by this treatment 
     <lb/>
     they have received from Lower Canadians and 
     <lb/>
     traitors among their own representatives. A sense 
     <lb/>
     of personal wrong and injury exists which we 
     <lb/>
     have never witnessed in so great a degree before. 
     <lb/>
     The iron of Lower Canada domination seems to 
     <lb/>
     have touched the soul of the people and the wound 
     <lb/>
     rankles. The word contempt does not express 
     <lb/>
     the feeling which is manifested. There is a spice 
     <lb/>
     of bitterness about it which takes it out of that 
     <lb/>
     category. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But, notwithstanding these evidences of dis<lb break="no"/>satisfaction, the act became law, and it re<lb break="no"/>mained for the present Government, by this 
     <lb/>
     scheme, to perpetuate the law. He was sur<lb break="no"/>prised that the Government, framed as it was, 
     <lb/>
     should become parties to such a scheme. They 
     <lb/>
     had not yet done with the school question. 
     <lb/>
     They proposed to protect the Protestant 
     <lb/>
     minority of Lower Canada, and a petition was 
     <lb/>
     on the table exhibiting what was desired. This 
     <lb/>
     was proof enough that the people were not 
     <lb/>
     satisfied ; and whether or not the scheme of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation were adopted, the Government 
     <lb/>
     should bring in a measure to do the petition<lb break="no"/>ers justice. Then from Upper Canada the 
     <lb/>
     Roman Catholics asked to be placed in a posi<lb break="no"/>tion precisely similar to that which the Pro<lb break="no"/>testants of Lower Canada were seeking, and 
     <lb/>
     if each of these minorities were suffering in<lb break="no"/>justice, why should not their complaints be 
     <lb/>
     redressed before a Confederation took place ? 
     <lb/>
     Let these measures prelude Confederation, 
     <lb/>
     and let not Parliament be asked to proceed 
     <lb/>
     blindfold. He was satisfied that if the Inter- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     colonial Railway project were taken out of the 
     <lb/>
     scheme, we would not hear much about it 
     <lb/>
     afterwards. Some leading men in Halifax 
     <lb/>
     had said, " the Railway first, and Confedera<lb break="no"/>ion next." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</quote>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SANB1">HON. MR. SANBORN</persName>—Hon. Mr. TLLLEY 
     <lb/>
     had said that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>—Then it would be 
     <lb/>
     better to try the Confederation without the 
     <lb/>
     railway. It would, after all, be much easier for 
     <lb/>
     the members from the Lower Provinces to 
     <lb/>
     come to Ottawa than it used to be for the 
     <lb/>
     members from Sandwich to go to Montreal at 
     <lb/>
     the time of the union. The Grand Trunk 
     <lb/>
     Railway had cost the province a vast sum, but 
     <lb/>
     then it had been of vast service to the country. 
     <lb/>
     But where is the company that would keep the 
     <lb/>
     Intercolonial Railway running for its earnings, 
     <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
          
     the road and the rolling stock being made over 
     <lb/>
     to them as a gift ? Suppose a merchant from 
     <lb/>
     Montreal wants to go to England, which road 
     <lb/>
     will he prefer ? Why, he would go by way of 
     <lb/>
     Portland. Would any produce be sent over 
     <lb/>
     such a road ? How much wheat was there 
     <lb/>
     sent over the Grand Trunk, even in winter ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FERR1">HON. MR. FERRIER</persName>—A great deal. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>—How much from 
     <lb/>
     Montreal ? And why did we hear complaints 
     <lb/>
     from Huron and Bruce ?  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     SEVERAL VOICES—They have no rail<lb break="no"/>way there. (Laughter.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>—Was there not the 
     <lb/>
     Buffalo and Lake Huron Railway passing 
     <lb/>
     through Huron ? It was our duty to hesitate 
     <lb/>
     and not to press on at railway speed, but to 
     <lb/>
     act like prudent men. We were sent here to 
     <lb/>
     place a check upon hasty legislation. But was 
     <lb/>
     there ever such hasty legislation as this ? Yet 
     <lb/>
     as the Government were strong in Parliament, 
     <lb/>
     they might attempt to press the measure with<lb break="no"/>out the consent of the people. If they do, how<lb break="no"/>ever, pursue such a course, they will perhaps 
     <lb/>
     receive a check in Nova Scotia or New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, for in these provinces they had no inten<lb break="no"/>tion to pass the measure without a free and 
     <lb/>
     full discussion.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. ROSS</persName>—Why, if it was good for 
     <lb/>
     them as the hon. member said, they might be 
     <lb/>
     glad to do it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCR2">HON. MR. MCCREA</persName>—If it was so unfa<lb break="no"/>vorable for Canada it must be in the same 
     <lb/>
     degree favorable to the Lower Provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>—Oh, that does not 
     <lb/>
     by any means follow ; they are a frugal, indus<lb break="no"/>trious and intelligent people, and it may be 
     <lb/>
     considered inadvisable by them to join a people 
     <lb/>
     who, in the short term of ten years, by a course 
     <lb/>
     of extravagance and prodigality increased the 
     <lb/>
     expenses of their government nearly four hun<lb break="no"/>dred per cent., independent of the increase of 
     <lb/>
     the public debt. They might also call to mind 
     <lb/>
     the Grand Trunk swindles. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. ROSS</persName>—When the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     said that there had been Grand Trunk swin<lb break="no"/>dles, he said what was not correct. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>—Perhaps he used a 
     <lb/>
     wrong term. He meant Grand Trunk frauds. 
     <lb/>
     Those people might hesitate about connecting 
     <lb/>
     themselves with a people that had almost 
     <lb/>
     brought themselves to the verge of national 
     <lb/>
     bankruptcy, and loaded themselves with such 
     <lb/>
     a heavy tariff, they might recall to mind the 
     <lb/>
     political dishonesty of our public men, men 
     <lb/>
     who had so maligned and blackened the pub<lb break="no"/>lic character of each other as to require a 
     <lb/>
     wider stage and a new audience to witness 
     <lb/>
         
            <pb n="53" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-07_Page_0053.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">53</fw>
          
     their future acts. They would also observe 
     <lb/>
     that all formerly connected with the Grand 
     <lb/>
     Trunk were urging this scheme forward. He 
     <lb/>
     then accused the Government of bad faith in 
     <lb/>
     bringing down these resolutions, instead of a 
     <lb/>
     measure simply for the Canadas; that the 
     <lb/>
     reform party only committed themselves to 
     <lb/>
     the latter scheme when Mr. BROWN entered 
     <lb/>
     the Cabinet, but now it was only secondary. 
     <lb/>
     To bear this out he read the following reso<lb break="no"/>lution adopted by that party :-<lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Moved by Mr. HOPE McKENZIE, and second<lb break="no"/>ed by Mr. McGIVERIN— That we approve of the 
     <lb/>
     course which has been pursued by Mr. BROWN in 
     <lb/>
     the negotiations with the Government. and that 
     <lb/>
     we approve of the project of a Federal union of 
     <lb/>
     the Canadas, with provision for its extension to 
     <lb/>
     the Maritime Provinces and the North-Western 
     <lb/>
     territory, as one based on which the constitutional 
     <lb/>
     difficulties now existing should be settled. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     He was not personally opposed to Con<lb break="no"/>federation in itself , but this measure was so 
     <lb/>
     defective that he could not support it, bearing, 
     <lb/>
     as it did, the seeds of decay apparent in its 
     <lb/>
     details. He heartily concurred in the views 
     <lb/>
     expressed recently at Halifax, by a distinguished 
     <lb/>
     Upper Canada Statesman—(MR. BROWN):— 
     <lb/>
     " On a survey of the whole case, I do think 
     <lb/>
     that there is no doubt as to the high advan<lb break="no"/>tages that would result from a union of all 
     <lb/>
     the colonies, provided that terms of union 
     <lb/>
     could be found just to all the contracting 
     <lb/>
     parties, and so framed as to secure harmony 
     <lb/>
     in the future administration of affairs. But 
     <lb/>
     it were wrong to conceal for a moment that 
     <lb/>
     the whole merit of the scheme of union may 
     <lb/>
     be completely marred by the character of its 
     <lb/>
     details." He asked who would not say that 
     <lb/>
     the details of this measure did not so mar as 
     <lb/>
     to spoil the scheme. If we are to have a Con<lb break="no"/>federation, let it be put upon a proper and 
     <lb/>
     permanent foundation, one that will be of ad<lb break="no"/>vantage to this young and vigorous province, 
     <lb/>
     and he expressed the hope that only such a 
     <lb/>
     scheme would be sanctioned by Parliament. 
     <lb/>
     (Hear, hear, and applause.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     lt being nearly six o'clock, HON. MR. 
     <lb/>
     Ross moved to adjourn the debate till the 
     <lb/>
     morrow, which was carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The House then adjourned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2016-12-12, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

           <!-- <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <fw type="num">LEGISLATIVE</fw>
            <fw type="running">ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
     TUESDAY, February 7, 1865. 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     ATTY. GEN. CARTIER rose to continue 
     <lb/>
     the debate on Confederation. He said that 
     <lb/>
     he approached this subject with a certain 
     <lb/>
     amount of diffidence, knowing it was not the 
     <lb/>
     first time he had had the honor of speaking 
     <lb/>
     upon it in the Lower Provinces and elsewhere. 
     <lb/>
     He felt that this was a momentous occasion, 
     <lb/>
     as for anything that he said on this grave 
     <lb/>
     question, he was responsible to his constituents 
     <lb/>
     and the country. Respecting this grave ques<lb break="no"/>tion, it had been said that the TACHÉ-MAC- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     DONALD Government had taken upon them<lb break="no"/>selves the solution of a problem which was not 
     <lb/>
     at the time of its formation before the coun<lb break="no"/>try, and had not even been mooted. Those 
     <lb/>
     saying so were ignorant of the parliamentary 
     <lb/>
     history of the past few years. He would briefly 
     <lb/>
     refer to the history of this great question, as 
     <lb/>
     far as it had been brought before the Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment and country. When the CARTIER-MAC- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     DONALD Government was constructed, after 
     <lb/>
     the downfall of the BROWN-DORION Adminis<lb break="no"/>tration, a programme of the policy of the 
     <lb/>
     former was laid before Parliament. Among 
     <lb/>
     the subjects contained in this programme of 
     <lb/>
     7th August, 1858, was one referred to in the 
     <lb/>
     following terms: " The late Government felt 
     <lb/>
     themselves bound to carry out the law of the 
     <lb/>
     land respecting the seat of Government, but, in 
     <lb/>
     the face of the recent vote on that subject, the 
     <lb/>
     Administration did not consider themselves 
     <lb/>
     warranted in incurring an expenditure for 
     <lb/>
     the public buildings, until Parliament has had 
     <lb/>
     an opportunity of considering the whole ques<lb break="no"/>tion in all its bearings ; and the expediency of 
     <lb/>
     a Federal Union of the British North American 
     <lb/>
     Provinces will be anxiously considered, and 
     <lb/>
     communication with the Home Government 
     <lb/>
     and the Lower Provinces entered into forth<lb break="no"/>with on the subject ; and the result of this 
     <lb/>
     communication will be submitted to Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment at its next session. The Government 
     <lb/>
     will, during the recess, examine into the organ<lb break="no"/>ization and working of the public departments, 
     <lb/>
     and carry out such administrative reforms as 
     <lb/>
     will be conducive to economy and efficiency." 
     <lb/>
     Here was this scheme of a union of the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces mentioned in the programme of the 
     <lb/>
     CARTIER-MACDONALD Government, in 1858. 
     <lb/>
     He merely quoted this passage to show that 
     <lb/>
     neither Parliament nor the country was now 
     <lb/>
     taken by surprise with regard to this scheme. 
     <lb/>
     (Hear, hear.) We had had general and spe<lb break="no"/>cial elections since 1858, and to pretend that 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>