<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPCLC_1865-02-06"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPCLCoun">Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1865-02-06">6 February 1865</date>, Province of Canada, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

       
          
         
               <title>Parliamentary Debates on the Subject of the Confederation of the British North American Provinces, 3rd Session, 8th Provincial Parliament of Canada</title>.
 
                    

          <date when="1865"/>. 
          

          <pubPlace>Quebec</pubPlace>: <publisher>Hunter, Rose &amp; Co., Parliamentary Printers</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="25"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0020.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0021.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0022.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0023.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0024.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0025.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-01">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-01">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0020">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0020.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0021">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0021.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0022">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0022.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0023">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0023.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0024">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0024.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0025">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0025.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="20" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0020.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">20</fw>

<!-- GL, 2016-12-01, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

           <!-- <p>
     the Resolutions on Confederation of the Provinces 
     <lb/>
     are set out. How does this differ from an Address 
     <lb/>
     moved to His Excellency , which always comes 
     <lb/>
     on motion upon a two days' notice given as in 
     <lb/>
     this case ? I cannot see how, as a point of Order, 
     <lb/>
     I can treat the matter other than as in the ordinary 
     <lb/>
     case of an Address. The argument is that it will 
     <lb/>
     be inconvenient so to discuss it. That is not 
     <lb/>
     addressed to a question of Order, but to one of 
     <lb/>
     convenience. The case cited by the honorable 
     <lb/>
     member for Chateauguay of Resolutions upon 
     <lb/>
     the question of a Bill for the Government of 
     <lb/>
     India was not one of Resolutions for an Address, 
     <lb/>
     but of Resolutions simply , containing the pro<lb break="no"/>posed principles of the Bill intended to be intro<lb break="no"/>duced. It is not pretended here that this House 
     <lb/>
     has any right to pass such a Bill, or that it is 
     <lb/>
     intended to present one on that subject here. The 
     <lb/>
     reasons why it is convenient to discuss matters in 
     <lb/>
     the form of a Resolution on which a Bill is after<lb break="no"/>wards to be introduced, is that Resolutions more 
     <lb/>
     easily admit of alteration. The Government 
     <lb/>
     have expressed their determination not to admit 
     <lb/>
     of any alterations in these Resolutions. Thus it 
     <lb/>
     is obvious that the same reasons for going into 
     <lb/>
     Committee do not hold. The member who 
     <lb/>
     moves an Address can force the vote on his 
     <lb/>
     motion in the manner he has put it, unless the 
     <lb/>
     form of it be changed by amendment, and this 
     <lb/>
     appears to be the only course open here. In 
     <lb/>
     truth the word ' Resolutions' might very well 
     <lb/>
     have been omitted altogether from this motion. 
     <lb/>
     Whatever might have been the result on a mere 
     <lb/>
     question of convenience, it is certain that the 
     <lb/>
    Specker does not decide that matter. His duties 
     <lb/>are to preserve order and decorum, and to decide 
     <lb/>questions of Order." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD moved 
     <lb/>
     that the debate be adjourned and made 
     <lb/>
     the first order for Monday after half-past 
     <lb/>
     seven o'clock, P.M. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     HON. MR. HOLTON raised the objection 
     <lb/>
     that this motion could not be put without 
     <lb/>
     two days' notice 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     ATTY. GEN. MACDONALD said if this 
     <lb/>
     was the sort of tactics to be pursued, and an 
     <lb/>
     attempt made to embarrass the Government 
     <lb/>
     at every step, he must withdraw the conces<lb break="no"/>sion made to the member for Peel, and would 
     <lb/>
     give notice that he would move on Tuesday , 
     <lb/>
     that the debate be continued from day to 
     <lb/>
     day until the Address was finally adopted or 
     <lb/>
     rejected by the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After some discussion, Hon. Mr. HOLTON 
     <lb/>
     withdrew his objection, and Atty. Gen. 
     <lb/>
     MACDONALD his notice. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>-->

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     MONDAY, <hi rendition="simple:italic">February</hi> 6, 1865. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName> said that, with 
     <lb/>the permission of the honorable member who  
     <lb/>had the floor (Hon. Mr. CURRIE), he would 
     <lb/>offer a few remarks upon one portion of the 
     <lb/>scheme of Confederation, to which allusion 
     <lb/>had been specially made in the House, and 
     <lb/>which, to a limited extent, had occupied the  
     <lb/>attention of the country . He referred to the 
     <lb/>proposed constitution of the Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cil under that scheme ; and in offering the 
     <lb/>reasons which had led the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and the other members of the Confer<lb break="no"/>ence, which, as honorable members knew, was  
     <lb/>composed of the leading men in the legisla<lb break="no"/>tures of the several provinces — the leading 
     <lb/>men in opposition as well as the leading man in 
     <lb/>office—to decide as they had done, he begged 
     <lb/>the House to believe that the decision had 
     <lb/>not been arrived at hastily, but after prolonged 
     <lb/>and anxious discussion, and after a full and 
     <lb/>careful consideration of the subject. It was 
     <lb/>not to be supposed that the Government of<lb/>Canada had itself laid down the scheme of 
     <lb/>the constitution as embraced in the resolutions 
     <lb/>on the table of the House. Honorable gentle<lb break="no"/>men must not misunderstand him. He did 
     <lb/>not mean to say that the Government did not 
     <lb/>heartily concur in and adopt the scheme, but 
     <lb/>that it was not its work alone, but that of the 
     <lb/>delegates from the other provinces as well. 
     <lb/>It was the result of deliberation, accommo<lb break="no"/>dation and compromise. When it became 
     <lb/>necessary for the Government to press the 
     <lb/>resolutions, he trusted honorable members 
     <lb/>would not suppose that they did so out of 
     <lb/>that love which people have for the creation 
     <lb/>of their own intellect, but would remember 
     <lb/>they were the joint production of the gentle<lb break="no"/>men to whom he alluded, and that any per<lb break="no"/>tinacity on his part arose from a sense of the 
     <lb/>sacrifices they had made to secure an agree<lb break="no"/>ment, and the difficulties which any failure  
     <lb/>now would create. He felt it had been im<lb break="no"/>possible for the Conference to arrive at any 
     <lb/>other understanding, and he only wished that 
     <lb/>those who looked with disfavor upon their 
     <lb/>plan, could have witnessed the anxious debates 
     <lb/>held at Charlottetown and Quebec before it 
     <lb/>was finally settled. The result arrived at 
     <lb/>would, he hoped, promote the welfare of the 
     <lb/>provinces interested, and be remembered with 
     <lb/>gratitude by their inhabitants many long years 
     <lb/>hence. And supposing this Chamber and 
     <lb/>the other were to come to a different opinion 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="21" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0021.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">21</fw>
          
     
     and reject the resolutions, what would 
     <lb/>
     be the effect ? The  sacrifices and com<lb break="no"/>promises submitted to by the representa<lb break="no"/>tives of the several provinces would go for 
     <lb/>
     nothing ; the efforts of the eminent men who 
     <lb/>
     had put aside personal and party differences 
     <lb/>
     to accomplish what they deemed a great and 
     <lb/>
     good work would be futile ; and yet, by such 
     <lb/>
     men only could such a scheme have been 
     <lb/>
     devised and matured. Considering then the 
     <lb/>
     earnest efforts made to secure this agreement, 
     <lb/>
     and the improbability that, if rejected, any 
     <lb/>
     other could be attempted with better hope of 
     <lb/>
     success, he felt he had a right to ask the House 
     <lb/>
     to give the subject a fair, patient, and favor<lb break="no"/>able consideration. If an amendment were 
     <lb/>
     proposed here, and another there, and espe<lb break="no"/>cially if the provision respecting the constitu<lb break="no"/>tion of the House were changed, it was pretty 
     <lb/>
     certain that the whole thing would miscarry, 
     <lb/>
     for he well knew that in respect of this point 
     <lb/>
     the legislatures of the Lower Provinces would 
     <lb/>
     come to a different conclusion. If the elective 
     <lb/>
     principle were insisted upon in Canada, and 
     <lb/>
     its Government bound over to maintain it, 
     <lb/>
     even though another Conference were called, 
     <lb/>
     no agreement could be expected, for as he had 
     <lb/>
     already said, the delegates from the other 
     <lb/>
     provinces would be sure to be charged with 
     <lb/>
     exactly different instructions. And as of this 
     <lb/>
     particular point, so of a hundred others, until 
     <lb/>
     it would be utterly impossible again to arrive 
     <lb/>
     at anything like unanimity. As the honorable 
     <lb/>
     member for Brock had so well said on a previous 
     <lb/>
     evening, any failure now would be extremely 
     <lb/>
     damaging to our credit abroad. It was well 
     <lb/>
    kown that the fact of our public men having 
     <lb/>thrown aside their political partisanship for 
     <lb/>the purpose of advancing the welfare of the 
     <lb/>country, the holding of the Conference, and 
     <lb/>the agreement secured, had already done us 
     <lb/>a great deal of good at home. But not 
     <lb/>only would this first fruit of the work be 
     <lb/>forfeited, but an injury more than correspond<lb break="no"/>ingly great would follow. (Hear, hear.) [ The 
     <lb/>honorable member elaborated this idea at some 
     <lb/>length with the view of showing the beneficial 
     <lb/>effect the adoption of the scheme of Confed<lb break="no"/>eration had produced, and the disasterous 
     <lb/>consequences which its rejection by Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment must inevitably entail.] He did not 
     <lb/>propose to follow his honorable friend the 
     <lb/>Premier in the discussion of the merits of the 
     <lb/>project as a whole ; the able manner in which 
     <lb/>that honorable member had presented it could 
     <lb/>not but have commended itself to every can<lb break="no"/>did mind. (Hear, hear.) He (Hon. Mr. CAMP<lb break="no"/>BELL) would, however, take up the point to 
     <lb/>
          

    
            <cb/>
         
     which he had alluded at the commencement, 
     <lb/>
     and from which he had for a moment digressed. 
     <lb/>
     and give the reasons which had induced the 
     <lb/>
     Conference to determine as they had done, 
     <lb/>
     upon the constitution of the Upper House. 
     <lb/>
     And the main reason was to give each of the 
     <lb/>
     provinces adequate security for the protection 
     <lb/>
     of its local interests, a protection which it 
     <lb/>
     was feared might not be found in a House 
     <lb/>
     where the representation was based upon num<lb break="no"/>bers only , as would be the case in the General 
     <lb/>
     Assembly. The number of representatives 
     <lb/>
     to the Legislative Council under the Federal 
     <lb/>
     constitution would be limited, and they would 
     <lb/>
     be appointed for life instead of elected by the 
     <lb/>
     people. For the purpose of securing equality 
     <lb/>
     in that House, the Confederation would be 
     <lb/>
     divided into two sections, vis. : Upper Canada, 
     <lb/>
     Lower Canada, and the Maritime Provinces, 
     <lb/>
     and each of these sections would send twenty- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     four members to the House. In Upper Ca<lb break="no"/>nada, as had been stated lately by an honor<lb break="no"/>able member, the population has increased 
     <lb/>
     very rapidly, and would probably go on in<lb break="no"/>creasing in a much larger ratio than that of 
     <lb/>
     Lower Canada or the other provinces, and if 
     <lb/>
     the Legislative Council were elective, the time 
     <lb/>
     might come when the people of that section 
     <lb/>
     would fancy themselves entitled to an increased 
     <lb/>
     representation in the Council, and commerce 
     <lb/>
     to agitate for it. They might object to the 
     <lb/>
     fishing bounties paid the Lower Province, to 
     <lb/>
     the money expended there in fortifications, or 
     <lb/>
     to something else, and claim a representation 
     <lb/>
     in the Council, more in accordance with their 
     <lb/>
     population to enforce their views ; and in view 
     <lb/>
     of such contingencies the delegates from those 
     <lb/>
     provinces conceived it would not be safe to 
     <lb/>
     trust their rights to an elective House. It 
     <lb/>
     was then determined that in one branch 
     <lb/>
     there would be a fixed number of members 
     <lb/>
     nominated by the Crown, to enable it to 
     <lb/>
     act as a counterpoise to the branch in 
     <lb/>
     which the principle of representation accord<lb break="no"/>ing to population would be recognized. It 
     <lb/>
     might be said that the principle of limita<lb break="no"/>tion of numbers could have been adopted, and 
     <lb/>
     that of election preserved. Well, he did not 
     <lb/>
     say the scheme was perfect, but it was the 
     <lb/>
     best that could be devised, and as the Lower 
     <lb/>
     Provinces felt the danger from their inferiority 
     <lb/>
     of numbers, being only 800,000 against double 
     <lb/>
     that number in Upper Canada alone, it was 
     <lb/>
     essential that the security which a fixed repre<lb break="no"/>sentation in the Council afforded to them 
     <lb/>
     should be acceded to. The Conference acted 
     <lb/>
     upon the conviction that they were not build<lb break="no"/>ing a structure for a temporary purpose, but, 
     <lb/>
  
            <pb n="22" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0022.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">22</fw>
       
     as they hoped, for centuries, and knowing 
     <lb/>
     how the doctrine of representation according 
     <lb/>
     to population had operated in distracting the 
     <lb/>
     popular branch of the Legislature in Canada, 
     <lb/>
     they endeavored to provide against a similarly 
     <lb/>
     disturbing cause in the Confederation. And 
     <lb/>
     their precaution appeared to him to be founded 
     <lb/>
     in wisdom and justice. For the sake of argu<lb break="no"/>ment let it be supposed that the elective prin<lb break="no"/>ciple is maintained, and that the limit of 
     <lb/>
     numbers now proposed, viz., 24 members for 
     <lb/>
     each of the three grand sections in the Council 
     <lb/>
     is also fixed ; let it be supposed further, that 
     <lb/>
     the population of Upper Canada continues to 
     <lb/>
     augment as in the past, what may not be that 
     <lb/>
     of the Saugeen, Tecumseth and Eastern Divi<lb break="no"/>sions (which now have 130,000, 90,000 and 
     <lb/>
     60,000 respectively) forty or fift years hence ? 
     <lb/>
     And is it not possible, nay, would, it not be like<lb break="no"/>ly, that these great constituences, when compar<lb break="no"/>ing them with the divisions in Prince Edward 
     <lb/>
     Island, numbering some twenty thousand to 
     <lb/>
     twenty-five thousand souls, would be disposed 
     <lb/>
     to set up claims for additional representation ? 
     <lb/>
     Who that looks to the future will say that with 
     <lb/>
     an elective Upper House the Constitution will 
     <lb/>
     last ? It was the apprehension of danger to 
     <lb/>
     its permanency that decided the Conference 
     <lb/>
     to adopt the principle of nomination to the 
     <lb/>
     superior branch, and it was the only way 
     <lb/>
     which suggested itself for averting it. And 
     <lb/>
     he must say for himself, that he fully and 
     <lb/>
     entirely concurred in the decision. He felt 
     <lb/>
     that the principle of election kept alive a germ 
     <lb/>
     of doubt as to the security of the Lower Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, and he was glad at a way was found 
     <lb/>
     of removing  it altogether. It was well known 
     <lb/>
     that even in the United States, where there 
     <lb/>
     was so prevalent a disposition to submit 
     <lb/>
     everything to the decision of the people, the 
     <lb/>principle of limitation to the Upper House 
     <lb/>was so fully recognized and settled by the 
     <lb/>Constitution, that no attempt was ever made 
     <lb/>to change it. In this way the smallest state, 
     <lb/>like Rhode Island, was as fully represented as 
     <lb/>the state of New York. And if that was 
     <lb/>considered necessary in a country so compact 
     <lb/>together as the United States, how much 
     <lb/>more would it not be proper in a Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, some of the sections of which were sepa<lb break="no"/>rated from each other by long, narrow strips 
     <lb/>of land, or wide estuaries, with small repre<lb break="no"/>sentation in the popular branch, and looking 
     <lb/>chiefly to their equality in the Upper Chamber 
     <lb/>for security for local rights and interests and 
     <lb/>institutions. He was gratified, upon another 
     <lb/>ground, that this decision had been attained, 
     <lb/>and this was on the ground of the respect he 
     <lb/>
            
    
            <cb/>
      
     bore to the life-members of this Chamber. In 
     <lb/>
     the law which had made the House elective 
     <lb/>
     there was no wiser provision than that which 
     <lb/>
     had guaranteed the seat of the members ap<lb break="no"/>pointed by the Crown, who then composed it. 
     <lb/>
     He had always felt the great advantage of the 
     <lb/>
     presence of those honorable members here. 
     <lb/>
     If the elective system had entirely superseded 
     <lb/>
     the nominated House, removed those gentle<lb break="no"/>men and brought together forty-eight entirely 
     <lb/>
     new members, the country would have suffered 
     <lb/>
     a grievous loss ; but the old members kept 
     <lb/>
     their places and the new ones came in twelve 
     <lb/>
     at a time, two years apart, so that the change 
     <lb/>
     from one system to the other was effected 
     <lb/>
     without any injury. The nominated members 
     <lb/>
     had retained their influence, and the tone of 
     <lb/>
     calmness and gravity which had obtained in 
     <lb/>
     their deliberations was insensibly acquired by 
     <lb/>
     the elective members as they came in, to the 
     <lb/>
     manifest advantage of the House. We 
     <lb/>
     (speaking of the elected members) had picked 
     <lb/>
     up the spirit of, and the instruction the 
     <lb/>
     Crown members were so fully competent to 
     <lb/>
     give us, and so had been enabled to discharge 
     <lb/>
     our duties in a way we could not possibly 
     <lb/>
     have done if had we been left to ourselves. 
     <lb/>
     If the life-members had been deprived of their 
     <lb/>
     seats, it was not probable that many, if any 
     <lb/>
     of them, would have sought a restoration to 
     <lb/>
     them by the elective process, for they were 
     <lb/>
     generally gentlemen of wealth, position, and 
     <lb/>
     delicacy of feeling, whose habits of mutual 
     <lb/>
     deference, quietness and order, would have 
     <lb/>
     unfitted them, or made them averse to face 
     <lb/>
     the turmoil and excitement of the unfavorable 
     <lb/>
     electioneering contests. These honorable 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen, under an elective system, must have 
     <lb/>
     been deprived of their seats, and their services 
     <lb/>
     have been lost to the country ; whilst under 
     <lb/>
     the nominative system they will stand on the 
     <lb/>
     same footing as the other members of this 
     <lb/>
     House, and have a fair representation along 
     <lb/>
     with the members holding their seats by 
     <lb/>
     election in the Legislative Council of the 
     <lb/>
     Confederate Parliament. (Hear, hear.) Pass<lb break="no"/>ing on to another point, he would remark that 
     <lb/>
     some persons had asked what would be done 
     <lb/>
     if the two Chambers of the Confederation 
     <lb/>
     came into collision ? He had already re<lb break="no"/>marked that the Legislative Council was 
     <lb/>
     intended as a counterpoise to the weight 
     <lb/>
     of numbers in the Assembly, but such a 
     <lb/>
     counterpoise did not necessarily imply the 
     <lb/>
     probability of collision. It was not likely that 
     <lb/>
     the two branches would come into such collision 
     <lb/>
     upon minor subjects, or subjects of minor im<lb break="no"/>portance, for two such bodies- should not, for 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="23" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0023.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">23</fw>
       

     the mere sake of resistance, oppose each other 
     <lb/>
     in such a way ; they would not venture to do 
     <lb/>
     it. He did not remember that there had been 
     <lb/>
     my really difficult matter of this kind for a 
     <lb/>
     long time. This House had rejected the 
     <lb/>
     Squatters' Bill, as it was called, seven or eight 
     <lb/>
     times after it had been passed by the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly, but that had not impaired the good un<lb break="no"/>derstanding between them. Indeed the effect 
     <lb/>
     had been of the best. The hon. life-member 
     <lb/>
     from Cobourg [Hon. Mr. BOULTON] , whom 
     <lb/>
     he did not see in his place, had, by the force 
     <lb/>
     of reasoning, convinced the House that the 
     <lb/>
     bill was destructive of the rights of property, 
     <lb/>
     and the consequence was that, year by year, 
     <lb/>
     the measure had been pruned of its most of<lb break="no"/>fensive features, until now, as he was informed, 
     <lb/>
     it was hardly open to objection. He could not 
     <lb/>
     recall another instance of persistent difference 
     <lb/>
     of opinion between the Chambers. The real 
     <lb/>
     danger of collision would be where one Cham<lb break="no"/>ber invaded the prerogatives of the other, and 
     <lb/>
     that danger, if it existed at all, would be great<lb break="no"/>ly increased were the Legislative Council made 
     <lb/>
     elective. (Hear, hear.) If the members were 
     <lb/>
     elected they might say, " We come from the 
     <lb/>
     people just as directly as the members of the 
     <lb/>
     Assembly do, and our authority is, therefore, as 
     <lb/>
     full and complete as theirs. Nay, more, for where 
     <lb/>
     we each represent 1000 electors, they only each 
     <lb/>
     represent 300, and we have, therefore, as much 
     <lb/>
     right to initiate money bills and impost bills as 
     <lb/>
     they have." Make the Council purely elective, 
     <lb/>
     and he would not promise that an agitation 
     <lb/>
     of this kind would not spring up. It had 
     <lb/>
     not been a theme as yet on the floor of the 
     <lb/>
     House, but it was well known that it had 
     <lb/>
    been freely discussed in the corridors, and if 
     <lb/>the subject had not been formally introduced, 
     <lb/>it was probably because it was thought by 
     <lb/>those who debated it that they could not 
     <lb/>rely upon the life-members. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>Let the Council propose to deal with taxation 
     <lb/>and the elective system would be sure in the 
     <lb/>course of time to urge it on to do so, and im<lb break="no"/>mediately the spirit of the Assembly would 
     <lb/>be aroused to resistance. This would be the 
     <lb/>way to provoke collisions, and with an elective 
     <lb/>Council it was not unlikely at all to be resort<lb break="no"/>ed to. In England, where the Upper House 
     <lb/>was composed of a class entirely distinct from 
     <lb/>the Commons, and having interests, as a 
     <lb/>general thing, diverse from  those of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple even there the collisions between the two 
     <lb/>had been but infrequent. Indeed 
     <lb/>there had been only one very serious collision 
     <lb/>in the course of centuries. When, however, 
     <lb/>such conjunctures arose, the crown overcame 
     <lb/>
            
    
            <cb/>
          
     them by the appointment of a sufficient num<lb break="no"/>ber of peers whose political views accorded 
     <lb/>
     with those of the government. The right to 
     <lb/>
     sit in the House of Lords being, however, 
     <lb/>
     hereditary, the son generally inherited the 
     <lb/>
     politics of his father and so the character of 
     <lb/>
     the body was always pretty well understood ; 
     <lb/>
     but be it what it might, and as much as 
     <lb/>
     possible removed from popular influences, it 
     <lb/>
     had yet learned so far to respect the will of the 
     <lb/>
     people as to know when to make concession 
     <lb/>
     of its own opinions. He did not say that it 
     <lb/>
     bowed to every breeze and instantly yielded 
     <lb/>
     to every demand, nor did he think that any 
     <lb/>
     Legislative Upper Chamber should do so, and 
     <lb/>
     be content merely to reflect the temper and 
     <lb/>
     complexion of the other branch. On the con<lb break="no"/>trary, he held that when it had and 
     <lb/>
     sufficient evidence, sufficient to satisfy itself 
     <lb/>
     that a proposed measure was unjust, it was 
     <lb/>
     bound to resist, and public opinion which 
     <lb/>
     generally came out right in the end, would 
     <lb/>
     sustain it in such an attitude. But there was 
     <lb/>
     very much less danger in countries like this 
     <lb/>
     that difference of opinion would even be as 
     <lb/>
     frequent between the Legislative Chambers as 
     <lb/>
     between the Lords and Commons in England, 
     <lb/>
     and the reason was clear : our  Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Councillors would not come from so different 
     <lb/>
     a class of society to the general population, as 
     <lb/>
     the peers of the British nation, compared 
     <lb/>
     with the people of that nation. The lords 
     <lb/>
     had ideas of caste and privileges which none of 
     <lb/>
     our people were imbrued with, and the common 
     <lb/>
     sympathy existing between all classes here 
     <lb/>
     would be felt equally by the Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Councillors and the Members of the Assembly. 
     <lb/>
     Both would be equally subjected to popular 
     <lb/>
     influences and be more or less controlled by 
     <lb/>
     them. The interests of the Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cillor, though a nominee of the Crown, would 
     <lb/>
     be the same as those of the mass, and the 
     <lb/>
     legislation which would be good for them 
     <lb/>
     would, as a general thing, be good for him 
     <lb/>
     too. He would have no ancestral estates, 
     <lb/>
     privileges, immunities and titles to protect, 
     <lb/>
     like the peers of England. He would be 
     <lb/>
     affected by the social changes which affected 
     <lb/>
     others, and would be moved by the same aims 
     <lb/>
     and aspirations as his friends around him. 
     <lb/>
     This being the case, it was not very probable 
     <lb/>
     that his Opinions would even be set in opposi<lb break="no"/>tion to those of other men as to make it likely 
     <lb/>
     that he would come in collision with them, or 
     <lb/>
     that, as a House, the Council would be in 
     <lb/>
     danger of a serious quarrel with the Assembly . 
     <lb/>
     Then the changes which time would inevitab1y 
     <lb/>
    bring about in a body like the proposed Legis<lb break="no"/><pb n="24" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0024.jpg"/><fw type="num">24</fw>lative Council, would be sufficiently great to 
     <lb/>
     prevent the possibility of a continued antagon<lb break="no"/>ism between it and the other branch, if unhap<lb break="no"/>pily it should arise. The demise, the resigna<lb break="no"/>tion and the loss of seat from other causes, 
     <lb/>
     would do this, and afford the Government of 
     <lb/>
     the day the opportunity of so reconstructing 
     <lb/>
     the House as to bring it more in harmony 
     <lb/>
     with public sentiment. He did not say it 
     <lb/>
     was desirable that at all times the Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Council should be a reflection of such opinion, 
     <lb/>
     though it was, of course, desirable that it 
     <lb/>
     should not continue violently to shock it. He 
     <lb/>
     would have that House conservative, calm, 
     <lb/>
     considerate and watchful, to prevent the enact<lb break="no"/>ment of measures which, in its deliberate judg<lb break="no"/>ment, were not calculated to advance the com<lb break="no"/>mon weal. Any more rapid changes in the 
     <lb/>
     composition of the House than those he now 
     <lb/>
     indicated, he did not consider wholesome or 
     <lb/>
     desirable. From the history of the present 
     <lb/>
     Chamber for the last few years, it would be 
     <lb/>
     seen that such changes, whether among the 
     <lb/>
     life members or the elected members, were 
     <lb/>
     much more frequent than might be generally 
     <lb/>
     supposed. According to the present elective 
     <lb/>
     system twelve members went out and twelve 
     <lb/>
     came in every second year. Supposing that a 
     <lb/>
     collision had taken place between the two 
     <lb/>
     branches of the Legislature, and that it was de<lb break="no"/>sirable to bring the Council more in accord with 
     <lb/>
     the representatives of the people, under this 
     <lb/>
     system, the same members might be returned, 
     <lb/>
     not because of the soundness of their political 
     <lb/>
     opinions on the topic which had brought about 
     <lb/>
     the collision, perhaps without the slightest 
     <lb/>
     reference to it, but from their position and 
     <lb/>
     their exertions. One might come back be<lb break="no"/>cause he was a wealthy man and had a social 
     <lb/>
     position which gave him a large influence, 
     <lb/>
     another because he was an able canvasser and 
     <lb/>
     well versed in election tactics, and others from 
     <lb/>
     causes equally removed from the political 
     <lb/>
     question upon which the two Houses of Par<lb break="no"/>liament were in antagonism. But suppose 
     <lb/>
     the twelve seats were at the disposal of the 
     <lb/>
     Government, and that an irreconcilable differ<lb break="no"/>ence had existed between the two Houses, 
     <lb/>
     would they not have the opportunity of re<lb break="no"/>dress at once and thoroughly by bringing in 
     <lb/>
     twelve members who would harmonise better 
     <lb/>
     in opinion with them and the country ? 
     <lb/>
     Undoubtedly. Well, within eight years the 
     <lb/>
     changes among the life-members had been as 
     <lb/>
     follows :-—When the House was made elective, 
     <lb/>
     there were 40 such members in it; two years 
     <lb/>
     afterwards, at the call of the House, the num<lb break="no"/>ber was found reduced to 31 ; two years after 
     <lb/>
       
            <cb/>
      
     that again to 26; in two years more, to 24; 
     <lb/>
     and to-day to 21, of which 21, one honorable 
     <lb/>
     member was now seriously indisposed . In 
     <lb/>
     eight ears, then, the number had been dimin<lb break="no"/>ished by half. Then changes nearly as great had 
     <lb/>
     occurred among the elected members. There 
     <lb/>
     had been 24 removals and changes by death 
     <lb/>
     and otherwise among these 48 ; and it should 
     <lb/>
     be remembered, that as the elected members 
     <lb/>
     came in by twelves, two years apart, the aver<lb break="no"/>age time had been only four years. This was 
     <lb/>
     sufficient to show the opportunity which, even 
     <lb/>
     among younger men than the life-members, the 
     <lb/>
     Government would have of keeping the House 
     <lb/>
     in accord with the true interests of the 
     <lb/>
     country , or of overcoming any unfortunate 
     <lb/>
     misunderstanding between the two branches. 
     <lb/>
     [The honorable member here went minutely 
     <lb/>
     into a statement of the changes effected 
     <lb/>
     by death, acceptance of office, and defeat 
     <lb/>
     at elections, among this class of members, 
     <lb/>
     which, however, we do not deem it neces<lb break="no"/>sary to specify.] These changes had cer<lb break="no"/>tainly altered, to some extent, the com<lb break="no"/>plexion of the House, and the future would, 
     <lb/>
     no doubt, be like the past in this respect. 
     <lb/>
     The Conference had taken all these things 
     <lb/>
     into consideration, and wisely concluded, as 
     <lb/>
     he believed, that while the chances of collision 
     <lb/>
     were much less under the nominative system, 
     <lb/>
     the opportunity of restoring harmonious 
     <lb/>
     action was infinitely more prompt and effec<lb break="no"/>tive, and that there was no such danger of 
     <lb/>
     collisons between the two branches of the 
     <lb/>
     General Legislature, as to make it a bar to 
     <lb/>
     the principle of nomination, which principle, 
     <lb/>
     in their judgment, offered the compensating 
     <lb/>
     advantage he had endeavored, in the earlier 
     <lb/>
     part of his observations, to point out. He 
     <lb/>
     sincerely hoped the House would concur in 
     <lb/>
     the views he had expressed, and would accept 
     <lb/>
     the measure now before them, as one which 
     <lb/>
     he believed calculated to promote the best 
     <lb/>
     interests of this country and the other pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, and to hand down to posterity a con<lb break="no"/>stitution analogous, as nearly as might be, to 
     <lb/>
     that of the empire under whose protection we 
     <lb/>
     had the happiness to live—a Constitution cal<lb break="no"/>culated further, as he was fully convinced, to 
     <lb/>
     perpetuate the connection between these colo<lb break="no"/>nies and that mighty nation, to the mutual 
     <lb/>
     benefit of both. ( Hear, hear, and applause.) 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:VIDA1">HON. MR. VIDAL</persName> here inquired from the 
     <lb/>
     honorable member why it was that the selection 
     <lb/>
     of Legislative Councillors from Lower Canada., 
     <lb/>
     in thé Confederation scheme, was to be left to 
     <lb/>
     the Local Government of that section of the 
     <lb/>
    province, while no such provision existed with 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="25" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-06_Page_0025.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">25</fw>
      
     respect to Upper Canada or the Lower Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName> said it was out of 
     <lb/>
     deference to the interests of the British Cana<lb break="no"/>dians of Lower Canada, who had some fear 
     <lb/>
     that they might not be sufficiently protected 
     <lb/>
     otherwise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:RYAN3">HON. MR. RYAN</persName> objected to this mode of 
     <lb/>
     selection, as calculated to perpetuate differences 
     <lb/>
     of nationality and creed, and thought it would 
     <lb/>
     be better to leave the selection unconditionally 
     <lb/>
     to the Crown. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [After this a number of questions were put 
     <lb/>
     to <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">Hon. Mr. CAMPBELL</persName> upon various points 
     <lb/>
     of detail, and a cross fire was kept up from 
     <lb/>
     both sides of the House, which made it next to 
     <lb/>
     impossible to keep track of the proceedings. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Among the questions asked was one as to 
     <lb/>
     whether the local governments should be con<lb break="no"/>stituted before the Constitution of the Confe<lb break="no"/>deration became law. The resolution concern<lb break="no"/>ing this point seemed involved and contradic<lb break="no"/>tory, as it supposed some part of the plan to 
     <lb/>
     be in force, which depended upon the action 
     <lb/>
     of local governments not themselves in exist<lb break="no"/>ence.]<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName> promised to give 
     <lb/>
     an explanation at the next sitting of the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SANB1">HON. MR. SANBORN</persName> then addressed the 
     <lb/>
     House for a few minutes, it being then nearly 
     <lb/>
     six o'clock. He did not declare himself directly 
     <lb/>
     opposed to the scheme as a whole, but believed 
     <lb/>
     that the abandonment of the elective principle 
     <lb/>
     in respect of the Legislative Council was a step 
     <lb/>
     backward and an unwise one. He quoted as 
     <lb/>
     a proof the opinion of the Premier of the 
     <lb/>
     Government expressed two years ago, and 
     <lb/>
     thought it not a little strange he should so 
     <lb/>
     readily have changed his views-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Cries of six o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Further debate was then postponed until 
     <lb/>
     the morrow, and the House immediately 
     <lb/>
     afterwards adjourned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2016-12-01, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


            <!--<fw type="num">LEGISLATIVE</fw>
            <fw type="running">ASSEMBLY.</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
     MONDAY, February 6, 1865. 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     ATTORNEY GENERAL MACDONALD 
     <lb/>
     moved, " That an humble Address be pre<lb break="no"/>sented to Her Majesty, praying that She 
     <lb/>
     may be graciously pleased to cause a meas<lb break="no"/>ure to be submitted to the Imperial Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, for the purpose of uniting the Colonies 
     <lb/>
     of Canada, Nova Scotia, New Brunswick, 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, and Prince Edward Island, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     in one Government, with provisions based on 
     <lb/>
     certain Resolutions, which were adopted at 
     <lb/>
     a Conference of Delegates from the said 
     <lb/>
     Colonies, held at the city of Quebec, on the 
     <lb/>
     10th October, 1864."* He said:— Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Speaker, in fulfilment of the promise made 
     <lb/>
     by the Government to Parliament at its last 
     <lb/>
     session, I have moved this resolution. I 
     <lb/>
     have had the honor of being charged, on 
     <lb/>
     behalf ot the Government, to submit a scheme 
     <lb/>
     for the Confederation of all the British North 
     <lb/>
     American Provinces—a scheme which has 
     <lb/>
    been received, I am glad to say, with general, 
     <lb/>if not universal, approbation in Canada. 
     <lb/>The scheme, as propounded through the 
     <lb/>press, has received almost no opposition. 
     <lb/>While there may be occasionally, here and 
     <lb/>there, expressions of dissent from some of 
     <lb/>the details, yet the scheme as a whole has 
     <lb/>met with almost universal approval, and the 
     <lb/>Government has the greatest satisfaction in 
     <lb/>presenting it to this House. This subject, 
     <lb/>which now absorbs the attention of the 
     <lb/>ple of Canada, and of the whole of British 
     <lb/>North America, is not a new one. For years 
     <lb/>it has more or less attracted the attention of 
     <lb/>every statesman and politician in these prov- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>inees, and has been looked upon by many 
     <lb/>far-seeing politicians as being eventually the 
     <lb/>means of deciding and settling very many 
     <lb/>of the vexed questions which have retarded 
     <lb/>the prosperity of the colonies as a whole, 
     <lb/>and particularly the prosperity of Canada. 
     <lb/>The subject was pressed upon the public at<lb break="no"/>tention by a great many writers and politi<lb break="no"/>cians; but I believe the attention of the 
     <lb/>Legislature was first formally called to it by 
     <lb/>my honorable friend the Minister of Finance. 
     <lb/>Some years ago, in an elaborate speech, my 
     <lb/>hon. friend, while an independent member 
     <lb/>of Parliament, before bein connected with 
     <lb/>any Government, pressed his views on the 
     <lb/>Legislature at great length and with his 
     <lb/>usual force. But the subject was not taken 
     <lb/>up by any party as a branch of their policy, 
     <lb/>until the formation of the CARTIER-MAC- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>DONALD Administration in 1858, when the 
     <lb/>Confederation of the colonies was announced 
     <lb/>as one of the measures which they pledged 
     <lb/>themselves to attempt, if possible, to bring 
     <lb/>to a satisfactory conclusion. In pursuance 
     <lb/>of that promise, the letter or despatch, which 
     <lb/>has been so much and so freely commented 
     <lb/>upon in the press and in this House, was 
     <lb/>addressed by three of the members of that 
     <lb/>Administration to the Colonial Offie. The 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     *For Resolutions, see Legislative Council, page 1 . 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

     </div>    </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>