<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgPCLC_1865-02-09"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgPCLCoun">Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1865-02-09">9 February 1865</date>, Province of Canada, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Canadian Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          
          
         
               <title>Parliamentary Debates on the Subject of the Confederation of the British North American Provinces, 3rd Session, 8th Provincial Parliament of Canada</title>.
                    

           <date when="1865"/>.
          

          <pubPlace>Quebec</pubPlace>: <publisher>Hunter, Rose &amp; Co., Parliamentary Printers</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="115" to="125"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0115.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0116.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0117.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0118.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0119.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0120.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0121.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0122.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0123.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0124.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0125.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-14">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0115">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0115.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0116">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0116.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0117">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0117.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0118">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0118.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0119">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0119.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0120">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0120.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0121">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0121.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0122">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0122.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0123">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0123.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0124">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0124.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0125">
         <graphic url="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0125.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="115" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0115.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">115</fw>
           
<!-- GL, 2016-11-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->


 <!--<p> Government presents this measure to the <lb/>
House. We do not present it as free from <lb/>
fault, but we do present it as a measure so <lb/>
advantageous to the people of Canada, that <lb/>
all the blemishes, real or
imaginary, averred <lb/>
against it, sink into utter insignificance in <lb/>
presence of its merits. (Hear, hear.) We pre<lb break="no"/>sent it, not in the precise shape we in Canada <lb/>
would desire it, but as in the best shape the five <lb/>
colonies to be united could agree upon it. We <lb/>
present it in the form in which the five gov<lb break="no"/>ernments have severally adopted it—in the <lb/>
form the Imperial Government has endorsed it <lb/>
—and in the form in which we believe all the <lb/>
legislatures of the provinces will accept it. <lb/>
(Hear, hear.) We ask the House to pass it <lb/>
in the exact form in which we have presented <lb/>
it, for we know not how alterations may affect <lb/>
its safety in other places, and
the process of <lb/>
alteration once commenced in four different le<lb break="no"/>gislatures—who can tell where
that would end? <lb/>
Every member of this House is free as air to <lb/>
criticise it if he so wills, and amend it if he is <lb/>
able—but we warn him of the danger of <lb/>
amendment, and throw on him all
the respon<lb break="no"/>sibility of the consequences.
(Hear, hear.) <lb/>
We feel confident of carrying this scheme as it <lb/>
stands—but we cannot tell what we can do if <lb/>
it be amended. (Hear, hear.) Let not hon<lb break="no"/>orable gentlemen approach this measure as a <lb/>
sharp critic deals with an abstract question, <lb/>
striving to point out blemishes
and display <lb/>
his ingenuity; but let us approach it as men <lb/>
having but one consideration before us—the <lb/>
establishment of the future peace
and pros<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <p>perity of our country. (Hear, hear.) Let
us <lb/>
look at it in the light of a few months back<lb break="no"/>in the light of the evils and
injustice to which <lb/>
it applies a remedy—in the light of the years <lb/>
of discord and strife we have
spent in seeking <lb/>
for that remedy—in the light with which the <lb/>
people of Canada would regard this measure <lb/>
were it to be lost, and all the
evils of past <lb/>
years to be brought back upon us again. <lb/>
(Hear, hear.) Let honorable gentlemen look <lb/>
at the question in this view—and
what one of <lb/>
them will take the responsibility
of casting his <lb/>
vote against the measure? Sir, the future <lb/>
destiny of these great provinces may be <lb/>
affected by the decision we are
about to give <lb/>
to an extent which at this moment we may be <lb/>
unable to estimate—but assuredly
the welfare <lb/>
for many years of four millions of people <lb/>
hangs on our decision. (Hear,
hear.) Shall <lb/>
we then rise equal to the occasion ?—shall we <lb/>
approach this discussion without
partisanship, <lb/>
and free from every rsonal feeling but the <lb/>
earnest resolution to discharge conscientiously <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p> the duty which an over-ruling Providence
has <lb/>
placed upon us? Sir, it may be that some <lb/>
among us will live to see the day when, as the <lb/>
result of this measure, a great and
powerful <lb/>
people may have grown up in these lands<lb break="no"/>when the boundless forests all around us shall <lb/>
have given way to smiling fields and thriving <lb/>
towns— and when one united government, <lb/>
under the British flag, shall extend from <lb/>
shore to shore:—but who would desire to <lb/>
see that day if he could not recall with sat<lb break="no"/>isfaction the part he took in this discussion? <lb/>
Mr. SPEAKER I have done. I leave the sub<lb break="no"/>ject to the conscientious judgment of the <lb/>
House, in the confident expectation and be<lb break="no"/>lief that the decision it will render will be <lb/>
worthy of the Parliament of Canada. (The <lb/>
honorable gentleman resumed his seat amid <lb/>
loud and continued applause.) <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion of the Hon. Mr. MCGEE, the <lb/>
debate was further adjourned till Thursday <lb/>
evening. <lb/>
            </p>-->

<div type="section">

            <head>LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL.</head>
            <p> THURSDAY, <hi rendition="simple:italic">February</hi>
9, 1865. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:ALLA1">HON. MR. ALLAN</persName> said, that if he acqui<lb break="no"/>esced, or thought that the House acquiesced, <lb/>
in the opinion expressed by the honorable gen<lb break="no"/>tleman who spoke at the close of the debate <lb/>
last evening, that under the circumstances in <lb/>
which the resolutions now before them were <lb/>
presented for their consideration, it was use<lb break="no"/>less to discuss their merits or express any <lb/>
opinion upon them; he would not now ven<lb break="no"/>ture to trespass on the time of the House with <lb/>
any remarks of his on the great scheme which <lb/>
had been submitted for their approval. But <lb/>
believing, as he did, that the Government had <lb/>
not invited them to express their opinion as a <lb/>
mere matter of form, but they were really <lb/>
asked in good faith to examine and discuss <lb/>
the measure, and then to express their ap<lb break="no"/>proval or disapproval of it as a whole, he <lb/>
would venture to occupy their attention for a <lb/>
few moments, while he stated to the House <lb/>
the reasons which induced him to give it his <lb/>
hearty concurrence and support. He would <lb/>
first, however, premise that he could not see <lb/>
the force of an objection which had also been <lb/>
made, that as they were precluded from mak<lb break="no"/>ing any alteration in the details of the scheme, <lb/>
they would be betraying their trust and vio<lb break="no"/>lating their duty to their constituents if they <lb/>
  
            <pb n="116" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0116.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">116</fw>
   
 acquiesced in the scheme as a whole, to
some <lb/>
of the particular features of which their own <lb/>
convictions might be opposed, and in reference <lb/>
to which they perhaps had no opportunity of <lb/>
ascertaining definitely the views of their con<lb break="no"/>stituents. Now, he would ask honorable gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen, did it not constantly happen that in <lb/>
the business of life they were obliged to dele<lb break="no"/>gate to a few the conduct of many matters in <lb/>
which they were most deeply interested them<lb break="no"/>selves, but which, from the very nature of the <lb/>
interests involved, could not be dealt with ad<lb break="no"/>vantageously otherwise, and if they had con<lb break="no"/>fidence in the judgment and ability of those to <lb/>
whom the task had been committed, were they <lb/>
not satisfied to accept their recommendations, <lb/>
although their views on all points might not <lb/>
coincide with their own ? Just so in the ease <lb/>
of the Confederation scheme—it was one which <lb/>
required special ability, tact and judgment, to <lb/>
deal with. It was one in which so many con<lb break="no"/>flicting interests, so many nice questions were <lb/>
involved, that it would have been next to im<lb break="no"/>possible to have arrived at any satisfactory <lb/>
settlement of the question, had the task been <lb/>
committed to a popular assembly or any other <lb/>
large body. Now, he was satisfied that the <lb/>
people of this country were
fully persuaded at <lb/>
the time of the Conference that the task of <lb/>
framing a scheme for the union of all the <lb/>
North American Provinces had been assumed <lb/>
by those statesmen who, by their ability, ex<lb break="no"/>perience and judgment were, of
all men, the <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>best qualified for the duty; and he had
yet to <lb/>
learn, from any expression of public opinion, <lb/>
either out of doors or in the press, that this <lb/>
confidence had been shaken, or that the scheme, <lb/>
as a whole, had been disapproved of. On the <lb/>
contrary, the people of Canada had now been <lb/>
acquainted with all the important features of <lb/>
the measure for some three months at least, <lb/>
and he believed the result had been that, <lb/>
while various opinions had been expressed in <lb/>
reference to the details of the scheme, the great <lb/>
majority of the people were perfectly satisfied <lb/>
to leave the matter in the hands of their re<lb break="no"/>presentatives, to be assented to by them as a <lb/>
whole, if, after a full discussion of its merits, <lb/>
they were satisfied that they so far outweighed <lb/>
its defects as to commend itself to their <lb/>
adoption. If then, in the best exercise of <lb/>
his judgment, he had come to the conclusion <lb/>
that the peculiar circumstances of the times, <lb/>
and the merits of the scheme as a whole, out<lb break="no"/>weighed any of the defects which might present <lb/>
themselves in the details, he thought he should <lb/>
be fully warranted, acting on behalf of his <lb/>
constituents, in according his support to the <lb/>
       
            <cb/>
    
measure, without being in any way
chargeable <lb/>
with a dereliction of duty or a betrayal of the <lb/>
trust committed to him. He would new state <lb/>
to the House what were the considerations <lb/>
which induced him to give his support to the <lb/>
measure, and which, to him at least, appeared <lb/>
of sufficient importance to outweigh all objec<lb break="no"/>tions that had been brought against it. They <lb/>
were twofold—arising in the first place from <lb/>
our internal condition, and in the second lace <lb/>
from our position with regard to the neighbor<lb break="no"/>ing States. And first, with regard to our in<lb break="no"/>ternal condition, while he partly agreed with
<lb/>
the remark which fell from the honorable <lb/>
member for the Brock Division, that our poli<lb break="no"/>tical differences alone could perhaps scarcely <lb/>
be said to necessitate such great and important <lb/>
constitutional changes as those involved in <lb/>
Confederation; yet taken in connection with <lb/>
our external relations, he thought no one would <lb/>
deny that the state of chronic weakness of the <lb/>
governing body had become a subject of grave <lb/>
apprehension to every well-wisher of their <lb/>
country. No one would deny that when storms <lb/>
were impending, it was doubly necessary that <lb/>
the ships of the state should be guided by firm <lb/>
and determined hands—that weakness and <lb/>
vacillation under such circumstances would be <lb/>
sure to end in disaster. Yet for the last few <lb/>
years, when the political horizon had been <lb/>
growing darker an darker, when fresh causes <lb/>
of irritation had unhappily sprung up from <lb/>
time to time between us and our neighbors, <lb/>
we had seen ministry after ministry break <lb/>
down, until anything like a stable and vigorous <lb/>
government seemed to have become a hopeless <lb/>
impossibility. Who could say that such a <lb/>
state of things was not fraught with danger to <lb/>
any community. He believed that in Federa<lb break="no"/>tion they had found a remedy for those sec<lb break="no"/>tional differences between Upper and Lower
<lb/>
Canada, which had so long agitated the <lb/>
country, and had been a source of weakness to <lb/>
so many administrations. Under the scheme <lb/>
now proposed, all causes of jealousy and dis<lb break="no"/>trust between the two provinces would be <lb/>
removed, and they might well hail with satis<lb break="no"/>faction any change which, by removing these <lb/>
stumbling-blocks which sectional feeling and <lb/>
party strife had placed in the way of so man <lb/>
successive ministries, had enabled the ablest <lb/>
men of all parties to unite their councils <lb/>
for the formation of a strong, vigorous and <lb/>
permanent government. For these con<lb break="no"/>siderations, amongst others, the measure <lb/>
before the House should have his hearty <lb/>
support, but there were to his mind graver
<lb/>
reasons still why the union of the provinces
<lb/>
          
            <pb n="117" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0117.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">117</fw>
        
should, if possible, be brought about
without <lb/>
further loss of time. No one who had watched <lb/>
the course of public opinion in Great Britain <lb/>
in reference to the colonies, as expressed during <lb/>
the last few years, either in Parliament or in <lb/>
the public press, could doubt that the feeling <lb/>
had been gaining ground there that the time <lb/>
had come for us to assume a larger share than <lb/>
we had hitherto assumed of those respon<lb break="no"/>sibilities which attach to every country <lb/>
aspiring to any sort of national existence or <lb/>
political standing. He need scarcely any that <lb/>
he alluded to the question of defence. This <lb/>
was a question which would have been forced <lb/>
upon us sooner or later under any circumstan<lb break="no"/>ces, because it was neither reasonable nor just <lb/>
that we should expect that Great Britain <lb/>
would continue to give us the protection of <lb/>
her fleets and armies, unless we showed that <lb/>
we were willing to hear our share of the bur<lb break="no"/>den, and were ready to contribute our quota <lb/>
of men and means towards the defence of our <lb/>
own hearths and homes should war unhappily <lb/>
threaten us. Under any circumstances, then, <lb/>
the consideration of this question must neces<lb break="no"/>sarily have occupied a large share of the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the Government and the Legislature, <lb/>
but no one would deny that it had acquired <lb/>
tenfold importance in view of our present re<lb break="no"/>lations with the United States, and that what <lb/>
might safely have been left to the unaided re<lb break="no"/>sources of Canada alone, had peace and harmony <lb/>
continued to prevail on our borders, would now <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>require all the assistance, all the
material aid <lb/>
and moral support, which a close and cordial <lb/>
union with nearly a million of our British <lb/>
fellow-subjects could alone give to us. Feel<lb break="no"/>ing then as he did upon these points, he could <lb/>
not help asking himself the question, what <lb/>
would be the result, as regards the well-being <lb/>
and prosperity of Canada, if this Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion scheme should fall through? Should we <lb/>
not suffer most seriously in all our relations <lb/>
both at home and abroad? Would not the <lb/>
effect on our credit in England be most dis<lb break="no"/>asterous? Would they not say that our own <lb/>
folly and want of patriotism had condemned <lb/>
us to a state of isolation and weakness, when <lb/>
union with our sister provinces would have <lb/>
made us strong, powerful and prosperous? <lb/>
Some honorable gentlemen had such strong <lb/>
objections to some of the details of the meas<lb break="no"/>ure—the alteration in the constitution of this <lb/>
House, for instance—that rather than bring <lb/>
themselves to vote for it, they were willing to <lb/>
run the risk of imperiling the whole scheme. <lb/>
For his own part, he thought it would ill be<lb break="no"/>come an elected member like himself to say <lb/>
        
            <cb/>
     
 anything against the elective system as applie <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> to this House;
although he earnestly believed <lb/>
that the majority of his own constituents were <lb/>
in favor of a Legislative Council
appointed <lb/>
by the Crown. As for the objection which <lb/>
had been urged that between an Upper House <lb/>
composed exclusively of life members, and an <lb/>
elective Lower House, there might be the <lb/>
danger of a direct collision in the event of <lb/>
one rejecting an important measure which the <lb/>
other had passed, he did not think there was <lb/>
much danger of such a contingency. Indeed <lb/>
he would remind honorable members that the <lb/>
only instance of anything like a dead-lock be<lb break="no"/>tween the two Houses, which had occurred <lb/>
within late years, at all events, was since the <lb/>
introduction of the elective principle, when the <lb/>
Council in 1859 refused to pass the Supply <lb/>
Bill on account of certain items contained in <lb/>
it, providing for the expense of the removal <lb/>
of the Government to Quebec. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment on that occasion were left in a minority <lb/>
in this House although they had a majority <lb/>
in the Assembly, and it was only after an
ad<lb break="no"/>journment of some days and upon a recon<lb break="no"/>sideration of the question, after bringing up <lb/>
some life members from Lower Canada, that <lb/>
the Government carried the vote be a majority <lb/>
of two or three. Upon the whole, however, <lb/>
he thought that the life members of the <lb/>
Council would admit that the elective mem<lb break="no"/>bers had so far, at all events, comported <lb/>
themselves in such a way as to maintain <lb/>
the character of the House as a conserva<lb break="no"/>tive body, free from all violent party feeling, <lb/>
and exercising a wholesome check against all <lb/>
ill-considered or hasty legislation. The real <lb/>
danger, he thought, was that if the House in <lb/>
process of time were to become a purely elec<lb break="no"/>tive body, and party lines became more closely <lb/>
drawn, the same partisan spirit which too <lb/>
often swayed the proceedings of the popular <lb/>
branch of the Legislature, might find its way <lb/>
into their chamber, larger powers, such as <lb/>
originating money bills, might be claimed, and <lb/>
a collision between the two Houses might then <lb/>
occur at any time. Another objection raised <lb/>
by some honorable gentlemen, was, that this <lb/>
measure was being urged upon the Parliament <lb/>
and people of this country with undue haste, <lb/>
and from the language of some honorable <lb/>
gentlemen it was quite clear that they did not <lb/>
think that our situation was by any means <lb/>
such a critical one as to call for an immediate <lb/>
change. For his own part, he did
not under<lb break="no"/>stand how any one could look abroad at what <lb/>
was passing on our borders and not take into <lb/>
consideration the fact that our communica<lb break="no"/><pb n="118" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0118.jpg"/><fw type="num">118</fw>tion
with the sea-board during the winter was <lb/>
about to be cut off—that our trade and com<lb break="no"/>merce with the United States was hampered <lb/>
by the most vexatious and needless restric<lb break="no"/>tions—and that, furthermore, measures of a <lb/>
military and naval character having special <lb/>
reference to our frontier relations, had found <lb/>
favor and countenance with the Government <lb/>
and people of the United States. Looking at <lb/>
all these things, he could not conceive how any <lb/>
Canadian could feel that this was a time for <lb/>
his country to remain in her present compara<lb break="no"/>tively weak and isolated condition, when an <lb/>
opportunity was offered of acquiring that <lb/>
strength which union with the sister pro<lb break="no"/>vinces could alone give us. It might be that <lb/>
there were some honorable gentlemen who <lb/>
did not view the question, so far as regarded <lb/>
our relations with the United States, in the <lb/>
same 1ight that he did. Now, from whatever <lb/>
point of view he looked at the
question of <lb/>
Confederation, he was equally convinced of <lb/>
the extreme desirableness of an early settle<lb break="no"/>ment of the question. He would be very <lb/>
unwilling to follow the example
of some hon<lb break="no"/>orable gentlemen in decrying the resources or <lb/>
underrating the position of Canada; but he <lb/>
was bound to say, that while be freely admit<lb break="no"/>ted and heartily acknowledged the many <lb/>
sources of material wealth and prosperity <lb/>
which Canada possessed, in her fertile soil, <lb/>
her rich minerals, her noble system of canals <lb/>
and railways, he nevertheless could not shut <lb/>
his eyes to the fact that our trade and <lb/>
revenue, our commercial and agricultural in<lb break="no"/>terests, had been so injuriously affected
by <lb/>
the state of things on the other side of the <lb/>
lakes, that unless we could find new avenues <lb/>
for our commerce, new markets for our pro<lb break="no"/>duce, we must inevitably suffer a most serious <lb/>
check to our prosperity and well-doing. In <lb/>
this Confederation scheme he believed that a <lb/>
golden opportunity was offered to us of remedy<lb break="no"/>ing the evils under which we were now suf<lb break="no"/>fering, and of opening out a new and pros<lb break="no"/>perous career for this country, if we would <lb/>
avail ourselves of it. He believed that it <lb/>
might be said of nations as of individuals:-<lb/>
            </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               <lg>
                  <l>There is a tide in the affairs of man</l>
                  <l>Which, taken at the flood, leads on to fortune;</l>
                  <l>Omitted, all the voyage of their life is spent</l>
                  <l>ln shallows and miseries.</l>
                  <l>On such a full sea are we now afloat</l>
                  <l>And we must take the current as it flows,</l>
                  <l>Or lose our venture.</l>
               </lg>
            </quote>
 
            <p> He would urge then upon the House, not <lb/>
to allow the opportunity to pass—even should <lb/>
it be at the sacrifice of individual opinions-<lb/>
       
            <cb/>
       
of forming a strong, powerful and prosperous
<lb/>
Confederation, and thus ensure for ourselves, <lb/>
and our children's children, a national ex<lb break="no"/>istence as British North Americans, which <lb/>
may endure for many ages tocome. (Cheers) <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SANB1">HON. MR. SANBORN</persName> said he rose for the <lb/>purpose of moving the resolution of which be <lb/>
had given notice, and would take the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of offering some observations on the <lb/>
general subject. In his opinion
it could not <lb/>
injured by discussion, and whatever might <lb/>
be its merits or demerits after going
through <lb/>
the crucible, the residuum must be
better than <lb/>
the present condition of the subject, both as <lb/>
regarded the legislature and the country. On <lb/>
a former occasion he had expressed himself as <lb/>
not averse to the question, but as inclined, <lb/>
from various considerations, to view Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation favorably; and acting in the same sense <lb/>
he would now state certain points, which, in <lb/>
his opinion, must lead to the conclusion that <lb/>
such a union would advance the prosperity of <lb/>
the colonies interested, and their ultimate es<lb break="no"/>tablishment as a nation. The principle of as<lb break="no"/>sociation, as exhibited in commercial partner<lb break="no"/>ships and corporations, continued a secret of <lb/>
rosperity, the precise nature of which it might <lb/>be difficult to elucidate and account for, but <lb/>
which no one could fail to recognize, and so <lb/>
far as it applied to nations its potency was <lb/>
sufficiently established to show that the anal<lb break="no"/>ogy was presumed and that it was as operative <lb/>
as in partnerships and corporations. He was <lb/>
also prepared to admit that diversity of inter<lb break="no"/>ests was no sufficient argument against union, <lb/>
—(hear)—since in this very particular might <lb/>
frequently be found the strongest bond of <lb/>
union. As in electricity, opposite poles at<lb break="no"/>tracted each other, so among nations a diver<lb break="no"/>sity of interests which might <hi rendition="simple:italic">a priori</hi> be pro<lb break="no"/>nounced a bar, was not unfreqnently the most <lb/>
effectual means of harmony, and thus a diver<lb break="no"/>sity of feeling which brought out talent, might <lb/>
lead to a comparison of opinions which would <lb/>
induce an enlarged policy calculated to elevate <lb/>
and not to depress national energies. He was <lb/>
prepared to admit that Confederation would <lb/>
enlarge the minds of all, and make us better <lb/>
to understand our resources and capabil<lb break="no"/>ities. It would make us more enquiring, <lb/>
and teach us so to use our industrial power <lb/>
as to secure the best results. (Hear, hear.) <lb/>
He was prepared to admit that the results of <lb/>
the union between Upper and Lower Canada <lb/>
had been beneficial to both, and he argued <lb/>
that union with the other provinces, inhabited <lb/>
by a peeple educated under different
circum<lb break="no"/>stances and of different origins, could hardly <lb/>
           
            <pb n="119" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0119.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">119</fw>
      
 be without mutual advantage. It would
give <lb/>
the inhabitants of each province the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of studying each other's habits and <lb/>
pursuits, and so induce larger and more com<lb break="no"/>prehensive views. He was prepared to admit <lb/>
that the assimilation of tariffs would be an <lb/>
advantage of no little moment, and that it <lb/>
would do away with much chafing in working <lb/>
the machinery of the government. He also <lb/>
admitted the advantage of having ocean sea<lb break="no"/>ports of our own, though he was not prepared <lb/>
to attach so much importance to that as some <lb/>
other honorable members. We were told that <lb/>
no inland country could ever be great, and <lb/>
that so long as we had no opening to the sea <lb/>
we could not expect permanent prosperity. <lb/>
He was quite proper to say that access to <lb/>
the ocean through the ports of St. John, N.B., <lb/>
and Halifax, was very desirable, but he was <lb/>
not at all certain that the grand effects pro<lb break="no"/>claimed would be realized. It was no doubt <lb/>
very desirable to secure all these advantages, <lb/>
but the measure contained some provisions <lb/>
which, if carried out, would, as he believed, <lb/>
be highly injurious to both the general and <lb/>
local governments. Then he must say he had a <lb/>
strong distrust of it on account of the manner <lb/>
in which it was originated. It was not in <lb/>
accordance with the analogy of things or with <lb/>
the lessons taught us by the history of the <lb/>
world, that a few gentlemen, however wise and <lb/>
well-intentioned, but self-elected, should meet <lb/>
together to form a constitution and erect a new <lb/>
nationality. If we looked to the United States <lb/>
(the history of whose Constitution he would <lb/>
presently allude to, and whose Constitution <lb/>
had been more closely followed in that now <lb/>
under consideration than the British Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion) we would see how patiently they had <lb/>
proceeded to construct it. [Here the honor<lb break="no"/>able member gave a history of the first instru<lb break="no"/>ment of federation, established for mutual con<lb break="no"/>venience and support, though not for national <lb/>
union, which occupied from the 7th October <lb/>
to the 15th November, 1777, in the discussing. <lb/>
He then said that this arrangement, not being <lb/>
found to answer the requirements of the States <lb/>
concerned, in September, 1787, they commenc<lb break="no"/>ed deliberating upon the adoption of a Consti<lb break="no"/>tution, which, after being arranged, was for two <lb/>
years before the individual states
and the peo<lb break="no"/>ple, being only ratified in October, 1789.] This <lb/>
showed how careful and particular they had <lb/>
been in this important matter, and a distin<lb break="no"/>guished member of the other branch of our le<lb break="no"/>gislature had said, only a few
evenings ago, that <lb/>
the greatest statesmen who ever lived had been <lb/>
engaged in the work. From the
length of the <lb/>
           
            <cb/>
     
discussions, and the time given to the <lb/>
people to study and understand the meas<lb break="no"/>ure, it was seen how anxious they were that <lb/>
it should be made perfectly satisfactory to <lb/>
them. But what was it that gave rise to <lb/>
the desire for federation first in the States? <lb/>
They were poor and comparatively helpless. <lb/>
They had just come out of an exhaustive war <lb/>
with Great Britain, and the duty fell upon <lb/>
them of organizing a government for a broad <lb/>
expanse of country, containing but two and <lb/>
a half or three million souls. This it was <lb/>
that led to the first attempt at federation, and <lb/>
afterwards to a closer union under the con<lb break="no"/>stitution of 1789. How was it with us? It <lb/>
was alleged that we had been led step by step, <lb/>
according to the strictest method of induction, <lb/>
to the necessity for the measure now proposed; <lb/>
that without it there must have been an irre<lb break="no"/>mediable dead—lock between the parties in the <lb/>
legislature, which would have rendered further <lb/>
progress impossible. But what was the real <lb/>
impediment? Want of patriotism—as not
the <lb/>
want of a good Constitution. If there had <lb/>
been less virulence of part spirit, and a better <lb/>
disposition to accommodate
matters, there <lb/>
would have been no dead-lock. (Hear,
hear.) <lb/>
            </p>



            <p> <persName ref="pers:ROSS8">HON. MR. ROSS</persName> hoped the honorable <lb/>
member felt this. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SANB1">HON. MR. SANBORN</persName>—If the leading men <lb/>
had felt as the ought to have felt, there would <lb/>
have been no dead-lock, for it existed more in <lb/>
name than in reality. There was no cause for <lb/>
saying that no government could be formed <lb/>
which could command a good majority. And <lb/>
what had the difficulties arisen from? From a <lb/>
persistent agitation for representation accord<lb break="no"/>ing to population, in consequence of which the <lb/>
people had at last come to believe that it was <lb/>
a fundamental axiom in government. (Hear, <lb/>
hear.) But did it follow that because there <lb/>
were difficulties that they could not be arranged <lb/>
without recourse to such a measure as this, and <lb/>
was it certain even that Confederation would <lb/>
remove them? Instead of meeting the diff<lb break="no"/>culties, the Government had travelled away <lb/>
from them and formed an agreement with <lb/>
provinces in which they had no existence, <lb/>
without devising means to relieve themselves. <lb/>
Federation was forthwith produced, like Mi<lb break="no"/>nerva from the head of Jupiter, fully armed <lb/>
and we were told it was just what we wanted <lb/>
to make all things right. We were told we <lb/>
must take it as presented, without any possible <lb/>
change; we must lay aside our character as a <lb/>
deliberative body, and without considering the <lb/>
country (which had been studiously kept in <lb/>
ignorance of the scheme) vote to accept or <lb/>
  
            <pb n="120" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0120.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">120</fw>
       
reject it. It was true that soon after
the reso<lb break="no"/>lutions had been agreed upon, copies had been <lb/>
sent to the members of both Houses confiden<lb break="no"/>tially, but the people must be kept in the dark. <lb/>
If the members had acted up to the implied
<lb/>
requirement of secrecy, and not divulged the <lb/>
provisions of the scheme, the people were to this <lb/>
day ignorant of its character, and it could not <lb/>
be said that it was ever constitutionally sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to the country. Then we were told that, <lb/>
as elective members and as patriots, it was our <lb/>
duty to accept the measure as it was, even <lb/>
though portions of it might not be satisfactory, <lb/>
rather than lose it altogether. It had been <lb/>
generally represented by the local newspapers <lb/>
in Upper Canada—fed to do so—that it was <lb/>
commonly approved; but while the simple idea <lb/>
of union might find favor, as he believed it <lb/>
did, it was not less true that the country was <lb/>
waiting for the details, of which they would <lb/>
judge when they had been discussed in Par<lb break="no"/>liament. When this had been done, and the <lb/>
bearing of the manifold
particulars was thor<lb break="no"/>oughly understood it was expected, at least <lb/>
among the English of Lower Canada, that it <lb/>
would not be passed until after having been <lb/>
submitted to the people. If it were passed <lb/>
through without such an appeal, he had no <lb/>
hesitation in saying that the Government would <lb/>
assume a very serious responsibility, and if, in <lb/>
after times, the union should prove disastrous, <lb/>
it would bring upon them imprecations instead <lb/>
of blessings. And he was under the impres<lb break="no"/>sion that the Government, whenever they had <lb/>
given their views on the subject, had never <lb/>
said it would not be so presented, but no doubt <lb/>
their utterances were very much like those of <lb/>
the Delphic oracle, susceptible of being un<lb break="no"/>derstood in two opposite ways. But what <lb/>
could such an indisposition to speak clearly <lb/>
indicate, if not a purpose to press the matter <lb/>
on to a result, even though the people might <lb/>
not want it. Under this measure the elective <lb/>
members would have a right to vote them<lb break="no"/>selves, two out of three at least, as members <lb/>
for life. Now it had been found necessary to <lb/>
enact a law to ensure the independence of <lb/>
Parliament, and for the purpose of removing <lb/>
all temptation to swerve from the right, they <lb/>
were precluded from occupying even the small <lb/>
offices of postmasters in the remotest parts of <lb/>
the count, or acting as security for such <lb/>
officers. For every day that a member occu<lb break="no"/>pied a seat in either House unlawfully, he was <lb/>
subject to the extreme penalty of £500, and if <lb/>
this strictness had been found necessary, was <lb/>
not the spirit of the law violated when this <lb/>
House was invited to pass a measure by which <lb/>
         
            <cb/>  
        
 the members of the Legislative Council of
the <lb/>
Confederation would be appointed for life, and <lb/>
selected from the members of the present <lb/>
Legislative Council—even allowing that all <lb/>
the Crown nominated members were to be first <lb/>
chosen, as the Honorable Commissioner of <lb/>
Crown Lands had left us to infer from his <lb/>
remarks. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName> said he had stated <lb/>
nothing of the kind, and the honorable mem<lb break="no"/>ber had no foundation whatever for his asser<lb break="no"/>tion. He (Hon. Mr. CAMPBELL) had used no <lb/>
such language, but had expressly stated that <lb/>
due consideration would be given to members <lb/>
of both sides of politics, and to life and elec<lb break="no"/>tive members equally. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SANB1">HON. MR. SANBORN</persName> said he had reason <lb/>
to suppose that what he had stated was a fair <lb/>
inference from what the Honorable Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner of Crown Lands said. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName>—The honorable <lb/>
member could not have been in the House <lb/>
when the statement was made, or how could <lb/>
he draw that conclusion? <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SANB1">HON. MR. SANBORN</persName> said he was ready <lb/>
to accept the explanation, as it would not affect <lb/>
his argument. And supposing all the mem<lb break="no"/>bers nominated by the Crown were appointed, <lb/>
he would say it was but just; nay, it would <lb/>
be unjust to deprive them of seats which had <lb/>
been given them for life. The Honorable Com<lb break="no"/>missioner of Crown Lands would thus see that <lb/>
he (Hon. Mr. SANBORN) had
attributed only <lb/>
such opinions to him as he himself conscien<lb break="no"/>tiously held to be right. Assuming then that <lb/>
the Crown members would retain their seats, <lb/>
there was a direct temptation presented to at <lb/>
least two out of three of the elective mem<lb break="no"/>bers. This, he thought, exhibited the project <lb/>
in a very damaging light. Such a measure <lb/>
was calculated to bias the judgment, and ought <lb/>
not to be presented to any legislative body. <lb/>
He held that elective members had received a <lb/>
sacred trust to exercise ; that they were sent <lb/>
here by their constituencies to represent them, <lb/>
and to do that only. Under these circum<lb break="no"/>stances he would ask, whether they could con<lb break="no"/>ceive they had the power to vote away the <lb/>
rights of their electors ? That was not in their <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">mandat</hi>, and if they did, they would be <lb/>
doing what the had no authority to do ; <lb/>
the would be doing what they could not do <lb/>
without going beyond the authority confided <lb/>
to them. Coming to the principle of elective <lb/>
legislative councils itself, he might say it. <lb/>
had already been adopted in four British <lb/>
colonies besides Canada. Canada, though the <lb/>
largest of these, was not the first to
adopt it, <lb/>
           

            <pb n="121" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0121.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">121</fw>
        
though it might claim to be foremost in
es<lb break="no"/>tablishing precedents—especially as with the <lb/>
addition of the Lower Provinces we are told <lb/>
we shall be the third largest
nation in the <lb/>
world—(hear, hear, and laughter)—since for <lb/>
a long series of years the demand had been <lb/>
made the people. They persisted against <lb/>
many discouragements, and the reform con<lb break="no"/>stituted one of the famous ninety-two resolu<lb break="no"/>tions of the constitutional in Lower <lb/>
Canada, until with other reforms it was at last <lb/>
conceded and consummated. When the sub<lb break="no"/>ject was under discussion, objections were <lb/>
made and fears expressed that there might <lb/>
be a feeling among the members, who came <lb/>
from the to claim the right to ori<lb break="no"/>ginate money ills, and that an antagonism <lb/>
would thus arise between the two branches, <lb/>
but no such conflict of opinion had ever hap- <lb break="yes"/>
and the Constitution had worked as <lb/>
heretofore. The infusion of the elective <lb/>
element was made gradually with the view of <lb/>
anticipating such a result, and the effect was <lb/>
attained, for there had been no clashing of <lb/>
interests. The elective principle had been <lb/>
applied to the Legislative Council of Prince <lb/>
Edward Island, and he would ask, how, <lb/>
under the 14th resolution of the Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation, that body was to be dealt with? He <lb/>
would read that part of the resolution to which <lb/>
he referred — " The first selection of the <lb/>
members of the Legislative Council to be <lb/>
made from the Legislative Councils of the <lb/>
various provinces, except as regards Prince <lb/>
Edward Island, &amp;c. What did this mean? <lb/>
Were the members from Prince Edward <lb/>
Island still to be elected ? <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName>—No; they were <lb/>
to be appointed. The resolution was so worded <lb/>
as not to limit the selection in Prince Edward <lb/>
Island to the Legislative Council now in ex<lb break="no"/>istence there. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SANB1">HON. MR. SANBORN</persName>—Was it because <lb/>
the elective principle had worked so badly in <lb/>
Canada that this change is proposed? <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName>—No; and there<lb break="no"/>fore in Canada the selection was to be made <lb/>
from the House itself. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SANB1">HON. MR. SANBORN</persName>—It appeared then, <lb/>
that Prince Edward Island, dissatisfied with <lb/>
the elective principle, had dictated terms, and <lb/>
Canada had yielded to the dictation. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName>—The Confer<lb break="no"/>ence had yielded to Prince Edward Island <lb/>
only in respect of its own members. They <lb/>
were so dissatisfied with their Legislative <lb/>
Council that, with reference to themselves, <lb/>
a choice from the people at large was
permit<lb break="no"/><cb/>ted, but this had no reference whatever
to <lb/>
Canada. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SANB1">HON. MR. SANBORN</persName> — Suppose the <lb/>
elective members should be swept off, what <lb/>
became of the people's right of representation <lb/>
by men of their own choice? <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CAMP2">HON. MR. CAMPBELL</persName>—No such thing <lb/>
was intended. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SANB1">HON. MR. SANBORN</persName> said he had only <lb/>
put the case hypothetically, but had been <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> glad to learn the reasons which had led
the <lb/>
delegates to resolve upon the
abandonment of <lb/>
the elective principle in respect of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Council. Canada, however, did not do- <lb break="yes"/>
serve to be used in this way. He would now <lb/>
ask whether the representatives of Canada in <lb/>
the Conference had any warrant from the <lb/>
country to justify their action? They had <lb/>
none whatever. If they had not acted under <lb/>
the dictation of Prince Edward Island, they <lb/>
had acted on their own motion, and without <lb/>
authority of any kind. The conclusion was
<lb/>
legitimate and logical. The position they <lb/>
had assumed was exceptional and
distasteful.<lb/>
Coming to the proposal to amend the resolu<lb break="no"/>tions, he would say there existed no reason <lb/>
why the House, if it thought proper, could <lb/>
not change them in any particular.
He wil<lb break="no"/>lingly admitted that they were
in the nature <lb/>
of a treaty, and we must accept them, if ac<lb break="no"/>cepted at all, so that their essential character <lb/>
should not be impaired; but when they were <lb/>
presented to us, we were bound to decide <lb/>
whether they were what we wanted or not. <lb/>
If they were so in the main, there was no <lb/>
necessity for taking exceptions which would <lb/>
affect our relations with the other provinces, <lb/>
but they might be modified and changed in <lb/>
so far as Canada was concerned, and the other <lb/>
provinces would have no cause of complaint. <lb/>
What interest had they in the manner of our <lb/>
choosing our own representatives? All they <lb/>
had a right to say in the matter was that
we <lb/>
should not have more than two-thirds of the <lb/>
whole number. There was a way of putting <lb/>
things so as to frighten and convince waver<lb break="no"/>ing minds; but he would ask the House to <lb/>
sift this matter to the bottom—to look at the <lb/>
reason of things—and to say if his amend<lb break="no"/>ment were adopted, which maintained intact <lb/>
the principle of representation laid down in <lb/>
the resolutions—only retaining the mode of <lb/>
choosing the members—the modification could <lb/>
lead to harm or to anything else than what <lb/>
had already been declared, viz., that the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Parliament might take the scheme with <lb/>
the amendment under consideration, and act <lb/>
upon said amendment. Mr. CARDWELL
had <lb/>
       
            <pb n="12" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0122.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">122</fw>
          
 already remarked upon that very point, and <lb/>
if it were changed, would it not be to retain <lb/>
the elective principle? If the Imperial Par<lb break="no"/>liament may do so, may we not ask them to <lb/>
do it? May we not record our views? And <lb/>
would they, upon a measure of such vast <lb/>
moment and pregnant with such results, pro<lb break="no"/>ceed to adopt a principle unless they knew its <lb/>
operation to be beneficial? Turning to his <lb/>
proposed amendment, the honorable member <lb/>
said that if it were adopted, the principle of <lb/>
federal representation in the resolutions would <lb/>
be retained; the same members would be <lb/>
retained (in Canada at least); and to render <lb/>
the proportion of the Lower Provinces rela<lb break="no"/>tively equal, he would allow them to
name ten <lb/>
life members. Were we to be told that such <lb/>
a form would be incongruous, and be deterred <lb/>
from considering the proposition?
Then we <lb/>
should be reflecting upon ourselves. He and <lb/>
other honorable members sat under a mandate <lb/>
from the people, while other honorable mem<lb break="no"/>bers set under a patent from the Crown. It <lb/>
would be a reflection both on our past and <lb/>
present condition. There were the same <lb/>
reasons now for adopting such a form as there <lb/>
were when the elective principle was adopted. <lb/>
It was a domestic matter, and should be left <lb/>
to domestic arrangement. Each province had <lb/>
its own peculiar interests, and should be left <lb/>
to the exercise of its judgment in the manage<lb break="no"/>ment of them. If subsequently a change were <lb/>
desired, it could be granted. He maintained <lb/>
that his views were correct and logical, and <lb/>
he was at a loss to see the incongruity with <lb/>
which they were charged. He could not dis<lb break="no"/>cover any sufficient cause for the proposed <lb/>
change, and as the people had not asked <lb/>
for it, and as Canada formed a large ma<lb break="no"/>jority of the whole, it ought not to have been <lb/>
granted without reference to their opinions. Representation according to population
was <lb/>
now looked upon as a cardinal principle, but
<lb/>
it certainly was not observed in dealing with <lb/>
this important question. We were told the <lb/>
vote was taken by provinces, not by numbers, <lb/>
still the Lower Provinces had the majority of <lb/>
representatives, though they represented but a <lb/>
minority of the people. Then it was said our <lb/>
delegates were leading men and men of talent, <lb/>
which he was quite prepared to allow, yet <lb/>
they did not compose all the talent or states<lb break="no"/>manship of Canada. In this way the one- <lb break="yes"/>
third of the populations interested had given <lb/>
the law to the other two-thirds. We were <lb/>
told again that the Constitution emanating- <lb break="yes"/>
from the Conference was desirable because it <lb/>
was, modelled on the British Constitution.<lb/>
       
            <cb/>  
          
 The British Constitution was unmatched in <lb/>
the world, and was not susceptible of imita<lb break="no"/>tion. It had grown by the
secretions of ages, <lb/>
by the independence of the people, and by <lb/>
their undying love of justice and fair play. <lb/>
(Hear, hour.) It had been produced by the <lb/>
strictest inductive method, and stood unri<lb break="no"/>valled as a monument of the greatest human <lb/>
wisdom. Except in remote future times, it <lb/>
could not be imitated—(hear)—and he did <lb/>
not urge this difference as a
demerit, for it <lb/>
was in the nature of things that it should <lb/>
exist. It had reform to
different kinds of <lb/>
people—to people of different
nine, and to <lb/>
people of new countries and altered circum<lb break="no"/>stances; but though an able theoretical com<lb break="no"/>position, it might fail to produce the antici<lb break="no"/>pated malts. It was not a copy
of that hor<lb break="no"/>ror of our Constitution-makers—the Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion of the United States—but he would <lb/>
show that the delegates had borrowed more <lb/>
largely from that Constitution than from any <lb/>
other, though to be sure, in some aspects, it <lb/>
differed very much from it, as
in the provision <lb/>
which gives to members of the
Upper House <lb/>
their seats for life. The resolutions provided <lb/>
that an equal representation should given <lb/>
to the three sections of the Confederation as <lb/>
having separate interests, while in the Lower <lb/>
House the representation was to be according <lb/>
to population. Both these provisions were <lb/>
copied from the American
Constitution. The <lb/>
life membership was supposed to be in con<lb break="no"/>formity with the British Constitution, but <lb/>
the limitation of the number of members was <lb/>
a violation of it. The limitation of the pow<lb break="no"/>er of the federal, and the power of the coal <lb/>
governments, was the old story of federal and <lb/>
state rights—in fact, the bone of
contention <lb/>
which had led to the present unhappy war; <lb/>
an apple of discord which our posterity might <lb/>
gather in fruits of the most bitter character. <lb/>
There was another branch of the subject he <lb/>would fail in his duty if he did not touch <lb/>
upon, and that was the situation in which the <lb/>
English of Lower Canada would be placed. <lb/>
The Honorable Premier had remarked at <lb/>
some length upon the disposition to
toleration <lb/>
and the indulgent spirit evinced by his people <lb/>
in past times, and he (Hon.Mr. SANBORN) was <lb/>
not prepared to detract from this. He would <lb/>
freely and fully concede the point. He had <lb/>
always lived in the midst of a mixed popu<lb break="no"/>lation, and his division was more French than <lb/>
English, and it would ill become him to cast <lb/>
reflections on their liberality and desire for <lb/>
fair play or justice to others. But this was <lb/>
the time, when treating of important arrange<lb break="no"/><pb n="123" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0123.jpg"/><fw type="num">123</fw>ments for the future, to lay aside all unneces<lb break="no"/>sary delicacy, and by our action to lay down <lb/>
the guarantees for the perpetuation of these <lb/>
kind feelings and this spirit of toleration so <lb/>
long existing, and which he devoutly hoped <lb/>
would never cease. No greater calamity could <lb/>
befall the English, or, in fact, both races, than <lb/>
the introduction of religious
discord among <lb/>
the people of Lower Canada. (Hear, hear.) <lb/>
It would, however, be a grievous mistake to <lb/>
overlook the safeguards and rules necessary
<lb/>
to perpetuate kindly feelings, and to prevent <lb/>
the disposition to aggressions which existed <lb/>
more or less in all minds. That principle<lb break="no"/>the love of power—was found in every human <lb/>
heart, none were exempt from it, and the <lb/>
history of the world showed that no people
<lb/>
had ever risen superior to it. The Honorable <lb/>
Premier had recognized this truth in the re<lb break="no"/>marks he had made in regard of the difficul<lb break="no"/>ties between Upper and Lower Canada. The <lb/>
French Canadians had persistantly
refused <lb/>
the demands of Upper Canada for represen<lb break="no"/>tation by population, because of the terror they <lb/>
felt that, if granted, their institutions would be <lb/>
in danger; and he had told the French mem<lb break="no"/>bers in the house that under the new
Consti<lb break="no"/>tution their rights were so effectually guarded<lb/>
that their autonomy was fully secured—the
<lb/>
safeguards thereof being put in their own <lb/>
hands. But, at the same time,
the English, <lb/>
who were a fourth of the population, and who, <lb/>
by habit and tradition, had their own views of<lb/>
public policy, were left entirely without guar<lb break="no"/>antee other than the good feelings and tolerant<lb/>
spirit of the French. Was this safe? The <lb/>
only safeguard they were to have was in regard <lb/>
of education, but in regard of
the rights <lb/>
of property they were to be left to the <lb/>
Legislature. And this brought him to the <lb/>
consideration of that part of the proposed Con<lb break="no"/>stitution which had reference to civil rights <lb/>
and rights of roperty. It was said that the <lb/>
civil laws of war Canada were now consoli<lb break="no"/>dated into a code, and this would enhance our <lb/>
credit; and if based upon sound principles and <lb/>
rendered permanent, it would undoubtedly do <lb/>
so, for what is so conducive to
the prosperity <lb/>
a country as well-protected rights of pro<lb break="no"/>perty and vested interests? This feature was <lb/>
engrained in the British mind, and in <lb/>
that of the United States also, insomuch that <lb/>
the American Constitution provides that no law <lb/>
could be passed which would affect the rights of property. This was
exemplified in the cele<lb break="no"/>brated Dartmouth College case, in which WEB<lb break="no"/>STER so distinguished himself, when the endow<lb break="no"/>ment was maintained and perpetuated. But <lb/>
         
            <cb/>  
    
to what power were the rights of com<lb break="no"/>mitted in these resolutions? When the Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Finance appealed to moneyed men <lb/>
abroad for a loan, could he say the Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion had provided guarantees against injurious <lb/>
changes, when it was known that the laws re<lb break="no"/>lating to property were left to
the caprice of <lb/>
the coal governments? Where was the <lb/>
security of the great religious societies of <lb/>
Montreal, if a sentiment hostile to monopolies <lb/>
were carried to extremes in the Local Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
<persName ref="pers:TACH1">HON. SIR. E. P. TACHÉ</persName>—The General <lb/>
Legislature had power to disallow
such acts. <lb/> <persName ref="pers:CURR2">HON. MR. CURRIE</persName>—This would be an <lb/>
interference with local rights. <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ROSS8">HON. MR. ROSS</persName>—It would preserve
local <lb/>
rights. <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SANB1">HON. MR. SANBORN</persName>—It was a wise <lb/>power and commended itself to all; it was, <lb/>however, not an ordinary power to be com-  <lb break="yes"/>
manly resorted to, but an extreme power, and <lb/>
one almost revolutionary. It was
a power <lb/>
somewhat similar to that which existed in the <lb/>
second branch of the Legislature to stop the
<lb/>
supplies, but in its very nature not one often <lb/>
to be exercised; and it could not be frequently
<lb/>
exercised without destroying the
very founda<lb break="no"/>tions of society, and occasioning evils of the <lb/>
greatest magnitude. On the whole he con<lb break="no"/>ceived that entrusting such power to the local <lb/>
governments was illogical and dangerous, and <lb/>
informing the world at the rights of property <lb/>
were not made sure. It was urged by some<lb/>
that, to make the measure now before the <lb/>
House answer the ends proposed, it must be <lb/>
immediately adopted, but he did not partici<lb break="no"/>pate in this opinion. He knew no reason for <lb/>
this haste, and could not believe that a few <lb/>
months would make any material difference. <lb/>
This union, when formed, was to strengthen
<lb/>
us so marvellously that we would be able to <lb/>
intimidate all the rest of the world, and guar<lb break="no"/>antee us a lasting peace with all mankind. It <lb/>
might increase facilities for communication, <lb/>
but could not increase our real strength. How <lb/>
the people of New Brunswick could be expect<lb break="no"/>ed to come up to Canada to defend us, and <lb/>
leave their own frontier unprotected, he could <lb/>
not comprehend. If he had misinterpreted <lb/>
the statements or explanations on this point, <lb/>
let the ministers show ow this greater <lb/>
was to be acquired. There would be three or <lb/>
four provinces more united together, but the <lb/>
frontier to be defended would be increased
in <lb/>
greater proportion than the additional number
<lb/>
of men acquired. It was said by the
advo<lb break="no"/>cates of the schemes that the naval power of<lb/>
          
            <pb n="124" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0124.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">124</fw>
  
 Great Britain would defend St. John, for<lb/>
instance, and leave scope for the volunteers to <lb/>
defend the frontiers; but the Intercolonial <lb/>
Railway, running as it would along the fron<lb break="no"/>tier, would be constantly subject to assaults, <lb/>
and would require all the force which could be <lb/>
spared for that purpose. Lower Canada would <lb/>
continue to be assailable from Maine and <lb/>
Vermont, and Up r Canada from the state <lb/>
of New York. Under these circumstances, <lb/>
each section of the Confederation would have <lb/>
enough to do to attend to its own affairs. We <lb/>
were told to love our neighbors as ourselves, <lb/>
but he was not aware that we were enjoined <lb/>
to love them better. (Hear.) We were not <lb/>
told what appropriations were to be made for <lb/>
defence, indeed pains had been taken to con<lb break="no"/>ceal that, and Hon. Mr. TILLEY said that the <lb/>
matter was not debated or determined. The <lb/>
province had already incurred an expense of <lb/>
$400,000 for the simple purpose
of sending a <lb/>
few companies of volunteers to our frontier, <lb/>
and if there were no guarantee in the scheme <lb/>
of union—and he did not see any—for in<lb break="no"/>creasing our strength, where was the use of <lb/>
haste? Were we not as safe now as we would <lb/>
be then? The Honorable Premier had stated <lb/>
we were on an inclined plane, and he (Hon. <lb/>
Mr. SANBOBN) supposed that like Holland we <lb/>
must dyke ourselves up, lest we slide away <lb/>
into the sea of the great American Confeder<lb break="no"/>acy. (Laughter.) Whether we were liable to <lb/>
be hurled thither by an avalanche or gradual<lb break="no"/>ly glide down, we could not prevent our going <lb/>
there except by Confederation, but Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion would stop us, and that was
something <lb/>
to be thankful for. His own impression was <lb/>
that our position would have been more im<lb break="no"/>proved by an agreement with Upper Canada <lb/>
than by the new nationality. Canada had had <lb/>
difficulties with the United States, but they <lb/>
had never exhibited a spirit of aggression <lb/>
towards us, except in times of war, which had <lb/>
arisen from issues between Great Britain and <lb/>
the United States, and he did not believe they <lb/>
entertained such purposes now any more than <lb/>
in former times. If we desired to have a <lb/>
Constitution which would afford good hope of <lb/>
permanency, it must be planted deep in the <lb/>
affections of the people—(hear,
hear)—for <lb/>
until their intellects were convinced of its <lb/>
excellence, they would not be prepared to <lb/>
uphold it and resist innovations. But they <lb/>
must feel and comprehend the obligation. <lb/>
(Hear.) To render it secure, it
must be in <lb/>
the hearts of the people. Why was it that <lb/>
the English had always resisted attempts upon <lb/>
their Constitution? Because every link of the <lb/>
         
            <cb/> 
         
great chain had been conquered by
resistance <lb/>
to oppression, and by sacrifices
of blood<lb break="no"/>(hear, hear)—by resistance to royal exactions <lb/>
and assumptions—(hear, hear)--and these <lb/>
achievements were preserved, held dear, un<lb break="no"/>derstood, valued, and clung to with all the <lb/>
tenacity of that great people's nature. (Hear, <lb/>
hear.) This was the reason why it rested <lb/>
upon such a solid foundation, why it had <lb/>
endured so long, and was likely to endure for <lb/>
ever. (Hear, hear.) The Constitution asked <lb/>
for was to be built on a flimsy foundation, <lb/>
consisting of certain ideas in the minds of a <lb/>
few men, who no doubt wished well to their <lb/>
country; but that Constitution was new after <lb/>
all, and they could not, in the small space of <lb/>
time they had given to the project, view the <lb/>
whole subject in all its bearings and aspects, <lb/>
as it was desirable they should. The honor<lb break="no"/>able member closed his remarks by reiter<lb break="no"/>ating his opinion that an appeal on the subject <lb/>
was due to the people whose voice had not been <lb/>
heard upon it. The acquiescence
spoken of <lb/>
was rather the patient awaiting of the details <lb/>
which were sure to be challenged, and the tes<lb break="no"/>timony of a subsidized press was not to be <lb/>
taken in evidence of its general acceptance. <lb/>
He was not prepared for one to take or reject <lb/>
the measure as presented. He believed the <lb/>
people would not approve of such a course, <lb/>
and, even were it infinitely better than it was, <lb/>
he would not take the responsibility of voting <lb/>
for it unless after it had been submitted to <lb/>
the country. (Hear, hear.) He would now <lb/>
move his amendment, which was as follows: <lb/>
            </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>That the following words be added to the
reso<lb break="no"/>lution now under consideration, as an amend<lb break="no"/>ment, by submitting for the eighth resolution the <lb/>
following:-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Upper Canada to be represented in the
Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Council by twenty-four elective members, <lb/>
and Lower Canada by twenty-four elective mem<lb break="no"/>bers, and the Maritime Provmces by twenty-four <lb/>
members, corresponding with the twenty-four <lb/>
elective members in each section of Canada of <lb/>
which Nova Scotia shall have ten, New Brunswick <lb/>
ten, and Prince Edward Island shall have four, <lb/>
and the present members of the Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cil of Canada, as well life members as elective <lb/>
members, shall be members of the first Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive Council of the Federal Parliament—the ap<lb break="no"/>pointed members to remain for life, and the elec<lb break="no"/>tive members for eight years from the date of <lb/>
their election, unless removed by death or other <lb/>
cause; their successors to be elected by the same <lb/>
divisions and electors as have elected them; and <lb/>
it shall be permitted to the Maritime Provinces to <lb/>
appoint ten additional members for life, four for <lb/>
New Brunswick, four for Nova Scotia and two
<lb/>
for Prince Edward Island, to correspond with the <lb/>
      


            <pb n="125" facs="final/images/Ont_Que_LC_1865-02-09_Page_0125.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">125</fw>
   

     present life members from Canada, and that after 
     <lb/>
     the first appointment of members in the Maritime 
     <lb/>
     Provinces, no new appointment shall be made, ex<lb break="no"/>cept to supply the vacancies by death or otherwise 
     <lb/>
     in the twenty-four members appointed to corres<lb break="no"/>pond with the elective members from the two 
     <lb/>
     sections of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And that in the eleventh section, after the word 
     <lb/>
     "Council," in the first line, the following words 
     <lb/>
     be added : "in the Maritime Provinces." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And that section fourteen be struck out. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Seconded by <persName ref="pers:BURE2">Hon. Mr. BUREAU</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACP1">HON. MR. MACPHERSON</persName> briefly ad<lb break="no"/>dressed the House in opposition to the amend<lb break="no"/>ment until the hour of adjournment, six 
     <lb/>
     o'clock, arrived. His remarks will be found 
     <lb/>
     recapitulated in the commencement of his 
     <lb/>
     speech on Friday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     At six o'clock the debate was adjourned, 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:MACP1">Hon. Mr. MACPHERSON</persName> having the floor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<!-- GL, 2016-11-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

       <!--     <p>
     ——o——  
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY. 
     <lb/>
               <lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <p>THURSDAY, February 9, 1865. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The order of the day for resuming the 
     <lb/>
     adjourned debate on the proposed Address 
     <lb/>
     to Her Majesty, on the subject of the Con<lb break="no"/>federation of the British North American 
     <lb/>
     Provinces having been called ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Honorable MR. McGEE said—Mr. 
     <lb/>
     SPEAKER, I rise to endeavor to fulfil the 
     <lb/>
     promise made in my name last evening by 
     <lb/>
     the Lower Canadian leader of this House. 
     <lb/>
     After the four speeches that have already 
     <lb/>
     been delivered from this quarter of the 
     <lb/>
     House, it may very well be supposed that 
     <lb/>
     little of essential importance remains to be 
     <lb/>
     said. On Monday the Attorney General 
     <lb/>
     West, in exposing the case for the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, in moving this Address to Her 
     <lb/>
     Majesty, went very fully through all the 
     <lb/>
     items of the resolutions agreed upon at the 
     <lb/>
     Quebec Conference, and gave us a full 
     <lb/>
     analysis of the whole project with his own 
     <lb/>
     constitutional commentaries upon the pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings of that body. On the next evening, 
     <lb/>
     the Attorney General East gave us his views 
     <lb/>
     also, treating chiefly of the difficulties in 
     <lb/>
     Lower Canada. The same night, my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend, the Minister of Finance, gave us a 
     <lb/>
     financial view of the whole subject ; and last 
     <lb/>
     evening the Hon. President of the Council 
     <lb/>
     gave us another extended financial and 
     <lb/>
     political address, with some arguments from 
     <lb/>
     " the Upper Canadian point of view," as the 
     <lb/>
     phrase is. It may well therefore seem that 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     after these speeches little of essential import<lb break="no"/>ance remains to be stated. Still this subject 
     <lb/>
     is so vast, the project before the House is so 
     <lb/>
     vast, and comprehends within it so many 
     <lb/>
     objects of interest, the atmosphere that sur<lb break="no"/>rounds a subject of this importance is so 
     <lb/>
     subtle and fluctuating, that there may be, I 
     <lb/>
     am feign to believe, a little joiner-work still 
     <lb/>
     left to do—there may be a hiatus here and 
     <lb/>
     there to fill up ; and although, as far as what 
     <lb/>
     is called " the preliminary case" is concerned, 
     <lb/>
     the question might perhaps very well have 
     <lb/>
     rested with the four speeches already 
     <lb/>
    delivered—there may be some slight addi<lb break="no"/>tional contribution made, and, such as it is, 
     <lb/>in my own humble way, I propose to make it 
     <lb/>to-night. (Hear, hear.) We all remember 
     <lb/>that in the nursery legend of the Three Kings 
     <lb/>of Cologne, CASPAR brought myrrh, and 
     <lb/>MELOCHIOR incense, and BALTASSAR gold, 
     <lb/>but I am afraid my contribution will be less 
     <lb/>valuable than any of these, yet such as it is 
     <lb/>I cheerfully bring it, particularly when there 
     <lb/>are so many in this and the other provinces 
     <lb/>who would like to know what my own views 
     <lb/>are in relation to the present crisis. (Hear-) 
     <lb/>With your approbation, sir, and the for<lb break="no"/>bearance of the House, I will endeavour to treat 
     <lb/>this subject in this way :—First, to give some 
     <lb/>slight sketch of the history of the question ; 
     <lb/>then to examine the existing motives which 
     <lb/>ought to prompt us to secure a speedy union 
     <lb/>of these provinces ; then to speak of the 
     <lb/>difficulties which this question has encoun<lb break="no"/>tered before reaching its present fortunate 
     <lb/>stage ; then to say something of the mutual 
     <lb/>advantages, in a social rather than political 
     <lb/>point of view, which these provinces will 
     <lb/>have in their union, and lastly to add a few 
     <lb/>words on the Federal principle in general, 
     <lb/>when I shall have done. In other words, I 
     <lb/>propose to consider the question of union 
     <lb/>mainly from within, and as far as possible to 
     <lb/>avoid going over the ground already so fully 
     <lb/>and so much better occupied by hon. friends 
     <lb/>who have already spoken upon the subject. 
     <lb/>My hon. friend, the member for Hoche- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>laga, thought he did a very clever thing the 
     <lb/>other evening when he disentombed an old 
     <lb/>newspaper article of mine, entitled " A 
     <lb/>New Nationality," and endeavored to fix on 
     <lb/>me the paternity of the phrase—destined to 
     <lb/>become prophetic—which was employed by 
     <lb/>a very distinguished personage in the Speach 
     <lb/>from the Throne at the opening of the 
     <lb/>session. I do happen to remember the 
     <lb/>article alluded to as one of my first 
     <lb/>essays in political writing in Canada ; but 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

    
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
