<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1865-04-27"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">Legislature</name>, <date when="1865-04-27">27 April 1865</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Canadian Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

  
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1865</title>.
                    

          <date when="1865"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="2"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-04-27_Page_001.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-04-27_Page_002.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-01">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-01">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-04-27_Page_001">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-27_Page_001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-04-27_Page_002">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-27_Page_002"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="001" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-27_Page_001.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">Provincial Parliament</fw>
            <fw type="running">House of Assembly</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">THURSDAY, April 27th.</fw>
            
            <p> This day
at 2 o'clock P.M., His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency the Lieutenant Governor came<lb/>
down to the Council Chamber, and hav<lb break="no"/>ing commanded the attendance of the<lb/>
House of Assembly, directed them to elect<lb/>
a Speaker. The Members of the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly then returned to the Lower House,<lb/>
when Dr. Vail was nominated for Speak<lb break="no"/>er by Colonel Boyd, seconded by Mr.<lb/>
Kern ; and Mr. McClellan was nominated<lb/>
by Mr. Sutton seconded by Mr. A. C.<lb/>
DesBrisay ; upon a division being taken<lb/>
Dr. Vail was declared elected. He then<lb/>
in an appropriate Speech thanked the<lb/>
Members of the House and received their<lb/>
congratulations. It was then announced<lb/>
that His Excellency would command the<lb/>
attendance of the House at 4 o'clock.</p>
            <p>Legislative
Council Chamber,<lb/>
4 o'clock, P. M.</p>

            <p> His Excellency the Lieutenant Gover<lb break="no"/>nor, being seated on the Throne com<lb break="no"/>manded the attendance of the House of<lb/>
Assembly who being come, His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency was pleased to open the Session<lb/>
with the following</p>
            <p>SPEECH : <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">" Mr. President, and Honorable Gentle<lb break="no"/>men of the Legislative Council :</hi></p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">" Mr. Speaker and the Gentlemen of the
House<lb/>
of Assembly :</hi> <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" I am directed by the Queen to in<lb break="no"/>form you that Her Majesty has been<lb/>
pleased to receive very graciously the<lb/>
Joint Address of the Legislature of this<lb/>
Province on the occasion of the Birth of<lb/>
the Son of their Royal Highnesses the<lb/>
Prince and Princess of Wales.</p>
            <p>" The Civil War which has so long<lb/>
raged in the neighbouring Republic ap<lb break="no"/>pears to be drawing towards a close. The<lb/>
restoration of Peace will, no doubt, be<lb/>
hailed by you with a lively satisfaction,<lb/>
both as putting an end to the further ef<lb break="no"/>fusion of blood, and as reopening to com<lb break="no"/>merce channels which have, since the<lb/>
commencement of the War, been closed.</p>
            <p>" The joy which pervaded the United<lb/>
States at the prospect of a speedy termi<lb break="no"/>nation of hostilities has, however, been<lb/>
clouded by the commission of a foul crime.<lb/>
I know I speak your sentiments when I<lb/>
say that we share the feelings of indig<lb break="no"/>nant reprobation which the murder of the<lb/>
President has evoked in every honest and<lb/>
generous heart, and that we join in the<lb/>
mourning of a great and kindred people.</p>

            <p> " In compliance with the desire ex<lb break="no"/>pressed by Addresses from both branches<lb/>
of the Legislature at the last Session, I<lb/>
appointed Delegates to meet others ap<lb break="no"/><cb/>pointed by the Lieutenant Governors of<lb/>
Nova Scotia and Prince Edward Island,<lb/>
for the purpose of considering the prac<lb break="no"/>ticability of effecting a Legislative and<lb/>
Administrative Union of the Maritime<lb/>
Provinces of British North America.<lb/>
The Report of these Delegates will immedi<lb break="no"/>ately be laid before you.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> " At the request of the Governor Ge<lb break="no"/>neral of Canada, and with the approba<lb break="no"/>tion of the Queen, I also appointed Dele<lb break="no"/>gates to a Conference of
Representatives<lb/>
of the British North American Colonies,<lb/>
held in Quebec in the month of October<lb/>
last, with a view of arranging the terms<lb/>
of a Federal Union of British North Ame<lb break="no"/>rica. The resolutions agreed to by this<lb/>
Conference appeared to me to be so im<lb break="no"/>portant in their character, and their adop<lb break="no"/>tion fraught with consequences so mate<lb break="no"/>rially affecting the future condition and<lb/>
well-being of British America, that, in<lb/>
order to enable the people of New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick to give expression to their wishes<lb/>
on the subject, I determined to dissolve<lb/>
the then existing House of Assembly. I<lb/>
now submit these Resolutions to your<lb/>
judgment.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> " You will do well to enquire whether it<lb/>
is possible to afford further facilities for<lb/>
the development and improvement of the<lb/>
Railway system already existing in this<lb/>
Province. Works for the completion and<lb/>
extension of the European and North<lb/>
American Railway, from the frontier of<lb/>
Nova Scotia to that of the United States,<lb/>
will be undertaken as soon as practicable ;<lb/>
but any immediate steps in this direction<lb/>
appear to be precluded by existing legis<lb break="no"/>lation.</p>
            <p>" I recommend you to consider whether<lb/>
it is necessary for the efficient discharge<lb/>
of the postal service of the Province, that<lb/>
the Head of that Department should be,<lb/>
as hitherto, one of the confidential advi<lb break="no"/>sers of the Crown<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> " Your attention will be called, with a<lb/>
view to their renewal, to several enact<lb break="no"/>ments which, owing to my inability to call<lb/>
you together at an earlier period, have<lb/>
either expired or are on the point of ex<lb break="no"/>piring. Among their number is the Act<lb/>
establishing the Provincial Militia. A<lb/>
Bill for the revival of that Force, and to<lb/>
provide for its increased efficiency, will<lb/>
immediately be laid before you ; and I<lb/>
am confident that you will desire, at as<lb/>
early a period as is compatible with the<lb/>
due consideration of the provisions of that<lb/>
measure, to put the Province again into<lb/>
possession of a Force, of which, for the<lb/>
last eighty years, it has never until now<lb/>
been altogether destitute. Active steps<lb/>
have been taken, and large sums of expend<lb break="no"/>ed to improve the organization of the Mi<lb break="no"/>litia in the neighbouring Provinces of Ca<lb break="no"/>nada and Nova Scotia. I cannot doubt<lb/>
that the loyal spirit of the people of New<lb/>
Brunswick will prompt them to efforts of<lb/>
               <cb/> 
               
               a similar character. Some correspond<lb break="no"/>ence on this subject has passed between<lb/>
the Imperial Government and myself. I<lb/>
have directed this correspondence to be<lb/>
laid before you.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> "The income of the past Fiscal Year<lb/>
was not only largely in excess of the es<lb break="no"/>timated amount, but is greater than that<lb/>
ever previously received in any one year ;<lb/>
and a considerable surplus remained after<lb/>
all charges on the Treasury had been de<lb break="no"/>frayed. I cannot, however, hold out to<lb/>
you any hope that the receipts of the pre<lb break="no"/>sent year will be of nearly equal amount.<lb/>
Trade has been depressed, and the Reve<lb break="no"/>nue has suffered from that depression, al<lb break="no"/>though I entertain hopes that some im<lb break="no"/>provement may be experienced before the<lb/>
year closes.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <hi rendition="simple:italic">" Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the<lb/>
House of Assembly :</hi><lb/>
            </p>

            <p> " I have
directed the Accounts of the<lb/>
Income and Expenditure of the past year<lb/>
to be laid before you.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> " Estimates for the current year will<lb/>
also be submitted to you. They have<lb/>
been framed with as close a regard to<lb/>
economy as is consistent with ? due pro<lb break="no"/>vision for the requirements of the public<lb/>
service.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic"> " Mr.
President, and Honourable Gentle<lb break="no"/>men of the Legislative Council :</hi><lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <hi rendition="simple:italic">" Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the<lb/>
House of Assembly :</hi><lb/>
            </p>

            <p> " Notwithstanding the temporary de<lb break="no"/>pression of trade, the condition of the<lb/>
Province is on the whole satisfactory ; and<lb/>
a feeling of contentment and of confi<lb break="no"/>dence in the Institutions under which we<lb/>
live generally prevails. It affords me sa<lb break="no"/>tisfaction to observe that, whatever dif<lb break="no"/>ference of opinion may on other subjects<lb/>
be manifested, there is but one unani<lb break="no"/>mous feeling of loyalty towards the<lb/>
Crown, and an universal desire to per<lb break="no"/>petuate the connection of this Province<lb/>
with Great Britain. I rejoice to perceive<lb/>
that you are fully sensible of the advan<lb break="no"/>tages you derive from that connection,<lb/>
and I cannot doubt that you will cheer<lb break="no"/>fully meet the corresponding obligations<lb/>
which it entails."<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> The members of the Assembly having<lb/>
returned to the Lower House, His Honor<lb/>
the Speaker read the opening Speech.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Col. BOYD brought in a Bill to provide<lb/>
for the expenses of the Legislature. Bill<lb/>
received and ordered to be read ? first<lb/>
time.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Mr. OTTY moved the following Address<lb/>
in answer to His Excellency's speech.<lb/>
            </p>


            <p> <hi rendition="simple:italic">To His Excellency The Honorable</hi> ARTHUR<lb/>
               HAMILTON GORDON, C. M. G., <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieu<lb break="no"/>tenant Governor and Commander in Chief<lb/>
of the Province of New Brunswick, &amp;c.,<lb/>
&amp;c., &amp;c.</hi><lb/>
            </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">May it please Your Excellency,</hi>—</p>
<p>1. We, the faithful Commons of New<lb/>
        
            <pb n="2" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-27_Page_002"/>
      
      Brunswick, thank Your Excellency for<lb/>
your Speech at the opening of the Session.</p>

            <p> 2. We are gratified to learn that Her<lb/>
Majesty was graciously pleased to receive<lb/>
our congratulations on the occasion of<lb/>
the birth of the Son of their Royal High-<lb break="yes"/>
nesses the Prince and Princess of Wales.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> 3 We share with Your Excellency the<lb/>
feelings of satisfaction at the prospect
of<lb/>
the speedy restoration of peace
in the<lb/>
neighboring Republic ; and we assure<lb/>
Your Excellency that you truly express <lb/>
our sentiments, when you say that we <lb/>
fully share the feelings of
indignant re<lb break="no"/>probation which the murder of
the Presi<lb break="no"/>dent has excited in every honest and <lb/>
generous heart, and participate in the <lb/>
grief of a great and kindred people.
<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p> We thank Your Excellency for the as<lb break="no"/>surance that the Report of the Delegates <lb/>
appointed for the purpose of considering <lb/>
the practicability of effecting a
Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive and Administrative Union of
the <lb/>
Maritime Provinces of British North <lb/>
America, will be laid before us. We also <lb/>
thank Your Excellency for the informa<lb break="no"/>tion that the Resolutions adopted at a <lb/>
Conference of Representatives of the <lb/>
British North American Colonies, held at <lb/>
Quebec in October last, relative to a <lb/>
Union of British North America, will be <lb/>
laid before us.</p>
            <p> 5. We
will consider whether further <lb/>
facilities can be afforded for the exten<lb break="no"/>sion of Railways in this Province.<lb break="no"/>We are pleased to learn that the
comple<lb break="no"/>tion and extension of the European and <lb/>
North American Railway, from the
fron<lb break="no"/>tier of Nova Scotia to the
boundary of <lb/>
the United States, will be undertaken as <lb/>
soon as practicable : and we
regret that <lb/>
existing laws preclude immediate
action <lb/>
for the accomplishment of this work. <lb/>
            </p>
 
            <p> 6. We will
give our attentive consid<lb break="no"/>eration to any measure that may be sub<lb break="no"/>mitted relating to the Postal Service
of <lb/>
the Province. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 7. We will give
our attention to such <lb/>
enactments as have recently expired,
or <lb/>
are about to expire. Any measure sub<lb break="no"/>mitted for the revival of the
Provincial <lb/>
Militia, and for increasing its
efficiency, <lb/>
will receive our most prompt and careful <lb/>
consideration. We thank Your Excel<lb break="no"/>lency for the assurance that the Corres<lb break="no"/>pondence between the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and Your Excellency, relating to <lb/>
this subject,
will be laid before us. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 8. We are gratiﬁed
to learn that the <lb/>
Revenue of the past Fiscal Year
was <lb/>
largely in excess of the
Estimate, and that <lb/>
a surplus remained after all
charges on <lb/>
the Treasury had been defrayed. We <lb/>
regret, however, that the depression in <lb/>
trade has caused so large a
falling off in <lb/>
the Revenue of the present year, but we <lb/>
trust that the hopes of improvement ex<lb break="no"/>pressed by Your Excellency may be<lb/>
realized.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>9. We thank Your Excellency for the<lb/>
assurance that the Accounts of the In<lb break="no"/>come and Expenditure of the past year, <lb/>
and the Estimates for the present
year<lb/>
will be laid before us. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> 10. We agree with Your Excellency <lb/>
that notwithstanding the present depres<lb break="no"/>sion of Trade, the condition of
the Prov<lb break="no"/>ince is, on the whole, satisfactory, and <lb/>
that a feeling of contentment
and confi<lb break="no"/>dence in the institutions under which we <lb/>
live prevails ; and we assure
Your Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency, that whatever differences of <lb/>
opinion may exist on other subjects, the<lb/>
feeling of loyalty to the Crown, for which<lb/>
the people of this Province have always<lb/>
been distinguished, animates them still.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>11. We are fully sensible of the advan<lb break="no"/>tages we derive from our connection with <lb/>
            <cb/> 
               
               Great
Britain, and will cheerfully meet<lb/>
the obligations it entails upon us.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> On motion of Mr. OTTY, Saturday next<lb/>
at 11 o'clock was the time fixed for the <lb/>
discussion. of the Reply. <lb/>
            </p>


            <p> On
motion of Mr. KERR, a Committee <lb/>
was appointed to confer with a
Committee <lb/>
of the Legislative Council, with regards to<lb/>
the Legislative Library.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> On motion of Mr. WILLISTON,
a Com<lb break="no"/>mittee was appointed to take into consid<lb break="no"/>eration the contingencies of the
House. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion of Mr. MCCLELLAN, a Com<lb break="no"/>mittee was appointed to whom shall be<lb/>
referred all matters relating to the Mining<lb/>
interests of the Province.</p>


            <p> On motion of Mr. NEEDHAM, a Standing <lb/>
Committee was appointed to whom
shall <lb/>
be referred all matters concerning
the <lb/>
privileges of the House. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. GILBERT moved a Resolution that <lb/>
the Rules in force in the late House be <lb/>
adopted in the present, until altered, <lb/>
amended, or repealed.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> After some discussion this Resolution <lb/>
was adopted. . <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion of Mr. BEVERIDGE a Com<lb break="no"/>mittee was appointed to take
into consid<lb break="no"/>eration all matters relating to the Lumber<lb break="no"/>ing interests of the Province. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion
of Mr. L. P. W. DESBRISAY, <lb/>
a Committee was appointed to take into <lb/>
consideration all matters connected with <lb/>
the Trade of the Province. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Hon.
ATTORNEY GENERAL brought in <lb/>
a Bill entitled, An act to regulate the sale <lb/>
of Spirituous Liquors. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. GILBERT brought
in a Bill to sim<lb break="no"/>plify the practice of Law in this Province, <lb/>
and to abolish special bail.</p>
            <p>Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL brought in <lb/>
a Bill to alter the division line between the <lb/>
Parishes Queensbury and Southampton, <lb/>
in the County of York. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion of Mr. WILLISTON, a Com<lb break="no"/>mittee was appointed to whom shall be <lb/>
referred all matters relating to the Fish<lb break="no"/>eries of this Province. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Hon. COMMISSIONER
OF THE BOARD OF<lb/>
WORKS, called the attention
of the House <lb/>
to the fact of the Reporters’ seats
being so <lb/>
situated and occupied that it will be very <lb/>
difficult for the ofﬁcial Reporters to give <lb/>
satisfaction, unless they have a position <lb/>
assigned them in corner of the Ladies'<lb/>
Gallery, that being the most suitable place
<lb/>
in the House. This created some discus<lb break="no"/>sion, and the matter was ﬁnally dropped. <lb/>
            </p>


            <p> On motion
of Mr. GILBERT, a Committee<lb/>
was appointed to whom shall be referred
<lb/>
all matters relating to Public accounts, <lb/>
with power to bring before them persons <lb/>
and papers.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion of Dr. THOMPSON, a Com<lb break="no"/>mittee was appointed to take into consid<lb break="no"/>eration all matters relating to Agriculture.
<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion, the House was adjourned <lb/>
until to-morrow at. 10 o'clock. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> T. P. D.
<lb/>
            </p>
         
         <!-- GL, 2016-11-01, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
            
            <!--<p>FRIDAY, April 28th. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of Mr. GILBERT leave was <lb/>
granted to introduce a Bill to provide for <lb/>
the fencing in of certain
intervale lands, <lb/>
and maintaining roads through the same <lb/>
in the County of Westmorland. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>On motion of Mr. GILBERT leave was
<lb/>
granted to lay before the House the peti<lb break="no"/>tion of Rev. P. Callahan and others, of <lb/>
Shediac, to provide for the fencing in of <lb/>
certain intervale lands, and maintaining <lb/>
roads through the same. </p>
            <p>Mr. WILLISTON moved for leave to<lb/>
bring in a Bill for the protection of Moose.<lb/>
This Bill on motion was read a first and<lb/>
second time and referred to a select com<lb break="no"/>mittee to report thereon.<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>

            <p>Mr. SCOVIL suggested the desirability<lb/>
of
having a law on the Statute Book
pro<lb break="no"/>viding for the preservation of partridges. <lb/>
(A member.—“ And another to preserve <lb/>
rabbits.")<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. WILLISTON brought in a Bill re<lb break="no"/>lating to French property at Alma, in
the<lb/>
County of Northumberland.<lb/>
            </p>


            <p> Mr.WILLISTON
on motion presented a <lb/>
petition from George Letson
and others<lb/>
of Alma, Northumberland, praying that <lb/>
the French may he required to support <lb/>
their own paupers in that
district without <lb/>
drawing from the poor law fund. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Hon. Mr. SMITH laid before the House <lb/>
the report of the Committee appointed by <lb/>
last House to attend to the reporting
and <lb/>
printing of the Debates. 
Report adopted. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. HATHEWAY stated that he had<lb/>
been requested to inform the members
<lb/>
that they could, if they wished,
have the <lb/>
copies, if they desired to send it to
their con<lb break="no"/>stituents, done up and mailed
from the <lb/>
Publisher's office on
the payment of four <lb/>
dollars for the Session. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. CONNELL
said the copies for the <lb/>
members ought to be done up and sent to <lb/>
the House, to be distributed by a person <lb/>
apppointed for the purpose. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. L. P. W. DESBRISAY presumed it <lb/>
was optional with members to do
as they <lb/>
pleased in the matter. He thought the <lb/>
idea a good one, and much preferable
to <lb/>
the plan adopted her? of
having <lb/>
them sent out from the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. BOYD moved that the number of <lb/>
Debates printed be 6000, instead of 4,500 <lb/>
mentioned in the report.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> APPORTIONMENT OF DEBATES. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Mr. CONNELL
moved that the distribu<lb break="no"/>tion of the Debates should be apportioned
<lb/>
according to population of 1861.
<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. MCMILLAN moved an amendment <lb/>
that the distribution be as formerly— a 
<lb/>
definite number to each member. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. BOYD said that in past years the <lb/>
distribution of the Debates by giving a <lb/>
certain number to each member had been <lb/>
very unequal and unfair. The small <lb/>
counties had received as many as
those <lb/>
with a population of 30 or 40 000, and he <lb/>
thought by carrying the resolution
a bet<lb break="no"/>ter order of things in this respect would <lb/>
be introduced, and much more general <lb/>
satisfaction given. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. SMITH asked if the resolution <lb/>
contemplated representation by popula<lb break="no"/>tion.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. LINDSAY said of course the Hon. <lb/>
ex-Surveyor General would go for the <lb/>
amendment, as‘he represented a county <lb/>
with a population of some 4 or
5,000, and <lb/>
he would like to get as large a number as <lb/>
Carleton with its 17 or 18 000.
<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Mr. MCMILLAN did not know where <lb/>
the hon. member got his information as to<lb/>
the population of the county he repre<lb break="no"/>sented, but he certainly had been
mis<lb break="no"/>informed. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. CAIE asked
if two counties, each <lb/>
with about the same population, the one <lb/>having four members in the House and <lb/>
the other but two, would receive the same <lb/>
number of copies, or would one get double <lb/>as many as the other. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. HUTCHISON thought St. John should <lb/>
not have as many copies according to <lb/>
population as the rural districts,
as they <lb/>
were well supplied with papers as
convey<lb break="no"/>ances of intelligence of  the doings of the <lb/>
House. With this exception he was fav<lb break="no"/>orable to a distribution apportioned ac<lb break="no"/>cording to population.<lb/>
            </p>






            <p> Mr. WILLISTON.— In Northumberland<lb/>
and Gloucester the people are
engaged in <lb/>
various employments, and require a larger<lb/>
diffusion of information than in counties<lb/>
            </p>
-->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
