<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgASLA_1898-09-14"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>,
          <date when="1898-09-14">14 September 1898</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA"> 
               <editor>Walter Scott</editor>.
          <title>The Leader</title>.
          <date when="1898-09-22"/>.
          <pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>:
          <publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="5"/>.
     
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1898-09-22_Page_004.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1898-09-22_Page_005.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-31">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-31">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="The_Leader_1898-09-22_Page_004">
         <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-22_Page_004.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="The_Leader_1898-09-22_Page_005">
         <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-22_Page_005.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="004" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-22_Page_004.jpg"/>
      
      
            <fw type="dateline">THE LEADER, THURSDAY EVENING, SEPTEMBER 22, 1898</fw>
            <fw type="num">4</fw>

            <head rendition="simple:centre">RE-CAST OF THE ELECTURAL DISTRICTS<lb/>
            </head>

            <head rendition="simple:centre">Boundaries Straightened Out, and Two New Dis<lb break="no"/>tricts Created.<lb/>
            </head>

            <head rendition="simple:centre">The Printing Contractor Made a "Blotch" of the Bill–Some <lb/>Items of Estimates Threshed Out in Committee—Brands <lb/>and School Law Amendments – The Question of Com<lb break="no"/>panies' Untaxable Lands—The Government Promises to <lb/>Issue the Brand Book—The "Boundaries" Resolution <lb/>Was Hard Hit-Game Laws Further Amended—No More<lb/>
            </head>


            <p rendition="simple:right">WEDNESDAY, Sept. 14, 1898.</p>
            
            
            <pb n="005" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-22_Page_005.jpg"/>

            <fw type="dateline">THE LEADER, THURSDAY EVENING, SEPTEMBER 22, 1898.</fw>

            <p>[...] of the present number? If the expense <lb/>
was the chief consideration, why not dis<lb break="no"/>pense with the House, and have simply<lb/>one great district represented by one<lb/>member? or perhaps two districts, Mac<lb break="no"/>leod and Moose Jaw? In supporting the<lb/>bill Mr. Dill said he was carrying out the<lb/>wish of his constituents whose wish was<lb/>reasonable and they were entitled to have<lb/>it granted. As hew as not a candidate he<lb/>could not be accused of attempting to<lb/>make things safe for himself. And Mr.<lb/>Gillis, whose district was affected, had<lb/>been opposed to the change when it was<lb/>first proposed. Mr. Gillis finally admit<lb break="no"/>ted the justice of the change and reluc<lb break="no"/>tantly consented to it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILL3">Mr. Gillis</persName> said that his district was<lb/>affected, and in a way which did not please <lb/>the people who were by the change to be<lb/>taken from Whitewood and put into the<lb/>new district of Grenfell. But he had to<lb/>admit the necessity for increased repre<lb break="no"/>sentation. The additions proposed by the<lb/>bill amounted to an increase of seven<lb/>per cent. in the representation.<lb/>Surely the population had increased<lb/>more than that in four years.<lb/>Personally he had no desire for the change<lb/>as affecting his district, but he couldnot<lb/>oppose it in the fact of its evident necessity.<lb/>The change places Broadview with a some<lb break="no"/>what light population on the eastern side<lb/>of the Grenfell district. The people of<lb/>Broadview fell that politically they will<lb/>have little weight, and they feel it keen<lb break="no"/>ly. Mr. Gillis said that he felt it too, but<lb/>saw no other course open. He referred<lb/>to the word "gerrymander" upon which<lb/>Mr. Mowat arose and denied that he <lb/>had made any accusation of "gerry<lb break="no"/>mander."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILL3">Mr. Gillis</persName> disclaimed the idea that<lb/>there had been any caucusing, or per-<lb break="yes"/>arranged meeting of the East Assiniboia<lb/>members.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName> said there was a chairman<lb/>and he heard a motion put.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:PAGE3">Mr. Page</persName> - Oh, no.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILL3">Mr. Gillis</persName> thought Mr. Mowat was mis<lb break="no"/>taken. He concluded by declaring that<lb/>he did not believe the Government in<lb/>proposing the changes were actuated by<lb/>any view as to their own safety, as there<lb/>was certainly no advantage for them in<lb/>the bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:PAGE3">Mr. Page</persName> said he was at the meeting<lb/>referred to by Mr. Mowat as a caucus.<lb/>It scarcely deserved the dignity of the<lb/>term "meeting". It had been a purely<lb/>casual and informal discussion. Mr.<lb/>Page questioned Mr. Mowat's figures.<lb/>If they turned up the public accounts and<lb/>took the expenses of legislation, the<lb/>average cost per member would be found<lb/>nothing like Mr. Mowat's calculation.<lb/>As concerning the work of a member, he<lb/>said that South Regina was not a good<lb/>criterion. All the business in that district<lb/>practically centered in one town. A<lb/>scattered rural district with a number of<lb/>market places made very much work for<lb/>a member. Mr. Page thought that his<lb break="no"/>tory might lead to the belief that Mr.<lb/>Mowat would not resent the suggestion<lb/>of the member for Wolseley for only two<lb/>members. With a member fro mCalgary<lb/>Mr. Mowat had at one time been willing<lb/>to take the responsibility of governing the<lb/>whole Territories.<lb/>Mr. Tims said if Mr. Mowat had follow<lb break="no"/>ed the pubic prints -- the Free Lance,<lb/>the Plaindealer, the Bulletin, -- he would<lb/>know that there had been an outcry for<lb/>increased representation. Victoria in<lb/>1896 had 1150 votes, and at least 200<lb/>more have been naturalized since, besides<lb/>200 families had moved into the district<lb/>this year. The other northern districts<lb/>had been growing in equal degree. Again<lb/>the area of those districts was very great.<lb/>No one man could attend adequately to<lb/>the business arising in those districts.<lb/>The economy cry might be a good cam<lb break="no"/>paign cry in some parts, but in this con<lb break="no"/>ection it would be useless in Northern<lb/>Alberta.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCA6">Mr. Macauley</persName> reminded Mr. Mowat<lb/>that there was such a thing as being penny<lb/>wise and pound foolish. To take any step<lb/>which would lead to the encouragement<lb/>of people to come into this country and<lb/>be satisfied was economy of the best kind.<lb/>Into the area which was to be erected as<lb/>the district of Wetaskiwin at least<lb/>400 families had come this year. The<lb/>northern members had not taken their<lb/>petitions to Mr. Mowat; they took them<lb/>to the Government. In the new district<lb/>there were the four flourishing towns of<lb/>Lacombe, Poneks, Leduc, and Wetaski<lb break="no"/>win - all market towns. To look after<lb/>the interests of a district with so many<lb/>commercial centers was no light task.<lb/>The people wanted the increase, and<lb/>would be pleased that the Government<lb/>proposed it. The lines were drawn <lb/>straight. No gerrymander was attempt<lb break="no"/>ed. The increase was wise and in the<lb/>best interests of the Territories as a <lb/>whole.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MALO3">Mr. Maloney</persName> said that his district was<lb/>only slightly affected and it had a right to<lb/>ask still larger representation. However,<lb/>with the very great interest Mr. Mowat<lb/>had been showing in the district, and<lb/>with due economy in other districts, Mr.<lb/>Maloney hoped that St. Albert would<lb/>be fairly well attended to. It<lb/>was his intention if all went well<lb/>to move at the end of the next<lb/>term for another alteration of<lb/>lines to give Northern Alberta what its<lb/>population entitles it to. St. Albert<lb/>showed 1800 voters in 1896. Such a<lb/>district ought to have two members and<lb/>he hoped hereafter to get less abuse for<lb/>asking only one-half of what the people<lb/>of his district deserved. Mr. Maloney<lb/>said the word "gerrymander" should be<lb/>left in the east. This bill proposed no<lb/>monstrosity. It was the North West<lb/>habit to increase the representation com<lb break="no"/>mensurately with development. South<lb/>Regina was a district which a mn could<lb/>go through in a day. Mr. Ross had<lb/>travelled straight ahead for six consecu<lb break="no"/>tive days in St. Albert and had then<lb/>seen only a part of the district. Mr.<lb/>Maloney regretted that Mr. Mowat would<lb/>not be in the next Assembly to continue<lb/>to assist in giving prominence to st. Al<lb break="no"/>bert.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:AGNE1">Mr. Agnew</persName> said that Saskatchewan was<lb/>satisfied with its number of members.<lb/>The population there was not large, but<lb/>the areas of the district were tremendous.<lb/>Large areas made widespread interests<lb/>and more work for the members. The<lb/>district of Mitchell was now filling up<lb/>rapidly, and likely by the end of next<lb/>term would require division. The change<lb/>made now by ratifying the Green Lake<lb/>settlement as in Prince Albert West was<lb/>no advantage to him. Green Lake did<lb/>not vote for him last time, and he had<lb/>no reason to expect that it would vote<lb/>for him next time. Shell River was put<lb/>back in his district. It belonged there<lb/>naturally, and the people had asked<lb/>to be put back.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ROSS11">Mr. Ross</persName> closed the debate. he said<lb/>that representation by population was a<lb/>good principle, but in a new country it<lb/>could not be followed absolutely. He<lb/>would instance battleford, whose popul<lb break="no"/>ation alone did not entitle it to a member<lb/>when the district was erected. But its<lb/>area and comparative isolation did entitle<lb/>it to representation. So with Medicine<lb/>Hat when that district was erected, and<lb/>with several others. but in the increases<lb/>which the Government now asked the<lb/>House to make, rep. by pop. was the<lb/>guiding principle. East Assiniboia was<lb/>
         
         
            <cb/>

       
       not large in area, but it was comparative<lb break="no"/>ly thickly populated. Moosomin com<lb break="no"/>prises only 28 townships, and at last elec<lb break="no"/>tion polled 1000 votes. In the present<lb/>proposition the Government were not go<lb break="no"/>ing in the dark. There was no guess<lb/>work. They had the facts, and during<lb/>the year had gathered information through<lb/>that organisation of many-sided useful<lb break="no"/>ness, the Statue Labor Districts. The<lb/>proposed district of Wolseley had reported<lb/>1059 male persons over 21 years of age.<lb/>Mr. Ross gave the figures by<lb/>townships from all that had been<lb/>organised, and gave calculations<lb/>for townships which were not organised.<lb/>His calculations and actual returns show<lb break="no"/>ed 2,800 voters in the present districts of<lb/>Whitewood and Wolseley. The two dis<lb break="no"/>tricts comprise 11 ranges. The bill propos<lb break="no"/>ed three districts with four ranges in each<lb/>Grenfell and Whitewood, and three ranges<lb/>in Wolseley. This would still leave Wol<lb break="no"/>seley with slightly the larger population.<lb/>As the average number of voters in all the<lb/>districts was between 600 and 700, he said<lb/>the increase was nothing but fair. One<lb/>advantage in the case of both additions<lb/>was that the changes would do away with<lb/>a certain friction which had existed be<lb break="no"/>tween the towns of Grenfell and wolseley,<lb/>and Red Deer and Wetaskiwin. This<lb/>advantage was not the object of the bill,<lb/>yet it was not a bad incidental advantage.<lb/>As to the increase in Northern Alberta<lb/>the Government had not been able to<lb/>procure the same definite statistics as in<lb/>the other case, but everyone knew that<lb/>in that part of the country there had been<lb/>a larger increase of population than in<lb/>other parts. Then again the map showed<lb/>that the present Red Dee district was<lb/>very large in area, containing, as Mr. Mc<lb break="no"/>Cauley had shown, a large number of<lb/>market towns, which made the work of<lb/>its representative exceedingly onerous.<lb/>With the conditions prevailing there, the<lb/>question of area had to be considered, and<lb/>with due regard to area and to population<lb/>that portion of the country was well en<lb break="no"/>titled to an extra member. The bill gave<lb/>no chance for any accusation of gerry<lb break="no"/>mander. The new map would show that<lb/>the present bill straightened several pecu<lb break="no"/>liar lines; -- a number of jogs were taken<lb/>out, and the whole bill had been framed<lb/>totally regardless of its effect upon any<lb/>member. They had been actuated by a<lb/>single motive, to do justice to the differ<lb break="no"/>ent portions of the country. Mr. Ross<lb/>said the members did well to refrain from<lb/>any remarks as to the East versus West<lb/>or North versus South. But lest any per<lb break="no"/>son should be inclined to say anything<lb/>from such a point of view, he would point<lb/>out that a calculation based on the respec<lb break="no"/>tive votes polled in 1896 election<lb/>would show the representation to be very<lb/>fairly divided as between Alberta and<lb/>Assiniboia. Alberta would now have 11<lb/>members, and East Assiniboia 10, and<lb/>that proportion fairly represented their<lb/>strength as shown in 1896. He thought<lb/>all wants were met by this redistribution.<lb/>Northern Alberta was entitled to the in<lb break="no"/>crease, and the new district had been ar<lb break="no"/>ranged in the proper place. It would be<lb/>composed of parts of the four present<lb/>districts all of which had been growing in<lb/>population. Even with the addition, all<lb/>those districts as well as the new district<lb/>contained voters in excess of teh average,<lb/>taking the Territories as a whole. In re<lb break="no"/>gard to Saskatchewan Mr. Ross pointed<lb/>out that the Assembly did not arrange its<lb/>representation. Saskatchewan had been<lb/>given six members, regardless of popula<lb break="no"/>tion, and to some extent properly so, by<lb/>Parliament before the subject was en<lb break="no"/>trusted to the Assembly. Parliament<lb/>had deemed it wise to give Saskatchewan<lb/>six members, and whether Parliament <lb/>was right or not, he at least thought it<lb/>would be unwise for the Assembly to dim<lb break="no"/>inish that representation. The area<lb/>was now filling rapidly, and it could be<lb/>hoped that by the end of another four<lb/>years Saskatchewan will have population<lb/>entitling it to more than six members.<lb/>As already explained some changes were<lb/>proposed in the lines between the dis<lb break="no"/>tricts in Saskatchewan. Large rivers in<lb/>some cases formed natural boundaries,<lb/>and in some cases they found townships<lb/>lying on one side of a river, with their in<lb break="no"/>terests all on their own side of the river,<lb/>but still attached to electoral districts on<lb/>the other side. The Government in the<lb/>bill before the House endeavored to make<lb/>the boundaries consistent with the inter<lb break="no"/>ests of the settlements. He did not know<lb/>what effect the changes would have upon<lb/>any members, nor did he care in that<lb/>sense. It was fair for him to<lb/>say that much. It was not<lb/>the Government's duty in framing a bill<lb/>of this kind to look after the particular<lb/>interests of individuals. They had con<lb break="no"/>sidered local conditions and endeavored<lb/>to mete out justice to every locality and<lb/>to the country as a whole. The map<lb/>would show no attempt at gerrymander.<lb/>They did not resort to that class of<lb/>political scheming and he hoped that in<lb/>the Territories they would long be able<lb/>to maintain regular electoral boundaries,<lb/>and that it might never be said of our dis<lb break="no"/>tricts as Joe Rymal had said of<lb/>certain eastern divisions, that they could<lb/>safely be worshipped because they were<lb/>like nothing in the heavens above,<lb/>nor in the earth beneath, niegher in<lb/>the water under the earth.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Second reading carried.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">DR. PATRICK'S RESOLUTION<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:PATR1">Dr. Patrick</persName> moved second reading of <lb/>his boundaries resolution which had been<lb/>amended in, and reported by, the com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the whole on the previous day.<lb/>He said again that the resolution was<lb/>not designed to affect internal relations,<lb/>but external relations. It was designed<lb/>as a club to be put i the hands of<lb/>North-West representatives in Parliament<lb/>to be used in behalf of the Territories.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Dr. Brett</persName> thought the resolution was<lb/>inexpedient, unnecessary and inadvisable.<lb/>He failed to see any need for us to gra<lb break="no"/>tuitously offer to give away territory to<lb/>Manitoba and British Columbia. The re<lb break="no"/>solution was inconsistent with the one<lb/>adopted by the House a year ago, which<lb/>declared against any diminution of area.<lb/>Now for no reason we are asked to give<lb/>away territory which one day might be a<lb/>very valuable asset. Why offer only <lb/>territory to the north of Manitoba and<lb/>to the north of British Columbia? Why<lb/>not offer a slice to the west of Manitoba<lb/>and to the east of British Columbia? Why<lb/>limit this generosity? Dr. Brett said the<lb/>time was already anticipated when we<lb/>would haveto make provincial settlement,<lb/>and we should keep out territory intact<lb/>at least until that time. Those remote<lb/>portions would then count as an asset, -<lb/>possibly as an equivalent in some re<lb break="no"/>spects. By all means it should be kept<lb/>until we are compelled to part with it.<lb/>The first clause of the resolution asked<lb/>for out bounds to be defined. It was<lb/>news to him to hear that our limits were<lb/>not defined. Of course the limits of<lb/>any province or provinces to be hereafter<lb/>erected are not defined, but certainly<lb/>the limits of the Territories are defined.<lb/>No definition which we can get so long<lb/>as we remain as Territories will be any<lb/>more fixed that the present definition.<lb/>It was unnecessary to define what is de<lb break="no"/>fined. As to the closing part of the<lb/>resolution, by which the House was ask<lb break="no"/>ed to commit itself to the principle of<lb/>one province for the whole Territories,<lb/>
        
        
            <cb/>
          
          Dr. Brett thought it unnecessary to raise<lb/>that question now and seek to commit<lb/>the House. We all could see the danger of <lb/>disintegration. That disaster had al<lb break="no"/>ready overtaken us so far as related to<lb/>the Yukon. There was teh fear that a<lb/>portion might be annexed to Manitoba.<lb/>That was a disaster we were trying to<lb/>avert, and the danger of which, in his<lb/>opinion, would be increased by the com<lb break="no"/>mittal of the House to the principle of<lb/>one province. The whole resolution was<lb/>unique. Here we were beggin to be<lb/>relieved of territory. Was it an encum<lb break="no"/>brance? Was it not very rich in timber<lb/>and minerals? He believed it was very<lb/>rich. Dr. Brett proposed to move an<lb/>amendment to refer the resolution back<lb/>to committee with instructions to strike<lb/>out all the paragraphs except the first<lb/>two, and to strike out a clause in the <lb/>second paragraph. The resolution would<lb/>then read: -<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               <p>"Whereas it is expedient that the<lb/>
                  "boundary lines between the North-West<lb/>
                  "Territories and the other provinces and<lb/>
                  "terriotries should be finally determined<lb/>
                  "at an early date; and whereas this<lb/>
                  "Legislature denies the right of the Parliam<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada to increase or diminish<lb/>
                  "or otherwise alter the limits of the<lb/>
                  "North-West Territories, without its<lb/>
                  "consent, because it claims for the people<lb/>
                  "it represents equal rights with the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of the Provinces in this respect."</p>
            </quote>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Dr. Brett</persName> moved the amendment ac<lb break="no"/>cordingly, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BANN2">Mr. Bannerman</persName>.</p>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>- What is the resolution?<lb/>
               The hon. gentleman proposes no con<lb break="no"/>clusion.</p>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Dr. Brett</persName>- Yes, that will be the con<lb break="no"/>clusion- the end of it.</p>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> said the amendment<lb/>
               would make the resolution mean nothing.<lb/>
               Did the hon. gentleman wish it to mean<lb/>
               nothing, or was this simply his method<lb/>
               of shunting the matter? He would leave<lb/>
               two bare recitals followed by no conclu<lb break="no"/>sion: Whereas so and so, and whereas<lb/>
               so and so, and there he stopped. Surely<lb/>
               the hon. gentleman was not serious. Such<lb/>
               an inconclusive resolution would be simply<lb/>
               nonsense, to apply no stronger language<lb/>
               to it. The original resolution had occu<lb break="no"/>pied considerable of the time of the<lb/>
               House; it had been considered in com<lb break="no"/>mittee, and definite conclusions had been<lb/>
               reached. Surely they were not to be<lb/>
               seriously asked to adopt such an amend<lb break="no"/>ment which would knock out those logi<lb break="no"/>cal conclusions and suggest no substitu<lb break="no"/>tion. Perhaps the hon. gentleman had<lb/>
               heard of the celebrated English poet,<lb/>
               Coleridge, who was famed as a conversa<lb break="no"/>tionalist. A peculiarity of his conversa<lb break="no"/>tions was that they started anywhere<lb/>
               and ended nowhere. Dr. Brett was ap<lb break="no"/>parently trying to gain similar celebrity<lb/>
               by a resolution which would transform<lb/>
               the proceedings of the Assembly into a<lb/>
               farce.</p>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Dr. Brett</persName> suggested that if the matter<lb/>
               was referred back to committee, the<lb/>
               committee would reach its own conclu<lb break="no"/>sions.</p>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:TIMS1">Mr. Tims</persName>,<lb/>
               moved in amendment to the amendment,<lb/>
               that the resolutions be read six months<lb/>
               hence.</p>
            
            <p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Dr. Brett</persName> withdrew his amendment.</p>
            
               
               
           
            
            <p>The six months' hoist motion was de<lb break="no"/>feated on a division, eleven supporting <lb/>the resolution to ten against. The divi<lb break="no"/>sion was as follows:-<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <p>For the Resolution—Messrs Mitchell, <lb/>Haultain, Ross, Page, Knowling, Boucher, <lb/>Macdonald, Eakin, Dill, Gillis, Patrick.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p>Against—Messrs. Mowat, Tims, Neff, <lb/>Maloney, Bannerman, Brett, Macauley, <lb/>Simpson, Agnew, Lineham.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            <p>The resolution was read a second time <lb/>and concurred in.<lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <!-- GL, 2018-10-31, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day -->     
            
           <!-- <p>PRAIRIE FIRES,<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Prairie and Forest fires bill was <lb/>put through committee, and reported, <lb/>and the House adjourned shortly before <lb/>midnight.<lb/>
            </p>
            <lb/>-->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>