<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgASLA_1903-04-16" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>,
<date when="1903-04-16">16 April 1903</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA"> <editor>William Franklin Kerr</editor>.
<title>The Leader</title>.
<date when="1903-04-23"/>.
<pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="4"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1903-04-23_Page_001.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1903-04-23_Page_004.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-31">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-31">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1903-04-23_Page_001"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1903-04-23_Page_001.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1903-04-23_Page_004"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1903-04-23_Page_004.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="001" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1903-04-23_Page_001.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="num">1</fw>

<fw type="running">THE LEADER.</fw> 


<fw type="running">REGINA, N.W.T., THURSDAY MORNING, APRIL 23, 1903.</fw> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">ASSEMBLY OPENED.</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">First Session of Fifth Legislature <lb/>
Now in Session.</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">SPEECH FROM THE THRONE.</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">Attention Directed to the Constitu<lb break="no"/>tional and Financial Position of <lb/>
the Territories, the Public Domain <lb/>
and Transportion Difficulties— <lb/>
Land Titles System to be Taken <lb/>
Over—Mr. Gillis (Whitewood) Elect<lb break="no"/>ed Speaker.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, April 16th, 1903.</p> 

<p>The first session of the fifth Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive Assembly of the North-West <lb/>
Territories was formally opened this <lb/>
afternoon by His Honor Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor Forget. There was a very <lb/>
large attendance of Members, only six <lb/>
out of a total of thirty-five being ab<lb break="no"/>sent. The attendance of the general <lb/>
public was also large, among the num<lb break="no"/>ber being Mr. C. A. Magrath, a former <lb/>
member of the Executive Council. <lb/>
Many of the fair sex graced the occa<lb break="no"/>sion with their presence, and altogeth<lb break="no"/>er the enlarged, and redecorated <lb/>
chamber presented a rather pretty <lb/>
picture. <lb/></p> 

<p>Sharp on time His Honor the <lb/>
Lieutenant Governor arrived, accom<lb break="no"/>panied by Lt.-Col. Macdonell, D.S.O. <lb/>
as A.D.C., Supt. Wilson and Capt. <lb/>
Gilpin Brown, of the N.W.M.P., and <lb/>
an escort of about fifteen men of the <lb/>
N.W.M.P. under command of Insp. <lb/>
Walke. As is always the case at the <lb/>
opening of the first session of a new <lb/>
Assembly, the usual proceedings were <lb/>
varied somewhat, His Honor, after <lb/>
entering the chamber, retiring after <lb/>
the formal announcement by the <lb/>
Territorial Secretary that he would <lb/>
withhold his message until the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly had elected a Speaker. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">MR. SPEAKER GILLIS.</p> 

<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Premier Haultian</persName>, <lb/>
seconded by <persName ref="pers:BULY1">Mr. Bulyea</persName>, Mr. A. B. <lb/>
Gillis (Whitewood) was unanimously <lb/>
elected Speaker. In moving the <lb/>
appointment of Mr. Gillis, the Premier <lb/>
paid a tribute to Mr. Gillis' services as <lb/>
Deputy Speaker and chairman of com<lb break="no"/>mittee in the last Assembly. His strict <lb/>
attention to the work of the House, <lb/>
his impartiality and knowlege of <lb/>
Parliamentary rules and procedure <lb/>
made him especially fitted for the posi<lb break="no"/>tion. He felt confident from his course <lb/>
in the past that Mr. Gillis would do <lb/>
honor to the high position. <persName ref="pers:GILL3">Mr. Gillis</persName> <lb/>
acknowledged the honor in a few words. <lb/></p> 

<p>His Honor the Lieutenant Governor <lb/>
having re-entered the chamber, and <lb/>
been informed by the Speaker of his <lb/>
election, delivered the following <lb/></p>
    
    <p rendition="simple:centre">SPEECH FROM THE THRONE.</p> 
    
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

<p>Mr. Speaker and Gentlemen of the Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive Assembly:— <lb/>
I have much pleasure in welcoming you to <lb/>
the First Session of the Fifth Legislative Assem<lb break="no"/>bly of the North-West Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p>During the past year, in common with our <lb/>
fellow subjects throughout the Empire, we heard <lb/>
with grief and alarm of the illness of the King, <lb/>
and I am sure that we all rejoiced in his Majes<lb break="no"/>ty's restoration to health and in the successful <lb/>
carrying out of the Coronation ceremonies. <lb/></p> 

<p>The abundant harvest of the past year, the <lb/>
general prosperity of the country and the <lb/>
remarkable growth of the Territories in mater<lb break="no"/>ial wealth and population must all be a source <lb/>
of profound gratification. <lb/></p> 

<p>But these circumstances, gratifying as they <lb/>
are from a national standpoint, have immeas<lb break="no"/>urably increased the duties and responsibilies <lb/>
of the North-West Government and Legislature. <lb/></p> 

<p>For some years past the Government and <lb/>
Legislature have been pressing upon the Feder<lb break="no"/>al Government the absolute necessity for <lb/>
larger powers and revenues if the duties and <lb/>
obligations already imposed upon them by <lb/>
Parliament and the further obligations imposed <lb/>
by new conditions are to be adequately fulfilled. <lb/></p> 

<p>In their latest negotiations with the Federal <lb/>
Government, my Government again forcibly <lb/>
impressed the immediate necessity for the <lb/>
granting of Provincial Institutions to the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. <lb/></p>

<cb/>

<p>Strong representations have also been made <lb/>
with regard to the present financial necessities <lb/>
of the Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p>As a result of these representations a confer<lb break="no"/>ence was held at Ottawa in the month of Feb<lb break="no"/>ruary last between members of my Government <lb/>
and a Sub-Committee of the Privy Council <lb/>
appointed for that purpose. <lb/></p> 

<p>I regret to say that no intimation has yet been <lb/>
given by the Federal Government as to the <lb/>
action they propose to take as a result of the <lb/>
Conference. <lb/></p> 

<p>All the papers relating to these important sub<lb break="no"/>jects will be laid before you, and you will be <lb/>
asked to take such action as may seem desirable <lb/>
to further enforce the just claims of the Territor<lb break="no"/>ies. <lb/></p> 

<p>I feel it to be my duty to ask your attention <lb/>
to the important question of transportation. <lb/></p> 

<p>This question is partially bound up with the <lb/>
Provincial question, but some of its larger <lb/>
phases falls more peculiarly within the Federal <lb/>
domain. <lb/></p> 

<p>In view of the transportation conditions pre<lb break="no"/>vailing since the close of lake navigation last <lb/>
year, and which threaten to continue in a more <lb/>
aggravated forum during the year to come, I <lb/>
feel justified in asking you to consider the <lb/>
advisability of making some representations to <lb/>
Parliament with regard to a question which so <lb/>
vitally affects the welfare of the Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p>The claim which has been made on the part <lb/>
of the Territories to the public domain will also <lb/>
justify an expression of opinion on your part <lb/>
with regard to further alienations of the public <lb/>
lands of the Territories for railway or other <lb/>
purposes except actual settlement. <lb/></p> 

<p>In response to a request by my Government <lb/>
the Federal Government have consented to ex<lb break="no"/>tend the jurisdiction of the Legislature to the <lb/>
important subject of land titles, and legislation <lb/>
to that effect has been promised at the present <lb/>
session of Parliament. This important exten<lb break="no"/>sion of your powers will necessitate legislative <lb/>
provision for the maintenance and control of <lb/>
the land titles system, and a measure for that  <lb/>
purpose will be presented to you. Federal <lb/>
legislation has also been promised which will <lb/>
give to the Legislative Assembly the right to <lb/>
fully control the qualification of its members, to <lb/>
legislate with regard to the constitution and <lb/>
jurisdiction of Civil Courts and other matters <lb/>
at present withheld from you by the provisions <lb/>
of the North-West Territories Acts. Measures <lb/>
necessitated by these further extensions of <lb/>
your powers will also be submitted to you. <lb/></p> 

<p>Your consideration will also be asked to <lb/>
Bills relating to Mechanics' Liens, Drainage, <lb/>
Mutual Fire Insurance and Succession Duties. <lb/></p> 

<p>Your attention will be invited to Bills to <lb/>
amend the law relating to Civil procedure and <lb/>
the sale of intoxicating liquor, and a Bill to <lb/>
amend and consolidate as amended the law <lb/>
relating to Brands. <lb/></p> 

<p>A statement of the receipts and expenditures <lb/>
of the past year and the estimates of expendi<lb break="no"/>ture for the current year will he laid before <lb/>
you. <lb/></p> 

<p>I now leave you to your deliberations with <lb/>
every confidence that your labors, under Divine <lb/>
Providence, will be directed to the advantage <lb/>
and welfare of the Territories. <lb/></p> 

    </quote>

<p>After His Honor had retired, and Mr. <lb/>
Speaker Gillis having taken the chair <lb/>
amid cheers, <persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Premier Haultain</persName> moved <lb/>
for leave to introduce a Bill to amend <lb/>
Chapter 46 of the Consoldiated Ordin<lb break="no"/>ances of 1898 regarding marriage. <lb/>
Leave having been granted the Bill <lb/>
was introduced and read a first time. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> moved that the Speech <lb/>
of His Honor be taken into considera<lb break="no"/> </p> 

<!--<p>(Continued on page 4.) <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="004" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1903-04-23_Page_004.jpg"/> <lb/>
    
    <fw type="num">4</fw>

<fw type="running">THE LEADER THURSDAY MORNING, APRIL 23, 1908.</fw> 
</div>
<div type="debate">
<head rendition="simple:centre">ASSEMBLY OPENED.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">(Continued from page 1.)</p> 

<p>tion on Monday next. Agreed. <lb/></p> 

<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Premier Haultain</persName> and <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BULY1">Mr. Bulyea</persName> the following Members <lb/>
were appointed a special committee to <lb/>
draft the select standing committees <lb/>
of the House: Messrs. McDonald, Ben<lb break="no"/>nett, Brown, DeVeber, Meyers, and <lb/>
the mover and seconder. Agreed. <lb/></p> 

<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Premier Haultain</persName> the <lb/>
house then adjourned at 3.15 pm. <lb/></p> 
    
    
    <!-- IC, 2018-10-31, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

<!--<p>MONDAY, April 20th. <lb/></p> 

<p>The House did not sit over an hour <lb/>
today but in that space of time consid<lb break="no"/>erable business was transacted and the <lb/>
Address in reply to the Speech from <lb/>
the Throne passed. The Speaker took <lb/>
the Chair at 2.45 p.m. Petitions were <lb/>
presented as follows:— <lb/></p> 

<p>By Dr. DeVeber asking for amend<lb break="no"/>ments to the Ordinance incorporating <lb/>
the Galt Hospital; also asking for <lb/>
amendments to the Municipal Ordi<lb break="no"/>nance to enlarge the powers of Leth<lb break="no"/>bridge. <lb/></p> 

<p>By Mr. Shera asking for the incor<lb break="no"/>poration of the Bishop of the Russian <lb/>
Greek Catholic Orthodox Church. <lb/></p> 

<p>The following Bills were introduced <lb/>
and read a first time:— <lb/></p> 

<p>By Mr. Young–To incorporate the <lb/>
Western Canada Historical Society; to <lb/>
amend the city charter of Calgary; to <lb/>
amend the Ordinance to incorporate <lb/>
the Calgary General Hospital. <lb/></p> 

<p>By A. S. Smith—To amend the Ordi<lb break="no"/>nance incorporating Moosomin. <lb/></p> 

<p>By Premier Haultain—Respecting <lb/>
Foreign Companies; Voluntary Wind<lb break="no"/>ing-Up of Joint Stock Companies; to <lb/>
Secure Uniform Conditions in Policies <lb/>
of Fire Insurance; respecting Mutual <lb/>
Fire Insurance; to provide for the <lb/>
payment of Succession Duties in Cer<lb break="no"/>tain Cases; respecting Notaries Public. <lb/></p> 

<p>By Mr. G. W. Brown to amend the <lb/>
Ordinance incorporating Regina Hos<lb break="no"/>pital. <lb/></p> 

<p>Before the Orders of the Day were <lb/>
called Premier Haultain laid on the <lb/>
Table of the House the correspondence <lb/>
with the Dominion authorities relating <lb/>
to the Memorial of the Assembly of <lb/>
May 2nd, 1900, upon the financial and <lb/>
constitutional position of the Territor<lb break="no"/>ies; also the report of the Attorney-<lb break="yes"/>General's department with reference to <lb/>
liquor licences. <lb/></p> 

<p>THE ADDRESS IN REPLY. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Address in Reply to the Speech <lb/>
from the Throne was then moved by <lb/>
Mr. Finlay (Medicine Hat). After <lb/>
touching briefly on the King's illness <lb/>
and Coronation, the general prosperity <lb/>
of the Territories and the consequent <lb/>
increase in responsibilities devolving <lb/>
on the Assembly, the speaker referred <lb/>
to the efforts made by the Territorial <lb/>
Government to secure provincial auton<lb break="no"/>omy and failing in that, a largely in<lb break="no"/>creased grant. He declared himself <lb/>
as being strongly in favor of provincial <lb/>
autonomy and stated that he could not <lb/>
understand why the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment should persist in refusing to give <lb/>
it. He would not uphold the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in doing wrong. He was there as <lb/>
a North-West man to uphold the <lb/>
rights of the North-West. The Dom<lb break="no"/>inion Government was doing a great <lb/>
injustice to the North-West by not <lb/>
granting what was their due. They <lb/>
had by giving the Territories ten <lb/>
members in the House of Commons <lb/>
acknowledged that there was a popula<lb break="no"/>tion of 250,000 in this country, and why <lb/>
then, asked the speaker, do they not <lb/>
grant us provincial autonomy; why <lb/>
not give us a larger grant? After <lb/>
touching on the question of transpor<lb break="no"/>tation, the public domain, tranfer of <lb/>
the land titles offices, etc., Mr. Finlay <lb/>
declared in conclusion that he would be <lb/>
thoroughly independent in treating all <lb/>
questions and he hoped the House <lb/>
would continue to carry out that inde-<lb break="maybe"/>

<cb/>

pendent spirit which it had maintained <lb/>
to the present time. <lb/></p> 

<p>MR. MACNUTT SECONDS. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. MacNutt (Saltcoats) in seconding <lb/>
the Address in Reply said he would <lb/>
not deal with the many questions re<lb break="no"/>ferred to in the Speech as in the later <lb/>
discussions in the House these would <lb/>
be fully dealt with. On the subject of <lb/>
provincial autonomy, however, he ex<lb break="no"/>pressed himselt strongly, and said that <lb/>
the sessions of the Territorial Assembly <lb/>
should not be dependent on the sessions <lb/>
of Parliament at Ottawa. The corres<lb break="no"/>pondence which had been laid on the <lb/>
Table of the House showed the strenu<lb break="no"/>ous efforts made by the local Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to secure autonomy and he be<lb break="no"/>lieved in keeping up the correspondence <lb/>
until the Dominion Government be<lb break="no"/>came so weary of it that they would <lb/>
grant the request. It was an injustice <lb/>
for the Dominion Government to send <lb/>
in immigrants from all parts of the <lb/>
earth by tens and tens of thousands <lb/>
and not provide the wherewithal to <lb/>
give these people educational, trans<lb break="no"/>portation and other facilities necessary <lb/>
in the country. On the question of <lb/>
transportation Mr. MacNutt said the <lb/>
natural resources of his part of the <lb/>
country could not be taken advan<lb break="no"/>tage of for lack of the necessary <lb/>
facilities. <lb/></p> 

<p>PREMIER HAULTAIN. <lb/></p> 

<p>Premier Haultain was the next <lb/>
speaker. He said that under ordinary <lb/>
circumstances he would not be address<lb break="no"/>ing the House just then. The usual <lb/>
procedure was for the leader of the <lb/>
Opposition to follow the mover and <lb/>
seconder and make what criticisms he <lb/>
had to offer on the policy of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, and then the leader of the <lb/>
Government spoke in reply. He took <lb/>
the absence of any such speech from <lb/>
the leader of the Opposition, or his <lb/>
representtive, as significant, and as <lb/>
implying that as the Speech from the <lb/>
Throne outlined subjects of such over<lb break="no"/>whelming importance to the Territories <lb/>
the Opposition were going to join with <lb/>
all the other Members in trying to <lb/>
come to some united action, on those <lb/>
important subjects. (Cheers.) This <lb/>
condition augured well for the succes-<lb break="maybe"/>ful meeting of the difficulties of the <lb/>
unfortunate position in which they <lb/>
found themselves at present. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Premier then congratulated the <lb/>
mover and seconder on the able man<lb break="no"/>ner in which they had performed their <lb/>
duties and went on to speak of the <lb/>
King's illness and Coronation. He <lb/>
dwelt on the significance of the latter <lb/>
ceremony and amid hearty cheers <lb/>
spoke eloquently of Britain as a free <lb/>
land for a free people. While it <lb/>
had been a great year in Imperial <lb/>
events it had also been a momentous <lb/>
year for the Territories. In speaking <lb/>
of their growth and added responsibili<lb break="no"/>ties they did not do so in a pessimistic <lb/>
or hopeless spirit. All they asked was <lb/>
that they should be in a position to <lb/>
meet those responsibilities, and he <lb/>
believed they were fully as capable of <lb/>
doing so as the people in any other <lb/>
portion of Canada. This was in fact <lb/>
the burden of the Speech from the <lb/>
Throne. It would be an unfortunate <lb/>
thing if the people, and Government <lb/>
and Legislature of the Territories <lb/>
should have to approach the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada with the methods of <lb/>
the unfortunate widow, as referred to <lb/>
by the hon. member for Saltcoats. It <lb/>
would be unfortunate for the Dominion <lb/>
Government to be placed in the posi<lb break="no"/>tion of the unjust judge, forced to <lb/>
recognise the widow's rights by reason <lb/>
of her importunities. More forcible <lb/>
means than those employed by the <lb/>
Territorial Government to gain these <lb/>
rights could not have been used than <lb/>
were used. They had resorted to <lb/>
everything short of force. <lb/></p> 

<p>NEGOTIATIONS FOR LARGER GRANT. <lb/></p> 

<p>The financial question, said the <lb/>
Premier, is one of the immedite <lb/>
present. We have a plain duty to the <lb/>
people at the present time. In the <lb/>
financial statement we submitted to <lb/>
the Federal Government we took the <lb/>
ground that the point we had reached <lb/>
had been arrived at largely through <lb/>
the want of consideration paid to our <lb/>
requests made in previous years. The <lb/>
financial position has been growing <lb/>
more aggravated and difficult for the <lb/>
past ten years and our needs have been <lb/>
growing rapidly year by year. In our <lb/>
negotiations with the Dominion <lb/>
authorities we set forth that it was <lb/>
absolutely necessary in order to carry <lb/>
on the work for this year, that is the <lb/>
Dominion fiscal year beginning 1st of <lb/>
July next, that we be given the sum of <lb/>
$880,000 and $250,000 as supplementary <lb/>
to meet the expenditures for the <lb/>
current year to June 30th next. New <lb/>
settlers are coming in, largely through <lb/>
the efforts of the immigration move<lb break="no"/>ment, and it would be unfortunate to <lb/>
meet them with a large tax bill on <lb/>
their arrival. We pointed out that <lb/>
unless the Government provided for <lb/>
the necessary roads, bridges, schools, <lb/>
etc., the people must pay additional <lb/>
taxes. <lb/></p> 

<p>ADVANCES ON CAPITAL ACCOUNT. <lb/></p> 

<p>I saw the other day in THE LEADER, <lb/>
continued the Premier, a telegram <lb/>
announcing in general terms the action <lb/>
to be taken by the Government. As <lb/>
yet we have not been officially inform<lb break="no"/>ed what action the Government pro<lb break="no"/>pose to take. In THE LEADER, how<lb break="no"/>ever, I saw that a supplementary <lb/>
amount would be voted to meet the <lb/>
overdraft for this year, and that <lb/>
instead of a larger grant being granted <lb/>
we would be given something on capi<lb break="no"/>tal account. I would like to inform <lb/>
the House and country that the Terri<lb break="no"/>torial Government did not ask for <lb/>
anything on capital account. (Cheers.) <lb/>
The suggestion of a capital advance <lb/>
runs through all the correspondence <lb/>
on this subject for a great many years. <lb/>
We have pointed out that the whole <lb/>
burden of capital expenditure has been <lb/>
thrown on the current revenues of this <lb/>
country, which we claimed were <lb/>
inadequate even as revenue. But we <lb/>
did not ask for an advance on capital <lb/>
account. It is bad enough to have to <lb/>
try to meet expenditures which are <lb/>
purely capital expenditures out of <lb/>
revenue but it would be still worse to <lb/>
have money which really belongs to us <lb/>
as revenue chargeable to capital. <lb/>

<cb/>

PROVINCIAL AUTONOMY. <lb/></p> 

<p>With regard to the provincial ques<lb break="no"/>tion itself, we have stated it as clearly <lb/>
as possible. We are not theorists,but <lb/>
sincere, practical men making a prac<lb break="no"/>tical proposition with regard to a <lb/>
practical question. We stand on <lb/>
the principle that this country must <lb/>
mange its own affairs. In a letter to <lb/>
the Minister of the Interior, dated 31st <lb/>
January last, I said: " We demand <lb/>
that system of government under <lb/>
which we shall have as full opportuni<lb break="no"/>ies for the exercise of our citizenship <lb/>
as our fellow-citizens in the provinces. <lb/>
The local Government and Legislature <lb/>
should have full and free scope of <lb/>
action left to them on many subjects <lb/>
which relate to the prosperity and <lb/>
happiness of the country and the <lb/>
North-West will not be satisfied until <lb/>
this is granted." That, said Mr. Haul-<lb break="yes"/>tain, is the position we take. <lb/></p> 

<p>TRANSPORTATION DIFFICULTIES. <lb/></p> 

<p>With regard to the transportation <lb/>
question Mr. Haultain said that condi<lb break="no"/>tions had reached such a point in this <lb/>
country, and so vitally affected the <lb/>
people, that he thought the Assembly <lb/>
was justified in " resoluting " a little on <lb/>
a question which was outside their <lb/>
jurisdiction. Everyone knew what <lb/>
the conditions have been and are and <lb/>
no one could tell what conditions <lb/>
would be within the next few months <lb/>
or during the year. The present condi<lb break="no"/>tions were largely due to the fact that <lb/>
the existing railway companies had <lb/>
not lived up to their contracts. He <lb/>
quoted the C.P.R. contract to the <lb/>
effect that the company was to forever <lb/>
maintain efficiency and work their <lb/>
railway. He did not need to elaborate <lb/>
on the fact that the company have not <lb/>
efficiently maintained or run their line <lb/>
during the past two years. He was <lb/>
afraid that while rival railway comp<lb break="no"/>anies are struggling for rights-of-way <lb/>
and covering grounds with posts and <lb/>
flags where railways would not be <lb/>
contstructed for years, or while they <lb/>
were after subsidies at Ottawa or <lb/>
waiting until the necessary power was <lb/></p> 

<p>(Continued on page 8.) <lb/></p> <lb/>
<milestone type="unknown"/>
-->
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>