<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgAS_LA_1897-12-06"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>, <date when="1897-12-06">6 December 1897</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA">
          

               <editor>Walter Scott</editor>.
          
         
          <title>The Leader</title>.
                    

          <date when="1897-12-09"/>.  
          

           <pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>: <publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="4"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1897-12-09_Page_004.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
      
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-06-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="The_Leader_1897-12-09_Page_004">
         <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1897-12-09_Page_004.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="004" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1897-12-09_Page_004.jpg"/>
         <fw type="num">4</fw> <fw type="running">THE LEADER, THURSDAY EVENING, DECEMBER 9 1897</fw>
          


<head rendition="simple:right">MONDAY, Dec, 6.</head>


            <p>At 2:40 o'clock Mr. Speaker took the <lb/>chair. </p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL1">Mr. HAULTAIN</persName> moved that the <lb/>House resolve into Committee of Supply, <lb/>and made a speech of about one and three <lb/>quarter hours duration,-a clear, plain, <lb/>important and well-delivered statement <lb/>of the financial position and prospects of <lb/>the Territories and the policy of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of which he is leader upon the <lb/>business in hand and upon some business <lb/>which they propose to take in hand. <lb/>(Only an outline—the tenor, so to speak <lb/>—of the debate can be reported in THE <lb/>LEADER this week, We hope we may <lb/>later succeed in an arrangement to pub<lb break="no"/>lish a verbatim report cf Mr. Haultain's <lb/>address and generous synopses of the <lb/>other speeches made on the occasion.)  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>In opening the Premier again explain<lb break="no"/>ed the reasons for the change in the fin<lb break="no"/>ancial year, making it, necessay now to <lb/>vete supplies for 16 months. They <lb/>could absolutely estimate receipts only to <lb/>1st July, 1898 Qf, course they could <lb/>hope that the Dominion vote for 98-99 <lb/>would not be less than this year's, and <lb/>could reasonably expect that it might be <lb/>greater, but it would not be safe to vote<lb/>
supplies on the hope of an increase. So <lb/>they had, to be counted upon with reas <lb/>onable absoluteness, the grant voted this <lb/>year, and a calculation of receiving for <lb/>the last half of '1898 a proportionate <lb/>amount, besides the local revenues for <lb/>1898 (from licenses, etc., which were <lb/>estinated at $32,000 On 1st Sept , the <lb/>beginning of he financial year, they had a <lb/>balance of $98,080 remaining from the<lb/>
      
<cb/>

first half of the Dominion 97-98 grant. <lb/>Calculating at the rate of this year's grant <lb/>they would get for the two halves of 1898 <lb/>$282,879. Add to this $32,000. estimated <lb/>local revenues, and the total is $412,999.<lb break="no"/>00 . They had already voted $30,260 in <lb/>preliminary Estimates for three months <lb/>salaries and current expenses. This left <lb/>$382,649 to be voted now. The Esti <lb/>mates brought down amounted to only <lb/>$340955. The remaining $41,604 they <lb/>proposed to leave to be voted in Supple<lb break="no"/>mentary Estimates at the 1898 session, <lb/>which would be required for the cost of <lb/>the session ($15,500) for provision for <lb/>the general elections to immediately fol<lb break="no"/>low ($15,000) leaving in round numbers <lb/>$10,000 for contingencies and making <lb/>further provision for agricultural socie<lb break="no"/>ties in the fall of 1898, etc. Any increase <lb/>which they might procure in the Ottawa <lb/>grant would also have to be voted next <lb/>year in Supplementary Estimates.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>ALL PLAIN FIGURING.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>This was the first time in their history <lb/>that all the money expected to be avail<lb break="no"/>able was really available. In nearly every <lb/>prior year some portion of the sum had <lb/>been withdrawn for sume purpose. For <lb/>instance, one year $45,000 was taken for <lb/>relief work which necessarily disorganized <lb/>their finalices. This year there were no <lb/>outstanding accounts, no old claims, no <lb/>overdrafts, no district votes to be read: <lb/>justed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>THE SAME OLD SERVICES.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>The Estimates were largely the same as <lb/>in previous years, and necessarily so. <lb/>They had to meet the same services, al<lb break="no"/>though they found some of them under <lb/>new names.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>After dwelling upon the change in or<lb break="no"/>ganization, the Premier said the House <lb/>would see that the pledge given at Moose <lb/>Jaw, that the machinery would not be <lb/>made dearer, was strictly observed. <lb/>There were a few increases in salaries, <lb/>which would have been made if there had <lb/>been no change in organization. These <lb/>were increases justified by new duties, in<lb break="no"/>creasing responsibilities, and more effi<lb break="no"/>ciency in the work done. Practically the <lb/>only increases in staff were in the Public <lb/>Works Department, where they provided <lb/>one stenographer, who would do duty for <lb/>several departments; and one official, who <lb/>would be Clerk of Assembly and Asst. <lb/>Secretary, and who was in reality only <lb/>transferred from the office of the Lieut.-<lb/>Governor (Mr. Gordon) He had been <lb/>formerly appointed by Federal Statute, <lb/>had been Clerk of Assembly, and Official <lb/>Secretary of the Governor, and in reality <lb/>held a position analagous to that of the <lb/>Grand Vizier in an Oriental dominion. <lb/>Practically this official was transferred to <lb/>the Assembly, and the salary attached <lb/>was also transferred.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Haultain said he would not discuss <lb/>the Estimates in detail. Most of the <lb/>items were familiar and could be discuss <lb/>ed in committee. They would notice the <lb/>vote for Administration of Justice, which <lb/>vote carried a significance and emphasiz<lb break="no"/>ed the change in form of government— <lb/>a change from Executive Committee to <lb/>Executive Council. A necessary adjunct <lb/>to any proper Council was a legal member, <lb/>who was absolutely indispensable, and <lb/>without whom no government could con <lb/>duct its business. He was the personal <lb/>legal adviser of the Lieut. Governor. The <lb/>administration of the liquor license law <lb/>came under this head.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>LAW WILL BE ENFORCED.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Premier made lengthy reference <lb/>to the difficulty of securing enforcement <lb/>of the liquor law, and the inability ef the <lb/>Inspectors to prevent breaches. He in <lb/>dicated that the Government were bound <lb/>to have the law respected. He said he <lb/>would not explain fully the course that <lb/>was intended, but hinted very plainly <lb/>that they had proposed to resort to the <lb/>means that was found necessary in other <lb/>provinces, and use the only tool that <lb/>proved to be effective in this regard, <lb/>namely detectives. He said that the <lb/>Government, and himself, were determin <lb/>ed to strain every resource to secure the <lb/>observance of the law, and if, after using <lb/>every known means, they failed,—if they <lb/>found the licensees would not respect the <lb/>privileges granted to them by the law, <lb/>and could not be compelled to, then <lb/>there would be no recourse but to cease <lb/>to grant any privileges by law.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>PUBLIC WORKS.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Haultain went minutely into the <lb/>idea upon which the Government worked <lb/>out the Public Works Estimates. They <lb/>had quit the division between Electoral <lb/>districts. Taking the whole Territories <lb/>as the district, they attempted to meet <lb/>the most immediate and urgent require<lb break="no"/>ments. This system had been adopted <lb/>by the House last year on the suggestion <lb/>of those responsible to the House. Re<lb break="no"/>garding the increase of staff—the creation <lb/>of the Department—no apology was neces<lb break="no"/>sary. The Department was needed to <lb/>take the place of the 29 Ministers of Pub<lb break="no"/>lic Works, engineers, surveyors, overseers, <lb/>—each embodying the duties of all— <lb/>whose valuable services they had been <lb/>deprived of last year by the change in <lb/>system of dealing with public works.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>NO DOMINION PARTY LINES.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>He touched on the party line question <lb/>much in the same terms as in his Moose <lb/>Jaw speach.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>After dealing at some length with the <lb/>question of Education, and touching upon <lb/>the matter of Consolidation of the Ordin<lb break="no"/>ances, the Premier turned to consider <lb/>the present position of the Territories <lb/>constitutionally and financially, saying <lb/>that the position was now more unique <lb/>probably than ever before, and demanded <lb/>most serious consideration. He said that <lb/>the new duties, increased responsibilities <lb/>and enlarged jurisdiction, involved much <lb/>heavier financial burdens, and Parliament <lb/>had always been more generous in ex<lb break="no"/>tending the legislative jurisdiction than <lb/>in extending legislative grants Consti<lb break="no"/>tutionally me have approached close to <lb/>provincial basis, but financialiy we are <lb/>a long distance from that basis. Still <lb/>there had been progress that was not <lb/>wholly unsatisfactory. In 1891 92 the <lb/>grant was $158,000. In 1897-98, the <lb/>grant is $282,900—an increase of $125,<lb break="no"/>000 in five years, or an increase of 80 <lb/>per cent since 1892,-not a small actual <lb/>or proportionate increase. But we are <lb/>entitled to far more. After pointing <lb/>out some of the difficulties in the way of <lb/>Territorial representatives at Ottawa, and <lb/>the difficulties which the Government <lb/>itself had to confront when they proposed <lb/>to increase the grant to the West, Mr. <lb/>Haultain said that no man would ever go <lb/>on a mission to Ottawa with a very wel <lb/>justified hope that he was going to get all <lb/>he wanted and would ask for. So far as <lb/>the present Minister of Interior was con<lb break="no"/>cerned, he said they had found him quite <lb/>wiling and capable of entering into and <lb/>comprehending the position of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories—he had appeared most ready to <lb/>hear what they had to say, and to give <lb/>all the encouragement in his power to <lb/>give. The unfortunate attitude of Par<lb break="no"/>liament was the principal reason which <lb/>prevented the Territories getting what<lb/>
we are entitled to. It was to be hoped <lb/>that the new developments—the Yukon <lb/>advertisement, etc.—would tend to effect <lb/>a change in the attitude of Parliament, <lb/>and create a greater and more intelligent <lb/>interest in the West. A good indication <lb/>was the fact that le: ding newspapers, -  <lb/>organs or both parties—were coming <lb/>interested,<lb/>
            </p>

 <cb/>


            <p>We have now a well-defined constitu<lb break="no"/>tional position and very large powers and  responsibilities, but no fixed or adequate <lb/>Income. Parliament had continued to <lb/>manufacture law-making and administra<lb break="no"/>tive machinery without adding the money <lb/>to carry it on.<lb/>
               <lb/>Last year the Assembly <lb/>came to the conclusion that it was useless <lb/>to hope for any increase on the present -<lb/> basis, and passed a memorial asking Par<lb break="no"/>liament to compute our grant on a Pro- . <lb/>vincial basis—not to make a province but <lb/>to make up the grant as the provincial <lb/>subsidies are computed—so much per <lb/>capita, so much for debt (to offset the <lb/>portion of the interest of the debts of the <lb/>old provinces which we contribute) so <lb/>much for government, and so much in<lb/>
               <lb/>lieu of lands.<lb/>On this basis we were <lb/>
               <lb/>entitled to $446,000.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <lb/>The Executive <lb/>pressed this Memorial at Ottawa. But <lb/>they were met with the statement that<lb/>the Dominion was paying for many ser<lb/>
vices in the Territories which were paid <lb/>for in the provinces by the provinces, <lb/>and were told that if they wanted to be <lb/>treated on a provincial basis they should <lb/>have to undertake all the services which<lb/>
the provinces carry on.<lb/>
That was cer<lb break="no"/>tailly embarrassing, because no Member <lb/>of the Executive or of the House, he <lb/>might say, had ever gone minutely into <lb/>the whole question,-and no Member <lb/>was in a position to sit down at once, or in <lb/>a week, and make anything like an accu<lb break="no"/>rate computation.<lb/>
They were thus<lb/>
forced back to, the position of making <lb/>a statement of requirements, as a basis <lb/>for the estimate of grant.<lb/>they made a detailed estimate which came to just<lb/>
about the amount asked in the Memorial <lb/>But the Gevernment was not prepared<lb/>
to go that length.<lb/>The Memorial was<lb/>more effective in regard to the powers<lb/>
asked. They were given practically all that<lb/>
was asked in that regard, excepting con<lb break="no"/>trol of registry offices, and one or two <lb/>minor things They did not particularly <lb/>press for the registry offices, not know<lb break="no"/>ing precisely what the effect would be <lb/>financially. <lb/>But they knew now, and<lb/>
               <lb/>they would follow up the Memorial, and<lb/>
he had every hope they would secure<lb/>
control of the registration system, to the<lb/>
advantage of the Assembly, and to the <lb/>advantage of the people in the way of<lb/>
having the cost of tranfers reduced.<lb/>
They hoped also to be given charge of <lb/>the irrigation system which is a matter<lb/>
purely of local and domestic concern.<lb/>
            </p>



















            <p>THE ALTERNATIVE.<lb/>
            </p>


            <p>The Premier went on to say that ad<lb/>ditional grants, additional financial recog <lb/>nition, were necessary.<lb/>
He said that if <lb/>we could not keep up the development<lb/>
in the subsidy to keep pace with the de<lb break="no"/>velopment in power, there was only one <lb/>alternative. <lb/>The practical meaning of <lb/>his statement was that if the Dominion <lb/>refused to give the Territories as favor<lb/>  <lb/>able grants as are given the provinces,<lb/>
then the only alternative was for the <lb/>Territories to take its position as a pro<lb/>vince and obtain a proper financial stand<lb break="no"/>ing. He made the plain declaration that <lb/>if due financial recognition is not given,<lb/>
his Government are prepared to take<lb/>
the lead in a movement for the estab <lb/>lishment of the Territories as a province. <lb/>Hitherto we had received enough money <lb/>to meet the necessary services, and pro<lb/>
bably, all things considered, were better<lb/>
off than if there had already been pro<lb break="no"/>vincial establishment. But we have now <lb/>reached the jumping off place, and can <lb/>go very little farther without becoming a <lb/>province as far as regards power, and <lb/>must have adequate revenues to meet the <lb/>enlarging burdens and responsibilities. <lb/>If the arbitrary amounts voted by Par<lb break="no"/>liament are to be based not upon present <lb/>requirements but upon the worn-out esti<lb break="no"/>mates of earlier requirements, then he <lb/>and his Government will go in for full <lb/>provincial establishment in order to get <lb/>financial recognition. <lb/>He next proceeded to show that the <lb/>question of terms is a very weighty and <lb/>involved question. At present the Do <lb/>minion is m eting what may be termed <lb/>local or provincial services—Justice, <lb/>Dairying, Public Works, Surveys, etc.— <lb/>including the Assembly Vote, to the <lb/>amount of $557,000,—a larger amount <lb/>than was claimed in the Memorial. Yet <lb/>that amount did not represent what the <lb/>Territories are entitled to, and how to <lb/>obtain our rights was the question. They <lb/>had memorialized, and excursionized, and <lb/>made representation after representation, <lb/>and largely without avail in a compara. <lb/>tive sense. When they started out for <lb/>provincial establishment, there would be <lb/>difficult questions to face, — questions <lb/>serious enough to give sobering effect to <lb/>any discussion. . There was no definite <lb/>basis of calculation - no rigid arithmeti<lb break="no"/>cal plan to follow. The subjects of debt <lb/>and ands were purely political, and it <lb/>really came down to a question of the <lb/>amount of politcal pressure they could <lb/>bring to bear.  It was not a matter of <lb/>paper and pencil. It was not a question <lb/>easy of solution Take the matter of <lb/>debt. How much does the Territories <lb/>contribute to the increst of provincial <lb/>debts  and how much will the Dominion<lb/>
        

<cb/>

wish to change back as an offset to the <lb/>amounts spent for opening up this coun<lb break="no"/>try? How much is to be claimed on ac<lb break="no"/>count of lands ? These were questions <lb/>which could not be settled in a day. <lb/>There were, however, only the two alter<lb break="no"/>natives—go on and obtain larger finan<lb/>
cial recognition as we are, -and if we <lb/>can not get it, take the only step open, <lb/>and become a province—one prevince of <lb/>the whole Territories as they stand to<lb break="no"/>day, not cut off in any portion, either <lb/>in the north (Yukon) or in the east to <lb/>the benefit of  Manitoba, one strong<lb/>
province, with all the resources of its gold <lb/>mines in the Yukon, and the golden <lb/>wheat fields of  Eastern Assiniboia, which <lb/>if they do no yield nuggets, yet do yield<lb/>
40 bus to the acre .  <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>EXEMPTED LANDS.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr., Haultain next went thoroughly <lb/>into the railway and colonization com. <lb/>panies exempted lands question, show<lb break="no"/>ing just how these lands are juggled with <lb/>and kept from liability to taxation to the <lb/>detriment of the settlers, of school dis<lb break="no"/>tricts, statute labor districts, to the <lb/>country as a whole. He spoke also of <lb/>the townsite grievance and, quoting Pre <lb/>mier, Laurier's declaration against ex<lb break="no"/>empting lands which are held for specula<lb break="no"/>tion, (made at Moose Jaw in 1894) ex<lb break="no"/>pressed the hope that this grievance <lb/>should speedily be removed. He said <lb/>he attached every importance to Mr. <lb/>Laurier's statement. Regarding the ex<lb break="no"/>empted lands he said that the Executive <lb/>proposed to take energetic action to have <lb/>these companies (which were granted no <lb/>exemption by Parliament, and which are <lb/>holding millions of acres free from taxa<lb break="no"/>tion and locked up from settlement) <lb/>forced to select their earned lands and <lb/>take out patents as soon as the lands are <lb/>reserved from settlement. He thought <lb/>it might be well for the House to make <lb/>some representation the matter. He <lb/>gave statistics. We shall at this time <lb/>quote only a sample. The Q. &amp; Long <lb/>Lake Ry. Co. are antitled to, or have earned <lb/>1,625,000 acres. They have had reserved, <lb/>to allow of selection, 2,743 591 acres. <lb/>In excess of 1,698 acres, which they have <lb/>sold and which will be liable to taxation <lb/>only when the purchase price is paid in <lb/>full (for by the arrangament not until <lb/>then does the patent issue) they have <lb/>selected none The total acreage to be <lb/>earned by railways built in the Territories <lb/>is 5,267,000. There are reserved <lb/>5,793,000 There have been earned <lb/>4,600,000; selected 2,400,000; patented <lb/>204,812. A worse side of the case was <lb/>the lands held by companies which have <lb/>not built a mile of railway in the Terri<lb/>tories Territorial lands were granted for <lb/>Manitoba railways. He deaſt also with <lb/>the C.P.R. lands exemptions, which he <lb/>said could not be settled yet, but should [...]<lb/>
            </p>

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>