<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgASLA_1896-11-05" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>,
<date when="1896-11-05" cert="medium">5 November 1896</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA"> <editor>Walter Scott</editor>.
<title>The Leader</title>. <date from="1896-11-05" to="1896-11-19"/>.
<pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="5"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1896-11-05_Page_005_copy.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-12-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-12-14">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1896-11-05_Page_005"> <graphic url="final/hocr/.../The_Leader_1896-11-05_Page_005.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="5" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1896-11-05_Page_005.jpg"/>
  
  <fw type="num">5</fw>
  
  <fw type="running">THE LEADER, THURSDAY EVENING, NOVEMBER 5, 1896.</fw>
    
    <head rendition="simple:centre">THE BILL OF RIGHTS.</head>
    <head rendition="simple:centre">The Assembly's Constitu<lb break="no"/>tional Memorial.</head>
      <head>Reasons Given for an Increase of <lb/>
      Constitutional Powers—An <lb/>
      Executive Council vs. Execu<lb break="no"/>tive Committee—Statement of <lb/>
    Present Shortage of Moneys.</head>
  
  <p><supplied><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Anonymous</persName></supplied></p>
    
    <p>The following is the Memorial to the <lb/>
      Governor-General in Council, adopted by <lb/>
      the Assembly, and which gave rise to the <lb/>
      "secession" debate which will be pub<lb break="no"/>lished later:
    </p>
    <p>
      The Legislature Assembly begs leave to <lb/>
      present to Your Excellency a statement <lb/>
      of their constitutional and financial posi<lb break="no"/>tion, and to suggest such amendments in <lb/>
      the North-West Territorial Act and other <lb/>
      Acts affecting the Territories and such in<lb break="no"/>crease in their grant or subsidy, as will <lb/>
      enable them to fulfil the duties they are <lb/>
      called upon to perform for the proper <lb/>
      government of the North-West Territo<lb break="no"/>ries in local matters. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      They beg to remind you that at various <lb/>
      times petitions and memorials on these and <lb/>
      kindred subjects have been sent down to <lb/>
      Your Excellency, or to one or more of <lb/>
      your advisers.
    </p>
    <p>
      They are glad to say that the Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada has been willing partly to <lb/>
      accede from time to time to some of their <lb/>
      just requests, so that at present they exer<lb break="no"/>cise control over certain funds put at the <lb/>
      disposal of the Lieutenant Governor of the <lb/>
      Territories, and have larger powers of <lb/>
      legislation; but they find that they are <lb/>
      not in a position to use the limited powers <lb/>
      they do possess to the best advantage, and <lb/>
      that their legislation on subjects coming <lb/>
      strictly within the duties of the Territorial <lb/>
      Assembly has not the necessary quality of <lb/>
      security or completeness. As, besides the <lb/>
      right of dissallowance which Your Excel<lb break="no"/>lency in Council possesses over their legis<lb break="no"/>lation as well as over that of provinces, <lb/>
      the legislation of the Assembly is also <lb/>
      "subject to any Act of Parliament at any <lb/>
      time in force in the Territories." Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, consequently, often passes Acts <lb/>
      diminishing the legislative powers of the <lb/>
      Assembly over parts of subjects ostensibly <lb/>
      <cb/>
      reserved for their control, and at other <lb/>
      times over-riding Ordinances passed by <lb/>
      them and approved of by Your Excellency <lb/>
      in Council. It is unnecessary to point <lb/>
      out how such concurrent powers will lead <lb/>
      to insecurity and conflict. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      The Assembly is of opinion that to <lb/>
      remedy this undesirable state of affairs it <lb/>
      is not necessary to have recourse to the <lb/>
      granting of a full provincial status. They <lb/>
      believe that till the time arrives, which <lb/>
      may be at a not distant day, when the <lb/>
      Territories should be taken into Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation (as one or more provinces) the pass<lb break="no"/>ing of a few amendments to the North<lb break="no"/>West Territories Act will allow them, <lb/>
      subject to disallowances of their Ordinan<lb break="no"/>ces, "to exclusively make laws in relation <lb/>
      to matters" already within their legisla<lb break="no"/>tive jurisdiction. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      They believe that such amendments <lb/>
      should be supplemented by a few further <lb/>
      changes. While they do not ask for some <lb/>
      rights inherent to provinces, notably the <lb/>
      rights to raise money on the public credit, <lb/>
      the chartering of railways, and the admin<lb break="no"/>istration of justice with relation to criminal <lb/>
      matters, they can see no good reason why <lb/>
      other privileges of a territorial or provin<lb break="no"/>cial nature should be withheld from their <lb/>
      administration. They may point out that <lb/>
      during the last five years they have exer<lb break="no"/>cised most of the rights of provincial <lb/>
      assemblies, and, in their opinion, have <lb/>
      proven themselves equal to the task. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      They further are of opinion that the <lb/>
      time has come that their executive govern<lb break="no"/>ment should be put on a firmer basis by <lb/>
      substituting for the Executive Committee <lb/>
      an Executive Council. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      The North-West Territories Act makes <lb/>
      provision for a Committee of the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly "to advise the Lieutenant Governor in <lb/>
      "relation to the expenditure of Territorial <lb/>
      "funds, and of such portion of any mon<lb break="no"/>"eys appropriated by Parliament for the <lb/>
      "Territories, as the Lieutenant Governor <lb/>
      "is authorised to expend by and with the <lb/>
      "advice of the Legislative Assembly, or of <lb/>
      "any Committee thereof." But it does <lb/>
      not provide for any responsible body <lb/>
      whose business it should be to advise the <lb/>
      Lieutenant-Governor in Executive matters. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      It is evident that the Assembly having <lb/>
      the power to vote money for distinct ser<lb break="no"/>vices should have the right to control the <lb/>
      proper carrying out of its intentions. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      As in the present more developed state <lb/>
      of the country, which has as much or more <lb/>
      need for an intelligent administration and <lb/>
      supervision of its sources and requirements <lb/>
      as any other part of Canada, it is impossi<lb break="no"/>ble for the Assembly to act as an execu<lb break="no"/>tive council; they have been obliged to <lb/>
      make provision in their several ordinances <lb/>
      to entrust the duty of administering their <lb/>
      laws to the Lieutenant-Governor, acting <lb/>
      by and with the advice and consent of the <lb/>
      committee, created by federal law for the <lb/>
      purpose of advising with relation to ex<lb break="no"/>penditure only. They cannot, however, <lb/>
      be sure that in taking the only possible <lb/>
      steps within their power to meet the <lb/>
      necessity, they have not exceeded their <lb/>
      powers. Besides, the present machinery <lb/>
      does not admit of development, as for <lb/>
      instance in the direction of division into <lb/>
      departments with responsible heads. The <lb/>
      Executive Committee also has not the <lb/>
      right to advise the Lieutenant-Governor <lb/>
      in matters not contained in the Ordinan<lb break="no"/>ces, notably the appointment of Justices <lb/>
      of the Peace, and the convening and dis<lb break="no"/>solving of an Assembly, &amp;c., &amp;c. And in <lb/>
      general, the Assembly is of opinion that <lb/>
      for purposes of government a permanent <lb/>
      committee of the House has no advantage <lb/>
      over an Executive Council. The first is a <lb/>
      creation without precedent to guide it and <lb/>
      lacks the well-defined constitutional status <lb/>
      which political development during a long <lb/>
      course of time in Great Britain and her <lb/>
      colonies has given to Executive Councils. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      In view of the foregoing the Legislative <lb/>
      Assembly would, therefore, respectfully <lb/>
      recommend the following amendments to <lb/>
      be submitted to the Parliament of Canada <lb/>
      at its next sitting: <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      1. Amend the section of the N.W.T. <lb/>
      Act of 1891 (54 55 Vict) which is substi<lb break="no"/>ted for sec. 13 of the N.W.T. Act, Chap<lb break="no"/>ter 50 R.S.C., so as to read:—<lb/>
    </p>
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>
      "The Legislative Assembly shall exclu<lb break="no"/>"sively have power to make Ordinances <lb/>
      "for the government of the organised <lb/>
      "Territories in relation to the classes of <lb/>
      "subjects next hereinafter mentioned, <lb/>
      "that is to say."
    </p>
    </quote>
    <p>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Note</hi>—While Parliament cannot divest <lb/>
      itself of its paramount right of legislation <lb/>
      in the Territories, it is desirable that it <lb/>
      should not, as it has often done uninten<lb break="no"/>tionally, perhaps, by legislation partly or <lb/>
      wholly affecting the Territories, conflict <lb/>
      with existing Ordinances, unless such is <lb/>
      their distinct intention. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      2. Add a clause to the N.W.T. Act giv<lb break="no"/>ing power to the Assembly notwithstand<lb break="no"/>ing anything in this Act, or any other Act <lb/>
      of the Parliament of Canada, to repeal the <lb/>
      "Territories Real Property Act," so far <lb/>
      as it applies to the organised Territories, <lb/>
      and also to re-enact the said Act or any <lb/>
      part of it, or substitute other provisions <lb/>
      in lieu thereof. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Note</hi>—Though it is within the compet<lb break="no"/>ence of the Assembly to legislate with <lb/>
      regard to property and civil rights and <lb/>
      they necessarily passed Ordinances affect<lb break="no"/>ing real property, as among others, relat<lb break="no"/>ing to Mechanics' Liens, Expropriation of <lb/>
      Lands, Tax Sales, and other official sales, <lb/>
      the question must frequently arise in how <lb/>
      far such ordinances are in harmony with <lb/>
      the Territories Real Property Act or can <lb/>
      be enforced with due reference thereto. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      3. Repeal section 17 of the N.W.T. Act <lb/>
      of 1894 and insert instead: <lb/>
    </p>
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>
      "There shall be a Council to aid and <lb/>
      "advise in the Government of the Terri<lb break="no"/>"tories, to be styled 'The Executive <lb/>
      "Council of the Territories,' and such <lb/>
      "Council shall be composed of such per<lb break="no"/>"sons and under such designations as the <lb/>
      "Lieutenant-Governor shall from time to <lb/>
      "time think fit." <lb/>
    </p>
    </quote>
    <p>
      4. Repeal sub-clause (c) of subsection <lb/>
      (7) of said section 13 re "Insurance Com<lb break="no"/>panies." <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Note</hi>—There is no reason why the As<lb break="no"/>sembly should not have power to incor<lb break="no"/>porate insurance companies with Territo<lb break="no"/>rial objects, notably, hail-insurance com<lb break="no"/>panies, stock insurance companies, &amp;c. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      5. Insert a clause in the N.W.T. Act <lb/>
      giving to the Lieutenant-Governor in <lb/>
      Council the power to appoint Sheriffs, <lb/>
      Clerks of the Court, Deputy Sheriffs, and <lb/>
      Deputy Clerks of the Court, anything <lb/>
      contained in the Act notwithstanding. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Note</hi>—The N.W.T. Act states that the <lb/>
      Assembly may define by Ordinance the <lb/>
      powers, duties and obligations of Sheriffs <lb/>
      and Clerks, and their respective Deputies <lb/>
      (subsection 4 of section 8 of 1891) and may <lb/>
      determine the places where such Sheriffs <lb/>
      and Clerks shall appoint Deputies. The <lb/>
      Assembly also prescribes the fees which <lb/>
      are allowed these officers in civil matters <lb/>
      which constitute nearly all their emolu<lb break="no"/>ments. Notwithstanding the fact that the <lb/>
      Assembly makes provision for both the <lb/>
      duties and the payment of these officers <lb/>
      their appointment remains in the hands of <lb/>
      the Federal Government. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      6. Insert, subject to conditions herein <lb/>
      after explained, the following sub-section: <lb/>
    </p>
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>
      "The establishment, maintenance and <lb/>
      "management of hospitals, asylums, <lb/>
      "charities and eleemosynary institutions <lb/>
      "in and for the Territories"; and <lb/>
    </p>
    </quote>
    <p>
      Repeal sections 103, 104 and 105 of <lb/>
      chapter 50 R.S.C., in so far as they are <lb/>
      inconsistent with the powers asked for. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Note</hi>—Lunatics from the Territories are <lb/>
      sent under an agreement expiring in 1898, <lb/>
      between the federal authorities and the <lb/>
      <cb/>
      Province of Manitoba, to the asylums of <lb/>
      the province. At present there are in <lb/>
      such asylums 74 persons, costing one dol<lb break="no"/>lar per day. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      The Assembly is of opinion that they <lb/>
      could perform such service as well and <lb/>
      more cheaply. On account of the extra <lb/>
      distances travelled by transport to Mani<lb break="no"/>toba the expenses are increased. The As<lb break="no"/>sembly, however, would only desire to <lb/>
      undertake the care of lunatics if the <lb/>
      federal authorities would provide the <lb/>
      necessary buildings, and make such in<lb break="no"/>crease in the grant or subsidy as would <lb/>
      pay for the maintenance of patients and <lb/>
      staff. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      As regards hospitals the Assembly do <lb/>
      already provide, as far as their insufficient <lb/>
      means allow, for the assistance of hos<lb break="no"/>pitals built and kept by private charity. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      7. Repeal section 21 of the N.W.T. <lb/>
      Act of 1894 and introduce an Act respect<lb break="no"/>ing "Roads and Road Allowances in the <lb/>
      North-West Territories," with similar <lb/>
      provisions to those contained in chapter <lb/>
      49 R.S.C., respecting Roads and Road <lb/>
      Allowances in Manitoba. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Note</hi>—This would do away with the <lb/>
      uncertainties and difficulties now connect<lb break="no"/>ed with the laying out and improving <lb/>
      roads and acquiring road by expropri<lb break="no"/>ation and it would give to the Assembly <lb/>
      the right to delegate such power to muni<lb break="no"/>cipalities. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      8. Add a clause giving to the Assembly <lb/>
      the power to repeal, alter, vary or re<lb break="no"/>enact the provisions for appointment of <lb/>
      Justices of the Peace and their qualifi<lb break="no"/>cations. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
        <hi rendition="simple:italic">Note</hi>—Only an Executive belonging to <lb/>
      and being in touch with the Assembly <lb/>
      has the facilities for judging the neces<lb break="no"/>sity of appointments to the commission of <lb/>
      the Peace and the eligibility of the per<lb break="no"/>sons to be appointed. Section 7 of the <lb/>
      N.W.T. Act of 1894 provides a property <lb/>
      qualification for Justices of the Peace con<lb break="no"/>sisting in the ownership in fee simple of <lb/>
      land of a certain value. In new settle<lb break="no"/>ments where few or not patents for home<lb break="no"/>steads have been issued it is impossible to <lb/>
      find suitable persons who can be appoint<lb break="no"/>ed. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      9. Repeal section 16 of the N.W.T. <lb/>
      Act of 1888 and enact a clause giving the <lb/>
      Assembly complete control as regard to <lb/>
      appointment, duties and salary of the <lb/>
      Clerk of the Assembly. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p rendition="simple:centre">FINANCES</p>
    <p>
      Regarding the financial position of the <lb/>
      Territories the Assembly must reiterate <lb/>
      in part their memorial of January 1892:— <lb/>
    </p>
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
    <p>
      "That the necessities of local govern<lb break="no"/>"ment in the North-West Territories de<lb break="no"/>"mand that instead of the annual vote by <lb/>
      "the Parliament of Canada of an indefin<lb break="no"/>"ite sum for expenses of government, a <lb/>
      "fixed amount in the nature of a subsidy <lb/>
      "should be granted to the Territories," <lb/>
      and "owing to the rapid increase of the <lb/>
      "population in the North-West the <lb/>
      "amount of subsidy should be fixed for a <lb/>
      "term of not more than four years." <lb/>
    </p>
    </quote>
    <p>
      The revenues of the Assembly are ob<lb break="no"/>tained from local sources and the grant <lb/>
      from the Parliament of Canada. As re<lb break="no"/>gards the local revenues they are and al<lb break="no"/>ways will be very slight as they are made <lb/>
      up of amounts received for granting <lb/>
      licenses for such occupations as the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly is allowed to regulate by legislation. <lb/>
      These revenues amounted in 1895 to 30,<lb break="no"/>000 dollars. All the assets which the <lb/>
      Provinces [except Manitoba, which has <lb/>
      been compensated for the lack of them] <lb/>
      possess, are retained by the Parliament of <lb/>
      Canada, who own and administer, with <lb/>
      power to roll, or grant to railway com<lb break="no"/>panies, their public lands, their hay lands, <lb/>
      their timber and their minerals. The <lb/>
      Assembly, however, is expected to pro<lb break="no"/>vide for educating the young, caring for <lb/>
      the sick and destitute, rendering the <lb/>
      country habitable by improving roads, <lb/>
      bridging rivers, protecting against prairie <lb/>
      fires, increasing the water suppply, etc., <lb/>
      etc.
    </p>
    <p>
      Owing to the vast area of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories and the widely scattered nature of <lb/>
      the settlement all the business of the <lb/>
      local government is rendered more expen<lb break="no"/>sive proportionately to population than in <lb/>
      any province. As regards roads this is <lb/>
      apparent, but with respect to schools it <lb/>
      will be found equally true. By consider<lb break="no"/>ing that under the most favorable circum<lb break="no"/>stances less than half the area in each <lb/>
      township is available for homesteading <lb/>
      and that as a rule only a small amount is <lb/>
      taken up, it will not create surprise to see <lb/>
      that in 1895 it took 341 schools with 401 <lb/>
      teachers to educate 11,972 enrolled pupils, <lb/>
      with a daily average attendance of 6,600, <lb/>
      and that out of these schools 223 were on<lb break="no"/>ly open during the summer months with a <lb/>
      daily average attendance of 11. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      The most cursory review of the increase <lb/>
      of population and the very small increase <lb/>
      during the same period of the grant from <lb/>
      Parliament for the government of the <lb/>
      Territories (which stands in the same posi<lb break="no"/>tion as the subsidies allowed to the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces), will afford a convincing proof of <lb/>
      the utter inadequacy of their resources. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      In 1891 the population was 66 799, the <lb/>
      number of schools in operation was 224 <lb/>
      (for that year no separate amount was <lb/>
      out at the disposal of the Assembly. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      In 1892 the number of schools in oper<lb break="no"/>ation was 237, and the Parliamentary <lb/>
      grant for government was $208,700 <lb/>
      ($193,200 and $15,500). <lb/>
    </p>
   <p>
     In 1895 the number of schools was 34.1 <lb/>
     being an increase in four years of over 52 <lb/>
     per cent.
   </p>
    <p>
      In 1896 the population is 104,331 (10 <lb/>
      per cent. per year added to census of 1894 <lb/>
      being the ratio of increase between 1891 <lb/>
      and 1894) and the grant from Parliament <lb/>
      is $242,879 (not including $25,000, supple<lb break="no"/>mentary vote to recoup the Assembly for <lb/>
      relief expenditure undertaken for and on <lb/>
      account of the Dominion Government), <lb/>
      being an increase in five years in popu<lb break="no"/>lation of 56 per cent, and in annual grant <lb/>
      during last four years of 16 per cent. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
     As the conditions of Government in the <lb/>
      Territories are somewhat analagous to <lb/>
      those in the Province of Manitoba, a com<lb break="no"/>parison between the amount voted to the <lb/>
      Territories, and the amount, calculated on <lb/>
      the same items, on which the subsidy to <lb/>
      Manitoba is based, would be fair and just. <lb/>
      Such an amount would be determined on <lb/>
      the following considerations: <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      1. That the population of the Territor<lb break="no"/>ies, according to the census of 1891, was <lb/>
      66,799 ; according to the census taken by <lb/>
      <cb/>
      the North-West Mounted Police in 1894 <lb/>
      it was 86,851, and that, according to that <lb/>
      ratio of increase, viz., thirty per cent., it <lb/>
      will be, in 1897, 112,906. That if treat<lb break="no"/>ed on the same basis as Manitoba, accord<lb break="no"/>ing to sub-section (b) of section 5 of chap<lb break="no"/>ter 46 R.S.C., the per capita grant would <lb/>
      be calculated on an approximate estimate <lb/>
      of the population two and a half years <lb/>
      from 1897, which at the known rate of in<lb break="no"/>crease (of ten per cent every year) would <lb/>
      be 141,132. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      2. That on capita grant, therefore, the <lb/>
      amount would be at 80 cents a head on <lb/>
      141,132 the sum of $112,905. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      3. That on debt account on a presum<lb break="no"/>ably actual population in 1897 of 112,906 <lb/>
      the amount would be five per cent. on <lb/>
      $32 44 per head, making the sum of $183,<lb break="no"/>133. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      4. That a grant for the support of the <lb/>
      Governmetn and Legislature in Manitoba <lb/>
      of $50,000 is allowed, and that such a <lb/>
      grant for the Territories should at least <lb/>
      be as liberal, making the sum $50,000. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      5. That as Manitoba has been held to <lb/>
      be entitled to an indemnity for the want <lb/>
      of public lands of $100,000, and as the <lb/>
      Territories have a stronger claim for com<lb break="no"/>pensation is as much as besides the land <lb/>
      grants to railways in and for the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, a great part of their public lands <lb/>
      have been given to railway companies in <lb/>
      aid of construction, not for the benefit of <lb/>
      the Territories, but <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      (a) For the general benefit of Canada, <lb/>
      and for the special benefit of the Eastern <lb/>
      Provinces and British Columbia. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      (b) For railways constructed for and in <lb/>
      Manitoba for which no sufficient land <lb/>
      grant could be found within that province; <lb/>
      and <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      Inasmuch as a very much larger total <lb/>
      amount of land is retained in the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories for the benefit of the whole Domin<lb break="no"/>ion of Canada than the amount of land <lb/>
      retained in the much smaller province of <lb/>
      Manitoba ; and <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      As the province of Manitoba has been <lb/>
      given all lands designated as swamp <lb/>
      lands, <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      They feel they are entitled to a compaara<lb break="no"/>tively larger amount than was allowed to <lb/>
      Manitoba, the exact figure of which they, <lb/>
      however, are not prepared to estimate un<lb break="no"/>til such time as they enter confederation. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      If treated as regards a subsidy on a <lb/>
      similar system as Manitoba the Assembly <lb/>
      recognize that it would be just to deduct <lb/>
      from such calculated amount  such sums as <lb/>
      would defray the expenses which they, as <lb/>
      a Territorial Government,  are not called <lb/>
      upon to pay, notably the expense of the <lb/>
      administration of the criminal law: <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      On the other hand, they find that it has <lb/>
      been the practice of Palriament to charge <lb/>
      votes for Lieutenant-Governor's Office, the <lb/>
      Clerk of the Legislative Assembly, Legal <lb/>
      Adviser, Registrars of Land Titles Offices, the <lb/>
      up to the Territories without giving them <lb/>
      the control over such moneys. They be<lb break="no"/>lieve that they could perform the services <lb/>
      for which such votes were given as well <lb/>
      and better, and that such service and votes <lb/>
      should be put under their control. They <lb/>
      also find that votes for services in unor<lb break="no"/>ganized territory (as for instance $5,000 <lb/>
      for schools in such unorganized territory) <lb/>
      appear among votes for the North-West <lb/>
      Territories, increasing thereby the appar<lb break="no"/>ent liberality of Parliament towards them. <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      The Legislative Assembly believes that <lb/>
      with the foregoing requests for legislation <lb/>
      and for subsidy they have given good and <lb/>
      sufficient ground for your Excellency's <lb/>
      advisers to recommend to the Parliament <lb/>
      of Canada ot deal in a liberal spirit with <lb/>
      their just complaints: <lb/>
    </p>
    <p>
      And they will ever pray &amp;c, &amp;c. <lb/>
    </p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>