<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgASLA_1896-11-19" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>,
<date when="1896-11-19" cert="medium">19 November 1896</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA"> <editor>Walter Scott</editor>.
<title>The Leader</title>. <date from="1896-11-05" to="1896-11-19"/>.
<pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="5"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1896-11-19_Page_005_copy.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-12-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-12-14">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1896-11-19_Page_005"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1896-11-19_Page_005.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="5" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1896-11-19_Page_005.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="num">5</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE LEADER, THURSDAY EVENING, NOVEMBER 19, 1896.</fw>

<head rendition="simple:centre">SECESSION</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">Shall the Territories Be <lb/>
Divided?</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">Mr. Haultain Emphatically Says, <lb/>
No! and Gives Good Reasons <lb/>
for His Answer — The Seces<lb break="no"/>sionists Admit Their Defeat, <lb/>
and Shirk a Vote.</head> 

<p>In the "Memorial" debate in the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly, Messrs Brett and Insinger spoke in <lb/>
the afternoon. At half-past five Mr. <lb/>
Magrath had the floor. He continued <lb/>
speaking half an hour after recess, and <lb/>
was followed by Mr. Fearon, whose <lb/>
speech was printed last week. It was <lb/>
about nine o'clock when the leader of the <lb/>
House rose to combat the plea of the <lb/>
secessionists. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">MR. HAULTAIN</persName></p> 

<p>said that after the debate which took <lb/>
place in the afternoon he ha not thought <lb/>
of taking up any of the time of the House, <lb/>
but it had taken a peculiar turn by rea<lb break="no"/>son of the amendment which had been <lb/>
    put in, — a turn which had a particular <lb/>
personal application to several members of <lb/>
the House on account of their coming <lb/>
from Alberta, and considering the impor<lb break="no"/>tance of the question at issue. He would <lb/>
refer to the amendment first and then <lb/>
proceed to make a few remarks with regard <lb/>
to the general line of debate which had <lb/>
been taken. The amendment was to the <lb/>
effect that the Assembly was of the opin<lb break="no"/>ion that until the Territories were admit<lb break="yes"/>ed into confederation as two or more <lb/>
provinces, which they considered was <lb/>
necessary at an early date for the compact <lb/>
government on local lines of such a vast <lb/>
country, that the passage of a few amend<lb break="no"/>ments at the first session of the Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment of CAnada to the N.W.T. Act would <lb/>
allow them, subject to disallowance of <lb/>
their ordinances to exclusively make laws <lb/>
in relation to matters already within their <lb/>
legislative jurisdiction. The amendment <lb/>
involved two questions. IN the first place <lb/>
was the statement that the Territories should <lb/>
be divided into two provinces at an early <lb/>
    date not particularly certain, — almost as <lb/>
vague as the words of the memorial; and <lb/>
in the second place that until that event <lb/>
    became a fact, — until the Territories were <lb/>
divided into two provinces, they should <lb/>
practically remain as they were. He did <lb/>
not know whether the hon. gentleman <lb/>
who had framed the amendment had alto<lb break="no"/>gether followed out exactly what he <lb/>
meant. The memorial asked that they <lb/>
should remain as they were with regard <lb/>
to their legislative jurisdiction, but that <lb/>
they should have that jurisdiction consid<lb break="no"/>erably extended in many important mat<lb break="no"/>ters. So that the amendment, in its pro<lb break="no"/>phetic allusion, was progress so far as <lb/>
the practical question with which the <lb/>
House was concerned; but in the other <lb/>
part the amendment was a stand still, if <lb/>
not retrograde, and for that reason he <lb/>
would have to oppose the amendment. <lb/>
They had a large number of powers <lb/>
which at present were not complete, and <lb/>
in which, so far as those powers were con<lb break="no"/>cerned, and so far as other things which <lb/>
at present generally came with their <lb/>
legislative jurisdiction, they must look <lb/>
    for an immediate extension, — not for a <lb/>
remote extension at the time when a pro<lb break="no"/>vince or provinces may be established. <lb/>
The memorial was the practical suggestion <lb/>
of a practical body with regard to the <lb/>
actual present needs of the Territories. <lb/>
The amendment said they wanted a cer<lb break="no"/>tain number of provinces at an indefinite <lb/>
period, and then proceeds to state they <lb/>
really did not want anything more in the <lb/>
way of extension to their legislative juris<lb break="no"/>diction, but were perfectly satisfied to re<lb break="no"/>main as they were in that respect, except <lb/>
that present jurisdiction should be round<lb break="no"/>ed out as far as it stands at present and <lb/>
be made complete. To his mind the <lb/>
    amendment nullified one fo the most im<lb break="no"/>portant parts of the memorial, — that part <lb/>
which asked for the extension of their <lb/>
legislation jurisdiction, and for that rea<lb break="no"/>son could not commend itself to the House. <lb/>
No matter what the hon. member, the <lb/>
mover of the amendment, might believe <lb/>
with regard to what number of provinces <lb/>
they should have at a future day; no mat<lb break="no"/>ter what any hon. member might believe <lb/>
to be the proper way of stating their <lb/>
position with regard to the legislative rights <lb/>
and financial claims, he could not accept <lb/>
the position of the amendment which said <lb/>
they did not want anything more than <lb/>
they had now. The amendment was not <lb/>
practical, it did not settle anything, but <lb/>
it left everything for the considereation of <lb/>
the future. The whole subject connected <lb/>
with the memorial had been very suffi<lb break="no"/>ciently and very fully discussed during <lb/>
    the afternoon — so far as the speech of <lb/>
the hon. gentleman from Yorkton was <lb/>
concerned, more fully and more ably dis<lb break="no"/>cussed than any question he ever heard <lb/>
debated in that House. Therefore he <lb/>
(Mr. Haultain) would not attempt to take <lb/>
up the time of the House in dealing with <lb/>
the details of the memorial, or in dealing <lb/>
with their financial position. Those were <lb/>
fully set out in the memorial, and with <lb/>
which they all pretty well agreed. The <lb/>
question so far as the amendment was <lb/>
concerned, so far as any differenece of <lb/>
opinion with the memorial was concerned, <lb/>
was a question of what should their insti<lb break="no"/>tutions be? He went further and said it <lb/>
was a question of what should their insti<lb break="no"/>tutions be now? not what they should be <lb/>
at some future date. That involved the <lb/>
questin of whether they should have a <lb/>
single province, or whether they should <lb/>
debate the system proposed in the memor<lb break="no"/>ial of a gradual development of the pre<lb break="no"/>sent Territorial system until they arrived <lb/>
at such a point that they would be albe to <lb/>
slide into confederation almost without <lb/>
knowing it. That question had been com<lb break="no"/>plicated by the amendment which meant <lb/>
that Alberta should be established into a <lb/>
province itself. As a member represent<lb break="no"/>ing an Albertan constituency, he must <lb/>
take exception to the position assumed by <lb/>
the hon. member for Banff in undertaking <lb/>
to represent the views of Alberta. He <lb/>
(Mr. Haultain) denied any right on the <lb/>
part of the hon. gentleman to attempt to <lb/>
represent what the opinions of the pepole <lb/>
of Alberta were except so far as those <lb/>
people were confined to the limits of his <lb/>
own electoral district. He might tell <lb/>
him, and other hon. gentlemen from Al<lb break="no"/>berta, that he did not believe Alberta <lb/>
wished to be made a province. He did <lb/>
not believe there had been a proper state<lb break="no"/>ment of the feeling of Alberta to-day. He <lb/>
agreed with what the hon. gentleman from <lb/>
Lethbridge (Mr. Magrath) said, that if a <lb/>
poll were taken to-day in Alberta on the <lb/>
question of whether Alberta should be set <lb/>
aside as a province there would be a very <lb/>
large majority against it in spite of the <lb/>
efforts of the Alberta autonomy movement <lb/>
in Calgary. That movement originated <lb/>
in the town of Calgary in one sense. It <lb/>
was a very praiseworthy movement in so <lb/>
far as it called attention to certain impor<lb break="no"/>tant public matters and gave opportunity <lb/>
to consider the larger question of the form <lb/>
of government in the Territories. But <lb/>
on the other side, if he might judge from <lb/>
the propaganda of the movement in the <lb/>
    
    <cb/>

shape of pamphlets, and from the speeches <lb/>
he had heard from prominent advocates <lb/>
of the movement, after all the movement <lb/>
was largely a very local one. They ap<lb break="no"/>pealed largely to the desparate condition <lb/>
into which certain portions of Alberta had <lb/>
unfortunately fallen. He heard of large <lb/>
and visionary schemes on provincial lines <lb/>
by which millions of dolars were going to <lb/>
be raised in the money markets of the <lb/>
world, by which large public works were <lb/>
going to be undertaken, and in fact, under <lb/>
the expenditure of which sums everyone <lb/>
was going to get work to be rich; to say <lb/>
nothing of the incidental fact that Cal<lb break="no"/>gary was going to be established as the <lb/>
capital of the future province, that public <lb/>
buildings were going to be built there; that <lb/>
the Assembly, or something like the pre<lb break="no"/>sent one, or better, was going to be estab<lb break="no"/>lished there; that there would be a com<lb break="no"/>pletely planned civil service, and that Cal<lb break="no"/>gary should blossom out from its present <lb/>
condition into a full blown capital. That <lb/>
was the most practical argument he heard, <lb/>
but it was not a practical argument that <lb/>
appealed to him, or that should appeal to <lb/>
the members of the House, or to the <lb/>
people of Alberta when asked to take <lb/>
such an important step as to separate <lb/>
from the Territories. As a member from <lb/>
Alberta he was not prepared to advocaate <lb/>
any scheme which meant the division of <lb/>
Alberta from the rest of the Territories <lb/>
and making it into a province. Consider<lb break="no"/>ing the practical interests of the country, <lb/>
considering the practical work they had <lb/>
to do, he did not feel disposed to be ask<lb break="no"/>ed to express an opinion upon the subject. <lb/>
The gentlemen who had advocated Alberta <lb/>
autonomy that day in the House did not <lb/>
go any nearer than saying it was some<lb break="no"/>thing to be hoped for in the near future, <lb/>
whatever that might be. Why, therefore, <lb/>
should the House be asked to spoil a <lb/>
memorial which dealt with their present <lb/>
needs; which dealt with their undoubted <lb/>
rights and the righteous demands they <lb/>
wished to make with regard to their <lb/>
immediate surroundings and their every<lb break="no"/>day institutions? Why should he be call<lb break="no"/>ed upon to express an opinion with regard <lb/>
to something which was simply anticipat<lb break="no"/>ory of a movment which might take place <lb/>
at some future date, as the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man put it in his amendment. The hon. <lb/>
gentleman from Banff referred to the <lb/>
present connection of Alberta as a part<lb break="no"/>nership in a firm, and said that member <lb/>
of the firm wished to withdraw. He (Mr. <lb/>
Haultain) did not know exactly what the <lb/>
hon. member meant when he spoke of a <lb/>
partnership existing between what was <lb/>
one single united country, and he believ<lb break="no"/>ed it would remain so. The diversity of <lb/>
interests which existed between various <lb/>
parts of the Territories had been spoken <lb/>
of as giving a good and strong ground for <lb/>
dividing the Territories up. What sort <lb/>
of a province did the hon. gentleman wish <lb/>
it to be? Did they want to have one <lb/>
sheep farm, or one wheat field, or one <lb/>
sort of a field devoted to some other sort <lb/>
of industry which their own insignificance <lb/>
would allow them to describe? If they <lb/>
wished to have a good strong province, <lb/>
strong in its own resources, they should <lb/>
have a diversity of resources (hear, hear.) <lb/>
Much better than having a comparatively <lb/>
small amount of land devoted to one or <lb/>
two interests would it be if they could <lb/>
have a very large area such as the organ<lb break="no"/>ized Territories were to-day with their <lb/>
diversity of interests, but not conflict of <lb/>
interests. They should look forward to <lb/>
having a very much stronger and better <lb/>
province than there would be if they ha <lb/>
to be divided up. Was there as much <lb/>
diversity of interest or conflict of interest, <lb/>
if they liked to use the expression, between <lb/>
the most remote portions of the Territoreis <lb/>
as there was between any sections of the <lb/>
older provinces? There was no conflict. <lb/>
He did not think any member of the <lb/>
House could state that at any time in the <lb/>
history of the House there was any con<lb break="no"/>flict of interest between those portions of <lb/>
the Territories known as Alberta, Assini<lb break="no"/>boia and Saskatchewan. He believed <lb/>
there was a Saskatchewan question at one <lb/>
time, but that lost a large amount of its <lb/>
significance in the comprehesive term <lb/>
"in other respects," so he was <lb/>
safe in saying there was no conflict of in<lb break="no"/>terest, at least very apparent. Hon. <lb/>
gentlemen who had argued with regard to <lb/>
the establishment of a small and weak <lb/>
province such as ALberta would be, look <lb/>
at the analogous case of Manitoba, Bri <lb/>
tish Columbia and other provinces. In <lb/>
the first place they were not analogous. <lb/>
Manitoba was not taken into confeder<lb break="no"/>ation under the same circumstances as the <lb/>
Territories would be taken into confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. Manitoba was taken in as a <lb/>
political necessity. In one sense they <lb/>
hoped the Territories to be taken in as a <lb/>
political necessity, but not in the same <lb/>
sense. In talking of two sides to a bar<lb break="no"/>gain, British Columbia when taken into <lb/>
confederation had a distinct say as to the <lb/>
terms upon which they would enter. On <lb/>
the other hand when they of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories were talking about two sides to a <lb/>
bargain, their position now and for a long <lb/>
time to come would be that, although <lb/>
they were in one sense one of the con<lb break="no"/>tracting parties, in reality the other con<lb break="no"/>tracting party had all the say, because it <lb/>
had all the power; so that the analogy <lb/>
between the terms of entrance into con<lb break="no"/>federation either between British Colum<lb break="no"/>bia or Manitoba did not hold good. The <lb/>
hon. gentleman had referred to direct tax<lb break="no"/>ation. If they did not have direct tax<lb break="no"/>ation they certainly could not have enough <lb/>
money for carrying on their business. <lb/>
They either had to have direct taxation <lb/>
or they mjust hae a municipal form of <lb/>
government under which people would <lb/>
levy the burdens upon themselves, if they <lb/>
would be a successful province. It was <lb/>
very easy to take, as the hon. gentleman <lb/>
from Banff did, a sheet of paper and with <lb/>
a few figures make a fortune out of them. <lb/>
The figures did not lie, but the average <lb/>
man who relied on the figures was very <lb/>
apt to find he was very much mistaken. <lb/>
The figures did not lie, but all the practi<lb break="no"/>cal questions involved in those figures <lb/>
had to be taken into consideration. Upon <lb/>
the credit of what, would any large sums <lb/>
of money be raised in the proposed <lb/>
province of Alberta? Not upon <lb/>
lands, because there were not going to be <lb/>
any lands; not upon minerals, because <lb/>
the mineral went with the lands and <lb/>
were already taken up by Federal <lb/>
authorities; so that when the hon. gentlemen <lb/>
indulged in fanciful figures in regard to <lb/>
large loans of money they should take one <lb/>
step further and explain exactly how they <lb/>
expected to raise those large sums of <lb/>
money. He did not think practical men <lb/>
living in Alberta had had any large oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of seeing that capital was particu<lb break="no"/>larly anxious to flow into the Territories. <lb/>
When hon. gentlemen talked about bor<lb break="no"/>rowing large sums of money they were <lb/>
simply begging the question and ignoring <lb/>
the practical side which precluded the <lb/>
possibility of any such loads being raised <lb/>
for a very long time to come. The hon. <lb/>
gentleman's argument with regard to the <lb/>
compactness of the province or provinces, <lb/>
and with regard to the desirability of <lb/>
having comparatively small areas formed <lb/>
into provinces, might e considered. The <lb/>
reference to the policy of the United <lb/>
States with regard to their Territories, <lb/>
was not a reference which should have <lb/>
great weight in that House. So far as <lb/>
they knew anything about American in<lb break="no"/>
    
    <cb/>

situations, he (Mr. Haultain) thought that <lb/>
was not exactly the part of the world to <lb/>
which they were going to look for prece<lb break="no"/>dents. If the States like to cut up their <lb/>
country into comparatively small terri<lb break="no"/>tories, presumably they did so for some <lb/>
reason, but not, he thought, for the rea<lb break="no"/>son advanced by the hon. member for <lb/>
Lethbridge. At what points were they <lb/>
going to draw an arbitrary line and say <lb/>
"at this point facility for governing this <lb/>
country ceases?" There were no great <lb/>
natural obstacles to communication in <lb/>
this country. They could communicate <lb/>
with the most remote parts in a rapid <lb/>
manner either by railroad or telegraph, so <lb/>
at what points would they draw that ima<lb break="no"/>ginary line? for after all it was a geograph<lb break="no"/>ical line drawn arbitrarily without any <lb/>
reference to any known number at all, and <lb/>
no position involving such a division <lb/>
could commend itself to that House as <lb/>
being based upon any sound principle, or <lb/>
even on good common sense. The argu<lb break="no"/>ment with regard to those narrow limits, <lb/>
and the special rights which exist within <lb/>
those norrow limits, seemed to be a de<lb break="no"/>cidedly provincial argument. He used the <lb/>
expression advisedly. He was not oppos<lb break="no"/>ed to the formation of a province, but he <lb/>
hoped hon. gentlemen who went in for <lb/>
the formation of a province would not <lb/>
take the other meaning of the term and <lb/>
indulge in arguments which could only be <lb/>
called both narrow and provincial. If <lb/>
they were going to confine themselves at <lb/>
once to the particular rights or particular <lb/>
claims of smaller portions of this country <lb/>
they might take the position proposed by <lb/>
the hon. members from Banff and Leth<lb break="no"/>bridge, and cut the whole country into <lb/>
small plots so that every man might be a <lb/>
province unto himself with three acres <lb/>
and a cow. But it seemed to him they <lb/>
should take the larger point of view, and <lb/>
not be bound by the narrow selfish inter<lb break="no"/>ests and claims, so-called, of any particu<lb break="no"/>lar portions of the Territories. The hon. <lb/>
member from Lethbridge referred repeat<lb break="no"/>edly to the fact that they were over-gov<lb break="no"/>erned. He (Mr. Haultain) believed the <lb/>
hon. gentleman was perfectly right. <lb/>
(Laughter.) They had heard about the <lb/>
movement going on now in the maritime <lb/>
provinces. He had not heard that it had <lb/>
taken any very definite shape, but he be<lb break="no"/>lieved there was a feeling in the maritime <lb/>
provinces at least that they were over-<lb break="yes"/>governed; that having three small pro<lb break="no"/>vincial governments instead of one strong <lb/>
government weakened their influence. <lb/>
But the hon. member from Lethbridge, <lb/>
when telling them about that state of be<lb break="no"/>ing over-governed in the Dominion, pro<lb break="no"/>ceeded, not in the most logical way, to <lb/>
recommend that they should follow the <lb/>
analogy of other parts of the Dominion <lb/>
by cutting up these Territories necessarily <lb/>
into a large number of small areas for the <lb/>
purposes of government. It would simply <lb/>
mean duplication, or triplication, or some <lb/>
other quantity of governments, or legisla<lb break="no"/>tures, of institutions of all sorts. In fact <lb/>
all of the larger institutions of the machine <lb/>
would simply be increased just so many <lb/>
times as the number of provinces it was <lb/>
decided there should be, without, so far <lb/>
as had been shown, any benefit being de<lb break="no"/>rived from it. For that reason, then, why <lb/>
should they have two or more small pro<lb break="no"/>vinces when one good strong province <lb/>
would do for all the Territories when the <lb/>
time for a province had come? He be<lb break="no"/>lieved they should have one province, but <lb/>
that they need not have it yet. He be<lb break="no"/>lieved they should go on, as they had <lb/>
been going on, with the gradual develop<lb break="no"/>ment of their present institutions, here <lb/>
and there gaining a little more power, <lb/>
here and their extending their jurisdic<lb break="no"/>tion, here and there getting more money. <lb/>
There were the practical questions for <lb/>
consideration, and that very discussion <lb/>
showed that they were not prepared to <lb/>
make any definite claim with regard to <lb/>
provincial questions. The very fact that <lb/>
there were three sets of opinions express<lb break="no"/>ed in the House showed they were not <lb/>
prepared to discuss the provincial ques<lb break="no"/>tion with a view to its immediate institu<lb break="no"/>tion. They had very difficult questions <lb/>
to be settled when formed into a province, <lb/>
questions with regard to their lands and <lb/>
many other matters. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man from Banff, the other day, in address<lb break="no"/>ing the House referred to the undignified <lb/>
position the Territories occupied through <lb/>
the annual pilgrimages which had to be <lb/>
made to Ottawa to ask for more money. <lb/>
If such an attitude was an undignified <lb/>
attitude for them in their present unde<lb break="no"/>veloped position, what word should he <lb/>
use to describe a similar proceeding on <lb/>
the part of the representatives of a full <lb/>
blown province, because that was what <lb/>
the hon. gentleman admitted must be <lb/>
done? If they were going to have a pro<lb break="no"/>vince established at once they were not <lb/>
going to get what they thought they <lb/>
ought to get, and they would be obliged <lb/>
to do exactly what Manitoba had been <lb/>
obliged to do, and would be obliged to <lb/>
    do, — to make those annual pilgrimages, <lb/>
only it would be very much more undig<lb break="no"/>nified to go down to Ottawa on behalf of <lb/>
the province and make those annual <lb/>
claims than it was merely for a member <lb/>
of that House, who happened to be a <lb/>
member of the Executive Committee, to <lb/>
go down to Ottawa from year to year, <lb/>
simply to say, "we have no agreement <lb/>
with you, we do not want to ake any <lb/>
agreement with you, but we want to get <lb/>
better terms, and we consider we are en<lb break="no"/>titled to better terms?" So far as the <lb/>
argument of the annual pilgrimages was <lb/>
concerned the hon. gentleman had better <lb/>
not have made reference to it. The Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories had gradually demanded and had <lb/>
gradually taken quietly, it was true, but <lb/>
not the less effectually, larger powers into <lb/>
their own hands. They had developed <lb/>
the Executive Committee, an institution <lb/>
which was their own creation, and had <lb/>
practically put into the hands of men re<lb break="no"/>sponsible to the House almost all the <lb/>
administrative business of the Territories. <lb/>
They had been going on gradually until <lb/>
they had at least arrived to-day very near<lb break="no"/>ly the position of a province so far as <lb/>
administrative business was concerned. <lb/>
The memorial stated very clearly the <lb/>
difference between their present position <lb/>
and that of a province. It went on to say <lb/>
they wanted further powers with the one <lb/>
exception that they did not want to be al <lb/>
lowed to assume a debt which might com<lb break="no"/>plicate the provincial question later on, <lb/>
and they did not want to be admitted into <lb/>
confederation simply becausse they did <lb/>
not feel prepared to discuss the terms of <lb/>
being admitted into confederation. The <lb/>
memorial enabled them to go on gradually <lb/>
developing their institutions, bradually <lb/>
practising self government until they had <lb/>
arrived at the time when they were fully <lb/>
enabled to negotiate with the stronger <lb/>
body at Ottawa in regard to the important <lb/>
questions he had mentioned. He did not <lb/>
think he need wast time in arguing upon <lb/>
the House that they were not ready to go <lb/>
into negotiations. There were questions <lb/>
which demanded a large amount of negoti<lb break="no"/>ation and which unfortunately were set<lb break="no"/>tled not so much on principles of right <lb/>
and justice, but more with respect to the <lb/>
amount of political pressure which could <lb/>
be brought to bear upon the Ottawa <lb/>
authorities. He defied any hon. member <lb/>
to say they were prepared by virtue of <lb/>
their representations at Ottawa, or by <lb/>
virtue of the strength of the Territories in <lb/>
population, or in any other respect, to go <lb/> 
    
    <cb/>

to Ottawa and negotiate with the authori<lb break="no"/>ties there for entrance into confederation. <lb/>
What they wanted was autonomy. Au<lb break="no"/>tonomy meant power to govern them<lb break="no"/>selves. Their jurisdiction was subject to <lb/>
continual incursions of Federal legislation. <lb/>
They made a useful law, and sometimes <lb/>
an Act was passed at Ottawa which rend<lb break="no"/>ered useless their own legislation. They <lb/>
wanted to be put in the position of a pro<lb break="no"/>vince of passing laws coming within their <lb/>
own jurisdictions, but wished to defer the <lb/>
settlement of the very difficult and com<lb break="no"/>plicated question as to the terms upon <lb/>
which they should enter into confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. To go further than that, they <lb/>
were met with this fact staring them in <lb/>
the face, that they were not agreed upon <lb/>
what they wanted to be in the future. <lb/>
Some wanted one province, some wanted <lb/>
two provinces, and possibly before they <lb/>
had gone much further they might find a <lb/>
claim for a province somewhere on the <lb/>
banks of the Saskatchewan. In view of <lb/>
the fact that the most ardent advocate <lb/>
of provincial autonomy was not prepared <lb/>
to show what he really wished to do, why <lb/>
should they complicate the consideration of <lb/>
practical questions which concerned their <lb/>
everyday needs, which come up every <lb/>
day, and concerned them to-day, and would <lb/>
continually, until that province or those <lb/>
    provinces had been established, — why <lb/>
should they complicate their position in <lb/>
the discussion of something upon which <lb/>
there were so many differences of opin<lb break="no"/>ion, and in the discussion of a question <lb/>
which could not be practially settle that <lb/>
night? They might as well drop that <lb/>
subject and get down to business. Their <lb/>
business was, What did they want for <lb/>
the present time, both with regard to <lb/>
their constitution and with regard to <lb/>
their finances, not what they wanted for <lb/>
the future with regard to their constitu<lb break="no"/>tion, and upon which they were not <lb/>
agreed. Let the reference in the memor<lb break="no"/>ial as to what they wanted be as explicit <lb/>
and as implicit as possible, but let them <lb/>
be unanimous as to what they want just <lb/>
now. The hon. gentleman from Leth<lb break="no"/>bridge said in his amendment that they <lb/>
should stand still until the change was <lb/>
made. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MAGR1">Mr. Magrath</persName>: I beg the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man's pardon, I say nothing of the kind. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> (reading the amend<lb break="no"/>ment): Waht I say is, the amendment <lb/>
as it reads is subject to only one construc<lb break="no"/>tion, and that is that it proposes that we <lb/>
should stand still until two or more pro<lb break="no"/>vinces are established. Of course, con<lb break="no"/>tinued Mr. Haultain, if the hon. gentleman <lb/>
did not intend that, he (Mr. Haultain) was <lb/>
very glad, but that was the only meaning <lb/>
he could give the amendment if it meant <lb/>
anything at all. If it meant something <lb/>
    else— <lb/> </p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MAGR1">Mr. Magrath</persName>: I certainly cannot see <lb/>
it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> proceeded that if the <lb/>
amendment did not mean that, he did <lb/>
not see what it did mean. He thought if <lb/>
they could be unanimous upon what they <lb/>
wanted, and upon what they ahd a right <lb/>
to have, they could agree to disagree with <lb/>
regard to what their future was going to <lb/>
be. Their present position demanded a <lb/>
remedy at once. The memorial set that <lb/>
out much more eloquently than anything <lb/>
he could say. Therefore let them set <lb/>
aside the larger question which was for <lb/>
the future, and turn their attention to <lb/>
the practical needs of the present moment. <lb/>
He thought he need not address an argu<lb break="no"/>ment to the Houe to be unanimous. If <lb/>
they were not unanimous they need not <lb/>
hope for anything from Ottawa. If the <lb/>
hon. member for Banff between now and <lb/>
next session advocated the Alberta auton<lb break="no"/>omy movement he would at least do a <lb/>
great deal of good in calling attention to <lb/>
the system under which the Territories <lb/>
were not working. It might be a very <lb/>
good educative movement, and he (Mr. <lb/>
Haultain) certainly would not object to it, <lb/>
but if dreams were to be dreamed, and if <lb/>
visions were to be seen, they had better <lb/>
be dreamed and better be seen outside of <lb/>
that House, which after all had only to <lb/>
do with practical work. If however they <lb/>
were going to consider the larger subject <lb/>
it should be a little larger that the com<lb break="no"/>paratively small area of Alberta and Sask<lb break="no"/>atchewan for after all those names <lb/>
were only applied for post office purposes. <lb/>
Their consideration of their needs on that <lb/> 
    
    <cb/>

question should be just as broad as the <lb/>
whole of the Territories. And if they <lb/>
were gong to dream a dream, the dream <lb/>
he would like to dream would be the <lb/>
dream of one large province with all its <lb/>
varied resources; a dream of one large <lb/>
province with a united population, and <lb/>
not a divided population; and if that <lb/>
dream could come true he believed it <lb/>
would be a much better dream, and a <lb/>
much more desirable dream than the <lb/>
dream which was dreamed by the hon. <lb/>
member for Banff. A dream of one large <lb/>
province holding its own in confederation, <lb/>
the most powerful province in confeder<lb break="no"/>ation, would be a much more desirable <lb/>
thing to think about, and to speculate <lb/>
about, than a number of small areas con<lb break="no"/>fined in their own powers and in their in<lb break="no"/>fluence. The dream he would like to <lb/>
dream would be the dream of the largest <lb/>
province and the most powerful province <lb/>
in the greatest and most glorious country <lb/>
attached to the mightiest empire the world <lb/>
has ever seen. (Applause.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CLIN1">MR. CLINKSKILL</persName></p> 

<p>(Battleford) said the committee in con<lb break="no"/>sidering the report as contained in the <lb/>
memorial, had decided that there were <lb/>
three possible propositions to bring up in <lb/>
the matter. One was the consideration <lb/>
of bringing the whole of the Territories <lb/>
into one province; or two or more <lb/>
provinces, and the third was the consider<lb break="no"/>ation of an enlargement of their powers as <lb/>
they were at present. In regard to the <lb/>
idea of asking for provincial rights the <lb/>
committee were not in a position very <lb/>
well to understand what was meant by <lb/>
the expression "provincial autonomy," <lb/>
as it had been used by some members of <lb/>
the House. The committee endeavored <lb/>
to find out their views, but were unable <lb/>
to find any union amongst them as to what <lb/>
they really wanted. Some did not want <lb/>
a province at all, they had no idea of <lb/>
provincial rights; some would be willing <lb/>
to take a province provided they took in <lb/>
half of Assiniboia and half of Saskatche<lb break="no"/>wan, and made them a province; others <lb/>
would be willing to go int as a province <lb/>
provided Athabasca was taken in. But <lb/>
the committee could not come to any con<lb break="no"/>clusion as to whether those hon. members <lb/>
were able to agree as to what they meant <lb/>
by provincial autonomy. Under the cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances the committee agreed that the <lb/>
best thing they could do would be to em<lb break="no"/>body their ideas which would be makeing <lb/>
a step forward in the position in which <lb/>
they now were. Regarding the powers <lb/>
which it would be for their advantage to <lb/>
have. Powers they did not wish to have <lb/>
they had not embodied in the report. <lb/>
He would refer especially to the point of <lb/>
borrowing money and the administration <lb/>
of criminal jurisdiction. As far as the <lb/>
arguments of the hon. member for Banff <lb/>
were concerned he did not think they <lb/>
moved in the right direction to convince <lb/>
that they had necessity to consider the <lb/>
question of asking for full provincial <lb/>
rights yet. That must come some day <lb/>
they were all agreed. The amendment <lb/>
proposed did not find fault with any of <lb/>
the propositions embodied in the memor<lb break="no"/>ial, it was not finding fault with any of <lb/>
the powers asked for, it was simply <lb/>
brought up on a few words contained in <lb/>
one of the clauses, which was brought in <lb/>
in parenthesis, the printing of which <lb/>
would indicate that it was simply a refer<lb break="no"/>ence to a condition which they would <lb/>
be in at some future date, when they <lb/>
would be in a position to ask for provin<lb break="no"/>cial powers for one, two, or more provin<lb break="no"/>ces. The fact of those words being in <lb/>
did not bind that it should be one pro<lb break="no"/>vince, or two, or any number at all. In <lb/>
the N.W.T. they had been for some time <lb/>
gradually moving towards increased pow<lb break="no"/>ers. The powers that had been granted <lb/>
to them had been exercised with judgment <lb/>
and with good results. The argument had <lb/>
been brought forward that they should <lb/>
ask for a great deal more than they ex<lb break="no"/>pected. He took issue with that. If <lb/>
they put forward claims on just principles <lb/>
and gave good sound reasons in support <lb/>
of them, they would be more likely to get <lb/>
what they wanted than if they asked for <lb/>
something which they could not justify. <lb/>
It had been said they had made progress <lb/>
slowly. He admitted they had not got <lb/>
the powers they asked for immediately, <lb/>
but they had had a change of administra<lb break="no"/>tion at Ottawa, whether <lb/>
Conservative or Liberal, there was always <lb/>
a thing hanging over those Governments, <lb/>
and that was shortness of money, and <lb/>
they would doubtless find that it did not <lb/>
matter what administration it was, they <lb/>
would always be inclined to keep as much <lb/>
of the money in their own hands as pos<lb break="no"/>sible. That was to say, they would not <lb/>
be willing to give the Territories any more <lb/>
money than they were entitled to, and it <lb/>
was necessary for them all the more de<lb break="no"/>cidedly to show what they actually requir<lb break="no"/>ed and they were not asking more than <lb/>
they could make use of. As to the devel<lb break="no"/>opment of the coal fields in Alberta, that <lb/>
would be very largely dependent upon the <lb/>
population of the Territories. It was all <lb/>
very well to say they could get a large <lb/>
market in the south, but there was be <lb/>
tween them and the south a wall of <lb/>
tariffs, and there was every prospect that <lb/>
that wall would be built higher every <lb/>
day, so that it would be a handicap upon <lb/>
the Alberta coal fields as regards markets. <lb/>
It would be better for Alberta to aid in <lb/>
getting the population into the Territories <lb/>
which would give a market for the miner<lb break="no"/>als of Alberta and which would result in <lb/>
getting the population into Alberta, and <lb/>
that again result in consuming the pro<lb break="no"/>ductions of the Territories. As regards <lb/>
the borrowing of money on public credit, <lb/>
he might say that in order to do that, they <lb/>
must have good security. He could not <lb/>
    
    <cb/>

see where the money was to come from, if <lb/>
they had a province such as Alberta, ex<lb break="no"/>cept from direct taxation, and direct tax<lb break="no"/>ation was always a cry which tended to <lb/>
keep population from going into the coun<lb break="no"/>try. The freer they could make a coun<lb break="no"/>try as far as direct taxation was concern<lb break="no"/>ed, the more likely they would be to get <lb/>
population. The hon. member for Banff <lb/>
instanced a cry that came from Saskatche<lb break="no"/>wan for provincial autonomy. He (Mr. <lb/>
Clinkskill) did not know that the hon. <lb/>
member was referring to anything except <lb/>
that once upon a time a very slight wail <lb/>
was heard to come from that vast terri<lb break="no"/>tory, but it was of such a very weak na<lb break="no"/>ture that it never reached very far, and <lb/>
they had heard nothing of it since that <lb/>
one time it was given expression to. He <lb/>
could not talk for the people of Saskatche<lb break="no"/>wan in the same way the hon. member <lb/>
talked for the people of Alberta, but he <lb/>
did know that he was in favor of one pro<lb break="no"/>vince and not of two, and he was in favor <lb/>
of a gradual development of the powers <lb/>
they had until the arrival of the time <lb/>
when the step into a province would be a <lb/>
very short step to take. He could not <lb/>
follow the hon. gentleman's figures. He <lb/>
showed that 78 per cent of the revenue <lb/>
was got from Alberta and 30 per cent. was <lb/>
spent on schools. He (Mr. Clinkskill) <lb/>
was very sorry to hear the hon. member <lb/>
from Yorkton accused of levity in speak<lb break="no"/>ing of that matter. The charge of levity <lb/>
should have been raised against the hon. <lb/>
member for Banff for raising the argu<lb break="no"/>ment that the country used so much on <lb/>
the one hand, and on the other hand spent <lb/>
so little in a proper direction. Certainly <lb/>
he (Mr. Clinkskill) did not think that <lb/>
was an argument in favor of a people <lb/>
being allowed full provincial powers. <lb/>
He was sorry the hon. member for Banff <lb/>
had not by this time come to reason, and <lb/>
was not assisting them in that progress <lb/>
which was desirable. At one time the <lb/>
hon. gentleman's career in that House was <lb/>
directly opposed to the progress of the <lb/>
House, and the move he was making now <lb/>
was nothing different from the stand he <lb/>
took at that time. The development that <lb/>
had taken place in their powers in the <lb/>
Territories, they had not to thank they <lb/>
the hon. member for Banff for. In con<lb break="no"/>clusion he (Mr. Clinkskill) said he was in <lb/>
favor of all the claims laid down in the <lb/>
memorial. He would like to have <lb/>
those granted, and he would like <lb/>
to say that if they be not grant<lb break="no"/>ed, or were not granted at an <lb/>
early day, he would be in favor of one pro<lb break="no"/>vince but not of two provinces. (Hear, <lb/>
hear). <lb/></p> 

<p>By permission of the House <lb/></p>
    
    <p rendition="simple:centre">
<persName ref="pers:BRET1">MR. BRETT</persName> <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
was allowed to speak. He said it would <lb/>
occur from the remarks just made <lb/>
by the hon. gentleman from Battleford <lb/>
that it was heresy, or taknig a stand <lb/>
against everything that was good and <lb/>
right in the direction of the progress of <lb/>
this country, to bring up a question that <lb/>
he (Mr. Brett) thought was an important <lb/>
one. However, the point of view raised <lb/>
by the amendment was not one that was <lb/>
not without suggestion. If hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men would read the paragraph in the <lb/>
memorial upon which the amendment was <lb/>
based, they would see there was practical <lb/>
invitation to the House to discuss one or <lb/>
more vital questions. There was an in<lb break="no"/>vitation there to discuss distinctly they <lb/>
principle involved in the amendment. It <lb/>
distinctly stated "one or more." If there <lb/>
happened to be a number of gentlemen in <lb/>
the House who conscientiously believed <lb/>
that when the time does come for the <lb/>
division of the Territories, and that it <lb/>
should not be a question of, one but of <lb/>
two, it was a proper thing and a proper <lb/>
time to discuss that in the frankest and <lb/>
fullest manner. That was the reason the <lb/>
amendment had been presented. So far <lb/>
as being unanimous, he dared say the <lb/>
House could be made perfectly unanimous. <lb/>
He did not think there was a dissenting <lb/>
voice in the House with reference to the <lb/>
memorial generally speaking, but there <lb/>
was a difference of opinion with reference <lb/>
to whether there should be one or two <lb/>
provinces. The hon. member for Macleod <lb/>
Mr. Haultain) wished the House to un<lb break="no"/>derstand that if the amendment was <lb/>
accepted it would practically nullify the <lb/>
whole of the memorial. If the amend<lb break="no"/>ment did that then most undoubtedly the <lb/>
clause as it appeared in the memorial <lb/>
nullified the balance of it. The amend<lb break="no"/>ment anticipated going on for some time <lb/>
at least on the lines indicated by the <lb/>
memorial, only that it asked that amend<lb break="no"/>ments be passed at next session of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment at Ottawa. So that the amendment <lb/>
aimed at really being immediately pro<lb break="no"/>gressive in that direction while the mem<lb break="no"/>orial did not. It had been asked, on what <lb/>
credit would the province of Alberta bor<lb break="no"/>row money? He answered, on precisely <lb/>
the same kind of credit as Manitoba <lb/>
borrowed money. Manitoba had no lands <lb/>
to pledge any more than they had; she <lb/>
pledged the credit of the province in its <lb/>
future on the public buildings already <lb/>
existing and hereafter to be built, and <lb/>
Alberta could take the same basis of <lb/>
credit, only with this difference, that Al<lb break="no"/>berta would have a very much larger <lb/>
country, if the extent of country was to <lb/>
be taken into consideration. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:INSI1">MR. INSINGER</persName>,</p>
    
    <p>
in speaking to the amendment, said he <lb/>
did at one time suggest to the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Banff that the amendment would <lb/>
better have come up as an amendment to <lb/>
the memorial as a whole. If it was not <lb/>
opposed to the memorial, then the hon. <lb/>
member must take the horn of the alter<lb break="no"/>native and profess that it did not mean <lb/>
anything at all. The amendment should <lb/>
have been brought in either as an amend<lb break="no"/>ment to the whole memorial, or as a sep<lb break="no"/>arate resolution. <lb/></p> 

<cb/>

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:SIMP1">MR. SIMPSON</persName></p>
    
    <p>
(Red Deer) said he thought the member <lb/>
of the House had no differences of opin<lb break="no"/>ion as to the memorial, and as to the differ<lb break="no"/>ence between the memorial and the <lb/>
amendment, for his part he would be <lb/>
in favor of the memorial as it stood. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:MCCA6">MR. McCAULAY</persName></p>
    
    <p>
(Edmonton) said he had received a good <lb/>
deal of information from listening to the <lb/>
debate. While he was very sorry to find <lb/>
out that Alberta had been charged with <lb/>
        being so — intemperate, he might say <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
(laughter) he had often heard it said <lb/>
that the people in the N.W.T., and es<lb break="no"/>pecially in Alberta, were cheerful drink<lb break="no"/>ers, yet he did not know they could be <lb/>
charged with so much in that line. But <lb/>
with regard to educational matters he <lb/>
thought they were up with the times, that <lb/>
they kept pace with the other parts of the <lb/>
Territories, and he was sorry to hear the <lb/>
insulting remarks of the hon. member <lb/>
for Yorkton respecting that matter. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:INSI1">Mr. Insinger</persName>: I simply tied to explain <lb/>
away certain things which the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Banff had said; but the charge me <lb/>
with having insulted Alberta because I <lb/>
tried to explain away certain insulting <lb/>
references by the hon. member for Banff <lb/>
is wrong. I accepted the actual state<lb break="no"/>ment of the hon. member for Banff, and <lb/>
any reflections upon that statement should <lb/>
not be made towards me, but to the hon. <lb/>
member who made the statement. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCA6">Mr. McCaulay</persName>: I will then charge <lb/>
the hon. member with repeating waht the <lb/>
hon. member for Banff did say. (Roars of <lb/>
laughter.) While I accpet that with a <lb/>
good grace and think any hon. member <lb/>
in this House should accept any statement <lb/>
there is one thing: when it comes down <lb/>
to charging Alberta with committing <lb/>
three-quarters of the crime committed in <lb/>
the Territories, I draw the line there <lb/>
(Hear, hear.) Continuing Mr. McCaulay <lb/>
said that while there was very little differ<lb break="no"/>ence, as far as he could see, in the amend<lb break="no"/>ment and the memorial, he thought that <lb/>
they all agreed that the time had now <lb/>
arrived for provincial autonomy. What <lb/>
    then should they quarrel of differ over <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
section where it said "one, two or more?" <lb/>
When the time came it would be time <lb/>
enough to decide whether it should be "one <lb/>
or two or more." Therefore he could not <lb/>
agree with the amendment. He would <lb/>
rather see one good province than two <lb/>
poor ones. He had made up his mind to <lb/>
support the memorial as it stood (Ap<lb break="no"/>plause.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:REID3">MR. REID</persName></p>
    
    <p>
(Prince Albert) said that after the <lb/>
expression made use of by the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Macleod that he expected to hear <lb/>
an expression from the borders of Sask<lb break="no"/>atchewan as to provincial rights, he might <lb/>
said that they hards nothing of provincial <lb/>
rights from there. There had been, some <lb/>
time ago, a wail from there, as the hon. <lb/>
member for Battleford had said, but it <lb/>
was buried in the back woods. He <lb/>
thought they were going on satisfactorily <lb/>
in the Territories and that the memorial <lb/>
was in the right direction. It had taken <lb/>
the Territories 20 years to reach the pre<lb break="no"/>sent stage and he thought it would, at <lb/>
the present rate of progress, be 20 years <lb/>
more before they were ready for provin<lb break="no"/>cial autonomy. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MAGR1">Mr. Magrath</persName>: For fear of losing the <lb/>
little support I had in connection with <lb/>
this amendment, I will, with the permis<lb break="no"/>sion of the House, withdraw it. <lb/></p> 

<p>Leave was given, and the amendment <lb/>
was withdrawn. <lb/></p> 

<p>The House then went into committee <lb/>
of the whole at 10:45. Progress was <lb/>
immediately reported. The memorial <lb/>
    passed a second and third time, was [<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
curred in, and a resolution adopted to the <lb/>
effect that His Honor the Lieut. Gover<lb break="no"/>nor be asked to forward the memorial to <lb/>
the Governor-General-in-Council. <lb/></p> 

<p>Adjournment of the House took place <lb/>
at 10:50. <lb/></p> <lb/>
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>