<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgASLA_1896-10-08"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>, <date when="1896-10-08">8 October 1896</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA">
          

               <editor>Walter Scott</editor>.
          
         
          <title>The Leader</title>.
                    

          <date when="1896-10-15"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>: <publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="5"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1896-10-15_Page_005.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
     
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-06-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

          <change who="lyallg" when="2018-06-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="The_Leader_1896-10-15_Page_005">
         <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1896-10-15_Page_005.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="5" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1896-10-15_Page_005.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">5</fw> <fw type="running">THE LEADER, THURSDAY EVENING, OCTOBER 15, 1896.</fw>
            


<head rendition="simple:centre">
     THE LEGISLATURE.      
 </head>

            <head rendition="simple:centre">An Able Speech by the Mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Moose Jaw.<lb/>
            </head>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">the Requirements and claims of  
     <lb/>The Territories from Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment well set Froth-Further<lb/>Considerations of School Legis<lb break="no"/>lation- Doctors' Fees and Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Notes.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p rendition="simple:centre">Thursday, 8th October, 1896. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <p rendition="simple:centre">CLAIM FOR INCREASED POWERS - ROSS 
     <lb/>MAKES OUT A STRONG CASE- SOMETHING<lb/>MUST BE DONE - THE HOUSE UNANIMOUS<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:ROSS11">Mr. Ross</persName>, in rising to move the <lb/>adoption of a motion which had been<lb/>some time before the House, said he wish<lb break="no"/>ed to refer to the position of the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly regarding memorials to the Parliament<lb/>of Canada, the position they had been in<lb/>heretofore, and his opinion with regard to <lb/>what views should be given, and at what<lb/>time, to the committee he proposed, should<lb/>it be appointed. It was nothing new for<lb/>the House to memorialize the Dominion<lb/>Government in regard to subjects contain<lb break="no"/>ed in the motion he was proposing. As<lb/>far back as 1886 the North-West Council<lb/>saw fit not only to memorialize the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government, but send a dele<lb break="no"/>gation to Ottawa to press upon Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and Parliament their views in regard<lb/>to their position. He was a member of<lb/>that delegation, and he remembered that <lb/>the Government gave them to understand<lb/>that they would be able to deal with the <lb/>Territories in a somewhat different man<lb break="no"/>ner than they had been dealing with the <lb/>provinces, and in a somewhat different<lb/>manner than what the Territories were<lb/>then being dealt with. They asked for<lb/>something to be given in the shape of<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">RESPONSIBLE GOVERNMENT<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>but not in it entirety. The Dominion<lb/>Government brought in legislation, giving <lb/>certain powers to the House, and ex<lb break="no"/>tended powers to the Assembly when <lb/>established, but it was found that the <lb/>machinery they proposed to give did not<lb/>work well. He thought a great deal was <lb/>due to the members who had composed <lb/>the executive. He did not speak for<lb/>himself, because the difficulties had been<lb/>gone through with before he became a <lb/>member; but a great deal was due to <lb/>then for the manner in which they had<lb/>been able to work out, under the institu<lb/>tion, or the law as established by the<lb/>Dominion, as satisfactory a solution of<lb/>those difficulties as they had done. Prior<lb/>to 1887 it was necessary for the people in<lb/>the Territories to petition Parliament<lb/>through the House. It was the custome<lb/>of the old Council to memoralize the<lb/>Dominion Government on all subjects,—<lb/>in fact it was the only way the people of <lb/>the Territories could speak to the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion Parliament. But in 1887, in accord<lb break="no"/>ance with a memorial, the Dominion<lb/>Government saw fit to give the Territories<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">REPRESENTATION IN THE HOUSE OF COMMONS<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>and the Senate. The Territories then<lb/>sent to Parliament four members to <lb/>represent their views, and it<lb/>was through these members they<lb/>expected their petitions should be <lb/>placed before Parliament, and through <lb/>them they had their wants explained<lb/>and pressed before the Parliament of <lb/>Canada. But this particular subject it had<lb/>become a necessity for the Assembly to <lb/>deal with it by memorial because it was<lb/>one which appertained to that House itself.<lb/>It was a question upon which the <lb/>House was seized of all facts, and in a<lb/>better position that Dominion members<lb/>to memorialize the Dominion Parliament.<lb/>In 1889 they memorialized Parliament<lb/>setting forth their position, and what they <lb/>considered to be their requirements. The <lb/>most important clause of that memorial<lb/>was that they asked for full responisble<lb/>government in teh Territories in addition<lb/>to the other powers possessed by the<lb/>Assembly granted by the British North <lb/>America Act, with the exception of that<lb/>most important power of raising money by<lb/>borrowing upon the public credit. In <lb/>1891 2 they again memorialized the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government, and the House was <lb/>of the same opinion as in 1889, respecting<lb/>the financial situation. He was pleased<lb/>to find that the Executive Committee at<lb/>no time in 1893-4-5 deviated one lots<lb/>from the views expressed by the Assembly<lb/>of 1889-92. Of course they had from<lb/>time to time very forcibly pointed out to <lb/>the Government the great needs of the<lb/>Territories under the institution which<lb/>had been provided : the increased services<lb/>on account of the increased population,<lb/>and it had been in such a way as to merit<lb/>the confidences of the House. He would <lb/>now endeavor to point out what in his<lb/>opinion should by the text of the next<lb/>memorial should the House see fit to<lb/>grant the Committee, and should that<lb/>Committee report to the House with re-<lb break="yes"/>grad to the subjects mentioned in the mo<lb break="no"/>tion. In the first place they required<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">AN EXTENSION OF POWERS.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>What extension did they require? The <lb/>powers they mow had as an Assembly very<lb/>nearly approached the powers the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces had except in regard to the great<lb/>power of borrowing money upon the public<lb/>credit. They required an extension that<lb/>instead of an Executive Committee, an <lb/>Executive council should be given the<lb/>House. Even supposing to day they were<lb/>able to exercise nearly all the power of<lb/>a Council, still if even only for status<lb/>it would give the House they should have <lb/>the powers of a Council. but it would <lb/>do more than that. It would place them<lb/>in the position that the Executive-Council<lb/>would also have the power of calling the House<lb/>together when they might see fit. It<lb/>would also have the power of advising as<lb/>to the dissolution of teh House; the pow<lb break="no"/>er to advise as to who should act during <lb/>elections in this country. They had for<lb break="no"/>tunately had Lieut.-Governors of late<lb/>who had always acceded to their request,<lb/>he believed, in this regard. But the time<lb/>might arrive when the Lieut. Governor in <lb/>the Territories might be arbitrary in these <lb/>matters, and they might find it work de<lb break="no"/>trimentally to the House. Again; they <lb/>would be given the<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">POWER TO APPOINT THE MAGISTRACY<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>of this country. They were entitled to <lb/>that as were the provinces, and he thought<lb/>they were in as good a position to regu<lb break="no"/>lating the appointment of coroners in this<lb/>country. Above all that, the Assembly<lb/>would be placed in this position that in<lb/>dealing with the higher powers at Ottawa<lb/>the House, through an executive council, <lb/>would be in a different position than it is<lb/>today. then again they would have as<lb/>absolute powers as the provinces with re<lb break="no"/>gard to legislation. To day they might<lb/>legislate upon any subject, and then their<lb/>legislation was subject to legislation at<lb/>Ottawa already on the Statute Book, or<lb/>which may be placed on the Statute Book<lb/>of the Dominions. As a case in point, he<lb/>referred to the Infectious Disease <lb/>(Animals) Ordinance. For many years<lb/>they had what was known as "glanders"<lb/>among horse herds of this country. It<lb/>was a serious matter, and the House<lb/>legislated upon it. They found no legis<lb break="no"/>
        
<cb/>

          lation had been passed by the Dominion<lb/>Government with regard to it, and he<lb/>believed he might say without any chance<lb/>of contradiction that the Assembly dealt<lb/>with it for a year or two longer he be<lb break="no"/>lieved that would have been stamped out<lb/>of this country. But a year ago legislation<lb/>was passed at Ottawa taking away the <lb/>jurisdiction of the Assembly, and they<lb/>were compelled to stop their steps in that<lb/>direction. In that one case it was shown <lb/>that the Assembly should have power<lb/>to deal with those questions, and not sub<lb break="no"/>ject anything except veto. He also<lb/>thought they should have further power<lb/>to legislate in regard to civil rights and <lb/>property. At present they had<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">A CLASHING JURISDICTION<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The land registration law was entirely<lb/>under the control of the Dominion by one<lb/>of its Acts. And in many cases they were<lb/>confronted with this question of juris<lb break="no"/>diction. The time had come when they<lb/>should have complete control in regard to <lb/>that subject. They found in the esti<lb break="no"/>mates $18,000 for the maintenance of <lb/>offices in the Territories, but they didn't<lb/>find a credit in regard to the revenue from<lb/>that particular source. The time had<lb/>come when they should deal- and they <lb/>could do it- with their financial laws,<lb/>because at the present time the Income<lb/>from the registration service was <lb/>about sufficient to cover the ex<lb break="no"/>penditures, Again; he considered<lb/>they should have legislation from <lb/>Ottawa along the same lines as the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of Manitoba respecting the roads<lb/>and road allowances. To-day the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly had to go through a torturous route to <lb/>obtain any action in regard to the closing<lb/>of old roads or opening up of new roads.<lb/>That question became a very burning one<lb/>in Manitoba and was dealt with by the<lb/>Dominion Parliament a few years ago by<lb/>giving the provinces certain powers of<lb/>legislation. The Assembly should ask<lb/>that similar powers be extended to the<lb/>Territories; they had a right to control<lb/>those matters. His reaction for making the<lb/>motion in the way he did was that the <lb/>House might discuss the question prior to<lb/>going into the committee . He thought they<lb/>should have a thorough discussion so that<lb/>when the committee sat, if it was ap<lb break="no"/>pointed, it would be seized of the views<lb/>of the members of the House and be<lb/>more able to intelligently draft a memo<lb break="no"/>rial in accordance with the wishes of the<lb/>majority of the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">THEY MUST BE A UNIT<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>in regard to this question if they expected<lb/>to get anything. It would never do to<lb/>have differences of opinion in regard to <lb/>what position or status they should be<lb/>placed in. Were they to have serious<lb/>differences of opinion with regard to that,<lb/>they might expect, when the Parliment<lb/>of Canada came to deal with them, that it<lb/>would be said "The people there are so<lb/>divided that we think we had better leave<lb/>this over for a year or two until they have<lb/>come to some conclusion as to what it is<lb/>they exactly want." The Assembly should<lb/>therefore thresh teh question well out<lb/>so that the memorial may express the<lb/>opinion of the House as a whole. He <lb/>would now deal with<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">THEIR PRESENT CONDITION FINANCIALLY.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>He would not exactly take the line taken<lb/>by past memorials for the purpose of <lb/>pressing their claim. It was very easy for<lb/>them to make out as they did in 1889<lb/>and in 1891-2, a very strong case showing<lb/>that they ought to be treated exactly the same as <lb/>other provinces in regard to their consti<lb break="no"/>tution. They must take a little different<lb/>ground in dealing with their financial<lb/>circumstances. If, for instance, they did<lb/>not ask for power to take over the<lb/>administration of justice pure and simple,<lb/>in the Territories, then they must admit<lb/>they were not exactly in the same position<lb/>as the provinces. If they did not ask for<lb/>power to borrow money upon the public <lb/>credit, and to subsidise railways, they<lb/>were again in a different position to the<lb/>people of the provinces. He proposed to<lb/>make the argument along the lines of their <lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">NEEDS AT THE PRESENT TIME,<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>and the services which would accrue from<lb/>year to year, and what would be required<lb/>to carry out those services. As had been<lb/>well put by the leaders of the House, the<lb/>present constitution was not of their<lb/>creating; it was a creation of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Parliament. They had placed the<lb/>Assembly to its present position. The<lb/>Dominion Parliament had for years<lb/>treated them as a branch of the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment of the Interior, and it was the right<lb/>and duty of the Dominion Government to<lb/>provide the money to run the machinery<lb/>which they (the Dominion Government )<lb/>has set in motion. Money, it had been<lb/>said, was like the oil to machinery, and if<lb/>they had created the machinery they must<lb/>provide the oil (hear, hear). In 1891 the<lb/>population of the Territories was 66, 799.<lb/>That was according to the Dominion<lb/>census. At the same time they found<lb/>that they amount granted for teh services<lb/>which were then being rendered was<lb/>$211, 200. that sum would be far more<lb/>than sufficient if the amount they were<lb/>getting to-day was anything like sufficient<lb/>for the Territories. But at that time it<lb/>was not more than sufficient; it was a <lb/>fair grant to the Territories. They had,<lb/>however, increased in their population,<lb/>and necessarily the services had increased,<lb/>from year to year the Executive had to<lb/>submit estimates to the House, and they<lb/>were painfully aware of the fact that<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">THEY HAD NOT SUFFICIENT MONEY<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>to meet the increasing services. It must<lb/>be a source of pleasure to know that<lb/>although the Territories were no making<lb/>great strides in population, still some<lb/>substantial increase in being made. In<lb/>1894 the population was 86,000 in round<lb/>numbers. If the population had increased<lb/>from 66, 799 and in 1891 to 86, 000 in 1894 it<lb/>was fair for them to assume that the<lb/>population had increased in that ratio they would<lb/>have to-day 113, 000 people in the Territo<lb break="no"/>ries. With that number of people the<lb/>services had increased necessarily in the<lb/>same ratio as between 66, 000 people and<lb/>113, 000 people. They found that instead<lb/>of $211, 000 as in 1891, they had $242, 000<lb/>to provide for these services. In other<lb/>words,as was well and ably put in the <lb/>House of Commons by a former member<lb/>of the Assembly the other day, they had<lb/>increased in their grants 15 per cent.<lb/>while their population had increased 70<lb/>per cent. That surely must be considered <lb/>by the Parliament of Canada in dealing<lb/>with the Territories; they saw that they<lb/>has increased from 66, 799 in 1891 to an<lb/>estimated population at the present day<lb/>of 113, 000. he would now turn for a<lb/>moment or two to the statement's which<lb/>had been made in the House with regard<lb/>to<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">WHAT SHOULD BE THEIR SUBSIDY<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>and the reasons why it should be so. He<lb/>was endeavoring from these statements to <lb/>prove that they were entitled to a larger<lb/>grant and to being put in the same posi<lb break="no"/>tion as the other provinces. They based<lb/>their calculations in former years nearly<lb/>altogether one estimated population; to-day<lb/>
      

        <cb/>

         
they were more able to come exactly to<lb/>their position. They had taken the in<lb break="no"/>crease between 1891 and 1894. With a<lb/>population of 113, 000 to-day, if they were<lb/>dealing with the Dominion Government<lb/>now as the provinces in asking for a sub<lb break="no"/>sidy, they might ask that the estimated<lb/>population be based upon a term of five<lb/>years. Were that done, they would find,<lb/>taking the same ratio of increase <lb/>as before stated they would be<lb/>entitled to an estimated popula<lb break="no"/>tion of 141, 000. The first item upon<lb/>which the subsidy was granted to the<lb/>different provinces was a per capita<lb/>grant on the estimated population. Un<lb break="no"/>der that head the Territories would, at<lb/>80 cents per head, to-day be entitled to<lb/>$112, 800, on the per capita subsidy.<lb/>Were the Territories dealing with the<lb/>Dominion Government upon the basis he<lb/>had stated they would be entitled to a<lb/>debt allowance, or a capitol amount, -<lb/> which was made up by an allowance made<lb/>per head to the different provinces of a <lb/>certain debt which was assumed by the<lb/>Dominion of Canada at Confederation. <lb/>Under that the Territories would be en<lb break="no"/>titled to $27.22 upon actual population.<lb/>That was the original computation at<lb/>confederation. Further debts were as<lb break="no"/>sumed from the older provinces, which<lb/>made it equal to $32.43 per head. Mani<lb break="no"/>toba was dealt with on that figure at the<lb/>last settlement made by them. To deal<lb/>with the Territories at this time, and<lb/>with an allowance of 5 per cent, they<lb/>would be entitled to a grant of $183, 229.<lb/>There was one other estimate in the sub<lb break="no"/>sidy of the provinces which the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, he supposed, would be entitled to.<lb/>That was an allowance for the cost of <lb/>government. The allowance for the differ<lb break="no"/>ent provinces ranged from $30, 000 to<lb/>$80, 000. In Manitoba, he believed, it<lb/>was $50, 000. If in the province of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba, with its smaller area to govern, they<lb/>were entitled to $50, 000 for cost of gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, it was fair to say that the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, - having an area many times larger<lb/>than Manitoba, having difficulties to over<lb break="no"/>come many times greater than Manitoba,-<lb break="yes"/>it was fair to say that the Territories should at<lb/>least be entitled to $50, 000 under that<lb/>head. They were therefore<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">ENTITLED TO THE SUM OF $346, 029.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>under those three heads alone. One other<lb/>source of revenue they could expect to<lb/>increase their income from was the land.<lb/>But all that could be done at the present<lb/>time would be able to make demand on account<lb/>of the want of lands. They could not at<lb/>this time go into any actual computation<lb/>and say what they would be willing to<lb/>accept in that regard. The province of<lb/>Manitoba, with only a small population<lb/>in its early days, felt that when the Dom<lb break="no"/>inion Government made certain proposi<lb break="no"/>tions to them with regard to the subsidy,<lb/>and saw they would allow Manitoba $45,<lb break="no"/>000 in lieu of the lands, they thought<lb/>they were getting quite a snap, and took<lb/>it quickly. And then at their leisure<lb/>they regretted it, for in a short time<lb/>Manitoba found that any such settlement<lb/>as that would be such as to put to pro<lb break="no"/>vince in a position as not to be able pos<lb break="no"/>sibly to carry on the business of govern<lb break="no"/>ment. They therefore had to go to the<lb/>Dominion Government and ask for better<lb/>terms in connection with that particular<lb/>item. He was very much mistaken if<lb/>Manitoba to-day was not in a very bad <lb/>position on account of the settlement they<lb/>made in regard to the lands. The Terri<lb break="no"/>tories must not put themselves in that<lb/>position by saying what they would be<lb/>willing to accept for many years in regard<lb/>to the great heritage they had become<lb/>possessed of. There was that<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">REVENUE COMING FROM THE LAND<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>which had been bartered away from the<lb/>community. The people, and they alone,<lb/>should be entitled to a revenue from that.<lb/>That had been recognized by the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion Government in dealing with different<lb/>provinces. In view of the fact that the<lb/>land had passed from them, the govern,<lb/>ment made Prince Edward Island an<lb/>allowance of $40, 000 a year. It was pos<lb break="no"/>sible the Territories could say they should<lb/>receive a certain a amount in view of the<lb/>fact that any revenue which accrued <lb/>from the land did not come to us but went to<lb/>the Dominion. It would be argued pos<lb break="no"/>sibly by the Government of Canada, and<lb/>by the people of Eastern Canada, that<lb/>there were no revenues from the lands in<lb/>this country. But there was a very ready<lb/>answer to that. He could not see how it<lb/>would be possible to gave a revenue from<lb/>the lands of this country when the lands <lb/>had been given away for public works in<lb/>this country. There had been given away <lb/>millions of acres of land here for subsides<lb/>to railways. The people of eastern Can<lb break="no"/>ada said, "we have built for you a large<lb/>public work in the building of the C.P.R."<lb/>True, but that work was undertaken for<lb/>Canada, and it was supposed it would be<lb/>of course a greater benefit to Eastern<lb/>Canada than to Western Canada, because <lb/>the population was in Eastern Canada.<lb/>Not only were the Territories placed in<lb/>the position of having so much to pay per<lb/>head on the indebtedness incurred<lb/>in the building of this road,- he meant in <lb/>the subsidy given to the C.P.R.,-but<lb/>they were also in the position that after<lb/>having paid their share equally with the<lb/>other people in cash, they had had their<lb/>lands taken away from them. They must<lb/>be taken into consideration, and he had<lb/>no doubt would be, by the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. Had the Territories been plac<lb/>ed in the same position as the other pro<lb break="no"/>vinces; had the Territories been, for the <lb/>building of this railroad, simply taxed so<lb/>much per head; had an extra csh sub<lb break="no"/>sidy of $25, 000, 000 been given to the<lb/>C.P.R. instead of the acres of land sub<lb break="no"/>sidy, which was valued at $1 per acre, it<lb/>would be found that Canada as a whole <lb/>would to-day be paying an increased<lb/>yearly interest of $750, 000. To<lb break="no"/>day the Territories had to pay<lb/>their portion of that $750, 000 of<lb/>interest upon the $250, 000, 000 of cash,<lb/>which was given to the C.P.R., and at the<lb/>time they were placed in the position of<lb/>having had taken from them their only<lb/>sources of revenue,- the lands. In all the<lb/>provinces the railroads had been subsidis<lb/>ed by cash subsides. In the Territories<lb/>not only had they subsidised the C.P.R.,<lb/>but even railways built in Manitoba had<lb/>been bonussed by lands taken out of the <lb/>Territories. To his mind<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">SUCH PROCEEDING WAS OUTRAGEOUS<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>unless the Dominion of Canada intended to<lb/>give the Territories a cash subsidy in lieu<lb/>of the land taken from them. To show<lb/>that the Parliament of Canada should at<lb/>once give them an increased subsidy,<lb/>he would point out that in 1891-2 there<lb/>were in operation in the Territories 245<lb/>schools; at the end of 1895 there were <lb/>from 395 to 400. They had increased<lb/>enormously in that service. Other ser<lb break="no"/>vices also had increased. The increased of<lb/>population in this country there had been<lb/>an increase of settlements, they had,<lb/>unfortunately in some instances, branched<lb/>out until there were<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">SETTLEMENTS AT THE VERY REMOTEST<lb/>OF PARTS<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>and facilities must be provided for mar<lb break="no"/>keting which people produced. With [...]<lb/>
            </p>


         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>