<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgASLA_1896-11-12" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>,
<date when="1896-11-12" cert="medium">12 November 1896</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA"> <editor>Walter Scott</editor>.
<title>The Leader</title>. <date from="1896-11-05" to="1896-11-19"/>.
<pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="5"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1896-11-12_Page_004.hocr.html"/> </item>
    <item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1896-11-12_Page_005_copy.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-12-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-12-14">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1896-11-12_Page_004"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1896-11-12_Page_004.jpg"/> </surface>
    <surface xml:id="The_Leader_1896-11-12_Page_005"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1896-11-12_Page_005.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="4" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1896-11-12_Page_004.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="num">4</fw>

<fw type="running">THE LEADER, THURSDAY EVENING, NOVEMBER 13, 1896.</fw> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">SECESSION</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">Shall the Territories Be <lb/>
Divided?</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">The Debate in the Assembly on <lb/>
    the Constitutional Memorial — Dr. Brett Proposes the Princi<lb break="no"/>ple of Secession of Alberta — In<lb break="no"/>singer's Reply — Magrath for <lb/>
    Secession — Fearon Champions <lb/>
Unity.</head> 

<p>The Memorial to the Governor-General <lb/>
in Council endorsed by the Assembly, <lb/>
setting forth the position of the Territo<lb break="no"/>ries and our immediate requirements, was <lb/>
published in full in THE LEADER last <lb/>
week. This week we commence the <lb/>
report of the debate on the question. THE <lb/>
LEADER possesses the only accurate and <lb/>
complete report of this debate that exists <lb/>
or was taken. It was probably the most <lb/>
important debate that has taken place in <lb/>
the Assembly for years, and, as such, is <lb/>
    deserving of the space which will be de<lb break="no"/>voted to it:— <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:ROSS11">MR. ROSS</persName></p>
    
    <p>
in moving that the House go into com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the whole to consider the drafted <lb/>
memorial from the special committee, <lb/>
setting forth the legislate and financial <lb/>
position of the Assembly, suggested that <lb/>
if discussion were to take place on the <lb/>
contents of the memorial, asking for Ter<lb break="no"/>ritorial autonomy as against provincial <lb/>
autonomy, it would be better for it to <lb/>
take place at once rather than in commit<lb break="no"/>tee where questions of principle ought not <lb/>
to be dealt with. Having already made a <lb/>
lengthy speech regarding the subject, he <lb/>
need say nothing now, except to express <lb/>
his pleasure that the memorial practially <lb/>
was along lines he had suggested. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:BRET1">MR. BRETT</persName></p>
    
    <p>
(Banff) said he agreed the time for pre<lb break="no"/>senting the memorial had arrived. The <lb/>
present question was probably the most <lb/>
important the House had before it for con<lb break="no"/>sideration. While, however, it was <lb/>
only a temporary measure the memorial asked <lb/>
for, he was onle of those who believed the <lb/>
time had come when they should with no <lb/>
uncertain sound tell the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, or indicate to them in what <lb/>
position they would like the Territories <lb/>
placed. He was not going to state that <lb/>
the memorial should indicate that a more <lb/>
radical change than was asked for therein <lb/>
should take place at once. It was a serious <lb/>
thing to too rapidly get to an advanced <lb/>
condition if the conditions of the country <lb/>
would not warrent it; still at the same <lb/>
time it was equally bad that they should <lb/>
linger along and not do that which they <lb/>
considered was for the best advancement <lb/>
of the country. In considering that <lb/>
question they were called upon to consider <lb/>
two great principles. In the first place <lb/>
should they ask for responsible govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and if they did hould they ask it <lb/>
for the Territories as a whole? He did <lb/>
not think that was somehting they could <lb/>
arrive at very suddenly, nor did he think <lb/>
it was probably wise to take his ideas or <lb/>
opinions on the matter, for everyone <lb/>
should be prepared to give his own views, <lb/>
and have good reasons for these views. <lb/>
There was no use disguising the fact that if <lb/>
the people of the Territories as a whole <lb/>
were asked "Do you want the Territories <lb/>
errected into a privince such as Ontario, <lb/>
or any other province in the Dominion?" <lb/>
he believed a large majority would at once <lb/>
exclaim "No!" (Hear, hear.) That <lb/>
answer would be very largely due to the <lb/>
fact that many people were not sufficiently <lb/>
educated on what it was really meant to get <lb/>
provincial powers and to be established <lb/>
into a province. Many people were <lb/>
laboring under mistaken ideas with refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the expenses that would naturally <lb/>
attach to the erection of a province. Some <lb/>
had the idea that immediately on the <lb/>
erection of a province they would be <lb/>
forced to form municipalities. That would <lb/>
not be necessary. It was true that in <lb/>
Manitoba and other provinces muni<lb break="no"/>cipalities had been formed. British <lb/>
Columbia, however, was an exception. <lb/>
The Territories had just as much power <lb/>
to-day in forming municipalities as they <lb/>
would have, had they full responsible <lb/>
government. In British Columbia they <lb/>
had a less number of municipalities than <lb/>
there were in the Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>: they have direct taxa<lb break="no"/>tion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Mr. Brett</persName>: So far as direct taxation is <lb/>
concerned we possess all the powers to-<lb break="yes"/>day of direct taxation of any province of <lb/>
the dominion. The direct taxation in <lb/>
British Columbia was poll tax, and the <lb/>
Territories could have the same thing. <lb/>
But it did not follow that if the Territo<lb break="no"/>ries were formed into a province, these <lb/>
powers would be exercised any more than <lb/>
now. He thought that would dispose of <lb/>
that objection. There were sufficient <lb/>
other considerations for them to think of <lb/>
in debating their present conditions. Was <lb/>
it going to be any advantage to them? If <lb/>
it was going to cost more than now, if <lb/>
they were going to have less money to <lb/>
expend on the industries of the country, <lb/>
and on improvements in the country, <lb/>
under provincial formation of government, <lb/>
that would probably be one of the strong<lb break="no"/>est reasons that iw was not advisable. If <lb/>
they were going to undertake a responsi<lb break="no"/>bility they did not think they could carry <lb/>
out, that was probably another reason <lb/>
why they should give it due consideration. <lb/>
As the memorial sets out, they are not <lb/>
now receiving as much money as they are <lb/>
entitled to. It was fair to assume, then, <lb/>
that so far as their financial position was <lb/>
concerned they would be better off were <lb/>
they in the form of a province, than they <lb/>
are now. The next thing for considera<lb break="no"/>tion was, were they prepared to under<lb break="no"/>take the responsibilities? He claimed <lb/>
that the Territories, with the present <lb/>
population, were as well qualified to <lb/>
assume responsibility as was the province <lb/>
of Manitoba, when she undertook full <lb/>
    provincial government — as was the pro<lb break="no"/>vince of British Columbia (hear, hear). <lb/>
Another point was in what position would <lb/>
it place the Territories with reference to <lb/>
the making of laws? He believed in a <lb/>
better. Another question was, had the <lb/>
time arrived when they should take this <lb/>
step? Some whould say the time had not <lb/>
arrived because they were not strong <lb/>
enough to assume the responsibilities. <lb/>
They were not strong enough to go to the <lb/>
Dominion Government and make a con<lb break="no"/>tract with them. He was not unmindful <lb/>
of the fact that there was a great deal in <lb/>
being strong. The stronger they were the <lb/>
better bargain they could make. <lb/>
But as he understood the matter in <lb/>
which portion of the Domion had been <lb/>
taken into confederation and established <lb/>
as provinces, they entered in on a basis <lb/>
which was stated in the British North <lb/>
America Act and which no government <lb/>
could go behind. If the Territories were <lb/>
taken into confederation to-day they <lb/>
would only received the same amount pre <lb/>
capita as they would were they ten times <lb/>
stronger. They would certainly receive <lb/>
more as population grew for the expenses of <lb/>
government. That amount was regulated <lb/>
according to population. Manitoba re<lb break="no"/>ceived $35,000 for expenses of govern<lb break="no"/>ment, while latterly a better arrange<lb break="no"/>
    
    <cb/>

ment was made them, and now they <lb/>
get $50,000. The same thing would at<lb break="no"/>tach to the Territories. Another question <lb/>
    to consider was, — as to the amount of <lb/>
money that should be claimed in lieu of <lb/>
lands over which they had no control. <lb/>
That resolved itself into the quesiton of <lb/>
making a bargain. They could state an <lb/>
amount they were willing to begin with, <lb/>
and the bargain ned not be made in a <lb/>
manner that finally settled it, so that <lb/>
later they could go to the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and ask for a greater amount in <lb/>
lieu of their lands. Another objection, to <lb/>
undertake great responsibilities now, was <lb/>
that business was depressed, and we had <lb/>
hard times; wait until there was a reviv<lb break="no"/>al of trade, and so on. Times had been <lb/>
bad all over the world, and the sooner <lb/>
they could help themselves, all the sooner <lb/>
they would relieve themselves of the de<lb break="no"/>pressed conditions. They would not, of <lb/>
course, interfere with the cause that had <lb/>
made the depression so general, but they <lb/>
    could during depressed times, — if they <lb/>
    had it within their power, — go on with <lb/>
public works, do things that in other pro<lb break="no"/>vinces were doing good for the people. <lb/>
Thus, he said, they would be hastening <lb/>
the time when they would not be suffer<lb break="no"/>ing from the effects of these hard times. <lb/>
The question of the Territories remaining <lb/>
as they are must come to an end some<lb break="no"/>time, and it was for the House very <lb/>
largely to determine whether it should <lb/>
come now or be deferred. He believed <lb/>
that so long as they curtailed their demands <lb/>
simply to a portion of what they were <lb/>
entitled to, they would receive less and <lb/>
less every year. The time had come <lb/>
when they should tell the Dominion Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment in unmistakable terms that at <lb/>
    the expiration of this Assembly, — two <lb/>
    years hence, — they would expect full pro<lb break="no"/>vincial powers would be given to the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, either as a whole or divided. He <lb/>
had state there were no provincial taxes <lb/>
in Manitoba, nor would it be necessary to <lb/>
have them here. He might be asked,— <lb/>
In what way are you going to raise the <lb/>
revenue to carry on the Government? In <lb/>
the first place they would get a grant of <lb/>
money sufficient for the expenses of <lb/>
Government as they do in British Colum<lb break="no"/>bia. then they would have in their pow<lb break="no"/>er the collection of other taxes, license <lb/>
fees, and so forth, as in British Columbia. <lb/>
He would now refer more particularly to <lb/>
Alberta. If provincial government would <lb/>
be a good thing for the whole of the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, he claimed it would not be unfair <lb/>
for a portion of the Territories to ask for <lb/>
it. The time had come not only for the <lb/>
Territories as a whole to ask for provin<lb break="no"/>cial powers, but is was high time some<lb break="no"/>thing should be done in the direction of <lb/>
giving to the western portion of the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories full provincial powers. The con<lb break="no"/>ditions of the eastern and western por<lb break="no"/>tions of the Territories were quite differ<lb break="no"/>ent in many respects. In the west there <lb/>
were resources which would greatly assist <lb/>
the country generally if properly develop<lb break="no"/>ed. They had ranching, grain growing, <lb/>
minerals, coal, industries in coal oil and <lb/>
so on, which under proper conditions <lb/>
would make that protion of the country <lb/>
one of the richest, if not the richest part of <lb/>
the whole of the Territories. With proper <lb/>
railway facilities those cola fields would <lb/>
immediately be go into active operation. <lb/>
That would largely incrase the popula<lb break="no"/>tion in those parts. Those people would <lb/>
furnish a local market for those who rais<lb break="no"/>ed cattle, grain and vegatables to the <lb/>
north of them. They had diversified in<lb break="no"/>terests there but that made them stronger <lb/>
because they could deal with each other. <lb/>
The benefits they would obtain from <lb/>
having a provincial form of government <lb/>
would be that they would have power to <lb/>
to do as they thought best for the develop<lb break="no"/>ment of the country. Nearly every mem<lb break="no"/>ber of that Assembly must have a feeling <lb/>
of disappointment with reference to the <lb/>
North-West Territories. They had been <lb/>
    standing still — marking time. He did <lb/>
not think the best efforts had been made <lb/>
in their behalf. The powers of the pro<lb break="no"/>vince would make them progress much <lb/>
more rapidly than it had. British Col<lb break="no"/>umbia to-day was attracting the attention <lb/>
of the world. They had not got the rich <lb/>
mines in the western part of the Territo<lb break="no"/>ries as in British Columbia, but they had <lb/>
mines which if developed, they did not <lb/>
know but what they might be as valuable <lb/>
as those in British Columbia. The mines <lb/>
being developed in British Columbia <lb/>
would not be developed were it not <lb/>
that the B.C. government had made good <lb/>
roads, and so made it possible for the <lb/>
people to get into the mountainous dis<lb break="no"/>tricts. Had British Columbia been de<lb break="no"/>pendent year after year as the Territories <lb/>
were, and asking for somehting and only <lb/>
getting a small amount, that province <lb/>
would not have progressed as it had done. <lb/>
There was another thing which might be <lb/>
an argument in support of his contention <lb/>
for provincial powers for Alberta. There <lb/>
was a good deal in a name. The name <lb/>
"The Territories," had an altogether <lb/>
different sone to intending immigrants <lb/>
than that of a "province." They did not <lb/>
dissociate in their minds the United States <lb/>
territories from the North-West Territo<lb break="no"/>ries. It was a cold, inhospitable name. <lb/>
The Territories was thought ot be a land <lb/>
of cold and snow for about two-thirds of <lb/>
the year. He had heard many people say <lb/>
the name was bad, and retarded immigra<lb break="no"/>tion. People said they would try "a <lb/>
province." It was a more civilized name, <lb/>
    — a more congenial name. Were they a <lb/>
province, the name of "The province" <lb/>
would enhance their chances of getting <lb/>
immigrants above what they were now. <lb/>
He hoped the House would amend the <lb/>
terms of the memorial by recommending <lb/>
to the Dominion Govenrment, that at the <lb/>
expiration of thta Assembly the time <lb/>
would have arrived when Alberta and <lb/>
Athabasca should be erected into a pro<lb break="no"/>vince. he hoped the House would <lb/>
remember he was speaking for Alberta. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>: What part of Alberta? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Mr. Brett</persName>: I am speaking for that <lb/>
portion as I understand it, and for that <lb/>
portion where my interests lie. Some <lb/>
might say, Why ask for Alberta to be set <lb/>
apart? The eastern and western parts <lb/>
of Assiniboia had not such a large popula<lb break="no"/>tion as Alberta. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:INSI1">Mr. Insinger</persName>: No, no; the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman is very much out there. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Mr. Brett</persName> thought if the hon. member <lb/>
would carry out the figures as they wre <lb/>
in the memorial he would find that Albert<lb break="no"/>
    
    <cb/>

ta had a larger population that the <lb/>
Assiniboias. No, (continued Mr. Brett, <lb/>
looking at a paper crowded with figures) <lb/>
the two Assiniboias hat a pupulation of <lb/>
about 10 per cent. more than Alberta, <lb/>
carrying out the figures on the same lines <lb/>
as was done in the memorial. Some <lb/>
might say, why have not Assiniboia and <lb/>
Saskatchewan asked to be made into a <lb/>
province? He had never seen a stronger <lb/>
appeal made than Saskatchewan was mak<lb break="no"/>ing some time ago for some form of pro<lb break="no"/>vincial government. He would now speak <lb/>
for Alberta as he understood it; not for <lb/>
the whole of Alberta but a portion of it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>: Hear, hear. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Mr. Brett</persName>, continuing, said if they <lb/>
would look at the increase of population <lb/>
as figured out in the memorial they would <lb/>
find out that in the years 1891-94 it was <lb/>
57 per cent., much larger than in Assini<lb break="no"/>boia. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PAGE3">Mr. Page</persName>: Does the hon. member con<lb break="no"/>tend that the increase has been the same <lb/>
during the last two years, that it was <lb/>
during the three preceding years? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Dr. Brett</persName> replied that the was discussing <lb/>
a memorial which had been placed before <lb/>
the House, and he dared say it had been <lb/>
prepared very carefully and with due re<lb break="no"/>gard to absolute correctness. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>: But that is Territorial <lb/>
increase. <lb/></p>
    
    <p>
<persName ref="pers:BRET1">Mr. Brett</persName>: Yes, that is certainly Terri<lb break="no"/>torial increase, but if in 1891-94 Alberta <lb/>
increased 57 per cent. there was no reason <lb/>
to his mind, why that incrase had not <lb/>
gone on since then. The increase of 40 <lb/>
per cent. claimed for the whole of the <lb/>
Territories in the memorial was based on <lb/>
the figures that Alberta had increased 57 <lb/>
per cent., Eastern Assiniboia 35 per cent., <lb/>
Western Assiniboia 24 per cent., Saskat<lb break="no"/>chewan 33 per cent Taking that as a <lb/>
basis the increase during 1891-97 would <lb/>
be Alberta 90 per cent., the two Assini<lb break="no"/>boias 92 per cent., and Saskatchewan 110 <lb/>
per cent. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:INSI1">Mr. Insinger</persName>: How does the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber compute these calculations out of the <lb/>
memorial? I know a little about the <lb/>
figures there, and I don't see how under <lb/>
any cicrumstances the deductions can be <lb/>
drawn from the memorial. The increases <lb/>
in the memorial are based on the whole <lb/>
population, but to jump from that to the <lb/>
incrase that happened in different parts <lb/>
is something a little absurd. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Mr. Brett</persName> answred that he would stand <lb/>
    accused of being absurd, — but the figures <lb/>
showed a general increase in 1892-95 of <lb/>
57 per cent., and in the Territories of 40 <lb/>
per cent., and there was no reason to show <lb/>
that Alberta had not increased as much <lb/>
since. He obtained his figures in the <lb/>
office, and he believed they were absolute<lb break="no"/>ly correct. They were from the census <lb/>
returns taken by the N.W.M. Police. If <lb/>
the hon gentleman who composed the <lb/>
committee to draft the memorial were <lb/>
warranted in saying that the whole of the <lb/>
Territories had increased at the rate of <lb/>
40, that was ten per cent a year, it was <lb/>
fair to assume, in the absence of anything <lb/>
to the contrary, that Alberta had increas<lb break="no"/>ed in the same rate since 1894 (Hear, <lb/>
hear) That was a fair thing. He might <lb/>
appear ridiculous, but he certainly didn't <lb/>
realized to a very large extent that he was <lb/>
ridiculous in make a computation of <lb/>
that kind. He was simply giving a rea<lb break="no"/>son, why, as a representative of Alberta, <lb/>
he was justified in asking the House to <lb/>
indicate to the Dominion Government <lb/>
that the time had arrived when it and <lb/>
Athabasca should be set apart as a pro<lb break="no"/>vince by itself. While the population <lb/>
was increasing, and they had been getting <lb/>
an increased grant year by year, it was <lb/>
found that Alberta had been contributing <lb/>
much more to the local revenues than <lb/>
other parts of the Territories. Of the <lb/>
total revenue contributed by the Territo<lb break="no"/>ries (30,040) Alberta contributed 56 per <lb/>
cent, and eastern and western Assiniboia 37 <lb/>
per cent. that made only 93 per cent. The <lb/>
other portions was made up of moneys he <lb/>
could not compute. Alberta contributed <lb/>
a good deal more than all the rest of the <lb/>
Territories. He would give a few items. <lb/>
The liquor license was $24,907. Of that, <lb/>
Alberta contributed $25,178; the balance <lb/>
of the Territories showed $9,729. that <lb/>
showed Alberta contributed the most, <lb/>
(Laughter, and an hon. member: "And <lb/>
it is a sign of progress!") The cost of <lb/>
collecting that $9,729 in the two Assini<lb break="no"/>boias and Saskatchewan was $4,076, so <lb/>
that the new amount contributed by <lb/>
those portions was $5,652; while to <lb/>
collect $15,178 in Alberta it only cost <lb/>
$1,849, so in that respect Alberta's net <lb/>
contribution was $13,329. Looking at it <lb/>
in that way Alberta contributed 78 per <lb/>
cent. of the net revenues of the Territo<lb break="no"/>ries. (Hear, hear, and laughter.) He <lb/>
knew those figures were rather startling. <lb/>
(Renewed laughter.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>: What is the magnificent <lb/>
total of the revenue? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Mr. Brett</persName>; The magnificent total of <lb/>
the revenue is $30,040. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>; What is this net reve<lb break="no"/>nue? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Mr. Brett</persName>: For licenses under the <lb/>
Liquor Ordinance, the only item I can <lb/>
give the hon. gentleman, the gross reve<lb break="no"/>nue is $24,908. The expenditure attend<lb break="no"/>ing the collection of that is $5,926, leav<lb break="no"/>ing a net revenue of $18,982. That is <lb/>
outside the expenses of the chief license <lb/>
inspector and so on. In it were not in<lb break="no"/>cluded the meetings of the commissioners, and <lb/>
so on. Proceeding, the hon. gentleman <lb/>
remareked, some might say the magnificent <lb/>
sum, as the hon. member for Macleod <lb/>
called it, was only $30,040, but even in <lb/>
that small amount if there was a very large <lb/>
disparity between the amount contributed <lb/>
by one partner in the firm with the <lb/>
amount he got out of it, he was justified <lb/>
in looking around for some remedy. <lb/>
Someone might ask, what if Alberta did <lb/>
contribute 78 per cent of the net revenue, <lb/>
what had that to do with it? Noting, if <lb/>
78 per cent. was spent in Alberta of the <lb/>
firm's money. But they found that Al<lb break="no"/>berta came out at the wrong end there. <lb/>
Last year Alberta received about 30 per <lb/>
cent. of the full amount paid for schools <lb/>
in the Territories. It might be said, <lb/>
whose fault was that? If Alberta had <lb/>
had a greater number of schools establish<lb break="no"/>ed she would have had a larger proportion <lb/>
of the money. He presumed that as many <lb/>
schools were required were established <lb/>
there; he did not know anything to the <lb/>
contrary. then the expense of spending <lb/>
that money was five times greater in <lb/>
    
    <cb/>

Assiniboia and Saskatchewan than in <lb/>
Alberta. Then on roads and bridges Al<lb break="no"/>berta had had a little over one-third the <lb/>
total money, having contributed over <lb/>
three-fourths of the net revenues from <lb/>
local sources. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>: The net revenue ex<lb break="no"/>pended upon roads and bridges? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BRET1">Mr. Brett</persName>: No. While Alberta had <lb/>
contributed over three-fourths of the new <lb/>
local revenue, they had received less than <lb/>
one-third in schools and only a trifle over <lb/>
a third in the full amount expended for <lb/>
roads and bridges. that condition of <lb/>
affairs justified him, as one representative <lb/>
of Alberta, to ask that Alberta should be <lb/>
relieved, and placed in a position of col<lb break="no"/>lecting its own revenues and doing as it <lb/>
liked. In conclusion the hon. member <lb/>
further argued that Alberta was entitled <lb/>
to provincial status on the ground of ex<lb break="no"/>cess in increase of population, and also of <lb/>
extent of acreage. He could understand <lb/>
it was not going to be an easy matter to <lb/>
get the sanction of the House. It was <lb/>
not anything the House would voluntarily <lb/>
tender to Alberta. He did not think the <lb/>
Territories were sufficiently tired of Alber<lb break="no"/>ta, or sufficiently discontented with the <lb/>
part Alberta played with reference to the <lb/>
contributions to the general fund and so <lb/>
on. He could not readily understand, as <lb/>
was always the case in secession, or one <lb/>
part seeking to be relieved from another <lb/>
portion, there always would be some ob<lb break="no"/>jection taken. But he thought the time <lb/>
would soon come when there would be <lb/>
unanimity of feeling that the course he <lb/>
proposed was the best thing not only for <lb/>
Alberta but also for several portions of <lb/>
the Territories to be constructed into a <lb/>
province. (Hear, hear.) <lb/></p> 

    <p rendition="simple:centre">(<hi rendition="simple:italic">Continued on Page 5.</hi>) <lb/></p>
    
    <pb n="5" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1896-11-12_Page_005.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="num">5</fw>
    
    <fw type="running">THE LEADER. THURSDAY EVENING, NOVEMBER 12, 1896.</fw>
    
</div>
    <div type="debate">
    
    <head rendition="simple:centre">SECESSION<lb/>
</head>
<p>
    (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Continued from page 4</hi>)
</p>
<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:INSI1">MR. INSINGER</persName></p>
<p>
  (Yorkton) remarked that certain reasons <lb/>
  were given a week or more ago by the <lb/>
  hon. member for Moose Jaw (Mr. Ross) <lb/>
  why it was necessary to reconsider their <lb/>
  position with regard to their constitution<lb break="no"/>al status. It was stated that their powers <lb/>
  were not sufficient, and that the powers <lb/>
  they had been ostensibly given were in<lb break="no"/>complete. The hon. member further <lb/>
  brought on the point which whould appeal <lb/>
  more strongly to the House, perhaps, than <lb/>
  anything else, that they should ask for <lb/>
  more money. That was a very tangible <lb/>
  question, and appealed not only to mem<lb break="no"/>bers of that House but to every man in <lb/>
  this country. If they could in justice put <lb/>
  in a claim for more funds from the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Parliament, if they could show <lb/>
  that the Territories were entitled to re<lb break="no"/>ceive more from the Dominion treasury, <lb/>
  they would be remiss in their duty if they <lb/>
  did not make some kind of a claim. He <lb/>
  believed the present to be a favorable time <lb/>
  to reconsider their position. As early as <lb/>
  1885 they made a similar petition, but <lb/>
  then they hadn't the same knowledge no r<lb/>
  the same experiences of legislation. The <lb/>
  requests they then made were premature. <lb/>
  When they asked for responsibility in <lb/>
  1885 and 1888 they asked for something <lb/>
  that probably had they get it they would <lb/>
  not have been in a position to use. But <lb/>
  they had now been administering the <lb/>
  affairs of this country nearly as much as <lb/>
  any of the provinces, and he thought they <lb/>
  could claim to have administered those <lb/>
  affairs, with no discredit to themselves, <lb/>
  and quite as well as the affairs of any pro<lb break="no"/>vince were administered. He therefore <lb/>
  thought they could put in a good claim, <lb/>
  with a good conscience, to the Dominion <lb/>
  Government for more powers and for more <lb/>
  funds. There was another reason why <lb/>
  to-day they were in a better position than <lb/>
  formerly. There had been a change of <lb/>
  Government on a certain date in June. <lb/>
  He did not want to say for a moment <lb/>
  that one side of the House was more fav<lb break="no"/>orable to the Territories than the <lb/>
  other side, and it was well known that <lb/>
  many members of the present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, when in opposition, made proposi<lb break="no"/>tions to give the Territories more powers <lb/>
  than had been given them. Mr. Davies, <lb/>
  now a member of the Government at <lb/>
  Ottawa in 1893 declared that it was the <lb/>
  duty of the Government in amending the <lb/>
  North-West Territories Act to give them <lb/>
    certain rights wholesale,—not to quibble <lb/>
  about and take back with one hand what <lb/>
    they give with the other. He (Mr. In<lb break="no"/>singer) — thought they could now go <lb/>
  to the Cabinet and remind its members of <lb/>
  certain statements made by them when in <lb/>
  opposition. They had now a member in <lb/>
  the House at Ottawa, who was more able <lb/>
  than any member they had had there be <lb/>
  fore, to present the claims of the Territo<lb break="no"/>ries before Parliament. He referred to <lb/>
  Mr. Oliver. It was not only his ability, <lb/>
  but by his long experience he was better <lb/>
  posted on the requirements of this coun<lb break="no"/>try, on their laws and general constitu<lb break="no"/>tional standing, than perhaps any other <lb/>
  member of that House. Then, too, he <lb/>
  was with the Territories on the present <lb/>
  question. But to proceed. A certain <lb/>
  day was appointed to draft a memorial to <lb/>
  consider the matter and to bring in a re<lb break="no"/>port accordingly. The mover of the mo<lb break="no"/>tion (Mr. Ross) made a speech in which <lb/>
  he laid down the lines in which he thought <lb/>
  the House should restrict itself in asking <lb/>
  for Territorial autonomy, and he gave his <lb/>
  reasons therefor. Every one in the <lb/>
  House thought they were in unison with <lb/>
  the expressions of the hon. member for <lb/>
  Moose Jaw. These members who it now <lb/>
  seemed were not kept silent and by their <lb/>
  silence assented in the expressions of the <lb/>
  hon. member for Moose Jaw. But as <lb/>
  soon as the committee met it was found <lb/>
  that that unanimity did not remain, and <lb/>
  from many parts came different opinions <lb/>
  upon the subject. He was not sorry that <lb/>
  that was so. It was made apparent there <lb/>
  were three possible propositions that <lb/>
  could be laid before the House. One <lb/>
  was to make one province of the whole of <lb/>
  the Territories and ask for full provincial <lb/>
  rights. Another proposition was to <lb/>
  divide the country into more than one <lb/>
  province, and make one province of Al<lb break="no"/>berta; the third proposition was to ask <lb/>
  that the powers they already had should <lb/>
  be completed and put beyond doubt, and <lb/>
    ask for more money, — or Territorial auto<lb break="no"/>nomy. He did not intend to follow the <lb/>
  hon. member and calculations, because he <lb/>
  simply couldn't. He did not think it <lb/>
  possible to follow the hon. gentleman into <lb/>
  anything that went to the bottom of his <lb/>
  heart, and that touched his sensibilities <lb/>
  keenly, because then his imagination ran <lb/>
  a little wild. The hon. gentleman at first <lb/>
  seemed to be under the impression that I <lb/>
  was rather premature to ask provincial <lb/>
  rights, but he blossomed slowly out into a <lb/>
  champion for provincial rights of the <lb/>
  Territories, and then he bloomed right <lb/>
  out into a champion for Alberta being <lb/>
  made into a province. He based his <lb/>
  claim on the consideration of the local <lb/>
  revenues; that a very large part came <lb/>
  from Alberta, and a very small part went <lb/>
  to Alberta. He showed that they had <lb/>
  more liquor drunk in Alberta, and that <lb/>
  there were more criminals in Alberta, and <lb/>
  that there were more people contributing <lb/>
  to the local revenue in Alberta by means <lb/>
  of fines. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:BRET1">Mr. Brett</persName>: What I did point out was <lb/>
  this, that the greater amount contributed <lb/>
  by fines came from the rest of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. Out of about $400, only $40 came <lb/>
  from Alberta. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:INSI1">Mr. Insinger</persName> was very glad to hear the <lb/>
  disclaimer by the hon. gentleman. There <lb/>
  was more hope for Alberta than the hon. <lb/>
  member had given hope for. It struck <lb/>
  him (Mr. Insinger) as a very peculiar <lb/>
  claim that Alberta should be held out by <lb/>
  one of its representatives as being a place <lb/>
  where more liquor was drunk than any<lb break="no"/>where else. Then the hon. member <lb/>
  pointed to the schools. Certainly it was <lb/>
  a very strange claim to put forward that <lb/>
  Alberta was a more ignorant place than <lb/>
  any other part of the Territories. (Laugh<lb break="no"/>ter.) The hon. gentleman had shown <lb/>
  that population had it creased in Alberta, <lb/>
  and he must know that the establishment <lb/>
  of schools would always be a few years <lb/>
  behind the incoming of the population. <lb/>
  So if the hon. member would only rest his <lb/>
  soul in patience, say for a year or so, he <lb/>
  (Mr. Insinger) had sufficient confidence in <lb/>
  the intelligence of the people of Alberta <lb/>
  to believe they would have the full num<lb break="no"/>ber of schools, and that they would before <lb/>
  long make a full drain upon the Territo<lb break="no"/>rial resources for payment of schools. <lb/>
  Another claim for the autonomy of Al<lb break="no"/>berta was made on the ground of popula<lb break="no"/>tion. The hon. member went into points <lb/>
  which he clearly did not understand, and <lb/>
  the parts he did understand he clearly <lb/>
  did not comprehend. (Laughter.) Any <lb/>
  body who knew Alberta knew what the <lb/>
  hon. member for Banff ought to know, <lb/>
  <cb/>
  but did not seem to know, namely, that <lb/>
  in Alberta, they had special immigration <lb/>
  in the years 1891-94, and that that special <lb/>
  immigration there is not going on now. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:BRET1">Mr. Brett</persName>: It is going on yet. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:INSI1">Mr. Insinger</persName>: It may be going on, but <lb/>
  if so, it is a very silent trend. What we <lb/>
  hear is only the rumbling of the wheels, <lb/>
  as it were, of the people who are going <lb/>
  out. (Laughter.) Still he believed there <lb/>
  always would be a certain number of peo<lb break="no"/>ple going into Alberta, but the calculation <lb/>
  made by the hon. member was utterly <lb/>
  wrong, and he knew it, or he ought to <lb/>
  know it. He must know that on the build<lb break="no"/>ing of the colonization railroad there was <lb/>
  a large influx of population, and that that <lb/>
  influx had stopped. So the large increase <lb/>
  shown to have taken place then had not <lb/>
  continued. Then the hon. member ought <lb/>
  to know, and he did know, that of the in<lb break="no"/>crease of population that went in during <lb/>
  those few years quite a number had gone <lb/>
  out, and the hon. member did know that <lb/>
  the population of Alberta had not in<lb break="no"/>creased in the same ratio in the last few <lb/>
  years as it had increased before. He (Mr. <lb/>
  Insinger) must therefore refuse to believe <lb/>
  any conclusions based on the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber ought not to make claims for rights <lb/>
  from the Dominion Parliament based on <lb/>
  figures which he knew were belied by <lb/>
  facts. Were the Assembly to allow that <lb/>
  to be done, it would make them the <lb/>
  laughing stock of the whole country. <lb/>
  When the hon. member speaks about the <lb/>
  development of industries, he must know <lb/>
  that in one large Territory they had more <lb/>
  industries, and of course larger chances of <lb/>
  development and would have more power <lb/>
  of development, and would have more <lb/>
  credit for their developments than any <lb/>
  particular portion of it would have. He <lb/>
  did not want to create an impression in <lb/>
  the mind of the hon. member that he <lb/>
  (the speaker) did not fully realize the <lb/>
  great importance and richness of Alberta. <lb/>
  There was no doubt that it was one of the <lb/>
  fairest parts they had, but that was not a <lb/>
  sufficient reason why it should be separat <lb/>
  ed from the rest of the Territories. In<lb break="no"/>deed it was a very good reason it should <lb/>
  stay in with the rest. But really the <lb/>
  point upon which the hon. member put <lb/>
  the most stress was because of his, well, <lb/>
    call it sentimental reason; — the senti<lb break="no"/>mental reason that the idea in the minds of<lb/>
  intending immigrants was that the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories was a country of continual snow. <lb/>
  How a territory should create an impres<lb break="no"/>sion of snow he could not see, but he did <lb/>
  know that Alberta would create an im<lb break="no"/>pression of snow upon the mountains in <lb/>
  the mind of anyone who knew anything <lb/>
  about it. Why did not the territories in <lb/>
  the United States create an impression <lb/>
  of snow in the United States? There was <lb/>
  this difference between the territories, and <lb/>
  it was to our advantage,   that this side the <lb/>
  border the Territories had the rights of <lb/>
  provinces, and on the other side the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories had not the rights of the states. <lb/>
  But if there really was anything in the <lb/>
  sentimental, and the main, reason of the <lb/>
  hon. gentleman, and if it would act as a <lb/>
  balm to soothe the wounds of his bleeding <lb/>
  heart, he (Mr. Insinger) saw no reason <lb/>
  why the conceding so small a thing as the <lb/>
  change of a name should not be granted. <lb/>
  He did not object to have the name <lb/>
  "Territories" taken away, and to calling <lb/>
  the whole of this country Alberta. If any <lb/>
  little thing like that would satisfy the <lb/>
  hon. gentleman he would have no more <lb/>
  objection to the Territories being tacked <lb/>
  on to Alberta than he would to Alberta be<lb break="no"/>ing tacked on to the Territories. (Hear, <lb/>
  hear.) By that, sentiment might be ap<lb break="no"/>peased and the hon. gentleman's heart <lb/>
  by at rest for a little time. He <lb/>
  (Mr. Insinger) had never yet met the immi<lb break="no"/>grant who was scared from coming into <lb/>
  this country because it was a <lb/>
  Territory. He found as a rule <lb/>
  that when people came to this coun<lb break="no"/>try they knew very little about it at all. <lb/>
  They knew that they came to America, and <lb/>
  if they were very clever they knew they <lb/>
  were coming to Canada, and that was <lb/>
  about the extent of their knowledge. He <lb/>
  was sorry the hon. member stated an <lb/>
  amendment might be brought in, but that <lb/>
  he was not going to bring it in now. This <lb/>
  was the proper time to bring in any <lb/>
  amendment if the amendment was draft<lb break="no"/>ed, for really, to give "home rule" to Al<lb break="no"/>berta was an amendment which attacked <lb/>
  the principle of the memorial. The mem<lb break="no"/>orial was drafted for the distinct purpose <lb/>
  of obtaining Territorial autonomy and <lb/>
  would not fit on to a province of Alberta. <lb/>
  It would certainly expedite matters if the <lb/>
  hon. member for Banff would bring on <lb/>
  his amendment in the full House. It <lb/>
  showed a certain amount of want of cour<lb break="no"/>age in not bringing his amendment down <lb/>
  to the full House when particularly asked <lb/>
  by the mover of the memorial to do so. <lb/>
  If it was meant that by becoming a pro<lb break="no"/>vince they should have the right of char<lb break="no"/>tering railways, that was a matter for <lb/>
  serious consideration. The hon. member <lb/>
  for Banff had spoken about making a con<lb break="no"/>tract, or bargain, with the Dominion <lb/>
  Government. On going to the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion Government, say they made a <lb/>
  contract, and a contract was supposed to <lb/>
  be binding. For the hon. member <lb/>
  to say they could enter into a contract <lb/>
  and consider the contract would only bind <lb/>
  the other side simply showed that the <lb/>
  hon. member did not know what the <lb/>
  word "contract" meant. The question <lb/>
  was, were they sufficiently strong to go <lb/>
  into the position to make a full contract, <lb/>
  and if they had the full power to make <lb/>
  these demands? Unless they had suffi<lb break="no"/>cient interest at Ottawa to enforce their <lb/>
  side of the question they would, to use a <lb/>
  vernacular expression, "get left" on the <lb/>
  contract. They had only four members <lb/>
  at present, although they might have five <lb/>
  in a short time. Were the Territories in <lb/>
  a position to fight all the other parts of <lb/>
  Canada, because fight they must. Would <lb/>
  the Parliament at Ottawa give them full <lb/>
  consideration for the large amount of pub<lb break="no"/>lic lands which had been taken from them <lb/>
  for the general benefit of Canada? The <lb/>
  Parliament at Ottawa would simply give <lb/>
  what they thought proper, and not what <lb/>
  the Territories wanted. More than 30 <lb/>
  millions of acres had been taken away <lb/>
  from the Territories for the C.P.R. <lb/>
  Could they put a price on that land? A <lb/>
  great part of that land at present had no <lb/>
    value. If this country developed, — as <lb/>
    it had, slowly it was true, but it had de<lb break="no"/>veloped, — surely that land would get a <lb/>
  larger value, and the Territories would be <lb/>
  in a better position a few years hence to <lb/>
  make a demand for compensation better <lb/>
  than they were now; and if they did <lb/>
  make a demand now they would get left. <lb/>
  Rather than that he would possess his <lb/>
  soul in patience a few years longer. <lb/>
  Reference had been made to the position <lb/>
  of Manitoba at the time it entered into <lb/>
  confederation. The Territories were not <lb/>
  in the same position as was Manitoba. <lb/>
  Manitoba was not made a province be <lb/>
  cause the people there wanted or liked it. <lb/>
  They were simply made a province because <lb/>
  they were compelled to; it was through <lb/>
  necessity. And when they wanted to <lb/>
  make a change in a few years <lb/>
  they found it would cost them a <lb/>
  rebellion nearly to shake off their con<lb break="no"/>tract and make a new one. The Terri<lb break="no"/>tories were not forced by force of circum<lb break="no"/>stances. When they went into a province <lb/>
  <cb/>
  they would do it with a free will, and with <lb/>
  power to make contracts which would be <lb/>
  binding upon their heirs forever. Con<lb break="no"/>sidering the lands here would have an <lb/>
  enormous value in a few years, and con<lb break="no"/>sidering that if they were to put a price <lb/>
  upon those lands now they would be do<lb break="no"/>ing a great injustice to the people who are <lb/>
  to come after; when they considered their <lb/>
  position, that they were not able to force <lb/>
  their claims, he thought they should halt <lb/>
  before entering into a binding contract. <lb/>
    The hon. member seemed to think — and <lb/>
    perhaps many people had expressed simi<lb break="no"/>lar opinions — that as soon as a province <lb/>
  was formed the revenue at once fell in, <lb/>
  be he (Mr. Insinger) did not know <lb/>
  from where. Probably from the sky, or <lb/>
  some other place equally remote. The <lb/>
  estimated revenue for the province of <lb/>
  Manitoba last year was $800,000. The <lb/>
  idea of having a province was to develop. <lb/>
  If they wanted to go into the developing <lb/>
  business they had to get the money, and <lb/>
  the whole thing hinged upon the fact that <lb/>
  when they became a province it would <lb/>
  give them more money. He did not <lb/>
  think that was the fact. If the hon. <lb/>
  member would look up the revenues of <lb/>
  Manitoba he would find that the estimat<lb break="no"/>ed revenue consisted in the first place of a <lb/>
  Dominion grant of $50,000. So far as <lb/>
  the Dominion grant was concerned the <lb/>
  Territories were making a claim for some <lb/>
  similar consideration. On that ground, <lb/>
  therefore, the province was in no better <lb/>
  position than the Territories. In the <lb/>
  next place the Manitoba revenue consist<lb break="no"/>ed of the magnificent sum of $6,000 local <lb/>
  revenues. These were the the same local <lb/>
  revenues as the Territories could levy <lb/>
  with the exception of a law stamp levy, <lb/>
  which brought in $12,000. The Territories <lb/>
  however, could bring in similar legislation <lb/>
  to provide for the same purposes, but up <lb/>
  to the present they had not thought fit to <lb/>
  do so. The balance of those revenues was <lb/>
  made up of fees which were not of par<lb break="no"/>ticular benefit to a province. They found <lb/>
    that Manitoba as a province — and the <lb/>
  Territories would be in the same position <lb/>
    — did not increase their revenue by <lb/>
  one single cent on the amount they would <lb/>
  get as a territory. Therefore the province <lb/>
  had no advantage over a territory. The <lb/>
  hon. member for Banff had stated that in <lb/>
  British Columbia they had local taxation, <lb/>
  but they had no municipal taxation ; and <lb/>
  in Manitoba they had municipal taxation <lb/>
  but no provincial taxation. From that he <lb/>
  seemed to infer that they would be the <lb/>
  same as British Columbia. Surely the <lb/>
  hon. member must see that because Mani<lb break="no"/>toba did not raise its money by provincial <lb/>
  taxation, and British Columbia raises its <lb/>
  money by a local taxation, that we could <lb/>
  do without either of them. But if the <lb/>
  Territories, as a province, went in for large <lb/>
  plans surely they must go in for some <lb/>
  taxation. Where was money to come <lb/>
  from? Was it to come from heaven, or <lb/>
  from England, or where, and bring in <lb/>
  capital and they never pay interest on it? <lb/>
  In Manitoba they had a local taxation for <lb/>
  the maintenance and building of their <lb/>
  Court houses, only they did not raise it <lb/>
  for the province, but divided it amongst <lb/>
  the municipalities, but after all it was ex<lb break="no"/>actly the same thing as provincial tax<lb break="no"/>ation. It was not necessary for the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories to go in for being made a province <lb/>
  in order to get what they were seeking; <lb/>
  the same object could be obtained by go <lb/>
  ing in for territorial autonomy, and with <lb/>
  the distinct advantage that the demand <lb/>
  for larger Territorial powers was on the <lb/>
  face of it, not a contract, but only an <lb/>
  arrangement that would hold good for a <lb/>
  few years, or until such time as they <lb/>
  might want something else. Another <lb/>
  great advantage the asking for Territorial <lb/>
  autonomy would have over asking <lb/>
  the erection of a province, was <lb/>
  that they had a great deal more chance of <lb/>
  getting it. The hon. member for Banff <lb/>
  seemed to think that in politics by asking <lb/>
  for a great deal more than you expect <lb/>
  you would get a little. A mistake of <lb/>
  that kind was worse than a mistake. It <lb/>
  was simply prejudicing the whole case. <lb/>
  If they went to Ottawa and showed that <lb/>
  they asked for more than they expected, <lb/>
  that they were asking for what they did <lb/>
  not want; if they went and asked for <lb/>
  things in the lump and did not know that <lb/>
  they had a distinct knowledge of the <lb/>
  items, he thought they ran a great chance <lb/>
  of getting nothing at all. Their principle <lb/>
  should be to go and ask for those things <lb/>
    in detail;— show why they wanted those <lb/>
  things, and prove that they really wanted <lb/>
  them. If they showed that they under<lb break="no"/>stood what they wanted, and that they <lb/>
  knew how to handle it, they stood a very <lb/>
  good chance of getting it. He did not <lb/>
  believe in asking for a whole lot of things <lb/>
  in the chance of getting a little. He be<lb break="no"/>lieved they should follow the lines laid <lb/>
  down in the memorial. In asking for <lb/>
  Territorial autonomy they did not ask for <lb/>
  the power to charter railways. The pow<lb break="no"/>er of chartering railways was absolutely <lb/>
  useless to them unless they were in a posi<lb break="no"/>tion to go and grant them the credit of a <lb/>
  country, and that they could not do. <lb/>
  Another power they did not ask for in <lb/>
  the memorial was the administration of <lb/>
  justice in criminal matters. That was a <lb/>
  point upon which a certain amount of <lb/>
  difference of opinion should be allowed. <lb/>
  He was inclined to ask that administration <lb/>
  of justice be given them, but it was found <lb/>
  there were certain very heavy charges <lb/>
  against the administration of justice, and <lb/>
  it would be foolish to take upon their <lb/>
  shoulders such a very large debt unless <lb/>
  there was a very good reason shown in <lb/>
  favor of it. In the memorial they asked <lb/>
  for certain amendments. First they ask<lb break="no"/>ed that the powers which were given un<lb break="no"/>der the North-West Territories Act, and <lb/>
  which were now subject to any Act of the <lb/>
  Parliament of Canada, should be secured <lb/>
  to the Assembly. That means that <lb/>
  the moment the Assembly had passed a <lb/>
  law in any subject some member of Par<lb break="no"/>liament might turn round and make some <lb/>
  bill in which one clause perhaps affected <lb/>
  the Territories, and therefore put aside <lb/>
  their ordinance. They had been in such <lb/>
  danger several times. For instance there <lb/>
  was the Animals Infections Acts. They <lb/>
  had the same danger when they brought <lb/>
  into that House a bill regarding the in<lb break="no"/>spection of coal mines. When they <lb/>
  brought in a bill respecting irrigation they <lb/>
  did not know whether they had power or <lb/>
  not to deal with the subject. The mem<lb break="no"/>orial asked that the powers they had, and <lb/>
  such other powers as they asked for, <lb/>
  should be given to them the same as to <lb/>
  any province in Canada. It was also <lb/>
  asked that the Executive Committee <lb/>
  should be changed for an Executive Coun<lb break="no"/>cil. An Executive Council had all the <lb/>
  political precedents of England and Can<lb break="no"/>ada to show it its way. An Executive <lb/>
  Committee never knew what it was at. <lb/>
  The memorial also asked that the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly should have powers to incorporate <lb/>
  insurance companies; that the appoint<lb break="no"/>ments of sheriffs and clerks should be put <lb/>
  in their hands; and they asked for other <lb/>
  powers which would not be of any great <lb/>
  value to them, but it certainly would be <lb/>
  policy to have them. They made a claim <lb/>
  for more funds for the reasons that they <lb/>
  stood greatly in need of more money, and <lb/>
  that the Parliament of Canada was respon<lb break="no"/>sible for the due administration of edu<lb break="no"/>cation in this country; as long as they <lb/>
  were a territory and not a province the <lb/>
  Parliament of Canada was responsible for <lb/>
  <cb/>
  the full government of affairs in this coun<lb break="no"/>try. They had also shown that if they be <lb/>
  allowed to make an analogy of what was <lb/>
  due to them, and what to the province, <lb/>
  they could show a very great claim for a <lb/>
  greater amount of money, but they did <lb/>
  not in the memorial want to base their <lb/>
  claim on that, and they did not want to <lb/>
  put a distinct figure on the subsidy they <lb/>
  might claim for compensation for lands. <lb/>
  He thought there were few occasions when <lb/>
  they, as a House, had to state their posi<lb break="no"/>tion as a House, and when those occasions <lb/>
  did arise it was their duty to give unre<lb break="no"/>servedly expression to their opinions, so <lb/>
  that not only the House but the country <lb/>
  should know exactly where they were. <lb/>
  He did not think it was their duty to <lb/>
  slowly follow public opinion, but to lead <lb/>
  public opinion. The Territories needed <lb/>
  more funds, and they had a right to more <lb/>
  funds. They contributed as much as any <lb/>
  province in Canada, and there was no <lb/>
  reason why other men in Canada should <lb/>
  be given fifty cents back out of every dol<lb break="no"/>lar they contributed, while they of the <lb/>
  Territories should be sent back only <lb/>
  ten or fifteen cents of the dollar they con<lb break="no"/>tributed. (Applause.) <lb/>
</p>
<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:MAGR1">MR. MAGRATH</persName>.</p>
<p>
  (Lethbridge) stated that as the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman who had just sat down had sugges<lb break="no"/>ted there should be an amendment before <lb/>
  the House on the lines the hon. member <lb/>
  for Banff had spoken, he rose to propose <lb/>
  such an amendment, which was seconded <lb/>
  by the hon. member for Banff (Mr. Brett.) <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  It was in connection with the following <lb/>
    clause of the memorial:— "The Assembly <lb/>
  is of opinion that to remedy this undesir<lb break="no"/>able state of affairs it is not necessary to <lb/>
  have recourse to the granting of a full <lb/>
  provincial status. They believe that till <lb/>
  the time arrives, which may be at a not <lb/>
  distant day, when the Territories should <lb/>
  be taken into Confederation (as one or <lb/>
  more provinces) the passing of a few <lb/>
  amendments to the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories Act will allow them, subject to dis<lb break="no"/>allowance of their ordinances, to exclus<lb break="no"/>ively make laws in relation to matters al<lb break="no"/>ready within their legislative jurisdic<lb break="no"/>tion." <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:MAGR1">Mr. Magrath</persName> said that according <lb/>
  to that clause they did not <lb/>
  appear to have fully made up their <lb/>
  minds as to whether that day was at an <lb/>
  early period or not. The next point was <lb/>
  as to whether they felt they "should be <lb/>
  taken into Confederation as one or more <lb/>
  provinces." The amendment he would <lb/>
  move simply meant that they should more <lb/>
  forcibly point out that it was the opinion <lb/>
  of the House that this country should be <lb/>
  taken into Confederation as two provinces <lb/>
  at a very early period, otherwise it did <lb/>
  not disturb the memorial in any matter <lb/>
  whatever. He did not follow the hon. <lb/>
  gentleman from Banff, but he did hear <lb/>
  the levity with which the hon. member <lb/>
  from Yorkton referred to Alberta. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:INSI1">Mr. Insinger</persName>: I didn't refer to Alber<lb break="no"/>ta with any levity at all. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:MAGR1">Mr. Magrath</persName>: I certainly accept the <lb/>
  hon. gentleman's view of the matter, but <lb/>
  it appeared to me in his referring to Al<lb break="no"/>berta that he did do so, and that, subse<lb break="no"/>quently, he made amends by asserting <lb/>
  that Alberta was after all one of the fair<lb break="no"/>est provinces. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:INSI1">Mr. Insinger</persName>: I might have referred <lb/>
  to the views expressed by the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Banff, but there is a difference be<lb break="no"/>tween the views expressed by the hon. <lb/>
  member for Banff respecting Alberta, and <lb/>
  Alberta itself. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:MAGR1">Mr. Magrath</persName>: I am glad to hear the <lb/>
  explanation. I feel the time will come <lb/>
  when we must enter Confederation as a <lb/>
  province. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:PAGE3">Mr. Page</persName> (Cannington): As a province? <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:MAGR1">Mr. Magrath</persName>: I say as a province. He <lb/>
  considered the interests in the Territories <lb/>
  were entirely different. In the west <lb/>
  they had to look to the west for their <lb/>
  trade, while in the east the trade was <lb/>
  largely diverted, or largely flowed towards <lb/>
  the east, and in that it appeared to him <lb/>
  there was a wide difference. As to being <lb/>
  created into a full province at the present <lb/>
  time he did not think it was desirable or <lb/>
  necessary. It was an unfortunate thing <lb/>
  in Canada to day, that they were over<lb break="no"/>governed. (Hear, hear.) There were <lb/>
  too many institutions in Canada, but he <lb/>
  felt, if they thought their interests were <lb/>
  going to be different in this country, that <lb/>
  they should emphasize their views in re<lb break="no"/>
    <cb/>
  lation to that so far as the creation of more <lb/>
  than one province was concerned. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  Half past five having arrived Mr. Speak<lb break="no"/>er left the chair, leaving the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man in possession of the floor. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  The House re-assembled at eight o'clock. <lb/>
  In the greater part of the evening the <lb/>
  chair was occupied by Mr. Deputy Speak<lb break="no"/>er Page, in the absence of the Speaker. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:MAGR1">Mr. Magrath</persName>, resuming, said the ques<lb break="no"/>tion for consideration was not a question <lb/>
  as to the importance of the memorial at <lb/>
  large; it was merely a question as to the <lb/>
  expression of opinion contained in one <lb/>
  clause of that memorial. He, and those <lb/>
  who held the same views as he did, wish<lb break="no"/>ed to go further than the memorial. <lb/>
  There was the difference. They all agreed <lb/>
  that the time would come when the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories would be taken into Confederation <lb/>
  (hear, hear.) They were a unit on that. <lb/>
  (Hear, hear.) But it had occurred to <lb/>
  those who held the same opinions as him<lb break="no"/>self that the memorial did not emphasize <lb/>
  that fact strongly enough. They had <lb/>
  never approached the Federal Government <lb/>
  on matters pertaining to the welfare of <lb/>
  this country that were conceded to them <lb/>
  when asked for. Were they going to wait <lb/>
  until the time had arrived when they <lb/>
  considered the time was ripe for the en<lb break="no"/>tering of the Territories into Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation before they brought the matter <lb/>
  strongly to the attention of the Federal <lb/>
  Government as they should? He did not <lb/>
  think that was desirable. There had <lb/>
  been a good deal of talk about educating <lb/>
  the country. He thought they had some <lb/>
  education to do in reference to this mat<lb break="no"/>ter. It was their duty to commence the <lb/>
  education, and commence it on vigorous <lb/>
  lines. He did not for a moment imagine <lb/>
  if they presented the memorial to the <lb/>
  Federal Government that it would be re<lb break="no"/>ceived, and that they would be received <lb/>
  with open arms. He also thought that <lb/>
  they should bring the matter very forcibly <lb/>
  before the Government, not that he <lb/>
  thought they were going to have it grant<lb break="no"/>ed, but that they might keep pressing it <lb/>
  from time to time. If they were satisfied <lb/>
  that the Federal Government would take <lb/>
  the memorial into consideration and act <lb/>
  upon it then he and his friends would sit <lb/>
  down. But their experience had been <lb/>
  otherwise, and for that reason they had <lb/>
  considered it necessary to draw attention <lb/>
  to that portion in one clause of it. There <lb/>
  was no diversity of opinion as to the main <lb/>
  point in that part of the amendment. <lb/>
  The next point he understood was they <lb/>
  considered that when the time did arrive <lb/>
  for the Territories to be taken into Con<lb break="no"/>federation, that the section of the country <lb/>
  from which he and his friends came should <lb/>
  be set apart as a province. They did not <lb/>
  presume to try to educate the House as to <lb/>
  what should be done with the rest of the <lb/>
  Territories. That remained for the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of the people of the balance of <lb/>
  the Territories. He thought he could <lb/>
  state confidently, that when the time had <lb/>
  arrived, the larger portion of Alberta <lb/>
  would be found a unit on that question. <lb/>
  (Hear, hear.) They had to bear in mind <lb/>
  that a portion of Alberta had already dis<lb break="no"/>cussed this matter. It had not been dis<lb break="no"/>cussed in his section. From the discus<lb break="no"/>sions that took place there was no ques<lb break="no"/>tion in his mind that the people of that <lb/>
  section of country had stated positively <lb/>
  and emphatically that they wished to be <lb/>
  set apart as a province. As to the other <lb/>
  sections it was a matter of question. He <lb/>
  believed if Alberta was canvassed to-day <lb/>
  that they would vote against provincial <lb/>
  institutions. (Mr. Haultain: "Hear, <lb/>
    hear.") — because they were frightened, he <lb/>
  thought, largely from the fact that there <lb/>
  was no question but there was too much <lb/>
  government in Canada. (Hear, hear.) It <lb/>
  was hardly possible to walk down any by <lb/>
  alley without meeting someone who was <lb/>
  in the business. So people for that rea<lb break="no"/>son, he considered, had just cause to feel <lb/>
  alarmed. But that did not alter the fact <lb/>
  that they were coming to it, that they had <lb/>
  got to come to it, and the question then <lb/>
  would be with the people of Alberta, <lb/>
  whether they wanted one or two provin<lb break="no"/>ces. When that time came, he was posi<lb break="no"/>tive that 90 per cent of the people of Al<lb break="no"/>berta would ask for Alberta being set <lb/>
  apart as one province. (Hear, hear.) It <lb/>
  might be argued that the Territories are <lb/>
  not as large as some of the provinces in <lb/>
  Canada. He was reminded the other day <lb/>
  that what was good for Ontario and else<lb break="no"/>where, it did not necessarily follow it was <lb/>
  good for this country, and he concurred <lb/>
  with that statement, although it did not <lb/>
  possibly suit his views at that time. But <lb/>
  the cases were not parallel. Ontario was <lb/>
    very large, probably much larger in ex<lb break="no"/>tent than were the Territories, — at least <lb/>
  much longer. But the populated portion <lb/>
  of Ontario was not, nor ever would be, as <lb/>
  large as the portions of the Territories <lb/>
  that were capable of population, and that <lb/>
  would be populated in due time. There <lb/>
  were good reasons that could be advanced <lb/>
  on the part of the people of Alberta which <lb/>
  it might not be desirable to advance, as <lb/>
  he might be accused of being narrow in <lb/>
  his views, but they all looked after their <lb/>
  own interests first, and although he be<lb break="no"/>longed to Alberta he was a Canadian, and <lb/>
  if he thought the portion of the country <lb/>
  to which he belonged, by having provin<lb break="no"/>cial rights of its own would be of, advan<lb break="no"/>tage not only to itself but to Canada, he <lb/>
  thought no one should blame him for hav<lb break="no"/>ing that wish. (Hear, hear.) The hon. <lb/>
  member from Banff had made quite a <lb/>
  lengthy speech in which he brought down <lb/>
  some figures. He (Mr. Magrath) did not <lb/>
  say he endorsed the ideas the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber advanced. He had no doubt the fig<lb break="no"/>ures were correct, but the hon. member <lb/>
  for Yorkton, in referring to them, stated <lb/>
  the figures were not fact, but he did not <lb/>
  try to dispute them, and he did not add <lb/>
  that figures don't lie. He (Mr. Magrath) <lb/>
  did not think the criticism of the hon. <lb/>
  member for Yorkton had the force he <lb/>
  would like the House to believe. There <lb/>
  were other matters referred to by the <lb/>
  <cb/>
  hon. members which he (Mr. Magrath) <lb/>
  need not reply to because he was good <lb/>
    enough to withdraw— <lb/></p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:INSI1">Mr. Insinger</persName>: I beg your pardon; <lb/>
  I didn't withdraw a single statement I <lb/>
  made. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:MAGR1">Mr. Magrath</persName>: I certainly understood <lb/>
    you to withdraw— <lb/></p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The Speaker</persName>: He withdrew nothing. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:MAGR1">Mr. Magrath</persName>: I accept the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man's correction. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:INSI1">Mr. Insinger</persName>: I accept the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man's apology. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:MAGR1">Mr. Magrath</persName>: I have a distinct recol<lb break="no"/>lection that the hon. gentleman referred <lb/>
  to several matters in Alberta deduced <lb/>
  from figures the hon. member for Banff <lb/>
  adduced. The deductions he drew were <lb/>
  that the tippling proclivities of the people <lb/>
  of Alberta were noted, and he made other <lb/>
  statements in reference to the Albertan's <lb/>
  ability for consuming liquor. (Laughter.) <lb/>
  As a representative from Alberta, of <lb/>
  course I don't like that. (Hear, hear) <lb/>
  I presume there are other representatives <lb/>
  from Alberta who are going to speak to<lb break="no"/>night, who are more capable of looking <lb/>
  after Albertan interest than I am, and I <lb/>
  leave it to them to either endure, if they <lb/>
  see fit, the expressions that the hon. <lb/>
  gentleman chose to make in reference to <lb/>
  that matter, or refute them if they think <lb/>
  it desirable. I therefore beg to move, <lb/>
  seconded by the hon. member for Banff, <lb/>
  "That the report be referred back to the <lb/>
  select committee with instructions to <lb/>
  strike out the first clause of the section <lb/>
  referred to, and insert in lieu thereof <lb/>
  the following: The Assembly is of the <lb/>
  opinion that until the Territories are ad<lb break="no"/>mitted into Confederation as two or more <lb/>
  provinces which they consider is necessary <lb/>
  at an early date for the compact govern<lb break="no"/>ment on local lines of such a vast country, <lb/>
  that the passage of a few amendments at <lb/>
  the first session of the Parliament of Can<lb break="no"/>ada to the North-West Territories Act <lb/>
  will allow them, subject to disallowance <lb/>
  of their ordinances, to exclusively make <lb/>
  laws in relation to matters already within <lb/>
  their legislative jurisdiction." (Applause.) <lb/>
</p>
<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:FEAR1">MR. FEARON</persName>,</p>
<p>
  (Medicine Hat) said he was in the em<lb break="no"/>barassing position of agreeing in part with <lb/>
  promoters of the memorial and in part <lb/>
  with the framers of the amendment. He <lb/>
  agreed with the first part of the question <lb/>
  as to whether the time had arrived that <lb/>
  steps should be taken towards admitting <lb/>
  the Territories into the Confederation as <lb/>
  a province. The framers of the memorial <lb/>
  as interpreted by the hon. member from <lb/>
  Yorkton seemed to infer that the time <lb/>
  had not yet arrived. The position they <lb/>
  took was that they would leave matters <lb/>
    as they are,—in the same indefinite man<lb break="no"/>ner as now exists. It was there that he <lb/>
  differed from them. He considered the <lb/>
  time had arrived that at least steps <lb/>
  should be taken to frame events which <lb/>
  would speedily allow the Territories to be <lb/>
  taken into Confederation as a province. <lb/>
  The hon. member from Yorkton, in giv<lb break="no"/>ing his reasons why he considered it pre<lb break="no"/>mature that such a step should be taken <lb/>
  gave as one, that even with an increased <lb/>
  subsidy the difference between the amount <lb/>
  of money coming to them as a province <lb/>
  and now, would not be sufficient to more <lb/>
  than bear the expenses of the Territories, <lb/>
  and that it would be absolutely necessary <lb/>
    to carry on the government,—that was on <lb/>
  the lines that a province should be carried <lb/>
    on to develop the resources of the coun<lb break="no"/>try,—that means would be taken to bor<lb break="no"/>row money. Mr. Insinger consider<lb break="no"/>ed it would be premature to do so. The <lb/>
  point then to be considered was, if, with <lb/>
  a population of 112,000 in the Territories, <lb/>
  that was not sufficient, when would they <lb/>
  arrive at that point? If with a member<lb break="no"/>ship in the Dominion Parliament of four <lb/>
  members they were not sufficient, how <lb/>
  many should they have before they would <lb/>
  be in a position to compel the Dominion <lb/>
  Government to grant the Territories terms <lb/>
  as favorable as they could desire? It was <lb/>
  constantly brought forward that admission <lb/>
  into Confederation as a province would <lb/>
  necessitate the borrowing of money. He <lb/>
  believed it would, but he did not consider <lb/>
  it so much of a bugbear as it was popular<lb break="no"/>ly supposed to be. They were in the <lb/>
  position of a business house, or a farmer, <lb/>
  who by cultivating part of his farm was <lb/>
  able to pay expenses. He had natural <lb/>
  resources in a large area, but he did not <lb/>
  attempt to cultivate simply because he <lb/>
  had not the means to do so. Was it better <lb/>
  for him to continue indefinitely only pay<lb break="no"/>ing expenses, or to borrow money, deve<lb break="no"/>lop his farm and make it a dividend pay<lb break="no"/>ing concern? That was the position they <lb/>
  were in regarding the Territories. Wheth<lb break="no"/>er would it be better for them to go on <lb/>
  for an indefinite period simply paying ex<lb break="no"/>penses, allowing their natural resources <lb/>
  to remain dormant, or whether it would <lb/>
  be better to borrow money and develop <lb/>
  the resources? The hon. member from <lb/>
  Yorkton, in speaking of British Columbia <lb/>
  and Manitoba, as the different systems of <lb/>
  carrying on municipal or provincial gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, showed it was absolutely neces<lb break="no"/>sary that some taxes had to be levied in <lb/>
  British Columbia, but he said the taxes <lb/>
  were levied by a provincial tax. That <lb/>
  was correct. But that tax in rural dis<lb break="no"/>tricts, other than municipalities, this year <lb/>
  was only 10 mills on the dollar. There <lb/>
  was a poll tax of $3 per head for all who <lb/>
  were not otherwise assessed. As he said, <lb/>
  the tax was only 10 mills on the dollar, <lb/>
  but they should bear in mind the provin<lb break="no"/>cial government paid all the expenses of <lb/>
    the scholl system,—that it included what <lb/>
  in the Territories was their school tax,<lb break="no"/>he asked did they consider that a very <lb/>
  high tax? How many school districts <lb/>
  were there in the Territories whose assess<lb break="no"/>ment was lower than 10 mills on the dol<lb break="no"/>lar? So that to-day they were assessing <lb/>
  themselves nearly as high as British Col<lb break="no"/>umbia assessed itself. British Columbia <lb/>
  had developed from a population of <lb/>
  20,000 to a population of 80,000 during <lb/>
  the last 15 years. British Columbia came <lb/>
  into confederation as a crown colony. But <lb/>
  supposing B.C. had been an undeveloped <lb/>
  portion of the North-West Territories, <lb/>
  and instead of going into confederation as <lb/>
  a province had simply been formed into a <lb/>
  local government on the lines of the <lb/>
  North-West Territories, what would have <lb/>
  been her position to-day? The amount <lb/>
  of money she would have had to expend <lb/>
  would only have been sufficient to pay <lb/>
  expenses, consequently they would have <lb/>
  had no money to make their roads and to <lb/>
  make the necessary improvements that <lb/>
  had produced that increase. British <lb/>
  Columbia not being an agricultural coun<lb break="no"/>try, it might be said the N.W.T had <lb/>
  increased in the same ratio, but with this <lb/>
    difference,—the Territories had an asset <lb/>
  that could be realized, upon agricultural <lb/>
  <cb/>
  lands ; British Columbia had none. So if <lb/>
  British Columbia had been in the position <lb/>
  of a Territoryshe would have been to-day <lb/>
  with very few more in population than <lb/>
  she was then. It was only by borrowing <lb/>
  money she was able to develop her natural <lb/>
  resources that made it possible for a <lb/>
  population of 8,000 or 9,000 to exist at <lb/>
  Cariboo, 300 miles from the railroad, and <lb/>
  made it possible for millions of money to <lb/>
  be invested there. It was not a danger <lb/>
  to have the power vested in a provincial <lb/>
  government to borrow money; it was only <lb/>
  by that means that it was possible to de<lb break="no"/>velop the uatural resources of the country. <lb/>
  He hoped he hd made himself clear on <lb/>
  that point. The first part of the question <lb/>
  was that he was distinctly in favor in the <lb/>
  near future of the best efforts being made <lb/>
  to admit the Territories into confederation <lb/>
  as a province. <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:INSI1">Mr.Insinger</persName>: One province? <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  <persName ref="pers:FEAR1">Mr. Fearon</persName>: That was where he agreed <lb/>
  with the framers of the memorial, and <lb/>
  where he differed with them in not going <lb/>
  far enough. Where he differed from the <lb/>
  framers of the amendments was where they <lb/>
  laid down that the Territories should be <lb/>
  admitted as two or more provinces. If <lb/>
  they entered as two provinces they would <lb/>
  enter as three. Was it desirable that the <lb/>
  Territories should be divided into three <lb/>
  provinces? He thought not. That would <lb/>
  be a state of affairs only parallel to the <lb/>
  Maritime provinces to-day, where there <lb/>
  was a movement to consolidate the three <lb/>
  provinces into one. The hon. member <lb/>
  from Banff spoke of the amount of money <lb/>
  paid into the local revenue fund from <lb/>
  Alberta. The amounts were small and <lb/>
  unimportant for the very reason that <lb/>
  they might from year to year alter the <lb/>
  amount of money obtained from licenses, <lb/>
  registration of companies; and other <lb/>
  sources of revenue were such that at any <lb/>
  time the case might be reversed. There <lb/>
  was no argument advanced why Alberta <lb/>
  should be separated from the Territories <lb/>
  and formed into a province that could not <lb/>
  be advanced in favor of any other part of <lb/>
  the Territories. In fact it was disintegra<lb break="no"/>tion, a principle opposed to the spirit of <lb/>
  the age. He was opposed to any division <lb/>
  of the Territories. There were many <lb/>
  arguments why they should remain united. <lb/>
  First, that as a whole they certainly would <lb/>
  be of more importance than they would be <lb/>
  divided. The hon. member for Lethbridge <lb/>
  (Mr. Magrath) thought the Territories <lb/>
  would be too large, and as evidence ad<lb break="no"/>vanced that the territories to the south <lb/>
  had recognized the principle and divided <lb/>
  as small as possible. It would be found, <lb/>
  however, that the territories, which are <lb/>
  now States, like Dakota, Texas and others <lb/>
  were as large or larger than the North<lb break="no"/>West Territories. It had not been shown <lb/>
  that there had ever been any difficulty <lb/>
  about the machinery of the Territories. <lb/>
  If it was possible for the Executive Com<lb break="no"/>mittee in a sparsely populated country, <lb/>
  now to manage the machinery of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in the North-West Territories under <lb/>
  present conditions he did not see how but <lb/>
  a provincial cabinet ought to be able to do <lb/>
  it with increased facilities. He would <lb/>
  have preferred seeing an amendment <lb/>
  brought in which would more clearly have <lb/>
  answered his position, but as it remained <lb/>
  at present between voting for the memor<lb break="no"/>ial as it stood, which left it in doubt, and <lb/>
  the amendment proposed, which distinctly <lb/>
  stated that two or more provinces should <lb/>
  be formed, he must vote against the <lb/>
  amendment and in favor of the memorial. <lb/>
  (Hear, hear.) <lb/>
</p>
<p>
  The debate will be continued in next <lb/>
  issue. <lb/>
  

  
</p>

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>