<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgASLA_1903-04-22" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>,
<date when="1903-04-22">22 April 1903</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA"> <editor>William Franklin Kerr</editor>.
<title>The Leader</title>.
<date when="1903-04-30"/>.
<pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="5"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1903-04-30_Page_001.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1903-04-30_Page_005.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-31">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-31">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1903-04-30_Page_001"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1903-04-30_Page_001.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1903-04-30_Page_005"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1903-04-30_Page_005.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="001" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1903-04-30_Page_001.jpg"/>
 
 <fw type="num">1</fw>

<fw type="running">THE LEADER.</fw> 

<fw type="running">REGINA, N.W.T., THURSDAY MORNING, APRIL 30, 1903.</fw> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">STRONG MEMORIALS</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">Adopted by the Legislative Assem<lb break="no"/>bly With Reference to</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">AUTONOMY &amp;TRANSPORTATION</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">Premier Haultain Outlines His Posi<lb break="no"/>tion re Party Lines—Important <lb/>
Amendments to the Liquor Licence <lb/>
and Hall Insurance Ordinances— <lb/>
Ottawa Government's Delay Makes <lb/>
Long Adjournment Necessary.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">WEDNESDAY, April 22nd.</p> 

<p>The House was in a very business<lb break="no"/>like mood to-day and quite a number <lb/>
of Bills were advanced from first to <lb/>
second readings and put through com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the whole. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">CONSTRUCTION OF FIREGUARDS.</p> 

<p>In reply to Mr. Wallace, the Com<lb break="no"/>missioner of Public Works stated that <lb/>
1,751 miles of fireguard had been con<lb break="no"/>structed long the C.P.R. main <lb/>
and branch lines in the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories in 1902 at a cost to the <lb/>
North-West Government of $9,309. <lb/>
The Commissioner stated that early in <lb/>
1902 an agreement had been made by <lb/>
which the C.P.R. would pay one-half the <lb/>
cost (which was $10 a mile), or $5.00 a <lb/>
mile towards the construction of these <lb/>
guards and also to pay $2.50 a mile per <lb/>
year, or in other words one-half, to <lb/>
maintain the guards each year. The <lb/>
agreement could be terminated by <lb/>
either party and the Commissioner <lb/>
informed the House that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had given notice to terminate it <lb/>
at the end of the present year. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">PRESENT A UNITED FRONT.</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>, in moving the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of the special committee compos<lb break="no"/>ed of Messrs. Bulyea, Elliott, Patrick, <lb/>
Bennett, McKay, Brown, Fisher, <lb/>
(Batoche), Rutherford and Haultain to <lb/>
draft a memorial to Ottawa on the <lb/>
questions of the constitutional and <lb/>
financial position of the Territories, <lb/>
railway transportation, and the public <lb/>
domain, said it was not necessary to <lb/>
dwell on the importance of presenting <lb/>
a united front on these questions. He <lb/>
believed they were all agreed on the <lb/>
broad lines involved in these questions, <lb/>
and also on the advisability of sending <lb/>
such a memorial to Ottawa. The <lb/>
motion passed without debate. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:YOUN3">Mr. J. J. Young</persName> moved for a return <lb/>
showing the correspondence relative to <lb/>
the Nose Creek bridge near Calgary <lb/>
and in doing so said it was a matter of <lb/>
considerable importance to the people <lb/>
of his constituency and he desired to <lb/>
have all the correspondence and facts <lb/>
brought down in order that it might <lb/>
be the more intelligently discussed. In <lb/>
the absence of the Commissioner of <lb/>
Public Works from the chamber the <lb/>
Premier said there would be no objec<lb break="no"/>tion to bringing the papers down. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PATR1">Dr. Patrick</persName> introduced Bills relating <lb/>
to the town of Yorkton and the York<lb break="no"/>ton Queen Victoria Cottage Hospital <lb/>
and these were read a first time. <persName ref="pers:RUTH1">Mr. <lb/>
Rutherford</persName> introduced a Bill to amend <lb/>
the Ordinance incorporating Strath<lb break="no"/>cona, which was also read a first <lb/>
time. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Bills to amend the Ordinances <lb/>
incorporating the Regina Victoria <lb/>
Hospital, respecting marriages, the <lb/>
Calgary General Hospital, and the town <lb/>
of Moosomin were each read a second <lb/>
time and passed through committee of <lb/>
the whole with some minor amend<lb break="no"/>ments to the latter one. The Bill to <lb/>
amend the Ordinance incorporating <lb/>
Calgary also passed its second reading <lb/>
after a brief explanation of the object <lb/>
of its clauses by Mr. Young and was <lb/>
taken up in Committee of the Whole. <lb/></p>

<cb/>

<p rendition="simple:centre">QUESTION OF PARTY LINES.</p> 

<p>Just before the Speaker left the <lb/>
chair <persName ref="pers:WALL6">Mr. Wallace</persName> (High River) rose to <lb/>
a question of privilege and said:—In <lb/>
connection with certain action taken <lb/>
by the convention recently held at <lb/>
Moose Jaw in favor of the introduction <lb/>
of party politics into this House, the <lb/>
matter was put to me at a public meet<lb break="no"/>ing very bluntly a short time ago in <lb/>
the form of a question 'What action <lb/>
do you intend to take with regard to <lb/>
it.' My answer was short. I said I <lb/>
had every confidence in Premier Haul<lb break="no"/>tain and would continue to have con<lb break="no"/>fidence in him so long as he continued <lb/>
in the same course he had previously <lb/>
followed and until he had made a pub<lb break="no"/>lic statement to the contrary. I think <lb/>
it is due to the people and to himself <lb/>
that the Premier should make a state<lb break="no"/>ment regarding his position and I <lb/>
would ask him for a short statement as <lb/>
to what he intends to do in the <lb/>
matter. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. Fisher</persName> (Batoche) said he consid<lb break="no"/>ered it important that the House <lb/>
should have an explanation from the <lb/>
Premier. They had every confidence <lb/>
in him as Premier and were also con<lb break="no"/>fident that he had governed the affairs <lb/>
of the country satisfctorily but he <lb/>
thought an explanation from him was <lb/>
due. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">PREMIER OUTLINES HIS POSITION.</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Premier Haultain</persName> in reply said:—I <lb/>
should have liked to have kept this sub<lb break="no"/>ject out of the discussion of the House <lb/>
in exactly the same way as we kept the <lb/>
discussion of federal party politics out <lb/>
of the House. But now that it has <lb/>
come up I cannot complain of the <lb/>
spirit or manner in which it has been <lb/>
introduced. It has confirmed my be<lb break="no"/>lief that the hon, gentlemen with <lb/>
whom I have been associated in the <lb/>
House in carrying out the pledges I <lb/>
have made to them, to the House and <lb/>
to the country, still extend their con<lb break="no"/>fidence to me. I am not myself aware <lb/>
that any public statement is necessary <lb/>
but I am perfectly willing to make it <lb/>
and I believe it will be satisfactory <lb/>
both to the members of this House <lb/>
and the country at large. From the <lb/>
earliest time in the history of this <lb/>
House there has been a practically <lb/>
unanimous opinion on the part of the <lb/>
country that this House in addressing <lb/>
itself to the business entrusted to it <lb/>
should not introduce questions, names <lb/>
and cries which had nothing whatever <lb/>
to do with the particular business in <lb/>
hand. That has been the policy of the <lb/>
House and of the Government and the <lb/>
principle on which I have been elected <lb/>
from year to year and on which I have <lb/>
been so loyally, and practically unani<lb break="no"/>mously, supported both in the House <lb/>
and country. It is quite unnecessary <lb/>
for me to say that at the last election I <lb/>
went to the country, on the same <lb/>
ground, and I can merely say to the <lb/></p> 
<!--
<p>(Continued on page 5.) <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="005" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1903-04-30_Page_005.jpg"/> 
 
 <fw type="num">5</fw>

<fw type="running">THE LEADER, THURSDAY MORNING, APRIL 30, 1903.</fw> 
</div>
 <div type="debate">

<head rendition="simple:centre">STRONG MEMORIALS</head> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">(Continued from page 1.)</p> 

<p>House and country at the present <lb/>
time that I propose to carry out the <lb/>
important duties which have been <lb/>
intrusted to me, faithfully and reso<lb break="no"/>lutely, and fulfill the pledges I have <lb/>
made to my constituency, to my col<lb break="no"/>leagues, to the Legislature and to the <lb/>
North-West Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p>In regard to the convention which <lb/>
the hon. gentleman has mentioned, I <lb/>
am not going to stop short at the state<lb break="no"/>ment I have made. On the question of <lb/>
Dominion policies I take the ground <lb/>
the I, in common with every member <lb/>
of this House, reserve to myself the <lb/>
right to have and to hold and profess <lb/>
my own political opinions in regard to <lb/>
national or other matters. I do not <lb/>
consider because of my position in this <lb/>
House that I am thereby practically <lb/>
disfranchised. I claim the right to <lb/>
exercise, and will exercise to the <lb/>
fullest extent, the liberty of speech and <lb/>
action and opinion with regard to <lb/>
federal matters, subject to the promise <lb/>
that I will not introduce them into <lb/>
local affairs. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">IS A LOYAL CONSERVATIVE.</p> 

<p>With regard to the organisation <lb/>
which was created at Moose Jaw, I had <lb/>
the honor of being elected its honorary <lb/>
president. I do not propose to shield <lb/>
myself, as, perhaps, I might, behind <lb/>
what is purely an honorary position. <lb/>
By accepting the honorary presidency <lb/>
of the association then formed I may <lb/>
be held to be in general principles of <lb/>
the party to which I have the honor to <lb/>
belong. A political party according to <lb/>
Edmond Burke, is a body of men unit<lb break="no"/>ed to promote by their joint endeavors <lb/>
principles they are all agreed upon. I <lb/>
am not bound to approve of <lb/>
every detail of the policy of the <lb/>
party to which I belong. The <lb/>
party may in the opinion of some <lb/>
of the members be wrong in certain <lb/>
directions without forfeiting in any <lb/>
degree the loyalty of those members. <lb/>
Every party in Canada is quite broad <lb/>
enough and big enough to allow differ<lb break="no"/>ences of opinion in its ranks. A politic<lb break="no"/>al party represents a large number of <lb/>
individuals and it would be perfectly <lb/>
unreasonable to suppose that every <lb/>
member would be agreed on every <lb/>
point. That would be to deny actual <lb/>
facts and actual experiences and actual <lb/>
circumstances. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Preaner then referred to the <lb/>
condition of both political parties in <lb/>
England who, at the present timme, <lb/>
different amongst themselves on very <lb/>
large and important pricniples, and <lb/>
then went on to say: With regard to <lb/>
my position with the Conservative <lb/>
party I am in thorough unison with it <lb/>
on an questions of principle, and am <lb/>
confident and believe that its members <lb/>
are just as strong now as they were in <lb/>
days of either success or adversity and <lb/>
that its principles are just as sound and <lb/>
good. But the policy of that party and <lb/>
those principles have nothing whatever <lb/>
to do with my position in this House. The <lb/>
country must be satisfied that I will <lb/>
faithfully and sincerely and impartially <lb/>
do my duty up front and trust on the <lb/>
times. I have given time and time again <lb/>
to my constituents, my colleagues, to <lb/>
the House and to the people of the <lb/>
Territories generally. The House then <lb/>
adjourned. <lb/></p> 


  <!-- IC, 2018-10-31, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day --> 


<!--<p>THURSDAY, April 23rd. <lb/></p> 

<p>The session of the Assembly this <lb/>
afternoon was spent in the considera<lb break="no"/>tion of a large number of Bills, by far <lb/>
the most important of which was the <lb/>
Bill to amend the Liquor Licence <lb/>
Ordinance introduced by Premier <lb/>
Haultain. Mr. Thos. W. Taylor, M.P.P. <lb/>
for Centre of Winnipeg occupied a seat <lb/>
on the floor of the House during Mr. <lb/>
Haultain's brief description of the <lb/>
objects of this Bill. <lb/></p> 

<p>ELECTION OF DEPUTY SPEAKER. <lb/></p> 

<p>After Mr. Speaker had taken the <lb/>
chair the Premier moved the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of Alexander Cameton Ruther<lb break="no"/>ford (Stratheona) as Deputy-Speaker of <lb/>
the House. The nomination was hearti<lb break="no"/>ly endorsed by Mr. R. B. Bennett, <lb/>
both speakers joining in testifying to <lb/>
the eminent fitness of Mr. Rutherford <lb/>
for the position, which, by reason of <lb/>
the fact that much of the actual busi<lb break="no"/>ness of the House was transacted in <lb/>
Committee, was a most important one. <lb/></p> 

<p>THE LIQUOR LICENCE ORDINANCE. <lb/></p> 

<p>In moving the second reading of the <lb/>
Bill to amend the Liquor Licence Or<lb break="no"/>dinance, Premier Haultain said the <lb/>
intention of the Bill was to increase <lb/>
the requirements of hotel premises <lb/>
entitled to receive licences and make <lb/>
them more efficient for the purposes <lb/>
for which they are operated. The <lb/>
standard of buildings and their equip<lb break="no"/>ment entitled to receive licences was, <lb/>
therefore, raised, and hotels in cities, <lb/>
and towns would have required to have <lb/></p>

<milestone type="unknown"/> <lb/>
 <lb/>

<p>at least 20 bedrooms for the use of the <lb/>
public, and in villages ten bedrooms. <lb/></p> 

<p>NO BEER ON RACE TRACKS. <lb/></p> 

<p>The bill also does away with the per<lb break="no"/>mits to sell beer on race tracks. This <lb/>
power, said the Premier, was limited a <lb/>
few years ago by doing away with the <lb/>
privilege in connection with races at <lb/>
agricultural shows but it was now pro<lb break="no"/>posed to go further and do away with <lb/>
it altogether. There was always <lb/>
trouble in connection with the issue of <lb/>
these permits and they were invariably <lb/>
abused. <lb/></p> 

<p>NO LICENCES TO MARRIED WOMEN. <lb/></p> 

<p>In future no licences would be grant<lb break="no"/>ed to a marriage woman that is to a <lb/>
lady whose husband is living. A diffi<lb break="no"/>culty had been met with in the case of <lb/>
men who had forfeited their licence <lb/>
securing others in the name of their <lb/>
wives. It was to put a stop to this practice. <lb/></p> 

<p>NEED OF BETTER HOTEL ACCOMODA-<lb break="maybe"/>TION. <lb/></p> 

<p>The proposition to increase the hotel <lb/>
accommodation was one Mr. Haultain <lb/>
said he thought should be generally <lb/>
approved. The hotel accommodation <lb/>
at the present time was quite insuffic<lb break="no"/>ient for the present demands of the <lb/>
travelling public and the business was <lb/>
increasing to such an extent that they <lb/>
were quite justified in raising the <lb/>
standard. <lb/></p> 

<p>LICENCES CONFINED TO CITIES, TOWNS <lb/>
AND VILLAGES. <lb/></p> 

<p>After this licence years, the Premier <lb/>
continued, is was proposed to restrict <lb/>
licences to cities, towns, and villages. <lb/>
This would affect certain hotels in <lb/>
country places which are more like <lb/>
stopping places than hotels. They <lb/>
were given a year, however, before the <lb/>
change would be made and many <lb/>
points at which hotels might reason<lb break="no"/>ably be established and conducted <lb/>
would have arrived at the village stage. <lb/>
The less liquor at what might be term<lb break="no"/>ed simply stopping places the better. <lb/></p> 

<p>There are also some important pro<lb break="no"/>visions for the simplification of the <lb/>
Liquor Licence Ordinance with refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the obtaining of convictions <lb/>
and in some cases the penalties are in<lb break="no"/>creased. <lb/></p> 

<p>A PROHIBITORY CLAUSE. <lb/></p> 

<p>One clause gives to the Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor in Council power by procla<lb break="no"/>mation to bring into force the pro<lb break="no"/>visions of the prohibitory clauses of <lb/>
the old N.W.T Act. In this connec<lb break="no"/>tion Mr. Haultain said there were some <lb/>
portions of the country where it was <lb/>
impossible to extend the licence system <lb/>
and where consequently there were <lb/>
practically no restrictions now and <lb/>
where the provisions of the old pro<lb break="no"/>hibitory law might with advantage be <lb/>
enforced and it was for this reason that <lb/>
they were asking for power to proclaim <lb/>
such provisions by order-in-council. <lb/></p> 

<p>BREWERIES TO BE LICENCED. <lb/></p> 

<p>They were also asking that brewer<lb break="no"/>ies and distilleries be licenced. At <lb/>
present there were not distilleries in the <lb/>
Territories but there were a number of <lb/>
breweries. Some of these were a credit <lb/>
to the Territories; others were the re<lb break="no"/>verse. It was only right that brewer<lb break="no"/>ies should pay a licence the same as all <lb/>
other dealers in intoxicating liquors. <lb/></p> 

<p>AN IMPORTANT DEPARTURE. <lb/></p> 

<p>Another important and new provis<lb break="no"/>ion provides that not only the man <lb/>
holding the licence but also the prem<lb break="no"/>ises may be disqualified under certain <lb/>
conditions for violations of the law. <lb/>
So long as landlords are willing to lease <lb/>
their premises without regard to the <lb/>
character of the lesser then they should <lb/>
suffer the penalty for infractions of <lb/>
the law. In conclusion Mr. Haultain <lb/>
said that it was proposed to ask for the <lb/>
second reading of the Bill, have it <lb/>
printed and distributed and considered <lb/>
by the Members and the country dur<lb break="no"/>ing the adjournment of the House so <lb/>
that all would be in a position to deal <lb/>
with it when the House reassembles in <lb/>
June. <lb/></p> 

<p>OPPOSITION'S MILD CRITICISM. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. R. B. Bennett said there was no <lb/>
legislation on the statute book about <lb/>
which there was a more uniform desire <lb/>
on the part of the House to see enforc<lb break="no"/>ed than the liquor legislation. So far <lb/>
as the general provision of the legisla<lb break="no"/>tion now proposed, that is, to provide <lb/>
for better accommodation in the coun<lb break="no"/>try for the travelling public and to en-<lb break="maybe"/>froce the authority of the Assumbly <lb/>
with respect to the liquor traffic, there <lb/>
would be general agreement. In view <lb/>
of the poor indoor-or rather outdoor <lb/>
accommodation-for the travelling <lb/>
public he thought the Legislature <lb/>
should pass the most drastic legislation <lb/>
to secure to the people some comfort <lb/>
at least. The hotels are making great <lb/>
sums of money and ought to provide <lb/>

<cb/>

good accommodation. He was also <lb/>
strongly in favor of restricting the <lb/>
granting of licences to hotels in settled <lb/>
communities. Anything to do away <lb/>
with the liquor at mere stopping places <lb/>
where people on their way to and from <lb/>
market towns wasted their money for <lb/>
liquor would be endorsed. As a gen<lb break="no"/>eral rule he was not in favor of legisla<lb break="no"/>tion which empowered the Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor in Council to act in the capa<lb break="no"/>city of a judge. He took it, however, <lb/>
that the cause in question relating to <lb/>
the prohibitory clauses of the old N. <lb/>
W.T. Act contemplates the taking of <lb/>
action in this way where a vote has <lb/>
been taken as to whether there should <lb/>
be licence or not. Mr. Haultain sigur-<lb break="maybe"/>ied that such was the intention, and <lb/>
Bennett said he thought anything <lb/>
which would prevent these continually <lb/>
squabbles over local option would be a <lb/>
good thing. He agreed also that it was <lb/>
time the loophole whereby licences <lb/>
were secured by a man in his wife's <lb/>
name should be stopped. The Bill was <lb/>
the read a second time. <lb/></p> 

<p>HAIL INSURANCE AMENDMENTS. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Haultain introduced a Bill <lb/>
amending the Municipal Ordinance; <lb/>
also one to amend and consolidate the <lb/>
Hail Insurance Ordinance. He ex<lb break="no"/>plained that this latter Bill provided <lb/>
for two changes. First, to add speltz <lb/>
to the list of insurable grains, and <lb/>
second, to change the charge for insur<lb break="no"/>ance from ten cents an acre, with a <lb/>
gratuitity for a second sum of ten cents <lb/>
should the first amount not cover all <lb/>
the claims, to a straight charge of fif<lb break="no"/>teen cents an acre, and also or a sural <lb/>
fee of fifty cents which could be paid <lb/>
to canvassers or agents to solicit busi<lb break="no"/>ness. During the year the main diffi<lb break="no"/>culty in connection with the Ordiance <lb/>
was the small number taking advan<lb break="no"/>tage of it and it was felt that it would <lb/>
be necessary to canvass for business. <lb/>
The Bill was read a second time. <lb/></p> 

<p>Just before adjournment Mr. Haul-<lb break="yes"/>tain laid on the Table of the House the <lb/>
correspondence with the Federal Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment relative to the financial ques<lb break="no"/>tion and the demand of the local Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment for a larger grant. <lb/></p> 

<p>FRIDAY, April 24th. <lb/></p> 

<p>On the opening of the Assembly to<lb break="no"/>day Premier Haultain moved that the <lb/>
House resolve itself into committee to <lb/>
consider the Supply to be granted to <lb/>
His Honor the Lieutenant Governor. <lb/>
A message from His Honor was re<lb break="no"/>ceived submitting an estimate of $100,-<lb break="maybe"/>000. In making the motion the Pre<lb break="no"/>mier said the government must be car<lb break="no"/>ried on until the final passage of the <lb/>
estimates. The estimate brought down <lb/>
simply provided for a lump sum to <lb/>
carry on the ordinary services of the <lb/>
Government. The Government was <lb/>
asking the House to place that much <lb/>
confidence in it and he thought the <lb/>
circumstances justified the course, <lb/>
especially as later on the Government <lb/>
would have to ask the House <lb/>
or its approval of a detailed <lb/>
statement of how this money was <lb/>
spent. The sum of $10,000 was also <lb/>
asked for to provide for the payment <lb/>
of one-half of the sessional indemnity <lb/>
and travelling expenses of the Mem-<lb break="maybe"/>oers. Both items were passed without <lb/>
discussion. <lb/></p> 

<p>OTTAWA GOVERNMENT RESPONSIBLE. <lb/></p> 

<p>In moving that when the House ad<lb break="no"/>journs to-morrow it do stand adjourn<lb break="no"/>ed until 8th June, the Premier said it <lb/>
was not necessary to enter into any <lb/>
lengthy explanation of the reasons for <lb/>
taking this step. The position breifly <lb/>
was that the North-West Government <lb/>
had not been made aware of the <lb/>
amount of money which is to be placed <lb/>
at the disposal of the Territories. Re<lb break="no"/>presentations had been made to Ottawa <lb/>
out up to the present time no action <lb/>
had been taken, at least officially, and <lb/>
communicated to the Legislature. On <lb/>
the morning after the Assembly met <lb/>
he had received an unofficial telegram <lb/>
from a member of the Ottawa Govern<lb break="no"/>ment informing him in general terms <lb/>
of the vote which is to be brought <lb/>
down. He was asked to consider the <lb/>
telegram as unofficical. The terms in<lb break="no"/>dicated in this telegram were not in <lb/>
the opinion of the local Government at <lb/>
all suitable and the North-West Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment immediately telegraphed a <lb/>
strong remonstrance with a vew of <lb/>
changing the demand of the Dominion <lb/>
Government. Negotiations were still <lb/>
in progress. Even if they had been <lb/>
officially informed at that time and had <lb/>
full information it would be impossible <lb/>
for the Government at that stage of <lb/>
the session, with all the other work of <lb/>
the session in hand, to sit down, and <lb/>
work out the detailed and elaborate <lb/>
estimates of expenditure for the year, <lb/>
and especially for this year, as in view <lb/>
of the storms and extra expenditure <lb/>
last year the accounts were in a rather <lb/>
mixed condition. This was the reason <lb/>
for asking for the adjournment. He <lb/>
need not emphasise the inconvenience <lb/>
of this state of affairs. It was suffici<lb break="no"/>ently emphasised by the fact that the <lb/>
House was absolutely obliged to ad<lb break="no"/>journ for several weeks in order to <lb/>
await information which they could <lb/>
reasonably claim the Legislatures should <lb/>
have had a month or six weeks ago. <lb/>
The whole onus or blame, if blame <lb/>
there was, for the ajournment did not <lb/>
rest on t he Government of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories but belonged at Ottawa. The <lb/>
motion was concurred in. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Haultain introduced a bill to in<lb break="no"/>corporate the Macleod Club, and Dr. <lb/>
Elnott one to provide for the protec<lb break="no"/>tion of horse breeders in the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, both of which were read a first <lb/>
time and stand for their second read<lb break="no"/>ings on 8th June. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Fisher (Banff) moved for a return <lb/>
showing all lands and the names of the <lb/>
original owners thereof in Local Im<lb break="no"/>provement District No. 500, that have <lb/>
been vested in the Crown for non-pay-<lb break="maybe"/>ment of local improvement or other <lb/>
taxes. Motion agreed to. <lb/></p> 

<p>BILLS PASSED. <lb/></p> 

<p>The following Bills were read a third <lb/>
time and passed:- To amend the Or<lb break="no"/>dinance incorporating Calgary; to <lb/>
amend the Ordinance incorporating <lb/>
Moosomin; to incorporate the Moose <lb/>
Jaw General Hospital; to amend the <lb/>
Ordinance incorporating the Galt Hos<lb break="no"/>pital; to incorporate the Toronto Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Trusts Corporation; to amend the <lb/>
Ordinance incorporating Lethbridge; <lb/>
to amend the Ordinance incorporating <lb/>
the Yorkton Hospital; to attend the <lb/>
Ordinance incorporating Yorkton. <lb/></p> 

<p>INCOMES OF $1,000 EXEMPT. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Bill to amend the Municipal Or<lb break="no"/>dinance was also passed. These amend<lb break="no"/>ments, Mr. Haultain stated, emanated <lb/>
from the Standing Committee on <lb/>
Municipal Law. They raise the amount <lb/>
of income exempt from the income tax <lb/>
from $600 to $1,000. The request for <lb/>
this amendment came from certain <lb/>
towns where a large number of railway <lb/>
employees reside and who are also pay<lb break="no"/>ing taxes as owners of property. It <lb/>
was not the men but the municipalities <lb/>
affected who asked for the change. <lb/></p> 

<p>HAIL INSURANCE. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Bill relating to hail insurance <lb/>
was also passed. A short discussion <lb/>
occurred on the working of the Ordi<lb break="no"/>nance last year which was participated <lb/>
in by R. B. Bennett, G. W. Brown, A. <lb/></p>

<milestone type="unknown"/> <lb/>

<p>S. Smith, A. S. DeRosenroll, the Com<lb break="no"/>missioner of Public Works and the <lb/>
Premier. Mr. Bulyea described the <lb/>
efforts made by the Department <lb/>
last year to bring the pro<lb break="no"/>visions of the Ordinance before the <lb/>
farmers in order to get them to take <lb/>
advantage of it. The amendment pro<lb break="no"/>viding for a fee of fifty cents with each <lb/>
application, and which it was intended <lb/>
should be used to pay canvassers send<lb break="no"/>ing in applications, was necessary in <lb/>
order to secure business. The -\-\-\-<lb break="maybe"/>ast year was the small amount of busi<lb break="no"/>ness done. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Haultain stated it was a remark <lb/>
able fact that last year the insurance <lb/>
that was taken out was in those very <lb/>
districts which were visited by han <lb/>
storms. The expenditure under the <lb/>
Ordinance was altogether out of pro<lb break="no"/>portion to the number taking advan<lb break="no"/>tage of it. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Bennett took some exception to <lb/>
the wording of the clause giving the <lb/>
Government power to appoint can<lb break="no"/>vassers and said they might be can<lb break="no"/>vassing for the Government as well as <lb/>
for hail insurance. The Bill passed <lb/>
without amendment. <lb/></p> 

<p>AUTONOMY AND MORE MONEY <lb/>
DEMANDED. <lb/></p> 

<p>Just prior to adjournment the Pre<lb break="no"/>mier presented the report of the <lb/>
special committee appointed to draft a <lb/>
memorial to the Governor General in <lb/>
Council on the questions of the consti<lb break="no"/>tutional and financial position of the <lb/>
Territories, railway transportation and <lb/>
the public domain. He stated that the <lb/>
committee had drafted two memorials, <lb/>
one dealing with the constitutional <lb/>
and financial question and the other <lb/>
with railway transportation. Tuesday <lb/>
he read, the first being as follows:<lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>To His Excellency the Right Honorable <lb/>
Sir Gilbert John Elliot, Earl of Minto <lb/>
and Viscount Melguid of Melgund, <lb/>
County of Forfar in the Peerage of <lb/>
the United Kingdom, Baron Minto <lb/>
of Minto, County of Roxburgh, in <lb/>
the Peerage of Great Britain, Baron<lb break="no"/>et of Nova Scotia, Knight Grand <lb/>
Cross of the Most Distinguished <lb/>
Order of St. Michael and St. George, <lb/>
etc., Governor General of Canada. <lb/></p> 

<p>MAY IT PLEASE YOUR EXCELLENCY: <lb/></p> 

<p>We, His Majesty's dutiful and loyal <lb/>
subjects, the Legislative Assembly on <lb/>
one North-West Territories of Canada, <lb/>
in session assembled, humbly approach <lb/>
Your Excellency for the purpose of <lb/>
representing-<lb break="yes"/></p> 

<p>That by an Address dated on the <lb/>
second day of May in the year one <lb/>
thousand nine hundred, a copy on <lb/>
which is attached hereto, the Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive Assembly pointed out that re<lb break="no"/>peated representations had been made, <lb/>
in various ways, to the Government of <lb/>
Canada with a view to obtaining just <lb/>
and equitable assistance towards pro<lb break="no"/>viding for the proper and effective <lb/>
administration of affairs in these Terri<lb break="no"/>tories and for the public necessities of <lb/>
their rapidly increasing population, <lb/>
and that such representations had been <lb/>
met by intermittent and insufficient <lb/>
additions to the annual grant, the pro<lb break="no"/>vision so made by the Parliament <lb/>
of Canada never bearing any adequate <lb/>
proportion by the enlargement and devel<lb break="no"/>opment of the political institutions <lb/>
created by itself; <lb/></p> 

<p>That by the said Address, the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Assembly humbly prayed that <lb/>
Your Excellency would be graciously <lb/>
pleased to cause an enquiry to be made <lb/>
into the position of the Territories, <lb/>
nuancial and otherwise, and to cause <lb/>
such action to be taken as would pro<lb break="no"/>vide for their present and immediate <lb/>
welfare and good government, as well <lb/>
as the due lumlment of the duties and <lb/>
obligations of Government and legis<lb break="no"/>lation assured with respect to these <lb/>
Territories by the Parliament of Cana<lb break="no"/>da, and it was furthermore humbly <lb/>
prayed that Your Excellency would be <lb/>
also graciously pleased to order en<lb break="no"/>quiries to be made and accounts taken <lb/>
with a view to the settlement of the <lb/>
terms and conditions upon which the <lb/>
Territories or any portion thereof <lb/>
should be established as a Province; <lb/></p> 

<p>That since the passing of the said <lb/>
Address further representations have <lb/>
been made in various ways to Your <lb/>
Excellency's Government with regard <lb/>
to the financial and constitutional <lb/>
position of the Territories; <lb/></p> 

<p>That during the past three years the <lb/>
immediate necessities of the Territories <lb/>
have been vastly increased by a re<lb break="no"/>markable immigration movement, <lb/>
which is still going on; <lb/></p> 

<p>That no adequate response has been <lb/>
made to the repeated requests for the <lb/>
financial assistance necessary for "the <lb/>
proper and effective administration of <lb/>
" the affairs of these Territories and <lb/>
" for the public necessities of their <lb/>
" rapidly increasing population." <lb/></p> 

<p>That the Legislative Assembly, re<lb break="no"/>presenting, as it does, the unanimous <lb/>
opinion of the people of the Territories, <lb/>
believes that nothing short of that <lb/>
system of government enjoyed by our <lb/>
fellow citizens in the Provinces will <lb/>
afford a solution of the Legislative and <lb/>
financial difficulties which confront it; <lb/></p> 

<p>Therefore we do humbly pray that <lb/>
Your Excellency in Council will cause <lb/>
such action to be taken as will provide <lb/>
for the present and immediate financial <lb/>
necessities of the Territories and will <lb/>
further provide for the establishment <lb/>
of provincial institutions upon fair and <lb/>
just terms analogous to those upon <lb/>
which the old Provinces have been <lb/>
dealt with; <lb/></p> 

<p>All which we humbly pray Your <lb/>
Excellency to take into Your Excel<lb break="no"/>lency's gracious and favorable con<lb break="no"/>sideration. <lb/></p> 

<p>C.P.R'S NEGLECT OF DUTY. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Premier also read the <lb/>
memorial on the subject of railway <lb/>
transportation. It was as follows: <lb/></p> 

<p>To His Excellency the Right Honorable <lb/>
Sir Gilbert John Elliot, Earl of Minto, <lb/>
etc., etc., Governor General of Can<lb break="no"/>ada. <lb/></p> 

<p>MAY IT PLEASE YOUR EXCELLENCY: <lb/></p> 

<p>We, His Majesty's dutiful and loyal <lb/>
subjects, the Legislative Assembly of <lb/>
the North-West Territories of Canada, <lb/>
in session assembled, humbly approach <lb/>
Your Excellency for the purpose of <lb/>
representing <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>That after making due allowance for <lb/>
the extraordinary circumstances with <lb/>
which the Canadian Pacific Railway <lb/>
Company has had to contend it appears <lb/>
to this House <lb break="no"/> </p> 

<p>That the practically continuous <lb/>
freight congestion of the last two <lb/>
years has abundantly demonstrated <lb/>
that the Canadian Pacific Railway <lb/>
Company has absolutely failed to pro<lb break="no"/>vide adequate facilities for the trans<lb break="no"/>portation of the grain, cattle and other <lb/>
natural products of these Territories <lb/>
and that there has resulted in conse-<lb break="maybe"/>sequence of the lack of suck facilities <lb/>
great loss and damage to the people of <lb/>
these Territories not only in respect of <lb/>
the depreciation in the market price of <lb/>
grain but also in respect of cattle and <lb/>
has further resulted in vexatious de<lb break="no"/>lays in the importation of merchandise <lb/>
and in the transaction of the ordinary <lb/>
business of the country: <lb/></p> 

<p>That the volume of business origin<lb break="no"/>ating along the main line of the Cana<lb break="no"/>dian Pacific Railway and in the terri<lb break="no"/>tory directly tributary thereto neces<lb break="no"/>sitates that the energies of the Com<lb break="no"/>pany should be concentrated on the <lb/>
providing of adequate facilities for <lb/>
handling such business (which are <lb/>
not now provided) and that good faith <lb/>
with the people of these Territories de<lb break="no"/>mands that branch lines already pro<lb break="no"/>mises and partially constructed should <lb/>
be completed this year rather than <lb/></p>

<milestone type="unknown"/> <lb/>

<p>cities in territory already provided with <lb/>
railway facilities and; <lb/></p> 

<p>That the prospective increase in the <lb/>
volume of traffic which largely increas<lb break="no"/>ed cultivation and settlement of lands <lb/>
in these Territories will certainly <lb/>
create will further tend to congest <lb/>
traffic between these Territories and <lb/>
the provinces to the east and unless it <lb/>
is held desireable to divert part of such <lb/>
traffic through foreign channels ade<lb break="no"/>quate facilities for its transportation <lb/>
must be immediately provided, and <lb/></p> 

<p>That this House does therefore hum<lb break="no"/>bly pray that Your Excellency may be <lb/>
pleased to take such actions as may be <lb/>
necessary or expedient to insure that <lb/>
the people of these Territories are pro<lb break="no"/>vided with an efficient transportation <lb/>
system as contemplated by the contract <lb/>
made between the people of Canada <lb/>
and the Canadian Pacific Railway <lb/>
Company. <lb/></p> 

<p>The memorials were unanimously <lb/>
adopted, ordered to be engrossed, <lb/>
signed by the Speaker and transmitted <lb/>
in Ottawa through the Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor. <lb/></p> 

<p>THE PUBLIC DOMAIN. <lb/></p> 

<p>With regard to the public domain <lb/>
the committee submitted a resolution <lb/>
as follows: <lb/></p> 

<p>"The believing in the justice of the <lb/>
claim made on behalf of any province <lb/>
or provinces hereafter established in <lb/>
the Territories to the beneficial owner<lb break="no"/>ship of the public domain, this House <lb/>
doth hereby record its emphatic opin<lb break="no"/>ion against any further alienation of <lb/>
the lands, timber or minerals of the <lb/>
Territories except for the purposes of <lb/>
homesteading and actual settlement." <lb/></p> 

<p>This was also unanimously adopted <lb/>
and copies ordered to be sent to Sir <lb/>
Wilfrid Laurier and the Minister of <lb/>
the Interior. <lb/></p> 

<p>In moving the adjournment Mr. <lb/>
Haultain stated that His Honor <lb/>
would attend at the Assembly to-mor-<lb break="maybe"/>row afternoon at three o'clock to give <lb/>
assent to the Bills which had been <lb/>
passed and then adjournment would <lb/>
take place. <lb/></p> 

<p>Before the Members left the chamber <lb/>
Speaker Gillis referred to the fact that <lb/>
some of the Members indulged in <lb/>
smoking during the sittings of the <lb/>
House and he asked that this be dis<lb break="no"/>continued, a request which was hearti<lb break="no"/>ly applauded by the House. <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>