<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgASLA_1904-09-27"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>,
          <date when="1904-09-27">27 September 1904</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA"> 
               <editor>William Franklin Kerr</editor>.
          <title>The Leader</title>.
          <date when="1904-10-05"/>.
          <pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>:
          <publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>,
          <biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="3"/>.
        </bibl>
        
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1904-10-05_Page_003.hocr.html"/>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1904-10-05_Page_001-edit7521.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
  
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-11-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="The_Leader_1904-10-05_Page_001.jpg">
         <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1904-10-05_Page_001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      
      <surface xml:id="The_Leader_1904-10-05_Page_003.jpg">
         <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1904-10-05_Page_003.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            
            
            
            <pb n="1"
               facs="final/images/The_Leader_1904-10-05_Page_001.jpg"/>
            
            
            <fw type="running">THE LEADER.</fw>
    
    

            <fw type="running">REGINA, N.W.T., WEDNESDAY, OCTOBER 5, 1904</fw>
            
  
  
            <head rendition="simple:centre">DEBATE ON <lb/>THE ADDRESS</head>
            
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">The Important Feature of Last <lb/>Week's Sittings of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Assembly.</head>

            <p rendition="simple:right">Tuesday, September 27th.</p>

            <p>The Legislative Assembly got down <lb/>to business to-day and in the course <lb/>of an hour and three-quarters dispos<lb break="no"/>ed of the Address in Reply to the <lb/>Speech of His Honor, the Lieutenant <lb/>Governor. After the presentation of<lb/>a couple of petitions, and the adop<lb break="no"/>tion of the report of the Committee <lb/>on Standing Orders and Private Bills <lb/> <persName ref="pers:GREE4">Mr. Greeley</persName>, (Maple Creek), moved <lb/>that "a humble address be presented <lb/>to His Honor, thanking him for the <lb/>gracious speech with which he open<lb break="NO"/>ed the Session."</p>
            
            <p>[...]</p>

            <p rendition="simple:centre">A Question of Taxation.</p>
            

            <p>The speaker expressed his regret at <lb/>the intimation in the Speech that it <lb/>was not the intention of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to bring down any very large <lb/>measures and stated his willingness <lb/>to stay there a while longer and <lb/>thresh out some of the important le<lb break="no"/>gislation which had been promised. <lb/>He referred more particularly to the <lb/>question of municipal organisation <lb/>and taxation. They all remembered <lb/>the work done last session and he re<lb break="no"/>gretted to say there did not appear <lb/>to be anything foreshadowed in the <lb/>Speech to lead them to infer that <lb/>this question would come up this ses<lb break="no"/>sion. The people in this district did <lb/>not care particularly for any large <lb/>municipal system but the question of <lb/>taxation was one that re-interested <lb/>them deeply and required some at<lb break="no"/>tention.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>There is, said Mr. Greeley, consid<lb break="no"/>erable dissatisfaction in some dis<lb break="no"/>tricts, more particularly the stock­<lb break="yes"/>growing sections, in regard to taxa<lb break="no"/>tion. This comes particularly from <lb/>the smaller landlord, who feels that <lb/>they are not being quite properly <lb/>dealt with, perhaps, in the matter of <lb/>taxation. The range conditions are <lb/>somewhat peculiar. It appears to <lb/>me there is no law nor any reason <lb/>why anybody should own anything <lb/>but stock. The condition of affairs <lb/>is that a man may go unto that dis<lb break="no"/>trict with from 100 to as many thou<lb break="no"/>sand head of cattle as he wants to <lb/>and go elsewhere and carry on his op<lb break="no"/>eration and by not leasing land prac<lb break="no"/>
        
        
            <cb/>
       
       tically pays no revenue into the Terri<lb break="no"/>torial treasury. He receives the bene<lb break="no"/>fits of roads, bridges, fire-guards, <lb/>etc., that are being paid for by the <lb/>small property owner who does not <lb/>own very many head of live stock <lb/>and these small property owners nat<lb break="no"/>urally feel that their taxes are not <lb/>being fairly distributed. Very many <lb/>of the large companies are paying <lb/>quite substantial sums into the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritorial funds, but there are a large <lb/>number of people who contribute <lb/>practically nothing to the mainten<lb break="no"/>ance of district needs and who should <lb/>be in some way got at. I had hoped <lb/>that this municipal legislation would <lb/>come up this session and result in <lb/>placing these matters in a more sat<lb break="no"/>isfactory position than they now <lb/>are.<lb/>
            </p>
            
           <p>[...]</p>


            <p rendition="simple:centre">Adequate Money Grants.</p>

            <p>I am very glad to note that the <lb/>Parliament of Canada has seen fit to <lb/>give us, approximately at any rate, <lb/>adequate grants. (Hear, hear.) After <lb/>all, while we have got an increased <lb/>vote this year, we also have an in<lb break="no"/>creased number of people coming in <lb/>and a strong demand will be made <lb/>on that vote. I do not think this <lb/>increase is anything to crow about. <lb/>(Laughter.) While we are all pleased <lb/>to know there is an increased grant <lb/>yet it had been held back for a long <lb/>time and much of it will be required <lb/>to meet accumulating necessities. I <lb/>do not consider the mere fact of re<lb break="no"/>ceiving a few dollars more or less is <lb/>any reason why we should be denied <lb/>the exercise of the right of self gov<lb break="no"/>ernment by the people of this coun<lb break="no"/>try. We all agree in the expressions <lb/>of regret that the establishment of <lb/>the Territories on the provincial bas<lb break="no"/>is has not been materially forward<lb break="no"/>ed during the past year. I feel sure <lb/>the House will press for it until we <lb/>reach that status. I see no reason, <lb/>nor have I heard any argument ad<lb break="no"/>vanced why we should not become a <lb/>province.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:BENN5">Mr. Bennett</persName> — One or two provin<lb break="no"/>ces ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GREE4">Mr. Greeley</persName> – I will say why we <lb/>should not receive provincial rights—</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BENN5">Mr. Bennett</persName> — Hear, hear.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:GREE4">Mr. Greeley</persName> – If that is satisfac<lb break="no"/>tory to the hon. gentleman. I am <lb/>myself in favor of provincial auton<lb break="no"/>omy and the people of this country <lb/>as a whole are in favor of it. It <lb/>seems to me that all the evidence <lb/>goes to show this. Every agitation <lb/>for enlarged local powers in the loc<lb break="no"/>al improvement districts, in towns <lb/>desiring to become cities, etc., are <lb/>only applications for provincial <lb/>rights, for after all what is a pro<lb break="no"/>vince but a large improvement dis<lb break="no"/>trict. (Cheers.)<lb/>
            </p>

            <p rendition="simple:centre">Mr. McIntyre Seconds the Motion.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MCIN5">Mr. A. D. McIntyre</persName>, (Mitchell), in <lb/>seconding the motion said:—<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Speaker</persName>,—It is with pleasure <lb/>that I rise on this occasion to second <lb/>the resolution moved by the Honor<lb break="no"/>able Member for Maple Creek to ex<lb break="no"/>press the sense of appreciation the <lb/>House has of the gracious speech <lb/>with which His Honor, the Lieuten<lb break="no"/>ant Governor opened this session of <lb/>the Legislative Assembly of the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories on Thursday of last week. I <lb/>understand that this occasion marks <lb/>the commencement of His Honor's <lb/>second term of office and I am sure I <lb/>but give utterance to the feelings of <lb/>the Members of the House when I <lb/>say that we all trust that His Honor <lb/>may be granted health and strength <lb/>to perform the duties devolving upon <lb/>him in his high office with that un<lb break="no"/>failing courtesy and graciousness <lb/>which we have all experienced from <lb/>time to time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>We can all join with His Honor in <lb/>thankfulness at the continuation of <lb/>the prosperous era which has mark<lb break="no"/>ed the history of the Territories dur-­<lb/>ing the past few years and we may<lb/>hope for its continuance for an indefin<lb break="no"/>ite period. Hard times will no doubt <lb/>recur, and seasons will come in which <lb/>the climatic conditions will be such <lb/>as to cause disaster and loss to our <lb/>crops, as, I regret to learn from His <lb/>Honor's speech, has been the case in <lb/>a few localities this year, but "hope<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> (Continued on Page 3.) <lb/>
            </p>
        
        
        
            <pb n="3"
               facs="final/images/The_Leader_1904-10-05_Page_003.jpg"/>
            
            <div type="section">
           
           
            <head rendition="simple:centre">DEBATE ON THE ADDRESS.</head>
            
            
            <p rendition="simple:centre">(Continued From Page 1.)</p>
           
               
        <p>[...]</p>
               
               <p>
            We were all glad to learn that the<lb/>
            Dominion Government has recognized<lb/>
            the necessities of the Territories in the<lb/>
            unprecedented increase to our grant,<lb/>
            which for the first time is the full<lb/>
            amount asked for. There is no Mem<lb break="no"/>ber in this House I feel safe in say<lb break="no"/>ing who has not time and again, felt<lb/>
            the pinch of poverty in our public fi<lb break="no"/>nances. I do not suppose that the<lb/>
            present remarkable increase will any<lb break="no"/>thing like meet all the requirements<lb/>
            of the country, for as usual the "sup<lb break="no"/>ply" will create a "demand." But I<lb/>
            think we should all recognise one<lb/>
            fact evidenced by the large increase in<lb/>
            our grant. We have all heard the<lb/>
            small grants we have had in the past<lb/>
            attributed to the difficulty met with<lb/>
            by the Dominion Government in in<lb break="no"/>teresting Members of Parliament from<lb/>
            Eastern constituencies in western af<lb break="no"/>fairs. The fact that such a large<lb/>
            grant has been given for this year<lb/>
            without any criticism shows, to my<lb/>
            mind, that that difficulty has been<lb/>
            done away with. Though we have not<lb/>
            been successful in obtaining provin<lb break="no"/>cial institutions, yet I am hopeful<lb/>
            from the fact that I have just mentioned,<lb/>
            that we are within a reasonable dis<lb break="no"/>tance of it.<lb/>
            </p>
               
               
            <p>
               Mr. Speaker, it is with much pleas<lb break="no"/>ure I second the resolution before the<lb/>
               House.<lb/>
            </p>
            
               
               <p rendition="simple:centre">
               The Opposition Leader.<lb/>
            </p>
               
               
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. D. H. McDonald</persName>, leader of the<lb/>
               Opposition, followed.<lb/>
            </p>
               
               <p>[...]</p>
               
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
               Received Full Amount Asked For.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               I quite agree with the Government<lb/>
               in expressions of pleasure that this<lb/>
               year we have received all the money<lb/>
               we asked for.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:PATR1">Dr. Patrick</persName> — Possibly they did<lb/>
               not ask for enough.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> — Well, then it is up<lb/>
               to them.</p>
               
               <p>[...]</p>
               
               <cb/>
      
      
            <p>
               Taking up the question of provin<lb break="no"/>cial autonomy, Mr. McDonald said he<lb/>
               sincerely hoped that when they next<lb/>
               met together, whether at a legisla<lb break="no"/>ture of the North-West Territories,<lb/>
               or as a provincial legislature, that at<lb/>
               that time the provincial question<lb/>
               would be settled. I believe, said<lb/>
               the speaker, that we should have this<lb/>
               question settled by this time. (Hear,<lb/>
               hear.) I am sincerely in favor of get<lb break="no"/>ting autonomy, but I understand<lb/>
               this Government has made it a con<lb break="no"/>sideration that there must be one<lb/>
               province. As you know, we of the<lb/>
               Opposition do not agree to that. I<lb/>
               believe a majority of this Legislat<lb break="no"/>ure is now getting to that way of<lb/>
               thinking. All we have to do today<lb/>
               is to keep plugging at the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and they will come around on<lb/>
               this as they have done on many<lb/>
               things. I do not believe there is<lb/>
               anyone in Canada who believe that<lb/>
               the whole North-West will be form<lb break="no"/>ed into one large province. This is<lb/>
               a matter in which we are not the<lb/>
               only people interested. When we be<lb break="no"/>come a province or provinces we en<lb break="no"/>ter into confederation with the other<lb/>
               provinces and they will have some<lb break="no"/>thing to say about our size. During<lb/>
               recent years we have been growing<lb/>
               in population, our representation in<lb/>
               the House of Commons has been in<lb break="no"/>creased, and we now have a larger<lb/>
               force at our back and should there<lb break="no"/>fore be in a position to obtain bet<lb break="no"/>ter terms than we could four or five<lb/>
               years ago. I do not know, there<lb break="no"/>fore, but that we have been actual<lb/>
               gainers by the matter of provincial<lb/>
               autonomy being postponed for a few<lb/>
               years. However, I believe the time<lb/>
               has come for the granting of pro<lb break="no"/>vincial institutions and I hope the<lb/>
               Government will have better success<lb/>
               before the House meets again.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">Poked Fun at Bennett.</p>
            
               
               <p>
               Although not informed officially,<lb/>
               we have reason to believe that a<lb/>
               number of Members in this Assembly<lb/>
               are endeavoring to secure seats in<lb/>
               the House of Commons and, we<lb/>
               trust, if any are successful that they<lb/>
               will represent the views of this As<lb break="no"/>sembly. (Hear, hear.) I have always<lb/>
               thought that it would be a very<lb/>
               good thing if certain Members of this<lb/>
               Legislature were in the House of<lb/>
               Commons. (Laughter.) Of course<lb/>
               there are some Members you cannot<lb/>
               recommend for that position. (More<lb/>
               laughter.) But I think we all ought<lb/>
               to be agreed that if any man resigns<lb/>
               his seat in this House and attempts<lb/>
               to secure a seat in the House of<lb/>
               Commons and is defeated he should<lb/>
               not endeavor to come back here.<lb/>
               (Loud laughter, during which Mr. R.<lb/>
               B. Bennett interjecting some remark.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> — I am sorry that<lb/>
               I have hurt the feelings of the Mem<lb break="no"/>ber for West Calgary, but he has<lb/>
               given up all idea of ever securing a<lb/>
               seat in the House of Commons.<lb/>
               (Laughter.) Aside from political con<lb break="no"/>siderations it would be a good thing<lb/>
               if some of the Members of this As<lb break="no"/>sembly were amongst those represent<lb break="no"/>ing us at Ottawa.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> in referring to the<lb/>
               Governor General, said he would<lb/>
               prove a good friend of the North-<lb break="yes"/>
               West and in bringing our great agri<lb break="no"/>cultural resources before the people<lb/>
               of Great Britain would do us a great<lb/>
               service as, after all, it was to the<lb/>
               mother country we looked for the<lb/>
               great number of people we expect to<lb/>
               have in this country.</p>
               
               <p>[...]</p>
               
               
               <cb/>
               
               <p>
               Member for the district, and that if<lb/>
               the Government had not sufficient<lb/>
               confidence in the Member they should<lb/>
               send an engineer in to investigate<lb/>
               and report. Mr. McDonald resumed<lb/>
               his seat amidst applause.<lb/>
            </p>
               
               
            <p rendition="simple:centre">The Premier's Reply.</p>
               
               
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Premier Haultain</persName> was received with<lb/>
               hearty applause on rising to reply.<lb/>
            </p>
               
             <p>[...]</p>
               
               <cb/>
               
               <p>We have received a</p>
               
               <p rendition="simple:centre">Very Substantial Increase.</p>
               
               <p>
                  to our Parliamentary vote and I<lb/>
                  am very glad that such is the case,<lb/>
                  and we will have no difficulty in<lb/>
                  knowing where to put it. This in<lb break="no"/>creased vote will be, as one of the<lb/>
                  speakers said this afternoon, only a<lb/>
                  temporary alleviation of our position<lb/>
                  and will only go to meet accumulated<lb/>
                  needs which have increased from year<lb/>
                  to year under insufficient grants.</p>
               
               <p>
                  So far as the provincial question<lb/>
                  is concerned, we in this House are<lb/>
                  one on that. I regret that the lead<lb break="no"/>er of the Opposition sounded even the<lb/>
                  one discordant note this afternoon<lb/>
                  of one or more provinces. The decid<lb break="no"/>ing of that question rests with<lb/>
                  Ottawa. What we want is pro<lb break="no"/>vincial instiutions and the right to
                  
                  <cb/>
                  
                  manage our own affairs. I have op<lb break="no"/>inions, and others have strong op<lb break="no"/>inions possibly, as to the area with<lb break="no"/>in which these institutions should<lb/>
                  be put in operation, but I consider<lb/>
                  that an unimportant item in any dis<lb break="no"/>cussion raised in this House. We<lb/>
                  should drop that and be united on<lb/>
                  this question so far as possible, and<lb/>
                  I believe we can continue to be unit<lb break="no"/>ed so far as we have been in the<lb/>
                  past, that is to say that this coun<lb/>try should have provincial institu<lb break="no"/>tions. We have required them for<lb/>
                  the past three years and if we re<lb break="no"/>quired them then, we require them<lb/>
                  much more to-day. (Cheers.)
                
               </p>
               
               
  
  
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>