<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgASLA_1903-11-21" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>,
<date when="1903-11-21">21 November 1903</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA"> <editor>William Franklin Kerr</editor>.
<title>The Leader</title>.
<date when="1903-11-26"/>.
<pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="12" to="13"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1903-11-26_Page_0012.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1903-11-26_Page_0013.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-31">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-31">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1903-11-26_Page_0012"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1903-11-26_Page_0012.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1903-11-26_Page_0013"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1903-11-26_Page_0013.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="12" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1903-11-26_Page_0012.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="num">12</fw>

<fw type="running">THE LEADER, THURSDAY, NOVEMBER 26, 1908.</fw> 

<p rendition="simple:right">SATURDAY, NOV. 21st.</p> 

<p>The House met at 11 o'clock this <lb/>
morning to resume the consideration <lb/>
of the Estimates. On the vote for the <lb/>
brand book, <persName ref="pers:FINL3">Mr. Finlay</persName> drew attention <lb/>
to the long delay which had occurred <lb/>
in the issue of the book and the great <lb/>
inconvenience which resulted. He <lb/>
suggested that a supplement to the <lb/>
book be issued every month and sent <lb/>
to all inspectors so as to enable them <lb/>
to identify and trace stock. <persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. <lb/>
McDonald</persName> suggested that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment should endeavor to ascertain how <lb/>
many export cattle there were in the <lb/>
country. An interesting discussion <lb/>
occurred on the vote for education, in <lb/>
which it was shown by several speakers <lb/>
how the foreign population coming <lb/>

<cb/>

into the Territories was adapting itself <lb/>
to our conditions and particularly in <lb/>
the desire to have educational facilities <lb/>
for their children. The Estimates were <lb/>
passed through committee and the <lb/>
House rose at 12.30 o'clock. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">DR. PATRICK RESUMES DEBATE.</p> 

<p>When the House re-assembled at <lb/>
two o'clock <persName ref="pers:PATR1">Dr. Patrick</persName> resumed the <lb/>
debate on the budget. He commenced <lb/>
by again referring to the reasons which <lb/>
the Opposition had to congratulate <lb/>
themselves on the legislation of the <lb/>
past three sessions. There had not <lb/>
only been an improvement in legisla<lb break="no"/>tion but also in the policy of the <lb/>
Government respecting several impor<lb break="no"/>tant Ordinances. <lb/></p> 

<p>On the question of provincial auto<lb break="no"/>nomy and one or more provinces Dr. <lb/>
Patrick said the first resolution they <lb/>
passed did not commit the House one <lb/>
way or the other. Later the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in their negotiations at Ottawa <lb/>
declared for one province, but now the <lb/>
House had once more urged for auto<lb break="no"/>nomy regardless of the number of <lb/>
provinces. The Premier in his last <lb/>
election address had said, if he remem<lb break="no"/>bered rightly, that one province would <lb/>
do for the present time; the other <lb/>
question could be considered later. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>. I said nothing of the sort. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PATR1">Dr. Patrick</persName>. Maybe my memory is <lb/>
at fault. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>. It is. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PATR1">Dr. Patrick</persName> then took up the question <lb/>
of the capital advance. At first he <lb/>
said he feared that it might be accept<lb break="no"/>ed but the announcement made in the <lb/>
House yesterday cleared the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment when the Premier declared that <lb/>
it was not intended to accept it. It <lb/>
would be a mistake for the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to borrow money from those who <lb/>
owed us. The question as to whom <lb/>
the advance would be made also arose <lb/>
as they did not know the boundaries <lb/>
of the provinces which were to be. As <lb/>
to the statement that it would be loan<lb break="no"/>ed without interest, the Speaker de<lb break="no"/>clared it would be charged against us <lb/>
for all time to come and after the <lb/>
settlement when we became a a province <lb/>
we would be mulcted for five per cent. <lb/>
for all time to come. The interest <lb/>
which we would lose would amount to <lb/>
$12,500 a year. He believed when we <lb/>
became a province we could borrow <lb/>
money as low as three per cent., which, <lb/>
capitalised at three per cent., meant <lb/>
$166,000. This represented the loss <lb/>
which would result to the country <lb/>
from the acceptance of the capital ad<lb break="no"/>vance. The Opposition felt constrain<lb break="no"/>ed to support the Government in its <lb/>
policy. The Legislature was powerless <lb/>
to do more than it had done. Unfor<lb break="no"/>tunately the Territories had been <lb/>
placed in an equivocal position by rea<lb break="no"/>son of the fact that the Territorial <lb/>
representatives at Ottawa thought one <lb/>
way and the representatives here <lb/>
thought another way. That was a <lb/>
position which the Assembly could not <lb/>
help or end without surrendering its <lb/>
opinions on the matter. The position <lb/>
could only be ended by the people of <lb/>
the Territories themselves and could <lb/>
only be done by sending to Ottawa <lb/>
men who believed in the immediate <lb/>
granting of provincial institutions, <lb/>
men who believed in granting to the <lb/>
people of the Territories their rights of <lb/>
local self-government. Until that time <lb/>
arrived they must be content with <lb/>
things as they were. In conclusion <lb/>
Dr. Patrick said that while the Oppo<lb break="no"/>sition supported the Government on <lb/>
its general policy they would examine <lb/>
their actions with a critical eye, but <lb/>
otherwise they would not oppose it, <lb/>
"not in the life of the present House <lb/>
at least." <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE OPPOSITION LEADER.</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> said the present ses<lb break="no"/>sion of the House was the most import<lb break="no"/>ant held for many years. Some of the <lb/>
legislation which they had to deal with <lb/>
touched them in a most important <lb/>
way. On that side of the House they <lb/>
had not said much in speech on the <lb/>
question of autonomy, but on looking <lb/>
into the matter fully he was satisfied <lb/>
that the Government had done the <lb/>
proper thing in refusing to take advan<lb break="no"/>tage of the capital account placed <lb/>
within its reach by the Dominion Par<lb break="no"/>liament. (Hear, hear). They should  <lb/>
let the authorities at Ottawa know <lb/>
that we are not going to be satisfied <lb/>
with money only. There were prin<lb break="no"/>ciples at stake. (Hear, hear). They  <lb/>
were pressing for autonomy and all the <lb/>
advantages that should go with it. If <lb/>
they had accepted the grant it might <lb/>
have placed them at the mercy of the <lb/>
Dominion Government forever. If at <lb/>
any time it was agreed upon by the <lb/>
Assembly to authorise the Government <lb/>
to seek for a capital advance from the <lb/>
federal authorities they should first <lb/>
decide on what works the money was <lb/>
to be expended. When matters came <lb/>
to be finally dealt with, when the time <lb/>
arrived to make two provinces, the <lb/>
matter of a final adjustment of capital <lb/>
account between the different parts of <lb/>
the Territories would have to be dealt <lb/>
with. The House should be unanimous <lb/>
on this question. The people in the <lb/>
country had watched the Opposition <lb/>
on this question as closely as they had <lb/>
watched the Government. They had <lb/>
suspicions that some Members of the <lb/>
House were going to treat this other <lb/>
than as a North-West question. It <lb/>
should be treated purely as a North-<lb break="yes"/>West question. (Hear, hear). <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. McDonald did not consider the <lb/>
present the most favorable time for <lb/>
holding the session of the Legislature. <lb/>
It was neither at the close of one fin<lb break="no"/>ancial year nor at the beginning of <lb/>
another. If they considered the best <lb/>
interests of the whole country the best <lb/>
time for holding the sessions would be <lb/>
in the early part of the calendar year, <lb/>
both for the convenience of Members, <lb/>
the benefit of the country and the <lb/>
transaction of business as it should be <lb/>
transacted. He looked with favor on <lb/>
the amendments brought in at the <lb/>
present session but he wished to again <lb/>
record his disapproval of establishing <lb/>
local districts of only four townships. <lb/>
The people would find that that area <lb/>

<cb/>

was much too small for any proper <lb/>
system. He also wished to take <lb/>
exception to some language used in <lb/>
the House the previous day with <lb/>
reference to our demands upon the <lb/>
federal government. He did not think <lb/>
it was a wise thing for the Leader of <lb/>
the House to say that no Government <lb/>
at Ottawa could grant their demands. <lb/>
They should not place ourselves in the <lb/>
position of saying that we have not <lb/>
got a good case, as the language used <lb/>
would lead them to believe. They had <lb/>
good demands and had evidence to <lb/>
support them and should urge them in <lb/>
that spirit. If, said Mr. McDonald, <lb/>
the Dominion Government believes <lb/>
that we do not believe in them <lb/>
ourselves, or that they cannot grant <lb/>
them, that is a very good argument <lb/>
for not meeting them. He trusted <lb/>
also that in future the Government <lb/>
would leave out the question of one <lb/>
province and simpy seek for the <lb/>
granting of provincial rights and then <lb/>
this point of contention would not be <lb/>
brought up in that House. They could <lb/>
agree with the Government on the <lb/>
main question of the day; other <lb/>
questions should under existing <lb/>
circumstances be left alone. (Applause.) <lb/></p>

<p rendition="simple:centre">FAVORED ACCEPTANCE OF ADVANCE.</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SMIT7">Mr. A. S. Smith</persName> (Moosomin) congra<lb break="no"/>tulated the Government on the very <lb/>
large amount of money they were able <lb/>
to vote during the session. The re<lb break="no"/>quirements of the country were very <lb/>
much greater than they were a year <lb/>
ago or even six months ago and they <lb/>
would continue to increase. The de<lb break="no"/>mands on the local Government would <lb/>
continue to increase and our demands <lb/>
on the federal Government would also <lb/>
continue to increase until provincial <lb/>
autonomy was granted. He neither <lb/>
agreed with the Government nor the Op<lb break="no"/>position on the question as to whether <lb/>
the capital advance should be accepted <lb/>
or not. In the past they were all well <lb/>
aware that the amounts of money suf<lb break="no"/>ficient to carry on the government of <lb/>
the country were not forthcoming. <lb/>
They voted and spent money and <lb/>
created debt and the federal Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment had paid it. The country re<lb break="no"/>quired roads and bridges today more <lb/>
than ever. The transportation question <lb/>
was the big question in the West and <lb/>
roads and bridges were a part of that <lb/>
question and affected it as much as <lb/>
anything else. He believed the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment should have accepted the <lb/>
capital grant. He would not like to <lb/>
go back to his constituents and say <lb/>
that he had not raised his voice against <lb/>
the Government refusing that grant. <lb/>
He understood at the summer session <lb/>
that it was because the amount neces<lb break="no"/>sary to construct the two bridges in <lb/>
the western portion of the Territories <lb/>
was being charged against this advance <lb/>
that the local Government would not <lb/>
accept it. That was the position then <lb/>
but it was altered now because the <lb/>
federal Government was paying for <lb/>
those two bridges and that objection <lb/>
was therefore withdrawn. <lb/></p> 

<p>In the House and in the country he <lb/>
had discussed the provincial question <lb/>
as strongly as any Member, and, <lb/>
while perhaps not with the same <lb/>
ability as some others, he had always <lb/>
brought the question before the people <lb/>
as forcibly as he had been able to do. <lb/>
As to the question of one or two <lb/>
provinces, if the time ever came when <lb/>
the Assembly and the country thought <lb/>
there should be two provinces it would <lb/>
then be for the people of the Territories <lb/>
themselves to decide. His opinion was <lb/>
one province and that it would be best <lb/>
for the whole country. It was never <lb/>
expected that the Dominion authorities <lb/>
would at the very first see eye to eye <lb/>
with the Territories in their demands. <lb/>
He hoped that eventually the <lb/>
settlement would be on the lines <lb/>
suggested by the Government of the <lb/>
North-West and the people would <lb/>
thank the Government in years to <lb/>
come. He regretted that on the <lb/>
question of the capital advance he had <lb/>
to take a different view of the question <lb/>
to that taken by the Members of the <lb/>
Government. His convictions forced <lb/>
him to it and he would stultify himself <lb/>
to do otherwise. (Applause.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:BENN5">MR. R. B. BENNETT</persName></p>
    
    <p>
congratulated the House on having <lb/>
been able to provide an expenditure <lb/>
which would not place the Territories <lb/>
in debt or which contemplated any <lb/>
overdraft, but the only solution of the <lb/>
difficulties with which they were faced <lb/>
was the granting of the provincial <lb/>
status. The Premier's speech appealed <lb/>
to the sound common sense of the <lb/>
House and would appeal to the country. <lb/>
It was not the speech of a party leader <lb/>
but of the leader of a great people <lb/>
crying out for a change. There had <lb/>
been two sets of reasons advanced by <lb/>
two sets of persons as to why the <lb/>
granting of provincial autonomy <lb/>
should be delayed. There were what <lb/>
he might call the official reasons and <lb/>
the semi-official reasons. The first of <lb/>
these were those given by the Premier <lb/>
of Canada and the Minister of the In<lb break="no"/>terior but it was not his purpose to dis<lb break="no"/>cuss these. They were not sound. The  <lb/>
House by the adoption of the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion that week had said they were not <lb/>
sound, that they were insufficient, in<lb break="no"/>adequate reasons, and he would leave <lb/>
them there. If by an accident there <lb/>
should be two sides at Ottawa seeing <lb/>
matters in a different light, that was <lb/>
no reason why one side should be con<lb break="no"/>sidered to know our affairs better than <lb/>
ourselves, or why if one side supported <lb/>
our claims and were willing to grant <lb/>
our petition we should not support <lb/>
them. He referred to the fight against <lb/>
railway monopoly in Manitoba, where, <lb/>
he declared, the Conservatives had op<lb break="no"/>posed their party friends at Ottawa in <lb/>
the interests of the province and he <lb/>
appealed to the patriotism of the Mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the House to stand united in <lb/>
the struggle whether it be against a <lb/>
Liberal or a Conservative government <lb/>
until the Territories received that <lb/>
measure of justice to which they were <lb/>
entitled. <lb/></p> 

<p>He would refer to the semi-official <lb/>
reasons for delay. The Member for <lb/></p> 

<!--<p>(Continued on page 5.) <lb/></p>-->

<pb n="13" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1903-11-26_Page_0013.jpg"/>
    
    <fw type="num">13</fw>

<fw type="running">THE LEADER, THURSDAY, NOVEMBER 26, 1908.</fw> 
</div>
    <div type="debate">
        
<head rendition="simple:centre">THE BUDGET DEBATE</head> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">(Continued from page 5.)</p> 

<p>Saskatchewan was clear and distinct <lb/>
on the question. He said we do not <lb/>
need provincial autonomy. He would <lb/>
leave that to the sound judgement of <lb/>
the thirty-five representtives in the <lb/>
Assembly. The Member for Alberta <lb/>
alleged that it was a good deal better <lb/>
to continue as we are and that it was <lb/>
only a matter of dollars and cents. <lb/></p> 

<p>Then there were the reasons ad<lb break="no"/>vanced by the Member for West <lb/>
Assiniboia as to why provincial auton<lb break="no"/>omy should be refused. These had <lb/>
been satisfactorily answered by the <lb/>
Attorney General. He ( <persName ref="pers:BENN5">Bennett</persName> ) had <lb/>
taken the attitude in times past in the <lb/>
House that the Government ought to <lb/>
co-operate as far as possible with the <lb/>
Members at Ottawa representing the <lb/>
North-West Territories to the end of <lb/>
procuring better terms. He believed <lb/>
that four Members at Ottawa support<lb break="no"/>ing the Government would have a <lb/>
great influence to that end. He had <lb/>
moved a resolution to that effect. It <lb/>
was no doubt in pursuance of that <lb/>
policy that Mr. Bulyea wrote his per<lb break="no"/>sonal letter, backed up by the Liberal <lb/>
Members of the Assembly. He had no <lb/>
fault to find with it in so far as it re<lb break="no"/>ferred to the Territories as a whole <lb/>
and not to a part of it. It was a com<lb break="no"/>mon thing to write such letters and he <lb/>
had done so himself in the past and <lb/>
would probably do so in the future. <lb/>
But the House had every reason to be<lb break="no"/>lieve that their representations would <lb/>
be received and considered with care <lb/>
at Ottawa. It came to him as a sur<lb break="no"/>prise the reasons given by the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Members. He had believed that <lb/>
these gentlemen would stand up for <lb/>
the rights of the West apart from all <lb/>
considerations. He did not intend to <lb/>
go into the reasons they had advanced <lb/>
as it would be idle to do so after the <lb/>
speech of the Attorney General. The <lb/>
House, however, owed a large duty to <lb/>
itself which it must discharge. He had <lb/>
read yesterday an editorial in a paper <lb/>
published by one of the gentlemen <lb/>
representing the Territories in the <lb/>
House of Commons, he referred to the <lb/>
Regina Leader, in which the statement <lb/>
was made that the solemn demand <lb/>
made by this House in 1900, in 1902, in <lb/>
1903 and reaffirmed the other day was, <lb/>
after all, what? Merely an attempt <lb/>
on the part of a great corporation to <lb/>
help to assist the movement for auto<lb break="no"/>nomy in order that certain rights <lb/>
might accrue to them and that the <lb/>
lands in these Territories, which we <lb/>
are so anxious to obtain, should be <lb/>
granted to the end that a Conservative <lb/>
administration might be empowered in <lb/>
the Territories. A statement like that <lb/>
called for refutation. It was not what <lb/>
he contended for; further it was not <lb/>
what the House contended for. It was <lb/>
a statement insulting not to one man <lb/>
alone but it did violence to every <lb/>
instinct of decency coming from such <lb/>
a source. Coming, as it did, from <lb/>
a journal which had supported the <lb/>
Government in this House, which <lb/>
called upon the federal Government to <lb/>
grant our demands, the statement of <lb/>
yesterday ill accorded with former <lb/>
statements. It ill accorded with the <lb/>
editorial utterances of that paper in <lb/>
the past and with the speeches of that <lb/>
gentleman. In the interests of a <lb/>
sound public opinion, in the interests <lb/>
of the stability of our institutions, he <lb/>
protested that the policy of a <lb/>
demagogue should not be intruded on <lb/>
a question such as this. He did not <lb/>
believe that any Member in the House <lb/>
believed that any attempt was being <lb/>
made by that Legislature to have <lb/>
provincial institutions granted to the <lb/>
country immediately and the lands <lb/>
given to us to promote any interests of <lb/>
any corporation. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">TAXATION OF C.P.R. LANDS.</p> 

<p>He had made the statement that so <lb/>
far as taxing C.P.R. lands in school <lb/>
districts was concerned that was a <lb/>
question that was solving itself. He <lb/>
made that statement before and he <lb/>
made it again and it was absolutely <lb/>
correct. He would say that it was an <lb/>
unfortunate thing that so large an <lb/>
exemption was granted to that <lb/>
corporation and it was the duty of the <lb/>
House to get some compensation for <lb/>
it. Who could cast the horoscope of <lb/>
the future and see 20 years in advance? <lb/>
No man in the House of Commons of <lb/>
that day could to it. The same policy <lb/>
had been followed in the United <lb/>
States. It was unfortunate that in the <lb/>
early stages school taxes were not paid <lb/>
for school purposes by that corporation, <lb/>
but was it any reason because a few <lb/>
thousand dollars of school taxes would <lb/>
be lost in Assiniboia that the Territories <lb/>
should be deprived of the right of <lb/>
self-government? He adopted the <lb/>
reasoning of the Attorney General <lb/>
with regard to the contention as to <lb/>
taxing stations, and the other property <lb/>
of the corporation in so far as the <lb/>
rights of school districts were <lb/>
concerned. If the court of last resort <lb/>
held that the Territories had a right to <lb/>
tax C.P.R. lands for school purposes <lb/>
then could not the Parliament which <lb/>
granted the exemption insert a <lb/>
provision giving us all the rights as a <lb/>
province which we have as Territories? <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">REASONS FOR REFUSING THE ADVANCE.</p> 

<p>The larger question had been raised <lb/>
as to whether or not they should spend <lb/>
the $250,000 held up before them by <lb/>
the Dominion Parliament. For one <lb/>
he said they should not. It would be <lb/>
unsound business to touch it. There <lb/>
were several reasons against accepting <lb/>
it. First, until our just demands had <lb/>
been satisfactorily met by the federal <lb/>
Government. Second, because it <lb/>
meant a direct lessening of the federal <lb/>
expenditure in this country. The <lb/>
Dominion Government was paying for <lb/>
the two bridges in the west which had <lb/>
been referred to but what happened <lb/>
the other day when a deputation went <lb/>
to Ottawa and asked for the construc<lb break="no"/>tion of a large traffic bridge at Saska<lb break="no"/>toon? Sir Wilfrid Laurier simply <lb/>
said "Go to Regina and they will <lb/>
build it for you out of the capital <lb/>
advance." That meant that instead of <lb/>
building the bridge and charging the <lb/>
cost against Canada as a whole it <lb/>
would be charged against the capital <lb/>
account of the Territories. Here in <lb/>
the West we had no canals or harbors <lb/>
to be constructed as public works by <lb/>
the Dominion and in this country he <lb/>
contended that these large bridges <lb/>
should be considered public works for <lb/>
the benefit of Canada and the whole of <lb/>
Canada should pay their share towards <lb/>
them in the same way as the people in <lb/>
the West were paying their share for <lb/>
digging canals, erecting lighthouses, <lb/>
dredging harbors, etc., in the old <lb/>
provinces. A third reason was that it <lb/>
was fastening a loan on the people of <lb/>
the Territories on terms about which <lb/>
they had nothing to say. With pro<lb break="no"/>vincial autonomy they could borrow <lb/>
money at least as low as four per cent. <lb/>
While they would get the sum offered <lb/>
without interest now it would ulti<lb break="no"/>mately cost them $12,500 per annum <lb/>
for ever. In the early days in the <lb/>
Western States the States and Terri<lb break="no"/>tories enjoyed the power of borrowing <lb/>
money and pledging the public credit <lb/>
and so confident were they of the <lb/>
future that they paid as high as ten <lb/>
per cent per annum and the invest<lb break="no"/>ment had proved a good one. Fourth, <lb/>
it would mean putting off the granting <lb/>
of provincial institutions. The Domin<lb break="no"/>ion would take the position of the federal <lb/>
Members that it was merely a question <lb/>
of money and not of principle. Fifth, <lb/>
the very fact of being styled Territories <lb/>
instead of having the dignity of a <lb/>

<cb/>

province was an injury and a man <lb/>
going abroad to do business would soon <lb/>
realise the great advantage of coming <lb/>
from a province rather than a terri<lb break="no"/>tory. The business men today were <lb/>
writing at the head of their letter <lb/>
paper "Regina, Canada," instead of <lb/>
"Regina, N.W.T.," or "Assiniboia." <lb/>
It was difficult to divest oneself entirely of <lb/>
party bias in dealing with this ques<lb break="no"/>tion but he had endeavoured to do so. <lb/>
In conclusion he appealed to his Liberal <lb/>
friends not to allow party exigencies <lb/>
to outweigh the country's interests. <lb/>
The constituencies which had returned <lb/>
them before to press for autonomy <lb/>
would return them again. (Applause.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BROW6">MR. G. W. BROWN</persName></p>
        <p>
followed. He congratulated the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment on the result of its efforts on <lb/>
behalf of the North-West, not only on <lb/>
the result of its appeals to Ottawa, but <lb/>
also on its legislation and the adminis<lb break="no"/>tration of the affairs of the Territories. <lb/>
He congratulated also the members of <lb/>
the Opposition upon the fact that they <lb/>
too had found themselves in complete <lb/>
unison with the Government policy on <lb/>
those questions which during past <lb/>
sessions they had complained of so <lb/>
strongly and that that legislation <lb/>
which they had been pleased to term <lb/>
as an invasion of the people's rights <lb/>
had been so modified that they had <lb/>
found themselves without a place as <lb/>
adverse critics and that henceforth we <lb/>
might expect to see them good and <lb/>
valiant supporters of the Government. <lb/></p> 

<p>So far as asking for provincial auto<lb break="no"/>nomy was concerned, or the demands <lb/>
made upon the Ottawa Government for <lb/>
increased financial assistance, as well as <lb/>
the extension of our Legislative powers, <lb/>
he said the House had taken no step at <lb/>
variance with his opinion. The ques<lb break="no"/>tion as to whether there should be <lb/>
one province or two, was, in his opin<lb break="no"/>ion, a minor matter as compared with <lb/>
the question of keeping the Territories <lb/>
as a whole separate from conditions <lb/>
other than conditions which they <lb/>
themselves had created. The great <lb/>
question was that the Territories should <lb/>
be either erected into one large pro<lb break="no"/>vince, or, if it were argued that on <lb/>
account of their immense area they <lb/>
should have a preponderating influence <lb/>
in the affairs of the Dominion, then it <lb/>
might be considered advisable to divide <lb/>
the Territories as now constituted into <lb/>
two or more provinces, but he did not <lb/>
think that any one in this country <lb/>
would disagree with him when he said <lb/>
that it would be unfair to any portion <lb/>
of these Territories to be united to <lb/>
any of the other provinces against their <lb/>
will and to be subjected to the con<lb break="no"/>ditions and burdens, the creation of <lb/>
which they are not responsible for. It <lb/>
might be argued that on their being <lb/>
thrust into another province, matters <lb/>
could be arranged so as to give them <lb/>
justice, but he submitted that even if <lb/>
such were done, the chances of the <lb/>
minority retaining in the end what <lb/>
they were morally entitled to would not <lb/>
be very promising. The interests of all <lb/>
parts of the Territories are similar, the <lb/>
conditions which obtain throughout <lb/>
the country are uniform. In the busi<lb break="no"/>ness world of today companies were <lb/>
amalgamating and consolidating in <lb/>
order that business might be conduct<lb break="no"/>ed more cheaply, and he believed the <lb/>
same business principles which govern <lb/>
private business could be applied with <lb/>
equal force to public affairs and he <lb/>
firmly believed in the one province <lb/>
idea. <lb/></p> 

<p>Regarding the financial position, <persName ref="pers:BROW6">Mr. <lb/>
Brown</persName> said, that while they all agreed <lb/>
that the amounts received from the <lb/>
Dominion Government in the past <lb/>
were not sufficient, nor what we were <lb/>
justly entitled to, still it was a matter <lb/>
for congratulation to the Government <lb/>
of the Territories that they had secur<lb break="no"/>ed such a very substantial increase to <lb/>
their current revenue. <lb/></p> 

        <!-- IC, 2018-10-31, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->


<!--<p rendition="simple:centre">RESULTS OF EDUCATION.</p> 

<p>When he first came into the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, nine years ago, he supported <lb/>
the North-West Government in their <lb/>
demands at Ottawa, both for increased <lb/>
financial assistance and extended <lb/>
legislative powers. He believed that <lb/>
our present Premier, Mr. Haultain, at <lb/>
that time was just as sincere and just <lb/>
as reasonable in making his demands <lb/>
then as he was during his last mis<lb break="no"/>sion to Ottawa and he believed that <lb/>
it was the intention of the then Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment at Ottawa to treat the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories fairly, and he also believed that <lb/>
the present Government desire to treat <lb/>
the Territories fairly. Nine years ago <lb/>
only 59 per cent. of our financial de<lb break="no"/>mands were granted, while over 20 per <lb/>
cent. more than that has been <lb/>
granted this year not taking into <lb/>
account this capital advance. " I <lb/>
do not desire," said Mr. Brown, "to <lb/>
show that the then Government at <lb/>
Ottawa was any more unfair to us than <lb/>
the present Government, but the point <lb/>
is that the action of this House has had <lb/>
an educating influence on Parliament. <lb/>
This is not only true regarding our fin<lb break="no"/>ancial demands, but it is true in other <lb/>
matters as well. From year to year <lb/>
we have been entrusted with increased <lb/>
legislative powers, which have greatly <lb/>
facilitated the legislation of this House <lb/>
and has enabled us to deal with ques<lb break="no"/>tions of purely local import in such a <lb/>
manner as to avoid the continual clash<lb break="no"/>ing of federal and local legislation. I <lb/>
still believe that the demands made <lb/>
upon the Federal Government for in<lb break="no"/>creased financial assistance and legis<lb break="no"/>lative powers are just and that in <lb/>
receiving anything short of our de<lb break="no"/>mands we are receiving less than the <lb/>
Territories are entitled to. I believe that <lb/>
if our case were as thoroughly under<lb break="no"/>stood at Ottawa as it is here that we <lb/>
to-day would have provincial auto<lb break="no"/>nomy with all the powers and revenues <lb/>
which we are entitled to, but we must <lb/>
remember that as North-West men <lb/>
dealing particularly with North-West <lb/>
questions, being in close touch with <lb/>
everything which affects our country, <lb/>
it should be expected of us to be first <lb/>
of all fully conversant with the necessi<lb break="no"/>ties of this country, and he considered <lb/>
it the duty of everyone, not only in the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly, but throughout <lb/>
the length and breadth of the country, <lb/>
to use every reasonable endeavor to <lb/>
educate the people of Eastern Canada <lb/>
and the Government at Ottawa as to <lb/>
requirements of the Territories. In <lb/>
order that we may receive justice, a <lb/>
great educational influence must be <lb/>
brought to bear on the East. For the <lb/>
future as well as for the past, it is still <lb/>
true that a wise agitation is the best <lb/>
educating influence in the world." <lb/>
(Hear, hear.) He believed that we <lb/>
were entitled to the $898,000 that we <lb/>
asked for this year but he also believed <lb/>
that we should not have got as much <lb/>
as we did if we had not asked for, agi<lb break="no"/>tated and pressed for it. He believed <lb/>
the Government is to be congtratulated <lb/>
on the increased amount granted. <lb/></p> 

<p>C.P.R. LAND TAX EXEMPTION. <lb/></p> 

<p>He wished to differ from the state<lb break="no"/>ment made by the member for West <lb/>
Calgary in connection with the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of the exemption of the Canadian <lb/>
Pacific Railway lands from school tax<lb break="no"/>ation. The member for West Calgary <lb/>
had stated that this was a matter of no <lb/>
importance: that when schools were <lb/>
needed in any particular district it was <lb/>
not until practically all the railway <lb/>
lands had been sold and that the set<lb break="no"/>tlers had to pay the taxes. While he <lb/>
did not believe that this statement <lb/>
even was correct, because there were <lb/>
very many school districts situated in <lb/>
parts of the country where practically <lb/>
all the land paying taxes were even <lb/>
sections, still, supposing that the state<lb break="no"/>ment of the member for West Calgary <lb/>
was correct, he differed very widely <lb/>
from him. Some years ago the prin-<lb break="maybe"/>

<cb/>

ciple of taxing all the land in this <lb/>
country for the purposes of local im<lb break="no"/>provements was established. It was <lb/>
argued that if the settlers by coming <lb/>
into this country, building roads and <lb/>
bridges, establishing schools and good <lb/>
government were giving to the vacant <lb/>
lands a value, they were doing a work <lb/>
which ought to be supplemented by a <lb/>
taxation of all lands throughout the <lb/>
Territories, however remote, which <lb/>
were being enhanced in value by the <lb/>
expenditure of the moneys belonging <lb/>
to the people then in the country. <lb/>
The principle that all lands which re<lb break="no"/>ceive benefit from taxation should pay <lb/>
taxes was thus established, and what <lb/>
was true, he argued, in connection <lb/>
with local improvement taxation, was <lb/>
to a greater extent true in connection <lb/>
with schools. If this country was <lb/>
proud to be able to invite men to make <lb/>
their homes in it on the ground that <lb/>
in every fairly settled district they <lb/>
would have schools at their doors, <lb/>
which in efficiency would be equal to <lb/>
those where they were leaving, <lb/>
he thought it was a still greater <lb/>
matter of congratulation to the <lb/>
people of this country to say <lb/>
that if settlers should come to it <lb/>
who should find it necessary to locate <lb/>
themselves in comparatively sparsely <lb/>
settled districts that they there would <lb/>
also have the same advantages <lb/>
belonging to the old established <lb/>
settlements in this country. In <lb/>
order to sustain schools under these <lb/>
circumstances without imposing a <lb/>
burden too heavy to be borne by the <lb/>
enterprising pioneer, it is necessary <lb/>
that every acre of land so benefited, <lb/>
whether directly or indirectly, should <lb/>
pay a tax, which while not heavy <lb/>
enough to be a burden to anyone <lb/>
would be of substantial assistance in <lb/>
assisting those settlers who are <lb/>
struggling to establish the institutions <lb/>
so much prized in the land they came <lb/>
from. He thought it was far <lb/>
more important that the district <lb/>
sparsely settled where very little <lb/>
railway land had been sold should be <lb/>
assisted in their initial stages than <lb/>
that even assistance should be given to <lb/>
the old and established settlements, <lb/>
who, having overcome the early <lb/>
difficulties and having become <lb/>
comparatively well off, would feel no <lb/>
difficulty in maintaining efficient <lb/>
schools. <lb/></p> 

<p>He did not take any stock at all in <lb/>
the argument that we should <lb/>
congratulate ourselves that the people <lb/>
here have the privilege of paying all <lb/>
the taxes that are necessary to make <lb/>
this country an attractive one to the <lb/>
immigrant and that the people who are <lb/>
particularly interested in the coming <lb/>
here of the immigrants in order that <lb/>
they may sell their lands at good <lb/>
prices should be allowed to go free. <lb/>
This line was hardly in keeping with <lb/>
one who had so loudly proclaimed <lb/>
himself a champion of the rights of the <lb/>
North-West settlers. <lb/></p> 

<p>CAPITAL ADVANCE NOT REQUIRED. <lb/></p> 

<p>With regard to the capital advance <lb/>
he was glad to be able to congratulate <lb/>
the Government on that matter too, <lb/>
seeing they considered that the affairs <lb/>
of the Territories were in such a posi<lb break="no"/>tion that, though with some incon<lb break="no"/>venience, they were able to minister to <lb/>
the wants of the people without expen<lb break="no"/>diture on capital account. Personally <lb/>
he had no objection to accepting the <lb/>
capital advance. If the advance were <lb/>
used he would not tkae it as evidence <lb/>
that we were getting all that we ought <lb/>
to have as current revenue. He did <lb/>
not believe we would have long to wait <lb/>
for provincial autonomy. The signs of <lb/>
the times all pointed that way. If, <lb/>
however, we were not to get provincial <lb/>
establishment for some time, he be<lb break="no"/>lieved it would be a bad principle to <lb/>
lay down that we will not accept any <lb/>
advance on capital account unless we <lb/>
are made a province. He congratulat<lb break="no"/>ed the Government on the fact that <lb/>
they had not refused definitely to ac<lb break="no"/>cept such an advance but that if at a <lb/>
later day it was considered advisable <lb/>
to do so we would be in a position to <lb/>
accept such. <lb/></p> 

<p>The honorable member for West Cal<lb break="no"/>gary had referred favorably to the fact <lb/>
that certain States to the south had bor<lb break="no"/>rowed money and paid ten per cent. <lb/>
and that the investment had proved a <lb/>
most profitable one. He condemned <lb/>
the idea of our taking the money with<lb break="no"/>out interest, because it might later be <lb/>
charged against an account on which <lb/>
the Territories would receive five per <lb/>
cent. interest. He (Brown) thought the <lb/>
proposition before the Territories was a <lb/>
far better one. (Cheers). He could not see  <lb/>
that any principle was being endang<lb break="no"/>ered by the acceptance of a capital <lb/>
grant, or that it could affect a final <lb/>
settlement of our admission to the <lb/>
provincial status. "There is no rea<lb break="no"/>son," continued Mr. Brown, "to say <lb/>
that we cannot borrow that money at <lb/>
a low rate of interest on our admission <lb/>
to confederation and pay it back. <lb/>
There is no precedent to say that we <lb/>
cannot." <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Bennett. "There is a precedent <lb/>
in the case of Nova Scotia." <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Brown. "That is no precedent. <lb/>
Nova Scotia was a Province. No Ter<lb break="no"/>ritory ever made application to do it. <lb/>
(Cheers). The money was made avail<lb break="no"/>able by a special Act of Parliament, <lb/>
and the question of whether we pay <lb/>
the money back or allow it to be as<lb break="no"/>sumed as a debt by the Dominion <lb/>
Government is one which for the first <lb/>
time must be settled at the time of our <lb/>
entering Confederation. The hon. <lb/>

<cb/>

Member from West Calgary has found <lb/>
a great deal of fault with a certain edi<lb break="no"/>torial in the Regina Leader. He has <lb/>
even gone so far as to term it "dema-<lb break="maybe"/>gogism," but I hardly think it savors <lb/>
more of demagogism than the argu<lb break="no"/>ment of a certain gentleman who ad<lb break="no"/>vanced the argument two or three <lb/>
weeks ago at Lumsden that the reason <lb/>
why provincial autonomy was being <lb/>
delayed by the Federal Parliament was <lb/>
that the lands of these Territories <lb/>
might be exploited and the revenues <lb/>
therefrom handed over to the Grand <lb/>
Trunk Pacific Railway Co." <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Bennett. "I forgot that matter. <lb/>
I will refer to it on the third reading <lb/>
of this Bill." <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Brown. "So the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man not content with having rambled <lb/>
all over the list of questions before the <lb/>
country and having treated us to the <lb/>
most learned disquisitions of the rights <lb/>
and privileges of the citizens of <lb/>
this country, is going to treat <lb/>
us to another of his poetical <lb/>
effusions. Surely he knows that he is <lb/>
talking to a body of representative <lb/>
men who are as intelligent as the <lb/>
honorable gentleman and who can ex<lb break="no"/>press their views without taking an in<lb break="no"/>terminable length of time or in using <lb/>
an uninterrupted stream of adjectives." <lb/>
(Loud laughter). <lb/></p> 

<p>THE SASKATOON BRIDGE. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Brown then took up Mr. Ben<lb break="no"/>nett's argument which that gentle<lb break="no"/>man based on the Saskatoon bridge. <lb/>
The hon. gentleman from West Cal<lb break="no"/>gary has instanced the construction by <lb/>
the Dominion Government of the <lb/>
numberless small harbors and wharves <lb/>
in the Maritime Provinces built by the <lb/>
Dominion Government solely for the <lb/>
purpose of pandering to a certain vote. <lb/>
He did not consider the case at all <lb/>
analogous. There is no doubt <lb/>
that if the capital advance had <lb/>
been accepted the Saskatoon bridge <lb/>
would have been built and charg<lb break="no"/>ed to the capital account. If the <lb/>
capital advance had not been voted the <lb/>
Saskatoon bridge might have been <lb/>
built by the Dominion Government and <lb/>
it might not have been. For fifteen <lb/>
years this bridge has been a great <lb/>
necessity but up to the present no <lb/>
Government at Ottawa has seen fit to <lb/>
make the expenditure from the consol<lb break="no"/>idated revenues of the Dominion. In <lb/>
the case of the province of Manitoba, <lb/>
many such bridges have been built and <lb/>
most, if not all of them, have been paid <lb/>
by the province and the cost of them <lb/>
have become part of the debt of the <lb/>
Province of Manitoba, and the proba<lb break="no"/>bility is that the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would expect this and similar <lb/>
bridges to be built in the same way. <lb/>
The hon. member from West Calgary <lb/>
instanced the bridge across the St. <lb/>
Lawrence. Surely he did not mean to <lb/>
say that a bridge across the Saskat<lb break="no"/>chewan river at Saskatoon would be a <lb/>
work of the same nature as a bridge <lb/>
across the St. Lawrence river near <lb/>
Quebec. Again, I say, that while I do <lb/>
not deny that if the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had not placed at our disposal <lb/>
the sum of $250,000, to be used on capi<lb break="no"/>tal account that they might have built <lb/>
this bridge, I do say that there was <lb/>
no great probability of this work being <lb/>
taken up as a Dominion work and that <lb/>
if we had accepted the capital expendi<lb break="no"/>ture the bridge would have been a cer<lb break="no"/>tainty, as well as other works which <lb/>
are urgently needed by the Territories <lb/>
and through whose noncompletion we <lb/>
are suffering serious inconvenience and <lb/>
hindrance to the business of several <lb/>
districts in the Territories. He was <lb/>
acquainted with the condition of mat<lb break="no"/>ters at Saskatoon and of the great <lb/>
necessity for the bridge and the great <lb/>
difficulties under which the people <lb/>
labor without it, and thought the Dom<lb break="no"/>inion Government should build the <lb/>
bridge, but if they would not build it <lb/>
the North-West Government had no <lb/>
business to keep the people as they are <lb/>
without it. (Cheers.) <lb/></p> 

<p>In conclusion Mr. Brown said he <lb/>
believed in pressing as strongly as <lb/>
possible for provincial establishment. <lb/>
When we secured the provincial status <lb/>
the work of educating the east as to <lb/>
our needs and wants would very large<lb break="no"/>ly have ceased. The country had at<lb break="no"/>tained a position where we could man<lb break="no"/>age our own financial affairs as well as <lb/>
others and we should have full provin<lb break="no"/>cial powers just as soon as possible. It <lb/>
was the duty of every Member to press <lb/>
for it with every argument and every <lb/>
reason there was in favor of it and the <lb/>
time was not far away when we would <lb/>
get it. (Cheers.) Until that time ar-  <lb/>
rived it was the duty of every Member <lb/>
of the House to provide for the busi<lb break="no"/>ness of the country and to advance as <lb/>
far as possibnle those things which had <lb/>
for their object the furtherance of the <lb/>
growth and development of the great <lb/>
and glorious province which we expect <lb/>
to have inaugurated in a very short <lb/>
time. (Loud cheers.) <lb/></p>-->

</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>