<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgASLA_1897-12-09" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>,
<date when="1897-12-09">9 December 1897</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA"> <editor>Walter Scott</editor>.
<title>The Leader</title>.
<date when="1897-12-09"/>.
<pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1897-12-16_Page_001-edit4229.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-11-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-11-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1897-12-16_Page_001-edit4229"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1897-12-16_Page_001.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="nk" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1897-12-16_Page_001.jpg"/> <lb/>
 
 <fw type="num">1</fw>

<fw type="running">THE LEADER.</fw> 

<fw type="running">REGINA, N.W.T., THURSDAY EVENING, DECEMBER 16, 1897.</fw> 



<head rendition="simple:centre">LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY PROROGUED</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">A SEVEN WEEKS' SESSION BROUGHT TO <lb/>
A CLOSE YESTERDAY.</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">Synopsis of Proceedings of the Last Week of Ses<lb break="no"/>sion — Unanimous Expression Against Mutilation <lb/>
of the Boundaries — Jubilee Address — <lb/>
Question of Jurisdiction in Yukon – New Brand <lb/>
Law – Important Municipal Amendments — <lb/>
Variety of Legislation.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, Dec. 9, 1897.</p> 

<p>Report was presented from select com<lb break="no"/>mittee appointed to redraft Rules of Pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings of the House, and Rules for <lb/>
government of the Library. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">PRESERVE THE BOUNDARIES. <lb/>

<persName ref="pers:GILL3">Mr. GILLIES</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:DILL1">Mr. Dill</persName>, mov<lb break="no"/>ed That in the opinion of this House, the <lb/>
North-West Territories as they are at <lb/>
present composed should be maintained <lb/>
intact for administrative purposes until <lb/>
the time has arrived for their entrance <lb/>
into confederation as a province. <lb/></p> 

<p>The mover said the subject had already <lb/>
been pretty fully discussed, and he had <lb/>
been well pleased with Mr. Haultain's <lb/>
references to it on Monday. It was possi<lb break="no"/>ble that they attached too much impor<lb break="no"/>tance to the suggestion made by the Pre<lb break="no"/>mier of Manitoba last year with reference <lb/>
to extending the bounds of Manitoba. It <lb/>
might be said, too, that the subject had <lb/>
dropped. Still he was of opinion that it <lb/>
was important that the Assembly should <lb/>
with all its might denounce any proposi<lb break="no"/>tion to cut into the boundaries of the <lb/>
Territories. When Mr. Greenway's sug<lb break="no"/>gestion was made, the people of Eastern <lb/>
Assimboia freely expressed their opinions. <lb/>
If any move had been made to carry out the <lb/>
suggestion, he should not wish to be re<lb break="no"/>sponsible for what might have occurred. <lb/>
They knew what did occur once at Edmon<lb break="no"/>ton over the proposed removal of a land <lb/>
office, and he believed one of the Mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the House (Mr. McCauley) took <lb/>
prominent and successful action in that <lb/>
occurrence. If any hon. Member would <lb/>
visit Eastern Assinibois he would <lb/>
find that there was an attempt to exag<lb break="no"/>gerate what was the feeling of the people <lb/>
there on this question. He was satisfied <lb/>
that if any move had been made, our own <lb/>
Executive would have taken energetic <lb/>
measures so far as lay in their power to <lb/>
oppose it. Probably the Government <lb/>
had been wise, as no move was made, to <lb/>
ignore the suggestion. He said that great <lb/>
credit was due the press of the Territories, <lb/>
particularly the Regina "Leader" and <lb/>
Moosomin "Spectator," as well as to <lb/>
certain private individuals, for the way <lb/>
they had discussed and opposed the pro<lb break="no"/>position to allow Manitoba to take a valu<lb break="no"/>able portion of the Territories; and it <lb/>
was, he believed, in no small measure <lb/>
due to their efforts and energy that the <lb/>
suggestion was nipped in the bud. There <lb/>
could not be the slightest doubt that the <lb/>
Premier of Manitoba had been sincere in <lb/>
his wish to annex a portion of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. In some quarters in the east it <lb/>
was urged that this country was too large <lb/>
for a province. That arguinent was per<lb break="no"/>fectly absurd, as the size and diversities <lb/>
of Ontario proved. He made the motion <lb/>
to give force to the arguments that had <lb/>
been put forth in behalf of the preserva<lb break="no"/>tion of our boundaries and to demonstrate <lb/>
to everybody interested that the people of <lb/>
the Territories will not agree to give away <lb/>
an inch of territory. We want it all — to <lb/>
become the most powerful and most pros<lb break="no"/>perous province of the Dominion. It was <lb/>
not necessary then to go into a question <lb/>
of provincial establishment, That point, <lb/>
as the premier had stated, depended upon <lb/>
whather the Federal authorities granted <lb/>
us enough money to carry on our business <lb/>
witnout becoming a province. We should <lb/>
not seek full provincial responsibilities <lb/>
until every means had been exhausted to <lb/>
get proper recognition without it. It may <lb/>
be that progress is not as rapid as we <lb/>
would like, yet our affairs are being man <lb/>
aged economically and in the best inter<lb break="no"/>ests of the people, and it was well to get <lb/>
safe and sure foundations laid before <lb/>
commencing the superstructure. He did <lb/>
not expect a long debate but would like <lb/>
to hear the Members express themselves <lb/>
on this subject. <lb/></p> 

<p>In reply to a question by Mr. Maloney, <lb/>
the Attorney-General stated that by the <lb/>
definition of the North-West Act, the <lb/>
North-West Territories embrace the coun<lb break="no"/>try right to the North Pole, including <lb/>
the Yukon. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PATR1">Dr. PATRICK</persName> said that some years ago <lb/>
he was an elector in Ontario, when an at<lb break="no"/>tempt was made to interfere with the wes<lb break="no"/>tern boundary of that province. The up<lb break="no"/>shot was that the rights of the electors of <lb/>
Ontario were respected, and the position <lb/>
sustained that their boundaries should not <lb/>
be changed against their wish. Later he <lb/>
removed to the Territories with the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of making a home here, and he was <lb/>
under the impression that by removal, he <lb/>
had forfeited no right as an elector, that <lb/>
he had possessed when in Ontario. The <lb/>
people here possessed the same right to <lb/>
have their wishes respected, and if any <lb/>
change is to be made, our consent must <lb/>
be gained. He well understood that cer<lb break="no"/>tain rights of the Territories were held in <lb/>
abeyance by the Federal authorities — but <lb/>
no right was forieited. The Dominion <lb/>
had the legal power in the matter of our <lb/>
boundaries, just as the Imperial authori<lb break="no"/>ties have the legal right to deprive the Do<lb break="no"/>minion of Canada of any right held by <lb/>
virtue of Imperial Statute. But it was <lb/>
not a question of legality; it was a ques<lb break="no"/>tion cf policy, — a question of expediency <lb/>
and of moral right. He asserted the right <lb/>
of the people of the Territories to have <lb/>
the boundaries of the country remain in<lb break="no"/>tact until they consented to alteration. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:EAKI1">Mr. EAKIN</persName> said the question was <lb/>
a live one in his district within the past <lb/>
year, and after Mr. Greenway's speech at <lb/>
Brandon the people were much excited <lb/>
and alarmed. Those residing nearest to <lb/>
the Manitoba boundary were the most <lb/>
strenuously opposed to the proposal of <lb/>
annexation, because they knew best the <lb/>
burdens of the people of Manitoba. The <lb/>
fact ist Manitoba was repeatedly asking <lb/>
for larger subsidy showed that the pro<lb break="no"/>vince was not in satisfactory condition.  <lb/>

<cb/>

The boundary had once been extended <lb/>
into the Territories, at a time when the <lb/>
people were sparse, and there was no <lb/>
doubt that Manitoba would like to secure <lb/>
another extension to procure another sec<lb break="no"/>tion of the very best agricultural land in <lb/>
Canada. He (Mr. Eakin) hai written to <lb/>
Mr. Douglas, M.P., on the subject, who <lb/>
returned reply that the Minister of Inter<lb break="no"/>ior (Mr. Sifton) stated that no such change <lb/>
would be contemplated unless a majority <lb/>
of the people wished it. He could say <lb/>
that he had never met a single ratepayer <lb/>
who favored joining Manitoba. <lb/> </p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. HAULTAIN</persName> said that after the dis<lb break="no"/>cussion which had taken place, both then <lb/>
and on a previous day, it was not neces<lb break="no"/>sary for him to say more that simply that <lb/>
the resolution had his hearty support. It <lb/>
expressed precisely what he had said on <lb/>
Monday, and he hoped it would have <lb/>
weight as being the opinion of the House, <lb/>
even if the question was not a live one at <lb/>
present. He hoped it would not become a <lb/>
live question. <lb/></p>
 
 <p>
<persName ref="pers:BRET1">Dr. BRETT</persName> questioned the advisability <lb/>
  of committing the House to the impor<lb break="no"/>tant principle of one province. That was <lb/>
not a question which had come promi<lb break="no"/>nently before the people, and had not been <lb/>
discussed by the people. He would regret <lb/>
to see any portion of the Territories taken <lb/>
away, but pointed out that to take in the <lb/>
whole north country would Inake an ex<lb break="no"/>ceedingly large province. He noticed a re<lb break="no"/>ference in the resolution to "administrative <lb/>
purposes," and said he would like to know <lb/>
just to what extent we were exercising jur<lb break="no"/>lediction in the unorganized district. He <lb/>
moved, seconded by Mr. Bannerman, to <lb/>
insert the words "or provinces" in the <lb/>
resolution, which, he said, would not im<lb break="no"/>pair its force. <lb/></p>
 
 <p>
<persName ref="pers:BANN2">Mr. BANNERMAN</persName> said there was <lb/>
quite as strong feeling in Alberta, at least <lb/>
in Calgary, against being tacked on to <lb/>
East Assiniboia, as there was in East As<lb break="no"/>siniboia against being tacked on to Mani<lb break="no"/>toba. He did not like motions to be sprung <lb/>
on the House in the way that this one <lb/>
was. The question should be discussed <lb/>
in a general election campaign to ascer<lb break="no"/>tain the feeling of the people. <lb/></p>
 
 <p>
  <persName ref="pers:AGNE1">Mr. AGNEW</persName> thought with Mr. Banner<lb break="no"/>man that the feeling of the people was not <lb/>
well enough known to enable the House <lb/>
to express an opinion on the question of <lb/>
provinces — whether there should be one <lb/>
or more. The people in Saskatchewan <lb/>
were not at one on the subject. Person<lb break="no"/>ally he was against Manitoba taking any <lb/>
of our territory. He suggessed to strike <lb/>
out the words "as a province" in the <lb/>
resolution. <lb/></p>
 
 <p>
<persName ref="pers:ROSS11">Mr. ROSS</persName> said the hon. Member for <lb/>
Whitewood he thought might well be <lb/>
congratulated upon his resolution. There <lb/>
was no doubt that in the eastern part of <lb/>
the Territories there was very strong <lb/>
feeling in opposition to the suggestion <lb/>
made some time ago by the Premier of <lb/>
Manitoba. That the people of Manitoba <lb/>
should wish to take a portion of this <lb/>
country was very natural. Manitoba was <lb/>
a small province, and unfortunately had <lb/>
made a very bad bargain in what was <lb/>
known as the Better Terms agreement. <lb/>
The people conducting the affairs of that <lb/>
province, he believed, were not so desirous <lb/>
of getting more territory, as they were to <lb/>
get opportunity to make a new deal with <lb/>
the Dominion. To make new terms, they <lb/>
would have to show new conditions. If <lb/>
they got an extension of territory, they <lb/>
would probably be enabled to make a new <lb/>
deal. We could sympathise with Manito<lb break="no"/>ba, but not to the extent of giving that <lb/>
province our territory. Manitoba no doubt <lb/>
desired the change, but he (Mr. Ross) did <lb/>
not think the change would ever be made. <lb/>
In fact it would not be to the political <lb/>
irterest of the men in power in Manitoba <lb/>
to take in a portion of East Assinibona <lb/>
against the wish of the people. In place <lb/>
of the weak O; position they have now, <lb/>
they would find that the representatives <lb/>
sent by the annexed portion would oppose <lb/>
the Government to a man. No man <lb/>
could be elected in the annexed territory <lb/>
to support any men instrumental in hav<lb break="no"/>ing their territory withdrawn and given <lb/>
to Manitoba. The Federal authorities <lb/>
too would think well before taking such <lb/>
step. They, too, at times had to reckon <lb/>
with and appeal to the people, and they <lb/>
were not likely to appeal with success if <lb/>
they so acted against the with of a large <lb/>
number of people. No matter what was <lb/>
the political complexion of the people, <lb/>
the people of the North-West Territories <lb/>
would disapprove by votes of any such ac<lb break="no"/>tion as involved in the Manitoba Premier's <lb/>
suggestion. Another point which would <lb/>
tend to do away with any Federal desire <lb/>
in this direction, was the fact that Mani<lb break="no"/>toba of late had not been a very happy <lb/>
family; certain people there believed <lb/>
they had not been fairly treated, and <lb/>
there would be objection on the part of <lb/>
people not residents of the Territories, <lb/>
to the extension scheme. The hon Mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Banff was fearful that the House <lb/>
would give any expression in favor of one <lb/>
province. He had two provinces on the <lb/>
brain, and whenever he got a chance he <lb/>
never failed to ring in an amendment. <lb/>
They need not discuss that question at <lb/>
this time. The question was as to wheth<lb break="no"/>er Manitoba should get a portion of our <lb/>
territory. The other question could be <lb/>
discussed by the people when it be<lb break="no"/>comes a live issue. That time may very <lb/>
speedily arrive if the Territories do not <lb/>
succeed otherwise in obtaining the neces<lb break="no"/>aary money to properly carry on the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. When the time comes they <lb/>
could and would discuss the question of <lb/>
one province or two provinces. Person<lb break="no"/>ally he always favored the idea of one <lb/>
province and had yet heard no argument <lb/>
to alter his conviction. It was an erron<lb break="no"/>eous idea that a large province could not <lb/>

 <cb/>

be well conducted. With the telegraph <lb/>
lines and railways, he believed the whole <lb/>
country from Lake Superior to the Rocky <lb/>
Mountains might very well be conducted <lb/>
by one administration. When they looked <lb/>
at Ontario's diversity of interests and re<lb break="no"/>sources — timber, minerals, fisheries and <lb/>
agriculture — they surely would see the <lb/>
absurdity of using the argument of diver<lb break="no"/>sity of interests against the idea of form <lb/>
ing the Territories into one province, and <lb/>
he hoped he would never hear that argu<lb break="no"/>ment advanced again. Respecting the <lb/>
statement of the Member for East Calgary <lb/>
that the people there objected to be <lb/>
"tacked on" to Assinibola, he (Mr. Ross) <lb/>
thought he must be speaking for himself, <lb/>
or for a very limited number of people in <lb/>
Calgary; because he had visited that <lb/>
locality, and talked with people up there, <lb/>
and never found indication of such feel<lb break="no"/>ing He did not believe that Alberta as a <lb/>
whole had any such feeling. There had <lb/>
at one time been a little grumbling at <lb/>
Calgary, and a certain number of men <lb/>
with very large ideas had wanted to have <lb/>
a province formed at once. Their chief <lb/>
idea, judging by their expressions, was <lb/>
that they should gain power to borrow <lb/>
money. In my opinion, said Mr. Ross, <lb/>
these men were not such as it would be <lb/>
desirable to vest with any large borrowing <lb/>
power in behalf of a province. He con<lb break="no"/>tended that until such time as the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories had gained from the Dominion all <lb/>
that we are entitled to, and all that can <lb/>
be expected, they had no right to consider <lb/>
the question of gaining borrowing power. <lb/>
After they had got their rights from Otta<lb break="no"/>wa, and found that they had need to bor<lb break="no"/>row, then and not until then, would they <lb/>
have right to borrow. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SIMP1">Mr. SIMPSON</persName> agreed entirely with <lb/>
the resolution, but his own opinion was <lb/>
that, when the time came for provincial <lb/>
erection, the eastern portion would be <lb/>
given to Manitoba. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MEYE1">Mr. MEYERS</persName> supported the resolution <lb/>
and said the people of his district were <lb/>
strongly opposed to the Manitoba sugges<lb break="no"/>tion. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:CLIN1">Mr. CLINKSKILL</persName> was sorry that for <lb/>
once he was compelled to disagree with <lb/>
Dr. Brett. He said the desirability for <lb/>
one strong province was so great, that the <lb/>
resolution should clearly contemplate one <lb/>
province, and he would oppose the <lb/>
amendment as indicating that any idea of <lb/>
other possibility was entertained. The <lb/>
diversity of resources was the best argu<lb break="no"/>ment for a large province. It was the <lb/>
familiar case of the bundle of sticks <lb/>
Separated they were weak. Joined they <lb/>
were strong. The resolution might leave <lb/>
a doubt as to their wish to have full juris<lb break="no"/>diction in the northern portion. They <lb/>
wanted it all — in all the country — Yukon <lb/>
and right up to the pole. <lb/></p> 

<p>On division only <persName ref="pers:BRET1">Dr. Brett</persName> and <persName ref="pers:BANN2">Mr. <lb/>
Bannerman</persName> voted for the amendment. <lb/>
The resolution was thereupon carried. <lb/></p> 

 <!-- IC, 2018-11-20, Commented out below as it is not relevant the debate day-->

<!--<p>MORNING SESSIONS. <lb/>
Mr. Haultain put through a resolution <lb/>
for morning sessions during the balance of <lb/>
the session. <lb/></p> 

<p>MUNICIPAL LAW, <lb/>
Mr. Buiyea moved second reading of a <lb/>
Municipal Bill. He exid the provisions <lb/>
in the old Ordinance for machinery for <lb/>
the organization of new municipalities <lb/>
were struck out of the Bll. <lb/>
With their Statute Labor Lºw, <lb/>
organization of municipalities would <lb/>
not be frequent. When any district <lb/>
wanted to be formed, special legislation <lb/>
couli he passed, and to disetºrumher hº <lb/>
Ordinance, thºse provisions had been left <lb/>
out. There had been a general rear <lb/>
rangement of the clauses of the Ordinance <lb/>
to secure consecutiveness. A year ago <lb/>
two Municipalities had been disorganized, <lb/>
and the reason was that they found the <lb/>
system too expensive;—the unremunerº­ <lb/>
ative expenditure had been too great as <lb/>
compared with the productive. It had <lb/>
cost too much to spend the revenues. <lb/>
The chief object of the present, Bill was <lb/>
to reduce the expense. There had been <lb/>
a collector, compelled to call upon every <lb/>
ratepayer, which added greatly to the ex; <lb/>
pense, especially in rural districts. It had <lb/>
been found that the greater portion of <lb/>
the taxes were paid at central points on <lb/>
days appointed by the collector. The <lb/>
office of collector was abolished, as well <lb/>
as the offices of clerk and treasurer. These <lb/>
three offices were replaced by one-styled <lb/></p> <lb/>-->
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>