<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgASLA_1900-05-02" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>,
<date when="1900-05-02">2 May 1900</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA"> <editor>Walter Scott</editor>.
<title>The Leader</title>.
<date when="1900-05-10"/>,
<date when="1900-05-17"/>.
<pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="6"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="10" to="10"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="4"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1900-05-10_Page_001.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1900-05-10_Page_006.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1900-05-10_Page_010.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1900-05-17_Page_001.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1900-05-17_Page_004.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-26">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="lyallg" when="2018-06-26">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
 <surface xml:id="The_Leader_1900-05-10_Page_001"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1900-05-10_Page_001.jpg"/> </surface>
 <surface xml:id="The_Leader_1900-05-10_Page_006"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1900-05-10_Page_006.jpg"/> </surface>
 <surface xml:id="The_Leader_1900-05-10_Page_010"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1900-05-10_Page_010.jpg"/> </surface>
 <surface xml:id="The_Leader_1900-05-17_Page_001"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1900-05-17_Page_001.jpg"/> </surface>
 <surface xml:id="The_Leader_1900-05-17_Page_004"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1900-05-17_Page_004.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

 <pb n="001" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1900-05-10_Page_001.jpg"/> <lb/>
 
 <fw type="num">1</fw> 
 <fw type="running">THE LEADER</fw>
 <fw type="dateline">REGINA, N.W.T. THURSDAY MORNING, MAY 10 1900.</fw>

<head rendition="simple:centre">FUTURE OF <lb/>
THE TERRITORIES <lb/></head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">Continuation of Mr. Haultian's <lb/>
Speech on the Territorial <lb/>
Position. <lb/></head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">THE HOUSE PROROGUED. <lb/></head> 

<p>partial amelioration of otherwise im<lb break="no"/>possible financial conditions and will <lb/>
ask you to take action leading to the <lb/>
earliest practicable solution of Territor<lb break="no"/>ial and administrative problems. In <lb/>
accordance with the promise practical<lb break="no"/>ly made to the House by the govern<lb break="no"/>ment in that portion of the speech the <lb/>
resolution which he moved, seconded <lb/>
by his colleague, Mr. Ross, had been <lb/>
placed on the order paper. He would <lb/>
not attempt to occupy much time in. <lb/></p>
 
<p rendition="simple:centre">PRELIMINARY REMARKS.</p> 
 
 <p>
  though in a matter dealing with so <lb/>
  many different points, involving so <lb/>
  many and such varied topics — each <lb/>
  one worthy of a speech in itself — any <lb/>
  remarks he must make would be long <lb/>
  and he asked the indulgence of that <lb/>
  House in that respect. The remarks in <lb/>
  themselves would not be particularly <lb/>
  original in themselves: but he was go<lb break="no"/>ing to introduce the most important <lb/>
  subject the House had ever had before <lb/>
  it, and he was doing this in order to <lb/>
  elicit discussion, not only in the House <lb/>
  but in the country: and he hoped the <lb/>
  references he should give, the citations <lb/>
  he should make, and the sources of in<lb break="no"/>formation he should indicate would <lb/>
  help in the future discussion of the <lb/>
  question, as well as point out where <lb/>
  any one would be able to get informa<lb break="no"/>tion on this very important subject. <lb/>
  The resolutions themselves were large<lb break="no"/>ly historical. They were taken almost <lb/>
  exclusively in their very words from <lb/>
  the public documents. They dealt <lb/>
  with the
 </p>
 
 <p rendition="simple:centre">HISTORY OF THE TERRITORIES</p>
 
<p>
 in a very concise way and gave in a <lb/>
 few pages the history of the Territories <lb/>
 since their acquisition by Canada. They <lb/>
 dealt also to some extent with the his<lb break="no"/>tory of the Dominion, and so dar as his <lb/>
 argument went, with the colonial poli<lb break="no"/>cy followed out by the Imperial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, especially in regard to their <lb/>
 lands. The object of the resolution <lb/>
 was to introduce the subject within the <lb/>
 realm of discussion. It was not a sub<lb break="no"/>ject that could be settled in a day: not <lb/>
 one that the House could settle at all, <lb/>
 perhaps unfortunately: or one that <lb/>
 could be settled in the immediate fu<lb break="no"/>ture: but in any event before it was <lb/>
 settled it required the fullest discus<lb break="no"/>sion. He would not make any further <lb/>
 remark as to whether the time was op<lb break="no"/>potune for the introduction of a re<lb break="no"/>solution of this sort. He would try to <lb/>
 <choice><sic>develope</sic><corr>develop</corr></choice> that in the course of his <lb/>
 speech. So he would simply begin at <lb/>
 the beginning and take up the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion clause by clause. The resolution <lb/>
 in the "be it resolved" parts dealt with <lb/>
 two phases of the buisness. First it <lb/>
 asked for the fullest enquiry into the <lb/>
 position of the territories, financial <lb/>
 and otherwise, and to cause action to <lb/>
 be taken for the present and immediate <lb/>
 welfare and the good government of the <lb/>
 Territories. The Assembly was a prac<lb break="no"/>tical House. It had to deal with the <lb/>
 practical buisness of this country sa <lb/>
 they found it today, doing buisness <lb/>
 as it came up. They had the duty im<lb break="no"/>posed on them, not of theorising as re<lb break="no"/>garded the future, but to deal with the <lb/>
 present. While they talked about
</p>
 
 <p rendition="simple:centre">THE FUTURE</p>
 
 <p>made propositions as to what <lb/>
  they would have at a future date, they <lb/>
  must remember that their buisness was <lb/>
  to deal with affairs as they come up <lb/>
  from day to day. Therefore the nec<lb break="no"/>essity for some resolution and some <lb/>
  comments by this House on the pre<lb break="no"/>sent and immediate future was just as <lb/>
  important as any buisness the House <lb/>
  had to do, and for which it was elected. <lb/>
  The first recitals in the resolution were <lb/>
  historical. Seven or eight of them <lb/>
  were plain statements of actual facts <lb/>
  taken from public documents. The <lb/>
  first recital pointed out that by the <lb/>
  British North America Act of 1867 <lb/>
  power was given on request by ad<lb break="no"/>dress to admit Rupert's land and the <lb/>
  North-West Territory into the Union. The <lb/>
  House would notice that running <lb/>
  through all these recitals there was <lb/>
  a certain consistent idea. He wanted <lb/>
  to impress upon the House the continu<lb break="no"/>ous chain of reference to the British <lb/>
  North America Act, the analogy that <lb/>
  existed between the Territories and the provinces: which made up the chain of <lb/>
  argument that pointed most clearly to <lb/>
  the duty of the Dominion Government <lb/>
  and Parliament in regard to this coun<lb break="no"/>try. With regard to this first recital, it <lb/>
  was founded on the resolutions of
 </p>
 
 <p rendition="simple:centre">THE QUEBEC CONFERENCE.</p>
 
 <p>
  It was the resolution of the Fathers <lb/>
  of Confederation and upon which was <lb/>
  founded the Confederation Act. He <lb/>
  would call attention to the Quebec re<lb break="no"/>solutions, an important document, that <lb/>
  it would be well for every hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man to look into when considering this <lb/>
  subject. The resolutions passed at the <lb/>
  Quebec conference showed that it was <lb/>
  not for the benefit of the people of this <lb/>
  country that confederation was estab<lb break="no"/>lished, it was for the development of <lb/>
  the trade of the great west on the sea<lb break="no"/>board and it was regarded as a subject <lb/>
  of the greatest importance, not to the <lb/>
  Territories but to the confederated <lb/>
  provinces, that the great west should <lb/>
  be opened up, and communication es<lb break="no"/>tablished between Eastern Canada and <lb/>
  British Columbia and Vancouver. He <lb/>
  would leave the first recital at that <lb/>
  point for the present. It simply point<lb break="no"/>ed out the reason it was desirable <lb/>
  the Northwest should be acquired by <lb/>
  Canada, and communication opened <lb/>
  up with it: viz, not for the benefit of <lb/>
  the Territories but for the development <lb/>
  of the trade of the provinces. The sec<lb break="no"/>ond recital showed that the necessary <lb/>
  addresses had been presented from the <lb/>
  Parliament of Canada asking for Ru<lb break="no"/>pert's Land and the Noth-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories to be united in Canada. These <lb/>
  addresses of the Parliament of Canada <lb/>
  were important the date of them is <lb/>
  December 1867 because they were <lb/>
  from the first parliament after confed<lb break="no"/>eration was completed and showed the <lb/>
  reason why Rupert's Land and the <lb/>
  North-West Territory should be taken <lb/>
  into the union. The Union, so said <lb/>
  the addresses, would promote the pros<lb break="no"/>perity of the Canadian people and con<lb break="no"/>duce to the advantages of the whole <lb/>
  Empire, by extending westward to the <lb/>
  Pacific Ocean. The addresses spoke of <lb/>
  the development of the minerla wealth, <lb/>
  the extension of means of intercourse

 
 <cb/>

as being dependent upon a stable gov<lb break="no"/>ernment in the maintenance of law and <lb/>
order in the Territories. A large popu<lb break="no"/>lation of British subjects were inhabit<lb break="no"/>ing these Territories, and it was con<lb break="no"/>sidered that the welfare of this popula<lb break="no"/>tion of political institutions bearing <lb/>
analogy to those that existed in the <lb/>
several provinces of the Union. These <lb/>
were the three reasons given by the <lb/>
joint addresses of the Parliament of <lb/>
Canada. Again, he would repeat that <lb/>
the reasons were, not for the benefit of <lb/>
this country, but for the prosperity of <lb/>
the Canadian people and incidentally <lb/>
only in a sense were the people of this <lb/>
country mentioned. He now came to <lb/>
the third recital. For the purpose of <lb/>
carrying out the arrangement it was <lb/>
necessary to have possession of the <lb/>
lands of</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE HUDSON'S BAY COMPANY.</p> 

<p>The Hudson's Bay Company's title <lb/>
had always been a matter of discuss<lb break="no"/>ion. It had always been an open <lb/>
question whether they possessed Terri<lb break="no"/>torial rights over all they claimed. He <lb/>
would not go into this subject as it was  <lb/>
one that would involve a very long ar<lb break="no"/>gument, and if any member of the <lb/>
House wished to look into the subject <lb/>
a little more fully he should read the <lb/>
report of Sir. Jacques Cartier and the <lb/>
Hon. Mr. McDougall, who were the <lb/>
delegates from Canada to England <lb/>
when the negotiations were going on, <lb/>
when incidentally the Hudson Bay <lb/>
Company's title was very fully discuss<lb break="no"/>ed, in the litigation in the celebrated <lb/>
Ontario boundaries case. Well, it was <lb/>
on the action taken under the Rupert's <lb/>
Land Act 1868, that a surrender of the <lb/>
Hudson's Bay Company of its rights to <lb/>
the Dominion of Canada took place, <lb/>
and the Dominion claimed the absolute <lb/>
title to the Lands of this North-West <lb/>
country in consequence of this. It had <lb/>
been said over and over again when <lb/>
the Territories made any claim, "Oh, <lb/>
we bought you." It might, however, <lb/>
be that the amount paid was not a <lb/>
purchase price, but was in settlement <lb/>
of claims that existed, however, it was <lb/>
said the North-West had nothing to do <lb/>
with these lands within their bounds, <lb/>
but if the lands of the Hudson's Bay <lb/>
Company had been bought and paid <lb/>
for, it must be remembered that all <lb/>
the Hudson's Bay Company's lands <lb/>
were so parted with. It was not only <lb/>
the provincial districts that now form<lb break="no"/>ed the Territories,but Athabasca, <lb/>
Mackenzie and the Islands, Keewatin, <lb/>
a portion of what was now Ontario, <lb/>
Ungava, and a large portion now in <lb/>
the province of Quebec. So when the <lb/>
question came up as a practical ques<lb break="no"/>tion, as to what rights were obtained <lb/>
by the payment of the $1,500,000 to the <lb/>
Hudson's Bay Company there would <lb/>
be the still larger question: against <lb/>
which portion of that very large area <lb/>
was it to be charged? He would not <lb/>
dwell upon that at present, except to <lb/>
point out that the way the Dominion <lb/>
Government was keeping its books at <lb/>
present, the whole of that amount was <lb/>
written up against the diminishing <lb/>
area of the North-West Territories. He <lb/>
came now to recital No. 4. He simply <lb/>
mentioned the recital just then for the <lb/>
purpose of trying always to keep in <lb/>
view that when the Parliament of <lb/>
Canada asked to have the Dominion <lb/>
extended westward, one of the grounds <lb/>
was that the welfare of the people <lb/>
of these Territories would be <lb/>
largely enhanced by the found<lb break="no"/>ation of political institutions, <lb/>
similar to those in the provinces; and <lb/>
he wished just now to lay stres upon <lb/>
this fact that throughout the whole <lb/>
history of the question, there is a con<lb break="no"/>sistent statement of intention and <lb/>
motive to deal with this country in a <lb/>
way analagous to the provinces. Re<lb break="no"/>cital 5 expressed the willingness of the <lb/>
Parliament of Canada to assume the <lb/>
duties and obligations of Government <lb/>
and legislation as regarded the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. Recital No 6 dealt with the <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">ADMISSION INTO CONFEDERATION</p> 

<p>of Rupert's Land and the North-West <lb/>
Territories. This was accomplished <lb/>
under an imperial order in council on <lb/>
June 23, 1870, and it came into effect <lb/>
July 13, 1870. Under that order in <lb/>
council the Territories and Rupert's <lb/>
Land were admitted into and became <lb/>
part of the Dominion of Canada, and <lb/>
had given to them power to legislate <lb/>
for the welfare and good Government <lb/>
of the country. Recital 7 went on to <lb/>
say that by the British North America <lb/>
Act of 1871, subsequently amended, <lb/>
the Parliament of Canada was given <lb/>
further power for time to time to make <lb/>
provision for the administration of <lb/>
peace, order and good Government of <lb/>
any Territory not included in a pro<lb break="no"/>vince. By reading the two authorities <lb/>
together it was found that only pow<lb break="no"/>er given to the Territories was to legis<lb break="no"/>late for their future welfare and good <lb/>
Government. He would again lay <lb/>
stress upon the particular words, for <lb/>
those words were really the only words <lb/>
upon which was based the right to <lb/>
deal with the question. Recital 8 was <lb/>
one which would not necessitate his <lb/>
making any argument upon. They <lb/>
were here going away from public <lb/>
documents and stating a fact, viz., <lb/>
that the Parliament of Canada had <lb/>
created political institutions in the <lb/>
Territories bearing a close analogy to <lb/>
those which existed in the several pro<lb break="no"/>vinces of the Dominion. He need <lb/>
hardly take up time in making any <lb/>
argument as to whether the Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment had or had not done so. Simply <lb/>
as a matter of reference he would refer <lb/>
the House to the North-West Amend<lb break="no"/>ment Act of 1891 and subsequent <lb/>
amendments to the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tories Act, in which would be found <lb/>
a full description of the powers given <lb/>
to the North-West Legislature. For a <lb/>
more ready means of reference the <lb/>
North-West Territories Act as amend<lb break="no"/>ed would be found at the beginning of <lb/>
the volume of the Consolidated Ordi<lb break="no"/>nance of the North-West Territories. <lb/>
He would now refer to Section 92 of <lb/>
the British North America Act. To <lb/>
put it shortly in order to show what a <lb/>
very slight difference there was be<lb break="no"/>tween the powers enjoyed by the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories to-day and those that were <lb/>
enjoyed by the Provinces. He would <lb/>
give in a very few words the exact <lb/>
difference that existed. The Terri<lb break="no"/>tories enjoyed nearly all the powers. <lb/>
They had not the power to amend the <lb/>
constitution, outside certain phases of <lb/>
their election law. They could not <lb/>
borrow money; they had no public <lb/>
domains; they could not establish cer<lb break="no"/>tain public institutions, such as hospit<lb break="no"/>als, asylums and either eleemosynary <lb/>
institutions; and they could not ad<lb break="no"/>minister the criminal law. That <lb/>
he thought would suffice on that head. <lb/>
In regard to recital 9 he might say at <lb/>
the very beginning that the bases upon <lb/>
which financial assistance was given to <lb/>
the provinces were well defined in one <lb/>
sense, but they were not exactly rigid. <lb/>
There had been many departures in <lb/>
some of the provinces. Under the <lb/>
British North America Act the follow<lb break="no"/>ing provisions were made as provincial <lb/>
revenues. A yearly grant from Domi<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

nion funds for the support of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, varying from $80,000 in Ontario <lb/>
to $35,000 in British Columbia; a per <lb/>
capita grant for local purposes of 80 <lb/>
cents, as was set forth in the Quebec <lb/>
resolutions. The assumption by the <lb/>
Dominion of the indebtedness, and the <lb/>
retention of all the provincial revenue <lb/>
producing sources such as customs, <lb/>
etc., were also part of the compact. <lb/>
These were extended to British Colum<lb break="no"/>bia and Prince Edward Island when <lb/>
they entered confederation, but were <lb/>
varied when Manitoba entered as <lb/>
would be shown later on. Such were <lb/>
the provisions that were made at the <lb/>
time of confederation for the revenue <lb/>
of the provinces. He now came to <lb/>
recital 10. They were departing a <lb/>
little from pure history and getting <lb/>
into controversial matter. The recital <lb/>
said that the Territories were <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">ENTITLED TO FEDERAL ASSISTANCE.</p> 

<p>to such federal assistance as would <lb/>
bear due proportion and analogy to <lb/>
that given to the provinces. Now the <lb/>
expression in the recital, "in integral <lb/>
part of the Dominion," had been used <lb/>
simply for this purpose; the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories had been created a political <lb/>
entity; they had political powers as <lb/>
separate as any province; they had a <lb/>
legislature; and with the exceptions <lb/>
he had already named, they stand <lb/>
very much the same as a province, <lb/>
and might fairly be called an integral <lb/>
part of the Dominion. There was no <lb/>
doubt of their having imposed upon <lb/>
them the duties and obligations in<lb break="no"/>cidental to the political institutions <lb/>
that had been given them. Their <lb/>
legislature had been created with cer<lb break="no"/>tain powers, and had imposed upon it <lb/>
the duties and obligations arising <lb/>
therefrom. The Parliament of Canada <lb/>
assumed for themselves those duties <lb/>
and obligations and had imposed them <lb/>
upon the Territories. He did not <lb/>
use the word "imposed" in any <lb/>
complaining sense. The point he <lb/>
wished to make in the recital <lb/>
was that the Territories were <lb/>
entitled, not only to be dealt with <lb/>
analogously to the other provinces, <lb/>
side by side with the institutions; but <lb/>
that if they were to have the institu<lb break="no"/>tions, the duties and the obligations, <lb/>
they were also entitled to an analogous <lb/>
and proportionate amount of financial <lb/>
assistance for so doing. That seemed <lb/>
to him to be a perfectly fair deduction <lb/>
to be made from the position and would <lb/>
commend itself to the House. [Hear <lb/>
hear.] In the memorials from the <lb/>
Assembly in 1892 and 1896, and the <lb/>
memorials that had been sent up from <lb/>
time to time by the Executive Com<lb break="no"/>mittee the same arguments had been <lb/>
forcibly made, in regard to recitals 11 <lb/>
and 12, he did not think it would be <lb/>
necessary from him to give any evidence <lb/>
or to make any arguments that re<lb break="no"/>peated representations had been made <lb/>
for just and equitable financial assis<lb break="no"/>tance, or that they had been made in <lb/>
the right way. All the assistance ne<lb break="no"/>cessary had been called in, yearly <lb/>
representations had been made with a <lb/>
view of obtaining just and equitable <lb/>
financial assistance. That would be <lb/>
agreed to by every member of the <lb/>
House. [Hear, hear.] The results of <lb/>
those representations could be seen <lb/>
in the journals of their House and in <lb/>
the Appropriation Acts of the dom<lb break="no"/>inion Parliament. These would be <lb/>
standing evidence that the Territories <lb/>
never had received a sufficient amount <lb/>
of money. Recital 13 went on to say <lb/>
that it was desirable a basis should be <lb/>
established upon which the claims of <lb/>
the Territories might be settled and <lb/>
agreed upon. This, also, was a state<lb break="no"/>ment that needed no long argument of <lb/>
his to establish. A satisfactory basis <lb/>
of a permanent character, a basis for a <lb/>
certain number of years would be a <lb/>
good thing for carrying on their <lb/>
business. He would again refer to the <lb/>
journals of the legislature's proceed<lb break="no"/>ings and to the memorials from the <lb/>
House. It would be seen then that <lb/>
from time to time the fixing for a term <lb/>
of years had been one of the promin<lb break="no"/>ent features. In 1892 the time asked to <lb/>
be fixed was four years, and in 1896 <lb/>
there was a similar request. There <lb/>
had, however, been no such dealing <lb/>
with the question either by Fed<lb break="no"/>eral Government or the Federal <lb/>
Parliament. He need not tell the <lb/>
House, these were incontrovertable <lb/>
facts. He now came to the resolution <lb/>
itself <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">"THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED."</p> 

<p>This (No. 14) dealt with their present <lb/>
position and their immediate future. <lb/>
He would like the House to understand <lb/>
that there had never been at any <lb/>
time any tendency on the part of the <lb/>
Territories to stand still and theorise, <lb/>
or to balance on a tight rope. He <lb/>
thought the policy of the Government <lb/>
had been a careful and gradual de<lb break="no"/>velopment both of their institutions <lb/>
and financial requirements. They had <lb/>
from time to time obtained a little <lb/>
more money and a little more power. <lb/>
At no time, had they or could they, <lb/>
come to a sudden stop and mark time. <lb/>
The work of the North-West must be <lb/>
carried on, the intentions of the legis<lb break="no"/>lature should be carried on, and they <lb/>
should not modify their requests, but <lb/>
should use to the full extent all the power <lb/>
they already possessed, and the nearer <lb/>
they got to what the law could give <lb/>
them as to provincial rights, the more <lb/>
close the analogy already insisted upon, <lb/>
the less felt would be the wrench, the <lb/>
less dangerous would be the jump, <lb/>
when the point was reached. One <lb/>
thing that would result from a definite <lb/>
and permanent basis was that it would <lb/>
do away with the much spoken of <lb/>
annual <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">PILGRIMAGE TO OTTAWA.</p> 

<p>He had always thought it was an un<lb break="no"/>desirable thing, an undignified thing <lb/>
that the representatives of that House <lb/>
had to go to Ottawa asking for what <lb/>
they considered their right. But such <lb/>
excursions had to be made. The cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances required that the fullest in<lb break="no"/>formation should be placed before the <lb/>
Dominion government, when they did <lb/>
not know from year to year that they <lb/>
should obtain as much as in the <choice><sic>pre<lb break="no"/>ceeding</sic><corr>preceding</corr></choice> year, and that any increase <lb/>
must depend upon the amount of re<lb break="no"/>presentation made. So long as that <lb/>
state of affairs existed, just so long <lb/>
would some one have to go down to <lb/>
Ottawa and press the claims of the <lb/>
Territories upon the Federal Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. The next advantage of having <lb/>
their financial affairs settled for two <lb/>
ears or a number of years, would be <lb/>
that there would be no speculation <lb/>
from year to year as to the amount of <lb/>
money they would have to spend. An <lb/>
opinion had been expressed as to the <lb/>
time for the sitting of the House. It <lb/>
should meet early in the year, the <lb/>
earlier the better, and more conven<lb break="no"/>ient. In present circumstances, if the <lb/>
Dominion parliament had not begun <lb/>
to sit, there would be no indication of <lb/>
what the Territories would receive. In <lb/>
what position would they be in fram<lb break="no"/>ing their estimates? They would not <lb/>
know what they were going to get, and [...]<lb/></p> 

<!--<p>Continued from page 10 <lb/></p>-->

 <pb n="006" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1900-05-10_Page_006.jpg"/> <lb/>

<fw type="num">6</fw> <fw type="running">THE LEADER, THURSDAY MORNING, MAY 10, 1900.</fw> 



<p rendition="simple:centre">WEDNESDAY, May 2.</p> 


 <!-- IC, 2018-10-26, Commented out below as it is not relevent the debate day-->

<!--<p>[...] much easier to enforce the law where <lb/>
there were a few licensees doing a good <lb/>
business, then when there were many <lb/>
licensees, doing unprofitable trade. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Horace Greeley objected to giv<lb break="no"/>ing a monopoly to one hotel in a village <lb/>
of 300 inhabitants. <lb/></p> 

<p>Dr. De Veber said the only way to <lb/>
provide good liquor was to have com<lb break="no"/>petition. <lb/></p> 

<p>Ultimately the bill passed through <lb/>
committee without alterations. <lb/></p> 

<p>THE SCHOOL ORDINANCE. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Haultain moved second reading <lb/>
of a bill to amend the School Ordi<lb break="no"/>nance. He said that in a future more <lb/>
or less remote he hoped there would <lb/>
be a general auditor for the whole of <lb/>
the school accounts of the Territories. <lb/>
They were not, however, ready for <lb/>
that to-day; but the bill proposed to <lb/>
apply the principle to some groups of <lb/>
districts where the persons could not <lb/>
read or write in English. Another <lb/>
point the bill dealt with was the child<lb break="no"/>ren of non-resident ratepayers. Non<lb break="no"/>resident ratepayers had the right to <lb/>
send their children to schools; and a <lb/>
man might buy a small $5 lot, and so <lb/>
get the privilege of sending his child<lb break="no"/>ren in the town schools. The bill pro<lb break="no"/>vided that non-resident ratepayers <lb/>
should not have the privilege when <lb/>
their assessment was less than the <lb/>
average assessment of the ratepayers <lb/>
in the town. <lb/></p> 

<p>The bill was read a second time. <lb/></p> 

<p>TAX SALE. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Haultain moved second reading <lb/>
of a bill respecting confirmation of <lb/>
sales of land for taxes. He said the <lb/>
object of the bill was that the produc<lb break="no"/>tion by proper officers of evidence of <lb/>
sale would be taken by the judge as <lb/>
proper evidence of the validity of the <lb/>
tax. The bill covered both municipal <lb/>
and school taxes.—Carried. <lb/></p> 

<p>PATRIOTIC GRANTS. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Haultain moved second reading <lb/>
of a bill to legalise the payment of <lb/>
grants by municipalities for patriotic <lb/>
purposes. He said there were some <lb/>
doubts as to whether municipalities <lb/>
were strictly within their rights in the <lb/>
grants recently made for patriotic pur<lb break="no"/>poses, and he therefore proposed the <lb/>
passage of this enabling bill.—Carried. <lb/></p> 

<p>REGINA HOSPITAL. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. G. W. Brown proposed second <lb/>
reading of a bill to incorporate Regina <lb/>
Hospital. The bill would enable G. T. <lb/>
Marsh, A. McDonald, F. N. Darke, <lb/>
Jas. Balfour, D. J. Goggin, G. Michea-<lb break="maybe"/>lis, W. G. Pettingell, G. H. V. Bulyea, <lb/>
G. W. Brown and such other persons <lb/>
as from time to time might become <lb/>
members of the corporation, to be in<lb break="no"/>corporated a body politic under the <lb/>
name of the Regina Hospital. The <lb/>
corporation would be enabled to ac<lb break="no"/>quire real and personal estate, pro<lb break="no"/>vided the real estate did not exceed <lb/>
$40,000. The bill contained the usual <lb/>
provisions as to management. A <lb/>
donation of $50 entitles the doner to <lb/>
life membership, and the annual sub<lb break="no"/>scribers will have a right to take part <lb/>
in the annual meeting. Provision is  <lb/>
also made for the free vaccination of <lb/>
all poor persons, and of any others at a <lb/>
charge of not more than 75 cents. <lb/></p> 

<p>The bill was read a second time. The <lb/>
House then went into committee of <lb/>
the whole, when several bills were <lb/>
advanced a stage. In the dentistry <lb/>
bill the qualification for students in <lb/>
regard to the second class non-profes-<lb break="maybe"/>sional certificate was left as in the old <lb/>
bill. <lb/></p> 

<p>The House adjourned at half past <lb/>
noon. <lb/></p> -->
 
 
 <div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">THE FUTURE OF THE TERRI<lb break="no"/>TORIES.</head>

<head rendition="simple:centre">SPEECH BY MR. HAULTAIN.</head>

<p>The House re-assembled shortly be<lb break="no"/>fore three o'clock, and precisely at that <lb/>
hour, <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> rose and was received <lb/>
with cheers. He moved the following <lb/>
resolution: <lb/></p> 

<p>1. Whereas by the British North <lb/>
American Act 1866 it was, among other <lb/>
things, enacted that it should be law<lb break="no"/>ful for the Queen, by and with the <lb/>
advice of Her Majesty's Most Honour<lb break="no"/>able Privy Council, on Address from <lb/>
the Houses of the Parliament of Can<lb break="no"/>ada, to admit Rupert's Land and the <lb/>
North-Western Territory, or either of <lb/>
them into the Union on such terms <lb/>
and conditions in each case as should <lb/>
be in the Addresses expressed and as <lb/>
the Queen should think fit to approve <lb/>
subject to the provisions of the said <lb/>
Act; <lb/></p> 

<p>2. And whereas by an Address from <lb/>
the Houses of the Parliament of Canada <lb/>
Her Majesty was prayed to unite <lb/>
Rupert's Land and the North-Western <lb/>
Territory with the Dominion of Can<lb break="no"/>ada; <lb/></p> 

<p>3. And whereas, in order to further the <lb/>
petition of the Parliament of Canada, <lb/>
Her Majesty, under the authority of <lb/>
the Rupert's Land Act 1896, accepted a <lb/>
surrender from the Governor and <lb/>
Company of Adventurers of England <lb/>
trading into Hudson's Bay of all the <lb/>
lands, territories, privileges, liberties, <lb/>
franchises, powers and authorities <lb/>
whatsoever granted or purported to be <lb/>
granted by certain Letters Patent <lb/>
therein recited to the said Company in <lb/>
Rupert's Land; <lb/></p> 

<p>4. And whereas in the said address <lb/>
it was represented to Her Majesty, as <lb/>
a reason for the extension of the Dom<lb break="no"/>inion of Canada westward, that the <lb/>
welfare of the population of these <lb/>
Territories would be materially enhan<lb break="no"/>ced by the formation therein of political <lb/>
institutions bearing analogy, as far as <lb/>
circumstnces will admit, to those <lb/>
which existed in the several provinces <lb/>
then forming the Dominion; <lb/></p> 

<p>5. And whereas the Houses of the <lb/>
Parliament of Canada by their said <lb/>
Address expressed to Her Majesty <lb/>
their willingness to assume the duties <lb/>
and obligations of government and <lb/>
legislation as regards the Territories; <lb/></p> 

<p>6. And whereas in pursuance and exer<lb break="no"/>cise of the powers vested in the Queen <lb/>
by the aforesaid Acts, Her Majesty, by <lb/>
and with the advice of Her Most Hon<lb break="no"/>ourable Privy Council, ordered and <lb/>
declared that from and after the fif<lb break="no"/>teenth day of July, 1870, Rupert's Land <lb/>
and the North-Western Territory <lb/>
should be admitted into and become <lb/>
part of the Dominion of Canada, and <lb/>
granted power and authority to the <lb/>
Parliament of Canada to legislate for <lb/>
the future welfare and good govern<lb break="no"/>ment of these Territories; <lb/></p> 

<p>7. And whereas by the British North <lb/>
America Act 1871 the Parliament of <lb/>
Canada was further given power from <lb/>
time to time to make provision for <lb/>
the administration, peace, order and <lb/>
good government of any Territory not <lb/>
for the time being included in any <lb/>
Province; <lb/></p> 

<p>8. And whereas under the several <lb/>
authorities so given the Parliament <lb/>
of Canada has created political insti<lb break="no"/>tutions in these Territories bearing a <lb/>
close analogy to those which exist in <lb/>
the several Provinces of the Dominion; <lb/></p> 

<p>9. And whereas by the Confederation <lb/>
compact the Provinces which formed <lb/>
the Dominion on the fifteenth day of <lb/>
July 1870, were furnished with the <lb/>
means of carrying on local self govern<lb break="no"/>ment upon certain well defined bases; <lb/></p> 

<p>10. And whereas the Territories being <lb/>
an integral part of the Dominion, and <lb/>
having imposed upon them the duties <lb/>
and obligations incidental to the <lb/>
political institutions which have been <lb/>
given to them and which said duties <lb/>
and obligations the Parliament of <lb/>
Canada has declared its willingness to <lb/>
assume, are entitled to such Federal <lb/>
assistance for their maintenance as <lb/>
will bear due proportion and analogy <lb/>
to that given to other portions of the <lb/>
Dominion for similar purposes; <lb/></p> 

<p>11. And whereas repeated representa<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

tions have been made in various ways <lb/>
to the Government of Canada with a <lb/>
view to obtaining just and equitable <lb/>
financial assistance towards providing <lb/>
for the proper and effective administra<lb break="no"/>tion of local affairs in the Territories <lb/>
and for the public necessities of their <lb/>
rapidly increasing population: <lb/></p> 

<p>12. And whereas such representations <lb/>
have been met by intermittent and in<lb break="no"/>sufficient additions to the annual grant <lb/>
the provision so made by the Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada never bearing any <lb/>
adequate proportion to the financial <lb/>
obligations imposed by the enlarge<lb break="no"/>ment and development of the political <lb/>
institutions created by itself; <lb/></p> 

<p>13. And whereas it is desirable that a <lb/>
basis should be established upon which <lb/>
the claims of the Territories to suitable <lb/>
financial recognition may be settled <lb/>
and agreed upon; <lb/></p> 

<p>14. Therefore be it resolved that an <lb/>
humble address to His Excellency the <lb/>
Governor General be adopted by this <lb/>
House praying him that he will be <lb/>
pleased to cause the fullest enquiry to <lb/>
be made into the position of the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, financial and otherwise, and to <lb/>
cause such action to be taken as will <lb/>
provide for their present and immedi<lb break="no"/>ate welfare and good government, as <lb/>
well as the due fulfillment of the duties <lb/>
and obligations of government and <lb/>
legislation assumed, with respect of <lb/>
these Territories, by the Parliament of <lb/>
Canada; <lb/></p> 

<p>15. And be it further resolved that, <lb/>
whereas by the British North America <lb/>
Act 1871 it was (amongst other things) <lb/>
enacted that the Parliament of Canada <lb/>
may from time to time establish new <lb/>
Provinces in any Territories forming <lb/>
for the time being part of the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion of Canada but not included in any <lb/>
Province thereof, and may, at the time <lb/>
of such establishment, make provision <lb/>
for the constitution and administration <lb/>
of such Province, His Excellency be <lb/>
also prayed to order enquiries to be <lb/>
made and accounts taken with a view <lb/>
to the settlement of the terms and con<lb break="no"/>ditions upon which the Territories, or <lb/>
any part thereof shall be established as <lb/>
a Province, and that before any such <lb/>
Province is established opportunity <lb/>
should be given to the people of the <lb/>
Territories through their accredited <lb/>
representatives of considering, and dis<lb break="no"/>cussing such terms and conditions. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> said that in the speech <lb/>
from the Throne with which the pre<lb break="no"/>sent session was opened there occurred <lb/>
the following sentence: "It is gratify<lb break="no"/>ing for me to be able to inform you <lb/>
that the Federal Government has pro<lb break="no"/>posed to Parliament now in session a <lb/>
moderate increase to your annual <lb/>
grant, and a large special vote for the <lb/>
purpose of restoring public works de<lb break="no"/>stroyed by the floods. In spite of this <lb/>
very substantial increase to the rev<lb break="no"/>enue, my government can only look <lb/>
upon it as affording a temporary and <lb/></p> 

<!--<p>Continued on Page 1. <lb/></p>-->



 <pb n="010" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1900-05-10_Page_010.jpg"/> <lb/>

<fw type="num">10</fw>
  <fw type="running">THE LEADER, THURSDAY MORNING, MAY 10, 1900.<lb/></fw> 

  <!-- IC, 2018-10-26, Commented out below as it is not relevent the debate day-->

<!--<p>|TOWN AND COUNTRY <lb/></p> 

<p>—Jas. Bonneau of Willow Bunch has <lb/>
been offering horses for sale in Regina. <lb/></p> 

<p>–Many new blocks and residences <lb/>
are promised for this year in Winni<lb break="no"/>peg. <lb/></p> 

<p>—A letter from the Yorkton Board <lb/>
of Trade arrived too late for insertion <lb/>
this week. <lb/></p> 

<p>—Tenders are called for the new <lb/>
steam ferry for service on the Saskat<lb break="no"/>chewan river at Battleford. <lb/></p> 

<p>—The Ottawa-Hull fire relief fund is <lb/>
assuming large proportions. Nearly a <lb/>
half million is now collected. <lb/></p> 

<p>—American and British flags grace<lb break="no"/>fully entwined, decorated the chamber <lb/>
of commerce in New York at its annual <lb/>
meeting. <lb/></p> 

<p>—Admiral Dewey has consented, if <lb/>
nothing prevents, to be the guest of <lb/>
the citizens of Canada during the early <lb/>
weeks of July. <lb/></p> 

<p>—The Regina high school yard has <lb/>
been enclosed by a neat new fence and <lb/>
contains 300 trees, planted by the <lb/>
students on Thursday last. <lb/></p> 

<p>-Miss Christiana Grant. of Lums<lb break="no"/>den, who has heen under treatment in <lb/>
the hospital for about two months, <lb/>
was able to return home on Monday. <lb/></p> 

<p>—A car load of 210 hogs, brought in <lb/>
free of charge by the C. P. R. and dis<lb break="no"/>tributed by the North-West Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, arrived at Calgary on Tuesday <lb/>
of last week. <lb/></p> 

<p>—On Monday night last a very en<lb break="no"/>joyable time was spent at Knox church <lb/>
Christian Endeavor, where a reception <lb/>
was given to a number of new recruits <lb/>
of the N.W.M.P. <lb/></p> 

<p>–Eighty teams are at work on the <lb/>
irrigation ditch near Lethbridge, under <lb/>
the superintendence of W. D. Ham<lb break="no"/>mond, who had charge of the contract <lb/>
at Pilot Hole, near Magrath. <lb/></p> 

<p>-There will be a celebration at Cal<lb break="no"/>gary on the 24th. Special rates will be <lb/>
given on the C.P.R. but they cannot be <lb/>
announced yet. Good prizes art offer<lb break="no"/>ed and a large gathering is anticipated. <lb/></p> 

<p>-Rev. Mr. Lee has resigned his <lb/>
pastorate at Prince Albert. He, occu<lb break="no"/>pied the pulpit in Knox Church, Regina <lb/>
on Sunday last and left for the east on <lb/>
Monday night. <lb/></p> 

<p>-Rat Portage had a big fire on <lb/>
Thursday last. Jas. Duncan, of the <lb/>
firm of Duncan &amp; Co., one of Regina's <lb/>
old timers, lost his flour and feed <lb/>
store. The stock was valued at $2,000 <lb/>
with $1,000 insurance. <lb/></p> 

<p>-Nurse Dahms, of the Regina hospi<lb break="no"/>tal, and Mrs. McIntosh, of Regina <lb/>
have gone for a holiday trip to Monc<lb break="no"/>ton, New Brunswick.. Miss Turnbull <lb/>
will be in charge of the hospital dur<lb break="no"/>ing Miss Dahms' absence. <lb/></p> 

<p>-The Indians of Muscowpetung <lb/>
are said to be 538 in number. They <lb/>
have cattle, horses and implements and <lb/>
Jast year raised 9,000 bushels of grain <lb/>
and 3,000 bushels of roots. Proposals <lb/>
are being made to get a steam thresh­ <lb/>
er. <lb/></p> 

<p>-Moose Jaw Liberals held a meeting <lb/>
in the Masonic hall on Saturday after<lb break="no"/>noon, May 19, at 2 o'clock, for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of electing delegates to represent <lb/>
the district at the convention to be <lb/>
held in Regina May 28. <lb/></p> 

<p>The suggestion comes from Moose <lb/>
Jaw Old Timers that neighboring dis<lb break="no"/>tricts should combine for an excursion <lb/>
to Banff. The suggestion is a good one <lb/>
and would afford a most enjoyable <lb/>
outing. <lb/></p> 

<p>–Some diſliculty is being experi<lb break="no"/>enced in the election of an officer to <lb/>
command the Canadian militia. The <lb/>
Canadian ministry seem reluctant to <lb/>
place another British official in charge, <lb/>
owing to the difficulties arising in the <lb/>
Hutton case. <lb/></p> 

<p>The executive committee of the <lb/>
Presbyterian century fund will meet <lb/>
on May 20, to prepare their report for <lb/>
the general assembly. They desire <lb/>
that all congregationswhich are can<lb break="no"/>vassed for the fund ill send in their <lb/>
report before May 12. <lb/></p> 

<p>-The Calgary Herald has published <lb/>
a notice similar to the one that ap<lb break="no"/>peared in THE LEADER and other pap<lb break="no"/>ers, in accordance with the action tak<lb break="no"/>en by the Western CanadaPress As<lb break="no"/>sociation regarding the publishing of <lb/>
free notices of entertainments, shows, <lb/>
races and other schemes for which an <lb/>
admission fee is charged. <lb/></p> 

<p>-SuperintendentGoggin's address <lb/>
at Vancouver, judging from newspaper <lb/>
comments, awakened them to the <lb/>
fact that they were behind the times. <lb/>
They have 219 training schools and are <lb/>
still in the stage when they have the <lb/>
mastery of numbers up to 100.000 on <lb/>
the programme for first form pupils. <lb/>
Miss Burnett has accepted a lucrative <lb/>
position as teacher of drawing to the <lb/>
teachers of Vancouver schools. <lb/></p> 

<p>- Mr. C. W. Speers, general coloni<lb break="no"/>zation agent, has been visiting the <lb/>
Doukhabor and Galician colonies in <lb/>
Saskatchewan recently and reports <lb/>
them in a satisfactory condition. They <lb/>
are well equipped with horses, and <lb/>
have made great progress considering <lb/>
the length of time they have been set<lb break="no"/>tled. They are applying to Russia for <lb/>
the proceeds of the sales of their pro<lb break="no"/>perty left behind them when they em<lb break="no"/>migrated. <lb/></p> 

<p>-Canadian delegates will present <lb/>
at the London Congress of the Cham<lb break="no"/>ber of Commerce for the Empire in <lb/>
July, where itisxpected that Imper<lb break="no"/>ial Federation will be one of the lead<lb break="no"/>ing subjects of discussion. Mr. Cham<lb break="no"/>berlain considers that it would be <lb/>
futile to attempt to consider the ques<lb break="no"/>tion from the standpoint of representa<lb break="no"/>tion just at present, but thinks that <lb/>
there may be a way of approahc <lb/>
through the tariff side. <lb/></p> 

<p>The members of the Regina fire <lb/>
brigade, after practice and roll call on <lb/>
Friday night last, took occasion to <lb/>
banquet their ex-chief, Mayor Mollard, <lb/>
and presented him with an address and <lb/>
a gold headed cane in token of their re<lb break="no"/>spect and good will. His Worship, <lb/>
though taken completely by surprise, <lb/>
made a suitable reply, referring to the <lb/>
work of the past year, urging. the im<lb break="no"/>portance of strict discipline and ended <lb/>
by complimenting the brigade upon the <lb/>
choice of their new chief. W. A. White. <lb/>
Toasts were proposed to the Queen, <lb/>
ex-chief and chief of the fire brigade, <lb/>
the press and the ladies, and were re<lb break="no"/>sponded to with a flow of wit and <lb/>
eloquence. <lb/></p> 

<p>BLOOD. Pure, Rich and Red <lb/>
or in other words, your good <lb/>
health will be insured by using <lb/>
"Capital" <lb/>
Sarsaparilla <lb/>
combined with Iodides. <lb/>
THE BEST SPRING MEDICINE, <lb/>
A large $1.00 bottle for 75c. <lb/>
Prepared by <lb/>
O. A. ANDERSON &amp; CO., <lb/>
Chemist and Druggists. <lb/>

<cb/>

–Miss Barrett, of Winnipeg, sang in <lb/>
St. Mary's church choir on Sunday <lb/>
last. <lb/></p> 

<p>-Edmonton town council is urging <lb/>
the necessity of precaution against <lb/>
smallpox. <lb/></p> 

<p>—A football match will be played at <lb/>
Barracks on Friday afternoon between <lb/>
the police and town teams. <lb/></p> 

<p>-Citizens of Regina are taking com<lb break="no"/>mendable interest in decorating their <lb/>
premises and planting trees. <lb/></p> 

<p>The brick work on the new land <lb/>
office is being rapidly pushed forward <lb/>
by contractors Willoughby and Mol<lb break="no"/>lard. <lb/></p> 

<p>–To-morrow (Friday) being Arbor <lb/>
Day the stores and places of business <lb/>
will be closed. Do your shopping to<lb break="no"/>night. <lb/></p> 

<p>—Mrs. C. J. McCusker and son left <lb/>
last night for Toronto and other <lb/>
points in Ontario on a two months <lb/>
visit. <lb/></p> 

<p>—Brandon is to have a new isolated <lb/>
hospital building at once, to take place <lb/>
of the temporary building erected two <lb/>
years ago. <lb/></p> 

<p>–Mr. John Hawkes has bought the <lb/>
Carnduff Gazette. He is a trenchant <lb/>
writer and may be expected to produce <lb/>
a live paper. <lb/></p> 

<p>Moose Jaw will celebrate Her <lb/>
Majesty's birthday with a big racing <lb/>
and sporting programe. Prizes to the <lb/>
amount of $[illegible] are offered. <lb/></p> 

<p>The town of Edmonton has pur<lb break="no"/>chased five hundred copies of <lb/>
Bulletin for distribution, giving in<lb break="no"/>formation about the district for <lb/>
intending settlers. <lb/></p> 

<p>- The cricket match between the­ <lb/>
Barracks and the Regina team result<lb break="no"/>ed in an easy victory for the former.­ <lb/>
The return match will be played in <lb/>
town on Saturday. <lb/></p> 

<p>- The fire brigade had a run to the <lb/>
C.P.R. track near Smith &amp; Ferguson's <lb/>
coal oil shed on Saturday. Cleanings <lb/>
from the stock cars were on fire and <lb/>
threatened the shed. <lb/></p> 

<p>The committee of the Dominion <lb/>
Parliament selected to enquire into Mr. <lb/>
Davies printing transactions is now <lb/>
sitting. Ec-Govenor Mackintosh and <lb/>
Mr. R. B. Gordon have been examined. <lb/></p> 

<p>There died in Toronto on April <lb/>
27th, Minnie C. Elliott, eldest daughter <lb/>
of the late George Douglas Ferguson, <lb/>
at the age of 16 years. Deceased lady <lb/>
was a sister of Messrs. R.B. and A.D. <lb/>
Ferguson. <lb/></p> 

<p>Gen. Sr. George White visited <lb/>
Windsor Castle on Wednesday of last <lb/>
week and was decorated the defender <lb/>
of Ladysmith, with the cross and <lb/>
star of Royal Victorian Order, by Her <lb/>
Majesty. <lb/></p> 

<p>The secretary of Regina Board of <lb/>
Trade has been informed by the Canad<lb break="no"/>ian Government agent in Scotland <lb/>
that domestic servants may be sent to <lb/>
Regina on payment of the fare out <lb/>
such payments to be considered as <lb/>
wages. <lb/></p> 

<p>The officers for [illegible] the Epworth <lb/>
League, Methodist church, Regina, <lb/>
[illegible] T.W. Pearl, president: Miss Cal-<lb break="yes"/>lender, Miss Ida Simpson, Miss Mac-<lb break="maybe"/>Farlane and Miss Young, vice-pres-<lb break="maybe"/>idents: W.A. White, sec., and Miss <lb/>
Etty, treas. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. David Lang of Winnipeg has <lb/>
been visiting his brother Mr. B. Lang, <lb/>
book keeper for John Dobbin, Regina, <lb/>
during the past week. On Tuesday <lb/>
night Mr. Lang addressed the Christian <lb/>
Endeavor of Knox church on mission <lb/>
work in British Colonies. He left on <lb/>
Tuesday night for Nelson, B.C. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Superintendent of [illegible] <lb/>
[illegible] F.W. Colbough, came west <lb/>
last week with about thirty tanks of <lb/>
white fish fry, about three weeks old, <lb/>
for Qu'Appelle lakes. There are about <lb/>
[illegible] little fish. They are hady <lb/>
and prepare to feeding as they are sup<lb break="no"/>posed with food season on which they <lb/>
ate until old enough to manage for <lb/>
themselves. <lb/></p> 

<p>The question of whether these per<lb break="no"/>sons who have depended upon the sale <lb/>
of [illegible] for a livelihood should be <lb/>
compensated for their loss in the event <lb/>
of prohibition is being [illegible] <lb/>
Manitoba [illegible]. Mr. Gladstone and <lb/>
Mr. [illegible]have both been quoted <lb/>
as taking the position that since the <lb/>
battle has been leaglized, compensa<lb break="no"/>tion for damages should be made by <lb/>
the states. <lb/></p> 

<p>A great wedding took place at <lb/>
Whitewood on Thursday of last week. <lb/>
when Mr. J. R. Levett baggage master <lb/>
on the C.P.R. between Moose Jaw and <lb/>
Medicine Hat and Miss Olae Gillis of <lb/>
Whitewood were united in marriage <lb/>
by the Rev. J. W. [illegible]. A. B. <lb/>
Gillis, [illegible] supported the groom <lb/>
and Miss Ida Gillis of Whitewood was <lb/>
bridesmaid. Mr. and Mrs. Levett left <lb/>
[illegible] months [illegible] in Winnepeg,  <lb/>
after which they will reside in Medi<lb break="no"/>cine Hat. <lb/></p> 

<p>Complaint is being made of [illegible] <lb/>
space for British colonial dis<lb break="no"/>played the Paris exposition. Canada <lb/>
has prepared an interesting and impor<lb break="no"/>tant exhibit, calculated to show the <lb/>
mineral and agricultural prestiges of <lb/>
the country. Nuggets will be shown <lb/>
from Klondike valued at $30,000. Grand <lb/>
and [illegible] glasses and tobacco will <lb/>
give testament to the agricultural [illegible] <lb/>
pf the Dominion. Among <lb/>
those in charge of Canada's exhibits <lb/>
are Lord Stratheson, Mr. Fisher, min<lb break="no"/>ister of agriculture, and Mr. Tatte, <lb/>
minister of public works. <lb/></p> 

<p>A young Sioux from Dakota came <lb/>
to Moose Jaw to visit his sweetheart <lb/>
whom he had know from boyhood, <lb/>
and from whom he had been unwilling<lb break="no"/>ly separated. He was gladly welcomed <lb/>
by the faithful lass, who is the sixteen <lb/>
year old [illegible] of [illegible] "Bow". <lb/>
Upon the refusal of the parents to <lb/>
allow them to marry, the galant young <lb/>
brave presented a couple of saddle <lb/>
horses and in company with the hope <lb/>
[illegible] heart started for the south. <lb/>
They were followed by the angry <lb/>
father who shot the house ridden by <lb/>
the determined lover and compelled <lb/>
his daughter to return home. The <lb/>
matter was ventilated in the courts. <lb/>
The father has since promised his <lb/>
daughter to the Indian when she has <lb/>
turned eighteen years of age. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Regina town council met on <lb/>
Monday night with the mayor and all <lb/>
the councillors present. Communica<lb break="no"/>tions were read from P. McAra stating <lb/>
that the assessment toll was completed: <lb/>
from J [illegible] McCarthy, secretary of <lb/>
Gratton school, asking for the pay<lb break="no"/>ment of any balance taxes collected on <lb/>
behalf of Gratton school district: from <lb/>
M. B. Jackson asking to redeem lots <lb/>
sold to the town for taxes: from the <lb/>
secretary of the tennis club asking for <lb/>
the use of Osler street park for a tennis <lb/>
court: and from J. G. Black, secretary <lb/>
of the management committee of the <lb/>
Regina football club, expressing regret <lb/>
that owing to strenuous opposition <lb/>
from several quarters to the Victoria <lb/>
park proposition they had decided to <lb/>
decline the kind offer made by the <lb/>
council. <lb/></p> 

<p>BUSINESS ANNOUNCEMENTS. <lb/>
Notices under this head Ten cents per lines <lb/>
Piques and Dennes, Khaki color, <lb/>
just arrived at the Glasgow House. <lb/>
Latest novelties in patriotic and <lb/>
other ties for ladies and men - JOHN <lb/>
DOBBIN. <lb/>
John Dobbin requests the plea<lb break="no"/>sure of your company at the special <lb/>
display of carpets and curtains in the <lb/>
house furnishing room over the store <lb/>
- good light, easy chairs, and a good <lb/>
time generally. <lb/>

<cb/>

REPLY TO SENATOR PERLEY. <lb/></p> 

<p>To the Editor of THE LEADER: <lb/>
Sir.-I notice in the Standard of <lb/>
11 inst. that Senator Perley has been <lb/>
spreading himself on the subject of <lb/>
Provincial Automy. Now this is a <lb/>
subject on which the average man does <lb/>
not know as much as he ought to. I <lb/>
am an average man and Senator Per<lb break="no"/>ley is evidently another. Nevertheless <lb/>
I so far agree with the Senator that <lb/>
the ventilation of the subject even by <lb/>
us may tend to throw fresh light on it. <lb/>
Mr. Haultain is said to advocate pro<lb break="no"/>vincial antonomy chiefly because we <lb/>
cannot get sufficient money from the <lb/>
Federal Government to run the coun<lb break="no"/>try properly. Mr. Perley says that if <lb/>
Mr. Haultain would accept the services <lb/>
of the North-West members and the <lb/>
two Senators, their influence with the <lb/>
Government would be so overpowering <lb/>
that we should secure an ample grant. <lb/>
Why? It seems to me that the <lb/>
proper party to make representations <lb/>
to theDominion Government is the <lb/>
North-West Executive, and that the <lb/>
influence of four party men, and two <lb/>
equally party Senators would be small. <lb/>
Mr. Perley's chief objection to our <lb/>
having provincial autonomy , is the <lb/>
fear lest we should run into debt for <lb/>
the purpose of building railways and <lb/>
public works. I don't think this <lb/>
should alarm him. Do not most of us <lb/>
as private individuals run into debt <lb/>
for the purpose of developing our <lb/>
business? Probably the Senator <lb/>
has done so himself. The best far<lb break="no"/>mers and business men most certainly <lb/>
do so.And what, progressive and <lb/>
civilized country is there that has not <lb/>
its national debt? Take New Zealand <lb/>
a country which in point of population <lb/>
and resources perhaps most nearly <lb/>
resembles the Territories. It has its <lb/>
debt, but it owns its railroads and is <lb/>
prosperous. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Perley gets a little mixed on the <lb/>
subject of raising a revenue in our <lb/>
prospective province. In one place he <lb/>
says farm land is the only thing from <lb/>
which we could raise a revenue and <lb/>
that that would not amount to much <lb/>
because we could not sell it, in which <lb/>
case Mr. Perley may set his mind at <lb/>
rest, assured that that will not amount <lb/>
to much either, as no capitalists will <lb/>
advance money without security. But <lb/>
in another part of his letter Mr. <lb/>
Perley says minerals, forests and fish <lb/>
are valuable sources of wealth, but the <lb/>
food producing country is the greatest <lb/>
of all. <lb/></p> 

<p>Perhaps so, but it follows if we <lb/>
accept this axiom that it will stand tax<lb break="no"/>ation with the greater case, and pro<lb break="no"/>duce the biggest revenue. <lb/></p> 

<p>Cannot Mr. Perley see how inconsis<lb break="no"/>tent it is for us without any protest <lb/>
from W. D. P. to allow our towns, <lb/>
municipalities and even school districts <lb/>
to raise money for public works, and <lb/>
yet to deny the privilege to a country <lb/>
the size of all the Maritime provinces <lb/>
put together? <lb/></p> 

<p>To read the Senator's remarks on <lb/>
immigration one would suppose that <lb/>
he was a trade unionist, and regarded <lb/>
every immigrant as a possible compet<lb break="no"/>itor and blackleg. He says "they (the <lb/>
immigrants) are not worth one dollar <lb/>
to any of the local governments." To <lb/>
be consistent Mr. Perley should set up <lb/>
a Chinese wall the Conservatives know <lb/>
what that is at the Manitoba boundary <lb/>
and not allow another immigrant to <lb/>
enter the Territories. In the mean<lb break="no"/>time it would appear that every Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and every little district goes into <lb/>
raptures over the arrival of every <lb/>
batch of these newcomers who are not <lb/>
worth a red cent. Strange, isn't it? I <lb/>
am at one with Mr. Perley in thinking <lb/>
that if there is to be provincial govern<lb break="no"/>ment there should be but one province <lb/>
for the whole of the Territories, and <lb/>
while $500 may be enough to pay our <lb/>
local members, still one cannot help <lb/>
thinking that a member of the Senate <lb/>
who draws, S1,000, besides perquisites <lb/>
and travelling expenses (which he <lb/>
pockets). is not the man to cast the <lb/>
first stone. <lb/></p> 

<p>As I was about to conclude this letter <lb/>
my eye caught the final sentence of <lb/>
Mr. Perley's epistle: "Then will be the <lb/>
time when we will want the right men <lb/>
in the right place." Taking this in <lb/>
connection with the Senator's farmer <lb/>
wild attacks on Mr. Haultain, we are <lb/>
justified in assuming that on this idea <lb/>
his whole article was based. Until we <lb/>
get the Senator's nominees in the <lb/>
Executive we are to mark time. How <lb/>
pleasant! <lb/></p> 

<p>C. P. PACKINSON. <lb/>
Chickney, April 13, 1900. <lb/></p> 

<p>QU'APPELLE STATION. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Essen of Brandon, has purchas<lb break="no"/>ed the manufactured material on <lb/>
hand in the Qu'Appelle felt factory, a <lb/>
carload of which was shipped on Mon= <lb/>
day. Mr. R. Johnston was fined $10 <lb/>
last week for allowing a fire to escape <lb/>
from his farm while burning stubble. <lb/></p> 

<p>The collection made throughout the <lb/>
country in and of the patriotic fund has <lb/>
been most loyalty responded to and <lb/>
the total will be between three and <lb/>
four hundred dollars. Mr. F. W. Col-<lb break="yes"/>dough, superintendent of the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion fish hatchery at Selkirk, arrived <lb/>
on Friday with a few million white <lb/>
fish fry, and with Fishery Inspector <lb/>
Miller, when out to the Fort, where <lb/>
they were safely deposited in the Qu'-<lb break="maybe"/>Appelle lakes. We trust that our local <lb/>
fish supply will become more abundant <lb/>
in a year or two as the result. We <lb/>
understand that Crooked and Round <lb/>
lakes also received a supply. A more <lb/>
even growth of the crop has probably nev<lb break="no"/>er been recorded in the N.W.T. than <lb/>
that of this year, and though some <lb/>
farmers would like rain, there is evi<lb break="no"/>dently enough moisture in the land to <lb/>
last a long time yet. The favorable <lb/>
seeding season is permitting many far<lb break="no"/>mers to do what few have done before, <lb/>
viz., put in their oats decently. The <lb/>
baseball club is doing some good prac<lb break="no"/>tising and should give a good account <lb/>
of itself when the gala days come on. <lb/></p> 

<p>Supreme Court Sitting at Regina. <lb/>
Judge Richardson held a special <lb/>
court at Regina on Tuesday last. Entry <lb/>
the following cases: Crown vs. J. <lb/>
Emerson, A. Hayward and De Phillpo, <lb/>
for theft at Moose Jaw: Crown vs. <lb/>
John Clark for theft, and D.Oylet <lb/>
Carte vs. Dennis, Pocklington, Brown, <lb/>
Briggs, Hamilton, Fraser, Haultain <lb/>
and Balfour re: infringement of play-<lb break="yes"/>right, in the Pirates of Penzance case. <lb/>
For a year cases of theft have been <lb/>
numerous at Moose Jaw, the thieves <lb/>
being bold enough to appropriate par<lb break="no"/>cels from the station platform. This week <lb/>
three arrests were made and convic<lb break="no"/>tions secured. In April a box contain<lb break="no"/>ing butter and other farm produce was <lb/>
shipped from Elkhorn to A. Smith of <lb/>
Moose Jaw. The box was missed <lb/>
from the platform at Moose Jaw and <lb/>
soon after J. Emerson, waiter in the <lb/>
C.P.R. hotel, was arrested, charged <lb/>
with the theft. Further investigation <lb/>
let to the arrest of two accomplices <lb/>
A. Hayward, who assisted to remove <lb/>
the box, and Rehan De Phillpo <lb/>
who secreted the stolen property. <lb/>
They had arranged to set up a bache<lb break="no"/>lor's shack and live on the contents of <lb/>
the box. Emerson and the Italian are <lb/>
old offenders. De Phillpo was the <lb/>
Italian implicated in the stabbing <lb/>
affair in the Ottawa hotel at Moose <lb/>
Jaw some time ago. As soon as the <lb/>
first case was settled a second charge <lb/>
was entered against Emerson and he <lb/>
pleaded guilt to stealing rings be<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

longing to the kitchen maid. Emerson <lb/>
was sentenced to one year's hard <lb/>
labor in Regina jail, Hayward to nine <lb/>
months and De Phillpo to six. A <lb/>
bunch of thirty-two keys, filed and <lb/>
twisted into many shapes was found <lb/>
in the Italian's possession. Hayward <lb/>
and Emerson are both young English­ <lb/>
men, aged 19 and 22 respectively. The <lb/>
latter wore Salvation Army uniform. <lb/>
 <lb/></p> <p/> 

<p>John Clark, a settler at Weyburn, <lb/>
was accused of stealing a horse be<lb break="no"/>longing to Thos. Good of Indian Head. <lb/>
Clark rode the horse across country to <lb/>
Weyburn and disposed of it for a suit <lb/>
of clothes and $5 to Adolphus Martin. <lb/>
He was very penitent and promised good <lb/>
behaviour. He was given six months. <lb/>
 <lb/></p> 

<p>The case for infringement of play <lb/>
right was adjourned until next Satur<lb break="no"/>day, after hearing a partial examina<lb break="no"/>tion of T. A. Briggs, touching the <lb/>
matter. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hospital Notes. <lb/></p> 

<p>The directors of the Regina Hospital <lb/>
acknowledge with thanks the follow<lb break="no"/>ing donation Miss Lawson, England, <lb/>
$50; Mrs. Grisdaie, Bishops Court, In­ <lb/>
dian Head, 10 jars, preserved fruit: <lb/>
Mrs. McCallum, Dandorn, seven dozen <lb/>
fresh eggs; Mrs. Michaelis, floor rug. <lb/>
batter prints, lampwire, Easter pud<lb break="no"/>dings: Mrs. Broder, floor mat: Mrs. <lb/>
McDonald, buns and bread: Mr. Ar<lb break="no"/>mour, fish: Mrs. Martin, dozen fresh <lb/>
eggs: Mrs. Callender. book; Mrs. J.H. <lb/>
Ross, tin of honey: , Mrs. P. McAra, <lb/>
pair large sheets, half dozen pillow <lb/>
cases, two pounds fresh butter; Mrs. <lb/>
Stemshorn, three ducks, two cabbages: <lb/>
Mrs. Mason, two bedroom lamps; one <lb/>
pair blankets, milk, eggs, chicken: <lb/>
Mrs. McIntosh, two nightengales, cook <lb/>
book: Mrs. Caley Hamilton, dozen <lb/>
silver forks; Mrs. Darke, package su<lb break="no"/>gar: Miss Hoyle, ten loaves bread: <lb/>
Friend, one steel: Friend. Winnipeg <lb/>
Daily Morning Telegram: Friend. <lb/>
gentleman's dressing gown: Ladies <lb/>
Hospital Aid, brush, whisks, four <lb/>
toilet mugs, combs, soap dishes, soup <lb/>
kettle, coffee strainer, two white <lb/>
spreads, four flannelette blankets, doz<lb break="no"/>en draw sheets, pair towels, toilet <lb/>
boxes; Easter donation by Regina <lb/>
school children—sack rolled oats, quart <lb/>
maple syrup, 7 sacks table salt, 3 pack<lb break="no"/>ages corn starch, 2 rolls bread, 3 pack<lb break="no"/>ages rolled oats, 3 bars soap, 3 cans of <lb/>
cocoa, package cocoa, package ginger, <lb/>
2 packages jelly, can baking powder, <lb/>
package caramel cereal, 2 gems honey. <lb/>
[illegible], jar preserved apples, 5 cans <lb/>
tomatoes,jam jelly, 2 cans strawberries. <lb/>
bottle pickles, package tapioca, peck <lb/>
potatoes, can pears, can [illegible], [illegible] <lb/>
[illegible] turtle soup, package barley, 11 <lb/>
parcels sugar, 9 parcels tea, bag gran<lb break="no"/>ules, 7 parcels rice, 17 lbs. butter,pack<lb break="no"/>age peaches, package apricots, 23 doz<lb break="no"/>en lemons, half dozen apples, dozen <lb/>
oranges, 17 dozen eggs, dozen buns <lb/>
packages coffee, package corn meal, <lb/>
package peanuts, 2 parcels, fancy, bis<lb break="no"/>cuits, 2 pounds raisins, pitcher jam, <lb/>
wild flowers, cash $5.46 <lb/></p> -->

 </div>
  <div type="debate">
<head rendition="simple:centre">THE LEGISLATURE.</head> 

<!--<p>Continued on Page 1. <lb/></p> -->

<p>even if they had private assurances, <lb/>
they could not act before the Federal <lb/>
House met. If they did questions <lb/>
would be asked in the Dominion House <lb/>
and there might be embarassment and <lb/>
inconvenience. If, however the finan<lb break="no"/>cial grant were on a fixed basis, the <lb/>
Territorial House could meet at a date <lb/>
most convenient to itself, because it <lb/>
would be easy to frame the estimates. <lb/>
Now the first resolution No. 14 dealt <lb/>
with the present position of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. The House was confronted <lb/>
with the actual position as it existed. <lb/>
They had to deal with the question <lb/>
not only on its financial side, for there <lb/>
were other sides, there was the consti<lb break="no"/>tutional side. No matter whether they <lb/>
got their finances on a permanent bas<lb break="no"/>is, for two years, or ten years, there <lb/>
were certain other things necessary <lb/>
for the proper carrying on of the busi<lb break="no"/>ness of the House. They had to, to ex<lb break="no"/>tend, extension was going on as popu<lb break="no"/>lation increased, and conditions became <lb/>
more complicated. Whatever the <lb/>
postponement of the financial questions <lb/>
however long a time it might be, it was <lb/>
the duty of the Assembly, an absolute <lb/>
necessity to ask for an extension of <lb/>
their power, not in ten years, or two <lb/>
years, but now, immediately. Cheers. <lb/>
They had not the power to regulate <lb/>
their own constitution. They ought to <lb/>
have it. There was no reason why <lb/>
they should not have it. There were <lb/>
several points involved that made it <lb/>
difficult to pass election laws, and they <lb/>
had no power to disqualify even a <lb/>
member of their own House. Again <lb/>
they ought to have the power to ad<lb break="no"/>minister criminal justice. There were <lb/>
two reasons why they should not: there <lb/>
were many reasons why they should. <lb/>
The Territories administered the civil <lb/>
law, and under the present system <lb/>
practically two sets of officials had to <lb/>
be kept up in the country. The Crown <lb/>
agency should be done by the At<lb break="no"/>torney General. Then they should <lb/>
have certainly, and had often asked <lb/>
for the control of the registry offices. <lb/>
The important power to legislate in re<lb break="no"/>gard to property and civil rights that <lb/>
the Assembly already had was practi<lb break="no"/>cally taken away by the Dominion <lb/>
Government dealing with land titles. <lb/>
One every side the Territories met with <lb/>
difficulties in regard to land titles, and <lb/>
if they had the right to deal with pro<lb break="no"/>perty, including land, they could make <lb/>
many improvements in general <lb/>
legislation. He believed that if this <lb/>
additional power were granted, if their <lb/>
land titles system were local, they <lb/>
would reduce very much the number <lb/>
of fees charged for various services <lb/>
performed. Now, it might be asked <lb/>
why come down with a resolution up<lb break="no"/>on this question at this time? Why <lb/>
should it be put so formally as by an <lb/>
address to the Governor General? He <lb/>
would say that the treatment hitherto <lb/>
accorded by the Dominion Government <lb/>
to the memorials and the resolutions <lb/>
already sent, had been such as to make <lb/>
it undesirable to continue. That line of <lb/>
somewhat internally dealing with the <lb/>
subject. They had arrived at a time <lb/>
when they were confronted with</p>
  
  <p rendition="simple:centre">A VERY PRACTICAL NECESSITY,</p>
  
  <p>
and the House should in the most for<lb break="no"/>mal way, not satisfied with the treat<lb break="no"/>ment dealt out to the Territories, ask <lb/>
that its financial claims be enquired <lb/>
into. (Hear, hear.) That was all he <lb/>
proposed to say in regard to the first <lb/>
resolution. It spoke for itself. It <lb/>
dealt altogether with the practical <lb/>
necessities of the position: it dealt <lb/>
with them as they were. It was gen<lb break="no"/>erally admitted by every member of <lb/>
the house that more money was need<lb break="no"/>ed, and more power: and there could be <lb/>
no objection to the strongest demands <lb/>
from the quarter from which alone <lb/>
they must derive both the money and <lb/>
the power. (Cheers.) He now come to <lb/>
the second resolution. (No. 15.) Before <lb/>
taking up the resolution he would <lb/>
simply ask the House to go over the <lb/>
recitals which led up to it. They show<lb break="no"/>ed and suggested the development of <lb/>
the method of action. The intention <lb/>
by Parliament to give institutions to <lb/>
this country, the restriction that <lb/>
anything done should be subject to the <lb/>
British North American Act after <lb/>
the country was acquired for <lb/>
the benefit, be remembered, <lb/>
of eastern markets and eastern <lb/>
trade: the consistent method <lb/>
which had been followed to establish <lb/>
institutions of the provinces: all these <lb/>
running through every document, <lb/>

<cb/>

though every act of Parliament, and <lb/>
through ever official statement made; <lb/>
all showed that the institutions of the <lb/>
North-West Territories should bear <lb/>
analogy to those of the provinces, and <lb/>
be dealt with under the British North <lb/>
American Act and the principle under<lb break="no"/>lying. A question would be raised at <lb/>
the very outset: How long should the <lb/>
gradual development of their present <lb/>
institutions to go on? Well, he should <lb/>
say it should go on until the question <lb/>
was settled. (Hear, hear.) To begin <lb/>
with he would point out that the <lb/>
institutions should be as nearly exact <lb/>
as possible to the provincial institu<lb break="no"/>tions. Their present position was an <lb/>
impossible one. They had <lb/></p>
 <p rendition="simple:centre">
EXHAUSTED EVERY MEANS <lb/></p>
 <p>
of obtaining an increase in their grants. <lb/>
(To be continued next week.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">PROROGATION.</p> 

<p>Precisely at half past three on Fri<lb break="no"/>day afternoon a trumpet flourish an<lb break="no"/>nounced the arrival of Lieutenant <lb/>
Governor Forget to prorogue, the <lb/>
Assembly. His Honor entered the <lb/>
House, accompanied by Supt. Strick<lb break="no"/>land, N.W.M.P., as aide de camp, and <lb/>
having given assent to the bills pass<lb break="no"/>ed by the Legislature prorogued the <lb/>
House by the following speech: <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Speaker and gentlemen of the <lb/>
Legislative Assembly:In relieving <lb/>
you of your legislative duties. I desire <lb/>
to thank you for the diligent considera<lb break="no"/>tion which you have given to the mat<lb break="no"/>ters to which your attention has been <lb/>
directed. I am glad to observe the <lb/>
unanimity with which the proposals <lb/>
submitted by my Government for <lb/>
meeting the present and immediate <lb/>
necessities, as well as the future posi<lb break="no"/>tion and condition of these Territories, <lb/>
have met your approval. I thank you <lb/>
for the supplies granted for the Public <lb/>
Service, and while regretting the sad <lb/>
occurrence at Ottawa and Hull, I am <lb/>
glad to observe that you have given <lb/>
practical expression to the sympathe<lb break="no"/>tic feelings of the people of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories for the suffering of our fellow <lb/>
countrymen in those cities. I now bid <lb/>
you farewell in full confidence that <lb/>
your labors will conduce to the welfare <lb/>
of the Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BULY1">Mr. G. H. V. Bulyea</persName>, Territorial <lb/>
Secretary, then announced the proro<lb break="no"/>gation and the proceedings terminated. <lb/></p>
 

 <pb n="001" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1900-05-17_Page_001.jpg"/> <lb/>

<fw type="num">1</fw>

<fw type="running">THE LEADER.</fw> 

<fw type="running">REGINA, N.W.T., THURSDAY MORNING, MAY 17, 1900.</fw>

  </div>
   <div type="debate">
 
<head rendition="simple:centre">THE N. W. LEGISLATURE</head>
<head rendition="simple:centre">FINISH OF PREMIER'S SPEECH.</head>
 

<head rendition="simple:centre">Railway Exemptions, School Lands, <lb/>
Justice to the Territories. <lb/>
Banff Park. <lb/></head> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">(Continued from last week.) <lb/></p> 

<p>However well disposed a government <lb/>
might be the conditions that existed in <lb/>
Parliament to-day would prevent any <lb/>
adeqtate amount being given to them. <lb/>
He made that statement: he believed <lb/>
that was the case. So long as the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories remained in a dependent posi<lb break="no"/>tion so long would it be impossible for <lb/>
them to secure even that adequate <lb/>
recognition without which they could <lb/>
not carry on. The North-West had <lb/>
gone through the preliminary stage. <lb/>
They had been founding their institu<lb break="no"/>tions for a number of years, and they <lb/>
had fairly well exhausted the power <lb/>
that had been given them. They had <lb/>
founded their institutions, and had <lb/>
got out of their foundations. The time <lb/>
had arrived for them to begin the super<lb break="no"/>structure. (Cheers.) They had had <lb/>
the foundation well; they had exhaus<lb break="no"/>ted the powers they possessed; and <lb/>
although he would not say that further <lb/>
progress was impossible, yet he did <lb/>
say that progress to a large amount <lb/>
was not possible, and to develop was <lb/>
was not possible under the existing <lb/>
institutions. (Hear hear.) They had, <lb/>
as the hon. member for Yorkton had <lb/>
said, grown out of their clothes. He <lb/>
did not believe their present institu<lb break="no"/>tions were suitable to their present <lb/>
conditions. The question arose, why <lb/>
should their jurisdiction be limited? <lb/>
They had been accorded very urgely <lb/>
the duties of a province. The part <lb/>
given was of more importance than <lb/>
the part witheld. They had arrived at <lb/>
a time when something more was <lb/>
necessary, some larger power given, <lb/>
and then left to work out their own <lb/>
salvation. They could not look to the <lb/>
Dominion Government. The surround<lb break="no"/>ing conditions would prevent any Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment from having a free hand. It <lb/>
could never be done satisfactorily until <lb/>
their institutions were so developed <lb/>
that they were put in a position to <lb/>
develop their own resources. Hitherto <lb/>
their Government's work had been <lb/>
mere administration. Having but a <lb/>
small vote they had been deprived of <lb/>
doing more than looking after the <lb/>
interests of the country. They wanted <lb/>
now to go on and develop its resources. <lb/>
The question was: What should we <lb/>
do? Should we simply stand still? <lb/>
He gathered from the expression of <lb/>
the House that they should never <lb/>
stand still. They must ask for further <lb/>
powers and demand more money. <lb/>
Why should not they <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">TAKE THE ACTUAL PLUNGE?</p> 

<p>When they had arrived at the actual <lb/>
point, both the financial point, and the <lb/>
constitutional point, they ought not to <lb/>
be diffident about the further step. <lb/>
That step was to go to the very limit <lb/>
allowed by the British North America <lb/>
Act. Even if to-morrow they were <lb/>
formed into a province or provinces, <lb/>
apart from the financial question to be <lb/>
settled, he did not fancy that any <lb/>
person in the whole Territories would <lb/>
feel that a large revolution had occur<lb break="no"/>red, because after all the provincial <lb/>
institution, as it touched the every day <lb/>
life of the people was much the same <lb/>
as at present. They were driven and <lb/>
driven by necessity, both by their fin<lb break="no"/>ancial conditions and constitutional <lb/>
position, to consider the assumption of <lb/>
provincial institutions. The question <lb/>
was, within what time? He did not <lb/>
think it would be desirable to <lb/>
involve the House in a discussion <lb/>
as to fixing the actual date of <lb/>
an event they had no power to <lb/>
bring about. After all, they had not <lb/>
the fixing of the date and any <choice><sic>expres<lb break="no"/>tion</sic><corr>expression</corr></choice> of the opinion of the House on <lb/>
the subject would only have weight <lb/>
in proportion to the unanimity with <lb/>
which it was expressed. But there <lb/>
was a certain date within which it <lb/>
could not be taken, but within which <lb/>
they could be getting ready. (Hear <lb/>
hear). Next year there will be <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">A CENSUS TAKEN.</p> 

<p>No action could be taken until the <lb/>
census was taken. The population of <lb/>
the country was the basis of the per <lb/>
capita grant. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BENN2">Mr. Bennett</persName>—Not impossible, only <lb/>
inexpedient. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>—Nothing was impos<lb break="no"/>sible. The Federal Parliament could <lb/>
bring in a bill tomorrow and make a <lb/>
dozen provinces if it so wished. Noth<lb break="no"/>ing was impossible, but it would be <lb/>
absurd for any parliament to attempt <lb/>
to lay down the terms and conditions <lb/>
until a census had been taken, as popu<lb break="no"/>lation was their basis. More than that! <lb/>
It was rather a significant coincidence <lb/>
that the term of the present legisla<lb break="no"/>ture ran out in 1902. They would have <lb/>
completed their term then and if <lb/>
things went along in their ordinary <lb/>
course the census would be completed <lb/>
just before the Assembly had completed <lb/>
its labors. A third point of the coinci<lb break="no"/>dence was that there would be a new <lb/>
Dominion Parliament between now <lb/>
and then. All of these facts falling <lb/>
together seemed to him to establish, <lb/>
not only a significant time, but <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">AN OPPORTUNE TIME.></p> 

<p>The time was not too long. Some <lb/>
things had to be understood, so many <lb/>
opinions to be expressed, so many <lb/>
claims to be enforced, that the short <lb/>
space of two years was not a bit too <lb/>
long for the full ussion of the sub<lb break="no"/>ject, for its consideration by every <lb/>
member of that House and every man <lb/>
in the North-West Territories. As he <lb/>
had already said, although the time <lb/>
was good, still the mere fact that they <lb/>
knew perfectly well no provinee or <lb/>
provinces could be established this <lb/>
year or next year, and before such pro<lb break="no"/>vince or provinces could be established, <lb/>
it would certainly be in the interest of <lb/>
the Territories, and of any portion of <lb/>
them that the fullest consideration <lb/>
should be given to all the important <lb/>
subjects he had indicated. There was <lb/>
another point that might be raised in <lb/>
regard to this subject. What right <lb/>
had they to act now, what brief or <lb/> 
what mandate had they to express <lb/>
even a theoretical opinion? It might <lb/>
be said they had no authority from the <lb/>
people to plunge them into the discus<lb break="no"/>sion. He would say, however, that it <lb/>
was not a new subject. There had <lb/>
been sufficiently clear indications that <lb/>
it would be a subject for discussion in <lb/>
the Assembly, though not with the <lb/>
view of making a deliberate statemeat <lb/>
as to whether they would have it or <lb/>
not. The subject involved too many <lb/>
questions for that. Bet it was brought <lb/>
in reply, before the House last summer and it <lb/>
was a theme of discussion from one <lb/>
end of the country to the other. He <lb/>

<cb/>

himself referred to the subject in a <lb/>
speech he made to the House in Sep<lb break="no"/>tember 1898, shortly before the general <lb/>
election. He referred to the matter <lb/>
when introducing the estimates. Then <lb/>
again he need only refer to the gener<lb break="no"/>al election of 1898 when he made much <lb/>
the same statement as he had made in <lb/>
the House. He stated that the time <lb/>
had arrived, and would be the last  <lb/>
work of the new legislature. There<lb break="no"/>fore, he now repeated, if they needed <lb/>
any mandate for taking the step he <lb/>
asked the House to take, that man<lb break="no"/>date had been fairly indicated. After <lb/>
all, they were not assuming on the <lb/>
part of the people of the Territories the <lb/>
right to make an agreement. They <lb/>
simply asked that negotiations should <lb/>
be opened. Indeed, the main result that <lb/>
would follow from the resolution <lb/>
would be the further discussion that <lb/>
would take place throughout the coun<lb break="no"/>try. The people needed to be brought <lb/>
face to face with the question: they <lb/>
needed to have explained to them the <lb/>
actual position in which they were. If <lb/>
nothing else resulted from the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion than the discussion throughout <lb/>
the country, the necessary education, <lb/>
in a sense, in regard to these impor<lb break="no"/>tant rights, would be in itself a suffi<lb break="no"/>cient justification for beginning the <lb/>
discussion at the present time. But it <lb/>
was <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">A LIVE QUESTION TO-DAY.</p> 

<p>It was a practical question. Under <lb/>
what institutions were they going to <lb/>
live and carry on the development of <lb/>
the country? The question had been <lb/>
discussed during the last few months, <lb/>
and it was discussed to-day. All over <lb/>
the Territories the subject was looming <lb/>
up larger than any other. The whole <lb/>
country was considering it, and was <lb/>
not opposing it. It had been said that <lb/>
if a poll were taken on the question <lb/>
seven out of ten would vote down an <lb/>
autonomy resolution. Perhaps they <lb/>
would if they did not understand it. <lb/>
But at any rate the country was not <lb/>
opposed to the discussion of the pro<lb break="no"/>vincial idea. What it was opposed to <lb/>
was a radical and immediate change. <lb/>
The people were somewhat alarmed by <lb/>
the speech he had made at Yorkton. <lb/>
They thought the direct result of the <lb/>
policy there enunciated would be <lb/>
direct taxation, the establishment of <lb/>
municipalities, and a large number of <lb/>
other things held up as bugbears <lb/>
wherever, the question of a province <lb/>
was raised. There was no necessity <lb/>
for any such alarm as that. If a cer<lb break="no"/>tain amount of misapprehension exist<lb break="no"/>ed it was their duty to remove it, not <lb/>
by shrinking from it but by discussing <lb/>
it: not by dangling these bugbears, <lb/>
direct taxation and municipalities, but <lb/>
by an intelligent discussion of what <lb/>
would be the only financial terms they <lb/>
could reasonably expect. He had <lb/>
always made a proviso of proper <lb/>
financial terms. He would never con<lb break="no"/>sent to the establishment of a province <lb/>
under such terms as were <lb/>
Olacc</p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">GRANTED TO MANITOBA.</p>
 
 <p>
They would be better as they now <lb/>
were than that. No, he had always <lb/>
coupled with any proposal, that adistinct <lb/>
understanding must be given in regard <lb/>
to proper, means to carry out both <lb/>
duties and obligations. There should <lb/>
be no misapprehension in regard to <lb/>
the matter, but no desire to plunge <lb/>
the country into it without a settle<lb break="no"/>ment of these important questions. <lb/>
He had no intention of rushing into <lb/>
direct taxation or municipal institu<lb break="no"/>tions. With the powers they had pos<lb break="no"/>sessed for fourteen years, direct taxa<lb break="no"/>tion and municipal institutions could <lb/>
not be used except in the modified <lb/>
sense they had used them already in <lb/>
their legislation. No legislation would <lb/>
plunge the people into these institu<lb break="no"/>tions. It was a matter for the people <lb/>
themselves. Now, his principal argu<lb break="no"/>ment for the immediate taking up of <lb/>
this question with a view to its settle<lb break="no"/>ment and discussion, was that they <lb/>
must make progress in this country, <lb/>
and without a change that would <lb/>
almost be impossible. Education was <lb/>
the instrument of progress, and with<lb break="no"/>out discussion progress would not take <lb/>
place. <lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> continued by saying <lb/>
that he now came back to the <lb/>
resolution. "Whereas parliament <lb/>
had certain powers." Remember that <lb/>
parliament had power to deal with the <lb/>
 <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> drives before <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> in the <lb/>
position of self governing colonies, like <lb/>
Prince Edward Island and British Col<lb break="no"/>umbia, which could please themselves <lb/>
whether they federated or not and <lb/>
could dictate their own terms. The <lb/>
Territories were simply the <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">CREATURE OF THE DOMINION</p> 

<p>parliament, and without reference to <lb/>
the Territories, were it so inclined, it <lb/>
could make a province or provinces. <lb/>
But they did claim as a moral right to <lb/>
be  treated in analogy to the other <lb/>
provinces; they claimed the right <lb/>
to discuss and negotiate; and if <lb/>
they had not the power to <lb/>
dictate terms, or to be one <lb/>
party to an agreement, they claimed <lb/>
to be treated in the same way as citizens <lb/>
in other parts of the Dominion were <lb/>
treated. The resolution had left out <lb/>
anything that could be called the con<lb break="no"/>troversial side of the question. The <lb/>
question whether there should be one, <lb/>
two, three or a dozen provinces was <lb/>
not for them to discuss. It was one of <lb/>
the most difficult things in drawing <lb/>
that resolution to so do it as to avoid <lb/>
controversy. They might waste a <lb/>
great deal of valuable time in discuss<lb break="no"/>ing these controversial points, and yet <lb/>
get no nearer a solution. He had, there<lb break="no"/>fore, purposely refrained from putting <lb/>
anything of a controversial nature <lb/>
into the resolution. They said at once <lb/>
that it was understood that parliament <lb/>
had the power to do what they liked in <lb/>
the matter, and they had the right to <lb/>
do so without any consultation with <lb/>
the people of the Territories. Again, <lb/>
the Territories were not in the position <lb/>
of a province seeking to enter confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. Parliament had power to carve <lb/>
the Territories out into as many pro<lb break="no"/>vinces as it saw fit; but the House <lb/>
could ask for an opportunity of im<lb break="no"/>pressing its views upon the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. They did say that their inter<lb break="no"/>ests and their future were so much <lb/>
bound up that they should at least <lb/>
assert a moral right to negotiate and <lb/>
discuss. For that reason the resolution <lb/>
had been put in the way it was put so <lb/>
as to keep out the controversial side of <lb/>
the question. They did not wish to <lb/>
theorize or indulge in an academic <lb/>
question, or to present themselves as a <lb/>
divided House, forated of little groups, <lb/>
each one with its pet idea. Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment would then say "These people do <lb/>
not know what they want, they do <lb/>
not help us in coming to a conclusion. <lb/>
We will deal with it ourselves." <lb/>
But he did say there were important <lb/>
ides of the financial question and the <lb/></p> 

<!--<p>Continued on page 4 <lb/></p>-->

 <pb n="004" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1900-05-17_Page_004.jpg"/> <lb/>

<fw type="num">4</fw>
<fw type="running">THE LEADER, THURSDAY MORNING MAY 17, 1900.</fw> 

</div>
 <div type="debate">

<head rendition="simple:centre">THE LEGISLATURE.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">Continued from page 1</p> 

<p>constitutional question that would effect <lb/>
not only one province, if there were to <lb/>
be one, but two or a half dozen, and <lb/>
would effect them all equally. They <lb/>
asked therefore for an enquiry and <lb/>
that accounts should be taken. Why? <lb/>
Because, as he had already said, the <lb/>
basis on which the various constitu<lb break="no"/>tions of the several provinces were <lb/>
formed at confederation had been <lb/>
departed from in some cases, and they <lb/>
might obtain more suitable conditions, <lb/>
when any portion of he Territories <lb/>
came to be formed into a province or <lb/>
provinces. What constitution and <lb/>
what Government should be given to <lb/>
the people in this country? He would <lb/>
ask the House to go back a little way. <lb/>
He had traced the history how it came <lb/>
about, what applications had been <lb/>
made, what had been the results, and <lb/>
how their treatment was to be analo<lb break="no"/>gous to those of the provinces. Now, <lb/>
he would go back a little in the history <lb/>
of the country. What was the actual <lb/>
state of the people who were here be<lb break="no"/>fore it was taken over by the Dom<lb break="no"/>inion. He would ask the members to <lb/>
refer to some letters written by the <lb/>
Secretary of Sate for Canada in <lb/>
1869, Mr. Joseph Howe. They would <lb/>
be found in the special report of the <lb/>
correspondence in regard to the North-<lb break="yes"/>West printed by order of parliament <lb/>
in 1870. hey would there find corrob<lb break="no"/>oration of the position he had taken. <lb/>
Now with regard to the constitutional <lb/>
side of the resolution, he need say but <lb/>
very little. The constitution of the <lb/>
provinces was fixed by the British <lb/>
North America Act, and following that <lb/>
and he analogy that existed, they <lb/>

<cb/>

might confidently expect that when <lb/>
the province or provinces were made, <lb/>
they would be accorded the same con<lb break="no"/>stitution. The most important side <lb/>
of the question here was, what means <lb/>
would be given to carry on the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment? Naturally in considering that <lb/>
question they looked to the other pro<lb break="no"/>vinces so that the inhabitants of this <lb/>
portion of the Dominion might fairly <lb/>
claim that when the question of finan<lb break="no"/>cial assistance was considered, that <lb/>
that financial assistance would bear <lb/>
analogy and due proportion to that <lb/>
of the provinces. He could see no <lb/>
difference between these parts of the <lb/>
Dominion and any other portion. <lb/>
When people came to the North-West <lb/>
they did not lose any portion of their <lb/>
birthright: did not come here to be <lb/>
treated in an entirely different way to <lb/>
their fellow citizens. In accordance with <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">EVERY FEELING OF JUSTICE <lb/></p> 

<p>and right, when they got the insti<lb break="no"/>tutions similar financial assitance <lb/>
should be given to carry on those in<lb break="no"/>stitutions. Now, the first item given <lb/>
was for the support of the goernment, <lb/>
and the amounts were: Ontario, $80,<lb break="no"/>000: Quebec, $70,000: Nova Scotia, <lb/>
$60,000: New Brunswick, $50,000: Brit<lb break="no"/>ish Columbia, $35,000. The amounts <lb/>
therefore were not fixed. This of it<lb break="no"/>self was an ample justification for the <lb/>
enquiry and negotiation asked for by <lb/>
the resolution. Were the Territories <lb/>
to get the maximum $80,000 or the <lb/>
minimum $35,000? In many portions <lb/>
of the Dominion work was done by <lb/>
municipal government, but here that <lb/>
was not so. The Government did the <lb/>
work, and in any grant to the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories that should be taken into con<lb break="no"/>sideration. There were reasons for a <lb/>
liberal allowance on this very particu<lb break="no"/>lar subject. Then there was a large <lb/>
area and a sparse population. These <lb/>
were reasons why they should have a <lb/>
large allowance. Then there was the <lb/>
per capita grant of 80 cents on the popu<lb break="no"/>lation. This allowance was given the <lb/>
other provinces in the language of the <lb/>
British North America Act, for local <lb/>
purposes, and as a matter of fact it <lb/>
was given under the Quebec resolutions, <lb/>
and several reasons were advanced in <lb/>
the confederation debates, one of which <lb/>
was that it was for the giving up to <lb/>
the Federal Government the provin<lb break="no"/>cial taxing powers, customs, duties, etc. <lb/>
Now, this question opened up several <lb/>
controversial sides, and that also suffi<lb break="no"/>ciently justified that an enquiry be <lb/>
made and accounts taken. The basis <lb/>
of the tax was population and in Man<lb break="no"/>itoba the arrangement was to be re<lb break="no"/>adjusted to population at certain fixed <lb/>
periods. This arrangement was to <lb/>
last until the population reached 400,<lb break="no"/>000. This limit of 400,000 was fixed as <lb/>
the basis upon which this suets should <lb/>
be paid. He had never been able to <lb/>
understand why such a limit should <lb/>
be imposed. Why, if within the next <lb/>
four or five years the 400,000 were ex<lb break="no"/>ceeded, they should not be paid suets, a <lb/>
head, he could not understand. That <lb/>
was another reason why enquiry <lb/>
should be made. The population in <lb/>
the east was uniform, but it was not <lb/>
so in the west. There had been a con<lb break="no"/>stant change in the proportions. He <lb/>
could give figures to show this but it <lb/>
was not necessary, as while the older <lb/>
provinces had been stationary, New <lb/>
Brunswick, for instance, in the west <lb/>
they had been increasing by leaps and <lb/>
bounds. Manitoba increased in a few <lb/>
years 240 per cent,. and in a few years <lb/>
the Territories would do the same. <lb/>
Thus there would be a very large ques<lb break="no"/>tion to be settled. What should be <lb/>
the basis of their per capita grant? <lb/>
Should it be on a revision as in Mani<lb break="no"/>toba, every two and a half years, and <lb/>
with a limit of 400,000 or should they <lb/>
not receive in proportion to their pop<lb break="no"/>ulation whatever it might be. These <lb/>
were open questions and justified the <lb/>
resolution that enquiry should be made <lb/>
and accounts be taken. He now came to <lb/>
the next important subject: <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE QUESTION OF DEBT.</p> 

<p>On this important matter he recom<lb break="no"/>mended hon. gentlemen to read <lb/>
Hon. Alexander Galt's speeches during <lb/>
the confederation debates. Mr. Galt <lb/>
was minister of finance at the time, <lb/>
and was one of the most eminent finan<lb break="no"/>ciers they ever had in Canada and <lb/>
one of the fathers of confederation. <lb/>
The principle proceeded upon was that <lb/>
as the Dominion assumed the debts of <lb/>
the provinces that first entered con<lb break="no"/>federation, then those that entered at <lb/>
a subsequent date would be entitled to <lb/>
a certain amount of rebate. Mr. Haul<lb break="no"/>tain also referred to the Quebec resolu<lb break="no"/>tions and the British North America <lb/>
Act on the subject, and strongly re<lb break="no"/>commended hon. members to study <lb/>
the sources he had indicated. As to <lb/>
Manitoba, when it was created a pro<lb break="no"/>vince, she was given a certain rebate <lb/>
for the debts that had been incurred <lb/>
by the other provinces and assumed <lb/>
by the Dominion at confederation, but <lb/>
before Manitoba entered. He suppos<lb break="no"/>ed that as they were taken into union <lb/>
at the same date as Manitoba 1870, <lb/>
they would be dealt with on the same <lb/>
basis. Then the question arose as <lb/>
to whether they should have <lb/>
the five years census and <lb/>
two and a half years readjustment as <lb/>
they had in Manitoba. There seemed <lb/>
to have been a faulty opinion as to the <lb/>
debt charged against this country. He <lb/>
had a document from the Department <lb/>
of the Interior which showed that $3,<lb break="no"/>800,000 were already charged up against <lb/>
the Territories, and it included quite a <lb/>
number of curious items. Thus there <lb/>
was $19,000 for the construction of Fort <lb/>
Garry road and Fort William road. <lb/>
That was an item charge to the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories for the benefit of the people of <lb/>
this country. Then there was $8,000 <lb/>
more for the same road: $15,000 for a <lb/>
canal in Manitoba: $27,000 for boats: <lb/>
$!63,000 for exploring the Red river: <lb/>
$10,100 for Red river rebellion: several <lb/>
other items such as $84,000 and $23,000 <lb/>
for Fort Garry road and Fort William <lb/>
road: and $45,000 for boats. These <lb/>
were only a few of such items that <lb/>
went to make up the $3,800,000 already <lb/>
charged up against the Territories. He <lb/>
thought that this justified the fullest <lb/>
enquiry and the taking of accounts as <lb/>
asked by the Territories. It was a <lb/>

<cb/>

wonder, it seemed to him, that they <lb/>
had not charged up against the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories the wars of 1812-13(cheers), which <lb/>
would be as appropriate. Everything <lb/>
that could was being charged up <lb/>
against the diminishing area of the <lb/>
North-West Territories. He now came to <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE RAILWAY DEBT.</p> 

<p>This was a most important side of <lb/>
the discussion. In the year 1898 the <lb/>
expenditure on railroads in the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion had reached $160,623,557. There <lb/>
was an expenditure for lines wholly <lb/>
within the provinces of $48,380,848. <lb/>
Now, he supposed it would be per<lb break="no"/>fectly reasonable for the representa<lb break="no"/>tives of the Territories to say "We <lb/>
should be allowed something in respect <lb/>
of that." The Dominion had done <lb/>
these works which were local in their <lb/>
nature: the $48,380,848 was for purely <lb/>
local lines in the provinces. Now, <lb/>
these formed part of the federal debt. <lb/>
Towards this debt the people of the <lb/>
North-West Territories contributed <lb/>
their share, man for man, with the <lb/>
rest of the Dominion, as much as any <lb/>
body else. And now note this also. <lb/>
Quite a different policy had been <lb/>
followed as regarded the railways in <lb/>
the Territories. Instead of subsidising <lb/>
them, except $3,000,000 in the case of <lb/>
the Crow's Nest which was very largely <lb/>
constructed in British Columbia, little <lb/>
over 100 miles in the Territories and <lb/>
the whole Dominion bearing its share, <lb/>
as in the others, instead of subsi<lb break="no"/>dising them, the Dominion took <lb/>
39,300,000 acres of land in the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories in Manitoba and gave them to <lb/>
the railways. Look for a moment at <lb/>
the difference. In the provvinces the <lb/>
Dominion shoulders the whole of the <lb/>
$48,380,848, and the Territories were <lb/>
helping pay for it: but for the lines in <lb/>
Territories they gave the lands of the <lb/>
Territories and no burden rested upon <lb/>
the people of the provinces. It was <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">MANIFEST INJUSTICE</p> 

<p>and unfairness. If they had to pay <lb/>
their share of the railway debt in other <lb/>
provinces, why should they not have a <lb/>
certain allowance made in lieu of that <lb/>
debt and of their lands taken away. <lb/>
Surely that was sufficient to justify the <lb/>
fullest enquiry and the taking of ac<lb break="no"/>counts. (Cheers.) Mr. Haultain then <lb/>
dealt with the mineral royalties and <lb/>
quoted Sir John. A. Macdonald, and <lb/>
Hon. A. Galt to show that each pro<lb break="no"/>vince ought to have the power of <lb/>
developing its own resources: and hon. <lb/>
Geo. Brown in regard to the lands. <lb/>
This, said Mr. Maultain was the most <lb/>
important side of <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE CONFEDERATION COMPACT.</p> 

<p>There would have never been any <lb/>
Dominion of Canada if there had been <lb/>
the giving up of the mines to the <lb/>
federal government. The principle of <lb/>
the claim to the lands was admitted. <lb/>
Every one of the older provinces had <lb/>
their lands, and Manitoba had a pay<lb break="no"/>ment in lieu of them. One of the <lb/>
reasons the C.P.R. was constructed <lb/>
was because of a pledge given to Brit<lb break="no"/>ish Columbia. There was not a line <lb/>
within that province, and it agreed to <lb/>
give a certain amount of its land for <lb/>
the construction of the C.P.R. For <lb/>
that reason and on that account the <lb/>
Dominion paid British Columbia $100<lb break="no"/>000 a year, which the people of the <lb/>
North-West Territories helped to pay: <lb/>
for that rocky belt along which the <lb/>
line ran. In the case of the Territories <lb/>
the whole land grant was simply made, <lb/>
and the claim was that the federal <lb/></p> 

<cb/>

<p>authorities own this country, and <lb/>
dealt with it for Dominion purposes. <lb/>
The question arose why should not <lb/>
the Territories be granted a portion of <lb/>
these lines? Why should any distinc<lb break="no"/>tion he made between the Territories <lb/>
and the provinces? It was claimed <lb/>
the Dominion had purchased the lands <lb/>
from the Hudson's Bay Company, and <lb/>
for the benefit of the whole Dominion. <lb/>
Well, when the Dominion got the <lb/>
Hudson's Bay lands, it got all of them. <lb/>
A portion now formed a part of the <lb/>
province of Quebec: another portion <lb/>
a part of the province of Ontario. The <lb/>
lands in the east being part of the <lb/>
bargain were also for the benefit of <lb/>
the whole of the Dominion, of which <lb/>
the Territories were entitled to <lb/>
be considered. The Dominion claimed <lb/>
"We bought you." Well, at any rate <lb/>
if that be so, the Territories were pay<lb break="no"/>ing their share of the money, and if <lb/>
there was anything in the "we bought <lb/>
you" doctorine, it was hardly fair to <lb/>
make the North-West pay a portion of <lb/>
the purchase money, and portion of <lb/>
the interest upon it. <lb/></p> 

<p>It being now 5:30 the House adjourn<lb break="no"/>ed until evening. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">EVENING SESSION.</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> resumed his speech at <lb/>
eight o'clock. He said that when they <lb/>
left the House that afternoon he was <lb/>
discussing the important part that <lb/>
public domains, lands, mineral, and <lb/>
what an important item they were at <lb/>
that period of the discussion. And <lb/>

<cb/>

particularly what a very essential part <lb/>
of the provincial revenue those lands <lb/>
were, and what an important part they <lb/>
would be in any negotiations for es<lb break="no"/>tablishing a future province or pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. He also pointed out that the <lb/>
British North America Act recognized <lb/>
what an important part it was, and in <lb/>
the negotitations subsequently this <lb/>
principle was recognized: in the case <lb/>
of Prince Edward Island, there was no <lb/>
grant to them because they did not <lb/>
have any public lands: in Manitoba <lb/>
because the lands had been withdrawn <lb/>
from them they received a grant in <lb/>
lieu; in British Columbia a strip of <lb/>
land belonging to them was given to <lb/>
the C.P.R., and provinces was re<lb break="no"/>compensed by an annuity of $100,000, <lb/>
which the Territories were help<lb break="no"/>ing to pay. He then began to discuss <lb/>
what the Dominion's claims to the <lb/>
Territorial lands were. he had con<lb break="no"/>tinued the argument to that point only, <lb/>
as it would loom up large when the <lb/>
establishment of public institutions <lb/>
was coming on. At present, however, <lb/>
the more practical side, the necessity <lb/>
of change on practical lines, the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of their financial position, was <lb/>
what they had to consider. The Am<lb break="no"/>erican precedent had been quoted by <lb/>
the Dominion Government to show <lb/>
it owned the land, because, when defi<lb break="no"/>nite terms were accorded to Manitoba, <lb/>
and presumably it would be the same <lb/>
in the west when the time came, they <lb/>
were able to show why the lands should <lb/>
be withdrawn. The American pre<lb break="no"/>cedent was the holding of the lands of [...]<lb/></p>

</div></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>