<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgASLA_1898-09-13" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>,
<date when="1898-09-13">13 September 1898</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA"> <editor>Walter Scott</editor>.
<title>The Leader</title>.
<date when="1898-09-15"/>,
<date when="1898-09-29"/>,
<date when="1898-10-06"/>.
<pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="5"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="9" to="11"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1898-09-15_Page_001.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1898-09-15_Page_005.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1898-09-29_Page_009.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1898-09-29_Page_010.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1898-09-29_Page_011.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1898-10-06_Page_001.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-23">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="lyallg" when="2018-10-19">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1898-09-15_Page_001"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-15_Page_001.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1898-09-15_Page_005"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-15_Page_005.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1898-09-29_Page_009"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-29_Page_009.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1898-09-29_Page_010"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-29_Page_010.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1898-09-29_Page_011"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-29_Page_011.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1898-10-06_Page_001"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1898-10-06_Page_001.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="001" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-15_Page_001.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">THE LEADER</fw> 
 
 
 <fw type="running">REGINA, N.W.T., THURSDAY EVENING SEPTEMBER 15, 1898.</fw> 
 <fw type="num">1</fw>
 
 
 <head rendition="simple:centre">YEAR OF FINANCIAL JUBILEE.</head> <head rendition="simple:centre">The Territories Have a Greatly Increased Revenue <lb/>
for 1898.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">Details of the Supplementary Estimates-Brief Summary <lb/>
of Mr. Haultain's Budget Statement, and an Indication <lb/>
of the Trend of the Debate—There is Need for all of the <lb/>
Increased Revenue, and the Future, When Only the <lb/>
Ordinary Revenue Can be Expected, is a Subject for <lb/>
Serious Consideration. <lb/></p> 
 
 
 <p rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, Sept. 13, 1898.</p> 

<p>[...]</p> 

<p>When the sitting was resumed at 2:30 <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> took up the Yukon question,­ <lb/>
making an extended statement of <lb/>
the Territorial position and the course of <lb/>
the Government in its relation. A new <lb/>
point brought out was that under the <lb/>
Act the Assembly is not empowered to <lb/>
frame regulations or pass Ordinances <lb/>
respecting the liquor permits. The duty <lb/>
devolves upon the Lt.-Governor, which <lb/>
means the Lt.-Governor by and with the <lb/>
advice of the Executive Council. Mr. <lb/>
Haultain combatted the contention that <lb/>
the permit clauses of the Act could <lb/>
absolutely or reasonably be held to con<lb break="no"/>template a prohibitive system. As to <lb/>
the satisfactory financial results of the <lb/>
Government's policy there could be no <lb/>
question. From that point of view there <lb/>
could be just as little question of the <lb/>
success of the expedition sent out. Apart <lb/>
altogether from the receipts from whole­ <lb/>
sale permits, amounting to $122,000, the <lb/>
expedition itself had resulted in the col. <lb/>
lection of $28,000 for retailing permits at <lb/>
Dawson. After explaining items relating <lb/>
to the Imperial Institute and the ex<lb break="no"/>penses of entertainment of certain press<lb break="no"/>men visiting the Territories, Mr. Haul<lb break="no"/>tain explained an additional estimate of <lb/>
$60,000 asked to cover the carrying on of <lb/>
the public business after the beginning of <lb/>
the new year until such time as the new <lb/>
House should meet. Of this amount <lb/>
$40,000 would go in January in school <lb/>
grants, and the balance remaining was <lb/>
only $20,000 to sustain the public service <lb/>
to probably some date in February. In <lb/>
this estimate they were following the <lb/>
practice adopted in the provinces. Hav<lb break="no"/>ing completed his explanations of the esti<lb break="no"/>mates, Mr. Haultain proceeded to say <lb/>
that a very significant feature in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with the extraordinary amount of <lb/>
these supplementaries was the fact that <lb/>
the need of them appeared without going <lb/>
outside of the fyles of the offices. There <lb/>
were few new departures, and the needs <lb/>
of the old and ordinary services were no <lb/>
more than met by the extraordinary and <lb/>
unusual increase in the revenue amounting <lb/>
to about $162,000. The only conclusion <lb/>
was that ordinary revenue was now total<lb break="no"/>ly inadequate; and in face of the fact that <lb/>
they could not with any reasonable ex<lb break="no"/>pectation look to Parliament to increase <lb/>
the grant to the extent of this year's <lb/>
increases from other sources, the question <lb/>
arose, What were they to do? The <lb/>
needs would not grow less. They were <lb/>
brought to the point which he had dis<lb break="no"/>cussed last year. Our present state was <lb/>
in many ways very suitable to our con<lb break="no"/>ditions,—was suitable in every way ex<lb break="no"/>cept that it did not yield enough money. <lb/>
If the financial question was capable of <lb/>
other solution he would be satisfied to <lb/>
remain as at present. The only thing <lb/>
there seemed to be to do was to think at <lb/>
least of negotiating for provincial <lb/>
establishment. He felt convinced that <lb/>
it would be the principal work of the <lb/>
new Legislature before the end of its <lb/>
four year's term to enter into such <lb/>
negotiations. With the greater develop <lb/>
ment that now seems assured the needs <lb/>
in respect of schools and improvements <lb/>
would certainly develop. Qutside of <lb/>
direct taxation there seemed no possi<lb break="no"/>bility of a solution except by provincial <lb/>
establishment—not perhaps to-day or <lb/>
next year, but in the reasonably near <lb/>
future. Mr. Haultain pointed out <lb/>
some of the expenditures now made <lb/>
by the Dominion which when we become <lb/>
a province will have to be borne locally, <lb/>
by way of emphasizing the fact that the <lb/>
negotiations would not be one-sided. <lb/>
Nevertheless he had no deubt that under <lb/>
any reasonable terms of settlement the <lb/>
subsidy received would be greater than <lb/>
the grant now voted by Parliament. He <lb/>
indicated that this Government would <lb/>
demand the cession to the Territories of all <lb/>
lands, minerals, etc., as have the original <lb/>
rovinces - entering Confederation, and <lb/>
would base the claim upon a legal and <lb/>
constitutional right, —a right which he <lb/>
inferred might be prosecuted before the <lb/>
highest tribunal in the realm if necessary. <lb/>
Be indicated also his firm belief that when <lb/>
the time for erection came there should <lb/>
be only one province erected. Mr. Haul<lb break="no"/>tain then referred to the charge that the <lb/>
Government had no policy. He thought <lb/>
there was no lack of policy even in the <lb/>
Supplementary Estimates. It seemed <lb/>
to him that in every item there cropped <lb/>
 
 <cb/>
 
 
 up a policy distinct and well defined. <lb/>
They had a policy in respect of civil gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, the development of the public <lb/>
 service, well organized and efficient de<lb break="no"/>partments, practical and economical ma<lb break="no"/>chinery. There was a policy connected <lb/>
with the Normal school item—connected <lb/>
with their School policy, to give to every <lb/>
child a good, plain, practical education—,  <lb/>
to give it to all children associated to­ <lb/>
gether without regard to race, religion or <lb/>
position. He thought their school policy <lb/>
had been attended with remarkable suc<lb break="no"/>cess, in that the animosities arising from <lb/>
certain difficult and delicate questions in <lb/>
other portions of Canada had be avoided <lb/>
here without any less practical or satisfac<lb break="no"/>tory results. To-day the Territorial school <lb/>
system was, if not in name, in reality a <lb/>
National school system. They had a <lb/>
policy for the training of teachers, which <lb/>
had already resulted so well that the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories are practically independent as re­ <lb/>
garded the supply of teachers, with the <lb/>
supply of higher grade teachers exceeding <lb/>
the demand. They had a policy in re<lb break="no"/>spect of coal mines, to look after the <lb/>
protection of lives and meet the necessi<lb break="no"/>ties of actual conditions,—a distinct and <lb/>
plain policy in respect of public works,— <lb/>
opening main highways, dealing with sur-  <lb/>
veys, making bridges, testing for water,  <lb/>
etc., etc.;-a policy, new, it was true,  <lb/>
and small as yet, respecting agriculture,  <lb/>
 in keeping with the traditions of the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, beginning moderately and devel<lb break="no"/>oping along with conditions, a policy pro<lb break="no"/>portionate to the resources, a policy calcu<lb break="no"/>lated to encourage the chief and most im<lb break="no"/>portant industries, the foundation of all  <lb/>
possible prosperity in the Territories.  <lb/>
They had a policy regarding hospitals and  <lb/>
charities, a policy to give all possible aid  <lb/>
to those most desirable, admirable and  <lb/>
beneficent institutions, and a policy to  <lb/>
 avoid the greation of those other institu<lb break="no"/>tions which are features, and necessarily  <lb/>
so, of all older countries, but which are  <lb/>
 not yet necessary with the comparative<lb break="no"/>ly young and able-bodied population of  <lb/>
the west, and the erection of which might  <lb/>
tend as an invitation to those unfortunate  <lb/>
helpless classes who are fortunately not  <lb/>
 yet found here in any considerable num<lb break="no"/>bers. They had had a decided and suc<lb break="no"/>cessful policy in relation to the Yukon.  <lb/>
They had grappled with the difficulties of  <lb/>
that situation which to judge from some  <lb/>
of the criticisms were very dangerous.  <lb/>
For policy he could further point to the  <lb/>
statutes. Every page of the statutes bore  <lb/>
evidence of what had been and was the  <lb/>
policy of the Government and no less of  <lb/>
the Assembly. They had a policy on the  <lb/>
 question of introducing Dominion politi<lb break="no"/>cal lines, clear and distinct as was all  <lb/>
other portions of their general policy.  <lb/>
The only suggestion of deficiency that any  <lb/>
of the critics had ever attempted to make  <lb/>
 was in regard to immigration. The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment's policy as regarded immigration  <lb/>
had not in view the fitting out of  <lb/>
agents to scour the by-ways and compel<lb/>
people to come to the Territories. If  <lb/>
they wished to do so, they could not, as <lb/>
 among the powers allotted to the Assem<lb break="no"/>bly the power of dealing with immigra<lb break="no"/>tion was not included. But they had a  <lb/>
solid policy, which was to try and meet  <lb/>
the needs of the people who are here and  <lb/>
who are coming, to supply good roads and  <lb/>
necessary bridges, schools; by providing  <lb/>
economical yet thoroughly efficient admin  <lb/>
istration of all the laws. They passed laws  <lb/>
not because like laws had been passed in  <lb/>
Ontario or anywhere else, but to suit the  <lb/>
 peculiar and particular needs of the con<lb break="no"/>ditions here and the circumstances of the  <lb/>
country. He believed that was the best  <lb/>
immigration policy for this Assembly to  <lb/>
follow, to make this a desirable country  <lb/>
to come to, a country with harmonious  <lb/>
communities, a satisfactory state of so-  <lb/>
ciety, good roads and safe bridges, effi<lb break="no"/>cient schools, good institutions of all  <lb/>
necessary kinds, and a country free from  <lb/>
debt and practically free from taxation.  <lb/>
That was as good an immigration policy  <lb/>
 as could be devised, considering the re<lb break="no"/>sources of this Assembly, for years to  <lb/>
come. He hoped that the Estimates  <lb/>
would meet the approval of the House and  <lb/>
if passed meet the idea of helping out all  <lb/>
interests and maintain adequately the  <lb/>
 public service of the Territories. (Pro<lb break="no"/>longed applause.)  <lb/></p>

<pb n="005" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-15_Page_005.hocr.html"/> <lb/>


 
 <fw type="running">REGINA, N.W.T., THURSDAY EVENING, SEPTEMBER 15, 1898.</fw>
 
 <fw type="num">5</fw>

<div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">QUESTION OF BOUNDARIES.</head> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PATR1">Dr. Patrick</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:PAGE3">Mr. Page</persName>, <lb/>
moved: Whereas it is expedient that <lb/>
the boundary lines between the North<lb break="no"/>West Territories and the other provinces <lb/>
and territories should be finally deter<lb break="no"/>mined at an early date; and whereas <lb/>
this Legislature denies the right of the <lb/>
Parliament of Canada to increase or di<lb break="no"/>minish or otherwise alter the limits of <lb/>
the North-West Territories, without its <lb/>
consent, because it claims for the people <lb/>
it represents equal rights with the people <lb/>
of the Provinces in this respect; and <lb/>
whereas, certain areas now comprised <lb/>
within the North-West Territories more <lb/>
properly belong to other Provinces or <lb/>
Territories, and should therefore be se<lb break="no"/>parated from the North-West Territories; <lb/>
therefore be it resolved that this Legis<lb break="no"/>lature doth consent to such alteration of <lb/>
the limits of the North-West Territories <lb/>
as will separate therefrom those areas <lb/>
lying north of the northern boundaries <lb/>
of the Provinces of British Columbia and <lb/>
Manitoba respectively. <lb/></p> 

 <p><persName ref="pers:PATR1">Dr. Patrick</persName> said the resolution was <lb/>
not designed to deal with the internal <lb/>
but with the external relations of the <lb/>
Territories—not with the relations of one <lb/>
part of the Territories with the other <lb/>
parts, but with our relations as affecting <lb/>
the province to the east and the province <lb/>
to the west. The resolution was not in<lb break="no"/>tended to bear at all upon the right of <lb/>
Parliament to establish a province or pro<lb break="no"/>vinces in the Territories. By Section <lb/>
2 of the B.N.A. Act Parliament's power <lb/>
and right to erect a province or provinces <lb/>
were clear and distinct. Neither was the <lb/>
resolution directed in any sense to the <lb/>
action of Parliament in separating the <lb/>
Yukon territory from the North-West <lb/>
Territories. But the question of the right <lb/>
of Parliament to place a part of an ex<lb break="no"/>isting province or territory into another <lb/>
province was another thing. The resolu<lb break="no"/>tion was declaratory of the expediency <lb/>
of determining the boundaries of the <lb/>
North-West Territories for certain rea<lb break="no"/>sons. Dr. Patrick referred to a resolution <lb/>
passed by the Assembly in 1897 respect<lb break="no"/>ing what was termed the integrity of the <lb/>
Territories. At that time the Assembly <lb/>
perhaps lost sight of the fact that there <lb/>
were portions of the Territories which <lb/>
were north of the provinces of Manitoba <lb/>
and British Columbia, and which more <lb/>
properly and reasonably belonged to and <lb/>
could be governed by the governments of <lb/>
those provinces. In 1876 and again in <lb/>
1881 Manitoba had made claim for the <lb/>
territory lying north of that province. It <lb/>
was perhaps scarcely right for the As<lb break="no"/>sembly to lay claim to all that territory <lb/>
without admitting the right of Manitoba <lb/>
to the portion lying on its north. If the <lb/>
right of the North-West to its hinterland <lb/>
was just, then Manitoba and British <lb/>
Columbia could reasonably lay claim to the <lb/>
portions of territory which were north of <lb/>
those respective provinces. The claim <lb/>
made by the Assembly last year would <lb/>
stand in the way of Manitoba's just claim. <lb/>
It would seem to be perfectly reasonable <lb/>
for Manitoba to claim the territory north <lb/>
of its present bounds. The province is aid<lb break="no"/>ing a railway towards Hudson's Bay, which <lb/>
will extend into the territory north of the <lb/>
province. Along that railway there would <lb/>
be settlement, and before settlement <lb/>
takes place it would be well that the peo<lb break="no"/>ple going in should know to what pro<lb break="no"/>vince they were going to belong. It <lb/>
therefore seemed expedient that the <lb/>
boundaries should be determined at an <lb/>
early date. Then came the question, who <lb/>
has the right to determine the boundaries? <lb/>
The precedent of the former Manitoba ex<lb break="no"/>tension would be cited, and it might be <lb/>
held that what was done once could well <lb/>
be done again. By a statement made at <lb/>
this session by the Commissioner of Public <lb/>
Works (Mr. Ross) it would appear that <lb/>
the Dominion Government is under the <lb/>
impression that the Territories may be <lb/>
chopped and carved by order in council. <lb/>
They had proposed to secure power from <lb/>
Parliament to separate portions of the <lb/>
Territories from time to time by order in <lb/>
council. A general impression was <lb/>
abroad that the country was threatened <lb/>
with division. He found that one only <lb/>
needed to scratch an ordinary Manitoban <lb/>
to find a Territorial annexationist, and <lb/>
believed that some Manitobans had a <lb/>
somewhat definite idea that all the terri<lb break="no"/>tory lying east of a line as far west as <lb/>
Moose Jaw should be added to Manitoba. <lb/>
Dr. Patrick then proceeded to discuss the <lb/>
clause in the Confederation Act deal<lb break="no"/>ing with the power of Parliament to "al<lb break="no"/>ter, diminish or extend" provinces. His <lb/>
conclusion as to the meaning of the sec<lb break="no"/>tion was that it was intended that the <lb/>
power should only be exercised upon, by <lb/>
and with the agreement and consent of <lb/>
the people of the provinces affected. A <lb/>
further conclusion was that the section <lb/>
was only intended to be operated in re<lb break="no"/>lation to provinces, —that was to say, the <lb/>
section could be given practical operation <lb/>
if all the territory of the Dominion was <lb/>
erected into provinces, and then changes <lb/>
could only be brought about with the <lb/>
mutual consent of all parties interested. <lb/>
He said it certainly was never the inten<lb break="no"/>tion that one local government should <lb/>
have its jurisdiction extended over <lb/>
the people outside its domain <lb/>
without the consent of those <lb/>
people. The N.W.T. had had a legisla<lb break="no"/>ture, in many respects provincial in char<lb break="no"/>acter, for many years. This year the <lb/>
fourth Assembly would be elected. The <lb/>
powers conferred upon the Assembly were <lb/>
conferred by Parliament, but because <lb/>
Parliament had the power to confer it did <lb/>
not follow that it had a right to withdraw. <lb/>
The powers possessed by Parliament were <lb/>
conferred by the Imperial Legislature. <lb/>
It was doubtless true that the Imperial <lb/>
Legislature could revoke the powers con<lb break="no"/>ferred upon Parliament, but did any one <lb/>
think the Imperial authorities could make <lb/>
practical use of their power of revokation? <lb/>
He would draw sharp distinction between <lb/>
the terms "power" and "right." The <lb/>
wretch who murdered the Empress of <lb/>
Austria proved his power to kill, but did <lb/>
that prove his right to take life? He <lb/>
would deny the right of Parliament to <lb/>
sharpen its stiletto to cut and carve the <lb/>
body politic of the Territories. (Ap<lb break="no"/>plause.) Once the people of England had <lb/>
believed that the Briton abroad had les<lb break="no"/>ser rights than the Briton at home, and <lb/>
history records the incident of the Boston <lb/>
tea party, and the encounter at Bunker <lb/>
Hill where Greek met Greek and the in<lb break="no"/>feriority failed to be established. There <lb/>
had been once a legislature in Ireland, <lb/>
with sovereignty quite as limited as that <lb/>
of this Assembly relatively; and while he <lb/>
would not go into the ways and means by <lb/>
which the consent was obtained, he would <lb/>
point to the fact that the existence of that <lb/>
Irish legislature did not end until its own <lb/>
consent was obtained, which showed that <lb/>
its consent was necessary to the ending of <lb/>
it. This House for instance has conferred <lb/>
powers upon the City of Calgary. Would <lb/>
anyone contend that after consenting to <lb/>
and in a way assisting in the establish<lb break="no"/>ment of the institutions of the City of <lb/>
Calgary, this House has the right to re<lb break="no"/>voke the powers conferred, without cause, <lb/>
reason or consent? The main principle <lb/>
of the preamble of the B.N.A. Act was <lb/>
based upon consent—those provinces <lb/>
which consented were included in con<lb break="no"/>
 
 <cb/>
 


federation, while the provinces which <lb/>
failed to consent were not included. In <lb/>
that Act it was cited that upon the Do<lb break="no"/>minion was conferred a constitution simi<lb break="no"/>lar in principle to the British constitution. <lb/>
The practice of the Imperial Parliament <lb/>
in respect of the alteration of the bounds <lb/>
of self-governing or Crown colonies was, <lb/>
to be guided by the desires of the colonies. <lb/>
By an Act passed in 1895 the consent of <lb/>
the people of the colonies is necessary to <lb/>
any alteration of bounds. Canada has <lb/>
a constitution similar to the British, and <lb/>
the measure meted by the Imperial legis<lb break="no"/>lature to Parliament should be meted by <lb/>
Parliament to this Assembly; if less was <lb/>
meted a grievance would be created <lb/>
which the people of the Territories would <lb/>
have a right to lay at the foot of the <lb/>
Throne. But it was not necessary to go <lb/>
far afield for precedents. Such could be <lb/>
found in Canadian history. When Can<lb break="no"/>ada purchased the right of the Hudson's <lb/>
Bay Company, it was forgotten that the <lb/>
inhabitants of the territory were entitled <lb/>
to a voice in their disposition and it was a <lb/>
historical fact that one Wandering <lb/>
Willie Macdougall was sent out to govern <lb/>
those inhabitants but was not allowed to <lb/>
come in and govern. He was not going <lb/>
to applaud the acts of the people who <lb/>
resisted authority but the fact was record<lb break="no"/>ed that an envoy extraordinary was sent <lb/>
from Ottawa to consult the wishes of the <lb/>
inhabitants, —sent out with full discre<lb break="no"/>tionary powers to treat with them. And <lb/>
delegates selected by the self constituted <lb/>
council of those inhabitants were invited <lb/>
to go to Ottawa, whose views were ac<lb break="no"/>cepted and embodied in the Manitoba Act <lb/>
of 1871. At a later date—in 1881—when <lb/>
the Manitoba boundaries were extended, <lb/>
the extension was made with the desire <lb/>
not only of the people of the province but <lb/>
also of the people who were taken into <lb/>
the province, as the words of Sir John <lb/>
Macdonald when the extension was dis<lb break="no"/>cussed in Parliament show. Proceeding, <lb/>
Dr. Patrick held that the people of the <lb/>
Territories have certain acquired rights. <lb/>
When men settled in the Territories they <lb/>
cannot be presumed to have expected that <lb/>
they might be later on made to bear the <lb/>
yoke and the debt of Manitoba —to assume <lb/>
the burden of the mistakes made by a <lb/>
legislature in which they had no repre<lb break="no"/>sentation. Territorial citizens have in<lb break="no"/>herently all the rights of the citizens of <lb/>
the provinces of Canada and of British <lb/>
subjects. A man coming here from one <lb/>
of the provinces forfeits no right by com<lb break="no"/>ing, although in the Territories he con<lb break="no"/>sents that certain of his rights shall be <lb/>
held in abeyance. There was every <lb/>
ground to deny the right of Parliament <lb/>
to alter the boundaries so far as related <lb/>
to any other province without obtaining <lb/>
the consent of the people of the Territor<lb break="no"/>ies. This statement did not affect the <lb/>
right of Parliament to erect a province or <lb/>
provinces in the Territories. The doctor <lb/>
prophesied that the next few years of the <lb/>
Assembly would be history making years. <lb/>
In considering the question they should <lb/>
keep in sight the fact that there was a <lb/>
court of final resort, and they might ex<lb break="no"/>pect that the spirit of the British consti<lb break="no"/>tution would be observed. In taking a <lb/>
stand for fairness, they should be prepar<lb break="no"/>ed to deal fairly. He thought it would <lb/>
be impolitic to claim all the present terri<lb break="no"/>tory; to do so would give a handle against <lb/>
them. They should claim no more than <lb/>
they had a good moral claim to. By <lb/>
claiming only their rights they would <lb/>
strengthen their position. By exercising <lb/>
their right to consent to a certain dimin<lb break="no"/>ution, their position would be made <lb/>
stronger. He was confident that the <lb/>
House would pass the motion in favor of <lb/>
the final determining of our relations, not <lb/>
with each other, but with those on each <lb/>
side of us. (Applause.) <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PAGE3">Mr. Page</persName> spoke from the immediately <lb/>
practical point of view of the people of <lb/>
the Territories who reside near Manitoba. <lb/>
He knew that many people were deliber<lb break="no"/>ately moving from Manitoba into the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, rather than to the newer portions <lb/>
of the province such as Dauphin, for the <lb/>
express purpose of escaping the burden <lb/>
of taxation imposed in that province, and <lb/>
to take advantage of the simpler and <lb/>
cheaper government in the Territories. <lb/>
He referred to imperial treatment of col<lb break="no"/>onists. The people in the African hinter<lb break="no"/>land were being allowed to make their <lb/>
own arrangements and bargains. The <lb/>
same remark applied to Australia. The <lb/>
Dominion ought to leave the people of <lb/>
the Territories to complete their own con<lb break="no"/>solidation. Parliament might well follow <lb/>
the maxim "Do unto others as ye would <lb/>
have them do unto you," and deal with <lb/>
the Assembly of the Territories as the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Parliament dealt with it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:EAKI1">Mr. Eakin</persName> spoke as the representative <lb/>
of a district bordering for a length of 120 <lb/>
miles upon Manitoba. His constituents <lb/>
were therefore interested in the question. <lb/>
He did not wish to refer particularly to <lb/>
Manitoba, but said there did appear to be <lb/>
an impression that because this territory <lb/>
was acquired by purchase by the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion, Parliament had the right to diminish <lb/>
or annex it at pleasure. The resolution <lb/>
of the member for Yorkton was generous. <lb/>
It proposed to give to Manitoba what she <lb/>
had a right to. Mr. Eakin held that the <lb/>
people of East Assiniboia had rights and <lb/>
he would hold firmly to the contention <lb/>
that their consent was necessary in a dis<lb break="no"/>position so vitally affecting them. He <lb/>
was confident, however, that they were <lb/>
not like the people of Red Deer; they <lb/>
were law abiding, and would seek in a <lb/>
constitutional way to have their rights <lb/>
recognised. Mr. Eakin quoted Hon. Mr. <lb/>
Gerard in support of Dr. Patrick's con<lb break="no"/>tention that before the bounds of Mani<lb break="no"/>toba were extended in 1881, the people <lb/>
taken in had expressed a desire to be an<lb break="no"/>nexed. The argument might be used that <lb/>
North-East Assiniboia and Manitoba had <lb/>
identical interests; that their products <lb/>
went east through Manitoba and their <lb/>
supplies came west through Manitoba <lb/>
That was true. Winnipeg, the Manitoba <lb/>
capital, was the gateway and door. But <lb/>
while they were proud of Winnipeg, there <lb/>
were reasons which caused them to hesi<lb break="no"/>tate about throwing in their lot with <lb/>
Manitoba. He thought that when the <lb/>
time came for the Territories to seek en<lb break="no"/>larged powers and a changed constitution, <lb/>
—when that time came it would be early <lb/>
enough to consider the question. He <lb/>
hoped that when it had to be considered, <lb/>
it would be considered as it deserved and <lb/>
that no sectional view would dominate, <lb/>
but that a broad view would be taken to <lb/>
lead to prosperity and development, and <lb/>
for the security and protection of the best <lb/>
interests of the country. For the pre<lb break="no"/>sent at least he was opposed to the idea <lb/>
of annexation. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BROW6">Mr. Brown</persName> looked upon the subject as <lb/>
one of great interest. Parliament's power <lb/>
to carve our territory we admit, but as <lb/>
British subjects we claim the right to be <lb/>
treated as such. He said that the people <lb/>
of the Territories have established a sys<lb break="no"/>tem of government peculiar in Canada; <lb/>
they had followed a course different from <lb/>
the course followed in any of the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. Undoubtedly provincial status <lb/>
could have been obtained years ago, but <lb/>
benefitting by the experience of the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces they had chosen the wiser course <lb/>
of having simple, efficient and inexpensive <lb/>
government. The boundaries might have <lb/>
been settled years ago, but because a diff<lb break="no"/>erent course had been followed was no <lb/>
reason why advantage should now be <lb/>
taken by Parliament to change the bound<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

aries. The root of the question was: <lb/>
Did Manitoba want a portion of our <lb/>
territory for our benefit, or for her own <lb/>
benefit? What Manitoba asks is to get <lb/>
our people to share with her the burden <lb/>
of the mistakes made by her legislature. <lb/>
It is only a few years ago that Manitoba <lb/>
disdained the Territories. The people of <lb/>
the province were wont to say that their <lb/>
bounds enclosed all the good territory in <lb/>
the west. As far as the argument about <lb/>
area was concerned, it could be pointed <lb/>
out that in area Manitoba is already the <lb/>
fourth province in Canada, and probably <lb/>
contained as much fertile land as any of <lb/>
the provinces, excepting the Territories. <lb/>
If the maritime provinces can get along <lb/>
with much less areas, then Manitoba <lb/>
should not be in a bad position. But the <lb/>
matter of taxation was at the bottom of <lb/>
Manitoba's desire to get a portion of the <lb/>
Assiniboias. Manitoba on one side of us <lb/>
has a debt of $5,000,000, and British <lb/>
Columbia on the other side a debt of $12,<lb break="no"/>000,000. Of debt and taxation the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories have none. Our people profited <lb/>
nothing by the expenditures which crea<lb break="no"/>ted Manitoba's burden and should not be <lb/>
legislated into a position of having to <lb/>
share it. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> was sure the members <lb/>
would be glad to hear the unanimous ex<lb break="no"/>pression of opinion on the question. Last <lb/>
year the House was equally unanimous in <lb/>
a protest made against the withdrawal of <lb/>
any portion of the Territories to add to <lb/>
Manitoba. The House had already stated <lb/>
definitely its opinion on the question. <lb/>
Mr. Haultain said he was interested in <lb/>
Dr. Patrick's arguments that afternoon, <lb/>
although he could possibly not go all the <lb/>
length in some of his analogies. The <lb/>
Territories were in a different position <lb/>
from the colonies or Ireland, and as re<lb break="no"/>garded the material point of action, our <lb/>
position in relation to Parliament was <lb/>
entirely different from the relation exist<lb break="no"/>ing between Ireland and the Empire. As <lb/>
had been said we were a colony within a <lb/>
colony, but in the most essential attri<lb break="no"/>butes our relation to Parliament differed <lb/>
from the relation of colonies to the Im<lb break="no"/>perial authority. The Territories were <lb/>
added to the Dominion under a provision <lb/>
in the B. N.A. Act, contemplating the <lb/>
admission of Territories into the union. <lb/>
Subsequently the powers of Parliament <lb/>
in relation to such territory were definite<lb break="no"/>ly fixed. He had heard it argued—and <lb/>
would repeat the argument without giving <lb/>
any opinion of his own—that Parliament <lb/>
did not possess power to add territory to a <lb/>
province,—but Parliament had exercised <lb/>
such power by adding territory to Mani<lb break="no"/>toba in 1881. Mr. Haultain analysed the <lb/>
section of the Act conferring power upon <lb/>
Parliament in respect of altering the <lb/>
boundaries of two provinces. Proceeding <lb/>
he discussed the terms "power" and <lb/>
"right," pointing out that in one sense <lb/>
power means right. He failed to see how <lb/>
there could be any difference of opinion, <lb/>
in face of the very plain terms of the <lb/>
Imperial Act, as to the power of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment over the area and boundaries of the <lb/>
Territories. He was willing to go the <lb/>
full extent as far as concerned the expedi<lb break="no"/>ency, the morality, or the justice of the <lb/>
claim of the Territories, but he could not <lb/>
go one inch in the direction of saying <lb/>
that Parliament did not possess the right, <lb/>
because Parliament's right was plainly <lb/>
expressed by the Imperial statute. He <lb/>
would go as far as anyone in objecting to <lb/>
any diminution of the Territories—ex<lb break="no"/>cepting the areas mentioned in the reso<lb break="no"/>lution, but he could not join in a state<lb break="no"/>ment denying a legal fact. He quite <lb/>
agreed with the line of argument taken <lb/>
against annexation, and was entirely in <lb/>
sympathy with the people who feared <lb/>
they might be pitchforked into another <lb/>
province. He was prepared if the ques<lb break="no"/>tion became a practical one to assist in <lb/>
doing all that could be done to prevent <lb/>
the injustice. But he was not prepared <lb/>
to accept all of the recitals of the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion. He did not criticise it hostilely, but <lb/>
in a friendly way. He thought they <lb/>
should get more directly at the point. <lb/>
Tha resolution was not conclusive. What <lb/>
they wanted to say was that they would <lb/>
resent any interference with the limits of <lb/>
the Territories. He was disposed to <lb/>
think that their offering to consent to a <lb/>
certain diminution of area would be of <lb/>
not much use. He wanted the resolution <lb/>
made more point blank—more definite. <lb/>
In dealing with a point of such vital in<lb break="no"/>terest it was important that any resolu<lb break="no"/>tion should have the unanimous support <lb/>
of the House. Continuing Mr. Haultain <lb/>
said the need of the whoel motion did <lb/>
not seem to be very pressing at this time. <lb/>
IF the House did not protest, they were <lb/>
still erecting barriers by their daily work. <lb/>
As our school system and other institu<lb break="no"/>tions enlarge, day by day there is less <lb/>
possibility of our being carved up. We <lb/>
are daily creating a political entity and <lb/>
unity. The longer we go on undisturbed, <lb/>
the less possibility there is of breaking <lb/>
through. Quietly erecting these forti<lb break="no"/>fications would see to be the best and <lb/>
most effective way of resisting any threat<lb break="no"/>ened attack. The analogies drawn even <lb/>
to-day of similar dealings in other parts of <lb/>
the world showed that questiosn of feasi<lb break="no"/>bility and justice were a greater determin<lb break="no"/>ing factor than the questions of symme<lb break="no"/>try on the map. A redistribution of the <lb/>
map of Europe might lead to improve<lb break="no"/>ment in artistic beauty, but it was found <lb/>
that deeper and more important questions <lb/>
governed the boundaries of countries and <lb/>
provinces. For ten years Territorial in<lb break="no"/>stitutions have been growing and develop<lb break="no"/>ing. To cut up and destroy the equili<lb break="no"/>ing.To cut up and destroy the equili<lb break="no"/>
 
 <cb/>brium of our institutions and all the mach<lb break="no"/>inery of government was every day be<lb break="no"/>coming a more serious and forbidding un<lb break="no"/>dertaking. Our strongest course was to <lb/>keep on as we have been going.To reach <lb/> a unanimous conclusion on the resolution<lb/> Mr.Haultain suggested to move the<lb/> House into Committee of the Whole.</p>
 
 <p><persName ref="pers:PATR1">Dr. Patrick</persName> agreed, and later in the day<lb/> this course was followed.</p>
 
 <p>In committee the resolution was amend<lb break="no"/>ed by inserting the words "except as<lb/> hereinafter mentioned" in the second<lb/> clause between the words "Territories"<lb/> and "without;" and the following was<lb/> substituted for the last clause:—</p>
 
 <p>"Therefore be it resolved that while<lb/> consenting to such alteration of the limits<lb/> of the N.W.T. as will separate therefrom<lb/> those areas lying north of the northern<lb/> boundaries of the Provinces of British<lb/> Columbia and Manitoba respectively, this<lb/> Legislature is firmly of opinion that the<lb/> political unity of the Territories should<lb/> not be disturbed."</p>
 
 <p>The resolution as amended was report<lb break="no"/>ed, and read the first time</p> 


<pb n="9" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-29_Page_009.jpg"/> 

<fw type="dateline">THE LEADER, THURSDAY EVENING, SEPTEMBER 29, 1898</fw> 
 <fw type="num">9</fw>

</div>
 
 <div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">THE TERRITORIAL POSITION</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">AS PRESENTED BY PREMIER HAULTAIN BEFORE THE LEGIS<lb break="no"/>LATURE, 13TH SEPTEMBER, 1898. <lb/></head> 

<p><emph>The Present is a Year of Financial Jubilee by Reason of Large <lb/>
Revenues Coming From an Unexpected Source—In Future <lb/>
Years the Revenues Will Fall to the Old Figures, Small <lb/>
Enough Before, and Totally Inadequate Now—The School <lb/>
System and Other Institutions Whose Growth Means Outlay, <lb/>
Advancing by Leaps and Bounds—The Only Remedy is Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Establishment if Parliament Fails to Very Largely In<lb break="no"/>crease the Territorial Grant</emph>.</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. HAULTAIN</persName> in moving the <lb/>
House into Committee of Supply on <lb/>
Tuesday, 13th Sept., 1898, stated at the <lb/>
outset that every item of the Supplemen<lb break="no"/>tary Estimates which the House was ask<lb break="no"/>ed to vote would be found to be of a pure<lb break="no"/>ly practical nature. Besides the supple<lb break="no"/>mentaries for the year 1898, there was an <lb/>
Estimate of $60 000 for 1899 to provide <lb/>
for carrying on the public business until <lb/>
the time that the House would be called <lb/>
to meet in that year, that was to say after <lb/>
the end of the present financial year. <lb/>
The reason for the policy of asking this <lb/>
$60,000 vote he would explain later. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">LAST YEAR'S EXPECTATIONS. <lb/></p> 

<p>The House would recollect that last <lb/>
year Supply was voted for 16 months in<lb break="no"/>stead of for an ordinary year. This <lb/>
course was adopted for several reasons. <lb/>
Up to the present the Territorial finan<lb break="no"/>cial year has ended on 31st August, and <lb/>
under the old system followed by Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment in the voting of the North-West <lb/>
grants which compelled the Assembly to <lb/>
hold its sessions in the summer or fall, <lb/>
that date was the most expedient. Now, <lb/>
however, the Assembly grant fro Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment is paid half-yearly as a subsidy, <lb/>
which enabled the Assembly to alter their <lb/>
financial year and make it coterminous <lb/>
with the calender year, which would be <lb/>
more convenient from many points of <lb/>
view. The reasons for the change were <lb/>
fully discussed last year and he <lb/>
would not repeat them. It had been fore<lb break="no"/>shadowed last year that the House at this <lb/>
session would be asked to vote certain <lb/>
supplementary items—for expenses of <lb/>
this session, to provide for the expenses of <lb/>
the general election, and to provide the <lb/>
grants to agricultural societies. They had <lb/>
estimated for supplementaries for these <lb/>
purposes to amount in round numbers to <lb/>
$40,000. The amount now asked far <lb/>
exceeded that amount, and he would try <lb/>
to justify the excess. The total revenue <lb/>
arising from all sources from 1st Sept., <lb/>
1897, to 31st August, 1898, amounted to <lb/>
$542,772.11. At the 1897 session the <lb/>
House appropriated $372,510.82, having <lb/>
then in view an additional $40,000 to be <lb/>
voted as supplementaries this year as he <lb/>
had explained. However the actual bal<lb break="no"/>ance between the amount voted last year <lb/>
and the total amount of the revenue was <lb/>
$170,261.29. The House was now asked <lb/>
to vote $163,925.24 instead of $40,000, <lb/>
and even then there would be left in the <lb/>
bank a sum exceeding $6,000 to go to <lb/>
swell the revenues of 1899, and this cal<lb break="no"/>culation did not include a sum of $28,000 <lb/>
collected for retaining permits in Yukon <lb/>
which also would go to the amount to be <lb/>
voted by the new Legislature for the ser<lb break="no"/>vices of 1899. So he could say at once <lb/>
that while they asked an extraordinary <lb/>
amount for supplementaries they were not <lb/>
overstepping the limits, and were not en<lb break="no"/>trenching a single dollar on the amount <lb/>
properly belonging to the new Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture. Besides the $6,000 balance, and <lb/>
the amount to come from Yukon, there <lb/>
would be several small unexpended bal<lb break="no"/>ances to go to the fund for next year. It <lb/>
was thought that as the present Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture ends within the present year and <lb/>
this was the last session, the Supply for <lb/>
1899 would more properly come within <lb/>
the jurisdiction and work of a new <lb/>
House. There had been a very large <lb/>
temptation to do as was always done else<lb break="no"/>where, and as would be done here if this <lb/>
had not been the last session of an expir<lb break="no"/>ing legislature, namely, vote the Supply <lb/>
for the succeeding year. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment could have brought down really <lb/>
magnificent estimates, adding next year's <lb/>
supply and this year's supplementaries <lb/>
together,—an amount between $500,000 <lb/>
and $600,000. That would have made a <lb/>
splendid showing in one sense, gratifying <lb/>
to the House and to hon. gentlemen's <lb/>
constituents. But they deemed it proper <lb/>
to resist, and they had resisted, the <lb/>
temptation. It would be possible for the <lb/>
new Legislature to meet soon after the <lb/>
elections; the new House would be called <lb/>
as soon as possible. It was the proper <lb/>
course for this House to leave to its suc<lb break="no"/>cessor the business of voting the supply <lb/>
for next year, and confine itself to deal<lb break="no"/>ing with what legitimately belonged to it. <lb/>
They would not, for the sake of making a <lb/>
good showing and bringing down splendid <lb/>
estimates, depart from a good sound con<lb break="no"/>stitutional principle; and they would not <lb/>
anticipate the business of the next year <lb/>
which came within the province of a <lb/>
House yet to be elected. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE REALIZATION OF THE YEAR.</p> 

<p>The increase in the revenues for <lb/>
this year had been extraordinary and <lb/>
unexpected. The largest increase was <lb/>
from fees for wholesale liquor permits for <lb/>
the Yukon. From this source the reven<lb break="no"/>ue was $122,000 to begin with. From <lb/>
fees for enrollment of advocates <lb/>
there had been considerable revenue, <lb/>
which also was caused by the <lb/>
rush to the Yukon. It was <lb/>
not surprising that there had been a rush <lb/>
of lawyers to that country. The great <lb/>
movement of people into the gold fields, <lb/>
the likelihood of many legal conflicts <lb/>
arising out of disputed claims, etc , and <lb/>
the large fees to be hoped for, were <lb/>
doubtless a great attraction for profes<lb break="no"/>sional gentlemen, apart altogether from <lb/>
the possibilities existing for any man to <lb/>
become possessed of a valuable mining <lb/>
claim himself. The business likely to <lb/>
arise out of the gold claims was sufficient <lb/>
to induce a rush of professional men, and <lb/>
the Territorial revenues reaped some <lb/>
$2,000 from fees for enrolment of advo<lb break="no"/>cates. Fees from appointment of notaries <lb/>
exceeded the estimate by $290. In all <lb/>
the Yukon yielded a revenue of more <lb/>
than $124,000,— an amount not calculated <lb/>
upon at all in the estimate of revenue <lb/>
available for this year made at last session. <lb/>
The ordinary local revenue had also <lb/>
taken an unexpected jump. They esti<lb break="no"/>mated it at $30,000. For a number of <lb/>
years the local revenue had been nearly a <lb/>
fixed amount, but this year it had exceed <lb/>
ed the estimate and exceeded the amount <lb/>
derived from local sources in former years <lb/>
by between $10,000 and $12,000. So in <lb/>
addition to the sum of $40,000 of their <lb/>
estimated revenue left unvoted last year,


<cb/>


they had now a further sum of about <lb/>
$140,000 in round numbers belonging <lb/>
of the amount now asked to be voted. <lb/>
be asked legitimately to vote. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">NO LACK OF NEED FOR THE INCREASE. <lb/></p> 

<p>If they had much larger revenues this <lb/>
year, they found also that there were <lb/>
larger expenses to meet. The legislation <lb/>
of last session had led to an incalculable <lb/>
increase in the work of the <lb/>
public offices. The increase could <lb/>
not be put down to any particular <lb/>
new policy adopted, excepting the case of <lb/>
brands registration; but the ordinary <lb/>
everyday work of the offices had increased <lb/>
fully 40 or 50 per cent. No one not <lb/>
right on the spot could notice the in<lb break="no"/>crease or see the reasons for it, but it was <lb/>
a fact experienced in every department <lb/>
that the work had increased simply by <lb/>
leaps and bounds. Possibly it was partly <lb/>
due to the organization of government <lb/>
and the institution of regular departments <lb/>
—to the change from the vague system <lb/>
under which no one was definitely re<lb break="no"/>sponsible and there were no organised <lb/>
departments, to the system of organised <lb/>
departments and appropriate individuals <lb/>
being appointed for the public to write <lb/>
to. For instance he had himself the <lb/>
honor to hold the title of Attorney <lb/>
General. The mere appointment of such <lb/>
an official had seemed to lead to a tre<lb break="no"/>mendous increase in the correspondence <lb/>
of the office. Every Justice of the Peace <lb/>
considered that he had a right to obtain <lb/>
information and advice upon all the <lb/>
business coming before him from <lb/>
the Attorney General, and others <lb/>
availed themselves of the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity afforded by the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of a law officer of the Crown <lb/>
in the Territories, to seek free legal <lb/>
advice and information. While it was <lb/>
not a part of the Attorney General's <lb/>
duties to deal out legal advice to every <lb/>
one who asked for it and upon every case <lb/>
or subject upon which his advice might <lb/>
be, and was, asked, yet he had attempted <lb/>
in all cases to give the benefit of his <lb/>
opinion when it was asked, and when <lb/>
there was nothing in the nature of the <lb/>
conditions or cases submitted to him to <lb/>
prevent him giving an opinion. In only <lb/>
a few cases he had been obliged to refuse <lb/>
the requests of gentlemen who sought his <lb/>
advice. The Attorney General's depart<lb break="no"/>ment was not nearly so directly in touch <lb/>
with the people generally as some other <lb/>
of the departments, but the work of the <lb/>
Attorney General's office had increased <lb/>
beyond all anticipation,—beyond any <lb/>
estimate that could possibly have been <lb/>
made. The general idea seemed to be <lb/>
that the Attorney General was appointed <lb/>
to give free advice, and often it was a <lb/>
very difficult and delicate task to lead <lb/>
people to comprehend that their cases <lb/>
were not of a public nature and involved <lb/>
no point of public interest, and should <lb/>
therefore be entrusted to a solicitor. But <lb/>
as he had said, whenever he was able he <lb/>
had given opinions to Justices and to <lb/>
individuals as well; he had sometimes <lb/>
perhaps strained a point to lead himself <lb/>
at least to believe that the cases sub<lb break="no"/>mitted were connected in some way with <lb/>
the public interest, and only in one or <lb/>
two instances had he refused to give the <lb/>
best opinion he could give on points sub<lb break="no"/>mitted. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">INCREASED WORK AND NEW OFFICIALS. <lb/></p> 

<p>Two notable items in the Estimates <lb/>
were asked to provide salaries for two new <lb/>
officials who had been appointed since the <lb/>
House last met. The House was asked <lb/>
to vote the salary for, and ratify the ap<lb break="no"/>pointment of, Mr. Robson as law clerk, <lb/>
and for Mr. Peterson as deputy in the <lb/>
Department of Agriculture. In neither <lb/>
of these instances did he think there any <lb/>
call for apology. He could personally say <lb/>
for Mr. Robson that he was a first rate <lb/>
man for the work. There had for a long <lb/>
time been a constant demand for a law <lb/>
clerk in the House. The want had been <lb/>
long recognized of an official skilled and <lb/>
trained in the work of drafting legisla<lb break="no"/>tion. There was a long standing feeling <lb/>
that the sooner they could see their way <lb/>
clear for the engagement of a law clerk, <lb/>
the better it would be for their legislation <lb/>
and general business. Mr. Robson would, <lb/>
too, fill the post of deputy to the Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General. In that regard he could <lb/>
only say that in view of the increase in <lb/>
the business of the office it had become a <lb/>
physical impossibility for the political <lb/>
head of the department to give the at<lb break="no"/>tention demanded to all the routine of <lb/>
the office. The House could have no <lb/>
idea of the number of points involving <lb/>
professional opinions, which came to the <lb/>
Attorney General's office, not alone from <lb/>
the outside public, but arising from the <lb/>
work of the other departments. From <lb/>
the work of the Public Works department <lb/>
there arose an innumerable and constant<lb break="no"/>ly increasing number of references—from <lb/>
the Statute Labour system, in regard to <lb/>
elections held under it, powers of Over<lb break="no"/>seers and questions of assessment. So <lb/>
with the Education department. Under <lb/>
their system of schools there were con<lb break="no"/>stantly arising difficult and complicated <lb/>
questions which properly belonged for <lb/>
settlement to the law department of the <lb/>
government. From all their departments, <lb/>
in fact, there were points continually <lb/>
coming up which had to be considered in <lb/>
in the Attorney General's office. Under <lb/>
the Public Works department, again, <lb/>
there were questions of trails and road <lb/>
allowances, often intricate questions re<lb break="no"/>lating to titles involving business with <lb/>
the registry offices, and which could only <lb/>
be handled by the Attorney General. <lb/>
The same was true of the Irrigation <lb/>
administration. He needed only to men<lb break="no"/>tion some of these points, and to leave the <lb/>
House to understand and appreciate the <lb/>
nature and amount of this kind of work. <lb/>
All the subsidiary work respecting muni<lb break="no"/>cipalities and like institutions brought <lb/>
the departments into very direct contact <lb/>
with the people on many questions in<lb break="no"/>volving legal points and questions of <lb/>
very important and often serious public <lb/>
interest,—points and questions upon <lb/>
which the departments must be in posi<lb break="no"/>tion to give well considered opinions. <lb/>
Again, prosecutions under the Ordinances <lb/>

<cb/>

were on the increase,—under the Liquor <lb/>
law particularly. The Government had <lb/>
been pushing the inspectors and during <lb/>
the year there had been a largely in<lb break="no"/>creased number of prosecutions, and no <lb/>
less than 21 convictions, a number equal <lb/>
to one-fifth of the licenses granted, and <lb/>
from which $1,900 had been received in <lb/>
the way of fines. Under the Prairie Fire <lb/>
Ordinance and other Ordinances there <lb/>
were constantly arising points, cases and <lb/>
work, which with his other duties—the <lb/>
Attorney General presided also over the <lb/>
Treasury and School departments—the <lb/>
member of the Government occupying <lb/>
the position of Attorney General could <lb/>
not begin to even casually consider. The <lb/>
time had come to install permanent men <lb/>
over the departments, and to cease con<lb break="no"/>fining the political heads to the clerical <lb/>
and routine work of the offices. The <lb/>
members of the Government were ex<lb break="no"/>pected to give consideration to new <lb/>
legislation and to develop new policies; <lb/>
they should be enabled to travel through <lb/>
the country to keep in touch with the <lb/>
people and to keep acquainted with the <lb/>
conditions of all portions of the country. <lb/>
The men entrusted with the policy of <lb/>
Government had larger and more import<lb break="no"/>ant work to engage them that the clerical <lb/>
and routine duties of the offices, and <lb/>
should not be held down in the office <lb/>
chairs attending to routine work which a <lb/>
reasonable addition to the staff could cope <lb/>
with and do well. In the past the routine <lb/>
work which the political heads were <lb/>
obliged to attend to had been too large. <lb/>
It had become a matter of difficulty to <lb/>
attend even to the daily mail, and in the <lb/>
multiplicity of affairs of detail which <lb/>
could not be avoided sometimes matters <lb/>
of larger interest had to be put to one <lb/>
side. The necessity of having permanent <lb/>
men in charge of the departments had <lb/>
been dwelt upon soundly in former years, <lb/>
—men whom political changes would not <lb/>
disturb and who would understand the <lb/>
law and the policy of the departments. <lb/>
The policy he referred to was quite dis<lb break="no"/>tinct from the political policy. Certain <lb/>
rules and lines would be followed in the <lb/>
departments, which would be the same <lb/>
no matter what administration was in <lb/>
control. Such permanent heads were <lb/>
absolutely necessary for the continuity of <lb/>
public business,—men trained and skilled <lb/>
and experienced in the office and depart<lb break="no"/>mental administration. The political <lb/>
heads might come and go,—they were <lb/>
always liable to change. At one stage of <lb/>
the not remote history of the Territories, <lb/>
so much of the knowledge of the detail <lb/>
and business relating to the government <lb/>
had been confined to the mind of an <lb/>
Executive Committee, that if a political <lb/>
revolution had removed the occupants of <lb/>
the offices or had illness taken away the <lb/>
members, a very great deal of the essen<lb break="no"/>tial knowledge of the business would have <lb/>
gone out with them, because the staff was <lb/>
insufficient and because there were no <lb/>
permanent head having hold of the <lb/>
threads and details of the business. He <lb/>
had personally often felt that his successor <lb/>
would have a nice amount of work just in <lb/>
gathering the threads and details. The <lb/>
appointment of an agricultural deputy <lb/>
would be bound to commend itself to the <lb/>
House. He would not need to dilate on <lb/>
the importance of that department. Ag<lb break="no"/>riculture was the main industry of the <lb/>
Territories, and the policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment should be directed to the promotion <lb/>
of the interests of and the development <lb/>
of that industry. They were initiating a <lb/>
policy. The House was not asked to <lb/>
devote a large amount of money towards <lb/>
it, but they were making a departure, a <lb/>
commencement. The Agricultural depart<lb break="no"/>ment, although its scope and interest <lb/>
were large and most important, was not <lb/>
itself large as yet. There were just the <lb/>
deputy and one clerk at present, and no <lb/>
doubt, with possibly an assistant or two, <lb/>
this staff would be able to carry on the <lb/>
work for some time to come. Though the <lb/>
expense was small the department was not <lb/>
the less important and they could all <lb/>
sincerely hope that it would fast grow <lb/>
in usefulness. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE BRANDS CHANGE. <lb/></p> 

<p>In the present year the aggregate ex<lb break="no"/>penses of the offices had been extraor<lb break="no"/>dinarily large. The extra work had been <lb/>
occasioned not only in the manner he had <lb/>
been describing, a more or less legitimate <lb/>
increase; but a more extraordinary, and it <lb/>
was to be hoped temporary, increase was <lb/>
caused by the change in the Brands <lb/>
registration system adopted by the House <lb/>
last year. It was always easy after the <lb/>
event to see what might have been done <lb/>
better. He was willing to admit that if <lb/>
they had allowed a longer time within <lb/>
which to effect the change a great deal of <lb/>
the rush of work would have been avoided <lb/>
as well as a great deal of the trouble and <lb/>
unnecessary friction. He said this simply <lb/>
by way of retrospection. The was not use <lb/>
in dwelling on what might have been. <lb/>
the gift of prophetic insight had not been <lb/>
given enough play in the circumstance. <lb/>
The change was made the harder by the <lb/>
very incomplete state of the old records, <lb/>
and by the fact that many people did not <lb/>
get hold of the effect of the new <lb/>
law. He did not intend to <lb/>
take up any time with the subject, <lb/>
which would be fully dealt with by his <lb/>
colleague from Moose Jaw. The work<lb break="no"/>ing of the new system had brought a <lb/>
revenue of $2,300 which more than paid <lb/>
for extra work and clerical services which <lb/>
the change had necessitated in the offi<lb break="no"/>ces. The work had been very great. <lb/>
No less than 4,600 letters were received, <lb/>
and 8,000 communications had been sent <lb/>
out from the office, 2,500 of them being <lb/>
circulars. The applications numbered <lb/>
5,000, and 3,700 brands had been re-<lb break="yes"/>allotted, or originally allotted. Each <lb/>
application and each brand dealt <lb/>
with involved more or less work. <lb/>
There had been two single cases <lb/>
of defective brands which took the time <lb/>
of one man two whole days to straighten <lb/>
out—a man who was skilled in the sub<lb break="no"/>ject and who was brought down from <lb/>
the stock country temporarily to deal <lb/>
in a scientific way with the wor of <lb/>
changing the system. He was a man <lb/>
familiar with all the western brands and 


<cb/>


yet it took him two whole days to reach <lb/>
a determination in those two cases. <lb/>
This fact would enable the House to <lb/>
have some idea of the difficulty and <lb/>
amount of work which had been done. <lb/>
A great deal of the work done in the <lb/>
offices in the past year was new work, <lb/>
and there had been a redistribution of <lb/>
the officials. While the total expense <lb/>
had increased, the increase was entirely <lb/>
due to new work. The general ten<lb break="no"/>dency was to simplify the work. In the <lb/>
Education and Treasury offices and in <lb/>
some of the subsidiary branches there <lb/>
had been certain simplification and <lb/>
lessening of expense. There were fewer <lb/>
officials in these offices than formerly, <lb/>
while the work had certainly not be<lb break="no"/>come less. New work was being dealt <lb/>
with by the new departments, and new <lb/>
officials were established only when they <lb/>
became necessary from the point of view <lb/>
of usefulness and convenience to the <lb/>
people of the country The Government <lb/>
could claim that they were keeping to <lb/>
their policy and their traditions and were <lb/>
doing the work with the smallest staff <lb/>
compatible with the public interest. No <lb/>
one knowing the work which had to be <lb/>
done could cavil, and he stated a fact <lb/>
when he said that there was not a single <lb/>
unnecessary official in their employ. <lb/>
During the year the staff had worked <lb/>
night and day endeavoring to keep up <lb/>
with the business arising,—the officials <lb/>
had worked over hours not only for <lb/>
weeks but for months at a stretch, and <lb/>
even then there had been absolute ne<lb break="no"/>cessity for the employment of extra <lb/>
temporary clerks. He had taken the <lb/>
ground in conversations with his col<lb break="no"/>leagues, that whenever it was shown that <lb/>
the staff was unable to cope with the <lb/>
work, he would rather take the respon<lb break="no"/>sibility of employing additional assistance <lb/>
and depend upon the House to sustain <lb/>
the action, than to come down to the <lb/>
House and meet the complaints which <lb/>
were sure to be heard if the work were <lb/>
not done. He could honestly say and <lb/>
claim that in every case where they had <lb/>
engaged an extra clerk or had made a <lb/>
new appointment, there had been an <lb/>
actual requirement. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">ITEMS OF THE ESTIMATES. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Public Works items he would <lb/>
leave to Mr. Ross to explain, who was <lb/>
better qualified to enter into the details. <lb/>
In a general way he might say that in <lb/>
the supplementaries there were votes <lb/>
asked for a few new items, but the bult <lb/>
of the items were for works which had <lb/>
been pressed for last year but <lb/>
could not be provided with the <lb/>
means then at the disposal of the <lb/>
House. The works for which votes <lb/>
were now asked were works which <lb/>
could be done and would be done <lb/>
this year; of course they would of neces<lb break="no"/>sity be done this year or the money would <lb/>
lapse. Of the new items, there was one <lb/>
for a Territorial map. There was not at <lb/>
present any up-to-date map of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. The map would include the <lb/>
electoral districts to be made at this <lb/>
session. The House was asked to pro<lb break="no"/>vide for 10,000 copies, and they would <lb/>
be ready very shortly after the House <lb/>
rose. Including the Statute Labor, <lb/>
School and Legislative Assembly districts, <lb/>
the map would contain a large amount of <lb/>
very valuable information taking the <lb/>
place of letter press description. The <lb/>
showing of the useful institutions of the <lb/>
country would constitute a valuable ob<lb break="no"/>ject lesson. It would be an unwritten <lb/>
pamphlet on the North-West Territories. <lb/>
There was a vote for the expenses of the <lb/>
inspection of steam boilers, which service <lb/>
is expected to return sufficient in fees to <lb/>
pay for itself and perhaps show a slight <lb/>
margin to the good. There was a vote <lb/>
to pay a portion of a bonus to a man at <lb/>
Wetaskiwin, the circumstances of which <lb/>
were the following: From the district <lb/>
grant a bonuse of $500 had been promisted <lb/>
to the man in consideration of his build<lb break="no"/>ing a flour mill and operating for three <lb/>
years. After one year's operation the <lb/>
mill was burned. It was insured in <lb/>
favor of the Government, who received <lb/>
the $500 from the policy. The man had <lb/>
operated the mill for one third of the <lb/>
term of his agreement, and it was thought <lb/>
right that he should receive one-third of <lb/>
the amount of the bonus. In regard to <lb/>
Public Works, Mr. Haultain hoped that <lb/>
in future years the Estimates would as<lb break="no"/>sume a different form, and that there <lb/>
would be fewer items for small works <lb/>
than had been necessary last year and <lb/>
were found necessary this year. Now <lb/>
that between 400 and 500 Statute Lavor <lb/>
Districts were organised and would be <lb/>
better able to cope with the smaller <lb/>
works and improvements as the organisa<lb break="no"/>tion became more effective through ex<lb break="no"/>perience of its working, it could reason<lb break="no"/>ably be hoped that year by year the <lb/>
Estimates would contain items for fewer <lb/>
small works, leaving the fund to be <lb/>
devoted to larger and enduring works <lb/>
which would live and go down to the <lb/>
credit of the members whose privilege it <lb/>
might be to recommend them and of the <lb/>
Government which might construct them. <lb/>
Nevertheless this year the position in <lb/>
regard to public works was most gratify<lb break="no"/>ing. Without drawing a cent of money <lb/>
legitimately belonging to another year, <lb/>
the House was able to vote, including <lb/>
the amounts asked in these supplementaries, <lb/>
a total sum of $197,385.00 to be expend<lb break="no"/>ed on public works and improvements in <lb/>
the 16 months ending 31st Dec., 1898. <lb/>
This splendid showing of course carried <lb/>
with it its own danger. Unless the funds <lb/>
of later years were increased as this <lb/>
year's funds had been, from some unex<lb break="no"/>pected source, they must drop again to <lb/>
the commonplace amounts of former <lb/>
years. In a way they were courting <lb/>
future disappointment. However the <lb/>
money they had this year rightly be<lb break="no"/>longed to them, and it ought to be spent <lb/>
by them, without concern as to what <lb/>
might happen in the future. The items <lb/>
included provision for the construction of <lb/>
bridges and culverts, and repairs to <lb/>
public works. The expenses for repairs <lb/>
would increase from year to year, as <lb/>
larger works were erected. A point had <lb/>
been arrived at when many of the works <lb/>
constructed years ago were showing the <lb/>
necessity for repairs. Whenever a road <lb/>
or a bridge became necessary and was <lb/>
constructed, there followed the necessity <lb/>
of keeping it in repair. Some of the <lb/>
items in these supplementaries would <lb/>
stand to the credit of future years in a <lb/>
sense. The tools, supplies and imple<lb break="no"/>ments provided for would not outlive <lb/>
their usefulness this year. Not an item <lb/>
could be found in the public works list <lb/>
which was not of a distinctly practical <lb/>
nature. <lb/></p> 



<p rendition="simple:centre">GROWTH OF EDUCATION.</p> 

<p>Education was one of the most impor<lb break="no"/>tant subjects dealt with by the Assembly. <lb/>
The House was asked to pass a very large <lb/>
supplementary vote for grands to schools. <lb/>
An amount was voted last year which was <lb/>
estimated to be sufficient for the 16 <lb/>
months. At last session he had given <lb/>
indication of certain circumstances which <lb/>
might lead to the necessity of making an <lb/>
additional vote this year, but the sum <lb/>
they were now obliged to ask ($25,000) <lb/>
was both extraordinary and unexpected. <lb/>
It made a serious drain on the general <lb/>
resources, and withdrew a very large sum <lb/>
from the amounts available for other pur<lb break="no"/>poses. On the other hand the circum<lb break="no"/>stances and conditions which made <lb/>
necessary the drain and the withdrawal 

<cb/>
  
were matters of congratulation, however <lb/>
much they might grudge the inroad. In <lb/>
the Estimates at the 1897 session, the <lb/>
Government had estimated for an increase <lb/>
in the number of schools and school <lb/>
children at a rate proportionate with the <lb/>
rate prevailing in previous years. How<lb break="no"/>ever, it was found that the ration of in<lb break="no"/>crease in 1897-98 in the number of <lb/>
teachers employed was twice as great as <lb/>
the ratio of increase in 1896-97. The <lb/>
House would at once recognize that this <lb/>
fact necessitated an increased expenditure, <lb/>
and at the same time that it was a sub<lb break="no"/>ject for congratulation. The increase in <lb/>
the number of children attending the <lb/>
schools amounted to more than twice the <lb/>
ratio of increase in the previous year. <lb/>
This was altogether astounding although <lb/>
very desirable. By the system of grants <lb/>
an amount was paid for every day that <lb/>
every child attended school, so that a <lb/>
large addition to the school attendance <lb/>
meant a large addition to the school <lb/>
grants. Another unexpected increase <lb/>
arose from the re-opening of no less than <lb/>
13 schools which had been closed, and of <lb/>
which there had been no reason last year <lb/>
to expect the re-opening. On the con<lb break="no"/>trary it had been expected they would be <lb/>
disorganised as they had seemed to stand <lb/>
in the way of re-erections of different <lb/>
districts. But they had suddenly re<lb break="no"/>vived, and they alone represented $3,000 <lb/>

Last session he had drawn attention to <lb/>
the decrease in the number of holders of <lb/>
3rd class certificates employed. The ten<lb break="no"/>dency was to employ the teachers of <lb/>
higher qualifications. The move was <lb/>
welcomed as being in the right direction <lb/>
in the interests of the schools, but they <lb/>
had had no idea how fast the movement <lb/>
was to go on. This year 3rd class teach<lb break="no"/>ers represent only 18 per cent of the <lb/>
number of teachers employed in the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories. This was a splendid showing. <lb/>
It was a significant fact that the <lb/>
number of lowest grade teachers engaged <lb/>
in the new Territories was smaller than <lb/>
the number engaged in the old and rich <lb/>
province of Ontario. In that province <lb/>
more than 50 per cent of the teachers are <lb/>
holders of lowest grade certificates as <lb/>
against only 18 per cent in the Territor<lb break="no"/>ies. Speaking comparatively as well as <lb/>
absolutely the fact spoke volumes for the <lb/>
nature of the education given in the <lb/>
common schools of the North-West Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, and showed that the trustees and <lb/>
ratepayers in this country appreciate the <lb/>
better qualified teachers. But their <lb/>
appreciation causes increased expenditure. <lb/>
Higher grades meant higher grants, and <lb/>
imposed an additional burden on the <lb/>
resources of the Assembly, a burden, <lb/>
however, they cheerfully recognised and <lb/>
met. The larger salaries paid to higher <lb/>
grade teachers affected the grants, as in <lb/>
a measure of the grants were governed by <lb/>
the salary paid to the teacher. Another <lb/>
feature of the increase was the changing <lb/>
of many of the shorter-term or "summer" <lb/>
schools into yearly schools, or which if <lb/>
not keeping open for the full year were <lb/>
prolonging the summer sessions. The <lb/>
Ordinance held out inducements for regu<lb break="no"/>lar attendance and likewise the <lb/>
grants. The general effect of the system <lb/>
of grants adopted two years ago had been <lb/>
to increase the attendance in summer <lb/>
schools. First there would be an increase <lb/>
in attendance, then the schools would be <lb/>
kept open a longer term, and finally the <lb/>
summer schools changed to yearly school. <lb/>
All these features showing the rapid <lb/>
development of the school system must be <lb/>
gratifying to every one interested in the <lb/>
education of the young people <lb/>
of the Territories. From a strict<lb break="no"/>ly financial point of view the <lb/>
increase was a misfortune, but on the <lb/>
other hand it was a source of gratifica<lb break="no"/>tion.</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre">AGRICULTURAL INTERESTS NOT NEGLECTED.</p> 

<p>The next feature of the Estimates had <lb/>
to do with Agriculture and Statistics. <lb/>
The Government had not been able yet <lb/>
to complete the scheme foreshadowed <lb/>
last year respecting agricultural societies <lb/>
and exhibitions. That the present plan <lb/>
of holding many small shows was simply <lb/>
a dissipation of money and a scattering <lb/>
of energies, all would agree. But the <lb/>
matter was a delicate one. Local habi<lb break="no"/>tations were likely to resent interference <lb/>
with their self governing powers; and it <lb/>
had to be admitted that in the early <lb/>
days the small societies did a very ex<lb break="no"/>cellent work. They had filled an unoc<lb break="no"/>cupied place and had been a dinstinct <lb/>
advantage to the new institutions grow<lb break="no"/>ing up under pioneer conditions. So far <lb/>
as their resources and organisation ad<lb break="no"/>mitted they had done well. But the <lb/>
time has passed by when they met the <lb/>
requirements and conditions of the coun<lb break="no"/>try. The Government were, however, <lb/>
not prepared to deal with the question <lb/>
now. If the elections resulted as they <lb/>
hoped, a scheme would be ready for <lb/>
submission to the House at its next <lb/>
session. Under the heading appeared <lb/>
two items which were new departures <lb/>
and the direct result of the establish<lb break="no"/>ment of an Agricultural department. <lb/>
The House was not asked to risk any <lb/>
great amount of money in this branching <lb/>
out. Any branching out they could do <lb/>
was of necessity very modest. Not mat<lb break="no"/>ter who was in control, there were cer<lb break="no"/>tain services which had to be met; and <lb/>
when those services were met there was <lb/>
not much money left for new schemes or <lb/>
any brilliant policy. Their Estimates had <lb/>
always shown a desire, and their policy had <lb/>
always been, to have their institutions <lb/>
grow up with the country. They had always <lb/>
endeavored to grapple with the conditions as <lb/>
they arose, and to have their institutions <lb/>
keep pace with the development of the <lb/>
country. It was in this spirit that they <lb/>
now endeavored to deal with the interests <lb/>
of agriculture and stock raising. The <lb/>
policy in regard to the latter interest <lb/>
would be to encourage "breeding up." <lb/>
In the western part of the country par<lb break="no"/>ticularly there was no question but that <lb/>
there had been in the last few years a <lb/>
most undesirable deterioration in quality of <lb/>
the cattle on the ranges. This was part<lb break="no"/>ly owing to the fact that the large own<lb break="no"/>ers had gone out of breeding. the quali<lb break="no"/>ty and value of the herds were not <lb/>
what they were eight, ten or twelve <lb/>
years ago. This statement applied <lb/>
to the west; possibly in the eastern <lb/>
part the tendency had been the <lb/>
other way. while the early herds in <lb/>
the west had been of splendid quality and <lb/>
value, the rule with settler in the <lb/>
eastern part had been that the first cattle <lb/>
he obtained were not of very good grade. <lb/>
At any rate all would agree that "grad<lb break="no"/>ing up" in both east and west would be <lb/>
a very great benefit; and anything which <lb/>
would tend to encourage this desirable <lb/>
improvement without making too large <lb/>
inroads upon their resources, would be <lb/>
good policy to adopt. The method pro<lb break="no"/>posed was to make arrangements for the <lb/>
transportation of the thoroughbred animals at <lb/>
nominal cost to the purchaser; to this <lb/>
extent, that a thoroughbred animal might <lb/>
be landed at the home of the purchaser in <lb/>
the Territories at just the cost of the ani<lb break="no"/>mal in the eastern province or wherever <lb/>
else purchased. Distance would simply <lb/>
be abolished so far as concerned the man <lb/>
in the Territories who wanted to procure <lb/>
a thoroughbred sire. The amount asked <lb/>
for this purpose ($2,000) was very small; <lb/>
in fact it looked to be an absurdly smal <lb/>
expenditure in view of the very great im<lb break="no"/>portance of the project, but the Govern<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

ment were satisfied that the amount <lb/>
would meet the needs of the ser<lb break="no"/>vice. Another amount of $2,500 was <lb/>
asked to initiate experimental work. <lb/>
Anyone who had visited the district sur<lb break="no"/>rounding Indian Head must have been <lb/>
struck with the splendid crops and the <lb/>
generally flourishing condition of the <lb/>
district. The special success attending <lb/>
farming in that neighborhood could not be <lb/>
due to any superiority of soil or conditions <lb/>
as compared with other districts; the <lb/>
success was due in great measure to <lb/>
practical facts relating to agriculture <lb/>
which farmers there obtain,— to the <lb/>
advantage they have of seeing scientific <lb/>
farming carried on under the identical <lb/>
conditions prevailing on their own farms <lb/>
The example offered by the Indian Head <lb/>
experimental farm, altough unfortunate<lb break="no"/>ly confined to the few who live immedi<lb break="no"/>ately around it, was still productive of <lb/>
practical good of which the Indian Head <lb/>
district was the standing proof. Excellent <lb/>
as was the work of the Indian Head <lb/>
farm, its usefulness was very largely <lb/>
confined to the neighborhood possessing <lb/>
the same soil and conditions as prevailed <lb/>
on the farm itself. The experiments <lb/>
which proved that a certain kind of <lb/>
wheat could be successfully grown at <lb/>
Indian Head, would not prove that the <lb/>
wheat could be grown on different soil <lb/>
and under differnt conditions. A trip <lb/>
of 40 or 50 miles in this country would <lb/>
often show totally changed soil and cli<lb break="no"/>mate, and the method good for one dis<lb break="no"/>trict might not be good for the other. <lb/>
So from the broad point of view, the <lb/>
work of one experimental farm in a coun<lb break="no"/>try having so many varieities of soil and <lb/>
conditions as the Territories, could <lb/>
not have any large practical use or im<lb break="no"/>portance. Everyone would admit the <lb/>
value of experimental work, and the <lb/>
question was, could this Government <lb/>
undertake the work with advantage? <lb/>
They believed they could do so. As the <lb/>
amount asked for would indicate, there <lb/>
was no proposal to buy farms or attempt <lb/>
any scheme which would involve great <lb/>
expense. They would be confined to <lb/>
work in the way of results and lessons, <lb/>
—the dealing with questions concerning <lb/>
the evry-day work of the every-day <lb/>
farmer. Their plan would be severely <lb/>
practical. He had no doubt they would <lb/>
find farmers in every dinstinct locality <lb/>
who were interested in experimental <lb/>
work, and would be willing to carry it <lb/>
on. He thought there would be no diffi<lb break="no"/>culty in finding good farmers to devote <lb/>
a few acres to experiments with seeds,   <lb/>
grains, vegetable and other things in <lb/>
return for a small amount to cover the <lb/>
cost of the labor expended in the opera<lb break="no"/>tions. The next item related to hide <lb/>
inspection. Possibly he was anticipating <lb/>
committee work by explaining these small <lb/>
items, but explaining them now might <lb/>
save time in committee. Under the old <lb/>
Ordinance hide inspectors were appointed <lb/>
who were remunerated by fees. Owing <lb/>
partly to a fault in the law, and to an <lb/>
unfortunate turn taken certain cases <lb/>
being prosecuted, ceratin inspectors <lb/>
not been able to enforce the collection of <lb/>
their fees. This direct loss to the inspec<lb break="no"/>tors was occasioned by a fault of the <lb/>
Ordinance and by difficulties in regard to <lb/>
proof which would have attended the <lb/>
prosecution of the cases, and the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment thought it right that the recompense <lb/>
of the inspectors should be made good. <lb/>
The House was asked to vote an additional <lb/>
$1000 for the 16 months to hospitals. <lb/>
They had never been able to give to <lb/>
hospitals the amounts which it would be <lb/>
desirable to give if the Territorial finan<lb break="no"/>cial conditions were more favorable. The <lb/>
hospitals of the Territories were doing <lb/>
splendid work. Under an Ordinance the <lb/>
Assembly provided for certain grants <lb/>
which were divided proportionately <lb/>
among the institutions according to the <lb/>
actual work done, but the amount they <lb/>
were enabled to vote had never equalled <lb/>
the amount held out in the Ordinance. <lb/>
The Ordinance held out 50 cents per <lb/>
patient on a certain calculation. They <lb/>
had never been able to pay more than 26 <lb/>
cents. The present year had been a <lb/>
heavy one upon some of the hospitals, <lb/>
particularly at Macleod and Lethbridge, <lb/>
on account of the building of the Crow's <lb/>
Nest railway. the one at Macleod had <lb/>
had to be enlarged twice to meet the <lb/>
requirements of many add itional <lb/>
patients. A large amount of private aid <lb/>
had been given. The same remark would <lb/>
apply to Lethbridge. Of course the <lb/>
patients who were railway employees <lb/>
were paid for, but the dollar a day charg<lb break="no"/>ed did not cover the whole expense, and <lb/>
a large part of the work of every hospital <lb/>
was left to be sustained by private <lb/>
generosity. The present year was a pros<lb break="no"/>perous one for the Assembly financially, <lb/>
and the House could well afford this year <lb/>
to increase the amount of aid for hospitals. <lb/>
An item of $1200 was asked to defray the <lb/>
expense of checking certain outbreaks of <lb/>
disease, occuring respectively at Saska<lb break="no"/>toon, Edmonton, Pincher Creek and <lb/>
Yorkton. Such votes would doubtless be <lb/>
found necessary from time to time. <lb/>
Hitherto the expenditure in this connec<lb break="no"/>tion had not been large, and he was sure <lb/>
they did not grudge a single cent voted <lb/>
for Hospitals, Charities and Public <lb/>
Health. There were in the Territories <lb/>
none of those institutions which were <lb/>
found necessary in older communities,— <lb/>
for incurables and indigent people. We <lb/>
had not those poorer classes in any num<lb break="no"/>ber in this country. While the people <lb/>
here were not rich, comparative<lb break="no"/>ly, yet partly because the country <lb/>
was young, and the population <lb/>
youthful, there were not many widows, <lb/>
orphans or incurables, who have to look <lb/>
to government and legislature for support <lb/>
under trying conditions. He did <lb/>
not think it would be wise yet to hold <lb/>
out definitely any promises of support to <lb/>
those classes. The holding out of a pro<lb break="no"/>mise would to a certain extent develop a <lb/>
demand. But he was sure the public did <lb/>
not grudge what was voted for charitable <lb/>
purposes. The average man in this coun<lb break="no"/>try was not over-burdened with legitimate <lb/>
claims upon his charity. <lb/></p> 

<p>It being half-past twelve o'clock , Mr. <lb/>
Speaker left the chair. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE YUKON ADMINISTRATION</p>

<p>Resuming his speech at 2:30 o'clock, <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> took up the item of $6,000 <lb/>
for expenses of administration of Terri<lb break="no"/>torial affairs in the Yukon district, to <lb/>
cover a special warrant. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment's policy on that question had already <lb/>
been variously and very generally dis<lb break="no"/>cussed, but at the expense of repetition <lb/>
he would recite a few of the points which <lb/>
led to the organisation of the expedition, <lb/>
and to the exercise of the powers con<lb break="no"/>ferred upon this Government of adminis<lb break="no"/>tering certain affairs in the Yukon. Be<lb break="no"/>tween the Dominion and the Territories <lb/>
the question was not one admitting of <lb/>
controversy. It had to be admitted that <lb/>
the question was one of ordinary law, in <lb/>
which any question of constitutional law <lb/>
had no relation. It was an indisputable <lb/>
fact of ordinary law that certain adminis<lb break="no"/>tration devolved upon the Lieut.-Gover<lb break="no"/>nor of the Territories, which meant that <lb/>
the Lieut.-Governor was to administer by <lb/>
and with the advice and consent of an <lb/>
Executive Council. The position of <lb/>
affairs in the Yukon threw a clear duty <lb/>
upon the North-West Government, and <lb/>
the Government proceeded to take steps <lb/>
to fulfil the duty. They organised an <lb/>
expedition to be sent to the district. <lb/>
They sent an officer or plenipotentiary <lb/>

<cb/>

clothed with full power to carry out the <lb/>
law within the scope of the responsibili<lb break="no"/>ties of the Territorial Government. The <lb/>
Government had been attacked with <lb/>
charges of having usurped the functions <lb/>
of the Legislature in not getting the <lb/>
sanction of the House for their course. <lb/>
That charge had already been met and <lb/>
explained. The Government had stated <lb/>
to the House that it was not the intention <lb/>
to bring down a proposition respecting <lb/>
the Yukon, but that as soon as the House <lb/>
rose the question would be taken up by <lb/>
the Government and the steps taken <lb/>
which seemed advisable; and the state<lb break="no"/>ment met with a certain sort of approval <lb/>
in the House. It was further charged <lb/>
that the Government usurped the <lb/>
functions of the Legislature in re<lb break="no"/>lation to the prohibitory sections <lb/>
of the Act. Such charge could <lb/>
have no other foundation than com<lb break="no"/>plete ignorance of the Act. The N .W.T. <lb/>
Act was the only law on the subject. <lb/>
Section 92 of the Act provided that "Ex<lb break="no"/>cept by special permission of the Govern-<lb break="yes"/>nor General in Council" (at Ottawa) no <lb/>
intoxicants should be manufactured in <lb/>
certain parts of the Territories. The mere <lb/>
fact that there were such provision in the <lb/>
Act showed that it was contemplated that <lb/>
at some time in the course of the develop<lb break="no"/>ment of the country there might be ne<lb break="no"/>cessity or desirability of allowing the <lb/>
manufacture of liquor. That provision <lb/>
placed beyond the chance of argument the <lb/>
contention that the Act intended a pro<lb break="no"/>hibitory law. Regarding the sale or pos<lb break="no"/>session of liquor the Act provided that <lb/>
there should be none excepting by the <lb/>
special permission in writing of the Lieut. <lb/>
Governor of the Territories. the Act pro<lb break="no"/>hibited the manufacture, sale or possession <lb/>
of liquor only until special permission was <lb/>
given. The Act could not be read partially. <lb/>
To get the intention of it the whole law <lb/>
had to be read together, and even the most <lb/>
casual reading would lead to the belief <lb/>
that the original intention of the Act was <lb/>
that there should be prohibition only so <lb/>
long as conditions required prohibition, <lb/>
and that when the conditions changed the <lb/>
provision made for allowing the manufac<lb break="no"/>ture, sale or possession of liquor should be <lb/>
utilized. This was the reasonable inter<lb break="no"/>pretation of the law. As to the point that <lb/>
the Government usurped the functions <lb/>
of the Legislature in regulating the im<lb break="no"/>portation and sale of liquor in the Yukon, <lb/>
he need only point to the Act, which fail<lb break="no"/>ed to show that the Legislature had any <lb/>
functions under the section dealing with <lb/>
liquor permits. The power of adminis<lb break="no"/>tration was given distinctly to the Lieut.-<lb break="yes"/>Governor. The only thing the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture could possibly do in reagrd to the <lb/>
subject would be to adopt resolutions to <lb/>
guide the Executive Council. It was ex<lb break="no"/>tremely unlikely that the Government, <lb/>
being subject to the will of the House, <lb/>
would exercise their executive functions in <lb/>
a manner contrary to the wish of the <lb/>
House; but the Legislature could not <lb/>
make regulations or Ordinances. All the <lb/>
House could do would be to express an <lb/>
opinion, which could be done in such a <lb/>
way that the Government would have to <lb/>
take it for guidance or give place to a <lb/>
Government which would be so guided. <lb/>
As to the date upon which the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment acted would not say more than <lb/>
that they acted at the very earliest possible <lb/>
moment. The Legislature at last session <lb/>
understood and acquiesced in the position <lb/>
which practically prevented earlier <lb/>
action. In support of his argument on <lb/>
the interpretation of the prohibitory <lb/>
sections of the Act he might quote a note-<lb break="yes"/>able precedent, Governor Royal's 1 per <lb/>
cent permits. It had of course been <lb/>
urged that Lieut.-Governor Royal in<lb break="no"/>fringed the spirit of the law; but the <lb/>
spirit of the law, he thought, depended <lb/>
upon the particular critic for the time be<lb break="no"/>ing . It seemed plain to him that the law <lb/>
intended that liquor might be sold in this <lb/>
country whenever the circumstances of <lb/>
the country warranted the sale. The <lb/>
Territorial expedition itself had not been <lb/>
entered upon until the sum of $6,000 had <lb/>
come to the Assembly funds from the <lb/>
Yukon source. The expense was not un<lb break="no"/>dertaken until the way opened up to meet <lb/>
it without charging the ordinary revenues. <lb/>
The mission had been called speculators, if <lb/>
the Government were obliged to seek ex<lb break="no"/>cuse, they might make an excuse <lb/>
of their success. But they did not <lb/>
need to do that. They had been con<lb break="no"/>fronted with a plain duty, and they un<lb break="no"/>dertook to carry out their duty. If they <lb/>
had not had means for an expedition they <lb/>
would have attempted to apply the law <lb/>
and the regulations otherwise. He would <lb/>
admit that the need of an expedition had <lb/>
not seemed so pressing when they lacked <lb/>
the money for it. Poverty was the root <lb/>
of a great deal of evil, and poverty might <lb/>
have obliged the Government to conclude <lb/>
not to send an expedition. It was for<lb break="no"/>tunate that the money appeared, and from <lb/>
the moment that it was in sight they had <lb/>
no more doubt about the desirability of <lb/>
the expedition. He would point out that <lb/>
when the Legislature was in session the <lb/>
money was not in sight, even if the policy <lb/>
had been in sight. It would have been <lb/>
difficult for the Legislature to point out <lb/>
the plain duty of the Government in face <lb/>
of lack of means. When the money did <lb/>
appear and when the policy was framed <lb/>
and adopted the Legislature was not in ses<lb break="no"/>sion, and the appropriation had to be made <lb/>
under order in council. The result <lb/>
of their policy and their expedition was <lb/>
eminently satisfactory from the financial <lb/>
point of view. Apart from the large <lb/>
receipts from wholesale permits, the ac<lb break="no"/>tual work of the expedition itself had re<lb break="no"/>sulted in the collection, if his informa<lb break="no"/>tion was reliable, of a sum aggregating <lb/>
$28,000, which in itself would very much <lb/>
more than pay its expenses. As to the <lb/>
desirability of the expedition, he expect<lb break="no"/>ed no one would question it. In sending <lb/>
it they had simply followed their plain <lb/>
duty, and attempted to do what in the <lb/>
circumstances ought to have been done <lb/>
even if their jurisdiction had embraced <lb/>
nothing but the administration in rela<lb break="no"/>tion to liquor. It had become a matter <lb/>
of common knowledge that open and un<lb break="no"/>restricted sale of liquor prevailed, with <lb/>
bars open night and day and attended <lb/>
with gambling and immoral devices. <lb/>
And liquor was only one of many mat<lb break="no"/>ters within this jurisdiction which would <lb/>
appeal to the knowledge of the House. <lb/>
There was a great number of adminis<lb break="no"/>trative duties arising with the increasing <lb/>
population in Klondyke. So good an <lb/>
authority as the Minister of the Interior <lb/>
expected an influx of 40,000 people last <lb/>
winter and spring, and this Government <lb/>
thus became responsible for seeing to the <lb/>
administration of all Territorial laws re<lb break="no"/>lating to municipal matters and public <lb/>
health. The expedition was not a whis<lb break="no"/>ky commission; it was sent to carry out <lb/>
all the laws the administration of which, <lb/>
so long as the Yukon was a part of the <lb/>
Territories, devolved upon the Territorial <lb/>
Government. There was the possibility <lb/>
that the district would demand and de<lb break="no"/>serve representation in the Assembly. <lb/>
When the expedition went out there had <lb/>
been no word of the cutting off of the <lb/>
territory,— not the slightest indication, <lb/>
beyond the vague fears expressed in the <lb/>
House of the possible lopping off of <lb/>
territory. In face of last year's resolution <lb/>
adopted by the House, no Government <lb/>
existing on the sufferance of the House <lb/>
could have dared to assume that Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment would set directly in the face of <lb/>
the unanimous wish of the representa<lb break="no"/>

<pb n="10" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-29_Page_010.jpg"/> 

<fw type="dateline">THE LEADER, THURSDAY EVENING, SEPTEMBER 29, 1986 <lb/></fw> <fw type="num">10</fw>


tives in the Assembly. The estimated <lb/>
expected population of the Yukon amount<lb break="no"/>ed to as much as one-half the total popu<lb break="no"/>lation of the organised Territories. There <lb/>
was every reason to expect that before <lb/>
the general election there would require <lb/>
to be a redistribution which would give <lb/>
the Yukon representation the House, <lb/>
in which event accurate information col<lb break="no"/>lected by a member of the Government <lb/>
would have been most desirable. It was <lb/>
true that a different destiny had overtaken <lb/>
the Yukon territory, but he was <lb/>
arguing from the point of view of last <lb/>
winter and from the conditions and cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances and possibilities which the <lb/>
Government had had to consider at the <lb/>
time. The financial side of their policy <lb/>
was fully justified. There was no use inThe Government were taking no part in <lb/>
the Territorial exhibition in the Institute, <lb/>
considering that the matter belonged to <lb/>
the Federal authority which retains ex-<lb break="yes"/>after itself. Referring to Mr. <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
tion. But the subscription would have to <lb/>
be paid, as it was agreed to by an authority <lb/>
competent at the time to make an agree<lb break="no"/>ment for the Territories. For some time <lb/>
Messrs. Redpath and Skinner, Canadian <lb/>
trustees of the Institute, had been them<lb break="no"/>selves paying the Territorial subscription. <lb/>
The time had some for the Territories to <lb/>
carry out the agreement made in their <lb/>
name,- to pay what is owing, but no <lb/>
more. No doubt the intention was excel<lb break="no"/>lent, but there were no such strikingly <lb/>
good results from it as would justify, in <lb/>
the state of Territorial finances, the pay<lb break="no"/>ment of $500 a year or even a lesser <lb/>
amount. The connection would be dis<lb break="no"/>continued. <lb/>
 <lb/>
arguing that they should have known that <lb/>
the territory would be cut off. Even if <lb/>
they had known that their jurisdiction <lb/>
would cease on 14th June, the expedition <lb/>
would still be justified. As to the mission <lb/>
all the particulars to be had before the <lb/>
return of the Commissioner had been <lb/>
given, and he would leave the question to <lb/>
the judgement of the House. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">A FOREIGN APPROPRIATION.</p> 

<p>The next item was one of $750 "to pay <lb/>
the Imperial Institute the proportion of <lb/>
expenses of the Canadian Court allotted <lb/>
to the Territories to Dec., 1898" He <lb/>
said that this one of the rapidly diminish<lb break="no"/>ing items, a few of which remained as a <lb/>
legacy from a previous period when the <lb/>
business of the country was carried on by <lb/>
the Lieut.-Governor and was left in prac<lb break="no"/>tically irresponsible hands. In 1894 the <lb/>
capital amount due on this particular <lb/>
agreement was $1824. The agreement <lb/>
had been made by the Lieut.-Governor <lb/>
and the Minister of Interior, the former <lb/>
in reality, acting upon instructions from <lb/>
the latter; and by it the Department was <lb/>
to provide $1,300, the Territories paying <lb/>
$500. Thus the Territories were commit<lb break="no"/>ted to the payment of that annual amount <lb/>
for the Territorial Court in the Institute. <lb/>
The arrangement would not be renewed. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE VISITING AMERICAN JOURNALISTS.</p> 

<p>Under the heading of Miscellanous <lb/>
there was an item to assist in defraying <lb/>
the expense of the entertainment of <lb/>
parties of members of American press <lb/>
associations. He had been personally <lb/>
present at the entertainment given to one <lb/>
of these parties at Regina. From what <lb/>
he could gather from the very large num<lb break="no"/>ber of papers received, he had no hesita<lb break="no"/>tion at all in stating that he plan was a <lb/>
first rate one. The country had received <lb/>
an amount of practically free and most <lb/>
appreciative advertising in the States <lb/>
represented by these parties through <lb/>
which we could reasonably hope to get an <lb/>
immigration that no expenditure in the <lb/>
way of salaries and expenses of agents <lb/>
could bring about. Certain communities <lb/>
undertook to arrange entertainment for <lb/>
the parties, and the Government was <lb/>
asked to help to defray the expenses. In <lb/>
no case were they proposing to pay more <lb/>
than half the expense incurred by com<lb break="no"/>munities. For every dollar the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would pay, the communities paid a <lb/>
dollar of their own. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">TO CARRY ON NEXT YEAR'S SERVICES.</p> 

<p>In addition to the supplementaries, the <lb/>
House was aksed to appropriate $60,000 <lb/>
for 1899. In changing the financial year <lb/>
they had several ends in view. One aim <lb/>
was to enable the holding of the annual <lb/>
legislative sessions in the early portion of <lb/>
the year instead of in the fall; and in <lb/>
arranging for winter sessions, to enable <lb/>
the public accounts to be brought down <lb/>
within a reasonable time after the closing <lb/>
of the financial year. They had to allow <lb/>
for a certain length of time to elapse <lb/>
between the closing of the year and the <lb/>
closing of the accounts,- either that or <lb/>
make use of Lieut.-Governor's warrants, <lb/>
because the accounts of no business whose <lb/>
year ended on a certain date could be <lb/>
closed up sharp on that date. They had <lb/>
approximated the desirable arrangement <lb/>
now- an unwritten and flexible arrange<lb break="no"/>ment of course- of having the House <lb/>
called early in the year. The Treasury <lb/>
Ordinance allowed one month after <lb/>
the end of the year for the closing <lb/>
of the accounts, and it would not be de<lb break="no"/>sirable to call the House together until <lb/>
four or six weeks after the new year. It <lb/>
was desirable that it should be called <lb/>
not later than he had indicated. It <lb/>
would be unconstitutional for the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to advise prorogation now with <lb/>
dissolution and elections approaching and <lb/>
with a new financial year commencing <lb/>
before the new Legislature could well <lb/>
meet, without asking Supply sufficient <lb/>
to carry on the public business until the <lb/>
new House was likely to meet. The <lb/>
amount so voted would practically settle <lb/>
the period at which the new House <lb/>
would have to be called. In asking an a <lb/>
amount for this purpose they were simply <lb/>
following Canadian constitutional pre<lb break="no"/>cedents- following the regular practice <lb/>
of the provinces. The amount asked <lb/>
($60,000) was not large enough to allow <lb/>
the Government to run on very long <lb/>
without a session. Two-thirds of the <lb/>
amount, or $40,000, would be paid out <lb/>
in January for school grants, leaving <lb/>
only $20,000 to carry on the ordinary <lb/>
business until the House met. So there <lb/>
was no need to apprehend any violent <lb/>
strain, or any attempt on the part of the <lb/>
Government to carry on the business too <lb/>
long without the sanction of the new <lb/>
Legislature. The amount, the House <lb/>
would understand, would have to be re-<lb break="yes"/>voted in the Estimates of the next ses<lb break="no"/>sion. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE LESSON OF THE ESTIMATES. <lb/></p> 

<p>He had now completed the explanation <lb/>
of the Estimates, and had explained in <lb/>
detail and at length, which would save <lb/>
time later on. He thought he had ex<lb break="no"/>plained every important item. Apart <lb/>
from those items there were certain <lb/>
matters which this was an appropriate <lb/>
time to consider. The amount asked in <lb/>
the supplementaries was extraordinarily <lb/>
and unexpectedly large. The most <lb/>
significant feature of the Estimates, it <lb/>
seemed to him, was the fact that <lb/>
although the revenue for this year was so <lb/>
very far in excess of their ordinary reven<lb break="no"/>ue, there appeared to be necessity for all <lb/>
of it. Here they were in the middle or <lb/>
just a little past the middle of a financial <lb/>
year for which Supply had already been <lb/>
voted, and without going outside the fyles <lb/>
of the office,- merely upon the represen<lb break="no"/>tations sent in by members, engineers <lb/>
and others, of work which demanded pub<lb break="no"/>lic expenditure, they easily found ample <lb/>
scope for the application of the extraor<lb break="no"/>dinary revenue. The new departures 

<cb/> 


made were insignificant financially. Up<lb break="no"/>on the old and regular services they easily <lb/>
found places for the disposition of the <lb/>
increase. If they could so easily expend <lb/>
the remarkably large amount- because <lb/>
$162,000 was a remarkably large amount <lb/>
to be supplementary to the regular reven<lb break="no"/>ue, they must conclude that the ordinary <lb/>
revenue was now by no means adequate <lb/>
to supply the ordinary wants of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. This conclusion had been looked <lb/>
upon as not far away before, but it was <lb/>
driven home with force to-day. Then <lb/>
followed the other question. What were <lb/>
they to do? In a single year they were <lb/>
expending upon actual requirements and <lb/>
necessities $162,000 more than in future <lb/>
years they were likely to get. Their <lb/>
necessities were constantly increasing, <lb/>
their services were growing, and the needs <lb/>
would never become less. What were <lb/>
they to do? It was plain that they could <lb/>
not possibly look for any such increases <lb/>
in revenue in future years. But the <lb/>
growth of the services, the extensions of <lb/>
schools, and other conditions obliged them <lb/>
to look for some means of obtaining an in<lb break="no"/>crease in revenue. They were brought <lb/>
to the point which he had discussed last <lb/>
year. The present transitory state <lb/>
was in a way very suitable, yet they <lb/>
were confronted with the fact that it did <lb/>
yield enough money to meet the condi<lb break="no"/>tions. The problem was one which <lb/>
would very soon have to be faced. It <lb/>
was all very well to say that the present <lb/>
institutions were suitable; that was very <lb/>
true. The Territories were not fixed and <lb/>
bound down by Imperial Acts as were <lb/>
the Provinces. We were not bound <lb/>
by fixed agreement or final terms. Our <lb/>
position depended only upon an Act of <lb/>
Parliament which might be amended <lb/>
or changed, and our Vote depended <lb/>
upon the annual will of Parliament, and <lb/>
could be increased at Parliament's pleas<lb break="no"/>ure. If the Territorial financial problem <lb/>
were solved, our present institutions <lb/>
would be suitable for all needs for some <lb/>
time to come. Our legislative jurisdic<lb break="no"/>tion was the same as possessed by the <lb/>
provinces, excepting that we lacked the <lb/>
borrowing power. In all respects, ex<lb break="no"/>cept the financial side, the legislative <lb/>
machinery and position were quite ade<lb break="no"/>quate. But the financial side was vital. <lb/>
The machinery and institutions must <lb/>
have money to keep them in operation. <lb/>
However excellent or desirable those in<lb break="no"/>stitutions, the country was confronted with <lb/>
the fact that the machinery and institu<lb break="no"/>tions were no longer feasible if side by <lb/>
side with them there was failure from <lb/>
the financial point of view. There seem<lb break="no"/>ed to be only one thing to do, only one <lb/>
step to take to relieve the position; and <lb/>
they should prepare for that step as prac<lb break="no"/>tical men, not as theorists. The argu<lb break="no"/>ment that provincial establishment meant <lb/>
taxation might be a very useful argument <lb/>
with which to appeal to the populace, <lb/>
and with which to carry meetings, but <lb/>
to men who take the trouble to see all <lb/>
sides of the question there was only one <lb/>
conclusion to come to, and that was that <lb/>
very little hope existed of relieving the <lb/>
atrain except by the Territories taking <lb/>
the final step and entering the confedera<lb break="no"/>tion of provinces. It could not reason<lb break="no"/>ably be hoped that Parliament would give <lb/>
the necessary increase in the present grants; <lb/>
and in his view it would be the principal <lb/>
work of the new Legislature at least be<lb break="no"/>fore the end of the next term to open <lb/>
negotiations for t he entrance of the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories into confederation. Personally <lb/>
he was not an ardent provincialist. He <lb/>
had always taken the ground that it was <lb/>
well to make haste slowly, and so long <lb/>
as we could work out our own salvation <lb/>
he favored the present status. But if <lb/>
we could not get the necessary revenues <lb/>
we simply could not continue to carry <lb/>
on the business. He had no hesitation <lb/>
in saying that even within the next <lb/>
year they would be unable to provide <lb/>
fully for the ordinary services with the <lb/>
pressent ordinary revenue. The rate at which <lb/>
the schools were growing while very grati<lb break="no"/>fying was none the less embarrassing. In <lb/>
every direction there was increasing <lb/>
growth, and every step of development <lb/>
in the school system meant an additional <lb/>
demand on the exchequer. There was <lb/>
every reason now to look for much more <lb/>
rapid growth than in the past. Every <lb/>
thing seemed to have taken a favorable <lb/>
turn. The Yukon had advertised the <lb/>
North-West Territories all over the civil<lb break="no"/>ised world, and more attention would be <lb/>
called to this country when the results <lb/>
of the present harvest became known. <lb/>
There was every indication of a flow of im<lb break="no"/>migration which unfortunately, however <lb/>
ardently hoped for, had not materialised <lb/>
in past years. So they had to look for<lb break="no"/>ward to increased inroads on the revenue <lb/>
available for schools and public works. <lb/>
To have to reduce the school grants would <lb/>
be a very distasteful necessity, but it <lb/>
would be a necessity in the near future <lb/>
if the present rate of increase in the <lb/>
school attendance continued, and if some <lb/>
remedy was not found financially. He <lb/>
thought unless the remedy was found the <lb/>
present school grants could not be con<lb break="no"/>tinued for more than two years longer; and <lb/>
even next year, with the revenue no larger <lb/>
than the present year's ordinary revenue, <lb/>
when the amounts for schools were pro<lb break="no"/>vided little would be left for public works <lb/>
and other purposes. As practical men <lb/>
they must conclude that the present in<lb break="no"/>stitutions would not do if joined with the <lb/>
financial embarrassment. Outside of the <lb/>
method of direct taxation for only meth<lb break="no"/>od open was to negotiate for entrance to <lb/>
confederation. There was no question <lb/>
that when we went in we would receive <lb/>
more money than we receive now. <lb/>
Whether we would receive all that the <lb/>
Territories would be entitled to was a <lb/>
different question, depending on the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and Legislature of the day, de<lb break="no"/>pending on the men entrusted with <lb/>
the negotiations. The settlement would <lb/>
not be consummated to-day, nor possibly <lb/>
next year, but the question was one which <lb/>
it seemed to him the new Legislature <lb/>
would have to take up, and he thought <lb/>
it was the most important question that <lb/>
the new Legislature would have to deal <lb/>
with. He made this statement for the <lb/>
Government as showing that the future <lb/>
attitude of this Government would have <lb/>
the end of the provincial establishment in <lb/>
view. <choice><sic>The</sic><corr></corr></choice></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">VISION WAS NOT ALTOGETHER GOLDEN. <lb/></p> 

<p>He had no thought that the change would <lb/>
make us wealthy. He had called atten<lb break="no"/>tion last year to the fact that when the <lb/>
Territories are erected under provincial <lb/>
establishment we would have to provide <lb/>
for several services which were no pro<lb break="no"/>vided by the Federal Parliament. <lb/>
Among these items was the administra<lb break="no"/>tion of justice which, exclusive of the <lb/>
salaries of the judges, costs $32,000 a <lb/>
year; towards agricultural societies in <lb/>
the Territories the Dominion pays $7,000 <lb/>
annually; $15,000 was expended last year <lb/>
and $5,000 was being expended this year <lb/>
in aid of creameries in the Territories, <lb/>
besides $200,000 last year and $165,000 <lb/>
this year passed in aid of dairying gener<lb break="no"/>ally, a large part of which was expended <lb/>
for the benefit of the Territories. The <lb/>
question of dairying was, by the way, <lb/>
one which confronted the Assembly; at <lb/>
no distant date no doubt they would be <lb/>
obliged to deal with that subject. The <lb/>
Mounted Police expenditure- $385,000 <lb/>
last year and $353,000 this year, of <lb/>
course he would always argue was an <lb/>
expenditure upon a federal force. The <lb/>
police were a federal necessity on account


<cb/>


of the Indians, and were not for local <lb/>
purposes. The Dominion Public Works <lb/>
department made may expenditures in <lb/>
the North-West for objects of provincial <lb/>
character. The Dominion built no jails <lb/>
nor court houses in the provinces. All <lb/>
these services, now carried out at federal <lb/>
expense, would fall upon the local <lb/>
authority under provincial establishment. <lb/>
Then there was the vote from which the <lb/>
Assembly derived the bulk of its rev<lb break="no"/>enues,- the vote for Government of the <lb/>
North-West Territories,- $358,000 last <lb/>
year, of which $282,000 came to the <lb/>
Assembly. The balance, expended from <lb/>
Ottawa, was for strictly domestic matters, <lb/>
including the maintenance of insane <lb/>
patients, the land titles offices, the ex<lb break="no"/>penses of Lieut.-Governor's office and <lb/>
Government House. besides the foregoing <lb/>
the Dominion was this year expending <lb/>
$150,000 upon surveys in the North-<lb break="yes"/>West, an item which would be charged <lb/>
against the capital account of the <lb/>
Territories, and which belonged to the <lb/>
domestic side, although so long as the <lb/>
Dominion holds the Crown lands the item <lb/>
could not be properly chargeable against <lb/>
us. However, he hoped that some day <lb/>
the item would appear in the Territorial <lb/>
Estimates. He certainly believed that <lb/>
we were as much entitled to </p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">POSSESSION OF EVERY ACRE <lb/></p> 

<p>of public lands as was any of the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. The bargain with the Hudson's <lb/>
Bay Company, by which a paltry amount <lb/>
was paid over from the Dominion <lb/>
treasury, was not to buy the country but <lb/>
to extinguish an imaginary title. The <lb/>
mere fact of that bargain did not in any <lb/>
sense constitute ownership. He believed <lb/>
that when we became erected into a <lb/>
province we would be as much entitled to <lb/>
all the lands, mines, hay and timber <lb/>
as the other provinces which hold and <lb/>
derive the revenues from these sources. <lb/>
It would be an important, difficult and <lb/>
perhaps delicate task to discuss this <lb/>
matter in the negotiations, but he did not <lb/>
believe it was a matter to be left at the <lb/>
bare dictation of Parliament. Although <lb/>
Parliament possessed the right to erect <lb/>
a province or provinces, the question of <lb/>
the lands and minerals involved a larger <lb/>
constitutional and legal right. His own <lb/>
opinion was that there was a strictly legal <lb/>
right to depend upon, and that such right <lb/>
might be successfully prosecuted before <lb/>
the highest tribunal in the realm if <lb/>
necessary. (Prolonged applause.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">ONE GRAND, UNITED, STRONG PROVINCE. </p> 

<p>There was only one way to begin the <lb/>
negotiations for erection as a province-<lb break="yes"/>not as provinces. He had had the mis<lb break="no"/>fortune to hear in that room an expression <lb/>
of a wish for division. There was no <lb/>
sound grounds for such a wish. Such <lb/>
desire was not founded upon any sound <lb/>
reason relating to administration or ex<lb break="no"/>penditure or anything else. It was an <lb/>
expression simply of local ambitions. He <lb/>
did not believe a single argument had <lb/>
ever been advanced in favor of division <lb/>
other than the desire of some locality <lb/>
relating to the capital establishment and <lb/>
the incidental local expenditure attending <lb/>
such establishment. (Applause.) He <lb/>
had heard a number of speeches but he <lb/>
hd not yet heard a single convincing <lb/>
argument in favor of division. It seemed <lb/>
to him that there was every reason for a <lb/>
single province. As far as concerned <lb/>
administration, where was the difficulty? <lb/>
What point was so remote in these <lb/>
days of telephones, telegraphs and rail<lb break="no"/>ways, - and in later days doubtless these <lb/>
conveniences would grow in scope and <lb/>
usefulness,- what point was so remote <lb/>
that the affairs of government could not <lb/>
be administered as well practically, so far <lb/>
as distance went, from the North Pole as <lb/>
from any other point? With one province <lb/>
they would avoid the elaboration of gov<lb break="no"/>ernments; they would have one strong <lb/>
and efficient set of machinery instead of a <lb/>
duplication of trebling of functionaries. <lb/>
So far as concerned any differences of in<lb break="no"/>terest or geographical location, there was <lb/>
not a single argument. In the Territories <lb/>
there was a great diversity of interest, but <lb/>
there was no conflict of interests. He <lb/>
had been a member of that House for <lb/>
ten years and of the North-West Council <lb/>
which preceded it; he had, he thought, <lb/>
taken a fairly active share in the work, <lb/>
and he could say that he did not recollect <lb/>
any single occasion when there had been <lb/>
any conflict in the interest upon any question <lb/>
raised in the House. That the situation <lb/>
showed diversity of interests, of conditions, <lb/>
of climate and of population was certain, <lb/>
which simply made the necessary diversity of <lb/>
treatment. That there had been any <lb/>
failure to deal with the diversified in<lb break="no"/>terests and conditions could not be suc<lb break="no"/>cessfully charged. They frequently made <lb/>
exceptions in the laws in favor of different <lb/>
areas with different conditions. There <lb/>
never had been conflict. All the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives had always had a ready hearing <lb/>
and had had full scope to carry out what <lb/>
was best for their particular part of the <lb/>
country. He did not mention this topic <lb/>
because of any indication in the House <lb/>
respecting conflicting interests, but there <lb/>
had been cries in the country, and he had <lb/>
heard rumors of such places as Alberta, <lb/>
Assiniboia and Saskatchewan. These <lb/>
places were never heard of in the House <lb/>
in relation to legislation or administration. <lb/>
He would strongly depreciate such cries at <lb/>
this particular and critical point in the <lb/>
history of the country. Now was the <lb/>
time to drop all local, or conflicting ques<lb break="no"/>tions and stand shoulder to shoulder on <lb/>
the important question which affected no <lb/>
one portion but all of the Territories as a <lb/>
unit. We had not yet population equal <lb/>
to the number of inhabitants of one eas<lb break="no"/>tern city, but the resources and the <lb/>
opportunities which were ours should <lb/>
nerve us to make the best effort <lb/>
to do the best with those resources <lb/>
and opportunities, and to push forward in <lb/>
the direction best for the future of the <lb/>
Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">NO LACK OF POLICY. <lb/></p> 

<p>At this point Mr. Haultain stated that he <lb/>
feared he was taking up too much time, <lb/>
but there were cried of Go on, Go on. <lb/>
Proceeding he said he would like to make <lb/>
some reference to the matter of policy. <lb/>
He thought no one could say, even in re<lb break="no"/>gard to those supplementary estimates <lb/>
alone, that there was any lack of policy. <lb/>
In every item there was policy cropping <lb/>
up. He made a hasty review of the items. <lb/>
The item for civil government involved a <lb/>
policy, - the policy of maintaining efficient <lb/>
departments, developing the public ser<lb break="no"/>vice for the convenience of the people, of <lb/>
having the public business done system<lb break="no"/>atically, and for providing machinery for <lb/>
carrying on the work with efficiency and <lb/>
economy.The items for schools were as<lb break="no"/>sociated with their educational policy, <lb/>
which no one would deny was in the <lb/>
right direction,- a policy to give a good <lb/>
plain practical education to every child in <lb/>
the Territories, and to have the children <lb/>
associated and educated together without <lb/>
any regard to race, religion or other con<lb break="no"/>sideration; they had avoided a number of <lb/>
the delicate and difficult questions which <lb/>
had divided the people in some of the <lb/>
provinces, and to-day the Territorial sys<lb break="no"/>tem was, if not in name, in reality a na<lb break="no"/>tional school system- if not in name, it <lb/>
was merely by reason of a certain constitu<lb break="no"/>tional right which he would not wish to, <lb/>
and there was to reason to, disturb. <lb/>
Their policy was to group all the children <lb/>
in the public schools regardless of class or <lb/>
position, creed or nationality, and their <lb/>
policy aimed at the extension of the sys<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

tem as far and as wide as the resources <lb/>
would allow. They paid as liberal <lb/>
grants to schools as any country in the <lb/>
world, which grants made it possible for <lb/>
the smallest conceivable community or <lb/>
collection of individuals to have a school <lb/>
and made it possible for nearly every child, <lb/>
- for every child except in very isolated <lb/>
localities to receive the advantages of a <lb/>
plain, common education. The aim of <lb/>
the system was to give a good common <lb/>
education rather than to support the <lb/>
higher branches. The Government be<lb break="no"/>lieved of course in higher education, and <lb/>
in time they would have to extend in that <lb/>
direction; but as yet they found the <lb/>
necessity of being strictly practical, situat<lb break="no"/>ed as they were yet in the position of <lb/>
settlers and pioneers. The development <lb/>
of the public, moon schools was the <lb/>
whole object as yet. The results of their <lb/>
policy in regard to the training of teachers <lb/>
they could look upon already with pride. <lb/>
The Territories were becoming independ<lb break="no"/>ent of the eastern provinces in the matter <lb/>
of supply of teachers. Of the higher <lb/>
grade teachers the supply was exceeding <lb/>
the demand. The item for inspection of <lb/>
coal mines indicated a policy,- a policy to <lb/>
look after the interests and lives of the <lb/>
men toiling in the mines; the item was <lb/>
small but it met the actual requirements. <lb/>
The public works items revealed policy,-<lb break="yes"/>the policy to do what was required to be <lb/>
done as substaintially as possible, and to <lb/>
distribute the amounts available for <lb/>
public works equitably between the <lb/>
natural divisions of the country, - a policy <lb/>
to provide first the most needful and im<lb break="no"/>portant works in the way of main high<lb break="no"/>ways, bridges, and water supply. They <lb/>
had a policy respecting surveys,- very <lb/>
important because it concerned the means <lb/>
of communication with markets and be<lb break="no"/>tween centres. In regard to Agriculture <lb/>
they were devising a policy in keeping <lb/>
with the traditions of the North-West <lb/>
Government. All their institutions had <lb/>
begun small and grown slowly. The <lb/>
agricultural policy now proposed was <lb/>
proportionate with their resources if not <lb/>
with their needs. The Government had <lb/>
recognized the necessity of action in the <lb/>
line of encouragement of those industries <lb/>
which are the foundation of all possible <lb/>
prosperity in this country; and as soon as <lb/>
money became available their policy ap<lb break="no"/>peared. The items under the heading of <lb/>
Hospitals, Charities and Public Health <lb/>
indicated policy,- the policy of avoiding <lb/>
a large number of institutions which <lb/>
might constitute a sort of invitation to <lb/>
helpless classes. The item for Yukon <lb/>
expenses was connected with a very <lb/>
distinct policy in relation to the adminis<lb break="no"/>tration of affairs in the Yukon, - a policy <lb/>
for which the Government claimed credit; <lb/>
it was a policy to assert the self govern<lb break="no"/>ing rights of the people of the Territories <lb/>
and to resist the arbitrary stack of the <lb/>
Federal Government which attempted to <lb/>
take away certain of those self-governing <lb/>
rights. They had grappled with the <lb/>
difficulties of far-off conditions,-difficul<lb break="no"/>ties which, to judge by some of the cri<lb break="no"/>ticisms of their policy, were extremely <lb/>
dangerous. But their policy shirked <lb/>
neither the difficulties nor dangers. <lb/>
The Government took their decided stand <lb/>
in connection with the Yukon question <lb/>
not so much in their own behalf as in <lb/>
behalf of the self-governing machinery <lb/>
which members of the Governmennt had <lb/>
taken considerable hand and part in obtain<lb break="no"/>ing for the Territories. For policy he would <lb/>
also point to the Statutes. He need not <lb/>
enumerate the laws and Ordinances, <lb/>
every one of which was associated with <lb/>
distinct policy. Some people were ask<lb break="no"/>ing, What was the policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment? In certain small communities <lb/>
there were men who seemed to be sitting <lb/>
waiting for something, for some new and <lb/>
brilliant scheme with which the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would appeal to the country at the <lb/>
election. He might say at once that there <lb/>
would be no appeal to the House or to the <lb/>
country on any new policy, or on any <lb/>
policy not appearing in the Estimates or <lb/>
as written in every page of their Statute <lb/>
book. The Government's policy would <lb/>
not be found in flippant speeches calcu<lb break="no"/>lated to tickle the ears and to arouse <lb/>
the short-lived enthusiasm of audiences, <lb/>
nor in bald resolutions. Their policy <lb/>
was one of practical legislation,- a policy <lb/>
to deal wisely with actual conditions for <lb/>
the best interest of the country and the <lb/>
people. The names of the Ordinances <lb/>
he need not repeat,- were they not writ<lb break="no"/>ten in the book of the Statutes? And <lb/>
could not the members of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment reasonably claim that they had been <lb/>
mainly instrumental in the initiation and <lb/>
framing of all the legislation within the <lb/>
past ten years? He did not make the <lb/>
claim as a boast. People who were <lb/>
searching for the Government's policy <lb/>
needed only to read the Statutes and they <lb/>
would find a policy worthy of their time and <lb/>
attention and which if they followed close<lb break="no"/>ly enough could not fail to make them <lb/>
wiser and better citizens. Only one sug<lb break="no"/>gestion had ever been made within his <lb/>
knowledge by these people who clamored <lb/>
for a policy. He would say that the <lb/>
Government did not ask to be supplied <lb/>
with a policy by the critics. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was never so badly off that they <lb/>
needed to trouble themselves searching <lb/>
for policies. But in all the criticisms and <lb/>
in all the little remarks made by little <lb/>
writers in little newspapers re<lb break="no"/>specting the no-policy of the <lb/>
Government, he had failed to see <lb/>
any indication of suggestion to supply the <lb/>
alleged lack. They did not ask their <lb/>
critics to make them a policy; and if the <lb/>
critics had suggested policies the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would likely have been glad <lb/>
not to be able to accept them. But <lb/>
approaching the end of a term of <lb/>
the Assembly, the critics ought to <lb/>
come down and be a little more definite. <lb/>
It would certainly be unfair to ask them <lb/>
to give away their hands, if they hold <lb/>
any hands, but they should surely be able <lb/>
to show where there had been deficiency, <lb/>
- to show that where, concerning any <lb/>
individual, class or interest, action had <lb/>
been demanded, action had not been tak<lb break="no"/>en. It was surely time now for these <lb/>
dumb oracles to speak. But they speak <lb/>
not, and there is heard only the general <lb/>
and unsatisfactory statement that the <lb/>
Government have no policy. From now <lb/>
on he was going to ay in answer to that <lb/>
statement, What policy? Policy upon <lb/>
what? The policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was crystallized upon the <lb/>
pages of the statute book of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. They had so dealt with every <lb/>
subject calling for attention that in all <lb/>
the criticisms there was failure to show <lb/>
any deficiencies. On the question of <lb/>
Dominion political lines in local affairs, <lb/>
the Government had a distinct policy. <lb/>
The Government's belief was that there <lb/>
was sufficiently important business in the <lb/>
Assembly and to be dealt with by the <lb/>
Government upon which party divisions <lb/>
could arise, and when the divisions came <lb/>
the Government would be prepared to take <lb/>
their own part and fight out their own <lb/>
side. But they would oppose the in<lb break="no"/>troduction of lines and names and cries <lb/>
which had nothing to do with the business <lb/>
entrusted to the Government and to the <lb/>
House. The single item of suggested de<lb break="no"/>ficiency in their policy was in respect of <lb/>
immigration. In one sense the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment did not have a policy on that sub<lb break="no"/>ject. They attempted nothing in the <lb/>
way of fitting out agents to scour the by<lb break="no"/>ways of the world, and compel people to <lb/>
come here. They did not have a policy <lb/>
because they did not have jurisdiction. <lb/>

<cb/>

In the North-West constitution the <lb/>
subject of immigration was expressly left <lb/>
out. They had no legal right to deal <lb/>
with the subject. But on the other hand <lb/>
even if they had the right they would not <lb/>
do differently. Their policy relating to <lb/>
immigration, for they had a policy, was a <lb/>
solid policy to attempt to meet the needs <lb/>
of the people who are in th ecountry and <lb/>
the people who may come to the <lb/>
Territories, by providing roads, bridges <lb/>
and means of communication, schools <lb/>
and other useful institutions throughout <lb/>
the country so as to be available for all, <lb/>
even for those settled in remote parts; to <lb/>
provide economical and efficient adminis<lb break="no"/>tration of the laws, and to make good <lb/>
laws suitable and applicable to the <lb/>
peculiar and particular conditions of <lb/>
the Territories The Government did <lb/>
not propose legislation because similar <lb/>
laws had been adopted in Ontario or any<lb break="no"/>where else. They endeavored to make <lb/>
laws suitable to the conditions of the <lb/>
people and localities of this country. <lb/>
They believed that this was a good im<lb break="no"/>migration policy,- to provide ready means <lb/>
of communication to the country, to pro<lb break="no"/>mote a harmonious state of society, and <lb/>
to assist in making the conditions of the <lb/>
communities of the country such that <lb/>
people could live in them and be pros<lb break="no"/>perous and contended. They provided <lb/>
roads and bridges, good schools and good <lb/>
Institutions of all necessary, advisable and <lb/>
possible kinds, with this object. They <lb/>
offered to people seeking homes a coun<lb break="no"/>try free from debt and practically free <lb/>
from taxation; and the Government <lb/>
believed that, in the financial position of <lb/>
the Assembly, their immigration policy <lb/>
was the best which could be devised for <lb/>
years to come. Mr. Haultain thanked <lb/>
the house for the patient hearing given <lb/>
an exceedingly long and, he was afraid, <lb/>
dry speech. He had detailed the Esti<lb break="no"/>mates, and hoped he had not overlooked <lb/>
any material fact or important point. <lb/>
He trusted that the Estimates would <lb/>
meet the views of the House and if pass<lb break="no"/>ed adequately meet the idea of helping all <lb/>
the interests of the country and maintain <lb/>
efficiently the public service. Having <lb/>
spoken a little more than three hours <lb/>
the Premier sat down amid the enthu<lb break="no"/>siastic plaudits of the members. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">MR. MOWAT</persName> (SOUTH REGINA)</p> 

<p>said that in the absence of the leader of <lb/>
the Opposition and his first lieutenant, <lb/>
it would devolve upon himself to make <lb/>
some reply to the able deliverance the <lb/>
House had listened to, and he felt quite <lb/>
unequal to the task. However, he had <lb/>
always assumed the role of opposition to <lb/>
his friend the hon. leader of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. He recognised in Mr. Haul-<lb break="yes"/>tain an able leader,- the ablest man in <lb/>
the House and the best fitted to fulfill <lb/>
the duties of the position he occupied. <lb/>
But there was necessity for some oppo<lb break="no"/>sition. It did not matter how good a <lb/>
Government was, there were bound to be <lb/>
some flaws in its acts,- something to <lb/>
pick a hole in, and to which improve<lb break="no"/>ment might be suggested. But to criti<lb break="no"/>cise so able and lucid an exposition as <lb/>
given that day by Mr. Haultain was not <lb/>
an easy matter. He would have to go <lb/>
back to last year's Estimates for points <lb/>
to criticse. The leader had made very <lb/>
clear explanation of the necessity of in<lb break="no"/>crease in the civil service, but he <lb/>
thought the increase was going beyond <lb/>
the ability of the country. There was no <lb/>
tangible evidence of increase in the popu<lb break="no"/>lation equal to the increase in the service. <lb/>
He could not understand why the depart<lb break="no"/>mental work had grown so largely. The <lb/>
Government were lavish and extravagant <lb/>
in the salaries. These should not be <lb/>
gauged by salaries paid in the East. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>- Certainly not, they <lb/>
should be larger here. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName> thought they should be <lb/>
gauged by the ability of the country to <lb/>
pay. He admitted that living costs a <lb/>
little more here. They had one official <lb/>
drawing more salary than the leader of <lb/>
the Government. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>- That may easily be re-<lb break="yes"/>mended. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName> thought the members of <lb/>
the Government were getting as much as <lb/>
the country could afford to pay. If they <lb/>
were in the East undoubtedly they would <lb/>
be worth higher salaries, because the pro<lb break="no"/>vinces were better able to pay. When <lb/>
the Government saw ahead financial hard <lb/>
times, as the House had been told, they <lb/>
should have guarded against that day by <lb/>
curtailing the expenses. Another official <lb/>
drawing a high salary was the deputy pub<lb break="no"/>lic works commissioner. He would not <lb/>
deprecate the best man for the position, and, <lb/>
in the rich provinces, would be worth all <lb/>
he received <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> the Territories could <lb/>
not afford to pay such high-priced men. <lb/>
Mr. Mowat condemned the Government <lb/>
because the Consolidated Ordinances were <lb/>
not printed. The expenditure upon the <lb/>
consolidation last year was largely wasted. <lb/>
The Government had of course explained <lb/>
the failure to print. They said tenders <lb/>
were called, and the lowest tenderer re<lb break="no"/>fused to agree to turn out the work with<lb break="no"/>in the time desired. Even after the ex<lb break="no"/>planation he (Mr. Mowat) still felt that <lb/>
some other reason existed. Perhaps the <lb/>
time limit was put on to prevent the suc<lb break="no"/>cessful tenderer from doing the work. <lb/>
The Government said that other tender<lb break="no"/>ers were ready to do it within the time. <lb/>
Mr. Mowat believed there was one other <lb/>
party who could do it because he had a <lb/>
great part of the work up in type. Pos<lb break="no"/>sibly the Government knowing this and <lb/>
wanting their favorite to get the work <lb/>
put on the time limit for the purpose of <lb/>
giving their friend the contract. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>- Name the friend. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName> - Make your own inference. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>- By what we are hearing <lb/>
this afternoon, it is hard to know who are <lb/>
one's friends. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName>- Oh, you have quite a <lb/>
number. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>- Hear, hear. <lb/></p> 

<p>Turning to the matter of the Peace <lb/>
River road expenditure, Mr., Mowat no<lb break="no"/>ticed that the House heard none of the <lb/>
eloquence which the member for Victoria <lb/>
and other Northern Alberta members <lb/>
poured fourth last year respecting the Ed<lb break="no"/>monton route. The Assembly had been <lb/>
lamentably short sighted in voting money <lb/>
towards that road. The money <lb/>
was thrown away. Parties who <lb/>
were misled and who went in <lb/>
by Edmonton were now coming back and <lb/>
cursing the route. The House no doubt <lb/>
felt the humiliation of the mistake. Any<lb break="no"/>way the silence on the subject of the <lb/>
Edmonton route this session was a great <lb/>
contrast to the noise made last session. <lb/>
The Commissioner of Public Works had <lb/>
had a pleasant excursion over the road, <lb/>
but the House had got no inkling relating <lb/>
to the trip, excepting its cost ($100). Be <lb/>
could not cavil at the cost. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MALO3">Mr. Maloney</persName>- Very cheap. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MALO3">Mr. Maloney</persName> said the opening of the road <lb/>
put more money in Mr. Maloney's district <lb/>
than was justifiable. He had noticed last <lb/>
year that Mr. Maloney had been hob<lb break="no"/>nobbing a great deal with the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner no doubt making good use of Irish <lb/>
blarney. The result was to be seen in <lb/>
the amounts spent in St. Albert. Mr. <lb/>
Mowat condemned the taking over of the <lb/>
Irrigation administration. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment refused to touch immigration, quite <lb/>
rightly. They should have refused to <lb/>
touch irrigation as well. It was argued <lb/>
that irrigation was an assistance to certain <lb/>
settlers, but the interest and assistance <lb/>
were not wide spread. In any case the 


<cb/>

settlers were not deprived of irrigation <lb/>
before. There had been irrigation legis<lb break="no"/>lation for several years. The taking over <lb/>
of the department was premature. It <lb/>
was another department taken over un<lb break="no"/>necessarily before the time was ripe. <lb/>
Referring to what he termed the very able <lb/>
reports of Mr. Dennis respecting the <lb/>
benefits of the transfer. Mr. Mowat said <lb/>
he thought that Mr. Dennis, would he <lb/>
advised that the administration could be <lb/>
done at Regina for half what it as cost<lb break="no"/>ing at Ottawa, was looking out for him<lb break="no"/>self. It was a mistake to accept the ad<lb break="no"/>ministration for less than it had been <lb/>
costing. Ever cent should have been <lb/>
demanded. And he believed that Mr. <lb/>
Dennis was getting an extra $900 through <lb/>
the transfer. ( <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Several members</persName>,- Hear, <lb/>
hear.) Mr. Mowat held that the deputy <lb/>
commissioner should give his whole time <lb/>
to the department for which the Assembly <lb/>
paid him $2,000. The Public Works <lb/>
Estimates were so mixed that Mr. Mowat <lb/>
could not understand them nor distin<lb break="no"/>guish them. Each member might be able <lb/>
to find his own, but one could not tell what <lb/>
the other fellow was getting. It was bad <lb/>
policy to imitate the provincial and <lb/>
Dominion plan of making the Estimates <lb/>
intricate. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MALO3">Mr. Maloney</persName> - How did you manage <lb/>
to find the St. Albert items? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName> found fault became no <lb/>
printed statement of the estimated rev<lb break="no"/>enues had been given the House. (Mr. <lb/>
Haultain at once sent to Mr. Mowat a <lb/>
type written statement.) He had no <lb/>
fault to find with Mr. Robson's appoint<lb break="no"/>ment as law clerk. He had recognised as <lb/>
far back as his first session in the House <lb/>
the serious need of a law clerk. The <lb/>
first break he made in the House was <lb/>
with a new school bill, the provisions of <lb/>
which bill he took pride in saying were <lb/>
still the main provisions of the school <lb/>
law. In fact the school law emanated <lb/>
from himself, although somewhat im<lb break="no"/>proved since he introduced it. But when <lb/>
he brought in that bill and ever since he <lb/>
had seen the need of a law clerk. The <lb/>
appointment was a good one. Mr. <lb/>
Robson was one of the ablest lawyers in <lb/>
the country. He had known him from <lb/>
boyhood, and had the greatest respect for <lb/>
him both in regard to ability and applica<lb break="no"/>tion. He did not agree with the next <lb/>
appointment, that of Mr. Peterson as <lb/>
Agriculture deputy. What were his <lb/>
qualifications? With a small primitive <lb/>
department it was a mistake to allot a <lb/>
salary as high as $1,200. The depart<lb break="no"/>ment was only of minor importance as yet. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANON1">Hon. members</persName>- No, no. <lb/></p> 

<p>As to public works Mr. Mowat had no <lb/>
complaint to make for his own district. <lb/>
He admitted that the princple of not <lb/>
equally dividing between electoral dis<lb break="no"/>tricts was proper. In the Education <lb/>
items the Premier had omitted to ex<lb break="no"/>plain the vote for paying certain district <lb/>
debentures; he had not referred to that <lb/>
among the various policies he enunciated. <lb/>
Mr. Mowat opposed the principle of pay<lb break="no"/>ing the debenture indebtedness of school <lb/>
districts which have failed through the <lb/>
removal of inhabitants. It was a danger<lb break="no"/>ous precedent to establish. The money <lb/>
lenders when they advance money know <lb/>
the risks they assume, and should bear <lb/>
the risks. He could see no reason <lb/>
for the vote. The plan to initiate <lb/>
agricultural experimental work he <lb/>
also opposed. That matter devolved <lb/>
upon the Dominion. The Dominion's <lb/>
work at Indian Head was bearing good <lb/>
results. The North-West lacked the means <lb/>
to cope with such, and the vote the <lb/>
House was asked to pass was too small <lb/>
to do any good. He looked at the scheme <lb/>
as an election dodge. The policy would <lb/>
he heralded in the newspapers. Every <lb/>
Tom, Dick, and Harry would think they <lb/>
had just the ability for farm instructors <lb/>
and just the right farm for the experi<lb break="no"/>ments, and they would apply to Mr. <lb/>
Ross, who with $2,500 was going to do <lb/>
the whole business. Mr. R as would say, <lb/>
Just hold on, we can't attend to this thing <lb/>
all at once. Before the refusal would have <lb/>
to be given the elections would be over. <lb/>
If the Assembly could prevail on the Do<lb break="no"/>minion to spread their experiments, it <lb/>
would be good policy. He would favor <lb/>
asking the Dominion to do so, and it <lb/>
would be all right to assist the Dominion <lb/>
with $2,500, but he thought that amount <lb/>
unaided would not accomplish much. <lb/>
He had heard they were to have a new <lb/>
scheme respecting agricultural societies. <lb/>
Where was it gone to? Mr. Ross had <lb/>
submitted a printed plan or sketch of a <lb/>
new scheme before the Agricultural Com<lb break="no"/>mittee; he seemed to have taken back <lb/>
water. Personally he approved the <lb/>
scheme, and only wished Mr. Ross had <lb/>
had the back bone to press it. On the <lb/>
Yukon question Mr. Mowat said he had <lb/>
never questioned the advisability of the <lb/>
Government's policy. They were to be <lb/>
commended for grappling with the <lb/>
situation. His objection was that action <lb/>
was not taken early enough, and he <lb/>
could not agree with the Premier's <lb/>
statement that the Legislature had no <lb/>
power to pass ordinances on the subject <lb/>
of Yukon liquor. He claimed that the <lb/>
Legislature had the power after the 1st <lb/>
Oct., 1897. The Government should <lb/>
have taken the House into its confidence. <lb/>
The House rose on 15th Dec., and on <lb/>
28th Dec. orders in council were being <lb/>
passed. The claim was made that the <lb/>
Government could not act because they <lb/>
were poverty stricken. Mr Haultain <lb/>
certainly knew that the $6,000 was <lb/>
coming. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> - No. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName> said the Government knew <lb/>
that the Lieut.-Governor had been issuing <lb/>
liquor permits. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> - No. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName> held that in any caase the <lb/>
Government should have got the sanction <lb/>
of the House for their course. It was <lb/>
strange that of the emissaries sent out a <lb/>
part had returned and of the other part <lb/>
they could get no word. There was some<lb break="no"/>thing wrong. There was a nigger in the <lb/>
fence. The Government should feel anx<lb break="no"/>ious in that peculiar circumstance. He <lb/>
expected that they would have sent a spe<lb break="no"/>cial messenger to meet Mr. Bulyea and <lb/>
hurry him up. He would like to know <lb/>
where Bulyea was. Perhaps he was afraid <lb/>
to come back and give an account. Bul<lb break="no"/>yea was a strong temperance man and <lb/>
perhaps had made a muddle of the busi<lb break="no"/>ness. Perhaps he had instituted a tem<lb break="no"/>perance question or a question of prohi<lb break="no"/>bition in the Yukon. Concluding, Mr. <lb/>
Mowat said he would like to go at the <lb/>
Executive Council, but they were good <lb/>
fellows, and in one way he hated to pitch <lb/>
into them. Now that he was leaving the <lb/>
House, he hoped that he enjoyed their <lb/>
good will. They had had their tilts, and <lb/>
often he had beencalled down, but he <lb/>
was not thin skinned. The five executive <lb/>
councillors were men of ability. In <lb/>
fact he thought that the ability of <lb/>
the House sat on the right side of <lb/>
Mr. Speaker, where he himself had his <lb/>
seat. Mr. Haultain was a good first min<lb break="no"/>ister, and Mr. Ross was capable, ami<lb break="no"/>able and agreeable first lieutenant. Of <lb/>
the remaining members, one perhaps de<lb break="no"/>voted a little too much attention to bridg<lb break="no"/>ing in Mitchell district; aother was hid<lb break="no"/>den away in the golden north. With the <lb/>
fifth (Mr. Magrath) he had a tilt re<lb break="no"/>cently, but was free to say he believed <lb/>
Mr. Magrath was a good, honest, repre<lb break="no"/>sentative, although he perhaps did look <lb/>
after the interests of his employers too <lb/>
much, as was evidenced by his frequent <lb/>
absences from the House and also by some 


<cb/>


of the bills he introduced in the House. <lb/>
Mr. Mowat said he expected to get round <lb/>
shot and shell in return for his crticisms, <lb/>
but he would endeavor to take the dose <lb/>
with good nature. (Applause.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:MALO3">MR. MALONEY</persName></p> 

<p>said that he believed the members for <lb/>
both South and North Regina would have <lb/>
no objection to doing away entirely with <lb/>
the district of St. Albert. If Mr. Mowat<lb/>
would study the report of the Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner of Public Works upon the amount<lb/>
Statute of Labor done in St. Albert and<lb/>
compare it with the work in South Re<lb break="no"/>gina, he would get a better idea of the <lb/>
reason for the difference in the grants if <lb/>
there was a difference. If Mr. Mowat <lb/>
had looked after South Regina as keenly <lb/>
as he was looking after St. Albert, Mr. <lb/>
Maloney thought he might be living there <lb/>
yet instead of leaving the district to look<lb/>
after itself. Reffering to Mr. Mowat's<lb/>
attack on the Peace River road, Mr. Ma<lb break="no"/>loney said that a portion of the road was <lb/>
in his district. Mr Ross had had travelled <lb/>
two or three hundred miles in St. Albert, <lb/>
but had seen only a small portion of the <lb/>
district. It as a district entitled to a <lb/>
good grant. The Statute Labour re[prt <lb/>
showed that in St. Albert before the mat<lb break="no"/>ter became compulsory more work was  <lb/>
done voluntarily in one season than was <lb/>
done in South Regina and and several other <lb/>
districts in many seasons. He knew<lb/>
nothing about any hobnobbing with the <lb/>
Commisioner. Mr. Mowat had given a  <lb/>
sermon in the agriculture line. If in the <lb/>
celebrated school bill, which he had boast<lb break="no"/>ed about, he had provided for agriculture <lb/>
in the schools, there would not be so much <lb/>
need now for an agricultural policy. As <lb/>
to the Yukon route Mr. Maloney said it <lb/>
was through no fault of the Edmonton <lb/>
route that people turned back. The road <lb/>
from Edmonton to St. Albert was not a <lb/>
hard road, but some of the people who <lb/>
thought to go to Yukon were unfit and un<lb break="no"/>able to follow the telegraph line from Ed<lb break="no"/>monton to St. Albert. Men who knew <lb/>
how to travel succeeded on the Edmonton <lb/>
route, and he could show some preoceeds <lb/>
from the efforts of one man whpo went <lb/>
in that way. (Mr. Maloney exhibited a <lb/>
nugget attached to his chain). On the <lb/>
whole Mr. Maloney felt like compliment<lb break="no"/>ing the member for South Regina who <lb/>
always manged to say something; wheth<lb break="no"/>er what he said was to the point or not <lb/>
was of course a different matter. </p> 

<p>At 5:30 o'clock Mr. Speaker left the <lb/>
chair. When the House resumed at 8 <lb/>
o'clock the first member to take the floor <lb/>
was <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:TIMS1">MR. TIMS</persName>, (VICTORIA) <lb/></p> 

<p>who replied to statements made Mr. <lb/>
Mowat against the Peace River road.<lb/>
Mr. Tims considered the expenditure had <lb/>
been petty considering the importance of<lb/>
the work. The road had no necessary <lb/>
bearing on the Yukon route question. <lb/>
Ten years ago, before the Yukon was <lb/>
heard of, the opening of a road to Peace <lb/>
River had been petitioned for. There <lb/>
were extensive settlements at Peace River <lb/>
er and also Slave Lake. At Peace <lb/>
River there was three mills, and at Slave <lb/>
Lake there was a mill. Mills were not <lb/>
erected and operated where there were no <lb/>
settlers. But the settlements were handi<lb break="no"/>capped by having no outlet except by <lb/>
water. The opening of the road had <lb/>
benefited not only Peace River but Ed<lb break="no"/>monton and Canada at large. Many who <lb/>
went in this year with their minds set on <lb/>
gold, when they saw the kind of country <lb/>
there was at Peace River decided to com<lb break="no"/>mence farming there, and the open<lb break="no"/>ed up a country which would be a source <lb/>
of wealth to the Dominion. In opening<lb/>
the road the Assembly was looking after <lb/>
the interests of the people who, although in a<lb/>
remote part, were just as much citizens <lb/>
of the Territories as any other people. As <lb/>
to the miners, so so-called miners, who <lb/>
were returning unsuccessful, Mr. Tims <lb/>
said that of the men who went into the <lb/>
northern district to search for gold, not<lb/>
one in ten was a genuine miner, and many <lb/>
of them were unfitted to be let loose out<lb break="no"/>side of city limits. In March last the <lb/>
Town of Edmonton engaged Mr. W. Tay<lb break="no"/>lor to make a trip to Pelly Banks. He <lb/>
made the trip, went 30 miles down the <lb/>
Pelly river, and was back at Edmonton <lb/>
in July, which proved that the road was <lb/>
not extremely difficult for anyone who <lb/>
knew how to travel. Mr. Tims <lb/>
was glad that the Commissioner of Public <lb/>
Works had had the courage of of his convic<lb break="no"/>tions to proceed with the opening of the <lb/>
Peace River road, and had had the pluck<lb/>
as well to make a trip over the road. Mr. <lb/>
Ross and Mr. McCauley made the trip<lb/>
over 260 miles of the road in six days- <lb/>
not bad travelling. Mr. Tims gave de<lb break="no"/>tails of some of the business which the <lb/>
opening of the road had already created, <lb/>
showing that from points in Manitoba, <lb/>
also Battleford, Qu'Appelle, India Head, <lb/>
horses and stock had been sent in,- a <lb/>
movement which the road was wholly to <lb/>
be credited with. He computed that <lb/>
$100,000 in cash had be circulated this <lb/>
year by it. Dr. Dawson stated that the <lb/>
best place to prospect for coarse gold was <lb/>
juts over the first range of mountains. <lb/>
From Peace River access could be had to <lb/>
that region; it was only 300 miles from <lb/>
Peace River, through a country open to <lb/>
either wagon road or railway. From  <lb/>
Peace River there was access also up the <lb/>
Nelson river, and up a branch to the west <lb/>
of Fort Halkett; and up the Liard Val<lb break="no"/>ley on to Lake Francis, and to the head <lb/>
waters of the Yukon. No wiser expendi<lb break="no"/>ture had been made than that upon the <lb/>
opening of the road. Before sitting down <lb/>
the speaker heartily congratulated Mr. <lb/>
Haultain upon his able, concise and busi<lb break="no"/>nesslike speech on the budget. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">MR. AGNEW</persName> (W. PRINCE ALBERT) <lb/></p> 

<p>expressed gratification with Mr. Haultain's <lb/>
very clear statement of the affairs of the <lb/>
Territories. He endorsed the Yukon <lb/>
policy, and thought action had been tak<lb break="no"/>en justin the nick of time. The mission <lb/>
had proved a success financially and other<lb break="no"/>wise. The institution of an Agri <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>
Department Mr. Agnew believed was a <lb/>
good move. At present the great major<lb break="no"/>ity of farmers never get to see the experi<lb break="no"/>mental farms. He believed the scheme <lb/>
for promotion of stock interests feas<lb break="no"/>ible. The heavy freights prevented stock<lb break="no"/>men from bringing in thoroughbreds sires <lb/>
The barrier had already been partially  re<lb break="no"/>moved by the railway companies, but it <lb/>
was high yet, and the Government's plan <lb/>
would be a great assistance. He was sat<lb break="no"/>isfied with the brands registration and <lb/>
with its administration; and his wonder <lb/>
was that a law clerk had not been engaged<lb/>
long ago; many errors of legislation <lb/>
might have been saved. The increase in <lb/>
schools and the number of higher class <lb/>
teachers was bound to be pleasing to all <lb/>
He regretted that no mention had been <lb/>
made of the French settlement schools. <lb/>
Mr. Haultain had visited those settle<lb break="no"/>ments, and Mr. Agnew had expected to <lb/>
hear that the schools would be re-opened; <lb/>
they ought to be re-opened with teachers <lb/>
having both languages. The people were <lb/>
unable to provide their own teachers, and <lb/>
unable to carry on the business of a school <lb/>
district. Their farms were very small; <lb/>
the hunting and freighting they were now <lb/>
deprived of. Their old modes of liveli<lb break="no"/>hood had been taken away from them. <lb/>
The children were no duller than others, <lb/>
and should not be deprived of education. <lb/>
The parents were anxious that their <lb/>
children should be taught English as well <lb/>
as French, recognising that English was <lb/>
the chief language of the country. Mr.




<pb n="11" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1898-09-29_Page_011.jpg"/> 

<fw type="running">THE LEADER, THURSDAY EVENING, SEPTEMBER 29, 1898</fw> 
 
 <fw type="num">11</fw>


Agnew opposed the payment of defunct <lb/>
school district debentures, commend<lb break="no"/>ed the proposal to obtain in you Territor<lb break="no"/>ial map. As to the salary of the deputy <lb/>
in the agricultural department, he thought <lb/>
it looked large, but if the gentleman was <lb/>
qualify for the position it was not large <lb/>
and of two complaint against. He noticed <lb/>
an item of $75.00 for a Speaker's chair. <lb/>
That was not a large sum for a good chair, <lb/>
but care should be exercised in its selec<lb break="no"/>tion. There was a small man in the <lb/>
House who wore a hat so large that it had <lb/>
to be padded: perhaps the man expected <lb/>
the head to swell, but it was impos<lb break="no"/>sible-the head was already as large as <lb/>
it would ever be. In buying a chair, one <lb/>
should be got which would not need to be <lb/>
padded. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ANON1">Hon. members</persName> - Order, order. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Speaker</persName>-The point of order is not <lb/>
well taken. The hon. gentleman own <lb/>
sense of good taste will prevent him <lb/>
making any statement against one whose <lb/>
position prevents any reply. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Mr. Agnew</persName> - I am very sorry. Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, that your position muzzles you. <lb/>
After brief references to the hospitals <lb/>
items, and to the work of agricultural <lb/>
societies, Mr. Agnew concluded his re<lb break="no"/>marks. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:EAKI1">MR. EAKIN</persName> (SALTCOATS,) <lb/></p> 

<p>has not great fault to find the supple<lb break="no"/>mentary estimates. The first grant for <lb/>
the salary of a law clerk supplied a long <lb/>
felt want. He had used to feel, particu<lb break="no"/>larly before the constitution was changed <lb/>
and when he had been personally as much <lb/>
responsible for legislation as the members <lb/>
of the executive committee, that he was <lb/>
at a loss because of the lack of some legal <lb/>
man around the House to whom all the <lb/>
members would have a right to go to get <lb/>
their ideas put in proper legislative form. <lb/>
But before entering upon any remarks, <lb/>
Mr. Eakin felt that he should compliment <lb/>
the hon. leader upon the speech he had <lb/>
made that day. Mr. Eakin had heard <lb/>
speeches by the renowned men in other <lb/>
Assemblies and Parliaments: and he had <lb/>
never heard a more lucid explanation of <lb/>
any position than Mr. Haultain had given <lb/>
that day, - a statement and a speech which <lb/>
would have been creditable in any Par<lb break="no"/>liament in Canada. If in time Mr. Haul-<lb break="yes"/>tain decided so choose a different or a <lb/>
large sphere, Mr. Eakin had no doubt <lb/>
that he would be found fitted for spheres <lb/>
even more exalted than the one he now <lb/>
occupied. Respecting Mr. Peterson had <lb/>
brought order out of chaos in the brand <lb/>
matter, and had been able to put the sys<lb break="no"/>tem on an orderly and businesslike basis. <lb/>
Perhaps the Government had been a little <lb/>
premature in changing the system, or had <lb/>
not given themselves long enough time to <lb/>
bring about the change; but it was easier <lb/>
to tear than to mend a hole. If the <lb/>
House had taken more time in putting <lb/>
through the mass of legislation passed <lb/>
last year, there might be less time requir<lb break="no"/>ed this year considering these laws. <lb/>
But no doubt many mistakes would have <lb/>
been avoided if they had had a <lb/>
deputy Attorney General. On the <lb/>
Yukon question he held that the <lb/>
Government was perfectly excusa<lb break="no"/>ble, considering all the circum<lb break="no"/>stances, in not having made up its mind <lb/>
in time to take the House into its confi<lb break="no"/>dence last year. The right action had at <lb/>
all events been taken. There was no <lb/>
possibility of preventing liquor going into <lb/>
the Yukon. If prohibition had been at<lb break="no"/>tempted, high wines and spirits danger-<lb break="yes"/>out to health and life would have been <lb/>
smuggled in. He would have censured <lb/>
the Government if action had not been <lb/>
taken to regulate the traffic. From the <lb/>
moral point of view their course was com<lb break="no"/>mendable. The N.W.M. Police could <lb/>
carry out regulations, but could not make <lb/>
regulations. Mr. Eakin did not want <lb/>
Me. Mowat to leave the country without <lb/>
full credit for the school bill he had intro<lb break="no"/>duced; but he had learned before he <lb/>
ever came to Regina; that Mr. Moway was <lb/>
only a sort of godfather to the bill, which <lb/>
had been largely compiled by a legal gen<lb break="no"/>tleman in the House. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName> - I deny that. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:EAKI1">Mr. Eakin</persName> cheerfully accepted the de<lb break="no"/>nial. In any eveny very important prin<lb break="no"/>ciples of the school law had been changed <lb/>
since Mr. Mowat's bill came down, and <lb/>
for the changes the Government and other <lb/>
members were responsible. All the mem<lb break="no"/>bers were entitled to some credit for the <lb/>
legislation on the statute books. Up to <lb/>
last year ever member was responsible <lb/>
for legislation. Formerly there were 29 <lb/>
equally responsible legislators. All had <lb/>
the privilege and the duty, equally with <lb/>
the Government, to bring in bills. With<lb break="no"/>in the one year since full responsible <lb/>
government came in vogue, there had <lb/>
been two sessions; and in these sessions <lb/>
the Government had shown a spirit of <lb/>
commendable progress. They were to be <lb/>
congratulated upon their ideas of develop<lb break="no"/>ment; and upon the modification and <lb/>
simplification of the laws, so that he who <lb/>
ran might read. The educational pro<lb break="no"/>gress was gratifying and was the direct <lb/>
result of the new system of grants. This <lb/>
year only 18 per cent, of lowest grade <lb/>
teachers were in the service. The old <lb/>
system paid by standards, not by grades. <lb/>
Under the present system trustees could <lb/>
engage 2nd class teachers at no greater <lb/>
cost to the district than 3rd class; <lb/>
and they thus got better eduction. <lb/>
The country schools especially required <lb/>
well qualified teachers, because in the <lb/>
country schools one teacher had to handle <lb/>
all the standards. Mr. Eakin did not <lb/>
wholly approve the present system of <lb/>
public works administration in all its <lb/>
bearings. The district engineers' work <lb/>
was not altogether a success. In this <lb/>
sparsely settled country, with people <lb/>
living so far apart, it was sometimes <lb/>
impossible to get tender and contract <lb/>
work done reasonably. He had two cases <lb/>
in mind. Only two men tendered, and <lb/>
their figured were far above the engineer's <lb/>
estimate. The reasonable belief was that <lb/>
the contractors had made a combination. <lb/>
Then again the district engineers had such <lb/>
extensive districts that they could not <lb/>
pay full attention to all parts. The <lb/>
system needed some change. Where the <lb/>
Statute Labour Overseer was a good man, <lb/>
would it not be possible to employ him? <lb/>
Mr. Eakin warmly approved of day labor <lb/>
in preference to tenders. In view of the <lb/>
failure to print the Consolidated Ordinan<lb break="no"/>ces this year, it was unfortunate that <lb/>
more copies of last year's Ordinances were <lb/>
not obtained for distribution. Inability <lb/>
to procure printed copies of the law had <lb/>
caused some dissatisfaction. If the Brand <lb/>
Ordinance had been put in the hands of <lb/>
the people much anxiety would have been <lb/>
relived. He regretted Mr. Mowat's <lb/>
allusion to the Public Works deputy. His <lb/>
own impression was that, judging by his <lb/>
ability and the value of his work, Mr. <lb/>
Dennis was the most ill-paid man in the <lb/>
service. Mr. Dennis was one who did <lb/>
not spare himself; his illness last summer <lb/>
had been directly due to overwork. Mr. <lb/>
Mowat's insinuation about the $900 he <lb/>
absolutely refused to believe, although he <lb/>
had no information about the matter. <lb/>
But if his ability to judge character was <lb/>
any good at all, he knew that Mr. Dennis <lb/>
was not a man who would do such a thing. <lb/>
He approved the plan to encourage <lb/>
improved stock breeding, but wanted to <lb/>
know how the plan was to be carried out.</p>

<cb/>

<p>
Would the money be divided between <lb/>
districts? or would every man who applied <lb/>
be attended to until the money was <lb/>
exhausted? If so, one wide-awake sec<lb break="no"/>tion might derive the whole benefit. He <lb/>
was not much in favor of the experimen<lb break="no"/>tal work policy. The Dominion had <lb/>
undertaken that work, and Prof. Robert<lb break="no"/>son said they were going to carry on on <lb/>
the very lines here proposed. He had <lb/>
not implicit faith in experiments. The <lb/>
experimenters once found a better wheat <lb/>
than Red Fyfe, but he noticed that both <lb/>
for output and price Red Fyfe was still <lb/>
king. A few years ago Brome grass was <lb/>
found to be the great thing, but this year <lb/>
Mr. McKay told him it had been a fail<lb break="no"/>ure. Except for a few kinds of grains <lb/>
and grasses, he feared the small sum voted <lb/>
would not be of much use; and to-day <lb/>
we had heard that money was not likely <lb/>
to be plentiful in the immediate future. <lb/>
He questioned the wisdom of going in for <lb/>
a scheme which they might be unable to <lb/>
follow up. The most important question <lb/>
of the day was the position of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. All other considerations amount<lb break="no"/>ed to little in comparison with the matter <lb/>
of looking forward to provincial status. <lb/>
He believed that the present subsidy was <lb/>
spent to the very best advantage, and <lb/>
believed that the people were well satis<lb break="no"/>fied with the present simple form of <lb/>
government. Until they could see a <lb/>
substantial advantage in a change, they <lb/>
would not favor it. Mr. Eakin thought <lb/>
it was too early for the change. The <lb/>
whole question should be maturely con<lb break="no"/>sidered. Four years from now it might <lb/>
be submitted to the people. He admit<lb break="no"/>ted that Mr. Haultain's argument respect<lb break="no"/>ing the necessities of the schools was <lb/>
very strong. The rungs of the ladder <lb/>
planted in the common schools should <lb/>
lead the child who wished to climb up to <lb/>
the university. If the alternative was to <lb/>
lessen the school grants or go in for pro<lb break="no"/>vincial establishment, there would be no <lb/>
room for choice. But they should first ask <lb/>
the Dominion to give all the Territories <lb/>
are entitled to, and remain as we were as <lb/>
long as possible. Of course, if the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion would hand over the lands and <lb/>
minerals, even though much of them had <lb/>
been squandered on corporations, he <lb/>
would say, Go in for provincial establish<lb break="no"/>ment right now. However, the advan<lb break="no"/>tages and disadvantages would have to be <lb/>
fully discussed before the step could be <lb/>
taken. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PATR1">DR. PATRICK</persName> (YORKTON) <lb/>
spoke as a comparatively new member. <lb/>
He had read that great latitude was <lb/>
allowed on the motion to go into <lb/>
supply. but confessed that he had <lb/>
had no idea of the length to which <lb/>
members might go. He was satis<lb break="no"/>fied with the civil service policy of <lb/>
the Government—with the manner of ap<lb break="no"/>pointment, and with the plan of paying <lb/>
good salaries to good men. The Rt. Hon. <lb/>
Joseph Chamberlain had explained the <lb/>
reason of the better management of <lb/>
public institutions in Great Britain than <lb/>
in the United States, by the statement <lb/>
that in Great Britain it was the policy to <lb/>
employ technical men for technical work <lb/>
and when the best available man was <lb/>
secured, he was paid whatever salary was <lb/>
necessary to retain him. It appeared to <lb/>
Dr. Patrick that the North-West Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had adopted this wise policy. Their <lb/>
head in the Education branch was a man <lb/>
of unquestioned reputation, whose mere <lb/>
presence in the Territories drew attention <lb/>
to the country. His salary was not any <lb/>
too large for a man of his standing. If it <lb/>
was an evil thing to pay the official a <lb/>
higher salary than was paid the political <lb/>
head, there was a remedy to be found in <lb/>
a different direction than suggested by Mr. <lb/>
Mowat. He had been himself very <lb/>
favorably impressed by the courteous, <lb/>
careful and complete replies received <lb/>
from the department over which Mr. <lb/>
Dennis was placed, a department which <lb/>
handled an immense volume of business <lb/>
connected with statute labor and other <lb/>
public works. He understood the depart<lb break="no"/>ment had been bringing up also arrears of <lb/>
work, and he had no difficulty in believ<lb break="no"/>ing that the illness from which Mr. <lb/>
Dennis suffered was the result of over <lb/>
work; his illness had been a loss, and the <lb/>
Government would likely have heard him <lb/>
(Dr. Patrick) growling only that he knew <lb/>
Mr. Dennis was ill. Mr. Mowat admitted <lb/>
his believe that Mr. Dennis earned the <lb/>
salary; it followed that there must be <lb/>
work for him to do. If there was not <lb/>
work he could not earn his salary. <lb/>
It followed again that if the <lb/>
salary was not paid the work would be <lb/>
left undone. Mr. Peterson, the Agricul<lb break="no"/>ture deputy, was a new man, not a <lb/>
native Canadian, but a Dane. Such being <lb/>
the case, it was patent that no family <lb/>
" pull " or influence gave him the posi<lb break="no"/>tion. He must have gained the position <lb/>
by some reason existing in himself. It <lb/>
spoke well for a foreigner that he was <lb/>
able to rise in this way by his own worth. <lb/>
He had been sizing up Mr. Peterson and <lb/>
was very favorably impressed. He notic<lb break="no"/>ed since Mr. Peterson's entry into the <lb/>
office an improvement in the brands <lb/>
business; his communications were busi<lb break="no"/>ness like. He found also that Mr. Peter<lb break="no"/>son had very extensive knowledge of <lb/>
agriculture. It was not easy to get bu<lb break="no"/>siness training and the knowledge of <lb/>
agriculture together. The House, pro<lb break="no"/>ceeded Dr. Patrick, had been told by <lb/>
the leader in his very clear statement <lb/>
that the Territories were verging upon <lb/>
provincial establishment, that the time <lb/>
would soon come when the revenue de<lb break="no"/>rived under the present system would <lb/>
prove insufficient for the requirements. <lb/>
It was certain that money could not be <lb/>
paid out if it did not come in. The <lb/>
possibilities of the widow's erase had no <lb/>
application in these days so far as gov<lb break="no"/>ernments were concerned. The sources <lb/>
of revenue were local and federal. Be<lb break="no"/>sides what came from Parliament, there <lb/>
were only the fees from licenses and <lb/>
other odd fees. Then there was the <lb/>
plan of direct taxation. The license <lb/>
fees would not increase relatively to the <lb/>
expenditure. Taxation would be a fer<lb break="no"/>tile source of revenue if all the lands <lb/>
were available; but it would be unfair <lb/>
to tax the small landlords while the cor<lb break="no"/>poration landowners were able to evade <lb/>
the tax. Again, there was the plan of <lb/>
borrowing money. While he would op<lb break="no"/>pose any reckless borrowing, yet he <lb/>
could see a justification in borrowing <lb/>
against the day when all these lands <lb/>
would be available for taxation. Practi<lb break="no"/>cally we had to look for revenue to Do<lb break="no"/>minion grant or subsidy, or to borrowing. <lb/>
He inferred that Mr. Haultain believed <lb/>
that under provincial establishement out <lb/>
subsidy would be greater than we can <lb/>
expect Parliament to grant under pre<lb break="no"/>sent conditions. He would be sorry to <lb/>
see the day of reckless borrowing, and <lb/>
the longer that they day was put off <lb/>
the better. The population was very <lb/>
small yet to be given the borrowing <lb/>
power; and too large a proportion were <lb/>
squatters or men with grazing leases who <lb/>
had no absolute permanent stake and <lb/>
might move away. Manitoba was placed <lb/>
under debt - he was not saying whether <lb/>
wisely or not - by men who are not now in <lb/>
the province. Joseph Martin was an in<lb break="no"/>stance; he was gone from the province, but <lb/>
the debt remained. Aside from the advisa<lb break="no"/>bility of going into debt, it was not good <lb/>
public policy to place unrestricted borrow<lb break="no"/>ing power even indirectly in the reach of <lb/>
a people many of whom have not definite<lb break="no"/>
 

<cb/>


ly decided to make their home in the <lb/>
country. When the time comes for estab<lb break="no"/>lishment there might be a suggestion that <lb/>
a more equitable division of the original <lb/>
Hudson's Bay Co.'s territory would have <lb/>
to be made. If there had to be further <lb/>
division the eastern territory would pre<lb break="no"/>fer to have two provinces made of the <lb/>
Territories than be forced to go into <lb/>
Manitoba. There was this point in favor <lb/>
of such a proposition: Every province <lb/>
received a certain subsidy for the support of <lb/>
government and legislature. Two pro<lb break="no"/>vinces would receive for these purposed <lb/>

twice as much as one province, but of <lb/>
course there would be some additional ex<lb break="no"/>pense borne by Canada. One province <lb/>
would undoubtedly best serve the inter<lb break="no"/>ests of the North-West Territories for all <lb/>
time to come. Before any serious endea<lb break="no"/>vor for establishment, every means, short <lb/>
of that, to get the necessary revenue <lb/>
should have been exhausted. Dr. Patrick <lb/>
wanted a clearer statement from the <lb/>
Premier as to the exercise of the borrow<lb break="no"/>ing power which provincial establishment <lb/>
would bring. Would he advocate having <lb/>
any limitation placed on the borrowing <lb/>
power? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MEYE1">MR. MEYERS</persName> (KINISTINO) <lb/></p> 

<p>thought the hon. member from Macleod de<lb break="no"/>served the congratulations of the House <lb/>
and country for his clear budget state<lb break="no"/>ment. There was also another member <lb/>
in the Government upon whose presence <lb/>
there the House also had reason to con<lb break="no"/>gratulate itself.- that was the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Moose Jaw. He was an experi<lb break="no"/>enced member; he had grown up with <lb/>
the Assembly; he had proved to be a <lb/>
man of practical ability well worthy of his <lb/>
position, and had carried on the affairs of <lb/>
his important departments to the satisfac<lb break="no"/>tion of the Assembly and the people of the <lb/>
country. Of the illness of the most <lb/>
capable deputy head of the Pub<lb break="no"/>lic Works department, Mr. Meyers had <lb/>
heard with regret. There was no doubt <lb/>
that the illness was caused by overwork, <lb/>
and he was very glad that Mr. Dennis was <lb/>
again able to give the country the benefit <lb/>
of his very valuable services. Mr. Meyers <lb/>
believed in the principle of securing good <lb/>
men and paying them well. He did <lb/>
not think that Mr. Dennis was receiving <lb/>
an adequate salary. The salary asked to <lb/>
be voted to Mr. Peterson was not large. <lb/>
From all he had seen of the Agricultural <lb/>
deputy he believed he was a very satis<lb break="no"/>factory man. The general policy of the <lb/>
Government had been already well dis<lb break="no"/>cussed, and as he had little to find fault <lb/>
with and few new points to suggest, he <lb/>
would not take up the time of the House. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">MR. MCDONALD</persName> (FT. QU'APPELE) <lb/>
said that one of the interesting topics <lb/>
during the past year and a half had been <lb/>
whether the enlarged powers had been <lb/>
used to advantage, and in relation to the <lb/>
Government and members of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature the question would shortly be <lb/>
answered by the people. The leader had <lb/>
aptly pointed to the statutes for the policy <lb/>
of the Government. It was by the Ordi<lb break="no"/>nances that the Assembly met the require<lb break="no"/>ments of the country. The statute labor <lb/>
law was a good sample, which furnished <lb/>
the most economical means ever exposed <lb/>
in any country of doing road improve<lb break="no"/>ments. The Village law, the Municipal <lb/>
law, the School law and others could be <lb/>
pointed to as embodying policy, -very <lb/>
expedient and advisable policy. As con<lb break="no"/>ditions changed and the country develop<lb break="no"/>ed, the laws were changed from time to <lb/>
time to meet new conditions. Although <lb/>
the House was not voting full. Estimates, <lb/>
and for that reason all the more gratify<lb break="no"/>ing, a new vote was asked for the promo<lb break="no"/>tion of the agricultural and ranching <lb/>
interests. To the smaller and isolated <lb/>
stockmen the scheme of assistance would <lb/>
prove particularly beneficial, He believed <lb/>
the idea underlying the scheme was cor<lb break="no"/>rect. Some years ago Canadian cattle <lb/>
commanded the highest price in Engladn, <lb/>
but of late years, although exportation, <lb/>
particularly from the North-West, was <lb/>
increasing, the quality had fallen to second <lb/>
places. He was gratified also with the <lb/>
proposal to initiate agricultural experi<lb break="no"/>ments. The only criticism of the plan <lb/>
was that it was not large enough. He <lb/>
believed himself there would be ground <lb/>
for criticism if the vote was not increased <lb/>
in succeeding years. He believed the <lb/>
settlers of the country would appreciate <lb/>
this work. The cost of experiments <lb/>
ought to borne by the Government. To <lb/>
depend on philanthropy was all right if <lb/>
the bill was filled; but the Government <lb/>
had a duty to further the interests of the <lb/>
country. Making comparison with gov<lb break="no"/>ernment in Manitoba, Mr. McDonald <lb/>
found that the North-West Estimates this <lb/>
year just about equalled Manitoba's in <lb/>
1884. With a revenue of half a million <lb/>
dollars Manitoba in 1884 spent upon its <lb/>
civil service $57,000. The Territorial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment spend less than half that amount. <lb/>
Manitoba aided schools to the extent of <lb/>
$70,000; the Territories are this year <lb/>
giving $139,000, just about double. The <lb/>
critics should consider some of those <lb/>
points. These facts were likely to affect <lb/>
the Territorial view on the question of <lb/>
annexation to Manitoba. There might be <lb/>
some temptations in regard to railway ex<lb break="no"/>tensions, but there would be decided <lb/>
educational and taxation disadvantages. <lb/>
He had been elected on a platform of one <lb/>
province for the Territories, and he <lb/>
would uphold that principle. <lb/>
Mr. McDonald, referring to the <lb/>
new Brand law, hoped the Government <lb/>
would not fall to see that men who had <lb/>
made due application and remitted fees <lb/>
before the change, and who had received <lb/>
back neither brand nor fees, would now <lb/>
be given a proper return; he would not be <lb/>
satisfied until they were. He also strong<lb break="no"/>ly advocated the taking of steps which <lb/>
would lead to the sale of certain of the <lb/>
school lands without loss of time. The <lb/>
lands in settled districts, as for instance <lb/>
around Indian Head and QuèAppelle, <lb/>
should be sold. The opening of the lands <lb/>
to settlement and taxation would be of <lb/>
assistance to the school and local improve<lb break="no"/>ment districts. In conclusion, Mr. Mc<lb break="no"/>Donald said that during his term in the <lb/>
House he had endeavored to judge all <lb/>
questions by their merits without regard <lb/>
to their source. He had been elected as <lb/>
an independent member, and he had in <lb/>
a majority of cases been compelled to give <lb/>
the Government his support because their <lb/>
estimates and their legislation were in the <lb/>
right direction. So long as affairs were <lb/>
conducted in the same way by the <lb/>
Government he would continue to sup<lb break="no"/>port them. The work of the district <lb/>
engineers had perhaps not come up to ex<lb break="no"/>pectations, but that was a matter of de<lb break="no"/>tail. The fault seemed to be a fault of <lb/>
economy. There was only one engineer <lb/>
where two were needed. <lb/></p> 

<p>It was nearly 10 o'clock when the Com<lb break="no"/>missioner of Public Works and <lb/>
Agriculture <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ROSS11">MR. ROSS</persName> (MOOSE JAW) <lb/></p> 

<p>took the floor which he held, and held the <lb/>
House interested, for almost two hours. <lb/>
He said that the House recognised with <lb/>
pleasure the fact that Canada as a whole <lb/>
could be congratulated upon having <lb/>
entered an era of almost unequalled pros<lb break="no"/>perity. The Dominion had gained a <lb/>
proud position, and was now taking a <lb/>
foremost part in the councils of the <lb/>
Empire. Canada was recognized as the <lb/>
 
 <cb/>



first of the colonies and everywhere were <lb/>
parked evidence of prosperity. As im<lb break="no"/>petus had been given to all lines and <lb/>
branches of business. The manufacturing <lb/>
industries were flourishing and the factory <lb/>
men were enlarging and extending their <lb/>
factories and operations to cope with the <lb/>
improved possibilities of trade. The <lb/>
importers of the Dominion were experienc<lb break="no"/>ing the same gratifying improvement, and <lb/>
all the mercantile classes and men in <lb/>
every branch of trade and business were <lb/>
feeling the effects of the "growing time." <lb/>
The North-West Territories were to be <lb/>
congratulated as well, for the same <lb/>
evidence of prosperity were to be seen <lb/>
here. Agricultural conditions had never <lb/>
been so flourishing and favorable; the <lb/>
prospects had never been equal to present <lb/>
prospects. Farm products were found to <lb/>
be of enhanced value, and the returns <lb/>
were generous and encouraging. The <lb/>
stock raising industry was in the same <lb/>
favorable condition. The value of cattle <lb/>
was high, and there had been nothing to <lb/>
interfere with a good calf crop. Even the <lb/>
Assembly which was not usually directly <lb/>
affected by the fluctuations of trade, com<lb break="no"/>merce or agriculture, found itself in a <lb/>
flourishing state financially, according to <lb/>
the budget brought down by his colleague <lb/>
the hon. member for Macleod. The <lb/>
House had good reason to be proud of a <lb/>
leader who could make so lucid a state<lb break="no"/>ment and so able an exposition of the af<lb break="no"/>fairs of the country as the member <lb/>
for Macleod had done that morning. It <lb/>
was satisfactory to the members, and he <lb/>
felt sure that it would be satisfactory to <lb/>
the people of the country when they <lb/>
read it. But the country would be more <lb/>
satisfied with it if they could have heard <lb/>
it. The country might be assured that <lb/>
the colleagues of the hon. leader of the <lb/>
Government fairly hugged themselves <lb/>
with satisfaction every time he took the <lb/>
floor and proved anew his ability to deal <lb/>
with force and intelligence with the <lb/>
affairs of the Territories. Some cries <lb/>
were heard outside about silent members, <lb/>
about lack of criticism, about one man <lb/>
power, and about the undue power of <lb/>
the Government. He did not know <lb/>
whether those cries were worth denying. <lb/>
As a matter of fact, that Assembly was <lb/>
not a silent Assembly. The members of <lb/>
the House might not blot on every op<lb break="no"/>portune and inopportune occasion, but it <lb/>
was a House in which was heard, and <lb/>
heard frequently, in fact, continually, <lb/>
intelligent discussion and criticism of <lb/>
legislation and of administration. He <lb/>
could say this as a member who had been <lb/>
in the Assembly or the North-West <lb/>
Council for a continuous period of fifteen <lb/>
years, and who had been regularly in <lb/>
his place in the House for seventeen con<lb break="no"/>secutive sessions. To the members as <lb/>
much as to the Government was due the <lb/>
credit for whatever was good in the legis<lb break="no"/>lation and statutes, and as a member of <lb/>
the Government he was pleased to ac<lb break="no"/>knowledge the fact that the memberss of <lb/>
the House had at all times shown a de<lb break="no"/>sire and a willingness to give suggestions <lb/>
and to lend the benefit of their best ad<lb break="no"/>vice towards the improvement of legis<lb break="no"/>lation and in the interest of the common <lb/>
cause of the Territories. In every <lb/>
Council and in every Assembly to which <lb/>
he had belonged, during 15 years and <lb/>
throughout 17 sessions, he could bear tes<lb break="no"/>timony to the fact that at all times and <lb/>
on every occasion the members as a whole <lb/>
had bent their energies and their abilities <lb/>
-and that there were good abilities was <lb/>
amply attested by the character of the <lb/>
laws and the excellence of the institu<lb break="no"/>tions thought out, framed and formed- <lb/>in the best interests of the Territories. <lb/>
Turning to the Estimates Mr. Ross said <lb/>
that the hon. leader had gone so thorough<lb break="no"/>ly and clearly into them, that he would <lb/>
not take up the time of the House in <lb/>
going over the same ground. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE PUBLIC WORKS. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName> had complained that the <lb/>
expenses of the public works department <lb/>
had increased. It could not be gainsaid. <lb/>
There were more officials in the depart<lb break="no"/>ment than formerly. It fact there had <lb/>
been no such thing as a public works <lb/>
department until this Government orga<lb break="no"/>nised it last year. Before that a member <lb/>
of the Executive Committee had in a cer<lb break="no"/>tain way looked after the expenditure <lb/>
upon public works, and each member of <lb/>
the House had been a member of a pub<lb break="no"/>lic works committee, and did according <lb/>
to his own sweet will with the moneys <lb/>
apportioned to his district. The necessity <lb/>
of changing the system and organising a <lb/>
department was recognised. He did <lb/>
not know but that the organization had <lb/>
been accomplished just about as soon as <lb/>
was advisable. At any rate it was de<lb break="no"/>cided to organised a department, and to <lb/>
himself was entrusted the duty. He <lb/>
first looked around fro a technical officer. <lb/>
He did not pretend himself to know parti<lb break="no"/>cularly anything about the technical part. <lb/>
After looking around he discovered in <lb/>
Mr. Dennis one whom he thought was <lb/>
the right man and he believed he had not <lb/>
been mistaken. Mr. Dennis was well <lb/>
equipped with a general knowledge of <lb/>
this country, gained in connection with <lb/>
the Surveys branch of the Interior De<lb break="no"/>partment; he had visited every portion of <lb/>
the Territories, and he (Mr. Ross) did not <lb/>
believe there was any other man in <lb/>
Canada who had as thorough knowledge <lb/>
of the Territories as Mr. Dennis. The <lb/>
Government had found him simply in<lb break="no"/>valuable. He was thoroughly well <lb/>
equipped, too, in other ways. Personally <lb/>
he had received an incalculable amount <lb/>
of assistance from Mr. Dennis. When <lb/>
petitions came in for works in any part, <lb/>
Mr. Dennis would be found to have <lb/>
knowledge of the very locality, and <lb/>
was able to give sound opinions, <lb/>
altogether apart from his office <lb/>
duties Mr. Mowat had condemned the <lb/>
high salary. Mr. Ross believed that a <lb/>
good man should be paid a good salary. <lb/>
Poorly paid work was not likely to be <lb/>
well done. He did not consider that Mr. <lb/>
Dennis was receiving the salary which he <lb/>
deserved. He considered that the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories and the Government were very <lb/>
fortunate in securing Mr. Denis. The <lb/>
Interior Department had been extremely <lb/>
anxious to retain him, going to the length <lb/>
of offering to increase his salary. The <lb/>
Minister of the Interior had bery kindly <lb/>
lent Mr. Dennis to the North-West <lb/>
Government for a time to give them the <lb/>
benefit of his experience and ideas in the <lb/>
organisation of the department, but the <lb/>
Minister had been very desirous to retain <lb/>
him in the Irrigation branch, and even <lb/>
after Mr. Dennis decided to come to the <lb/>
North-West Government the Minister <lb/>
desired him to keep control of the Irriga<lb break="no"/>tion branch and paid him $900 a year for <lb/>
directing that service. Mr. Ross said he <lb/>
had exercised all this ingenuity to advance <lb/>
arguments to induce Mr. Dennis to <lb/>
become deputy commissioner of public <lb/>
works, and he was pleased and satisfied <lb/>
that he had induced him to come. In <lb/>
connection with the references made to <lb/>
Mr. Dennis's reports favoring the Irriga<lb break="no"/>tion transfer. Mr. Ross said he hoped <lb/>
the Mr. Mowat did not mean to insinuate <lb/>
that Mr. Dennis got up the memos for <lb/>
the purpose of securing more salary for <lb/>
himself; if he did he was entirely wrong. <lb/>
Mr. Dennis was receiving the $900 on <lb/>
account of the Irrigation work before the <lb/>
transfer; in that regard the change made <lb/>
no difference to Mr. Dennis. The In<lb break="no"/>terior Department had such confidence in <lb/>

<cb/>

him that they were willing that he should <lb/>
oversee their irrigation business after he <lb/>
came to the North-West Government. <lb/>
There were excellent reasons for this <lb/>
Government to desire the control of the <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">IRRIGATION ADMINISTRATION. <lb/></p> 

<p>Excepting to a very small extent in <lb/>
British Columbia, irrigation was a subject <lb/>
affecting no part of Canada but the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. To the Territories it was a <lb/>
question of local importance. The local <lb/>
Government was in close touch with the <lb/>
people interested, and therefore better <lb/>
calculated to manage the system from the <lb/>
point of view of the people's convenience. <lb/>
At Ottawa the administration was only a <lb/>
side issue, and was very liable to fail to <lb/>
receive the attention that it would be <lb/>
given by a government more closely in <lb/>
touch with the people affected. This <lb/>
Government made their proposition with <lb/>
a view to gain full control of the adminis<lb break="no"/>tration, They did not succeed wholly, but <lb/>
had been put in the position of agents for <lb/>
the Interior Department, which in reality <lb/>
did give them the privilege of control and <lb/>
management. The change put the North-<lb break="yes"/>West Government in control of water <lb/>
rights. This was important to the eastern <lb/>
part as well as the west apart altogether <lb/>
from the question of irrigation. They <lb/>
were desirous of improving the water sup<lb break="no"/>ply throughout the country which was <lb/>
one of the most important problems in <lb/>
the country. The change removes the <lb/>
necessity of applications for water rights <lb/>
going to Ottawa a tedious and inconveni<lb break="no"/>ent course. Such applications may now <lb/>
be made to, and can be decided upon at <lb/>
Regina, much more expeditiously. The <lb/>
Government took the ground that they <lb/>
should have control of all matters of pure<lb break="no"/>ly Territorial or local importance, and <lb/>
would endeavor to get control of all of <lb/>
these matters. In the irrigation adminis<lb break="no"/>tration they had the wedge well driven <lb/>
in already, and hoped soon to gain com<lb break="no"/>plete control. Considerable had already <lb/>
been done in the western part of the coun<lb break="no"/>try in the way of irrigation. There are <lb/>
135 ditches and canals constructed, cover<lb break="no"/>ing a distance of 280 miles. These canals <lb/>
represent a cost of at least $120,000, <lb/>
and a point worthy of note was that in <lb/>
connection with them neither this nor any <lb/>
Government had ever been asked for a <lb/>
cent's bonus. Farmers were bonused in <lb/>
connection with creameries and experi<lb break="no"/>mental forms were established at public <lb/>
cost in the interest of agriculturists, but <lb/>
not a cost of public money had been <lb/>
given to the people who were making the <lb/>
experiment of applying water on the arid <lb/>
lands in the Territories. He thought <lb/>
that great credit was due the men <lb/>
who were showing the pluck to take <lb/>
the risks of this new departure <lb/>
in Canada, and hoped that before long <lb/>
something might be done in their assist<lb break="no"/>ance. Commencing last year surveys <lb/>
were being made of all the streams and <lb/>
water courses between Moose Jaw and <lb/>
Yorkton with a view to the development <lb/>
of a scheme for reservoiring water for the <lb/>
use of settlers. Returning to the public <lb/>
works department, Mr. Ross said he had <lb/>
secured a deputy commissioner and an <lb/>
organised department was the result. <lb/>
Dr. Patrick was perfectly right in his <lb/>
remark about the very great amount <lb/>
work done in the department, and about <lb/>
there being arrears of work to cope with. <lb/>
The arrears were not the fault of anyone. <lb/>
There had been no department before to <lb/>
attend to the work. He gave some <lb/>
statistics to show the amount of work <lb/>
done. For instance within the year the <lb/>
department had received 8000 and had <lb/>
sent out 10,990 letters, and average of 48 <lb/>
per day. Then there were 6000 circulars <lb/>
sent out. The communications altogether <lb/>
averaged 62 per day. Fyles were made <lb/>
to the number of 2735. Previously there <lb/>
had been no fyles, and no records kept. <lb/>
It was a common occurrence for the <lb/>
deputy to come to him saying I've found <lb/>
another bridge this morning, or I've just <lb/>
located another dam. By and by, he <lb/>
supposed, the department would get hold <lb/>
of all the public property; up to date they <lb/>
were constantly finding works of which <lb/>
there had been no record kept. There <lb/>
had been 387 road surveys made and not <lb/>
properly recorded; this involved a very <lb/>
large amount of work. The plans had <lb/>
been in possession of the members, or <lb/>
the engineers. Some were mislaid; <lb/>
some where lost, which was a serious <lb/>
matter. The work had cost <lb/>
about $20,000. What constituted <lb/>
valuable property had been left <lb/>
in scattered hands, and no index or <lb/>
record kept. Another feature of the loss <lb/>
was that some of the surveys had involv<lb break="no"/>ed the acquirement of lands, where there <lb/>
had to be deviating surveys. Usually the <lb/>
possession had been given for a nominal <lb/>
consideration, sometimes for a dollar, <lb/>
sometimes for no consideration. But <lb/>
now in many cases it is found that the <lb/>
person who have possession is dead or <lb/>
removed, and the new people are not <lb/>
willing to renew the arrangement. It <lb/>
was impossible to estimate the loss caus<lb break="no"/>ed by failure to find the plans and re<lb break="no"/>cords in such cases <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">SOME OF THE DETAILS. <lb/></p> 

<p>The department had made 420 survey <lb/>
plans for public works, in addition to <lb/>
425 special surveys; had awarded 370 con<lb break="no"/>tracts; had received 127 applications re<lb break="no"/>opening highways; and 57 applications <lb/>
re the closing of public highways. The <lb/>
western members would be able to ap<lb break="no"/>preciate the difficulties in the latter ap<lb break="no"/>plications. The regular survey system <lb/>
did not well fit the foothill country, where <lb/>
straight roads were not possible. In these <lb/>
 questions particularly Mr. Dennis was <lb/>
 invaluable. Within the past few months <lb/>
 a great many knotty questions had been <lb/>
 straightened out. The items of the Es<lb break="no"/>timates, main and supplementary, this <lb/>
 year totalled 871 separate works. The <lb/>
 correspondence over these alone was no <lb/>
 little matter. There had been handled <lb/>
 since 1896, no less than 1,300 items of <lb/>
 work, involving an expenditure of $318,<lb break="no"/>000. The House would realize that there <lb/>
 must be considerable work associated <lb/>
 with that amount of expenditure, a great <lb/>
 deal of which was upon small works. <lb/>
 There had been the examination and pass<lb break="no"/>ing of 3,500 accounts, and the posting, <lb/>
 etc. $2,078 had been received in revenue, <lb/>
 which had to be accounted for and attend<lb break="no"/>ed to. If the expenses of the adminis<lb break="no"/>tration were increasing there was some <lb/>
 return from it. This $2,078 would be <lb/>
 augmented by about $1000 by tthe end <lb/>
 of the year. The departmetn had, and <lb/>
 was directing the operation of, 23 road <lb/>
 graders and 24 well boring machines. <lb/>
 The numbers of the machines were re<lb break="no"/>corded; the department would not lose <lb/>
 track of these machines, and no machine <lb/>
 would be lost in the future as had once <lb/>
 occurred in the past. There were 28 <lb/>
 coal mines in the Territories, the inspec<lb break="no"/>tion of which the department was carry<lb break="no"/>ing out. The steam boilers inspection <lb/>
 had involved the sending out and the <lb/>
 receipt of a large number of application <lb/>
 forms. He came now to Statute Labor, <lb/>
 a very important branch of the depart<lb break="no"/>ment's work. There were 358 districts <lb/>
 organized, with 58 in process, making 416 <lb/>
 districts to be in operation next year. <lb/>
 The returns from each separate district <lb/>
 had to be audited, and the department <lb/>
 had to prepare such forms and send out <lb/>
 such instructions as to enable intelligent <lb/>
 work to be done. These details would <lb/>

<cb/>

give some idea of the work of the de<lb break="no"/>partment. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE POLICY OF THE DEPARTMENT. <lb/></p> 

<p>The policy of the department was to, <lb/>
as far as possible, elect permanent public <lb/>
works. Whenever feasible, they were <lb/>
putting up steel instead of wooden <lb/>
bridges. At the present low price of steel, <lb/>
a bridge of steel placed on piles could be <lb/>
built for $700 which if made of wood <lb/>
would cost $600. Wooden structures <lb/>
would necessitate continual large votes <lb/>
for repairs. They hoped later to be able <lb/>
to use cement for foundations, so that <lb/>
their bridges would stand for at least 40 <lb/>
years with a renewal of floors. In mak<lb break="no"/>ing distribution of the public works fund <lb/>
the Government kept the whole Terri<lb break="no"/>tories in view. The district expenditure <lb/>
had been cast aside. It would do Mr. <lb/>
Mowat no good if he were able to pick <lb/>
out what each district got. Expenditures <lb/>
were not made because of the pressure <lb/>
of the members, although that was cer<lb break="no"/>tainly a factor, and the members were <lb/>
able to give valuable information and ad<lb break="no"/>vice. But other considerations were <lb/>
given weight. They had the reports of <lb/>
their engineers, and they had their own <lb/>
information and ideas about the respec<lb break="no"/>tive requirements, to guide the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture. It was impossible yet to absolutely <lb/>
follow the rules of spending the money <lb/>
where it would be of greater value, be<lb break="no"/>cause there were certain requirements in <lb/>
every position which had met; but <lb/>
it was the aim of the department to <lb/>
expend the money only on works of first <lb/>
importance in the different portions of the <lb/>
country. The electoral districts were not <lb/>
considered at all in the distribution. The <lb/>
great divisions, however, were considered. <lb/>
In the west bridges were required, whic <lb/>
they were endeavoring to provide. In <lb/>
the east - the grain growing area - good <lb/>
roads were the requirement, so that <lb/>
farmers might haul large loads and lessen <lb/>
the cost of conveying their grain to mar<lb break="no"/>ket; so in the east the department <lb/>
devoted attention to main highways and <lb/>
trails. They endeavored to encourage <lb/>
the Statute Labor districts to undertake <lb/>
the small works, by spending a certain <lb/>
amount of money in them. They had <lb/>
expended $10,600 through the district <lb/>
Overseers. From last year's returns, <lb/>
when there were 99 districts in operation, <lb/>
it was found that 8,470 days' work was <lb/>
done; 350 miles of road was made; 250 <lb/>
miles of fireguard; 16 bridges were built; <lb/>
five dame built; four dams repaired; 47 <lb/>
culverts made. This year he had reason <lb/>
to believe that fully 1,000 miles of road <lb/>
was made; 600 miles of fireguard; 30 or <lb/>
40 bridges, probably considerably more; <lb/>
about 100 culverts and 15 or 20 <lb/>
dames; 25,000 days' work was done, worth <lb/>
$37,000. This was good development. <lb/>
Regarding this inspection of public works, <lb/>
he intended to arrange to lessen the cost. <lb/>
The member for Salcoats had referred to <lb/>
the district engineer lacking time to at<lb break="no"/>tend to all the work. That was true. He <lb/>
had not felt justified in enlarging the <lb/>
staff, but hoped to work out a better pol<lb break="no"/>icy for the inspection of small works. He <lb/>
had managed local inspection of $10,000 <lb/>
worth of small works done this year <lb/>
through the Statute Labor districts. The <lb/>
plan answered well. It put the depart<lb break="no"/>ment in closer touch with the Overseer, <lb/>
who became interested in the work and <lb/>
did his best. The department had this <lb/>
year constructed $200,00 worth of works. <lb/>
Works to the value of $50,000 had not <lb/>
required inspection, leaving $150,000 <lb/>
worth of work to be inspected. The cost <lb/>
of inspection was $6,000 - really only $5,<lb break="no"/>000 for $1,000 had gone into bridges. So <lb/>
the inspection after all amounted to only <lb/>
4 per cent. He thought that was not an <lb/>
unreasonable cost, and could not help <lb/>
thinking that a mistaken impression ex<lb break="no"/>isted regarding the inspection. But he <lb/>
hoped to do better still. As to the policy <lb/>
of giving contracts by tender,-he knew <lb/>
of an instance where two men put up a job. <lb/>
There was always liability of such occur<lb break="no"/>ring; but he could tell the House that <lb/>
day labor was not without its possibilities <lb/>
of collusion either. The department had <lb/>
to contend with these difficulties. This <lb/>
year a large amount of work had been <lb/>
done by day labor; it had been difficult <lb/>
in many cases to get work done at all. <lb/>
The times were so prosperous and men <lb/>
were engaged in other ways; contractors <lb/>
wouldn't tender on the small works done <lb/>
by the Government, and the department <lb/>
had had to fall back on day labor. Or <lb/>
where the tenders received were consider<lb break="no"/>ed insatisfactory, they would not award <lb/>
the contract, but have the work done by <lb/>
day labor. The works for which money <lb/>
was voted last year were all either com<lb break="no"/>pleted or well under way,-every piece of <lb/>
work. In no year had so much propor<lb break="no"/>tionately been done of the work voted <lb/>
for. The items provided for in the sup<lb break="no"/>plementaries would be proceeded with as <lb/>
fast as possible. The Government had <lb/>
no intention of holding any of the work <lb/>
back as an election dodge; they would be <lb/>
careful in every particular piece of work, <lb/>
and if it was found possible to complete <lb/>
it, ti would be completed this yar. He <lb/>
was certain that 90 per cent. of <lb/>
all the work appropriated for in <lb/>
the 16 months would be completed within <lb/>
the time, and even hoped that 100 per <lb/>
cent. would be completed. In dealing <lb/>
with all their work and all their patron<lb break="no"/>age the Government acted in a manner to <lb/>
merit the confidence of the people. The <lb/>
Public Works, together with the Agricul<lb break="no"/>ture department, was the largest spending <lb/>
department. The Education department <lb/>
paid out large sums, but it was all paid <lb/>
under Ordinance. It was the greatest de<lb break="no"/>partments should be managed on business <lb/>
principles, and they had adopted and <lb/>
strictly adhered to business principles. In <lb/>
consequence they could go before the <lb/>
electors and claim that there could not be <lb/>
a shadow of ground for charges of favor<lb break="no"/>itism against the Government/ A strong <lb/>
plank in the Government's policy was <lb/>
that Dominion party lines should not be <lb/>
recognised in that House. It would be <lb/>
useless to expect that people to believe <lb/>
that the Government was sincere in that <lb/>
stand, if they say that men could come to <lb/>
the Government and because they were <lb/>
Grits or because they were Tories could <lb/>
obtain work or obtain favors from the <lb/>
Government. If the party lines were ever <lb/>
drawn it would be largely on account of <lb/>
the use made by the Government of the <lb/>
patronage at its disposal, and because the <lb/>
people had come to believe that men could <lb/>
get favors from the Government because of <lb/>
their particular stripe. He would</p>
  
  <p rendition="simple:centre">DEFY ANY MAN </p>

<p>
in the House or in the country to show <lb/>
that in any work done by this Govern<lb break="no"/>ment any favoritism was shown in the <lb/>
letting of the contract or in any way. So <lb/>
far as concerned local patronage, and there <lb/>
was considerable at the capital - and for <lb/>
his part he believed that the capital would <lb/>
remain in the same place for a long time <lb/>
to come - he had adopted this principle: <lb/>
If there were two or three men in the line <lb/>
of business, his instructions were to <lb/>
buy from them alternately, to make an <lb/>
equal division. That was fair and pro<lb break="no"/>per. Every citizen who was helping to <lb/>
build up town and country had a right <lb/>
to the patronage in equal measure. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">SOME OF THE VOTES.</p> 

<p>In the items the House would see one <lb/>
of $1,000 for repairs to furniture and <lb/>
buildings, and for new furniture for some <lb/>
 

<cb/>


of the public offices. They contended <lb/>
that the Ottawa Government was under <lb/>
the duty to supply the necessary buildings <lb/>
and furnishings for this local Government. <lb/>
He had applied to the Minister of Public <lb/>
Works at Ottawa for certain improve<lb break="no"/>ments, but the application was not heed<lb break="no"/>ed; and the local department had been <lb/>
compelled to carry out the improvements. <lb/>
But he was glad to say that the Ottawa <lb/>
authority had since recognised the claim, <lb/>
and although this $1,000 appeared in the <lb/>
Estimates, in reality $886 of the amount <lb/>
had already been repaid by Ottawa. <lb/>
There was $100 to be voted for inspection <lb/>
of coal mines. If their Ordinance was to <lb/>
be of any avail proper inspection of the <lb/>
mines must be made. They had provided <lb/>
for two inspections in the past year <lb/>
and had secured for inspector a man who <lb/>
was very well qualified. Upon the bene<lb break="no"/>fit to be derived from the item for a Ter<lb break="no"/>ritorial map, he would not enlarge. <lb/>
some comment had been made upon the <lb/>
item for a Speaker's chair. In all legis<lb break="no"/>latures it was usual at the end of the term <lb/>
for the Speaker to take home the chair <lb/>
and the gown, and Mr. Ross trusted that <lb/>
the House would not deny their Speaker <lb/>
this privilege. Mr. Speaker had filled <lb/>
the responsible and important position to <lb/>
the satisfaction of the House, and was <lb/>
well entitled to the chair to be handed <lb/>
down as an heirloom in his family. <lb/>
(Laughter.) $1000 was providced for <lb/>
Steam Boiler inspection. The House had <lb/>
adopted legislation this session dealing <lb/>
with the matter, from which it was ex<lb break="no"/>pected the service would more than repay <lb/>
its cost. There was the item to pay one-<lb break="yes"/>third of the bonus to a grist mill owner <lb/>
whose mill had been burned; this was <lb/>
not really paying out public money, be<lb break="no"/>cause the Government had derived the <lb/>
money from insurance on the mill. <lb/>
There was an item of $2,000 for the sub<lb break="no"/>structure of a bridge over the Kooteney <lb/>
river. Southern Alberta required and <lb/>
should have large improvements in the <lb/>
way of bridges. The country was tra<lb break="no"/>versed by swift and dangerous streams. <lb/>
There had been many drownings. The <lb/>
Dominion authority should have bridged <lb/>
those streams. Some of the work was <lb/>
beyond the present power of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories. He was endeavoring to get the <lb/>
Government at Ottawa to make provision <lb/>
for bridging the Belly river, and hoped <lb/>
the Dominion would recognize the neces<lb break="no"/>sity. The Territories were assisting to <lb/>
bridge the Kootenay river; the bridge would <lb/>
be a steel structure and in every way a <lb/>
credit to the department. Provision was <lb/>
made for a dam over the Qu'Appelle river <lb/>
at Katepwe. There had been two dams <lb/>
in that neighborhood. One had gone out, <lb/>
and had left land drying up which was <lb/>
a menace to health. A survey had been <lb/>
made by Mr. Child, who reported that <lb/>
one dam at Katepwe would be better than <lb/>
the two. They would put in a dam which <lb/>
he hoped would stand for several years. <lb/>
Respecting items for ferries, Mr. Ross <lb/>
said it was the policy of the Government <lb/>
to acquire the ferries and cheapen the fees. <lb/>
The barriers against settlers who had to <lb/>
cross rivers should be made as light as <lb/>
possible. If the Government had the <lb/>
money the rivers ought to be bridged, but <lb/>
in many cases that was out of the <lb/>
question, and they were in duty bound to <lb/>
make the hardships attending the <lb/>
crossing of these rivers as light as pos<lb break="no"/>sible. While the expenditure upon the <lb/>
ferries was shown, there was also reven<lb break="no"/>ues from them which would not appear <lb/>
until the receipts of next year, Another <lb/>
$1,000 was asked for well-boring. While <lb/>
the operation of the well-borers had this <lb/>
year been fairly satisfactory with <lb/>
which they had to deal. It was simply <lb/>
impossible to estimate any approximate <lb/>
result from any given expenditure. <lb/>
For a time things would proceed <lb/>
well, then a piece of territory <lb/>
would be struck yielding noth<lb break="no"/>ing but disappointment. The deep borers <lb/>
were very expensive. After sinking a <lb/>
certain distance the cost increased very <lb/>
largely. To bore a foot at a depth of 150 <lb/>
feet cost very much more than at 50 feet <lb/>
depth. He hoped still to do much better in <lb/>
the operation of this branch. He was <lb/>
giving the subject his very best attention, <lb/>
believing that it was one of the questions <lb/>
most important to the people that they <lb/>
should have supplies of good spring water. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE PEACE RIVER ROAD. <lb/></p> 

<p>The opening of the road to <lb/>
Peace River had been criticized. The <lb/>
road had been dubbed "the Yukon route." <lb/>
He could say that this Government never <lb/>
had any idea of building a road or any <lb/>
part of a road to Yukon. The road was a <lb/>
road to Peace River, for the benefit of <lb/>
of and for the opening up of the Peace <lb/>
River country. It was by no means a <lb/>
new subject. As far back as 1884 Mr. <lb/>
Oliver in the North-West Council had <lb/>
made out a strong case for the opening of <lb/>
the road, asking an appropriation of $2,000. <lb/>
The Council had been unable to under<lb break="no"/>take the work; but they "resoluted." <lb/>
The usual fate attended their resoluting, <lb/>
and nothing was done. Later on further <lb/>
efforts were made, but the Assembly was <lb/>
always prevented by lack of funds from <lb/>
doing anything. Last year upon very <lb/>
strong representations made by the mem<lb break="no"/>bers for Edmonton, Victoria and St. Albert <lb/>
the Government decided to undertake <lb/>
the work, and when the House at last <lb/>
session was asked for a vote for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose, the proposition was supported al-<lb break="yes"/>mos unanimously, one member (Mr. <lb/>
Bannerman) going so far as to express his <lb/>
willingness to forego all works in <lb/>
his own district in favor of <lb/>
the Peace River road; although <lb/>
he (Mr. Ross) had been obliged to remark <lb/>
then that Mr. Bannerman did still want <lb/>
a few things done in his district. (Laugh<lb break="no"/>ter.) The Government had the route ex<lb break="no"/>plored, and last fall went on opening it <lb/>
up. They met more difficulties than <lb/>
had been expected. The common idea <lb/>
was that the country north of Edmonton <lb/>
was bluffy; but for a distance of 200 <lb/>
miles the road ran through solid bush i <lb/>
which no open space was found as large <lb/>
as the area of the town of Regina. It <lb/>
was solid timber,-heavy spruce. There <lb/>
was 27 miles width of the best spruce <lb/>
he had ever seen, the trees standing <lb/>
from 60 to 80 feet without a limb. In <lb/>
other portions there was cottonwood and <lb/>
poplar. Having put their shoulder to <lb/>
the wheel, having commenced the work, <lb/>
the Government decided to complete it, <lb/>
and depend upon the House to sustain the <lb/>
action and the additional cost. He had <lb/>
no fears but that the House would sup<lb break="no"/>port the expenditure when he informed <lb/>
them of the benefits which had already <lb/>
accrued. The opening of a road to Peace <lb/>
River have the people of the Territories <lb/>
an opportunity to do the trading of and <lb/>
sell the supplies to both <lb/>
the Findlay river country and the Omen<lb break="no"/>ica country in Northern British Columbia. <lb/>
It also enabled prospectors to go to the <lb/>
Nelson and Liard country, and enabled <lb/>
the Territories to tap the trade of all <lb/>
those areas. At Slave Lake there were <lb/>
700 people; there was a Roman Catholic <lb/>
mission and all the institutions which <lb/>
prevail in other communities, including <lb/>
schools, churches, etc. The people at <lb/>
Peace River sustained a cost of $300 a <lb/>
month for mail service, which showed <lb/>
that it was a district of no mean impor<lb break="no"/>tance. <lb/></p> 

<p>(To be concluded next week.) <lb/></p>



<pb n="1" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1898-10-06_Page_001.jpg"/>
<fw type="dateline">THE LEADER, THURSDAY EVENING, OCTOBER 6, 1898.</fw>
<fw type="num">1</fw> 

 </div>
 
 <div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">THE DEPARTMENT OF AGRICULTURE</head>
<head rendition="simple:centre">ITS DUTIES. SCOPE AND IMPORTANCE DEMONSTRATED BY THE <lb/>
COMMISSIONER OF AGRICULTURE.</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">Conclusion of the Budget Debate Report- Explanation of the <lb/>
Schemes for Assisting the Agricultural and Stock Interests-<lb/>Mr. Ross Hotly Resented the Insinuations of Favoritism Made <lb/>
by Mr. Mowat- Speech of the Leader of the Opposition- Mr. <lb/>
Mitchell Termed the Government's Policy a John Bull Policy-<lb/>Mr. Haultain Would Not Accept Provincial Establishment <lb/>
With Any Less Powers Than the Provinces Posses. <lb/></head> 

  <p rendition="simple:centre">(<hi rendition="simple:italic">Continued from last issue.</hi>)</p> 

<p>THE LEADER'S Budget debate report <lb/>
(N.W.T. Legislature, 13th Sept., 1898) <lb/>
broke off last week in the middle of the <lb/>
speech of the Commissioner of Public <lb/>
Works and Agriculture. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:ROSS11">MR. ROSS</persName> <lb/></p> 

<p>had detailed the reasons which impelled <lb/>
the Government to undertake the open<lb break="no"/>ing of the Peace Rive rroad, and explain<lb break="no"/>ed the work done on the road. He then <lb/>
proceeded to show some of the benefits <lb/>
reaped from the Government's action and <lb/>
policy in that connection, as follows:-<lb break="yes"/></p> 

<p>He had taken the trouble to <lb/>
ascertain as nearly as possible the exact <lb/>
results in trade at Calgary and Edmonton <lb/>
accruing from the opening of the road. <lb/>
This Government could not be held <lb/>
responsible if there had been people <lb/>
foolish enough to think they could go to <lb/>
Yukon by that route. From the Presi<lb break="no"/>dent of the Board of Trade at Edmonton <lb/>
he learned that the trade of that town <lb/>
from 1st Sept. 1897 to 1st Sept. 1898 <lb/>
amounted to one and one quarter millions <lb/>
of dollars; the trade of the town had <lb/>
increased 50 per cent. over the former <lb/>
year, and one half of the increase was <lb/>
due to the Yukon trade. That was to say <lb/>
the trade of Edmonton had increased by <lb/>
$675,000, and the opening of the road to <lb/>
Peace River led to $337,000 of th in<lb break="no"/>crease. That fact in itself was ample <lb/>
justification for the expenditure. From <lb/>
Mr. Morris, of Calgary, a banker and a <lb/>
reliable authority, he learned that the <lb/>
northern trade resulted in the sale of <lb/>
horses to the value of $40,000 and in <lb/>
general business in supplies to the ex<lb break="no"/>tent of $100,000 at Calgary. Many <lb/>
parts of the Territories could give like ex<lb break="no"/>periences. The districts of Indian Head <lb/>
and Regina he knew had sold horses and <lb/>
oxen and dogs for the northern trade. <lb/>
Even if no Yukon existed it was right <lb/>
and proper for the Government to take <lb/>
hold and develop a portion of the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories having such possibilities as the <lb/>
Peace River country. If the Assembly <lb/>
and Government did their duty, they <lb/>
would not have to pass resolutions in the <lb/>
House to save their territory, but the <lb/>
people in all portions would pass the <lb/>
resolutions and show their desire to re<lb break="no"/>main as a part of the Territories. <lb/>
(Applause.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE AGRICULTURE DEPARTMENT.</p> 

<p>The House at last session had made <lb/>
provision for a department of agriculture, <lb/>
but no estimate was made for the engage<lb break="no"/>ment of a deputy. When the department <lb/>
was organized the Clerk of the Council, <lb/>
Mr. Reid, took charge of it. Mr. Reid's <lb/>
time, however, was so fully taken up with <lb/>
other duties that, even working night and <lb/>
day for weeks and months, as he had done, <lb/>
he could not attend to the duties, particu<lb break="no"/>larly when the brands registration busi<lb break="no"/>ness had to be taken hold of. Mr. Ross <lb/>
said he wished now that they had allowed <lb/>
longer time in which to effect the change <lb/>
in the brands system; a longer time <lb/>
would have saved himself a very great <lb/>
deal of trouble and worry. Mr. Reid <lb/>
had tackled the work with a will, but al<lb break="no"/>though he worked almost without ceasing, <lb/>
his many other duties prevented his pro<lb break="no"/>per attention to the brands business. <lb/>
Mr. Ross saw that in the interests of the <lb/>
department and of the people there should <lb/>
be a chief clerk. As he had done in the <lb/>
case of the public works, he looked around <lb/>
for a suitable man, and finally selected <lb/>
Mr. Peterson. This gentleman was not a <lb/>
deputy head yet, but Mr. Ross hoped he <lb/>
would be one in a very few days. He <lb/>
ventured to say that the House would <lb/>
find that in his choice of Mr. Peterson he <lb/>
had been no less successful than in <lb/>
the choice of Mr. Dennis. The member <lb/>
for Yorkton had sized him up, and had sized <lb/>
him up well. Mr. Peterson was well <lb/>
equipped for the post. He was not only <lb/>
a first class office man, but was a practical <lb/>
agriculturist and had been an experi<lb break="no"/>menter himself. He took a very deep in<lb break="no"/>terest in agriculture. Mr. Peterson had <lb/>
come out to this country and had farmed <lb/>
in Manitoba where had had to carry water <lb/>
ten miles for use on his farm; he had farm<lb break="no"/>ed also at Calgary where to succeed the <lb/>
farmer was obliged to apply water to his <lb/>
land. In connection with the brands <lb/>
administration Mr. Peterson had proved <lb/>
a treasure. He came in on the 1st of <lb/>
May and ever since had devoted all his <lb/>
time, even the time that should be his <lb/>
own for recreation, to the work of the <lb/>
office. Mr. Ross was glad of the occa<lb break="no"/>sion to express his opinion thus publicly <lb/>
of Mr. Peterson; he would not have felt <lb/>
like doing so had the question of Mr. <lb/>
Peterson's qualifications not been raised. <lb/>
He would again say that he had not the <lb/>
slightest doubt but that the country <lb/>
would endorse the appointment when his <lb/>
work had time to be seen. After speak<lb break="no"/>ing of the work of the department <lb/>
with the brands system, Mr. Ross said <lb/>
the department was also charged with <lb/>
the collection and publishing of general <lb/>
statistics. Very little in that line had <lb/>
yet been done, but they hoped to do some<lb break="no"/>thing this fall. The deputy would also <lb/>
be of assistance in preparing legislation <lb/>
dealing with agriculture, as for instance <lb/>
in relation to agricultural societies. Mr. <lb/>
Mowat had accused him (Mr. Ross) of <lb/>
having prepared a good scheme in this <lb/>
connection. He admitted that he had <lb/>
been thinking out a scheme. But there <lb/>
had been no bill printed. He submitted <lb/>
his views in type written for mto the <lb/>
Agricultural Committee. Mr. Mowat <lb/>
could scarcely be in earnest in his sug<lb break="no"/>gestion that his (Mr. Ross's) fears had <lb/>
induced him to withdraw his proposition. <lb/>
He thought no member would accuse him <lb/>
of being afraid to press h is views. <lb/>
The accusation had always been the other <lb/>
way, - that he was too apt in pressing <lb/>
his views. He had not changed his views <lb/>
about the scheme proposed, but doubted <lb/>
whether the time had quite come for  <lb/>
applying it. The plan was not thoroughly <lb/>
digested; he hardly thought he had all <lb/>
the information required. He had plac<lb break="no"/>ed the matter before the Agricultural <lb/>
Committee to get the views of the mem<lb break="no"/>bers; he was always willing to learn. <lb/>
He was going to go further, and place <lb/>

<cb/>

the scheme before the agricultural socie<lb break="no"/>ties of the country. He did not claim <lb/>
to know everything about every subject, <lb/>
and was perfectly willing to seek ad<lb break="no"/>vice from those qualified to give it. He <lb/>
hoped next year to be able to bring in <lb/>
a bill dealing with the subject on the <lb/>
lines of the scheme. While on that sub<lb break="no"/>ject he might say that it was his inten<lb break="no"/>tion to have a section of the Agricultural <lb/>
Societies Ordinance amended to enable a <lb/>
society of 50 members to draw the grant. <lb/>
Last year, having this scheme in view, <lb/>
the House had raised the minimum <lb/>
membership to 100. The object soguht <lb/>
for would be reached in another way. <lb/>
While the societies had undoubtedly done <lb/>
an excellent work, they were <lb/>
too much disposed to hold small shows. <lb/>
It would be proposed to hold larger <lb/>
district shows in which more than one <lb/>
society might join. If nothing untoward <lb/>
occurred in the uncertain meantime, the <lb/>
scheme would be introduced at the first <lb/>
session of the new Legislature. Other <lb/>
very important subjects to which the <lb/>
attention of the department of agricul<lb break="no"/>ture would have to be given were Noxi<lb break="no"/>ous Weeds, Estray Animals and the ad<lb break="no"/>ministration of the votes passed by the <lb/>
Assembly for Hospitals, Charities and <lb/>
Public Health. With such branches as <lb/>
these, added to those regarding which he <lb/>
had entered more into detail, the House <lb/>
would recognize that the Department <lb/>
was one of very great importance. There <lb/>
was full scope for all the organisation <lb/>
which they were providing. Mr. Ross was <lb/>
sorry to hear anyone suggest that it was <lb/>
a minor department, and preferred to <lb/>
believe that Mr. Mowat thought that as <lb/>
yet the size of the department and the <lb/>
amount of work it could do made it a <lb/>
minor one. Every member must recog<lb break="no"/>nise that the future of the North-West <lb/>
Territories depends upon the agricultural <lb/>
interests; and it did not need to be de<lb break="no"/>monstrated at this date that it was pos<lb break="no"/>sible for a great deal of assistance to be <lb/>
given agriculturists and stockraisers <lb/>
through a well organised department <lb/>
whose business it was to devote atten<lb break="no"/>tion to those interests. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE ASSISTANCE SCHEMES. <lb/></p> 

<p>After devoting some remarks in an-<lb break="yes"/>answer to the hint that the agricultural policy <lb/>
was invented to catch votes, Mr. Ross <lb/>
said he was perfectly satisfied as to the <lb/>
advisability of endeavoring to assist the <lb/>
stockraisers to improve their grades. It <lb/>
was evident that within the past few <lb/>
years the quality of the stock had been <lb/>
deteriorating. He had had an opportu<lb break="no"/>nity of seeing an example of what might <lb/>
be done in the line of improvement. <lb/>
Anyone who had been up the Manitoba <lb/>
and North-Western railway and had seen <lb/>
the thoroughbred stock farm at Binscarth <lb/>
and the quality of cattle raised in the <lb/>
district surrounding, would realise the <lb/>
benefit to be derived. There was already <lb/>
an arrangement in force with the railways <lb/>
for reduced rates on shipments of <lb/>
thoroughbreds, made at the instance of <lb/>
the Department of Agriculture at Otta<lb break="no"/>wa. But the fact of the arrangement <lb/>
did not seem to be well understood. <lb/>
One of the <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> of this department would <lb/>
be to spread information of the advan<lb break="no"/>tages of that arrangement, and in addi<lb break="no"/>tion, the House was aksed to vote a sum <lb/>
to give a small bonus for each head of <lb/>
thoroughbred stock brought to the coun<lb break="no"/>try. The proposition was this: The de<lb break="no"/>partment would receive an application <lb/>
from a man who wished to import one <lb/>
head of male stock; the importer would <lb/>
have to make his own provision in regard <lb/>
to selection and purchase, because the <lb/>
Government were not going to leave <lb/>
themselves open to any charge of collu<lb break="no"/>sion in buying animals. The bonus would <lb/>
be given in such an amount that the <lb/>
cost of the man of bringing the animal <lb/>
to his own station would be $5, that was <lb/>
to say the cost of the animal would be <lb/>
precisely its cost in Ontario plus $5. <lb/>
The bonuses would be so applied that <lb/>
the resident in any part of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories could secure an animal at the same <lb/>
cost as a resident in any other part. <lb/>
The man would have to notify the de<lb break="no"/>partment of his purchase in the east, <lb/>
and the department would, whenever a <lb/>
certain number had been purchased, <lb/>
have a man to collect them, come in <lb/>
charge of them, and distribute them at <lb/>
stations to which they mgiht be destined. <lb/>
Mr. Eakin had feared that some section <lb/>
of country or some collection of indivi<lb break="no"/>duals would get in their applications <lb/>
first and scoop the whole fund and the <lb/>
whole advantage. Mr. Ross did not share <lb/>
the fear. In the first place every por<lb break="no"/>tion of the country would be given notice <lb/>
at the same time, and in the second <lb/>
place his fear was that for the first year <lb/>
anyway the scheme would not be taken <lb/>
advantage of to even the full extent of <lb/>
their small vote. Before a man could <lb/>
take advantage of the scheme he must <lb/>
be able to pay the first cost of the <lb/>
thoroughbred animal. The average <lb/>
cost to the Government per animal <lb/>
would be from $12.00 to $18.00 <lb/>
according to the locality to which the <lb/>
animal was taken. If there were 100 ap<lb break="no"/>plications in the first year it was all they <lb/>
could reasonably expect. He expected <lb/>
that in the time the settlers would become <lb/>
able to take more advantage of the scheme <lb/>
and hoped that in future years the House <lb/>
might have to vote a larger sum for the <lb/>
purpose. The Government's arrange<lb break="no"/>ments in connection with this scheme <lb/>
were all but completed, and they would <lb/>
be ready very shortly to receive applica<lb break="no"/>tions as he had explained. The next <lb/>
item was the one of $2,500 to initiate ex<lb break="no"/>perimental work in the Territories. <lb/>
The whole House would agree that great <lb/>
advantage had accrued to those sections <lb/>
of country where experimental farms had <lb/>
been located. The farms were an object <lb/>
lesson to all who could get to see them. <lb/>
He would not claim that all the good <lb/>
work done in Indian Head district was <lb/>
attributable to the experimental farm <lb/>
there, but no one could doubt that the <lb/>
farm had greatly benefitted that district. <lb/>
If the good work was to be taken full ad<lb break="no"/>vantage of, then it had to be brought <lb/>
nearer home to a greater number of farm<lb break="no"/> 

<cb/>

ers. What advantage was the Indian <lb/>
Head farm to a farmer in Edmonton dis<lb break="no"/>trict? Even if he could go to see it, the <lb/>
conditions on his own farm and on the <lb/>
farm at Indian Head were entirely differ<lb break="no"/>ent. What advantage to Southern Al<lb break="no"/>berta would be the establishment of an <lb/>
experimental farm at Prince Albert? Not <lb/>
very great, certainly. Mr. Eakin said <lb/>
that the experimenters had advocated <lb/>
certain grains and grasses but now found <lb/>
them unsuitable and unsuccessful. That <lb/>
showed precisely the great value of ex<lb break="no"/>perimental work. Was it not cheaper <lb/>
for one experimenter to prove the un<lb break="no"/>suitability of a certain grain, than for a <lb/>
great numbers of farmers to have to learn <lb/>
the fact from their own experiences and <lb/>
losses? The greatest work of an experi<lb break="no"/>mental farm was not in showing what <lb/>
should be done, but in showing what <lb/>
should not be done. The sum to be de<lb break="no"/>voted to the work by this Government <lb/>
was small; it was for initiatory work. <lb/>
They did not expect to be able to start <lb/>
experimental work everywhere at once, <lb/>
but he did hope that in time this <lb/>
Government would be able to do <lb/>
something practical for the advance<lb break="no"/>ment of the interests of agricul<lb break="no"/>ture in this country. It was all very <lb/>
well to say that the Dominion was <lb/>
doing the work and that Prof. Robertson <lb/>
was doing the work. He hoped that the <lb/>
Dominion would continue its good work, <lb/>
and that Prof. Robertson would continue <lb/>
and increase the amount of his good work; <lb/>
but after all that the Dominion would or <lb/>
could do, there was a great deal left to be <lb/>
done, and he believed that it was time for <lb/>
the local Government to commence to or<lb break="no"/>ganise and to supplement the work done <lb/>
by the Dominion. The cry thgat the <lb/>
scheme was an election dodge was the <lb/>
veriest buncombe. The farmers of the <lb/>
country would not thank the man who <lb/>
raised that cry. If the Government <lb/>
might not dare to adopt any policy for the <lb/>
benefit of the farmers the farmers would <lb/>
be left in a poor position. If they heeded <lb/>
that cry, nothing could be done near the <lb/>
close of a term. The cry that the scheme <lb/>
was an election dodge was the poorest <lb/>
kind of argument. The department <lb/>
had been in existence less than a year; <lb/>
this was the first opportunity it had had <lb/>
to make through the Executive Council to <lb/>
the House any proposition, and he thought <lb/>
it was a matter for congratulation that <lb/>
upon this, the very first opportunity, the <lb/>
department was able to propound, and <lb/>
had propounded, a policy and a scheme to <lb/>
benefit the agriculturists and ranchers of <lb/>
the country. The House must have some <lb/>
faith in the Government and in their pro<lb break="no"/>posals. When it ws found that a scheme <lb/>
was unwise, then would be the time to <lb/>
condemn. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE SCHOOL DEBENTURE QUESTION. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName> had criticised the proposal <lb/>
to pay certain school debenture indebted<lb break="no"/>ness, arguing that a bad precedent would <lb/>
be established. Mr. Mowat unfortunate<lb break="no"/>ly was not aware of the conditions which <lb/>
made it necessary to propose that vote. <lb/>
The leader of the Government had over<lb break="no"/>looked the explanation of that item. <lb/>
They did not justify the payment of the <lb/>
debentures on the plea that the districts <lb/>
had failed. They were not paying the <lb/>
amounts to save the debenture holders. <lb/>
In one of the districts affected every set<lb break="no"/>tler but one had left, and this unfortun<lb break="no"/>ate one might be pounced upon for the <lb/>
whole debt of the district. The cases <lb/>
were in reality a legacy to this Govern<lb break="no"/>ment from the days when the Lieut.-<lb break="yes"/>Governor conducted the business of the <lb/>
Territories. In those days sufficient <lb/>
caution was not observed in allowing <lb/>
districts to raise money on debentures. <lb/>
Such cases were not likely to occur again. <lb/>
They were very careful now, and demand<lb break="no"/>ed evidence showing that sufficient lands <lb/>
within the district were patented to form <lb/>
ample security for the debt. There was <lb/>
no danger of precedent. Such cases <lb/>
would not occur again. The cases were <lb/>
an old score, and payment was proposed <lb/>
first to save the unfortunate man who <lb/>
might be crushed out through no particular <lb/>
fault of his own, secondly to remove the <lb/>
bar against the re-settlement of lands; <lb/>
with the debt hanging over them the lands <lb/>
would never be settled, and thirdly in the <lb/>
interest of the credit of the school dis<lb break="no"/>tricts of the Territories which it would be <lb/>
unfortunate to have injured. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">RESENTS BASELESS INSINUATIONS. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MOWA1">Mr. Mowat</persName> had renewed his complaints <lb/>
and insinuations about the non printing <lb/>
of the Consolidated Ordinances. Mr. <lb/>
Ross thought that the House realized that <lb/>
Mr. Haultain had made a full explanation <lb/>
of that matter, and he had himself stated <lb/>
to the House the reasons which induced <lb/>
the Government to withhold the printing. <lb/>
The manuscript had not been finished <lb/>
when expected. He had already stated <lb/>
the facts respecting the tenders. Mr. <lb/>
MOwat had mistaken on one point. The <lb/>
tenderer he had in mind was not the low<lb break="no"/>est; he was the lowest tenderer in the <lb/>
Territories. The Government were of the <lb/>
opinion that unless there was a great differ<lb break="no"/>ence in the tenders, they would not be <lb/>
justified in sending the work out of <lb/>
the Territories. It could not be <lb/>
conveniently done out of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories on account of the time which <lb/>
would necessarily be taken up with the <lb/>
sending of proofs. The Queen's Printer <lb/>
had made a recommendation in favor of <lb/>
the acceptance of the lowest Territorial <lb/>
tender. Then they found that the con<lb break="no"/>tactor was not willing to agree to complete <lb/>
the work within any certain time; the con<lb break="no"/>tractor gave as his reason for refusing to <lb/>
agree to any time, that two years had been <lb/>
spent in preparing the work . Did the <lb/>
House ever hear of such an argument? <lb/>
The contractor didnt seem to know <lb/>
whether he could do the printing in <lb/>
12 weeks, 12 months or 12 years. <lb/>
While the Government were thus <lb/>
negotiating with the contractor, the <lb/>
Chairman of the Consolidation Commission <lb/>
suggested to them by letter that it would <lb/>
be well to delay the work until after a <lb/>
a further session. The Government agreed <lb/>
to this suggestion because they be<lb break="no"/>lieved it was in the best interests of the <lb/>
country. Any insinuation of improper <lb/>

<cb/>

motives in relation to the contractors he <lb/>
would. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">HURL BACK IN THE TEETH</p> 

<p>of the man who made it. There were no <lb/>
record since the hon. member for Macleod <lb/>
became entrusted with public business in <lb/>
the North West Territories to show that he <lb/>
had ever in any way favored one contract<lb break="no"/>or against another. (Applause.) He would <lb/>
tell the hon. member for South Regina <lb/>
that there should be something stronger <lb/>
than mere vague suspicions to warrant <lb/>
such charges as he had made, and if he <lb/>
were going to make such insinuations he <lb/>
had better produce some evidence to bakc <lb/>
them up. (Applause.) Such damaging <lb/>
charges were not to go unchallenged, <lb/>
and Mr. Mowat would need better <lb/>
ground to asperse the character of <lb/>
any member of this Government. <lb/>
(Applause). Continuing, in reply to Mr. <lb/>
Eakin, the Commissioner stated that the <lb/>
Important Ordinances of 1897 had been <lb/>
printed separately and distributed, as for <lb/>
instance the Statute Labor, Brands, <lb/>
Estrays, etc. but possibly they were not <lb/>
distributed thoroughly enough. A mis<lb break="no"/>take had been made in not printing <lb/>
more copies of the Ordinance book of last <lb/>
session, but the reason was that they ex<lb break="no"/>pected to have the Consolidated Ordi<lb break="no"/>nances out early in the year, which would <lb/>
have superseded all other Ordinances, and <lb/>
they had tried to be economical as they <lb/>
always did. Mr. Mowat had also made <lb/>
insinuations of favoritism towards Mr. <lb/>
Maloney and his district. He (Mr. <lb/>
Ross) had not looked into the esti<lb break="no"/>mates carefully enough to find out <lb/>
how Mr. Maloney fared. He remem<lb break="no"/>bered having asserted last year that <lb/>
the Estimates would show a fair distribu<lb break="no"/>tion of the moneys between the great div<lb break="no"/>isions of the country. He believed a fair <lb/>
analysis would show that to be the case; <lb/>
and he thought the wants of all the areas <lb/>
and districts had been fairly well attend<lb break="no"/>ed to. He could only say that if Mr. <lb/>
Maloney did fare as well as Mr. Mowat <lb/>
thought he did, then the member for St. <lb/>
Albert had not dealt very fairly by him <lb/>
(Mr. Ross) in kicking as much as he had <lb/>
done about the unfulfilled needs of <lb/>
St. Albert. It was perfectly natural for <lb/>
hon. members to believe that their dis<lb break="no"/>tricts were entitled to large imporvements, <lb/>
but his duty was to hold the scales equit<lb break="no"/>ably, and he hoped to do so as long as he <lb/>
occupied the position he was in. With <lb/>
the present Supplementary Estimates <lb/>
they were providing for many works which <lb/>
members had desired done last year, and <lb/>
which there had been a right to expect <lb/>
last year, only that there were no moneys <lb/>
available for the purpose. Mr. Ross con<lb break="no"/>cluded by asserting in the hearing of all <lb/>
the members who were certainly aware of <lb/>
the fact or otherwise of his statement, that <lb/>
none could allege that through the pat<lb break="no"/>ronage or though the public works ex<lb break="no"/>penditure the Government had ever or on <lb/>
any occasion endeavored to influence any <lb/>
member of that House. (Prolonged <lb/>
applause.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:BRET1">DR. BRETT</persName>, (BANFF)</p> 

<p>the hon. leader of the Opposition, spoke <lb/>
very briefly as the hour was approaching <lb/>
midnight. Dr. Brett had only arrived on <lb/>
the evening train after an absence of <lb/>
several days from the House, having been <lb/>
called to Chicago by the illness of a rela<lb break="no"/>tive. He regretted his inability to hear <lb/>
the speech made by the hon. leader of the <lb/>
Government, and ws sure that it had <lb/>
been a lucid and acceptable statement. <lb/>
He congratulated Mr. Ross upon the read<lb break="no"/>iness of his possession of the details re<lb break="no"/>lating to his departments. The House <lb/>
could not help noticing the large amounts <lb/>
they were voting in the Estimates before <lb/>
them; it was proof of the fact that the <lb/>
Territories were progressive, and that <lb/>
their business was growing larger year by <lb/>
year. He did not wonder that they <lb/>
amounts were large for expenses of govern<lb break="no"/>ment, but it did seem that the expenses of <lb/>
government as compared with the reven<lb break="no"/>ues were very large. He did not intend <lb/>
critisise the departments. He recognis<lb break="no"/>ed that in inaugurating a new system, the <lb/>
officials would be new to their work; they <lb/>
would become capable of handling more <lb/>
work after practice in the offices. He en<lb break="no"/>dorsed the policy of selecting the best <lb/>
available men for the deputy heads. As <lb/>
the business of the country grew, the <lb/>
responsibilities of the Government be<lb break="no"/>came larger. As the amounts they were <lb/>
spending enlarged year by year, it became <lb/>
more necessary for them to watch closely <lb/>
the management and policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Dr. Brett believed the new policy in <lb/>
regard to the stock interests was in the right <lb/>
direction. Mr. Ross had waxed eloquent <lb/>
over an insinuation made by someone that <lb/>
the scheme was for an eleciton purpose. <lb/>
Dr. Brett hope that if the scheme did <lb/>
no good in the election, that it might do <lb/>
no harm anyway. The amount appropri<lb break="no"/>ated ws less than would be justifiable. <lb/>
THere was one policy which the members <lb/>
of the Government had not seemed anx<lb break="no"/>ious to explain,- that was the policy they <lb/>
had indulged in of ignoring the Assembly <lb/>
in certain matters. His reference was to <lb/>
the Yukon administration. They had <lb/>
made their regulations and sent an expe<lb break="no"/>dition without obtaining the sanction of <lb/>
the House.Their action involved a great <lb/>
principle, the principle of license or pro<lb break="no"/>hibition. They had established a license <lb/>
system without sanction. Before the <lb/>
license system was established in the or<lb break="no"/>ganised Territories there had been great <lb/>
discussion, the Assembly had considered <lb/>
the matter in all its bearings, and came to a <lb/>
decision after a great deal of thought. <lb/>
No Government should have taken so <lb/>
great a responsibility as to institute <lb/>
license in any country without full dis<lb break="no"/>cussion and sanction of the people's <lb/>
representatives. Dr. Brett opposed the <lb/>
item of $1750 for paying school debent<lb break="no"/>ures. It seemed to him that this was <lb/>
making a bad precedent. Why not sell <lb/>
the lands if the speculators in the east <lb/>
who advanced the money had now to be <lb/>
reimbursed? It seemed to him that when <lb/>
speculators made a bad investment they <lb/>
had no right to come to the Assembly for <lb/>
remedy. Touching upon the loss of the <lb/>
Yukon territory, Dr. Brett said the fact <lb/>
of the loss gave rise to a certain amount <lb/>
of alarm. If it was the policy of the <lb/>
Government to allow the Territories to be <lb/>
disintegrated without resistance, then he <lb/>
could not agree with it. The delay of <lb/>
two or three years in the printing of the <lb/>
public accounts was another policy he <lb/>
could not agree with. The Government <lb/>
had not apologised so much for these <lb/>
omissions as they sought applause on ac<lb break="no"/>count of the things they thought they had <lb/>
done well. On immigration the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had no policy, contending that the <lb/>
funds were too limited, but he <lb/>
thought a fully organised government <lb/>
ought to be able to do something, even <lb/>
were it no larger than this policy with <lb/>
which they were now appealing to the <lb/>
farmers, namely to spend $2,500 on ex<lb break="no"/>periments. The Government were will<lb break="no"/>ing to rely entirely on the Dominion to <lb/>
select the classes of people for settlers <lb/>
in these Territories. On the whole the  <lb/>
wants and revenues of the Territories were <lb/>
growing less rapidly than the expenses <lb/>
of Government. He would not say that <lb/>
these expenses were increasing too rapid<lb break="no"/>ly, but they were certainly becoming <lb/>
proportionally very great. Not having <lb/>
heard the Premier's speech, he did not <lb/>

<cb/>

know whether any mention had been <lb/>
made of provincial rights. Some policy <lb/>
in this regard should emanate from the <lb/>
Government and he hoped an expected <lb/>
that Mr. Haultain had dealt with the <lb/>
subject. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:MITC3">MR. MITCHELL</persName> (MITCHELL) <lb/></p> 

<p>just wished to allude to one matter which <lb/>
had been omitted, relating to education. <lb/>
During this year Mr. Haultain had visit<lb break="no"/>ed the country north of Saskatoon, where <lb/>
the schools had not been running satis<lb break="no"/>factorily. In regard to these half breed <lb/>
schools there was great difficulty in se<lb break="no"/>curing and retaining teachers, who had <lb/>
been poorly paid. Many of the schools <lb/>
had been closed. Mr. Haultain had <lb/>
made a personal inspection, and found <lb/>
that in several districts the trustees were <lb/>
not able to properly attend to the busi<lb break="no"/>ness of the districts. It was suggested <lb/>
that Commissioners be appointed to carry <lb/>
on the business and get the schools re<lb break="no"/>opened. It was very important that <lb/>
some adequate provision be made for <lb/>
the education of those children, so that <lb/>
when they grow up they shall be able <lb/>
to perform the duties of trustees. Deal<lb break="no"/>ing with some remarks of the member <lb/>
for South Regina, Mr. Mitchellsaid that <lb/>
that hon. gentleman in examining the <lb/>
Estimates appeared to have a great deal <lb/>
of time to spare for figuring out the <lb/>
amounts for St. Albert. Mr. Mowat had <lb/>
probably forgotten that the idea was done <lb/>
away with of giving personally to mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the public works moneys and thus <lb/>
furnishing them with "wads for voters." <lb/>
But it was the Independent member's <lb/>
privilege to recommend works which he <lb/>
believed should be done; this idea did <lb/>
not seem to please Mr. Mowat, who <lb/>
changed his ground so often that it as <lb/>
difficult to follow him. Mr. Mowat had <lb/>
certainly paid the right side of the House <lb/>
a great compliment, and had taken up a <lb/>
great deal of time in mixing up his com<lb break="no"/>pliments and allusions to certain mill<lb break="no"/>stones in the Government and certain <lb/>
references to members interested in <lb/>
draining and others interested in bridg<lb break="no"/>ing. He would just say to Mr. Mowat <lb/>
that he (Mr. Mitchell) had one acquire<lb break="no"/>ment, if no other, which was that he was <lb/>
able to close his mouth in six languages, <lb/>
whereas Mr. Mowat did not seem able to <lb/>
do so in one tongue. Something had <lb/>
been said about the policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. He would suggest that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment's policy deserved the name of <lb/>
the John Bull policy, because it was a <lb/>
policy of integrity, for transacting the <lb/>
public business without fear or favour; <lb/>
and he hoped this Government would <lb/>
stick to that policy. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:BANN2">MR. BANNERMAN</persName> (EAST CALGARY)</p> 

<p>warmly commended the proposed to ini<lb break="no"/>tiate experimental work in agriculture. <lb/>
He said the farm at Indian Head was <lb/>
of little use to Alberta. He trusted that <lb/>
in the scheme of irrigation areas of <lb/>
Southern Alberta and the great wheat <lb/>
areas of Northern Alberta would <lb/>
not be forgotten. Mr. Bannerman ad<lb break="no"/>mitted that Mr. Mowat in his speech <lb/>
that afternoon had had a heavy load to <lb/>
carry, and had carried it well. Mr. <lb/>
Mowat took umbrage at the salaries of <lb/>
the officials, seeming to forget that it <lb/>
was worth 25 per cent. more to live in <lb/>
Regina than anywhere else. Mr. Mowat <lb/>
himself had com to see this and had <lb/>
swapped with Vancouver. Mr. Mowat <lb/>
had also critisised the Peace River trail. <lb/>
The House would recollect that last year <lb/>
when the paltry vote of $10,000 was <lb/>
proposed, he (Mr. Bannerman) suggested <lb/>
that he was willing to forego any works <lb/>
in his district in favor of the Yukon <lb/>
road. Where was the member for South <lb/>
Regina then? He sat there in his chair <lb/>
as still as a frozen frog in January. <lb/>
(Laughter.) Now Mr. Mowat was finding <lb/>
fault because the Government did not <lb/>
proceed with the Yukon business at an <lb/>
earlier stage. The youth and beauty <lb/>
which had overflowed the galleries of the <lb/>
House that afternoon reminded Mr. <lb/>
Bannerman of the fact of the total in<lb break="no"/>adequacy of the Assembly chamber. It <lb/>
had been his privilege to introduce a <lb/>
resolution on that subject, and he had <lb/>
been told that he should not have intro<lb break="no"/>duced the resolution because he was <lb/>
afraid to name the proper place for the <lb/>
location of the capital. He scorned the <lb/>
baseless insinuation. How could he be <lb/>
afraid? The City of Calgary was the <lb/>
second city in size and importance west <lb/>
of Pembroke. (Laughter.) It had a <lb/>
splended system of waterworks, all mo<lb break="no"/>dern conveniences, and two magnificent <lb/>
rivers, than which there were no purer <lb/>
streams in the world. Around Calgary <lb/>
there were millions upon millions of the <lb/>
finest agricultural lands that could be <lb/>
found under the blue canopy of heaven. <lb/>
(Laughter). <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:BOUC3">MR. BOUCHER</persName> (BATOCHE)</p> 

<p>spoke as the representative of the French <lb/>
people of the Territories. Most of the <lb/>
members of the House represented a <lb/>
certain number of the French element, <lb/>
and all should be able to appreciate <lb/>
statements he would make, and which <lb/>
he personally knew to be true, respect<lb break="no"/>ing the French people. In asking for <lb/>
the printing o the Ordinances in French <lb/>

<cb/>

these people were asking merely for jus<lb break="no"/>tice. The Act prescribed that the Ordi<lb break="no"/>nances "shall" be so printed; the Act <lb/>
did not say "may," but "shall," and it <lb/>
was simply asking for justice to ask for <lb/>
the printing in both languages. Mr. <lb/>
Boucher referred to the visit made by the <lb/>
Premier to the school districts in the <lb/>
northern settlements. He trusted that <lb/>
the schools which were standing closed <lb/>
should soon be re-opened, and the chil<lb break="no"/>dren given the advantages of education. <lb/>
He resented certain remarks of Mr. Ag<lb break="no"/>new respecting the character of the <lb/>
people in Batoche district. He haertily <lb/>
endorsed the policy of the Government <lb/>
on the question of Dominion party lines, <lb/>
and wondered why Mr. Mowat had omit<lb break="no"/>ted any mention of Batoche district. <lb/>
The Estimates, he was glad to see, made <lb/>
provision for some very much needed <lb/>
roads. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">MR. HAULTAIN</persName> </p> 

<p>rose at a quarter past twelve to close the <lb/>
debate. He said there were just two <lb/>
points which he desired to mention. The <lb/>
first was in respect of the schools in <lb/>
Batoche and surrounding districts. He <lb/>
had visited that part of the country. <lb/>
The schools referred to were situated <lb/>
almost exclusively in half-breed settle<lb break="no"/>ments, and the older people had not en<lb break="no"/>joyed the advantages which he hoped the <lb/>
younger people will have. The difficulty <lb/>
in connection with the schools were, <lb/>
first, a deficiency in the mangement, <lb/>
and secondly, the difficulty of getting <lb/>
suitable teachers. The teachers must be <lb/>
possessed of the two languages, as an <lb/>
English teacher could make no headway <lb/>
with children who could speak only <lb/>
French. It was suggested to make use <lb/>
of the provision for the appointment of <lb/>
Commissioners to take the management <lb/>
of the districts, and he hoped soon to <lb/>
have in operation again the schools which <lb/>
were closed, and to have the other schools <lb/>
going on more satisfactorily. It was no <lb/>
small thing to have large communities <lb/>
of children deprived of the advantages  <lb/>
of education. The communities were <lb/>
large and he found that there were a <lb/>
great number of children, most of the <lb/>
districts having from 25 to 30 children. <lb/>
It was lamentable to think of these chil<lb break="no"/>dren growing up in ignorance. The de<lb break="no"/>partment was no being to a certain ex<lb break="no"/>tent successful in an attempt to procure <lb/>
qualified teachers able to speak French. <lb/>
The other point was one raised by Dr. <lb/>
Patrick in connection with provincial <lb/>
status,-in regard to the position the <lb/>
Government would take as to borrowing. <lb/>
In his opinion it would be necessary <lb/>
for the carrying on of the provincial business <lb/>
in the Territories that they should have <lb/>
the borrowing power. With vast unde<lb break="no"/>veloped lands and other resources, it <lb/>
woudl be necessary to discout the future. <lb/>
The power to borrow as not bad in it<lb break="no"/>self. He would be unwilling to go into <lb/>
provincial establishment deprived of any <lb/>
power possessed by the provinces. In the <lb/>
exercise of all the powers, they would <lb/>
take warning by the experiences of sis<lb break="no"/>ter provinces, but the possession of the <lb/>
borrowing power would be absolutely <lb/>
essential. He did not put this <lb/>
as the opinion of the Government, <lb/>
but as his own opinion. Mr. <lb/>
Eakin had seemed to fear precipitancy. <lb/>
He (Mr. Haultain) had certainly not in<lb break="no"/>tended to give the impression that pro<lb break="no"/>vincial establishment could be arranged <lb/>
in any hurry. What he had said was <lb/>
that the question would have to be taken <lb/>
up by the next Assembly. He quite <lb/>
agreed with the view that the county <lb/>
would need education on the question,  <lb/>
and it was altogether likely that the <lb/>
country would be asked for an expression <lb/>
of opinion when any negotiations should <lb/>
have reached a certain stage. It was <lb/>
quite likely that any Government in <lb/>
power would wish t oget the verdict of <lb/>
the people. He did not want to <lb/>
jump into provincial establishment. <lb/>
But it was time to think about getting <lb/>
ready to negotiate; it was time to con<lb break="no"/>clude that the period when negotiations <lb/>
would have to be entered upon would ar<lb break="no"/>rive before the end of the term of the Leg<lb break="no"/>islature about to be elected. Mr Haul-<lb break="yes"/>tain said he was well satisfied with the <lb/>
line the debate had taken. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment always expected criticism. There <lb/>
would always be differences of opinion. <lb/>
Referring to Mr. Mowat's withdrawal from <lb/>
the House and to the attitude he had taken <lb/>
in the House, the Premier said that the <lb/>
hon. gentleman and himself had had <lb/>
many tilts in debate, had had <lb/>
many differences of opinion which had <lb/>
often been expressed forcibly and to the <lb/>
point; but he would say now to Mr. <lb/>
Mowat and to others that however <lb/>
strongly he had ever felt he believed he <lb/>
could claim that he had never indulged <lb/>
in personalities, and he had at least never <lb/>
willingly been actuated by personal feel<lb break="no"/>ings of hostility in any debates or discus<lb break="no"/>sions in the House. He was glad that he <lb/>
could part with Mr. Mowat on perfectly <lb/>
friendly terms, and with the best of wishes <lb/>
for his future welfare. <lb/></p> 

<p>The motion carried and the House re<lb break="no"/>solved into Committee of Supply, passed <lb/>
one item, reported progress, and the <lb/>
House adjourned at 12:30 o'clock. <lb/></p>


 <!-- GL, 2018-10-31, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day --> 
<!--<cb/>

success than his predecessor in the Fin<lb break="no"/>ance Department, for while Mr. Foster's <lb/>
predictions have all been falsified, every <lb/>
one of Mr. Fielding's estimates have <lb/>
been more than realized. Six months <lb/>
ago in making his budget speech, the <lb/>
Minister of Finance anticipated a revenue <lb/>
of $39,000,000; the returns show that <lb/>
it is $40,275,704, an increase of nearly <lb/>
$2,500,000 over the previous year. The <lb/>
expenditure on the consolidated fund <lb/>
account was estimated by the Minister <lb/>
at $38,750.00, but it is $50,000 less and <lb/>
instead of $550,000 which he anticipated <lb/>
at his surplus last April he has over <lb/>
$1,500,000. <lb/></p> 

<p>A POINT TO BE REMEMBERED. <lb/></p> 

<p>So much has been said about the in<lb break="no"/>creased expenditure since the accession <lb/>
of the Liberals to power that it is worth <lb/>
while to call attention here to one other <lb/>
point which cannot be too strongly em-<lb break="maybe"/>phasised while Conservative speakers and <lb/>
writers persist in their contention that <lb/>
the slightly increased expenditure <lb/>
is indicative of extravagance. <lb/>
When the Liberals came into office, <lb/>
they found that Mr. Foster had prepar<lb break="no"/>ed his estimates for the ensuing year and <lb/>
these estimates called for a total, - main <lb/>
and supplementary, - of $41,930,237. <lb/>
When it is remembered with what faci<lb break="no"/>lity the extra supplementaries were always <lb/>
swelled by additional items in every de<lb break="no"/>partment, it is not hard to supposed that <lb/>
amount would have been exceeded by <lb/>
two or three million dollars. In addition <lb/>
to this there was a number of heavy ex<lb break="no"/>penditures proposed out of the capital <lb/>
fund. Instead however of that $41,930,-<lb break="maybe"/>237, the actual expenditure of that same <lb/>
year, after the new Government assumed <lb/>
control,- main and supplementary and <lb/>
extra supplementary, - was but $38,335,-<lb break="maybe"/>086. <lb/></p> 

<p>SOME HEAVY EXTRAS. <lb/></p> 

<p>It should be further borne in mind <lb/>
that the heavy expenditure in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with the government of the Yukon <lb/>
which is an item hitherto unknown in <lb/>
the public accounts, is included in this <lb/>
total; and another item which is destined <lb/>
to prove an invaluable investment to <lb/>
Canada is the money spent in deepending <lb/>
the St. Lawrence canals. It has been <lb/>
pointed out repeatedly in the Liberal <lb/>
press that expenditure and extravagance <lb/>
are not synonymous terms under the <lb/>
present Government, though they are so <lb/>
often used interchangeably by Oppo-<lb break="maybe"/>sitionists, and this very material fact <lb/>
cannot be too constantly borne in mind <lb/>
in considering the report of the Finance <lb/>
Minister. <lb/></p> 

<p>STILL CROAKING OF FAILURE. <lb/></p> 

<p>The High Joint Commission will re<lb break="no"/>sume its deliberations in Quebec next <lb/>
Tuesday and its confidently hoped that <lb/>
the Commissioners will be prepared with <lb/>
definite proposals upon which action may <lb/>
be had. Though the Commission has <lb/>
been adjourned its critics have not taken <lb/>
a holiday, and numerous lugubrious pro<lb break="no"/>phecies of failure have been given publi<lb break="no"/>city. One reaction has persistently reiter<lb break="no"/>ated the assertion that there is no possi<lb break="no"/>bility of any reciprocal trade arrange<lb break="no"/>ment, another has declared that there is <lb/>
no hope of settling the Alaska boundary <lb/>
dispute; while the Sealing controversy, <lb/>
the Inshore Fisheries trouble, and other <lb/>
momentous issues are declared to be hope<lb break="no"/>lessly involved, and impossible of settle<lb break="no"/>ment. It is very satisfactory to realise <lb/>
that the Commissioners are statesmen, <lb/>
who will go about their business and <lb/>
attend to the duties of their high office <lb/>
without regard to those croakers. Pat<lb break="no"/>riotic citizens whether of the Empire or <lb/>
the Republic are still firm in the beliefe <lb/>
that substantial and lasting benefit will <lb/>
result to all parties before the Commis<lb break="no"/>sion finally adjourns. <lb/></p> 

<p>THE OTHER FELLOW CLAIMED THAT. <lb/></p> 

<p>Speaking of the splendid harvest, the <lb/>
marked improvement in trade, and the <lb/>
general condition of prosperity which <lb/>
they are compelled to admit, the Mail <lb/>
and Empire editorial remarked the other <lb/>
day, "it is assumed that the electorate <lb/>
will attribute the blessings from above <lb/>
to the Ottawa people," That is just <lb/>
where the Mail and Empire falls into <lb/>
error. It is not the Liberal party that <lb/>
has shown a weakness in the past, or at <lb/>
any time, for appropriating to itself credit <lb/>
for the benefits conferred by Providence. <lb/>
That is a recognised tenet of Conserva<lb break="no"/>tive faith, but all that is claimed for the <lb/>
present Administration is that they have <lb/>
honestly done their best to supplement <lb/>
Nature's benefits rather than depreciate <lb/>
them by unnatural laws and restrictions. <lb/></p> 

<p>SPEED THE PARTING GUESTS <lb/></p> 

<p>Preparations are well under way for <lb/>
the farewell functions in connection with <lb/>
the rapidly approaching departure of the <lb/>
Earl and Countess of Aberdeen early in <lb/>
November. It is proposed to tender the <lb/>
Governor-General a banquet in the Rus<lb break="no"/>sel House as was so succesfully done <lb/>
when Lord Lanedowne was leaving, and <lb/>
the Local Council of Women are arrang<lb break="no"/>ing a social at which the Countees will <lb/>
say good-bye. In other parts of the <lb/>
province and in the east the public mani<lb break="no"/>festations of esteem and regret that the <lb/>
gubernatorial and widespread as they will be <lb/>
gratifying to their Excellencies. <lb/></p> 

<p>TRYING TO BRACE THEM UP. <lb/></p> 

<p>Conservative leaders have been active<lb break="no"/>ly engaged this warm weather with or-<lb break="maybe"/>ganisation work in various parts of the <lb/>
Dominion, and the story continues to be <lb/>
industriously circulated that a general <lb/>
Federal election is approaching. Of <lb/>
course it is the unexpected that happens <lb/>
sometimes, but the politician who can <lb/>
see unmistakable indications that the <lb/>
Government is preparing to appeal to <lb/>
the country has a fine intuition or else <lb/>
a great imagination. <lb/></p> 

<p>To prevent is better than to repent. <lb break="no"/>A little medicine in the shape of the <lb/>
wonderful pellets which are known as <lb/>
Parmelo's Vegetable Pills, administered <lb/>
at the proper time and with the direc<lb break="no"/>tions adhered to often prevent a serious <lb/>
attack of sickness and save money which <lb/>
would go to the doctor. In all iregul-<lb break="maybe"/>larities of the digestive organs they are <lb/>
an invaluable corrective and by lceansing <lb/>
the blood they clear the skin of imper-<lb break="maybe"/>fections.  <lb/></p>-->

</div></div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>