<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgASLA_1902-03-24" xml:lang="en" type="full">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title> <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgASLA">Legislative Assemblies of Alberta and Saskatchewan</name>,
<date when="1902-03-24">24 March 1902</date>, Alberta and Saskatchewan Debates over Confederation with Canada.</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
<persName ref="pers:HUDS1">Isabelle Carré-Hudson</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt> 

<p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p> </publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<bibl corresp="bibl:lgASLA"> <editor>William Franklin Kerr</editor>.
<title>The Leader</title>.
<date when="1902-04-03"/>.
<pubPlace>Regina</pubPlace>:
<publisher>Nicholas Flood Davin</publisher>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>,
<biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="5"/>.
</bibl>

<list>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1902-04-03_Page_001.hocr.html"/> </item>
<item> <ptr target="final/hocr/The_Leader_1902-04-03_Page_005.hocr.html"/> </item>
</list>

</sourceDesc>

</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc> <samplingDecl> <p/> </samplingDecl> </encodingDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change who="mholmes" when="2018-10-30">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>
<change who="ichudson" when="2018-10-30">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<facsimile>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1902-04-03_Page_001"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1902-04-03_Page_001.jpg"/> </surface>
<surface xml:id="The_Leader_1902-04-03_Page_005"> <graphic url="final/images/The_Leader_1902-04-03_Page_005.jpg"/> </surface>
</facsimile>

<text>

<body>

<div type="debate">

<pb n="001" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1902-04-03_Page_001.jpg"/> <lb/>
  
  <fw type="num">1</fw>

<fw type="running">THE LEADER.</fw> 

<fw type="running">REGINA, N.W.T., THURSDAY MORNING, APRIL 3, 1902.</fw> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">ADDRESS ADOPTED</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">After a Short But Interesting De<lb break="no"/>bate in the Assembly.</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">PROVINCIAL AUTONOMY</head> 

<head rendition="simple:centre">The Subject Which Received Most <lb/>
 Attention — Speeches By Dr. Elliott <lb/>
 and Mr. Fisher — Mr. Haultain Out<lb break="no"/>lines Government's Position — Mr. <lb/>
 McDonald Speaks of Delays — Dr. <lb/>
Patrick Wants Two Provinces.</head> 

<p rendition="simple:right">MONDAY, March 24.</p>
 <p>
The debate in the Legislative Assembly <lb/>
on the Address in reply to the Speech <lb/>
was a short one this year and the <lb/>
great question of provincial autonomy <lb/>
was the subject which naturally re<lb break="no"/>ceived the most attention. Mr. Speak<lb break="no"/>er took the chair at 2.30 p.m. Mr. D. <lb/>
H. McDonald moved: "That an order <lb/>
of this House do issue for a return <lb/>
showing what action has been taken <lb/>
by this Government on the resolution <lb/>
passed by this House at the last session <lb/>
regarding the liquor traffic."<lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> said he thought the <lb/>
hon, gentleman would attain his ob<lb break="no"/>ject as easily and more reasonably if <lb/>
he put it in the form of a question <lb/>
rather than a motion for a return. <lb/>
The action taken by the Government <lb/>
in this question was necessarily in the <lb/>
form of correspondence with publish<lb break="no"/>ers, government officials, and others, <lb/>
among them being the authorities in <lb/>
South Carolina, Sweden, and other <lb/>
places where a system similar to these <lb/>
exists. The replies were in the form of <lb/>
letters, pamphlets, blue books and <lb/>
other works on the subject which the <lb/>
hon. gentleman would understand could <lb/>
hardly be copied within reasonable <lb/>
time. Mir. Haultain did not think the <lb/>
information obtained by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was for the information of the <lb/>
House. Their instructions were to <lb/>
enquire into the matter. It would be <lb/>
quite impossible within the limits of <lb/>
a year probably to bring down any <lb/>
such return as this because it <lb/>
would involve writing out a number of <lb/>
long reports in technical language. He <lb/>
thought the hon. gentleman should be <lb/>
satisfied to accept the statement that <lb/>
the Government had been getting all <lb/>
the information, literature and docu<lb break="no"/>ments possible on the subject in accord<lb break="no"/>ance with the resolution of the House. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> said he could quite <lb/>
understand that it would be impossible <lb/>
to get the return in time in view of <lb/>
their experience of the difficulty of <lb/>
getting much shorter papers in pre<lb break="no"/>vious sessions. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>—I do not propose to <lb/>
bring these papers down because they <lb/>
are not matters in which the House is <lb/>
particularly interested at the present <lb/>
time. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName>—I must say this is <lb/>
very unsatisfactory: it will not be <lb/>
satisfactory unless the papers are laid <lb/>
before the House. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Hauitain</persName> –Does the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man wish to press the matter? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. MacDonald</persName> –Certainly, the mo<lb break="no"/>tion is before the House. <lb/></p> 

<p>A vote was then taken, two members <lb/>
supporting Mr. McDonald and the re<lb break="no"/>mainder of the House voting with Mr. <lb/>
Haultain. The Speaker declared the <lb/>
motion lost. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">MORE RETURNS WANTED.</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> then moved for a re<lb break="no"/>turn of all correspondence between <lb/>
this Government and the Federal Gov<lb break="no"/>ernnment in connection with the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion passed by this Assembly at the <lb/>
last session urging the advisability of <lb/>
making grants of land to volunteers <lb/>
from the Territories engaged in the <lb/>
war in South Africa. This was agreed <lb/>
to. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> presented a third mo<lb break="no"/>tion for a return showing the names, if <lb/>
any, of residents in the Territories in <lb/>
any of the Large Local improvement <lb/>
Districts. who have been allowd to pay <lb/>
taxes assessed against their land <lb/>
at less than the amount charg<lb break="no"/>ed againist these lands: and also <lb/>
a fourth motion for a return showing <lb/>
(1) the total amount charged against <lb/>
the Canadian Pacific Railway Co. and <lb/>
the Hudson Bay Co. for taxes on lands <lb/>
in the Large Local Improvement Dis<lb break="no"/>tricts in the Territories for the years <lb/>
1899, 1900 and 1901; and (2) the amount <lb/>

<cb/>

accepted by the Government in settle<lb break="no"/>ment of the taxes referred to, and the <lb/>
date of settlement. <lb/></p> 

<p>In regard to these Mr. Sifton said <lb/>
there was no objection to them The <lb/>
staff of the local improvement branch <lb/>
was very busy, but the returns would <lb/>
be brought down hefore the end of the <lb/>
session. <lb/></p> 

 <p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> — Will the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man say these returns will be brought <lb/>
down as soon as possible? <lb/></p> 

 <p><persName ref="pers:SIFT2">Mr. Sifton</persName> — They will be just as soon <lb/>
as the notices of this year's assessment <lb/>
are issued, which the hon. gentleman <lb/>
will realise is also an important matter <lb/>
as we need the money. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:PATR1">Dr. Patrick</persName> (Yorkton) –Perhaps the <lb/>
hon. gentlenian will be a little more <lb/>
definite and say if they could be brought <lb/>
down before the budget debate? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:SIFT2">Mr. Sifton</persName> –Yes, they will be brought <lb/>
down before the budget debate. The <lb/>
motions were then agreed to. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">A QUESTION OF PRIVILEGE.</p> 

<p>Upon the Orders of the Day being <lb/>
called Mr. McDonald rose to a question <lb/>
of privilege. He said a matter had <lb/>
been brought up in the Senate of Can<lb break="no"/>ada, within the last few days. He <lb/>
would call the attention of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to a question asked in the Senate <lb/>
on the 21st of March by Senator Per<lb break="no"/>ley, Mr. McDonald then read from a <lb/>
newspaper report as follows: <lb/></p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>Senator Perley enquired if the Government of <lb/>
the North-West Territories made application to <lb/>
enter confederation under full provinclal auton<lb break="no"/>omy, and if so, what were the terms and condi<lb break="no"/>tions proposed by them. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Scott said an application had been made <lb/>
for the admission of a portion of the Territories. <lb/>
but nothing had been done or was likely <lb/>
to be at present. The papers were confidential <lb/>
and could not be brought down without the <lb/>
leave of the North-West Government. <lb/></p> 

<p>In answer to Mr. Lougheed, he said the mat<lb break="no"/>ter could not be dealt with at the present ses<lb break="no"/>sion. It was under consideration. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. Lougheed of the North-West <lb/>
Government had been in Ottawa. The feeling <lb/>
in the Territories was strongly in favor of pro<lb break="no"/>vincial autonomy, and the present government <lb/>
were understood to be not adverse to giving <lb/>
the Territories autonomy. He was sure there <lb/>
would be great disappointment if some measure <lb/>
along these lines was not brought down at <lb/>
once. <lb/></p> 

<p>Hon. Mr. Scott said there were several ques<lb break="no"/>tions to be settled, such as whether there should <lb/>
be one province or several: and where the <lb/>
capital should be. <lb/></p> 
</quote>



<p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> continuing said: This <lb/>
came I am sure as a surprise to a large <lb/>
number of people in the North-West. <lb/>
After years of delay on this question <lb/>
 and after the leader of the Govern<lb break="no"/>nment—</p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> here raised a point of <lb/>
order and Mr. Speaker ruled Mr. Mc<lb break="no"/>Donald out of order saying: "This is <lb/>
referred to in the Speech." <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>—The hon. gentleman <lb/>
might call the attention of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to certain statements. I <lb/>
would not object to that. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName>—Our desire was to <lb/>
find out if the papers were held secret <lb/>
at the instance of this Government and <lb/>
for what reason. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>—No, the papers were <lb/>
not held secret at the instance of this <lb/>
Government. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> –It's a question then <lb/>
between you and Hon. Mr. Scott. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> —The hon. gentleman <lb/>
is attributing statements to Mr. <lb/>
Scott which are not in the report he <lb/>
read. Mr. Scott said the papers could <lb/>
not be brought down without the leave <lb/>
of the North-West Government. Any<lb break="no"/>one would understand that negotia<lb break="no"/>tions pending between two govern<lb break="no"/>ments are confidential. The matter <lb/>
then dropped. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE ADDRESS IN REPLY. <lb/></p> 

<p>Dr. Elliott (Wolseley) then rose <lb/>
amid cheers to move that a humble <lb/>
address be presented to His Honor. <lb/>
He made an eloquent reference to the <lb/>
visit of the Duke and Duchess of Corn<lb break="no"/>wall and York, to the great object <lb/>
lesson their world-wide tour was to the <lb/>
un-British world, and to the interest <lb/>
the Duke and Duchess took in Canada <lb/>
as was made manifest by the address <lb/>
of His Royal Highness in London where <lb/>
he spoke of Canada's need of popula<lb break="no"/>tion and made an appeal to send of <lb/>
their best. Referring to the inrush of <lb/>
immigrants Dr. Elliott noted the fact <lb/>
that every man in the West, seemed to <lb/>
think his district the best and the new <lb/>
settlers seemed imbued with the same <lb/>
idea for they think they can pick out a <lb/>
better one and the vast majority of <lb/>
them go out to new portions of the <lb/>
country. This large immigration <lb/>
would entail a very great expenditure <lb/>
on the part of this Government in <lb/>
building roads and bridges and opening <lb/>
up schools. He considered the federal <lb/>
government would only be doing its <lb/>
duty if it dealt very liberally with the <lb/>
people of the Territories. <lb/></p> 

<p>Speaking of the big crop of last year, <lb/>
Dr. Elliott said the crop bulletin issued <lb/>
by the Territorial Department of Agri<lb break="no"/>culture was probably more reliable <lb/>
than any issued by any department in <lb/>
Canada. That document was an <lb/>
interesting one and showed that the <lb/>
wheat area of the Territories was not <lb/>
confined to East Assiniboia, but West <lb/>
Assiniboia, Saskatchewan and Alberta <lb/>
were also included. There was a crop <lb/>
of 13,000,000 bushels of wheat, and <lb/>
11,000,000 bushels of oats and yet only <lb/>
a very small portion of the best of the <lb/>
land had seen the plow. At Rosthern <lb/>
500, 000 bushels of wheat would this <lb/>
year he exported and the district of <lb/>
Saskatchewan would in a very short <lb/>
time produce a million bushels, And <lb/>
wheat was not the only grain grown <lb/>
in the Territories. Of the 11,000,000 <lb/>
bushels of oats the vast bulk of it was <lb/>
grown west of the 3rd meridian and <lb/>
one-third of the total crop of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tories, was grown west of the 3rd <lb/>
meridian. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE GRAIN BLOCKADE.</p> 

<p>We have, continued Dr. Elliott, not <lb/>
only grown a vast amount of grain but <lb/>
we have experienced a great deal of <lb/>
trouble in exporting it, and I must <lb/>
congratulate the Minister of Agricul<lb break="no"/>ture on the efforts put forth in an <lb/>
endeavor to bring public opinion to <lb/>
bear on the C.P.R. to get them to move <lb/>
the grain. It is all very well for people <lb/>
1,500 miles to the east to talk of there <lb/>
being no blockade in this country, but <lb/>
there is no use telling men who have <lb/>
stood in their offices and seen hund<lb break="no"/>reds of loads of grain standing on the <lb/>
streets and the elevators closed because <lb/>
they could not get cars and were taking <lb/>
much less for their grain. There was a <lb/>
standing offer by some people of <lb/>
five cents over and above the <lb/>
market price, provided the grain <lb/>
was loaded on cars, but the C. P. <lb/>
R. in its wisdom did not see fit to <lb/>
supply farmers with cars. They had <lb/>
loading platforms and other facilities <lb/>
but the cars did not come. After <lb/>
public sentiment had been worked up <lb/>
to its highest pitch and the Minister of <lb/>
Agriculture, boards of trade and others <lb/>
had brought pressure to bear, the <lb/>
C..P.R. at last made a move and de<lb break="no"/>cided to allow some of the grain to be <lb/>
shipped via North Portal and other <lb/>
roads to the American side where there <lb/>
was room to store it, but I am sorry to <lb/>
say that their efforts have not contin<lb break="no"/>ued as long as they should have done. <lb/>

<cb/>

And when we consider the expense the <lb/>
farmers of this country have gone to in <lb/>
 building warehouses— in 14 towns at <lb/>
least 400 buildings costing at least <lb/>
$20,000–to store wheat and with hun<lb break="no"/>ds of thousands of bushels lying to<lb break="no"/>day in great danger of having a con<lb break="no"/>siderable portion destroyed if stormy <lb/>
 weather comes, — I say when we con<lb break="no"/>sider these things and all that the <lb/>
farmers have done for the C.P.R., they <lb/>
should in all fairness and honesty have <lb/>
done everything possible to prevent <lb/>
the danger of having the crop damaged <lb/>
by having it put on the market before <lb/>
spring opened. <lb/>
 <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">PROVINCIAL AUTONOMY <lb/></p> 

<p>I am pleased to notice in His Honor's <lb/>
speech that the Government has been <lb/>
in communication with the federal <lb/>
government, but that no answer has <lb/>
been received. This certainly is a dis<lb break="no"/>appointment to the people of this <lb/>
House and country. (Hear, hear.) It <lb/>
is time the people of the country were <lb/>
prepared to give to their representa<lb break="no"/>tives full powers of provincial man<lb break="no"/>hood, and the representatives have done <lb/>
their duty when the House passed the <lb/>
mermorial and sent it to Ottawa and <lb/>
since then the Government have been <lb/>
in communication with the federal <lb/>
authorities and they have simply been <lb/>
marking time and putting the matter <lb/>
off. The delay has been caused by the <lb/>
action of the Dominion Government. <lb/>
Representations have been made to <lb/>
them. Every member of this House <lb/>
who takes an intelligent interest in <lb/>
what has been said in and out of the <lb/>
House knows what those representa<lb break="no"/>tions have been or almost. They knew <lb/>
them from the speeches delivered in <lb/>
1900, from the speech at Indian Head, <lb/>
and by the budgets of the last three or <lb/>
four years. Everyone knows the con<lb break="no"/>ditions that the people and Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of this country are asking for. <lb/></p> 

 <p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> — Is the Indian Head <lb/>
speech the condition? <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:ELLI1">Mr. Elliott</persName> —it is only a part of it, <lb/>
The conditions the people are asking <lb/>
are only, the ordinary conditions of <lb/>
British subjects, the same as the other <lb/>
provinces. We are not paupers and <lb/>
are not asking for special favors or <lb/>
special rights. They are not fancy <lb/>
terms: we ask for our rights, nothing <lb/>
nore and expect to receive nothing <lb/>
less from the hands of the Dominion <lb/>
Government. (Hear, hear.) The terms <lb/>
upon which the North-West wishes to <lb/>
enter confederation are practically <lb/>
public property but up to the present ­ <lb/>
hour we have not the slightest indica<lb break="no"/>tion bow our terms are going to be re<lb break="no"/>ceived by the Ottawa government. <lb/></p> 

<p>Referring to the increased represen<lb break="no"/>tation in the House Dr. Elliott said <lb/>
they were pleased to think that the <lb/>
people thought so much of the memb<lb break="no"/>ers of the House that they wanted <lb/>
more of them (Laughter). When they <lb/>
talked of increased representation, he <lb/>
wondered where they were going to <lb/>
put them. Unless they had provincial <lb/>
autonomy and power to put up build<lb break="no"/>ings it would be an impossibility to ac<lb break="no"/>commodate the new members. <lb/></p> 

<p>Dr. Elliott in speaking of the receipts <lb/>
and expenditures said it had always <lb/>
been the policy of this Government to <lb/>
deal fairly with the people of the coun<lb break="no"/>try in always giving them all the <lb/>
information they desired in regard to <lb/>
the expenditures. With the growing <lb/>
population, the vast, increase in the <lb/>
number of school children and the <lb/>
number of schools, the Government <lb/>
would have a hard task to manage the <lb/>
country unless the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment gave a largely increased grant. <lb/>
He hoped they would do so. Dr. <lb/>
Elliott concluded by moving that the <lb/>
following address he presented to His <lb/>
Honor: We. His Majesty's dutiful and <lb/>
loyal subjects, the Legislative Assem<lb break="no"/>bly of the North-West Territories in <lb/>
session assembled, thank Your Honor <lb/>
for the gracious speech which Your <lb/>
Honor has been pleased to address to <lb/>
us at the opening of this present ses<lb break="no"/>sion. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">MR. FISHER SECONDS THE MOTION. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. Fisher</persName> (Batoche) seconded the <lb/>
motion. After congratulating Dr. <lb/>
Elliott on his speech, he referred to the <lb/>
great prosperity and happiness now <lb/>
general not only in the Territories but <lb/>
throughout Canada. Mr. Fisher con<lb break="no"/>fined his remarks largely to Saskat<lb break="no"/>chewan which he said had in former <lb/>
years been more or less neglected, <lb/>
immigrants being encouraged to take <lb/>
some other direction. Conditions had <lb/>
now taken a radical change and Sas<lb break="no"/>katchewau was getting a great share <lb/>
of the immigrants. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> –That is due to the <lb/>
Government at Ottawa. <lb/></p> 

 <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. Fisher</persName> — Possibly that has a great <lb/>
deal to do with it. (Cheers. ) Mr. <lb/>
Fisher then devoted considerable time <lb/>
to a comparison of the yields of grains <lb/>
in Saskatchewan and other portions of <lb/>
the Territories showing that in West <lb/>
Saskatchewan the yield had run near<lb break="no"/>ly five bushels more to the acre than <lb/>
elsewhere. The new settlers had great <lb/>
confidence in the Saskatchewan dis<lb break="no"/>trict and while the census showed a <lb/>
population of 25,579 he would venture <lb/>
to say it had now increased to 30,000 <lb/>
and before the end of the present year <lb/>
would be 35,000, and before four years <lb/>
elapsed Saskatchewan would contain <lb/>
75,000 souls. <lb/></p> 

<p>The speaker then made a most elo<lb break="no"/>quent reference to the visit of the <lb/>
Duke and Duchess of Cornwall and <lb/>
York. Referring to the recent census, <lb/>
which was somewhat disappointing, <lb/>
Mr. Fisher said he believed the next <lb/>
one would show an increase to double <lb/>
the present figures. The coronation of <lb/>
King Edward VII would be an event <lb/>
such as had never occurred before and he <lb/>
was glad the premiers of the different <lb/>
provinces had been invited. (Hear, <lb/>
hear.) Let me say in particular, con<lb break="no"/>tinued Mr, Fisher, that it must be a <lb/>
matter of great pride to the gentle<lb break="no"/>man who occupies that position in this <lb/>
House to take part in that great cere<lb break="no"/>mony. (Cheers.) All should entertain <lb/>
very bright hopes of the future of the <lb/>
North-West Territories. We have <lb/>
citizens of different nationalities, dif<lb break="no"/>ferent religions, but we must all re<lb break="no"/>member that we are all lhere with the <lb/>
same view, to build up the country <lb/>
(Loud cheers) founded on principles of <lb/>
liberty and equal lights to all. (Cheers.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">LEADER OF THE OPPOSITION. <lb/></p> 

<p><persName ref="pers:MACD10">Mr. McDonald</persName> on rising to reply was <lb/>
greeted with cheers. He said: Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, if there was no other reason <lb/>
why l should get up on this occasion, <lb/>
if nothing else would bring me to my <lb/>
feet, I should take the opportunity to <lb/>
congratulate the hon. member who has <lb/>
just taken his seat, upon his fervent <lb/>
and loyal speech and the eloquent <lb/>
tribute he his paid to the representa<lb break="no"/>tives of the British Empire, who have <lb/>
passed through this country during the <lb/>
past year. We have had the pleasure <lb/>
of hearing the hon. member before. <lb/>
He speaks in a language which is not <lb/>
the language of his youth, but we can <lb/>
safely say that during the term of <lb/>
this legislature he need not apologise <lb/>
to anybody of take a back seat for any <lb/>

<cb/>

speech he has made. I congratulate <lb/>
him on that account. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Speaker, I am sure with the rest <lb/>
of the members of this assembly, pos<lb break="no"/>sibly not those entirely in the confid<lb break="no"/>ence of the Government, we were sur<lb break="no"/>prised at the opening of this House to <lb/>
to find the bill of fare presented to us <lb/>
in the condition it is. We have had <lb/>
during the past years, questions of im<lb break="no"/>portance that have been before the <lb/>
Territories for some time, brought be<lb break="no"/>fore this House and discussed by the <lb/>
principal members of this House, and <lb/>
for which the unanimous approval of <lb/>
this House was asked. We had hoped <lb/>
that these would have been dealt with <lb/>
more fully at the opening of the House. <lb/>
We have been advised that the time <lb/>
is one characterised by great prosperity <lb/>
in all sections of the country. This is <lb/>
evident not only to the people of this <lb/>
country, but it is evident also to the <lb/>
people of Eastern Canada. There has <lb/>
never been any time in the history of <lb/>
North-West Canada or even of the <lb/>
whole Dominion, when, I suppose, <lb/>
there has been such a prosperous year <lb/>
as the year 1901. The fame of Canada <lb/>
has gone abroad to all parts of the Bri<lb break="no"/>tish Empire that this year has been one <lb/>
of great prosperity. It is indisputable <lb/>
even in the old land and one of the <lb/>
most important papers in the world <lb/>
had special reference to Canada in its <lb/>
first issue of the year. I quote from <lb/>
the London Times: "During the year <lb/>
just closed Canada has reached a high<lb break="no"/>er imark in her progress, than she has <lb/>
hitherto attained." There is not a <lb/>
question of a doubt, that from the <lb/>
eastern part of Canada to the borders <lb/>
of Manitoba they look to the west as a <lb/>
support to the east. Eastern manufac<lb break="no"/>turers look to the west and all the <lb/>
traffic that comes from the east is paid <lb/>
for by the people of the west. It is re<lb break="no"/>gretable, Mr. Speaker, that the condi<lb break="no"/>tions of prosperity which we here speak <lb/>
of, cannot be taken full advantage of <lb/>
by the people of this country. This <lb/>
has been a great year for the people of <lb/>
this country in a general way, but in<lb break="no"/>dividually it has come very hard upon <lb/>
some of the settlers of this country. <lb/></p>
 <p>
During the past year we had the <lb/>
pleasure of the visit of the Duke and <lb/>
Duchess of Cornwall and York. The <lb/>
eloquent tributes that have already <lb/>
been paid to then by preceding speak<lb break="no"/>ers were sufficient to allow me to pass <lb/>
them over, further than to say that we <lb/>
join with them in their loyal remarks <lb/>
and the pleasure it gave this country <lb/>
to welcome the representatives of the <lb/>
British Crown. Nothing could have <lb/>
  been better than the reception in Re<lb break="no"/>gina and Calgary,—the wheat arches <lb/>
and cattle. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">CREDIT DUE THE G.G.A.</p> 

<p>The third subject dealt with in the <lb/>
Speech says the unprecedented crop of <lb/>
last season brought the transportation <lb/>
question before the public. Now, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, this is a question that has <lb/>
been discussed in all parts of the Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, and has been before the people <lb/>
from the early part of the shipping <lb/>
season of 1901-1902. We had expected <lb/>
from such a large crop in this country <lb/>
that the people would have been able to <lb/>
reap the advantage from it, they de<lb break="no"/>served, but unfortunately the circum<lb break="no"/>stances that prevailed have severely <lb/>
handicapped the farmers in marketing <lb/>
their crops. I quote from the Speech <lb/>
that the Government claims the farm<lb break="no"/>ers in this country are now in receipt <lb/>
of perhaps 10 per cent. advance in <lb/>
prices owing to their efforts with the <lb/>
C. P. R. in endeavoring to relieve the <lb/>
blockade, but when the Department of <lb/>
Agriculture takes to itself credit for <lb/>
relieving the block of a few weeks ago, <lb/>
they are stretching the point. This <lb/>
evil existed several months before <lb/>
three weeks ago. What happened <lb/>
then? Where was the Department of <lb/>
Agriculture? The Department of <lb/>
Agriculture should give credit <lb/>
where credit is due. Who brought <lb/>
this matter before the people <lb/>
of the country but the farmers of this <lb/>
country. What about the Grain Grow<lb break="no"/>ers' Association? They are the ones <lb/>
who deserve the credit. <lb/></p> 

<p>It is true one of the preceding speak<lb break="no"/>ers said the Grain Growers Association <lb/>
backed up the Department of Agricul<lb break="no"/>ture. I think the Grain Growers' <lb/>
Association were in this before the <lb/>
Department of Agriculture. There <lb/>
has been no victory gained for the <lb/>
farmers of this country but what they <lb/>
have worked for themselves. <lb/></p> 

<p>This difficulty existed in December, <lb/>
1901. In that month the Grain Grow<lb break="no"/>ers' Association was organised, and <lb/>
ever since they have been actively <lb/>
endeavoring to get the C.P.R. to help <lb/>
them. The Winnipeg board of trade <lb/>
and grain exchange took the matter up. <lb/>
If the Department of Agriculture have <lb/>
taken such an interest in the matter <lb/>
why is it not done more actively to<lb break="no"/>day. At Qu'Appelle Station in the <lb/>
constituency which the honorable gen<lb break="no"/>tleman represents, and at Indian Head <lb/>
there is still a grain blockade, and <lb/>
further than that, Mr. Speaker, <lb/>
this is not the only product produced <lb/>
by the people of this country in which <lb/>
there has been a blockage. What <lb/>
about the shipments of cattle last sea<lb break="no"/>son: Where was the department when <lb/>
the farmers and ranchers were bring<lb break="no"/>ing in cattle and keeping them for <lb/>
days? The cattlemen looked to the <lb/>
Winnipeg board of trade for relief and <lb/>
it was them who assisted. If possible <lb/>
this was a more vital question than <lb/>
even the wheat blockade. (A voice, <lb/>
No.) We know that wheat call be <lb/>
stored in a building or taken back <lb/>
home and does not suffer as do cattle <lb/>
in being driven to the station. The <lb/>
cattlemen also have their space secur<lb break="no"/>ed at Montreal. I think the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment of Agriculture is stretching this <lb/>
a little too far in taking credit for this <lb/>
much. But let them persevere in their <lb/>
efforts. There was raised north of the <lb/>
Qu'Appelle Valley last season at least <lb/>
from one million to a million and a <lb/>
half bushels, most of it is still there. <lb/>
The farmers are unable to get it out <lb/>
and are getting discouraged about <lb/>
growing wheat. What has the De<lb break="no"/>partment of Agriculture done to re<lb break="no"/>lieve the people north of the Qu'Ap<lb break="no"/>pelle Valley? Their influence with the <lb/>
C. P. R. is so great now, they have got <lb/>
to be so friendly with them, since they <lb/>
remitted their taxes, (Laughter), that <lb/>
they can do anything, they can fully <lb/>
persuade them to build railways in all <lb/>
parts of the country, One of our repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives from the North-West, in the <lb/>
House of Commons last week estimat<lb break="no"/>ed that the farmers of Manitoba, and <lb/>
the North-West had lost seven million <lb/>
dollars on the price of wheat owing to <lb/>
the grain blockade. It would seem a <lb/>
pity if this Government had any in<lb break="no"/>fluence with the C. P. R. that they did <lb/>
not save to this country some portion <lb/>
of these seven million dollars. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">A REGRETTABLE DELAY.</p> 

<p>Now, Mr. Speaker, we come to the <lb/>
paragraph of the Speech, which <lb/>
says: During the recess my Govern<lb break="no"/>ment has been in communication with <lb/>
the Federal Governument" and goes on <lb/>

<cb/>

further. This is a paragraph which I <lb/>
believe we are most interested in. We <lb/>
had thought that before this we would <lb/>
have had some definite reply to that <lb/>
memorial of 1900, but year after year <lb/>
we have been put off with the state<lb break="no"/>ment that it is the Government at <lb/>
Ottawa that is at fault. (Hear, hear.) <lb/>
And further we have been told from <lb/>
Ottawa in reply to a question by the <lb/>
Hon. Senator Perley in the Senate on <lb/>
the 21st of March, that nothing had <lb/>
been done or was likely to be done at <lb/>
present with regard to the admission <lb/>
of a portion of the Territories as <lb/>
province. I think, Mr. Speaker, that <lb/>
we all agree on this point that we are <lb/>
disappointed. (Hear, hear.) We had <lb/>
anticipated after passing that memor<lb break="no"/>ial in 1900 that our Government would <lb/>
ere this have been able to get some<lb break="no"/>thing for the people of this country. <lb/>
We are anxious to be unanimous on <lb/>
this question and give them all the <lb/>
support they deserve and it was that <lb/>
motive that prompted the members of <lb/>
this side of the House to be unanimous <lb/>
in passing that resolution. We are <lb/>
not anxious to make this a party ques<lb break="no"/>tion if we can believe that this Govern<lb break="no"/>ment is sincere in their demand. We <lb/>
have taken the statement of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment for years that they are urging <lb/>
these matters. We had a statement <lb/>
from Ottawa last year that only then <lb/>
had they been asked to put their re<lb break="no"/>presentations in writing: up to that <lb/>
time they had been verbal. They have <lb/>
put in their written demand, and judg<lb break="no"/>ing by a remark made by the <lb/>
hon. leader of this Government, <lb/>
at Indian Head these demands <lb/>
in some particular, were con<lb break="no"/>sidered absurd. A very rash state<lb break="no"/>ment, I think, for any member of a <lb/>
government of this country to make, <lb/>
that after this House had been session <lb/>
after session passing resolutions and the <lb/>
Government making their annual trips <lb/>
to Ottawa, that now some of these <lb/>
demands were considered absurd. It <lb/>
was a very weak point, I think, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, for our representative to <lb/>
admit of the case he was pleading. <lb/></p> 

<p>Now, Mr. Speaker, there is one thing <lb/>
with regard to the demands that have <lb/>
 been made, — the people of this country <lb/>
do not know what they are. Some <lb/>
will tell you to look at the Indian Head <lb/>
speech, some to the memorial, some to <lb/>
the Yorkton speech, some to the Carn<lb break="no"/>duff speech, but never yet has this <lb/>
Government laid before this House the <lb/>
demands the Government has made. <lb/>
It is time we had them. If they are <lb/>
sincere and their demands are just, we <lb/>
ought to know them so we can back <lb/>
them up as unanimously as we did <lb/>
the memorial passed in 1900. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">RETURNS DELAYED.</p> 

<p>Now, Mr. Speaker, I just want to <lb/>
deal with a few remarks nade by some <lb/>
of the previous speakers. One hon. <lb/>
gentleman said that we had been <lb/>
accustomed to get fair statements of <lb/>
receipts, expenditure and returns from <lb/>
this Government. I wish to question <lb/>
that statement. We have had occasion <lb/>
to know that, in one year in this <lb/>
country;we did not get a fair state<lb break="no"/>ment. We had occasion to know that, <lb/>
in one year a sum of $20,000 was added <lb/>
to the receipts of this country, (Laugh<lb break="no"/>ter) and if the hon. gentleman calls <lb/>
that a fair statement he must be draw<lb break="no"/>ing on his imagination. And also with <lb/>
regard to the returns. We have some<lb break="no"/>times been criticised for asking for <lb/>
returns which occupied too much time <lb/>
of the civil servants in preparing them <lb/>
for the House, but I wish to draw the <lb/>
attention of the Government to the <lb/>
return asked for last session of $92,000 <lb/>
which was voted by the Dominion <lb/>
Government to the North-West Ter<lb break="no"/>ritories, for a special purpose. That <lb/>
return was not brought down at the <lb/>
session at which it was asked for, and <lb/>
we were not able to see whether that <lb/>
sum, was spent for the purpose, for <lb/>
which it was voted. Now if the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment were as fair as the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber says they are we should have had <lb/>
that return in time. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">CORPORATIONS' TAXES.</p> 

<p>I wish to take up another matter <lb/>
just now, as I fear owing to dilatoriness <lb/>
in bringing down returns we may not <lb/>
have an opportunity of discussing it <lb/>
very early this session. I refer to <lb/>
the taxes in the large local improve<lb break="no"/>ment districts on the C. P. R. and Hud<lb break="no"/>son's Bay Co. lands. We know, Mr. <lb/>
Speaker, that this has been a matter of <lb/>
litigation and dispute. We had ex<lb break="no"/>pected last year that after the leader of <lb/>
the Government had passed his re<lb break="no"/>troactive legislation, which we objected <lb/>
to, not because it affected these cor<lb break="no"/>porations but on principle. We were <lb/>
accused of corporation leanings and as <lb/>
being on the side of the corporations <lb/>
as against the country, but I do not <lb/>
think they had a good right to charge <lb/>
us with that statement. The hon. <lb/>
member for West Calgary (Mr. Ben<lb break="no"/>nett) made the stateanent that, the <lb/>
Hudson's Bay Co. and other corporations <lb/>
should pay their taxes, and we believed <lb/>
that then and we believe it now. <lb/></p> 

<p>It has been stated openly that the <lb/>
Government has allowed these cor<lb break="no"/>porations to pay their taxes for less <lb/>
than one hundred cents on the dollar <lb/>
and they have never contradicted it. <lb/>
We may be able to account for one <lb/>
reason for the influence of this Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, with the C. P.R. when we see <lb/>
what they related to the company on <lb/>
their taxes. I do not see any reason <lb/>
why the Government should put their <lb/>
hands in their pocket to pay the C. P. <lb/>
R.'s taxes. If they can successfully <lb/>
deny this, we will withdraw it, but I <lb/>
have it on the best authority from one <lb/>
of the large corporations that they did <lb/>
make a settlement at less than one <lb/>
hundred cents on the dollar. We claim <lb/>
for the rest of the ratepayers in these <lb/>
local improvement districts the same <lb/>
treatment. If they have settled with <lb/>
the corporations for less than one <lb/>
hundred cents on the dollar, then they <lb/></p> 

<!--<p>(Continned on page 5.) <lb/></p> <lb/>-->

<pb n="005" facs="final/images/The_Leader_1902-04-03_Page_005.jpg"/> <lb/>
</div>
 <div type="debate">
   
   <fw type="num">5</fw>
   
<head rendition="simple:centre">ADDRESS ADOPTED</head>

<p rendition="simple:centre">(Continued from page 1.)</p>

<p>should make an equal allowance to <lb/>
other ratepayers in those districts. It <lb/>
is not fair that one corporation should <lb/>
receive a benefit that is withheld from <lb/>
other settlers. During the time <lb/>
that I have represented the el<lb break="no"/>ectoral district of North Qu'<lb break="no"/>Appelle I have almost every year <lb/>
brought before them the lack of water <lb/>
in that district especially north of the <lb/>
Qu'Appelle Valley. This Government <lb/>
has not yet successfully coped with <lb/>
that question, in fact they have mae <lb/>
a complete failure of it. Had they <lb/>
been a business-like Government they <lb/>
would have ere this, secured for these <lb/>
settlers a bountiful supply of water. <lb/>
They have even discouraged the people <lb/>
in that district as they have gone in <lb/>
and made unsuccessful attempts to get <lb/>
water. <lb/></p> 

<p>I would refer also to the dilatoriness <lb/>
in doing road work. There was a vote <lb/>
in 1900 re-voted in 1901 for roads that <lb/>
to this day are not done. If the hon. <lb/>
gentleman would call that a business<lb break="no"/>like government he had a poor idea of <lb/>
business. <lb/></p> 

<p>I would call attention to the exces<lb break="no"/>sive cost of selling lands for arrears of <lb/>
taxes. If we have not the expensive <lb/>
numerical system of Manitoba and the <lb/>
other provinces, there is to my mind <lb/>
nothing more expensive than the <lb/>
system of confiscating lands in the <lb/>
local improvement districts. My at<lb break="no"/>tention was called to one case where <lb/>
the arrears were $5.00 and the land <lb/>
was redeemed within three or four <lb/>
months and the costs were $14.00, mak<lb break="no"/>ing a total of $19.00. I do not think <lb/>
the Commissioner of Public Works or <lb/>
any member of the Government can <lb/>
bring to the attention of the House a <lb/>
case in any province where such an ex<lb break="no"/>cessive cost is charged up. I had a case <lb/>
from Manitoba brought to my atten<lb break="no"/>tion where the costs were not one-<lb break="yes"/>third as much proportionately as in <lb/>
this case. <lb/></p> 

<p>We are told that there has been a <lb/>
great increase in the population and <lb/>
that we would have additional repre<lb break="no"/>sentation. I think as members of the <lb/>
Opposition we will see that as far as <lb/>
the Government are concerned they <lb/>
would like to legislate us out of the <lb/>
House (Cries of 110, 110). I only hope <lb/>
the will show that fairness which the <lb/>
settlement in this country demands. <lb/>
They should take into consideration <lb/>
what will happen in the next few <lb/>
years. There are some of us who can<lb break="no"/>not credit that they will give all the <lb/>
people of the Territories that justice <lb/>
which we think they should have. We <lb/>
are probably judging them a little too <lb/>
harshly (Hear, hear), by time will tell. <lb/>
We will be willing to give them the <lb/>
benefit of our judgment in the matter <lb/>
but I am doubtful if they will accept <lb/>
it. <lb/></p> 

<p>I would like to see the papers be<lb break="no"/>tween the Ottawa Government and <lb/>
this Government over provincial <lb/>
autonomy. This Government is likely <lb/>
pressing for it but have they pressed <lb/>
strongly enough? What the people <lb/>
require is to have it now. (Cheers.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE PREMIER REPLIES. <lb/></p> 

<p>Premier Haultain replied to Mr. <lb/>
McDonald. He said: Mr. Speaker, I <lb/>
am very glad to be able once <lb/>
in a while to join with my hon. friend <lb/>
opposite, and on this occasion do so in <lb/>
the matter of congratulating the hon. <lb/>
gentleman who moved and seconded <lb/>
the Address in reply to the Speech. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> — I only congratulated <lb/>
the seconder. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> — I, then, on behalf of <lb/>
myself and the members of this House <lb/>
congratulate the hon. member who <lb/>
moved the Address. It is not the first <lb/>
time we have had the pleasure of hear<lb break="no"/>ing him and he had already established <lb/>
his reputation and nothing he might <lb/>
say would add to it. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men opposite has made criticisms on the <lb/>
sins of omission and commission of <lb/>
this Government, and over the actions <lb/>
of the Dominion Government, the C. P. <lb/>
   R—and as such large lines, and also in <lb/>
regard to well boring in his own <lb/>
particular district. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man has to a certain extent anticipation <lb/>
what he has not called but insin<lb break="no"/>uated he might have called the gerry<lb break="no"/>mander bill. He can be perfectly cer<lb break="no"/>tain that the Government and the <lb/>
House may be safely left to deal with <lb/>
it fairly and justly as we are accus<lb break="no"/>tomed to deal with matters that come <lb/>
before this House. We do not pro<lb break="no"/>pose to deal with this question on pro<lb break="no"/>phetic lines at all. We do not propose <lb/>
to ask for representation for a popula<lb break="no"/>tion which may be here in the here<lb break="no"/>after. We propose to deal with it as a <lb/>
business question. Sufficient unto the <lb/>
population of to-day is the represen<lb break="no"/>tation thereof, and sufficient unto the <lb/>
population of to-morrow will be the <lb/>
representation of that day. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">COST OF TAX SALES.</p> 

<p>The hon. gentleman complained of <lb/>
the meagreness of the bill of fare out<lb break="no"/>lined in the Speech, which was the <lb/>
stereotyped criticism of leaders of <lb/>
oppositions. The Speech was fair as it <lb/>
deals with the business of the country. <lb/>
It was enough to call forth two good <lb/>
speeches from the mover andseconder <lb/>
and a long one from the leader of the <lb/>
Opposition. The hon. gentleman car<lb break="no"/>rying out the suggestion I made last <lb/>
year that he brings in the confidence of <lb/>
 the corporations is able to get informa<lb break="no"/>tion not otherwise obtainable, — <lb/></p> 

<cb/>

  <p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> — I did not say that <lb/>
information was confidential. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> — I said the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man being in the confidence of these <lb/>
corporations could get the information. <lb/>
He has referred to the excessive cost <lb/>
of tax sales under the Local Improve<lb break="no"/>ment Districts Ordinance. he men<lb break="no"/>tioned a case where the costs amounted <lb/>
to $14.00 and says this was caused <lb/>
to some taxpay who did not know of <lb/>
the arrears. One of the fundamental <lb/>
principles of our local improvement <lb/>
tax system is that gentelmen who own <lb/>
land are supposed to take sufficient <lb/>
interest in the country to know there <lb/>
are local improvement taxes; other<lb break="no"/>wise they are running a risk. The <lb/>
hon. gentleman had also referred to a <lb/>
case in Manitoba. If the taxpayers <lb/>
who are living in Manitoba can redeem <lb/>
their land more cheaply, so far as <lb/>
expenses are concerned they will more <lb/>
than make up for it in the amount of <lb/>
taxes they will have to pay. For my <lb/>
part I would rather have the burden <lb/>
on the occasional man who does not <lb/>
pay his taxes than on the people as a <lb/>
whole. <lb/></p> 

<p>Referring to the large immigration <lb/>
movement at present in progress, the <lb/>
premier said: I believe it is only the <lb/>
forerunner of one of the largest move<lb break="no"/>ments of population this continent has <lb/>
ever seen. <lb/></p> 

<p>The royal visit, said <persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName>, <lb/>
has brought us very much nearer home <lb/>
to the old country and the governing <lb/>
family of the Empire. I will not say <lb/>
it has caused greater loyalty on our <lb/>
part for it is not necessary to have <lb/>
royal visits to increase our loyalty. <lb/>
(Cheers.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">DEPARTMENT DESERVES CREDIT.</p> 

<p>The question of the crop and railway <lb/>
transportation is not one that is <lb/>
necessary for me to take up now. <lb/>
What the Grain Growers' Association <lb/>
is entitled to, or what portion it is <lb/>
entitled to, of the credit for relieving <lb/>
the blockade I do not know; it is a <lb/>
question of arithmetic for the hon. <lb/>
gentleman to settle himself. All I <lb/>
know is that the question was taken <lb/>
up by the Department backed by the <lb/>
Association. I do not care so much <lb/>
about the praise but believe in giving <lb/>
praise where it is due. If the relief <lb/>
brought about by the action of the <lb/>
Department was only temporary, as <lb/>
my hon. friend says, we do not take <lb/>
credit for the removal of the whole of <lb/>
the evil, nor do we propose to take <lb/>
blame for the evil. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE ALL IMPORTANT QUESTION.</p> 

<p>Now with regard to the negotations <lb/>
with the Federal Government over the <lb/>
question of provincial autonomy. We <lb/>
are not to blame if those negotiations <lb/>
are stretched out. Hon. gentlemen on <lb/>
the opposite side of the House think all <lb/>
they have to do is write a letter to Otta<lb break="no"/>wa to get your demands granted. They <lb/>
will realise if ever they attain their <lb/>
ambition to sit on this side of the House <lb/>
that it requires a great deal more. The <lb/>
Government here and the legislature <lb/>
has, I believe, been pressing as strong<lb break="no"/>ly as they possibly could. The delay in <lb/>
1900 was caused by an exceptionally <lb/>
late session at Ottawa followed almost <lb/>
immediately by the campaign for the <lb/>
election of that same year. Last year <lb/>
when we went to Ottawa in January <lb/>
1901 we made our representations ver<lb break="no"/>bally and followed them up with a <lb/>
written statement. Later on we asked <lb/>
to be allowed to go down and continue <lb/>
them but were told a special com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the Council would have to be <lb/>
appointed and could not be appointed <lb/>
until after the federal session. When <lb/>
the session was over we renewed our <lb/>
request and in reply were told that the <lb/>
minister of finance, who was a member <lb/>
of the special committee, had gone to <lb/>
England and would not be back till <lb/>
August. As soon as August came we <lb/>
again asked by telegraph for an ap<lb break="no"/>pointment. One was made for Octo<lb break="no"/>ber and kept. We had our interview <lb/>
with the special committee of the <lb/>
Council and at their request put in a <lb/>
more elaborate statement than at first. <lb/>
And although we have been in Ottawa <lb/>

<cb/>

since pressing for settlement we have <lb/>
up to the present received no answer. <lb/>
I believe this is largely due to the ill<lb break="no"/>ness of the Minister of the Interior, <lb/>
who has been absent from Ottawa <lb/>
almost since the session opened. I <lb/>
have an assurance from Sir Wilfrid <lb/>
Laurier that as soon as Mr. Sifton gets <lb/>
back an answer will be sent. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre"><persName ref="pers:SCOT2">HON. MR. SCOTT</persName> CORRECTED.</p> 

<p>The Government at Ottawa has, <lb/>
however, anticipated that answer <lb/>
somewhat by Hon. Mr. Scott's answer <lb/>
in the Senate. I can hardly credit the <lb/>
report published of that answer as it <lb/>
showed a little more ignorance on the <lb/>
part of that gentleman than he usually <lb/>
displays in North-West affairs. In his <lb/>
reply to Senator Perley he is reported to <lb/>
have said that the cause of delay arose <lb/>
on account of the difficulty to decide <lb/>
whether there should be one province <lb/>
or several and the location of the <lb/>
capital. Everybody knows, or ought <lb/>
to, that the location of the capital will <lb/>
not be dealt with at Ottawa but by <lb/>
the first provincial legislature after a <lb/>
province is created and cannot, there<lb break="no"/>fore, be one of the questions to be de<lb break="no"/>cided. <lb/></p> 

<p>We have negotiated in person, by <lb/>
letter and by telegraph. If the answer <lb/>
has not come it is not our fault. We <lb/>
cannot take the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment by the throat and carry out <lb/>
highway robbery methods. These <lb/>
might suggest themselves to members <lb/>
of the Opposition but are not the way <lb/>
the business of the Government is <lb/>
carried on. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE GOVERNMENT'S POSITION.</p> 

<p>The Government has no desire <lb/>
whatever to withhold the fullest state<lb break="no"/>ment of its position from the members <lb/>
of this House or the people of the <lb/>
country. So far as could be done <lb/>
without divulging the negotiations <lb/>
while they were pending this has been <lb/>
done. And while there has probably <lb/>
been no formal statement by myself or <lb/>
anyone else on behalf of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, everyone in this House and coun<lb break="no"/>try knows what the principal points are. <lb/>
It is not at all likely that the members <lb/>
of the Government in this House and <lb/>
on the platform should be speaking <lb/>
along certain lines, making certain <lb/>
points, advancing certain arguments, <lb/>
and then go down to Ottawa and give <lb/>
them up. The members of this <lb/>
House have a pretty clear idea of what <lb/>
the Government thinks should be done. <lb/>
The papers will be brought down at <lb/>
the first possible opportunity. We <lb/>
regret the delay. We have put it in <lb/>
the mouth of the lieutenant governor, <lb/>
the strongest possible way under our <lb/>
system of government, that we regret <lb/>
the delay. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">WHAT IS THE OPPOSITION POLICY?</p> 

<p>Now, Mr. Speaker, as the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man says we have trifled with this <lb/>
matter, that we have done nothing. I <lb/>
will ask what have the hon. gentlemen <lb/>
on the other side of the House been <lb/>
doing to develop public opinion on this <lb/>
question? What have they been doing <lb/>
towards educating the people on this <lb/>
question? The hon. gentleman has for <lb/>
the first time broken silence on this <lb/>
question and has had the hardihood to <lb/>
say that the people demand this pro<lb break="no"/>vincial autonomy at once. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> — I beg your pardon, it <lb/>
is not the first time. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> — On what other occa<lb break="no"/>sion did you express an opinion on the <lb/>
question? <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> — In my speech in this <lb/>
House two years ago. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> — In what way? <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> — I said it was time we <lb/>
had provincial autonomy. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> — I accept the hon. <lb/>
gentleman's statement but I have no <lb/>
recollection of it. I am glad, however, <lb/>
to know that at intervals of two years <lb/>
he has been able to express an opinion <lb/>
on this important question. What <lb/>
have he and his colleagues been doing <lb/>
to develop that public sentiment, to <lb/>
educate the people of this country on <lb/>
this important question? What did <lb/>
the hon. gentleman say when it was <lb/>
up? Was it that silence, I suppose <lb/>
indicating the unanimous approval of <lb/>
which they have spoken several times? <lb/>
On this side of the House we are not <lb/>
accustomed to draw from silence un<lb break="no"/>animous approval. When hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen opposite have nothin to find <lb/>
fault with and criticise, it is that later <lb/>
on they ay have something to criticise, <lb/>
and for one I am not disposed to <lb/>
accept the silence of the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men as a sign of unanimous approval. <lb/></p> 

<p>Other questions have been up of <lb/>
indefinitely less importance, except <lb/>
possibly of some personal interst to <lb/>
hon. gentlemen attached to them, and <lb/>
there heavy been memorials and resolu<lb break="no"/>tions by the hon. gentleman as leader <lb/>
of the Opposition on matters not half <lb/>
so important. He has devoted himself <lb/>
to questions of half breed scrip and to <lb/>
asking questions with regard to the <lb/>
education of deaf and dumb children, <lb/>
and then when the question of scrip is <lb/>
settled he discovers a new one for the <lb/>
volunteers, a very laudable thing in <lb/>
itself. But when a large question, the <lb/>
absorbing question the most import<lb break="no"/>ant question the House will every have <lb/>
to deal with has been up the hon. <lb/>
gentleman has sate mute and never had <lb/>
an opinion except once, he says, two <lb/>
years ago and once to-day. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">WHERE DOES THE OPPOSITION STAND?</p> 

<p>Not only the hon. gentleman, but <lb/>
where does his following stand on this <lb/>
important question? I suppose it <lb/>
would be somewhat indelicate for me <lb/>
to intrude into their little differences. <lb/>
I would ask where does the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen stand with his following? <lb/>
Where are other hon. gentelmen on <lb/>
this important question? What unan<lb break="no"/>imity do they show, what common <lb/>
opinion do they hold on this question? <lb/>
Take the hon. gentleman from Calgary <lb/>
West and see what he has to say <lb/>
about it. He said the time had <lb/>
come to consider all the phases of the <lb/>
question so that public opinion <lb/>
might be developed and educat<lb break="no"/>ed. What has he been doing? The <lb/>
nearest he got to it last session was to <lb/>
say that it is a very large question. <lb/>
And the hon. gentleman himself after <lb/>
two years has just come to realise that <lb/>
we really have a very important ques<lb break="no"/>tion to deal with. This helps about as <lb/>
much as the unanimous and silent con<lb break="no"/>sent he accords. <lb/></p> 

<p>Now, I am glad to see the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman has broken that silence and is <lb/>
able to express an opinion, because I <lb/>
think it is important that the members <lb/>
of the Opposition when they have <lb/>
grouped themselves under the leader<lb break="no"/>ship of the hon. gentleman should <lb/>
know exactly where he stands on this <lb/>
most important question. The mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Calgary West is holding meet<lb break="no"/>ings now and it seems to me it would <lb/>
be an appropriate time for him to ex<lb break="no"/>press and opinion. I find in the Olds <lb/>
Oracle, a paper very friendly to him <lb/>
and published in a part of the constit<lb break="no"/>uency where he is strongest, that in <lb/>
the course of an addresswhich is <lb/>
described as "a clear, concise and <lb/>
masterly statement of a man who has <lb/>
strong convictions" the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man for West Calgary devoted his <lb/>
entire speech to petty questions of <lb/>
expropriation for taxes, steam boiler <lb/>
inspection, hail insurance and school <lb/>
taxes, while at the same time his <lb/>
leader is regretting that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment has done nothing to secure pro<lb break="no"/>vincial autonomy and practically <lb/>
charging us with retarding the move<lb break="no"/>ment. <lb/></p> 

<p>Another hon. gentleman, the mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Prince Albert West, what is his <lb/>
opinion? He goes in for a northern <lb/>
province, that wonderful and fearful <lb/>
division of two strips making a north<lb break="no"/>

<cb/>

ern and southern province that each <lb/>
might have a line of railway. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">A DIRECT QUESTION.</p> 

<p>And what does the hon. leader of <lb/>
the Opposition favor, asked Mr. Haul<lb break="no"/>tain, and he waited for a reply. <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:MCDO10">Mr. McDonald</persName> — I did not express <lb/>
myself as to one or two provinces. <lb/>
(Laughter). What are you in favor <lb/>
of? <lb/></p> 

  <p><persName ref="pers:HAUL2">Mr. Haultain</persName> — I am in favor of one <lb/>
province. (Hear, hear) I have said so on <lb/>
the platform and we stated so in our <lb/>
memorial to Ottawa. The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man is afraid to express his opinion <lb/>
and so I think we must attribute his <lb/>
silence, not as the silence of the <lb/>
Sphinx, but because he has taken the <lb/>
attitude of waiting to see what one his <lb/>
followers take and that popular opin<lb break="no"/>ion will take. <lb/></p> 

<p>The member for Prince Albert East <lb/>
says he has had to go to Ottawa to <lb/>
present our plan being adopted there. <lb/>
His attitude is a little more definite, is <lb/>
more clearly defined and clear cut <lb/>
than this leader. <lb/></p> 

<p>I have pointed out these differences <lb/>
to allow the hon. gentlemen and the <lb/>
country to see what a united and <lb/>
happy family they are on the one, the <lb/>
most important question which the <lb/>
House has to deal with to-day. The <lb/>
hon gentleman from South Regina <lb/>
belives in creating one province im<lb break="no"/>mediately. On that question he goes <lb/>
a little further than his leader. I am <lb/>
not aware of the opinions of the hon. <lb/>
gentlemen from Victoria and St. Al<lb break="no"/>bert may be, but I am perfectly cer<lb break="no"/>tain they may be or may not be in <lb/>
accord with the opinion which is going <lb/>
to be pronounced sometime in the <lb/>
hereafter by the hon. gentleman for <lb/>
North Qu'Appelle. It is no wonder <lb/>
that they sit down and wait for public <lb/>
opinion and for things to happen. <lb/>
They have several sets of opinion and <lb/>
everyone who goes off is practically a <lb/>
party, so that besides a small and de<lb break="no"/>creasing party we have a multiplicity <lb/>
of leaders. It is not at all wonderful <lb/>
that they find themselves in difficulty. <lb/>
They are trying to do the impossible. <lb/>
Their leader is trying to decide which <lb/>
horse he will ride of two or three and <lb/>
he will probably be put in the position <lb/>
of trying to ride two or three at the <lb/>
same time. In the meantime what do <lb/>
we find them doing? They have no <lb/>
opinion, they simply sit down and wait <lb/>
until popular opinion shall have dis<lb break="no"/>closed itself and then, I suppose, they <lb/>
will be ready to jump. I am perfectly <lb/>
sure of this, that when the member for <lb/>
West Calgary does come out and state <lb/>
his opinion it will be one his leader <lb/>
cannot accept. He would be perfectly <lb/>
willing that a portion be handed over <lb/>
to Manitoba that a western province <lb/>
could be formed. <lb/></p> 

<p>The hon. gentlemen refers to the <lb/>
fact that there is a growing opposition <lb/>
to the Government of the Qu'<lb break="no"/>Appelle valley. I certainly congratu<lb break="no"/>late the hon. gentleman on his new <lb/>
ally. I congratulate him that he <lb/>
stands on the same platform, or so <lb/>
nearly, that he can claim the support <lb/>
of the most active annexationist in the <lb/>
whole of Eastern Assiniboia. I must <lb/>
console myself with this fact, that if <lb/>
there is a growing opposition headed <lb/>
by Mr. Motehrwell north of the <lb/>
Qu-Appelle valley, the Opposition in <lb/>
this House is rapidly decreasing. <lb/>
(Laughter.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">THE GOVERNMENTS POLICY.</p> 

<p>On the one hand we have a clear cut <lb/>
opinion on the part of the Government: <lb/>
on the other side we have a number of <lb/>
opinions differing in every detail, <lb/>
differing in every important question. As a <lb/>
consequence its leaders are placed in <lb/>
the position of not being able to say or <lb/>
do anything but simply maintain the <lb/>
hopeless and helpless attitude of do-<lb break="yes"/>nothings. They say nothing, do nothing, <lb/>
and so far as we can gather they know <lb/>
nothing. We have a clear and defi<lb break="no"/>nite policy and we are united on it. <lb/>
We believe in once province with all <lb/>
rights of other provinces: we believe <lb/>
in the full control of the lands, the <lb/>
mines, the minerals and all the royalties <lb/>
of this country: we believe in adequate <lb/>
compensation for all the public lands <lb/>
that have been used for Federal pur<lb break="no"/>poses: we believe in getting a fair <lb/>
adjustment of any outstanding debt <lb/>
there may be against the Territories; <lb/>
we believe in the subsidy being given, <lb/>
not on a population of 400,000 people, <lb/>
but that it should be as large as that <lb/>
received by any other province; in fact, <lb/>
we believe in being treated the same <lb/>
as the other provinces, and that is the <lb/>
proposition we made to the Federal <lb/>
Government, with the provision that we <lb/>
be made into one province and not <lb/>
into a number of small ones. I believe <lb/>
that in this we are backed up by a <lb/>
loyal following in this House and <lb/>
knowing the justness of our claim we <lb/>
rest assured of the outcome. (Cheers.) <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">WANTS TWO PROVINCES.</p> 

<p>Dr. Patrick (Yorkton) followed the <lb/>
premier and made a vigorous attack <lb/>

<cb/>

on the one province idea. He propos<lb break="no"/>ed to take advantage of the latitude <lb/>
which the debate offered to say many <lb/>
things which he regretted to have to <lb/>
say. Referring to the speech made by <lb/>
the Duke of York in London after the <lb/>
royal tour in which His Royal High<lb break="no"/>ness spoke of the liberal laws of the <lb/>
colonies. Dr. Patrick said he surely <lb/>
had no reference to some legislation <lb/>
passed by this House last session <lb/>
which proposed to expropriate the <lb/>
property of free men and give them <lb/>
what compensation a commissioner <lb/>
might see fit. <lb/></p>

<p>Dr. Patrick then devoted himself to <lb/>
the provincial autonomy question. <lb/>
He said: I think I may safely claim not <lb/>
to be open to the indictment made <lb/>
against others. It is nearly 12 years <lb/>
since I first had something to do with <lb/>
local politics. I was so taken with <lb/>
the attitude of the premier that I fol<lb break="no"/>lowed him and have done so faithfully <lb/>
to this day. I was a strong believer in <lb/>
the one province idea and held these <lb/>
views up to 1897 because I believed <lb/>
that the assumption was correct that <lb/>
larger arrears were more cheaply <lb/>
governed. I followed with a good <lb/>
deal of interest the debate on the <lb/>
autonomy motion of the number for <lb/>
Banff, but in 1897 the position was <lb/>
taken by Manitoba that it should in<lb break="no"/>clude a part. I believe that position <lb/>
was taken by Manitoba as the direct <lb/>
result of the debate here in 1806 when <lb/>
the unanimous resolution was passed <lb/>
in favor of one province. This led me <lb/>
to see that the position of Manitoba <lb/>
was such that they had a fair right to <lb/>
have some say in this matter. <lb/>
I felt then that the matter must <lb/>
be dealt with from a Dominion <lb/>
rather than a local point of view. <lb/>
In the session of 1809 I express<lb break="no"/>ed the opinion that we should have two <lb/>
territories united under one local <lb/>
government. I made the suggestion <lb/>
in the hope that the leader of the <lb/>
Government would see his way clear <lb/>
to recede from a position I held to be <lb/>
dangerous to the people of this country <lb/>
and their local interests. I sought re<lb break="no"/>election not as such a declared follower <lb/>
of the hon. gentleman. I have con<lb break="no"/>tinued to hope that he would not bind <lb/>
himself to the once province idea but <lb/>
 <lb/>
make an alternative proposition, but I <lb/>
gather that he has nailed his banner <lb/>
to the one province. (Hear, hear.( <lb/>
And I as firmly nail my banner to two, <lb/>
I think the one province idea highly <lb/>
prejudical to the interests of the people <lb/>
of this country, and I would rather <lb/>
stay at home and advocate two pro<lb break="no"/>vinces than come here to advocate <lb/>
one. I can understand and appreciate <lb/>
the position of Manitoba but I am op<lb break="no"/>posed to the annexation of any portion <lb/>
of the Territories to that province, ex<lb break="no"/>cept the portion lying to the north of <lb/>
that province: that I think they are <lb/>
entitled to. If the Territories are <lb/>
organised into one large province it <lb/>
will certainly dwarf Manitoba in the <lb/>
estimation of the people of Canda <lb/>
and on the map of Canada, and I say <lb/>
here today the settlement will be <lb/>
either two provinces or annexation <lb/>
and that two provinces is the proper <lb/>
solution. <lb/></p> 

<p rendition="simple:centre">COST OF GOVERNMENT.</p> 

<p>It is said that the two provinces <lb/>
would be more expensive than one. <lb/>
It is not an axiom; it is not a self-evi<lb break="no"/>dent truth. The hon. gentleman <lb/>
should go further than he does and tell <lb/>
the people that we have large and <lb/>
small provinces and show that they <lb/>
large provinces and show that the <lb/>
large provinces are the cheaper. I say <lb/>
that the records show that it will be <lb/>
cheaper and more economical to have <lb/>
two provinces than one. I do <lb/>
not intend to prove it at this time. <lb/>
The reverse is the assumption on which <lb/>
the hon. gentleman's case for one pro<lb break="no"/>vince rests. He should take the records <lb/>
of the small provinces and by a com<lb break="no"/>parison with the large provinces show <lb/>
that he is correct. It is the only posi<lb break="no"/>tion on which he can stand. No man <lb/>
can stand on the position that we <lb/>
should wish one province to be so pre<lb break="no"/>dominant as to cause strife. The hon. <lb/>
gentlemn should by a comparison <lb/>
between large provinces and stuall <lb/>
provinces, by a comparison between <lb/>
large States and small States, by a <lb/>
comparison between the 5,000,000 of <lb/>
Canada and the 75,000,000 of the United <lb/>
States, by a comparison between New <lb/>
Brunswick with its 330,000 of a popula<lb break="no"/>tion and Ontario with its 2,000,000 show <lb/>
that in any case or a majority of cases <lb/>
the larger are cheaper than the smaller. <lb/>
For the purpose of putting him to this <lb/>
proof I deny it. Let him take the <lb/>
people into his confidence and prove <lb/>
that his contention is a correct one. <lb/></p> 

<p>The motion adopting the Address in <lb/>
reply to the Speech was then put and <lb/>
carried, Dr. Patrick alone protesting. <lb/>
The House then adjourned. <lb/></p> 


  <!-- IC, 2018-10-30, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day --> 
<!--<p>TUESDAY, March 25. <lb/></p> 

<p>The Spaker took the chair at 2:30 <lb/>
p.m. The order paper contained noth<lb break="no"/>ing but the usual routine procedure. <lb/>
Hon. Mr. Bulyea presented a petition <lb/>
from Indian Head praying to be incor<lb break="no"/>porated as a town. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. R. S. Lake (Grenfell) drew the <lb/>
attention of the member for Prince <lb/>
Albert East (Mr. McLeod) to a news<lb break="no"/>paper report of a speech by him in <lb/>
which he was reported as saying that <lb/>
the members of the Opposition were <lb/>
working together to keep the autonomy <lb/>
question from being settled for some <lb/>
years. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. McLeod denied the correctness <lb/>
of the report but said he had made <lb/>
certain statements which he was will<lb break="no"/>ing to back up. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. G. W. Brown gave notice of a <lb/>
bill respecting chemists and druggists. <lb/></p> 

<p>Mr. Haultain mvoed that when the <lb/>
House adjourn it stand adjourned <lb/>
until April 3rd. The House had met <lb/>
early this year in deference to the ex<lb break="no"/>pressed wish of members, and they <lb/>
had no reason to suppose that they <lb/>
would not ahve been in possession of <lb/>
all material relating to the provincial <lb/>
question in the form of a reply from <lb/>
the Dominion Government. Had they <lb/>
known as much six weeks ago as they <lb/>
now knew, it would have been wise to <lb/>
postpone the calling of the House until <lb/>
after Easter. As far as the work of <lb/>
the Government was concerned, they <lb/>
had very little to occupy the attention <lb/>
of the House this year. There would <lb/>
be one or two unimportant amending <lb/>
bills, certain resolutions, which would <lb/>
arise from correspondence with the <lb/>
Federal Government and the redistri<lb break="no"/>bution bill. After the adjournment <lb/>
they would have the estimates, redis<lb break="no"/>tribution bill and any other legislation <lb/>
ready and ought to have the answer of <lb/>
the Dominion Government. The busi<lb break="no"/>ness of the Government would not <lb/>
occupy the House much more than a <lb/>
week or ten days. <lb/></p> 

<p>Dr. Patrick opposed the adjourn<lb break="no"/>ment on behalf of the members who <lb/>
had come long distances and could not <lb/>
return to their homes for Easter. He <lb/>
would consent to it if he thought there <lb/>
was any hope during the Easter time <lb/>
of Mr. Haultain considering his sins, <lb/>
and seeking to be shriven for them, <lb/>
and being converted from his one pro<lb break="no"/>vince heresy. <lb/></p> 

<p>The House then adjourned till Thurs<lb break="no"/>day, April 3rd. <lb/></p>

<milestone type="unknown"/> <lb/>-->
</div>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>