<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_PEI_1870-02-17"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-02-17">17 February 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Prince Edward Island</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="32"/>.
        

          <idno type="legislature"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18700217_Page_032.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-09-28">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>

<change who="taekema_sarah" when="2016-10-15">Marked-up people. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18700217_Page_032">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700217_Page_032.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="32" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700217_Page_032.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">32</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 17, 1870</fw>
            
            
            <p>
              <add><persName ref="pers:GALT1">Hon. Mr. Galt</persName></add>-  <!--Brunswick.--> He could not congratulate the 
               <lb/>
               House upon progress of Confederation. It was 
               <lb/>
               time it was carried, but from expressions he 
               <lb/>
               had heard from members of this House he was 
               <lb/>
               forced to conclude that the Province was not 
               <lb/>
               satisfied. The policy of the Government with 
               <lb/>
               reference to the Intercolonial Railway had 
               <lb/>
               already been fully discussed and he did not 
               <lb/>
               intend to say anything further than that he 
               <lb/>
               should have been glad to have seen the policy 
               <lb/>
               with reference to the construction of that road 
               <lb/>
               materially altered. He thought a policy of 
               <lb/>
               economy should have been pursued. The policy 
               <lb/>
               which had been adopted in the construction of 
               <lb/>
               the Intercolonial Railway has given us the 
               <lb/>
               management of several hundred miles of rail<lb break="no"/>way—an arrangement that could not be carried 
               <lb/>
               on as well under Government control as by 
               <lb/>
               private parties, and it involved responsibilities 
               <lb/>
               which it would have been better not to assume. 
               <lb/>
               He was convinced that the expenditure upon 
               <lb/>
               this railway would itself form a serious burden 
               <lb/>
               upon the resources of the country. He regretted 
               <lb/>
               to observe that the policy which had been pur<lb break="no"/>sued with reference to Newfoundland and 
               <lb/>
               Prince Edward Island had borne results worse 
               <lb/>
               than barren. They had received a more decided 
               <lb/>
               negative from Newfoundland as regards Con<lb break="no"/>federation. And this House stood in the awk<lb break="no"/>ward position of having legislated with regard 
               <lb/>
               to terms to be offered to Prince Edward Island, 
               <lb/>
               which terms had been rejected entirely. With 
               <lb/>
               regard to the North-West question he was 
               <lb/>
               sorry to arrive at the same conclusion. An 
               <lb/>
               avowed resistance had been given to attempts 
               <lb/>
               to incorporate that Territory into the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion. Who was responsible for that state of 
               <lb/>
               things he would not pretend to say until all the 
               <lb/>
               correspondence and other papers connected 
               <lb/>
               with the matter had been laid before the 
               <lb/>
               House. When he looked from one end to the 
               <lb/>
               other of the Dominion he must pronounce the 
               <lb/>
               administration of the hon. member for Kings<lb break="no"/>ton a failure as regards the important measure 
               <lb/>
               entrusted to him, (hear, hear). He would fur<lb break="no"/>ther say that if there had been one thing that 
               <lb/>
               had saved Confederation from public disap<lb break="no"/>proval, it was not what had been done by the 
               <lb/>
               Dominion Government but the efficient man<lb break="no"/>agement which had characterized the Local 
               <lb/>
               Governments of Quebec and Ontario—emi<lb break="no"/>nently the populous and wealthy Province of 
               <lb/>
               Ontario, and these Provinces could be appealed 
               <lb/>
               to as a proof of the satisfactory manner in 
               <lb/>
               which local powers had been administered. The 
               <lb/>
               Speech of the Governor General was a serious 
               <lb/>
               disappointment to him. There was but one 
               <lb/>
               source of congratulation in that Speech—it was 
               <lb/>
               thankfulness for the bountiful harvests; there 
               <lb/>
               was no hope held out that there would be a 
               <lb/>
               reconciliation of difficulties with that Prov<lb break="no"/>ince, and there is nothing to make us hope that 
               <lb/>
               
               
            </p>
            
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
