<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_PEI_1873-05-17"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1873-05-17">17 May 1873</date>, Canadian Confederation with Prince Edward Island</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>David Farr</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, Second Parliament, First Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2013"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="603" to="604"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18730517_Page_603.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18730517_Page_604.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-09-29">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
         
         <change who="taekema_sarah" when= "2016-11-28">Marked-up people</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18730517_Page_603">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18730517_Page_603.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18730517_Page_604">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18730517_Page_604.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="603" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18730517_Page_603.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline"> May 17, 1873 <lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
            <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS</fw>
            <fw type="dateline"> Saturday, May 17,
               1873 <lb/>
               
            </fw>
<!-- "ST, again, unsure who Speaker is" -->            
            <p> The SPEAKER took the
               chair at 3 pm. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Prayers</hi> <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
      <div type="section">  
            
            <head> PRINTING <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:BLAN1">Hon. Mr. BLANCHET</persName>
               moved the adoption of the report of the <lb/>
               Joint Committee on Printing.-Carried.
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
<p> *** <lb/></p></div> 

<div type="section">
            <head>PRIVATE BILLS</head>
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCDO3">Hon. Mr. MCDONALD</persName>
               (Antigonish) moved the adoption of the <lb/>
               report of the Committee on Private Bills, recommending an <lb/>
               alteration ofthe rules.-Carried.
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> *** <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">         
         
            
            <head> INCREASE OF SALARIES
               - LIBRARY <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
            <p>After routine, <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The Library
               Committee’s report, recommending an increase of <lb/>
               salaries was adopted. <lb/>
               
            </p>
  <p> *** <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">         
         
            
            <head> PACIFIC RAILWAY
               INVESTIGATION COMMITTEE <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. HOLTON</persName>
               desired to call the attention of the House to <lb/>
               a matter of some importance. The House had ordered a Committee <lb/>
               of investigation into certain matters connected with the
               Paciﬁc <lb/>
               Railway. That Committee had adjourned until the 2nd July. It was <lb/>
               empowered to summon witnesses, and to adjourn, not only from <lb/>
               time to time, but from place to place. Under the ordinary procedure <lb/>
               of the House, committees had no authority to incur any expenditure <lb/>
               whatever connected with the summoning of witnesses until those <lb/>
               witnesses had appeared. The Committee would undoubtedly require <lb/>
               to incur expenses of various kinds and of a contingent nature. It was <lb/>
               quite possible that witnesses might decline to travel considerable <lb/>
               distance until their travelling expenses were furnished. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> It appeared to him,
               therefore, that it was essentially necessary in <lb/>
               some way to place the Chairman in a position to defray the <lb/>
               necessary expense of prosecuting the inquiry, whether it was by the <lb/>
               vote of the House or by action of Government. It was quite clear <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <cb/>
         <fw type="num">603 <lb/></fw>
            
            <p> something ought to be
               done in order to carry out the express will of <lb/>
               the House in the matter. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir JOHN A.
               MACDONALD</persName> said he quite agreed with <lb/>
               the hon. gentleman, and he suggested that the necessary sums <lb/>
               should be advanced by Mr. Speaker from the Contingencies, on the <lb/>
               demand of the chairman of the Committee. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The suggestion was
               agreed to. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> *** <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">     
         
            
            <head> ADMISSION OF PRINCE
               EDWARD ISLAND <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>
               moved, “That
               the House will on Monday <lb/>
               next resolve itself into a Committee of the Whole to consider <lb/>
               certain resolutions with reference to the proposed admission of <lb/>
               Prince Edward Island into the Dominion of Canada, and the <lb/>
               message of His Excellency the Governor General on that
               subject.” <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> He said it was pretty
               well known what was the nature of the <lb/>
               proposition made to the Island Government in 1869 under the <lb/>
               authority of this House by resolutions authorizing the Government <lb/>
               to enter into negotiations and in those negotiations to provide for <lb/>
               the purchase of lands owned by absentee proprietors. The <lb/>
               Government then undertook on behalf of the Parliament of Canada <lb/>
               to give the Island a sum of $800,000 in lieu of crown lands, to <lb/>
               enable the Government of the Island to purchase the lands owned <lb/>
               by absentee proprietors. Hon. members generally were aware that <lb/>
               the proposition of 1869 varied very little from that made to the <lb/>
               other Provinces except in this particular, and also in the fact that
               the <lb/>
               Government undertook to maintain steam communication between <lb/>
               the Island and the Dominion. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> He would state the
               changes which had been made in subsequent <lb/>
               negotiations. In the proposition of 1869 the Island was to come in <lb/>
               with a debt of $27.77 per head according to populations, and, of <lb/>
               course, was to receive eighty cents per head, to be increased every <lb/>
               ten years aﬁer the taking of the census. One of the changes <lb/>
               consisted in increasing the debt to $50 per head. That was arrived at <lb/>
               in this manner. The expenditure on the Intercolonial Railway had <lb/>
               not been made in 1869, neither had the money been voted for the <lb/>
               Paciﬁc Railway, neither had the canal policy, involving a
               large <lb/>
               expenditure of money, been settled by the Parliament of Canada; <lb/>
               neither had the Island constructed any public works of consequence. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName>:
               The canal policy had been settled. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said
               the extent of it had not been settled. The <lb/>
               Commission had been appointed since then, and it was upon that <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <pb n="604" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18730517_Page_604.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">604</fw>
            
            <p> report that the
               nature and extent of the canal works were decided <lb/>
               upon. Since that date, the Island Government had entered into <lb/>
               contracts for the construction of railways nearly 200 miles in length <lb/>
               at a cost of $3,250,000, including the purchase of lands and other <lb/>
               matters. These public works would become the property of the <lb/>
               Dominion. Some of the railway was under construction, and a <lb/>
               portion about ninety miles long would be completed by <lb/>
               midsummer. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> From the fact that
               the Dominion Government and Parliament had <lb/>
               undertaken the construction of the lntercolonial Railway at a cost of <lb/>
               $20,000,000, that the Paciﬁc Railway was to be built with a <lb/>
               contribution on the part of the Dominion of $30,000,000, that <lb/>
               $20,000,000 or $25,000,000 was to be expended on canals, that it <lb/>
               was contemplated to readjust the debts of the Dominion by <lb/>
               assuming the Surplus of Ontario and Quebec and giving sums in <lb/>
               proportion to the other Provinces, and that the Island would not <lb/>
               have public works constructed aﬁer it came into the Dominion
               at all <lb/>
               in proportion to the other Provinces, it was agreed to extend the <lb/>
               Island debt to be assumed to $50 a head. At the negotiations in <lb/>
               January last the sum was ﬁxed at $45 a head. That had been <lb/>
               submitted to the people of the Island and the result was that the <lb/>
               newly elected Legislature had rejected the terms and authorised <lb/>
               another deputation to come to Ottawa, with power to enter into <lb/>
               negotiations with the Government for the extension of the amount <lb/>
               to $50. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. HOLTON</persName>: Does
               that increase extinguish the <lb/>
               $800,000 to be paid for the purchase ofthe land? <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said
               no, that still remained. The only other <lb/>
               change from the proposition of 1869 was that, as the Island had <lb/>
               constructed a building used as a post ofﬁce and court house,
               which <lb/>
               would be used partly for Dominion purposes, the Government <lb/>
               should take that building on paying the Island $69,000. The Island <lb/>
               had also entered into a contract for the construction of a dredge at a <lb/>
               cost of$22,000 and the Dominion took that off their hands, and also <lb/>
               undertook to assume a liability of $2,000 a year, payable to a <lb/>
               Company to keep up the telegraphic communication by cable <lb/>
               between the Island and the Dominion. These were the changes <lb/>
               made in the propositions of 1869, and those in the terms agreed on <lb/>
               in January were only to increase the debt from $45 to $50 per head, <lb/>
               and to undertake to pay the $2,000 a year for the telegraphic <lb/>
               communication. The papers would be printed this afternoon, and <lb/>
               would be in the hands of hon. gentlemen a sufﬁcient time to
               enable <lb/>
               them to consider them. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLlN</persName> asked
               if the provision for steam <lb/>
               communication was in the original arrangement. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>: Yes <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CART3">Mr. CARTWRIGHT</persName> asked
               if the Crown Lands would become <lb/>
               the property of the Dominion. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
     <cb/>
            
            <fw type="dateline"> May 17, 1873 <lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said
               they would be the property of the <lb/>
               Island. The Province was in a different position to that of any other <lb/>
               Province in the Dominion. What passed to the other Provinces as <lb/>
               Crown Lands had, in the case of Prince Edward Island, been sold to <lb/>
               parties in England by the Imperial Government, so that they had no <lb/>
               Crown Lands, and derived no revenue from such a source for local <lb/>
               purposes as every other Province did. These lands being held by <lb/>
               absentee proprietors, the only persons living on them were tenants, <lb/>
               and this was a very unsatisfactory state of things, and had prevented <lb/>
               the Island from taking the position it would otherwise have taken. It <lb/>
               was in consequence of this that the Legislature, in 1869, authorised <lb/>
               the Government to make arrangements for the admission of the <lb/>
               Island including the purchase of the Crown Lands. The Island had <lb/>
               since then purchased some small portion, but a very large portion <lb/>
               remained in the hands of absentee proprietors. The quantity yet to <lb/>
               be purchased was between 400,000 and 500,000 acres. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName>:
               It was about 800,000 in 1869. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY </persName>said
               no, the Island altogether with the small <lb/>
               Islands adjacent to it had only about a million and a quarter, and <lb/>
               there were yet about 400,000 or 500,000 acres which had not been <lb/>
               purchased. The construction of the railway required the payment of <lb/>
               a larger sum now than in 1869, but the lands would be also more <lb/>
               valuable. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName>
               asked if the papers contained any <lb/>
               statement of the present revenue and expenditure of the Island. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>
               thought not. The Government had it before <lb/>
               them, but it did not enter into the correspondence. They could, <lb/>
               however, send it to be printed. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE</persName>
               said it was evident that all these <lb/>
               ﬁnancial statements should go with the other papers. Of
               course they <lb/>
               were all very glad at the prospect of the Island joining the <lb/>
               Confederation-(<hi rendition="simple:italic">hear, hear</hi>)-and no
               member of the House, <lb/>
               especially amongst those who were the originators of the <lb/>
               Confederation project, would be disposed to treat the matter <lb/>
               otherwise than in an amicable way. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear</hi>.) Still it was <lb/>
               necessary to have the fullest information. The Islanders had very <lb/>
               properly manifested a careful survey of their own particular <lb/>
               position and interest and while the smaller party might be supposed <lb/>
               to have very strong views on that subject more than the stronger <lb/>
               party, still it was necessary to have such data as would enable the <lb/>
               House to discuss the matter intelligibly. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said
               he would have the statement printed at <lb/>
               once. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The motion was then
               carried. <lb/></p>

<p>
               * * * <lb/></p>
</div>

<div type="section">
              <head> THE CHICOUTIMI AND CHARLEVOIX ELECTIONS <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> On the orders of the
               day having been called, <lb/>
               
            </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
