<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_PEI_1870-02-23"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-02-23">23 February 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Prince Edward Island</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="167" to="168"/>.
        

          <idno type="legislature"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18700223_Page_167.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18700223_Page_168.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-09-28">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18700223_Page_167">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700223_Page_167.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18700223_Page_168">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700223_Page_168.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="167" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700223_Page_167.jpg"/>
        <!--    <fw type="dateline"> 23 février
               1870 <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p> place in the House,
               or amongst gentlemen, and <lb/>
               should be expelled if possible. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The matter was then
               dropped. <lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
              <head> INTERCOLONIAL RAILWAY LOAN <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> moved an address for copies of the
                  <lb/> correspondence between the Imperial and <lb/> Canadian Governments. He said
                  that a rumour <lb/> had been current last session in that House <lb/> that a
                  portion of the loan raised for the purpose <lb/> of the construction of the
                  Intercolonial Rail<lb break="no"/>way had been expended to meet some of the <lb/>
                  general expenditure of the country. That <lb/> rumour had been commented on by
                  various <lb/> members of the House as presenting a serious <lb/> breach of the
                  obligations which their Govern<lb break="no"/>ment owed to the Imperial
                  Government, con<lb break="no"/>sidering the terms on which their loan had <lb/>
                  been made. A motion was made by him (Mr. <lb/> Blake) for an address on the
                  subject, but the <lb/> address was presented at the end of the ses<lb break="no"
                  />sion, and it being so late the correspondence <lb/> was not brought down. He
                  begged to call the <lb/> attention of the gentlemen opposite to that <lb/> fact.
                  He would say, however, in advance of the <lb/> papers that he had asked for, that
                  the course <lb/> which was taken by the Government in the <lb/> matter was not
                  such as ought to have been <lb/> taken. The Act provided that the Imperial Gov<lb
                     break="no"/>ernment might guarantee the interest on a loan <lb/> of £3,000,000
                  to the Government of Canada for <lb/> the purpose of constructing the road and
                     fur<lb break="no"/>ther provided that the guarantees should not <lb/> be given
                  until provisions had been made on the <lb/> part of Canada for appropriation and
                     expendi<lb break="no"/>ture on the construction of the Railway Loan, <lb/> so
                  that the money thus raised by Act of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment was secured to the
                  appropriation and <lb/> expenditure on the construction of the line. In <lb/>
                  accordance with that Act, the Government <lb/> passed an Act which was accepted by
                  the Com<lb break="no"/>missioners as a satisfactory fulfillment of the <lb/>
                  obligations which were obliged to be fulfilled <lb/> by the Government before the
                  money could be <lb/> raised. A part of it was left in the Treasury, the <lb/>
                  money being raised before they were ready to <lb/> expend it for financial
                  consideration, which it <lb/> was not now necessary to explain, and, under <lb/>
                  these circumstances, he thought that it was the <lb/> duty of the Government that
                  that balance <lb/> should have been kept intact, so that it should <lb/> be ready
                  for expenditure on the completion of <lb/> the road, and that its duty to the
                  Imperial <lb/> Government, by reason of their common inter<lb break="no"/>est with
                  them, and of the conditions under <lb/> which it had guaranteed the interest of
                  the <lb/>
                  <pb n="168" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700223_Page_168.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">168</fw><fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> loan, gave it a
                  just right to complain if the <lb/> money had been expended in any other way,
                  <lb/> even if the finances of the country should <lb/> enable the Government to
                  “recoup," which was <lb/> the felicitous phrase by which it had been <lb/>
                  described, the money so expended. He believed <lb/> that a rebuke had been
                  received from the <lb/> Imperial Government on that point, and that <lb/> rebuke
                  was followed by remonstrance, and an <lb/> intimation that a change might take
                  place in <lb/> the policy of Her Majesty’s Government What <lb/> was the fate of
                  that remonstrance he did not <lb/> know, nor care how this Government thought
                  <lb/> they could bring sufficient power to bear upon <lb/> the Imperial Government
                  to induce them not <lb/> to change their policy; but when the papers <lb/> came
                  down the House would have more infor<lb break="no"/>mation on the point. He
                  thought that the trans<lb break="no"/>action was not one which was creditable to
                  the <lb/> Government which had made this country <lb/> responsible for it. <lb/>
               </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said there <lb/> could be no
                  objection to bringing down the <lb/> papers; but the Government declined to enter
                  <lb/> into a discussion on the matter before they <lb/> were so brought down. A
                  discussion had been <lb/> entered into last session before there were any <lb/>
                  papers on the table, and had been replied to by <lb/> Sir John Rose. He believed
                  that Sir John Rose’s <lb/> answer was satisfactory, and that the honour <lb/> and
                  credit of that House had been fully sus<lb break="no"/>tained by the hon.
                  gentleman. He believed that <lb/> the House would be of opinion when the papers
                  <lb/> were brought down that the honour of the <lb/> House and the pecuniary
                  interests of the coun<lb break="no"/>try had been guarded. It would be found that
                  <lb/> there had been no breach of faith on the part of <lb/> the Government. The
                  papers would be brought <lb/> down without delay, and the House and the <lb/>
                  country would have every opportunity for dis<lb break="no"/>cussing the question.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            
</div>

<div type="section">    
            
            <head> CORRESPONDENCE <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> moved an address for copies of <lb/> correspondence
                  and Orders in Council, respect<lb break="no"/>ing the admission of Prince Edward’s
                  Island or <lb/> British Columbia into the Union, etc—Motion <lb/> carried. <lb/>
               </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> moved for copies of correspond<lb break="no"/>ence
                  touching legislation in any of the Prov<lb break="no"/>inces and disallowance of
                  acts, etc. He said he <lb/> understood that general instructions upon the <lb/>
                  subject of Provincial Legislation had been <lb/> issued by His Excellency—Motion
                  carried. <lb/>
               </p>
            
</div>       
 
<div type="section">           
            <head> PAYMENT TO SIR A.
               MACNAB <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:RYMA1">Mr. Rymal</persName> moved for a select committee to <lb/> enquire into the
                  payment of $20,000 to the late <lb/> Sir Allan MacNab. He spoke at some length,
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
