<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_PEI_1870-03-18" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-03-18">18 March 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Prince Edward Island</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1870">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="513" to="514"/>.
        

          <idno type="legislature"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18700318_Page_513.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18700318_Page_514.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-09-28">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18700318_Page_513">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700318_Page_513.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18700318_Page_514">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700318_Page_514.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="513" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700318_Page_513.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline"> 18 mars 1870 <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p>[...] cious and unfriendly
               to say beforehand, what <lb/>
               the electoral franchise shall be in the Prov<lb break="no"/>inces, not yet in the Union; to tell them, in fact, <lb/>
               that their influence here shall not be felt. He <lb/>
               called the attention of the House to the irrele<lb break="no"/>vancy of the franchise proposed. He thought <lb/>
               that the Minister of Justice could, with pro<lb break="no"/>priety, adopt the franchise of the local Houses. <lb/>
               His opinion was that the time was not far off, <lb/>
               when every man in the country would have a <lb/>
               vote, when the political sentiment of the coun<lb break="no"/>try would not be demoralised by the registra<lb break="no"/>tion system. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:WOOD1">Hon. Mr. Wood</persName>—The hon. gentleman says <lb/> that it is desirable
               that the elections should not <lb/> be simultaneous and on one day, because it <lb/>
               would deprive persons having votes in differ<lb break="no"/>ent constituencies from
               exercising the fran<lb break="no"/>chise in more than one constituency. Should he
               <lb/> not then, to be logical, provide for the elections <lb/> to take place in each
               constituency on succes<lb break="no"/>sive days, so as to give full opportunity for
               all <lb/> having the franchise in different constituen<lb break="no"/>cies, (hear,
               hear). <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. Gray</persName>—Why this would be impos<lb break="no"/>sible; it
               is the <hi rendition="simple:italic">reductio ad absurdum</hi>. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:WOOD1">Hon. Mr. Wood</persName>—It is_ reducing your <lb/> argument <hi rendition="simple:italic">ad absurdum</hi>, (hear, hear and laugh<lb break="no"/>ter). <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. Gray</persName> thought that the House was <lb/> indebted to the
               hon. member for Bothwell for <lb/> awakening an interest in another subject of <lb/>
               discussion than the one they had for the last <lb/> seven or eight days, (hear). If
               every man were <lb/> an educated man, and if there were no moral <lb/> wrong, then
               the theories of the hon. gentleman <lb/> would be right. But they must take men as
               <lb/> they were, and look at the interest a man had <lb/> in the country in which he
               resided. The posses<lb break="no"/>sion of property was an evidence of capacity of
               <lb/> an interest in the country to be affected by <lb/> legislation, and should
               serve as a criterion on <lb/> which the franchise should be based, (hear, <lb/>
               hear). As to the argument that the proposed <lb/> franchise was different from that
               of New<lb break="no"/>foundland and Prince Edward Island, with <lb/> whom we were
               negotiating to enter the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion, he (Col. Gray) would say that it
               would be <lb/> absurd to frame a measure not based upon the <lb/> wishes, the wants,
               or the interests of the 4,000,<lb break="no"/>000 of the Dominion, but on the local
               practice <lb/> of a population not larger than two of our <lb/> counties in Ontario,
               and of Provinces which <lb/> refused to join us, (hear, hear). If the Govern<lb break="no"/>
               <pb n="514" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700318_Page_514.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">514</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">March 18, 1870</fw>

ment had brought down
               a measure of that <lb/> character, it would be absurd. One might as <lb/> well ask
               the people of the United States to <lb/> frame their laws on the customs of the
                  inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants of the Fiji Islands. If there were any <lb/> attempts
               to deprive the people of the Maritime <lb/> Provinces of their rights, as the member
               for <lb/> Bothwell seemed pleased to intimate, there <lb/> were men from those
               Provinces, their own rep<lb break="no"/>resentatives, who were perfectly able to look
               <lb/> after their interests. The people of New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick were content
               with the franchise as they <lb/> had it, and the franchise there was based on <lb/>
               the £100 qualification, mixed of real and per<lb break="no"/>sonal estate or
               income—and in case of land of <lb/> $100. In Ontario the franchise had always been
               <lb/> connected in some way or other with the land. <lb/> In the Maritime Provinces
               the franchise went <lb/> further, and was based on salary and income. <lb/> The
               principle of the Bill was to extend to <lb/> Ontario the same advantages which were
                  pos<lb break="no"/>sessed by the Maritime Provinces, (hear, hear). <lb/>
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—The franchise for the coun<lb break="no"/>ties remains the same as it is now in Ontario —<lb break="yes"/> $100.
               <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. Gray</persName> said that the provisions of <lb/> the Bill were
               more liberal to Ontario than <lb/> those of the Act passed by their own Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture last winter. In this respect this Bill repre<lb break="no"/>sented the interests of Ontario better than <lb/> their own Legislature represented
               them. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—Hear, hear. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col Gray</persName>—Another principle of the Bill
               <lb/>was to prevent the floating population of the <lb/> country from controlling the
               affairs of the <lb/> country, by making residence a qualification of <lb/> voting.
               Registration as well as residence and <lb/> property was required. If the
               representatives <lb/> of Ontario were prepared to adopt the principle <lb/> of
               universal suffrage, then he would say that <lb/> the people of the Maritime Provinces
               would <lb/> not have it, (hear, hear). Those people were <lb/> determined that
               practical and not theoretical <lb/> qualifications should be the result of voting.
               <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MILL4">Mr. Mills</persName>—But you would employ these men
               <lb/>who have no property to defend the country? <lb/> (Hear, hear.) <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Col. Gray</persName> said he would trust every<lb/>man brought up in
               the country to defend it <lb/> even if he had not a shilling, (hear, hear). <lb/>
            </p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>