<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_PEI_1870-03-16" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-03-16">16 March 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Prince Edward Island</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1870">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="467" to="467"/>.
        

          <idno type="legislature"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18700316_Page_467.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-09-28">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18700316_Page_467">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700316_Page_467.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="467" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700316_Page_467.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline"> 16 mars 1870 <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p>[...] ysis of the
               mover's motion there would be a <lb/>
               definition of Customs Union, while there had <lb/>
               only been an attack on the policy of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, which they were quite able to bear, <lb/>
               and he had the consolation to know that his <lb/>
               political friend knew what he was doing. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—Keep the camp in order. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART1">Hon. Sir George-È. Cartier</persName>—Yes, keep the <lb/> camp in order,
               because they all had confidence <lb/> in each other and nothing was so conclusive to
               <lb/> this as acting from the heart. He had looked for <lb/> facts in the mover's
               speech, but had found <lb/> nothing but abuse. He had no obligation to <lb/> water
               drinking, but his hon. friend the member <lb/> for Shefford had drunk too much water
               in the <lb/> course of his speech, he had drowned his ideas <lb/> in the three
               tumblers of cold water he had <lb/> swallowed. (Laughter) <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HUNT2">Hon. Mr. Huntington</persName>—How do you know <lb/> there was not any
               whiskey in it? <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART1">Hon. Sir George-È. Cartier</persName> said if there was <lb/> whiskey in
               it, that it was just what he did the <lb/> other day; he had sent a boy for some
               before he <lb/> spoke. (Renewed laughter.) He asked what had <lb/> the Government
               done, he pointed to Nova <lb/> Scotia. Well, is she not conciliated? The Red <lb/>
               River difficulty will be expected next, and it <lb/> followed. But there was nothing
               to answer. He <lb/> had forgotten Newfoundland and other things. <lb/> He (Sir
               George), would fill up his speech on <lb/> that subject, and on Prince Edward Island.
               In <lb/> these cases they had no right to coerce, it must <lb/> be a mutual agreement
               and this had not yet <lb/> been accomplished. The member for Shefford <lb/> had never
               referred to the Zollverein at all in <lb/> his speech, nor had the member for
               Hochelaga; <lb/> they had merely spoken of free trade and <lb/> argued that from a
               protective side. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:DORI1">Hon. Mr. Dorion</persName> said he argued that they <lb/> wanted no
               protection but a market. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART1">Hon. Sir George-È. Cartier</persName> said, well, he <lb/> pointed to the
               United States, and they could <lb/> not expect a Customs Union without collecting
               <lb/> an equal tariff with theirs to the exclusion of <lb/> all foreign goods, and to
               the shutting up of <lb/> manufactures by the oppressive excise duties. <lb/>
               Protection meant the levying of taxes on the <lb/> agriculturists and land owners for
               the benefit <lb/> of a few. They argued for a policy in respect to <lb/>
               discriminating duties which had never been <lb/> admitted by Colonial or British
               legislation <lb/> since the inauguration of the present policy. In <lb/> 1846
               intimation was received from the Colonial <lb/> office to the effect that we should
               not impose <lb/> any more discriminating tariffs. But the mover <lb/> thought free
               trade and reciprocal trade were <lb/> synonymous. Yet in Manchester and Birming- [...]<lb/>
            </p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>