<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_PEI_1873-05-20"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1873-05-20">20 May 1873</date>, Canadian Confederation with Prince Edward Island</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>David Farr</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, Second Parliament, First Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2013"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          


<!--GL 2016-09-29 Created github ticket to ask Dan about explanation of page choices. Why is 629 relevant? Reason for omission of subsequent pages?-->
          <biblScope unit="page" from="629" to="629"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="634" to="635"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18730520_Page_629.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18730520_Page_634.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18730520_Page_635.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-09-29">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18730520_Page_629">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18730520_Page_629.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18730520_Page_634">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18730520_Page_634.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18730520_Page_635">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18730520_Page_635.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="629" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18730520_Page_629.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline"> May 20, 1873 <lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
<div type="section">
            <head> PROVINCIAL ASSUMPTION
               OF DEBTS <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Sir JOHN A.
               MACDONALD moved the second reading <lb/>
               of the Bill to readjust the provincial debt. He said in consequence of <lb/>
               the resolution of the House last night in regard to the printing <lb/>
               contract, there had been some delay in the printing of the Bill, but <lb/>
               his hon. friend the Minister of Finance desired to move its second <lb/>
               reading today. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. CAUCHON
               said, without speaking at all of the <lb/>
               question of the liabilities of the respective Provinces, some <lb/>
               provision should be made by which Upper and Lower Canada <lb/>
               should be treated on the same basis, and have as equal and fair <lb/>
               share of compensation arising out of this distribution as the other <lb/>
               Provinces. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> He gave notice that
               on the third reading he would move, <lb/>
               seconded by Hon. Mr. Dorion, in amendment to the fourth clause of <lb/>
               the Bill, that the following words be added:-“Provided
               always that <lb/>
               these last amounts go towards equalizing the debts and subsidies <lb/>
               between all the Provinces, according to population, real or assumed, <lb/>
               with which they entered Confederation.” <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. WOOD said
               the Hon. Minister of Finance (Hon. <lb/>
               Mr. Tilley) must keep a running account with the Provinces, and <lb/>
               when the debt of any party exceeded that stipulated in the statute be <lb/>
               charged that Province 8 per cent upon the differences, or vice versa <lb/>
               when the amount was under the stipulated sum. It was an <lb/>
               impossibility, notwithstanding the remarks of the Minister of <lb/>
               Justice the other night to close that account. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. TILLEY: You
               are right, we cannot do it. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. WOOD said,
               speaking generally, he did not see that <lb/>
               this would in any way settle the difference between Ontario and <lb/>
               Quebec. He wished it would. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear</hi>.) However, they had <lb/>
               always managed to keep their tempers over the matter. He <lb/>
               contended that the difference surrounding this matter would be as <lb/>
               great as before. As to the advantages to the Provinces, it seemed to <lb/>
               him it would be very small. Ontario and Quebec would each receive <lb/>
               between $3,000,000 and $4,000,000, Nova Scotia over $67,000, <lb/>
               New Brunswick over $60,000, British Columbia about $11,000, and <lb/>
               that to Manitoba as small as $6,967. This was too little for that <lb/>
               poor, small Province, and the Minister of Finance would require to <lb/>
               make some provision for it. Increasing subsidies all round <lb/>
               amounted to $13,386,934. The debt at Confederation was <lb/>
               $77,000,000, and it might surprise those who had studied the matter <lb/>
               thoroughly that it had now reached the sum of $82,000,000. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> This was caused by
               subsidies to the several Provinces being <lb/>
               treated as an usual charge upon the revenues instead of being <lb/>
               capitalized and treated as a consolidated debt, as was the case in the <lb/>
               old Provinces of Canada. Then there were $40,000,000 to be <lb/>
               expended upon Public Works, $1,000,000 on the lntercolonial <lb/>
               Railway, $20,000,000 on Canals and $30,000,000 upon the Canada <lb/>
               Paciﬁc Railway subsidies alone, without accounting for the
               sum <lb/>
               voted the other day to New Brunswick, under the heading of <lb/>
               
         
            
      <cb/>
            
            <fw type="num"> 629 <lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
         
            
           compensation for
               timber dues, would amount to over $34,000,000. <lb/>
               New subsidies, as he had already stated, amounted to $13,284,000, <lb/>
               New Brunswick export duty $3,000,000, Prince Edward Island <lb/>
               $7,704,000; that is to say a total of $226,683,700 of debt up to the <lb/>
               present time. These items were so simple that they were easily <lb/>
               calculated, and he did not see how his hon. ﬁiends could
               have <lb/>
               arrived at the conclusion to which they pointed. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> It was said the
               country was very prosperous which conclusion <lb/>
               was arrived at upon the basis of the treaty, returns, imports and <lb/>
               exports particularly. He reminded the hon. gentleman of the debts <lb/>
               that followed the period of ﬁnancial prosperity from 1846 to
               1864, <lb/>
               during which so many railways and public works were under <lb/>
               construction. No doubt for a few years to come the expectations of <lb/>
               the Finance Minister would be realized, but we were heading up <lb/>
               against time, the tide turned and heavy burdens were being laid <lb/>
               upon the country by this Government against the future. He <lb/>
               reminded by asserting that our public debt was not a cent less than <lb/>
               he had concluded, namely above $110,000,000. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. TILLEY: If
               the hon. gentleman had gone on and <lb/>
               extended all the obligations of the Dominion he might have greatly <lb/>
               increased the amount of the liabilities of the country. By the bill the
               <lb/>
               debt would be increased from $62,500,000 to $73,000,000. He <lb/>
               hoped some means could be divided by which Ontario and Quebec <lb/>
               would agree upon the assets. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. DORION (Napierville) referred to the passing of the <lb/>
               Act of Confederation, when it was expected everything would work <lb/>
               smoothly; yet they had extended upon the ﬁrst session of
               the second <lb/>
               Parliament when it was proposed to have everything to place. It was <lb/>
               prepared to give to New Brunswick a subsidy which was agreed to <lb/>
               about $1,000,000, and which would be $800,000 more than they <lb/>
               were entitled to by the ﬁgures of the Finance Minister
               himself <lb/>
               When the Government were asked how it was they happened to <lb/>
               take up the question, a reply was given that it was the member from <lb/>
               Napierville who had proposed such arrangement two years ago. He <lb/>
               denied that he made any such proposition. It was of a different <lb/>
               nature. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The Finance Minister
               (Hon. Mr. Tilley) had shown that he was <lb/>
               unable to grapple with the question of the settlement of the decision <lb/>
               of the debt between Ontario and Quebec. If he could not deal with it <lb/>
               let him appoint a committee to enquire into the whole subject. He <lb/>
               held that under the Confederation Act, the Great Western and <lb/>
               Northern Railway debts should go to the reduction of the debt of <lb/>
               Ontario and Quebec, and he argued that, judging from what had <lb/>
               been stated in the House, we would have a demand in a few years <lb/>
               from the New Brunswick and Nova Scotia Governments to hand <lb/>
               over the railways in these Provinces to them. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. WOOD: We
               will be willing to give them to them. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. DORION (Napierville) said that taking into <lb/>
               consideration the position of these roads he promised the Dominion <lb/>
               would not raise much objection. He argued that the Government <lb/>
               should take into their hands the settlement of the whole question of <lb/>
  
            
            <pb n="634" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18730520_Page_634.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">634</fw>
            
           amendments to the
               following bills, and asking the concurrence of <lb/>
               the House in the same: <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> To incorporate the
               Canada Investment and Guarantee Agency. <lb/>
               To incorporate the Merchants’ Warehousing Company. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> To empower the
               Montreal and Northern Colonization Railway <lb/>
               Company, and to extend its line. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> To incorporate the
               Labrador Company. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> To grant additional
               powers to the Quebec and Gulf Steamship <lb/>
               Company. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> To incorporate the
               Goldsmiths Company of Canada. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
    <p> *** <lb/></p></div>

<div type="section">
            <head>PRINCE EDWARD ISLAND</head>
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. TILLEY moved
               the House in Committee to consider <lb/>
               certain proposed resolutions respecting the admission of Prince <lb/>
               Edward Island into the Dominion of Canada, and the message of his <lb/>
               Excellency the Governor General on that subject. He stated that the <lb/>
               Government had been endeavouring since confederation, to get this <lb/>
               beautiful and fertile Island into the Union. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The
               difﬁculty had always been that in consequence of their <lb/>
               isolated position they could not receive an appropriation for local <lb/>
               purposes, as they were entitled to, a debt having been incurred by <lb/>
               the Island Railway. A deputation had in January been sent up to <lb/>
               arrange terms of union. Another delegation had been recently sent <lb/>
               up, empowered to enter into the ﬁnal arrangements which were
               now <lb/>
               submitted to Parliament. The great local works there having been <lb/>
               now completed, there could never be any large local expenditure in <lb/>
               the future, and it was in consideration of this fact that the Dominion <lb/>
               Government had granted such liberal terms. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The House went into
               Committee, Mr. CHIPMAN in the chair. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. TILLEY
               explained that the expenditure of the Island <lb/>
               would be $480,000, and the receipts would, under the Dominion <lb/>
               tariff, have been $441,898 last year. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE
               enquired what loss would accrue to <lb/>
               the Dominion by having the Island Railway. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. TILLEY did
               not think any loss would accrue to the <lb/>
               Dominion. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> In answer to Mr.
               Cartwright, <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. TILLEY said
               the railway was under contract and the <lb/>
               Dominion would not be liable for any excess of these contracts, but <lb/>
               that excess would be charged against the debt of the Islands. In <lb/>
               reference to the tariff he said that the Island charged a duty of <lb/>
               11 1/2 per cent, on what the Dominion charged 15. <lb/>
               
    
            
            <cb/>
            <fw type="dateline"> May 20, 1873 <lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
         
            
           Hon. Mr. WOOD
               advocated the assumption of the whole debt <lb/>
               of the Island by the Dominion and the giving to the Island of all <lb/>
               local works. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Aﬁer some
               further discussion the resolutions were reported <lb/>
               without amendment. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The report was
               adopted amid applause on both sides of the <lb/>
               House. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> *** <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>

<div type="section">      
            
            <head> THE NORTH WEST
               TERRITORIES <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> The resolutions
               providing for the administration of justice and <lb/>
               the establishment of a police force in the North West Territories <lb/>
               passed through Committee. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The bill was reported
               with a triﬂing amendment, which was <lb/>
               concurred in. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
 <p> *** <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>CONTESTED ELECTIONS</head>
            
            <p> On motion of Hon. Sir
               JOHN A. MACDONALD the <lb/>
               amendment to the bill to make better provision respecting Election <lb/>
               Petitions and Contested Elections was read a second time. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
 <p> *** <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>EXTRADITION</head>
            
            <p> Hon. Sir JOHN A.
               MACDONALD moved the second reading <lb/>
               of the bill to make further provision for the extradition of <lb/>
               criminals-Carried.
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The House went into
               Committee adopted the bill with certain <lb/>
               amendments, rose and reported, and the bill was read a third time <lb/>
               and passed. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
      <p> *** <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>

<div type="section">    
            
            <head> PRINCE EDWARD ISLAND <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. TILLEY moved
               that an Address embodying the <lb/>
               resolutions with respect to the admission into the Union of Prince <lb/>
               Edward Island be presented to Her Majesty, and that a Select <lb/>
               Committee, composed of Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald, Hon. <lb/>
               Messrs. Langevin, Tupper and the mover, be appointed to draw up <lb/>
               such address-Carried.
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The Committee
               presented the address, which was read a ﬁrst and <lb/>
               second time, and was ordered to be engrossed. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> On motion of Hon. Mr.
               TILLEY, the House went into <lb/>
               Committee, adopted the resolutions, rose and reported, and a bill <lb/>
               
        
            
            <pb n="635" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18730520_Page_635.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline"> May 20, 1873 <lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
       founded on the
               resolutions was introduced and read a ﬁrst and <lb/>
               second time. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. TILLEY
               introduced a bill extending to Prince Edward <lb/>
               Island the Customs law of the Dominion. He explained that it <lb/>
               provided that goods imported into the Island before the sales and <lb/>
               brought back again to other parts of the Dominion aﬁer the
               sales <lb/>
               shall have to pay the difference in duty on being as bought back. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The Bill was read a
               second time. <lb/></p>
 <p> *** <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>

<div type="section">
              <head> EXTRA SITTING <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Sir JOHN A.
               MACDONALD proposed to the House that <lb/>
               they should meet at eleven o’clock on Wednesday. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> This was agreed to. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
       <p> *** <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>
<div type="section">   
            
            <head> ADJOURNMENT <lb/> </head>

 <p>              In answer to Hon. Mr. Dorion (Napierville), <lb/></p>
               
           
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Sir JOHN A.
               MACDONALD said the House would <lb/>
               probably get through the business on Wednesday, and in that case <lb/>
               he would move the adjournment of the House till some day in <lb/>
               August. <lb/>
               
            </p>
   <p> *** <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>

<div type="section">          
         
            
            <head> PROMISSORY NOTES <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> Mr. KIRKPATRICK in
               the absence of Hon. Mr. CAMERON <lb/>
               (Cardwell), moved that the bill to amend the law relating to <lb/>
               promissory notes and bills of exchange be not now read a third <lb/>
               
       
          <cb/>
            
            <fw type="num"> 635 <lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
         
            
             time, but that it be
               referred back to a Committee of the Whole to <lb/>
               make certain amendments-Carried.
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The bill passed
               through Committee, and was read a third time <lb/>
               and passed. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
      <p> *** <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>

<div type="section">    
            
            <head> CHANGE OF COUNTY
               LIMITS <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> On motion of Mr.
               DUGAS the bill to change the limits of the <lb/>
               Counties of Montcalm and Joliette was read a third time and passed. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
 <p> *** <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>
            
         
 <div type="section">           
            <head> FUNERAL OF HON. SIR
               GEORGE-E. CARTIER <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Sir JOHN A.
               MACDONALD desired to give notice of a <lb/>
               proposition that he should submit to the House at its next meeting. <lb/>
               He was able to do so now though he was not able to do so a while <lb/>
               ago. He considered that the life and history of Sir George-É. Cartier <lb/>
               was mixed up with the history of Canada, and especially with the <lb/>
               history of Confederation and believed that the country owed the <lb/>
               latter to him more than to any other man in Canada, since it had <lb/>
               been under British institutions. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> He was quite
               unprepared to make a speech on the question, but <lb/>
               did think that if ever there was an occasion which the House should <lb/>
               show its regard for a great man now was the time, and if ever there <lb/>
               was a man who deserved that expression of regard it was Sir <lb/>
               George-É. Cartier. He should therefore propose, the following <lb/>
               English precedent, that the funeral of Sir George-E. Cartier should <lb/>
               be a public funeral, and that the country should defray the expenses <lb/>
               connected therewith. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The House then
               adjourned at 1.30 am. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
