<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_1873-03-19"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1873-03-19">19 March 1873</date>, Canadian Confederation with Prince Edward Island</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Canadian Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>David Farr</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, Second Parliament, First Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2013"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="80"/>.
        

          <idno type="legislature"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18730319_Page_080.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-09-28">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18730319_Page_080">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18730319_Page_080.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="80" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18730319_Page_080.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">80</fw>
            
            <p> magniﬁcent
               and complete confederation of all the British<lb/>
               possessions. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear.</hi>) <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> For these reasons any
               route which placed us within the smallest <lb/>
               possible distance from Great Britain should receive the serious <lb/>
               consideration of the House; and he moved that a Select Committee <lb/>
               be appointed for the purpose of enquiring into the matter, to consist <lb/>
               of Messrs. Campbell, Anglin, Fortin, Young (Montreal West), <lb/>
               Young (Waterloo South), MacKay, and the mover. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. ANGLlN said
               the importance ofthis subject could not <lb/>
               well be over-estimated, but it could not have been dealt with <lb/>
               sooner. He wished to point out a few of the facts, as laid down in <lb/>
               Fleming’s report, which had not been noticed by the mover of
               the <lb/>
               resolution. The proposed route was not only the shortest to Europe <lb/>
               from this country, but it was also the shortest from New York to <lb/>
               Europe, and, therefore, in the summer season a very large passenger <lb/>
               trafﬁc might reasonably be expected over this route, which
               would <lb/>
               diminish the risks and inconvenience and sufferings of a sea <lb/>
               voyage. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> From his own personal
               knowledge he could say that the <lb/>
               expenditure on the continent would be a mere triﬂe. A branch
               <lb/>
               railway from the lntercolonial Railway, down to Shippegan would, <lb/>
               according to Mr. Fleming, be about 22 miles in length. He knew the <lb/>
               country, and knew that except on the prairies there was no country <lb/>
               where a railway could be more cheaply constructed. There would <lb/>
               be no bridges nor cuttings required of any importance. With regard <lb/>
               to the harbour, it was one of the ﬁnest in America. There
               was <lb/>
               magniﬁcent entrance to the Bay of Chaleur. The entrance to <lb/>
               Miramichi Bay would need some improvement, but some <lb/>
               expenditure would be required anyway. He considered the time had <lb/>
               now come when this subject should receive the serious <lb/>
               consideration of the Government and Parliament. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> There was an
               impression that the interior of Newfoundland was <lb/>
               waste and uninhabited; but explorations had of late been made <lb/>
               which showed that the country was well watered and timbered, and <lb/>
               a railway could be built through it without any great expense. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> It might be said that
               Newfoundland was not within the <lb/>
               Dominion, and therefore the Dominion could not be expected to <lb/>
               seriously entertain any project which would involve an expenditure <lb/>
               of public money to a very large extent upon the island. That was, no <lb/>
               doubt, true, but he believed the Government hoped at no distant day <lb/>
               to induce Newfoundland to join the Union. It was scarcely probable <lb/>
               that Prince Edward Island and Newfoundland would remain outside <lb/>
               of the Union for any very great length of time, and one of the means <lb/>
               of inducing Newfoundland to come into the Union probably would <lb/>
               be to hold out the expectation that, in addition to other advantages, <lb/>
               the Island would be opened up by a railway running across it, <lb/>
               bringing a stream oftravel to and from Europe, which would be of <lb/>
               great advantage to the country. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The importance of the
               subject having been so fully stated by the <lb/>
               mover of the resolution, it was not necessary for him to dwell upon <lb/>
               
               <cb/>
               <fw type="dateline"> March 19, 1873 <lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para " March 19, 1873 
               
            ..." merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
          it. He might say that
               the harbour of Shippegan was very <lb/>
               conveniently situated on a point of land which ran down from the <lb/>
               mainland, having the Bay of Chaleur on one side and Miramichi on <lb/>
               the other, and it was stated by Mr. Fleming that this port was the <lb/>
               nearest point, on the mainland to Europe, excepting a point on <lb/>
               Gaspe, which was out of the question as a shipping point. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Sir JOHN A.
               MACDONALD regretted that Hon. Mr. <lb/>
               Tupper was not present, as he had always taken a special interest in <lb/>
               the subject. He agreed that this matter was one of very great <lb/>
               importance, and the House was very much indebted to the mover of <lb/>
               the resolution for having brought the matter before them so ably. <lb/>
               The Committee, he had no doubt, would be able to report some <lb/>
               valuable suggestions, and after that, perhaps, the question
               might be <lb/>
               again discussed by the House this session. The motion was agreed <lb/>
               to. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
<p> *** <lb/></p>

         
            <div type="section">
            <head> COLLECTING DEBTS FROM
               VESSELS <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> Mr. KIRKPATRICK moved
               that the House go into Committee <lb/>
               on the following resolution,-"That
               it is expedient to make further <lb/>
               provision for the collection of demands against vessels navigating <lb/>
               certain lakes and inland waters of Canada for seamen’s wages
               and <lb/>
               debts contracted, for necessary provisions supplied, repairs made <lb/>
               and for towage and other services rendered to such vessels, and for <lb/>
               damages arising out of collisions by vessels, by making the same a <lb/>
               preferential lien on them.” <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> He proceeded to say
               that the principle of this resolution had long <lb/>
               been acted upon in other countries, and the Act of the Ontario <lb/>
               Legislature giving a lien to mechanics was an additional reason for <lb/>
               the passage ofthe proposed measure. He referred to cases of loss of <lb/>
               wages and damages, for which there was at present no remedy. If <lb/>
               this measure was passed, it would improve the whole shipping <lb/>
               interest, because it would have a tendency to reduce the rate of <lb/>
               wages, as employees, having a security against loss, could afford to <lb/>
               accept lower wages. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> He argued that as a
               matter relating to trade and commerce, and <lb/>
               shipping, it came within the jurisdiction of this House, the question <lb/>
               of civil rights being merely incidental to it. No local Government <lb/>
               could deal with it, as they could not seize a foreign vessel-at any <lb/>
               rate trouble would be very apt to arise if they did do so. His <lb/>
               measure was conﬁned to the inland waters, as he believed
               that <lb/>
               Admiralty Court of the Maritime Provinces had jurisdiction to deal <lb/>
               with the questions involved. Since he had introduced the measure <lb/>
               last session, he had received many assurances from gentlemen <lb/>
               interested in shipping that it was a much needed motion. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> It was agreed to, and
               the House went into Committee, <lb/>
               Mr. DOMVILLE in the chair. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Mr. KIRKPATRICK moved
               the adoption of the resolution. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
