<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_PEI_1870-02-22" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-02-22">22 February 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Prince Edward Island</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="138" to="138"/>.
        

          <idno type="legislature"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18700222_Page_138.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-09-28">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
         <change who="heidt_daniel" when="2016-11-28">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18700222_Page_138">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700222_Page_138.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="138" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18700222_Page_138.jpg"/>

            <fw type="num">138</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 22, 1870</fw>

            
            <p> (Sir F. Hincks) had
               not entered into the <lb/>
               charges against himself that had been pub<lb break="no"/>lished in the newspapers. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HINC1">Hon. Sir Francis Hincks</persName>—Of course, in <hi rendition="simple:italic">The <lb/> Globe</hi>, I suppose? <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:YOUN2">Mr. Young</persName> said that he should only be too <lb/>
               happy to hear those charges denied, but they <lb/> had not been successfully cleared
               up; and yet it <lb/> was to such a man that Sir John A. Macdonald <lb/> had entrusted
               the most important part of the <lb/> public service. He could not but apply to him in
               <lb/> that office the quotation of Mr. Baldwin, that <lb/> "Confidence was a plant of
               slow growth; when <lb/> once it was broken, it was difficult to restore <lb/> it."
               Then, with regard to the policy of the <lb/> Government, they had violated the
                  Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion in their grant to Nova Scotia; and the <lb/> Ontario
               Legislature had passed resolutions <lb/> asking that Imperial legislation might be
               taken <lb/> which would prevent such acts in the future, <lb/> and there was no doubt
               that the example <lb/> would be attempted to be followed by the other <lb/> Provinces
               at present in the Confederation. This <lb/> would account in some measure for the
                  dis<lb break="no"/>turbances at Red River. The conduct of the <lb/> hon. member
               for Cumberland, in regard to the <lb/> grant to Nova Scotia, was answered, and he
               <lb/> thought that if a different course had been <lb/> pursued in regard to this
               matter, the difficul<lb break="no"/>ties that had been experienced in Newfound<lb break="no"/>land and Prince Edward Island would have <lb/> been overcome. He was
               astonished to find that <lb/> the Government had taken credit for economi<lb break="no"/>cal management of the Dominion; and he was <lb/> astonished even more
               to hear the hon. mover of <lb/> the Address refer to it. He would like to know <lb/>
               where the economy of the Government was to <lb/> be found. Was it in the creation of
               new Cabinet <lb/> officials, and in the way the Intercolonial Rail<lb break="no"/>way
               was being managed? He was afraid that <lb/> instead of economy the very opposite
               course <lb/> had been pursued. The public debt of the <lb/> Dominion, after payment
               of the expenses con<lb break="no"/>templated, would amount to $120,000,000, and <lb/>
               would entail a heavy taxation of the country. If <lb/> they put the same duties upon
               articles entering <lb/> the Dominion as the Americans did, they <lb/> would be in
               fact cutting off their noses because <lb/> the Americans did theirs. (Laughter.) He
               <lb/> would go for any national policy which would <lb/> benefit Canada; but he did
               not approve of a <lb/> tariff which would place them in the same <lb/> position as
               America. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:TUPP1">Hon. Dr. Tupper</persName> said that his equal tariff <lb/> referred to
               articles which now went free, but <lb/> which should then be placed on an equal
                  foot<lb break="no"/>ing with the American tariff. <lb/>
            </p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>