<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_PEI_1869-06-04"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-06-04">4 June 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Prince Edward Island</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="613" to="616"/>.
        

          <idno type="legislature"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_613.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_614.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_615.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_616.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-09-28">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>

<change who="taekema_sarah" when="2016-10-15">Marked-up people. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_613">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_613.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_614">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_614.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_615">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_615.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_616">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_616.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="613" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_613.jpg"/>
            <div type="section"><!--<fw type="dateline"> 4 juin 1869 <lb/>
               
            </fw>-->
            
            <p> might elapse between
               the issuing of the proc<lb break="no"/>lamation and the convening of Parliament. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
    
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName>  asked if
               this was the only Bill <lb/>
               which was to be introduced on the subject. <lb/>
               Did the Government think there would be <lb/>
               sufficient
               time to consider a measure of such <lb/>
               magnitude? The President of the Council, who <lb/>
               was so much opposed to this measure at one <lb/>
               period, was now among those who were press<lb break="no"/>ing it on, when members were almost leav<lb break="no"/>ing for home. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName> said
               that the business could <lb/>
               be got through well enough if hon. gentlemen <lb/>
               on the other side would not waste so much <lb/>
               time in wrangling. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> thought
               the President of the <lb/>
               Council ought to be the last man to complain <lb/>
               of taking up the time of the Dominion; for if <lb/>
               any person took up the time of the House, not <lb/>
               perhaps talking nonsense, but something <lb/>
               which had no bearing on the subject, it was <lb/>
               that hon. gentleman. (Hear and cheers.) The <lb/>
               President of the Council was not to be the <lb/>
               judge of what was important and what was <lb/>
               unimportant. (Hear). The House was told the <lb/>
               other night that the measure just introduced <lb/>
               was a great one on which to expend our <lb/>
               thoughts. For his part, he thought the discus<lb break="no"/>sion of such a measure only a waste of time <lb/>
               and would not enter on it. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <p> The second reading of
               the Bill was ordered <lb/>
               for Tuesday. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            </div>    
            <div type="section">
            <head> NEWFOUNDLAND AND
               PRINCE EDWARD <lb/>
               ISLAND <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> A message was brought
               down from His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency enclosing copies of minutes of the <lb/>
               Privy Council of Canada and delegates from <lb/>
               Newfoundland, on the subject of the union of <lb/>
               that colony with the Dominion, and copies of <lb/>
               the resolutions adopted as the basis of such <lb/>
               union. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <p> Another message was
               sent from His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency transmitting copies of minutes of a meet<lb break="no"/>ing of the Privy Council of Canada on the <lb/>
               subject of the admission of Prince Edward Is<lb break="no"/>land into the Dominion of Canada, which His <lb/>
               Excellency recommended to the consideration <lb/>
               of the House. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> moved
               for a committee on <lb/>
               Tuesday next, to consider the resolutions on <lb/>
               Newfoundland. He explained the resolutions <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">seriatim</hi>. It was proposed that Newfoundland <lb/>
               should receive ﬁve per cent interest on the <lb/>
               difference between its actual debt and the <lb/>
               
               <pb n="614" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_614.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">614</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 4, 1869</fw> 

amount with which it
               would be entitled to <lb/>
               come into the Union according to population <lb/>
               as compared with Nova Scotia and New <lb/>
               Brunswick. It was also proposed to allow <lb/>
               the colony an annual subsidy of $35,000, and <lb/>
               an allowance of eighty cents per head until <lb/>
               the population should increase to 400,000; the <lb/>
               same arrangement as that made with the other <lb/>
               Maritime Provinces. In consideration of the <lb/>
               surrender of its mineral and wild lands to the <lb/>
               General Goverment, there was a further pay<lb break="no"/>ment to be made of $150,000 per annum. The <lb/>
               8th resolution referred to a local matter—a <lb/>
               water company in St. John’s—for $400,000 of <lb/>
               the bonds of which the Government of the <lb/>
               Province was responsible, and it was provided <lb/>
               that the Local Government should retain the <lb/>
               power of imposing a water rate on the inhab<lb break="no"/>itants, and tonnage and coal dues in the <lb/>
               harbour of St. John’s on vessels supplied by <lb/>
               this Company with water. It was provided in <lb/>
               the resolutions that the Government of Can<lb break="no"/>ada should assume all the charges in the Prov<lb break="no"/>ince of Newfoundland which are borne by <lb/>
               it in the other Provinces. The union of New<lb break="no"/>foundland with Canada would take place on <lb/>
               a day named by proclamation, which procla<lb break="no"/>mation should also contain the names of the <lb/>
               four Senators to represent the Province in <lb/>
               the Senate of Canada. The Militia Law of the <lb/>
               Dominion was to be modiﬁed on its operation <lb/>
               in Newfoundland to meet the peculiar circum<lb break="no"/>stances of the population, and the Dominion <lb/>
               Government would be pledged to use its in<lb break="no"/>ﬂuence with the Imperial Government to <lb/>
               maintain a garrison at St. John’s. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> said
               that in the new <lb/>
               Constitution,
               under which we hoped to live, <lb/>
               a Railway formed a very conspicuous feature, <lb/>
               rather a novel one to him; but the hon. the <lb/>
               Minister of Justice is fertile in expedients, <lb/>
               and we have in that Act, as the foundation <lb/>
               of his policy, a railway. In the revised edition <lb/>
               of the Constitution, now proposed, a steamboat <lb/>
               line forms a prominent feature (Hear, hear, <lb/>
               and laughter.) His hon. friend had earned an <lb/>
               additional claim to immortality by this feat. <lb/>
               (Laughter) <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A.
               Macdonald</persName>—Perhaps the hon. <lb/>
               gentleman is not aware that the motto of the <lb/>
               Macdonalds’ is—“By Sea and
               Land.” (Laugh<lb break="no"/>ter.) <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The motion carried. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> moved
               that on Tuesday next <lb/>
               thel House resolve itself into Committee of <lb/>
                <lb/>
               
               <pb n="615" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_615.jpg"/>
              <!-- <fw type="dateline"> 4 juin 1869 <lb/></fw>-->
               
                
the Whole on the
               resolutions respecting Prince <lb/>
               Edward Island. Those resolutions, of course, <lb/>
               did not embody any conclusive arrangement, <lb/>
               but were rather an authority for opening <lb/>
               negotiation with Prince Edward Island on <lb/>
               terms which the Government were not with<lb break="no"/>out hope would result in completing the Union <lb/>
               of the British North American Provinces on <lb/>
               the seaboard at least. The Island was owned <lb/>
               by some 62 individuals, to whom it was origi<lb break="no"/>nally granted by the Crown at a merely nom<lb break="no"/>inal rent, and as their titles obstructed the <lb/>
               Union it was thought they ought to be extin<lb break="no"/>guished. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> thought
               the hon. Finance <lb/>
               Minister ought to have informed the House <lb/>
               what correspondence there had been with the <lb/>
               Prince Edward Island Government or any one <lb/>
               else respecting so extraordinary a proposition. <lb/>
               By whom was the correspondence originated? <lb/>
               It was very desirable indeed that Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island should join the Confederation, <lb/>
               and any reasonable proposition leading to <lb/>
               that end would receive his cordial assent; but <lb/>
               it was quite possible that the annexation of <lb/>
               this Island might be purchased too dearly. In <lb/>
               its present shape the proposition was just <lb/>
               another Seignorial Tenure business, and One <lb/>
               he would have nothing to do with. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>
               said there had been <lb/>
               no correspondence with the Government, or <lb/>
               any one in Prince Edward Island, on the mat<lb break="no"/>ter. The subject of the admission of Prince <lb/>
               Edward Island into the Union had been fre<lb break="no"/>quently debated. The terms proposed on both <lb/>
               sides were pretty well canvassed, and will be <lb/>
               canvassed again when we go down. It was <lb/>
               clearly worth while for the Government of <lb/>
               the Dominion to make an effort to induce <lb/>
               Prince Edward Island, the last fraction of <lb/>
               British North America, to enter the Union. <lb/>
               (Hear). He hoped the Government would be <lb/>
               accorded a hearty support by honourable gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACD6">Mr. D. A. Macdonald</persName>
               wondered where the <lb/>
               present movements for the acquisition of ter<lb break="no"/>ritory and their organization were going to <lb/>
               end. Were the Government to go on purchas<lb break="no"/>ing up Colonies in this way? It was absurd, <lb/>
               had been opposed by him from ﬁrst to last, <lb/>
               and would continue to get his opposition. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GALT1">Hon. Mr. Galt</persName> did not
               agree with the hon<lb break="no"/>ourable gentlemen who had just spoken. He <lb/>
               (Mr. Galt) believed it would be a great mis<lb break="no"/>fortune if Prince Edward Island did not join in <lb/>
               
               <pb n="616" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18690604_Page_616.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">616</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 4, 1869</fw> 

 Confederation. He
               objected, also, to the hon<lb break="no"/>ourable member for Glengarry speaking of <lb/>
               the people of the Maritime Provinces as hav<lb break="no"/>ing been purchased. By the next session of <lb/>
               Parliament, he hoped to see all the Provinces <lb/>
               spoken of in the Union. (Cheers). <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:YOUN2">Mr. Young</persName> questioned
               the advisability of <lb/>
               the Dominion Government taking the initia<lb break="no"/>tive, and making the ﬁrst advance in secur<lb break="no"/>ing the admission into the Union of Prince <lb/>
               Edward Island. The Government delegation <lb/>
               to that Island would do much more harm <lb/>
               than good. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> asked if it
               was understood that <lb/>
               public faith would be in no way pledged to <lb/>
               these resolutions before Parliament meets? <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A.
               Macdonald</persName>—Certainly. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName>
               instanced these resolutions <lb/>
               as another proof of the extreme fertility of <lb/>
               resources possessed by the Minister of Justice. <lb/>
               His (Mr. Holton’s) admiration for that hon. <lb/>
               gentleman was unbounded. First, their Con<lb break="no"/>stitution was burdened with a railway, then <lb/>
               it was amended by two or three steamboat <lb/>
               lines, now it was to be amended by a provision <lb/>
               binding us to re-purchase the rights of certain <lb/>
               land-holders in Prince Edward’s Island. <lb/>
               (Laughter) He had never heard of such a <lb/>
               Constitution. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>
               could not compli<lb break="no"/>ment the hon. gentleman on his study of <lb/>
               Constitutional history. Agreements similar to <lb/>
               those alluded to by the hon. member formed <lb/>
               a portion of the Constitution of Great Britain <lb/>
               and Ireland. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MACD2">Hon. John
               Sandﬁeld Macdonald</persName> could only <lb/>
               account for the Government delegation going <lb/>
               to Prince Edward Island by remembering that <lb/>
               Gen. Butler had lately been there, and was <lb/>
               pretty well known, (laughter), and that the <lb/>
               Premier was determined to head off
               that offi<lb break="no"/>cial. He approved the resolutions but derided <lb/>
               what the Prince Edward Islanders would call <lb/>
               reasonable terms. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The motion was
               carried. <lb/>
               
            </p>
           </div> 
         
         <div type="section"> 
            <head> SUBSIDY TO NOVA
               SCOTIA <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p> <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> then
               moved that on Tuesday <lb/>
               next the House resolve itself into Committee <lb/>
               of the Whole on the subject of an additional <lb/>
               subsidy to Nova Scotia. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <p> In answer to Mr.
               Blake. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
       
            </div> 
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
