<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_1872-05-14"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1872-05-14">14 May 1872</date>, Canadian Confederation with Prince Edward Island</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName>Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Canadian Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>David Farr</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Fifth Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="2007"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Library of Parliament</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="232" to="235"/>.
        

          <idno type="legislature"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_232.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_233.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_234.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/en/PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_235.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-10-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-09-28">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_232">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_232.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_233">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_233.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_234">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_234.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_235">
         <graphic url="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_235.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="232" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_232.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">COMMONS</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="num">232</fw>
            
            <p> from this the member
               for Durham would see that the exclusion <lb/>
               of the Americans was not quite as efﬁcient as we imagined. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE
               asked whether they were within the <lb/>
               headlands. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. TUPPER said
               he could not speak as to that; but the <lb/>
               question was altogether a captious one, for it was well known <lb/>
               that the headland limit had not been enforced for years. He <lb/>
               maintained that the member for Durham West gave us the whole <lb/>
               argument when he spoke of bounties being necessary to enable <lb/>
               the Americans to compete with the Canadian ﬁshermen. If <lb/>
               however, the hon. member would read the proceedings of <lb/>
               Congress, he would ﬁnd that the question of bounties had
               been <lb/>
               scouted from the very ﬁrst, and that it was admitted on all
               hands <lb/>
               that a system of bounties was utterly impossible; but further, the <lb/>
               highest system of bounty would be $400 to a vessel, while the <lb/>
               relief would amount to $1,200; and therefore the bounty could <lb/>
               not, under any circumstances, do away with the advantages on <lb/>
               the side of Canadian ﬁshermen. He again referred to what he <lb/>
               termed the unpatriotic action of members last year. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. HOLTON
               thought the hon. gentleman was out of <lb/>
               order in reﬂecting on the action ofthe House. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Sir JOHN A.
               MACDONALD said it was not out of <lb/>
               order, for the action ofthe House was always open to appeal. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. TUPPER said
               he was quite satisﬁed to ﬁnd the <lb/>
               hon. gentleman acknowledge that a reference to his former <lb/>
               action was a reﬂection. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. HOLTON said,
               however that might be, the hon. <lb/>
               gentleman assumed the responsibility of that action. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. TUPPER said
               that was under compulsion. If hon. <lb/>
               gentleman would read a statement recently made by the <lb/>
               chairman of the Committee of Ways and Means of the United <lb/>
               States they would see that it would be impracticable for the <lb/>
               United States to adopt a policy that would counteract the <lb/>
               advantages derived by Canadian ﬁshermen. He would now ask <lb/>
               hon. gentlemen to turn their attention to the effect of the <lb/>
               Treaty on the shipping interest of the country. The member for <lb/>
               Halifax (Mr. Power) had told them that he went to visit a <lb/>
               ﬁshery in which he was concerned, when the Treaty of 1884 <lb/>
               was in force, and found that, out of the forty or fifty vessels, <lb/>
               scarcely one was American; but that on another occasion, after <lb/>
               the abrogation of that treaty, among an equal number of <lb/>
               vessels, scarcely one was Canadian. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> It must be remembered
               that our marine amounted to a <lb/>
               million tons, and the House would see that, whether in <lb/>
               connection with the ﬁshery or the ship-building interest,
               the <lb/>
               value of the Treaty could not be over-rated. He would now <lb/>
               refer to the state of public opinion in Nova Scotia. When the <lb/>
               Treaty ﬁrst became known the Nova Scotia Government put a <lb/>
               very strong resolution in their journals. Since then the Treaty <lb/>
               
               <milestone type="day"/> May 14, 1872 <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para " May 14, 1872 
               
            ..." merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p> had been promulgated
               to the world, and had been read by <lb/>
               every ﬁsherman in the Province, and now the same House had <lb/>
               been in session for over two months, and there had not been <lb/>
               one word of disapproval of the Treaty. He believed that the <lb/>
               feeling in Nova Scotia was that Parliament could not inﬂict <lb/>
               greater wrong on them, and could not paralyze their industries <lb/>
               more than by refusing to ratify the Treaty, which promoted <lb/>
               and protected the great national industries without injuring a <lb/>
               single interest, or being counterbalanced by a single drawback; <lb/>
               and that a refusal would also tend to prevent the obtaining of <lb/>
               reciprocity in the future. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> He was not so well
               prepared to speak as to New Brunswick; <lb/>
               but the same thing took place there. The New Brunswick <lb/>
               Legislature at ﬁrst strongly opposed the Treaty, but though <lb/>
               they had now been six or eight weeks in session, there was not <lb/>
               a single hostile resolution on their records. As to Prince <lb/>
               Edward Island, the Treaty was as good as accepted. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. MACKENZIE
               asked whether they had repealed <lb/>
               the former resolutions. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. TUPPER said
               he would not detain the House <lb/>
               further, and regretted that he had trespassed so long at so late <lb/>
               a stage of the discussion; but the question was one in which <lb/>
               not only the interests of Nova Scotia and New Brunswick and <lb/>
               the whole Dominion were concerned, but also the interests of <lb/>
               the Empire, and he would not have done justice to himself if <lb/>
               he had not given utterance to his views. The hon. gentleman <lb/>
               took his seat amid loud cheers. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Mr. JONES (Halifax)
               said he was obliged to ask the <lb/>
               indulgence of the House at this late hour, while he referred to <lb/>
               the arguments of the hon. gentleman who had just sat down <lb/>
               (Hon. Mr. Tupper). He would say, in the ﬁrst place, that he <lb/>
               desired to approach the consideration of this subject in a <lb/>
               manner worthy of its importance. He would further say that he <lb/>
               came to the House in full expectation of being able to sustain <lb/>
               the Government in the course they had taken in the earlier part <lb/>
               of these negotiations, when it was made known through <lb/>
               ofﬁcial and semi-ofﬁcial sources what was the
               course the <lb/>
               Government were taking. He shared the views they then <lb/>
               expressed, and up to the present time he had seen no reason to <lb/>
               change his opinion. The hon. gentleman who had preceded <lb/>
               him, as well as others on that side of the House, had sought to <lb/>
               convey the impression that the adoption of this Treaty was in <lb/>
               the interests of permanently peaceful relations between the <lb/>
               United States and the Empire. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> He might refer by way
               of illustration to the celebrated <lb/>
               Tichborne trial. The claimant brought witnesses to prove his <lb/>
               pretensions; but when he was put in the witness box himself,
               <lb/>
               his case broke down. So it was in the case of the Ministers. <lb/>
               When their own statements were placed in evidence against <lb/>
               their present arguments, it might be held their case had broken <lb/>
               down. The argument that the Treaty was in the interest of <lb/>
               
               <pb n="233" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_233.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">COMMONS</fw>
               <fw type="running">DEBATES</fw>
               <fw type="dateline"> May 14, 1872 <lb/>
               
               </fw> peace was
               contradicted most emphatically by the despatches of <lb/>
               the Government. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear.</hi>) In their minutes of Council of <lb/>
               the 28th of July last-and
               when they penned that they knew <lb/>
               the provisions of the treaty just as well as they do now-they <lb/>
               knew then as well as now whether it was in the interests of <lb/>
               peace, whether it was for the interests of the Dominion, that it <lb/>
               should be accepted-yet
               in that minute they state as a reason <lb/>
               why they could not accept the treaty that the principal cause of <lb/>
               difference between Canada and the United States had not been <lb/>
               removed by the treaty but remained a subject for future <lb/>
               anxiety. He answered the hon. gentleman out of their own <lb/>
               mouths. The last speaker had referred to the remarks of his <lb/>
               colleague from Halifax (Mr. Power) respecting the advantage <lb/>
               the treaty would have conferred upon the ﬁshing trade of
               Nova <lb/>
               Scotia had it been in operation last year. He stated that in that <lb/>
               case Nova Scotia would have saved between $500,000 and <lb/>
               $600,000 on the duties on herrings and mackerel which had <lb/>
               been sent to the United States. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para " peace was
               contradicted most emphatically by the despatches of 
 ..." merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p> He (Mr. Jones) held
               in his hand the trade and navigation returns <lb/>
               for the past year, which he presumed were tolerably accurate. He <lb/>
               found from this document that the total amount of pickled ﬁsh-<lb break="yes"/>
               herring and mackerel and alewives-sent
               into the United <lb/>
               States last year was 47,000 barrels, which, at $2 a barrel, <lb/>
               would be $94,000, instead of $600,000 as claimed by the hon. <lb/>
               gentleman opposite. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear.</hi>) <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The hon. President of
               Council (Hon. Mr. Tupper) also stated <lb/>
               that the treaty of 1854 was a great boon. Well, no one denied <lb/>
               that; but contrast that treaty with the present treaty. Under the <lb/>
               former one, agricultural products, our coal and lumber, were <lb/>
               admitted free of duty into the United States. How different <lb/>
               was this from the present treaty! The same hon. gentleman <lb/>
               stated as one reason why this Treaty must be a good one for us <lb/>
               that the American ﬁshermen were opposed to it. The hon. <lb/>
               member for Durham West (Hon. Mr. Blake), the other night, <lb/>
               speaking on this point had hit the nail on the head. He stated <lb/>
               that the reason why American ﬁshermen opposed the Treaty <lb/>
               was that Gen. Butler had gone down to Gloucester and <lb/>
               harangued them, telling them that now was their time to wrest <lb/>
               from Congress what they had long wanted, namely, a system <lb/>
               of bounties and the bonding of their supplies. That was the <lb/>
               sole course of their outcry against the Treaty, and the Minister <lb/>
               of Justice (Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald) knew it very well, <lb/>
               and he (Mr. Jones) had grave apprehensions that such a policy <lb/>
               would be adopted by Congress. Of course they would not do <lb/>
               so while the Treaty was pending but when this Parliament <lb/>
               accepted the Treaty then would be their time to grant bounties <lb/>
               to their ﬁshermen, and to allow the bonding of their
               supplies. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The President of the
               Privy Council (Hon. Mr. Tupper) had <lb/>
               contended that the admission of American ﬁshermen into our <lb/>
               waters would not destroy the value of our ﬁsheries, but the <lb/>
               reports of the Minister of Marine and Fisheries (Hon. Senator <lb/>
               Mitchell) had told a different story. He gave the value of the <lb/>
               ﬁsheries before and during the Reciprocity Treaty, and
               showed <lb/>
               
               <milestone type="day"/> 233 <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para " 233 
               
            ..." merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p> conclusively that if
               we had adopted an exclusive policy after <lb/>
               the abrogation of the treaty, we would now have had control of <lb/>
               the American markets. The House was told that the arbitrators <lb/>
               appointed to decide upon the relative value of our ﬁsheries <lb/>
               and the American fisheries would pay us what we lost in <lb/>
               giving up our ﬁsheries; but the very
               ﬁrst question that would <lb/>
               have to be decided before they could estimate the relative <lb/>
               value was where were they to draw the boundary line of our <lb/>
               ﬁsheries, whether from headland to headland, or along the <lb/>
               coast? lfthe former, of course our ﬁsheries would be greatly
               <lb/>
               increased in value; but how were the arbitrators to decide? It <lb/>
               was, therefore, of the very greatest importance that the High <lb/>
               Joint Commissioners should have settled deﬁnitely the <lb/>
               question of headlands, so that the arbitrators would have had a <lb/>
               basis on which to make their valuation. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The hon. gentlemen
               opposite, particularly the Premier, had <lb/>
               stated that the American markets were the only markets we <lb/>
               had for our ﬁsh. He had not had the pleasure of listening to
               the <lb/>
               speech of his colleague from Halifax (Mr. Power); but he <lb/>
               understood that gentleman had given some ﬁgures to show <lb/>
               that a large portion of our ﬁsh was sent to the United
               States. <lb/>
               He was not aware from what source that gentleman drew his <lb/>
               information, but he felt it his duty to be as correct as possible <lb/>
               and he had taken the trouble to consult the public documents <lb/>
               for 1862, 63, 64 under the Reciprocity Treaty, and also after <lb/>
               that Treaty in 1869, 70, 71, when the United States imposed <lb/>
               duty on our ﬁsh. He found that under the Reciprocity Treaty <lb/>
               only about 7 per cent more of our ﬁsh went to the United <lb/>
               States than when the duty was imposed. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The American
               ﬁshermen stood in a very different position <lb/>
               from our ﬁshermen in many respects. 1n the ﬁrst
               place they <lb/>
               had larger and better vessels, larger outfits, larger capital, and <lb/>
               they had in operation a system of mutual insurances. They had <lb/>
               the additional advantage of being able to fish all the year <lb/>
               round. Our fishermen ﬁshed in the early part of the year
               only; <lb/>
               but, after the mackerel ﬁshing was over in the fall, the <lb/>
               American ﬁshermen went off to the banks, and caught halibut <lb/>
               and other fish, which our fishermen could not do. He would <lb/>
               tell the hon. gentleman why. lf he were to send his vessel there <lb/>
               he would have to sell his cargo wholesale, and would not be <lb/>
               able to pay the expense of taking it to market. But those <lb/>
               people had a market at their own doors. The American <lb/>
               ﬁshermen thus had the advantage over ours. They were able to
               <lb/>
               earn during the winter season what would pay their expenses <lb/>
               all the year round, and that was a very important <lb/>
               consideration. The hon. gentleman had referred to the position <lb/>
               of the American markets during that time. Within the last two <lb/>
               years so great had been the increase of American ﬁshermen, <lb/>
               since the war, since they had gone back and engaged in old <lb/>
               pursuits, that ﬁsh had been cheaper in Boston than Halifax, <lb/>
               and there had been large imports from Boston, and the West <lb/>
               Indies markets had been trading from Boston instead of <lb/>
               Halifax. 1f the hon. gentleman understood the matter as he did <lb/>
               he would see those people would come with better appliances <lb/>
               
               <pb n="234" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_234.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">COMMONS</fw>
               <fw type="running">DEBATES</fw>
               <fw type="num">234</fw> and they would
               compete with us as they had during the last <lb/>
               two years in the markets of the West Indies. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para " and they would
               compete with us as they had during the last 
    ..." merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p> If under his views we
               would gain a triﬂe in the American <lb/>
               market-even
               supposing such things were correct, which he <lb/>
               contended were not-we
               would more than lose the advantage <lb/>
               in our trade with other countries. We had exported last year <lb/>
               163,000 barrels of pickled ﬁsh, only 45,000 of which went to
               <lb/>
               the United States; and if American ﬁshermen competed with <lb/>
               us they would send their ﬁsh to the West Indies and decrease
               <lb/>
               the price more in proportion than what the hon. gentleman <lb/>
               claimed we would gain by having their markets. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> It was said our
               fishermen were in favour of the Treaty. He <lb/>
               denied it. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear.</hi>) Many of them were, but he utterly <lb/>
               denied that the majority of the people ofNova Scotia favoured <lb/>
               it. He did not mean to say that every man who was in favour of <lb/>
               it was an annexationist, but he did assert that every man in <lb/>
               Nova Scotia who was an annexationist and looked forward to <lb/>
               early political connection with the States was in favour of it. <lb/>
               (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear</hi>). And they were right enough from their point of <lb/>
               view, because they argued, if you give those people the water <lb/>
               they will soon own the land. If our ﬁshermen were not so <lb/>
               much opposed to the Treaty as he thought they ought to be it <lb/>
               was because of the argument of hon. gentlemen opposite, to <lb/>
               the effect “in the interest of the empire;” and
               “England would <lb/>
               not protect us;” and “we had better take a loaf
               than no bread;” <lb/>
               and that if they did not accept this emasculated arrangement, <lb/>
               which just condemns themselves, the Americans would get the <lb/>
               whole-those
               were the circumstances under which these men <lb/>
               were not all satisﬁed. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> But ﬁsh
               was not all Nova Scotia produced. She had great <lb/>
               mineral wealth, and her coal interest was of even greater <lb/>
               importance than her fisheries, yet this had been entirely <lb/>
               overlooked. Those interested in the case said and with very <lb/>
               great force, that if the Government had been earnestly desirous <lb/>
               of reducing the duty on coal, they would have avoided the <lb/>
               seizures which they made during last year. From the moment <lb/>
               the schooner Horton was recaptured by the Americans and <lb/>
               towed into Gloucester, whatever chance existed for the <lb/>
               reduction of the duty on coal and lumber was lost. The hon. <lb/>
               gentlemen opposite and the Minister of Justice especially had <lb/>
               asked hon. members not to put troublesome questions, not to <lb/>
               suggest doubts with reference to the Treaty; yet the hon. <lb/>
               member for Peel (Hon. Mr. Cameron) in his brilliant address <lb/>
               had left an impression on the House that Americans almost <lb/>
               had a right to the Fisheries, because they had enjoyed them for <lb/>
               17 years longer than they had been excluded from them. He <lb/>
               (Mr. Jones) took a directly opposite view of the question. His <lb/>
               colleague referred last night to one argument in favour of the <lb/>
               Treaty, that trade to Cuba would be injured by its annexation <lb/>
               to the United States. The hon. gentleman should know that we <lb/>
               are obliged to pay a duty on goods exported to that island, <lb/>
               double that on the same goods exported to the United States: <lb/>
               
               <milestone type="day"/> May 14, 1872 <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para " May 14, 1872 
               
            ..." merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p> therefore trade would
               hardly be injured by the annexation of <lb/>
               the island. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The hon. member for
               Lanark North (Hon. Mr. McDougall) <lb/>
               had referred to the fact that Prince Edward Island and <lb/>
               Newfoundland had accepted the Treaty; and New Brunswick <lb/>
               and Nova Scotia had not apparently been very warmly <lb/>
               opposed to it. The hon. gentleman had also sought to create <lb/>
               the impression that the Government of New Brunswick were <lb/>
               acting in concert with the Clear Grit party when they took the <lb/>
               step they did in communicating with the Government of Nova <lb/>
               Scotia on the subject. The resolution of the New Brunswick <lb/>
               Legislature was passed on the 18th February, while the High <lb/>
               Commission was sitting, and when it was thought that the <lb/>
               opinion of the Legislature would strengthen the hands of those <lb/>
               who had charge of our interests; they accordingly telegraphed <lb/>
               to Newfoundland, and as the latter had no interest but the <lb/>
               ﬁshing interest to consider, they replied that they were
               well <lb/>
               satisﬁed to leave the matter to England, for the reason that
               she <lb/>
               had left them to exercise their own discretion and free will on <lb/>
               the subject of entering the Confederation or not. That was a <lb/>
               very good reason for Newfoundland, because she had been <lb/>
               accorded a privilege which had been denied Nova Scotia. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> He might here remark,
               as an instance of the singular <lb/>
               inaccuracies and want of information which characterized the <lb/>
               whole negotiation, that the important interest of seal
               ﬁshing <lb/>
               had been entirely unprovided for in the Treaty. The Governor <lb/>
               of Newfoundland made a communication to Earl Kimberley, <lb/>
               enclosing a copy of a minute of the Council of the Local <lb/>
               Government on the subject. That minute of the Council was <lb/>
               not among the papers submitted to the House. The reply of the <lb/>
               Government of Prince Edward Island was worthy of attention, <lb/>
               because they occupied a position precisely similar to that of <lb/>
               Nova Scotia. The people of Prince Edward Island had valuable <lb/>
               ﬁsheries, but they said they were in the hands of the <lb/>
               Americans already; and the agricultural product of that Island <lb/>
               far exceeded the value of the ﬁsheries. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The people of Prince
               Edward Island had precisely the same <lb/>
               interest in the ﬁsheries as we had, but they were willing
               for <lb/>
               Imperial interests alone to agree to what was asked of them by <lb/>
               the Government of England. The people of Prince Edward <lb/>
               Island did not adopt the policy of the Canadian Government <lb/>
               and say, “Give us so much money for our rights and we will <lb/>
               ratify the Treaty.” (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Applause.</hi>) No; they took a
               higher and <lb/>
               more manly and national view of the case; and pursued a <lb/>
               course which contrasted most favourably with that pursued by <lb/>
               the Canadian Government. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Applause.</hi>) The people of Prince <lb/>
               Edward Island were not willing to put their loyalty into the <lb/>
               English market and have it quoted at any ﬁgure. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear,
               hear.</hi>) <lb/>
               On the contrary, they were willing to make a sacriﬁce for
               the <lb/>
               Empire, though the Treaty did not give their agricultural <lb/>
               interests the market in the United States which they had under <lb/>
               the Reciprocity Treaty. A minute of Council, dated July 25, <lb/>
               1871, from the Lieut. Governor of Prince Edward Island to <lb/>
               
               <pb n="235" facs="final/images/PEI_H_of_C_18720514_Page_235.jpg"/>
               <fw type="num">COMMONS</fw>
               <fw type="running">DEBATES</fw>
               <fw type="dateline"> May 14, 1872 <lb/>
               
               </fw> Lord Kimberley, would
               show the position in which that Island <lb/>
               stood, as follows:-“It
               is stated in the minute that the different <lb/>
               Governments and Legislatures of this Colony have always <lb/>
               hoped that these ﬁsheries (the fisheries of Prince Edward <lb/>
               Island) would have done much to secure the advantages of <lb/>
               another Reciprocity Treaty, or of some tariff concessions <lb/>
               authorize the free admission into the United States of the <lb/>
               products of our agriculturists, who form the majority of our <lb/>
               population, and which would have resulted in promoting the <lb/>
               prosperity of the Colony; and that, in the opinion of this <lb/>
               Council, the inhabitants of Prince Edward Island are now <lb/>
               asked to surrender to the citizens of the United States these <lb/>
               invaluable fisheries without receiving in return any just or fair <lb/>
               equivalent, such as was hoped to be obtained.” <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->   <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para " Lord Kimberley, would
               show the position in which that Island 
  ..." merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p> The people of New
               Brunswick from the ﬁrst had been <lb/>
               entirely opposed to the Treaty, and the Legislature of that <lb/>
               Province, as well as the Lieut. Governor, had spoken of it in <lb/>
               the strongest terms of denunciation. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear.</hi>) The people <lb/>
               of New Brunswick, Prince Edward Island, and Newfoundland <lb/>
               did not accept the Treaty in the spirit in which this House was <lb/>
               asked to accept it. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear.</hi>) <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Under those
               circumstances he felt as a representative of <lb/>
               Nova Scotia, that, however anxious he might be for the <lb/>
               establishment of reciprocal trade relations with the States on <lb/>
               fair terms, he was not willing to give the United States <lb/>
               everything that we had to offer as an inducement for <lb/>
               reciprocity. If we gave them permission to ﬁsh in our waters
               <lb/>
               
               <milestone type="day"/> 235 <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <!--Milestone merged into previous para.-->
            
            <!--Para " 235 
               
            ..." merged into previous para.-->
            
         
            
            <p> we put them in
               competition with our own ﬁshermen, and <lb/>
               reduced the value of the ﬁsh. He stood here not to represent
               <lb/>
               one country or one province, but the whole interests of the <lb/>
               Dominion, (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Hear, hear</hi>) and in that capacity he would feel it <lb/>
               his duty to vote against the ratiﬁcation of the treaty. <lb/>
               (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Applause.</hi>) He denied that this treaty was calculated to settle <lb/>
               all disputes between Great Britain and the United States, and he <lb/>
               said that, if trouble arose at the present time between England and <lb/>
               America, the latter would not ratify the treaty, and if we pressed it <lb/>
               we would receive a snubbing for our pains. In the interest of the <lb/>
               Dominion, and in the interest of all its products, he considered it <lb/>
               would not be for our advantage to ratify the treaty at the present <lb/>
               time. (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Applause.</hi>) <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Mr. KILLAM would vote
               for the ﬁshery clauses of the Treaty; <lb/>
               and thought that a majority of the representatives of Nova Scotia <lb/>
               would favour its ratiﬁcation as the best means of securing
               peace <lb/>
               between the two countries. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Mr. HOLTON moved
               the adjournment of the debate. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> Hon. Sir JOHN A.
               MACDONALD would not oppose the <lb/>
               motion, coming as it did from so distinguished a member of the <lb/>
               House as the hon. member for Châteauguay; but he hoped that the <lb/>
               debate, which had now lasted some days, would terminate to<lb break="no"/>morrow, and wished that it should stand ﬁrst on the orders
               of the <lb/>
               day. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The House adjourned
               at 11.50. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
