<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="treaty_11"
     type="full">
<teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreaty">Treaty Document(s)</name>, <date when="1921-06-27">27 June 1907</date>, Treaty No. 11 and Adhesion (July 17, 1922) with Reports, etc..</title>
        

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName></respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion from HTML to TEI</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLM3">Martin Holmes</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">LAYOUT IS NOT EXACTLY LIKE ORIGINAL</hi></p>
<p>Reprinted from the edition of 1907</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <title>Treaty No. 11</title>.
                    

          <date when="1957"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Edmund Cloutier, c.m.g., o.a., d.s.p. Queen's Printer and Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          
  <orgName>
               
                  <orgName xml:lang="en">Indigenous and Northern Affairs Canada</orgName>
               </orgName>
        
        </bibl>
 

            <list>
               <item>
           <ptr target="https://www.aadnc-aandc.gc.ca/eng/1100100028916/1100100028947"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-11-21">Transformed original HTML to TEI.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treaty">
            
                       <head>REPORT OF THE COMMISSIONER FOR TREATY No. 11</head>
         

                     <p>OTTAWA, October 12, 1921.</p>
              

                  <p>D. C. Scott, Esq.,<lb/>
Deputy Superintendent General,<lb/>
Department of Indian Affairs,<lb/>
Ottawa.</p>
                  <p>SIR,--I have the honour to submit herewith the report on treaty
made by me on authority granted by Order in Council, dated March
14, last, as Commissioner to negotiate a treaty with the Indians
occupying the territory north of the 60th parallel and along the
Mackenzie river and the Arctic ocean.</p>
                  <p>I left Edmonton on June 8, 1921, accompanied by Inspector W. B.
Bruce, Constable Wood and Constable Campbell, of the Royal Canadian
Mounted Police. Constable Campbell acted as my clerk for the
summer.</p>
                  <p>Arriving at Fort McMurray on June 11, we left there on the 14th
in a houseboat, the property of the Hudson's Bay Company, which
company had made all arrangements for the transportation of the
treaty party during the summer in the North.</p>
                  <p>We arrived at Fort Fitzgerald on June 18, crossed the portage to
Fort Smith, and boarded the ss. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mackenzie River</hi> on June 20
for Fort Providence, at which place the first adhesion to Treaty 11
was to be taken. July 5 was the date set for the meeting of the
Indians and myself to take place at Fort Providence, and, in order
to arrive in good time, I thought it better for me and my party to
proceed there by the ss. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mackenzie River</hi>, and let the
houseboat take us up again at this point. The transportation of the
houseboat across the portage at Fort Smith took several days.</p>
                  <p>On our arrival at Fort Providence, on June 20, I found the
Indians were not at the post, as we were there before the date set
for the meeting, so word was sent of my arrival, and the majority
of the Providence Indians living at Willow Lake arrived on June 25,
those at Trout Lake not till July 2. I had several meetings with
them, and explained the terms of treaty. They were very apt in
asking questions, and here, as in all the other posts where the
treaty was signed, the questions asked and the difficulties
encountered were much the same. The Indians seemed afraid, for one
thing, that their liberty to hunt, trap and fish would be taken
away or curtailed, but were assured by me that this would not be
the case, and the Government will expect them to support themselves
in their own way, and, in fact, that more twine for nets and more
ammunition were given under the terms of this treaty than under any
of the preceding ones; this went a long way to calm their fears. I
also pointed out that any game laws made were to their advantage,
and, whether they took treaty or not, they were subject to the laws
of the Dominion. They also seemed afraid that they would be liable
for military service if the treaty was signed, that they would be
confined on the reserves, but, when told that they were exempt from
military service, and that the reserves mentioned in the treaty
would be of their own choosing, for their own use, and not for the
white people, and that they would be free to come and go as they
pleased, they were satisfied.</p>
                  <p>Practically all the bands dealt with wanted more provision for
medical attendance at each post, schools for their children, and
supplies for their old and destitute.</p>
                  <p>I pointed out that they were still able to make their own
living, and that Dr. A. L. McDonald, of the Indian Department, was
then with me, and that they could see him, and that he would attend
them free if they wished, but that it was impossible for the
Government to furnish regular medical attention, when they were
occupying such a vast tract of territory. Schools were already
established, and their children receiving free education, and
supplies were left at each point for the sick and destitute.</p>
                  <p>The treaty was signed at Fort Providence on June 27, and the
following were paid:--</p>
             
                     <p>1 Chief,<lb/>
2 Headmen, and<lb/>
255 others.</p>
                  
                  <p>Our houseboat arrived on July 5, and we left Providence for Fort
Simpson on the 7th, securing adhesion to the treaty there on July
11.</p>
               
                     <p>1 Chief,<lb/>
2 Headmen, and<lb/>
344 other Indians were paid.</p>
                  
                  <p>Adhesions to the treaty were obtained at Fort Wrigley on July
13.</p>
                 
                     <p>1 Headman, and<lb/>
77 others were paid.<lb/>
                     </p>
                  
                  <p>At Fort Norman on July 15,--</p>
                
                     <p>1 Chief,<lb/>
2 Headmen, and<lb/>
205 others were paid.</p>
                  
                  <p>At Good Hope, July 21,--</p>
                
                     <p>1 Chief,<lb/>
1 Headman, and<lb/>
208 others were paid.</p>
                  
                  <p>At Arctic Red River on July 26,--</p>
               
                     <p>1 Chief,<lb/>
1 Headman, and<lb/>
169 others were paid.</p>
                  
                  <p>At Fort McPherson on July 28,--</p>
                 
                     <p>1 Chief,<lb/>
1 Headman, and<lb/>
217 others were paid.</p>
                  
                  <p>At Fort Rae on August 22,--</p>
             
                     <p>1 Chief<lb/>
2 Headmen, and<lb/>
440 others were paid.</p>
                  
                  <p>Practically all the Indians were dealt with at Fort Providence,
Simpson, Wrigley, Arctic Red River and McPherson, and about 65 per
cent at Fort Norman, Fort Good Hope and Rae, the remainder of these
Indians having been at these posts in the spring and left word that
they were willing to take treaty, but had to return to their
hunting grounds for their summer's work.</p>
                  <p>At Fort Rae is the largest band of Indians, about 800, and this
is the most inaccessible, being on the arm of Great Slave lake,
difficulty in crossing this lake being experienced, more especially
in the late summer and fall on account of storms, our party being
stormbound at Hay River for five days prior to crossing. These
Indians hunt in every direction from the fort, some as far as 200
miles, and only come to the post in spring to trade their furs, so
that, in future, I would suggest that this be the first post
visited when making payments.</p>
                  <p>We crossed the lake from Hay River to Rae in the Hudson Bay
schooner <hi rendition="simple:italic">Fort Rae</hi>, leaving our houseboat to take us up at
Resolution, from which place we went on August 25, arriving at Fort
Smith on August 30, Fort McMurray and Edmonton in September.</p>
                  <p>I much regret that I was unable, owing to the lack of time, to
visit Fort Liard, and secure adhesion to the treaty by the Indians
at that point, although they had sent word to Fort Simpson of their
willingness to accept the same. I considered it advisable to
proceed to Great Slave Lake, and cross to Fort Rae at the first
opportunity, as the season was getting late.</p>
                  <p>Dr. A. L. McDonald joined the party at Fort Providence, and
accompanied it to Good Hope, at that place having to return to Fort
Resolution on account of smallpox having been reported, which
report, fortunately, proved untrue. He joined the party again at
Hay River, and remained with it until arrival at his headquarters
at Fort Smith.</p>
                  <p>I was very glad to be accompanied by His Lordship Bishop
Breynat, O.M.I., who has considerable influence with the Indians in
the North, and would like here to express my appreciation of the
help and hospitality accorded to me and my party in his missions,
and I desire also to express my appreciation of the services
rendered by Inspector Bruce, of the Royal Canadian Mounted Police,
and by his party. Constables Woods and Campbell performed their
duties in the most creditable manner.</p>
        
<table>
<row><cell>The actual number of Indians paid was:-</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>7 Chiefs at $32 each<lb/>
12 Headmen at $22 each</cell><cell>.......................$</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">488</cell></row>
<row><cell>and 1,915 Indians at $12 each</cell><cell>.........................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$22,980</cell></row>
</table>


                  <p><persName ref="pers:CONR3">H. A. CONROY</persName>,<lb/>
                     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner, Treaty No. 11</hi>.</p>

  <div type="section">

<head>TREATY NUMBER ELEVEN</head>


                  <p>ARTICLES OF A TREATY made and concluded on the several dates
mentioned therein in the year of Our Lord One thousand Nine hundred
and Twenty-One, between His Most Gracious Majesty George V, King of
Great Britain and Ireland and of the British Dominions beyond the
Seas, by His Commissioner, Henry Anthony Conroy, Esquire, of the
City of Ottawa, of the One Part, and the Slave, Dogrib, Loucheux,
Hare and other Indians, inhabitants of the territory within the
limits hereinafter defined and described, by their Chiefs and
Headmen, hereunto subscribed, of the other part:--</p>
                  <p>WHEREAS, the Indians inhabiting the territory hereinafter
defined have been convened to meet a commissioner representing His
Majesty's Government of the Dominion of Canada at certain places in
the said territory in this present year of 1921, to deliberate upon
certain matters of interest to His Most Gracious Majesty, of the
one part, and the said Indians of the other.</p>
                  <p>AND WHEREAS, the said Indians have been notified and informed by
His Majesty's said commissioner that it is His desire to open for
settlement, immigration, trade, travel, mining, lumbering and such
other purposes as to His Majesty may seem meet, a tract of country
bounded and described as hereinafter set forth, and to obtain the
consent thereto of His Indian subjects inhabiting the said tract,
and to make a treaty, so that there may be peace and good-will
between them and His Majesty's other subjects, and that His Indian
people may know and be assured of what allowances they are to
expect and receive from His Majesty's bounty and benevolence.</p>
                  <p>AND WHEREAS, the Indians of the said tract, duly convened in
council at the respective points named hereunder, and being
requested by His Majesty's Commissioner, to name certain Chiefs and
Headmen, who should be authorized on their behalf to conduct such
negotiations and sign any treaty to be founded thereon, and to
become responsible to His Majesty for the faithful performance by
their respective bands of such obligations as shall be assumed by
them, the said Indians have therefore acknowledged for that purpose
the several chiefs and Headmen who have subscribed thereto.</p>
                  <p>AND WHEREAS the said Commissioner has proceeded to negotiate a
treaty with the Slave, Dogrib, Loucheux, Hare and other Indians
inhabiting the district hereinafter defined and described, which
has been agreed upon and concluded by the respective bands at the
dates mentioned hereunder, the said Indians do hereby cede,
release, surrender and yield up to the Government of the Dominion
of Canada, for His Majesty the King and His Successors forever, all
their rights, titles, and privileges whatsoever to the lands
included within the following limits, that is to say:</p>
                  <p>Commencing at the northwesterly corner of the territory ceded
under the provisions of Treaty Number Eight; thence northeasterly
along the height-of-land to the point where it intersects the
boundary between the Yukon Territory and the Northwest Territories;
thence northwesterly along the said boundary to the shore of the
Arctic ocean; thence easterly along the said shore to the mouth of
the Coppermine river; thence southerly and southeasterly along the
left bank of said river to Lake Gras by way of Point lake; thence
along the southern shore of Lake Gras to a point situated northwest
of the most western extremity of Aylmer lake; thence along the
southern shore of Aylmer lake and following the right bank of the
Lockhart river to Artillery lake; thence along the western shore of
Artillery lake and following the right bank of the Lockhart river
to the site of Old Fort Reliance where the said river enters Great
Slave lake, this being the northeastern corner of the territory
ceded under the provisions of Treaty Number Eight; thence westerly
along the northern boundary of the said territory so ceded to the
point of commencement; comprising an area of approximately three
hundred and seventy-two thousand square miles.</p>
                  <p>AND ALSO, the said Indian rights, titles and privileges
whatsoever to all other lands wherever situated in the Yukon
Territory, the Northwest Territories or in any other portion of the
Dominion of Canada.</p>
                  <p>To have and to hold the same to His Majesty the King and His
Successors forever.</p>
                  <p>AND His Majesty the King hereby agrees with the said Indians
that they shall have the right to pursue their usual vocations of
hunting, trapping and fishing throughout the tract surrendered as
heretofore described, subject to such regulations as may from time
to time be made by the Government of the Country acting under the
authority of His Majesty, and saving and excepting such tracts as
may be required or taken up from time to time for settlement,
mining, lumbering, trading or other purposes.</p>
                  <p>AND His Majesty the King hereby agrees and undertakes to lay
aside reserves for each band, the same not to exceed in all one
square mile for each family of five, or in that proportion for
larger or smaller families;</p>
                  <p>PROVIDED, however, that His Majesty reserves the right to deal
with any settlers within the boundaries of any lands reserved for
any band as He may see fit; and also that the aforesaid reserves of
land, or any interest therein, may be sold or otherwise disposed of
by His Majesty's Government for the use and benefit of the said
Indians entitled thereto, with their consent first had and
obtained; but in no wise shall the said Indians, or any of them, be
entitled to sell or otherwise alienate any of the lands allotted to
them as reserves.</p>
                  <p>It is further agreed between His Majesty and His Indian subjects
that such portions of the reserves and lands above indicated as may
at any time be required for public works, buildings, railways, or
roads of whatsoever nature may be appropriated for that purpose by
His Majesty's Government of the Dominion of Canada, due
compensation being made to the Indians for the value of any
improvements thereon, and an equivalent in land, money or other
consideration for the area of the reserve so appropriated.</p>
                  <p>And in order to show the satisfaction of His Majesty with the
behaviour and good conduct of His Indian subjects, and in
extinguishment of all their past claims hereinabove mentioned, He
hereby, through his Commissioner, agrees to give to each Chief a
present of thirty-two dollars in cash, to each Headman, twenty-two
dollars, and to every other Indian of whatever age of the families
represented, at the time and place of payment, twelve dollars.</p>
                  <p>HIS MAJESTY, also agrees that during the coming year, and
annually thereafter, He will cause to be paid to the said Indians
in cash, at suitable places and dates, of which the said Indians
shall be duly notified, to each Chief twenty-five dollars, to each
Headman fifteen dollars, and to every other Indian of whatever age
five dollars, to be paid only to heads of families for the members
thereof, it being provided for the purposes of this Treaty that
each band having at least thirty members may have a Chief, and that
in addition to a Chief, each band may have Councillors or Headmen
in the proportion of two to each two hundred members of the
band.</p>
                  <p>FURTHER, His Majesty agrees that each Chief shall receive once
and for all a silver medal, a suitable flag and a copy of this
Treaty for the use of his band; and during the coming year, and
every third year thereafter, each Chief and Headman shall receive a
suitable suit of clothing.</p>
                  <p>FURTHER, His Majesty agrees to pay the salaries of teachers to
instruct the children of said Indians in such manner as His
Majesty's Government may deem advisable.</p>
                  <p>FURTHER, His Majesty agrees to supply once and for all to each
Chief of a band that selects a reserve, ten axes, five hand-saws,
five augers, one grindstone, and the necessary files and whetstones
for the use of the band.</p>
                  <p>FURTHER, His Majesty agrees that, each band shall receive once
and for all equipment for hunting, fishing and trapping to the
value of fifty dollars for each family of such band, and that there
shall be distributed annually among the Indians equipment, such as
twine for nets, ammunition and trapping to the value of three
dollars per head for each Indian who continues to follow the
vocation of hunting, fishing and trapping.</p>
                  <p>FURTHER, His Majesty agrees that, in the event of any of the
Indians aforesaid being desirous of following agricultural
pursuits, such Indians shall receive such assistance as is deemed
necessary for that purpose.</p>
                  <p>AND the undersigned Slave, Dogrib, Loucheux, Hare and other
Chiefs and Headmen, on their own behalf and on behalf of all the
Indians whom they represent, do hereby solemnly promise and engage
to strictly observe this Treaty, and also to conduct and behave
themselves as good loyal subjects of His Majesty the King.</p>
                  <p>THEY promise and engage that they will, in all respects, obey
and abide by the law; that they will maintain peace between
themselves and others of His Majesty's subjects, whether Indians,
half-breeds or whites, now inhabiting and hereafter to inhabit any
part of the said ceded territory; that they will not molest the
person or property of any inhabitant of such ceded tract, or of any
other district or country, or interfere with, or trouble any person
passing or travelling through the said tract or any part thereof,
and that they will assist the officers of His Majesty in bringing
to justice and punishment any Indian offending against the
stipulations of this Treaty, or infringing the law in force in the
country so ceded.</p>
                  <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, His Majesty's said Commissioner and the said
Chiefs and Headmen have hereunto set their hands at the places and
times set forth in the year herein first above written.</p>
                  <p>SIGNED AT PROVIDENCE on the twenty-seventh day of June, 1921, by
His Majesty's Commissioner and the Chiefs and Headmen in the
presence of the undersigned witnesses, after having been first
interpreted and explained.</p>
                

                <p>Witnesses:</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BRUC3">W.V. BRUCE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Insp. R.C.M.P.</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:KITT2">F.H. KITTO</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MILL6">A.H. MILLER</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BREY1">G. BREYNANT</persName>, O.M.I., <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bishop of Adr.,<lb/>
Vic. Apost. of Mackenzie</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BALS1">J.A.R. BALSILLIE</persName>.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:CONR3">H.A. CONROY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Comm</hi>.
</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:LAFO2">PAUL LAFOIN</persName> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief</hi>, his x mark.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:FRAN2">HARRY FRANCIS</persName> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, his x mark.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:SABO1">BAPTISTE SABOURINE</persName> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, his x mark.</p>





                  <p>SIGNED at Simpson on the eleventh day of July, 1921, by His
Majesty's Commissioner and the Chiefs and Headmen in the presence
of the undersigned witnesses, after having been first interpreted
and explained.</p>
               

    <p>Witnesses:<lb/>
(Sgd.)</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BREY1">G. BREYNANT</persName>, O.M.I., <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bishop of Adr.,<lb/>
Vic. Apost. of Mackenzie</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CORR1">JOHN G. CORRY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BRUC3">W.V. BRUCE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Insp. R.C.M.P.</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CAMS1">A.F. CAMSELL</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HARR7">T.W. HARRIS</persName>.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:CONR3">H.A. CONROY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Comm</hi>.
</p>

<p>( <persName ref="pers:ANTO1">ANTOINE</persName>) [indigenous characters]</p>

<p>( <persName ref="pers:KORW1">KORWERGEN</persName>) [indigenous characters]</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BEDS1">BEDSEDIA</persName> his x mark</p>

                  <p>SIGNED at Wrigley on the thirteenth day of July, 1921, by His
Majesty's Commissioner and the Chiefs and Headmen in presence of
the undersigned witnesses, after having been first interpreted and
explained.</p>
             
    <p>Witnesses:<lb/>
(Sgd.)</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BREY1">G. BREYNANT</persName>, O.M.I., <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bishop of Adr.,<lb/>
Vic. Apost. of Mackenzie</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BRUC3">W.V. BRUCE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Insp. R.C.M.P.</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCDO20">A.L. McDONALD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BACO1">F.H. BACON</persName>.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:CONR3">H.A. CONROY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Comm</hi>.
</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:YEND1">Yendo</persName> [indigenous characters]</p>


                  <p>SIGNED at Norman on the fifteenth day of July, 1921, by His
Majesty's Commissioner and the Chiefs and Headmen in the presence
of the undersigned witnesses, after having been first interpreted
and explained.</p>
              
    <p>Witnesses:<lb/>
(Sgd.)</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BREY1">G. BREYNANT</persName>, O.M.I., <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bishop of Adr.,<lb/>
Vic. Apost. of Mackenzie</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BRUC3">W.V. BRUCE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Insp. R.C.M.P.</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:JOHN8">GEO. P. JOHNSTON</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CAMP6">G.H.M. CAMPBELL</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Const. R.C.M.P.</hi></p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:CONR3">H.A. CONROY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Comm</hi>.
</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:WRIG7">ALBERT WRIGHT</persName>,</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BLON1">SAUL BLONDIN</persName> his x mark</p>



                  <p>SIGNED at Good Hope on the twenty-first day of July, 1921, by
His Majesty's Commissioner and the Chiefs and Headmen in the
presence of the undersigned witnesses, after having been first
interpreted and explained.</p>
                
    <p>Witnesses:<lb/>
(Sgd.)</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BREY1">G. BREYNANT</persName>, O.M.I., <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bishop of Adr.,<lb/>
Vic. Apost. of Mackenzie</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BRUC3">W.V. BRUCE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Insp. R.C.M.P.</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BACO1">F.H. BACON</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BRAS2">J.H. BRASHAR</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Cpl. R.C.M.P.</hi></p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:CONR3">H.A. CONROY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Comm</hi>.
</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:SIME1">SIMEON</persName> his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:NATE1">FRANCOIS NATEGAL</persName> his x mark</p>


                  <p>SIGNED at Arctic Red River on the twenty-sixth day of July,
1921, by His Majesty's Commissioner and the Chiefs and Headmen in
the presence of the undersigned witnesses, after having been first
interpreted and explained.</p>
             
    <p>Witnesses:<lb/>
(Sgd.)</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BREY1">G. BREYNANT</persName>, O.M.I., <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bishop of Adr.,<lb/>
Vic. Apost. of Mackenzie</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BRUC3">W.V. BRUCE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Insp. R.C.M.P.</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LECU1">J. LECUYER</persName>, Pr. O.M.I.,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:PARS3">J. PARSONS</persName>.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:CONR3">H.A. CONROY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Comm</hi>.
</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:PAUL1">PAUL</persName> his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:NIDE1">NIDE APHI</persName>,</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:FABI1">FABIEN-LALOO</persName>.</p>


                  <p>SIGNED at McPherson on the twenty-eighth day of July, 1921, by
His Majesty's Commissioner and the Chiefs and Headmen in the
presence of the undersigned witnesses, after having been first
interpreted and explained.</p>
        
    <p>Witnesses:<lb/>
(Sgd.)</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:BRUC3">W.V. BRUCE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Insp. R.C.M.P.</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:PARS3">J. PARSONS</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BACO1">F.H. BACON</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FIRT1">JAMES FIRTH</persName>.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:CONR3">H.A. CONROY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Comm</hi>.
</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:LALO3">JABY LALO</persName>,</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KIKA1">JOHNNIE KIKAWCHIK</persName>.</p>


                  <p>SIGNED at Liard on the day of, 1921, by His Majesty's
Commissioners and the Chiefs and Headmen in the presence of the
undersigned witnesses, after having been first interpreted and
explained.</p>

   <p>Witnesses:</p>
  
                  <p>SIGNED at Rae on the twenty-second day of August, 1921, by His
Majesty's Commissioner and the Chiefs and Headmen in the presence
of undersigned witnesses, after having been first interpreted and
explained.</p>


    <p>Witnesses:<lb/>
(Sgd.)</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BREY1">G. BREYNANT</persName>, O.M.I., <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bishop of Adr.,<lb/>
Vic. Apost. of Mackenzie</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ODON2">W.J. O'DONNELL</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BRUC3">W.V. BRUCE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Insp. R.C.M.P.</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HERO1">ED. HERON</persName>, H.B. Co.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LAFO3">CLAUDE Wm. LAFOUNTAIN</persName>.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:CONR3">H.A. CONROY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Comm</hi>.
</p>


<p><persName ref="pers:MORP1">MORPHY</persName> his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:JERM1">JERMAIN</persName> his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BEAU7">JOSUE BEAULIEU</persName> his x mark.</p>

</div>

<div type="section">
                 

                        <head>ORDER IN COUNCIL</head>
                   
<p>
RATIFYING TREATY No. 11<lb/>
P.C. 3985</p>

<p>
PRIVY COUNCIL CANADA<lb/>
AT THE GOVERNMENT HOUSE AT OTTAWA,<lb/>
</p>

<p>
SATURDAY,<lb/>
the 22nd day of October, 1921.</p>

<p>
PRESENT:<lb/>
HIS EXCELLENCY<lb/>
THE GOVERNOR GENERAL IN COUNCIL</p>
           

                  <p>WHEREAS the Superintendent General of Indian Affairs submits
herewith Treaty Number Eleven made, in accordance with the terms of
Order in Council of 14th March, 1921 (P.C. 686), by Henry Anthony
Conroy, Esquire, who was appointed a Commissioner by the said Order
in Council, to negotiate with the Slave, Dogrib, Loucheux, Hare and
other Indians for the cession by the said Indians to the Crown of
all their rights, titles and privileges whatsoever in the territory
north of the sixtieth parallel and along the Mackenzie river and
the Arctic ocean in the Dominion of Canada.</p>
                  <p>THEREFORE His Excellency the Governor General in Council, on the
recommendation of the Superintendent General of Indian Affairs, is
pleased to ratify the said Treaty Number Eleven, made and
negotiated as hereinbefore recited, and the same is hereby ratified
and confirmed accordingly.</p>
                  <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">RODOLPHE BOUDREAU</persName>,<lb/>
Clerk of the Privy Council.</p>
                  <p>The Honourable<lb/>
The Superintendent General of Indian Affairs.</p>
                  <p>Owing to the death of Commissioner Conroy on April 27, 1922, and
to the fact that he had not had an opportunity during the summer of
1921 of obtaining the adhesion to the Treaty by the Slave Indians
of the Liard district, it was necessary to make other arrangements.
Accordingly the authority of His Excellency the Governor General in
Council was obtained for the appointment of T. W. Harris, Indian
agent at Fort Simpson, N.W.T., as Commissioner to secure this
adhesion.</p>
                  <p>Following is a copy of the Order in Council:--<lb/>
                  </p>
                  <p>P.C. 993</p>
                  <p>CERTIFIED COPY of a <hi rendition="simple:italic">Report of the Committee of the Privy
Council approved<lb/>
by His Excellency the Governor General on the 9th May,
1922</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Committee of the Privy Council have had before them a
Report, dated 2nd May, 1922, from the Superintendent General of
Indian Affairs, submitting, with reference to Order in Council of
the 14th March, 1921, under which Mr. H. A. Conroy, Inspector for
Treaty No. 8, was authorized to act as Commissioner to negotiate a
Treaty (known as Treaty No. 11) with the Indians occupying the
territory north of the 60th parallel and along the Mackenzie river
to the Arctic coast, that owing to lack of time Mr. Conroy was
unable to visit the Fort Liard Indians last year with a view to
securing their adhesion to the treaty.</p>
                  <p>The Minister states that owing to Mr. Conroy's death, which
occurred on the 27th April, 1922, it is essential that someone
should be deputed to complete the treaty negotiations.</p>
                  <p>The Minister, therefore, recommends that Mr. T. W. Harris,
Indian agent at Fort Simpson, N.W.T., be authorized to complete the
work entrusted to the late Mr. Conroy in connection with the treaty
above mentioned.</p>
                  <p>The Committe concur in the foregoing recommendation and submit
the same for approval.</p>
                  <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">RODOLPHE BOUDREAU</persName>,<lb/>
Clerk of the Privy Council.</p>
                  <p>The Honourable<lb/>
The Superintendent General of Indian Affairs.</p>
                  <p>Accordingly Commissioner Harris, accompanied by His Lordship
Bishop Breynat and Reverend Father Moisan, visited Fort Liard on
July 17th. The terms of the treaty having been explained by the
Commissioner, the Chief and Headmen, who had previously been
elected, signed the treaty on behalf of the Indians as indicated in
the following Indenture:--</p>
                  <p>SIGNED at Liard on the seventeenth day of July, 1922, by His
Majesty's Commissioner and the Chiefs and Headmen in the presence
of the undersigned witnesses, after having been first interpreted
and explained.</p>
        

    <p>Witnesses:<lb/>
(Sgd.)</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BREY1">G. BREYNANT</persName>, O.M.I., <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bishop of Adr.,<lb/>
Vic. Apost. of Mackenzie</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MOIS1">F. MOISAN</persName>, O.M.I. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Pire</hi>.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BORB1">A. BORBIN</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Const. R.C.M.P.</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BERR1">JOSEPH BERRAULT</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Interpreter</hi>.</p>

<p>(Sgd.)</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HARR7">THOMAS WILLIAM HARRIS</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Comm</hi>.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KINL1">THOMAS E. KINLA</persName> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:FANT1">JOSEPH FANTASQUR</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:CELI1">DAVID CELIBETA</persName> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, his x mark</p>


<table>
<row><cell>The Number of Indian paid was:-</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>1 Chief at $32...................................$</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">32</cell></row>
<row><cell>2 Headman at $22...................................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">44</cell></row>
<row><cell>147 Indians at $12...................................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,764</cell></row>
</table>

</div>

<div type="section">
                        <head>ORDER IN COUNCIL<lb/>
RATIFYING ADHESION TO TREATY No. 11</head>
                  

            

                  <p>March 29, 1923.</p>
                  <p>The Committee of the Privy Council, on the recommendation of the
Superintendent General of Indian Affairs, submit herewith for
ratification and confirmation by Your Excellency in Council, an
instrument, in duplicate, containing the adhesion to Treaty No. 11
of the Indians of Fort Liard taken the seventeenth day of July,
1922, by Mr. T. W. Harris, who was appointed by an Order of Your
Excellency in Council of 9th May, 1922 (P.C. No. 993), as His
Majesty's Commissioner to take the said adhesion; one copy of the
instrument to be returned to the Department of Indian Affairs and
the other to be kept on record in the Privy Council Office.</p>
                  <p>(Sgd.) <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">RODOLPHE BOUDREAU</persName>,<lb/>
Clerk of the Privy Council.</p>
                  <p>The Honourable<lb/>
The Superintendent General of Indian Affairs.</p>

     



</div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
