<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="treaty_06"
     type="full">
<teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreaty">Treaty Document(s)</name>, <date when="1877-08-23">23 August 1877</date> and <date when="1877-08-28">28 August 1877</date>, Treaty No. 6.</title>
        

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName></respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion from HTML to TEI</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLM3">Martin Holmes</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">LAYOUT IS NOT EXACTLY LIKE ORIGINAL</hi></p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:treaty_6">
          
               <title>Copy of Treaty No. 6 between Her Majesty the Queen and the Plain and Wood Cree Indians and other Tribes of Indians at Fort Carlton, Fort Pitt and Battle River with Adhesions</title>.
                    

          <date when="1964"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Roger Duhamel, F.R.S.C. The Queen's Printer and Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          
  <orgName>
               
                  <orgName xml:lang="en">Indigenous and Northern Affairs Canada</orgName>
               </orgName>
        
        </bibl>
 

            <list>
               <item>
                <ptr target="https://www.aadnc-aandc.gc.ca/eng/1100100028710/1100100028783"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-11-21">Transformed original HTML to TEI.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treaty">
        

                  <fw type="running">Treaty Texts - Treaty No. 6</fw>
                  <fw type="running">Copy of Treaty No. 6 between Her
Majesty the Queen and the Plain and Wood Cree Indians and other
Tribes of Indians at Fort Carlton, Fort Pitt and Battle River with
Adhesions</fw>
                  

                  <head>Treaty No. 6</head>
          

                     <p>ARTICLES OF A TREATY made and concluded near Carlton on the 23rd
day of August and on the 28th day of said month, respectively, and
near Fort Pitt on the 9th day of September, in the year of Our Lord
one thousand eight hundred and seventy-six, between Her Most
Gracious Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, by Her
Commissioners, the Honourable Alexander Morris, Lieutenant-Governor
of the Province of Manitoba and the North-west Territories, and the
Honourable James McKay, and the Honourable William Joseph Christie,
of the one part, and the Plain and Wood Cree and the other Tribes
of Indians, inhabitants of the country within the limits
hereinafter defined and described by their Chiefs, chosen and named
as hereinafter mentioned, of the other part.</p>
                     <p>Whereas the Indians inhabiting the said country have, pursuant
to an appointment made by the said Commissioners, been convened at
meetings at Fort Carlton, Fort Pitt and Battle River, to deliberate
upon certain matters of interest to Her Most Gracious Majesty, of
the one part, and the said Indians of the other.</p>
                     <p>And whereas the said Indians have been notified and informed by
Her Majesty's said Commissioners that it is the desire of Her
Majesty to open up for settlement, immigration and such other
purposes as to Her Majesty may seem meet, a tract of country
bounded and described as hereinafter mentioned, and to obtain the
consent thereto of Her Indian subjects inhabiting the said tract,
and to make a treaty and arrange with them, so that there may be
peace and good will between them and Her Majesty, and that they may
know and be assured of what allowance they are to count upon and
receive from Her Majesty's bounty and benevolence.</p>
                     <p>And whereas the Indians of the said tract, duly convened in
council, as aforesaid, and being requested by Her Majesty's said
Commissioners to name certain Chiefs and Headmen, who should be
authorized on their behalf to conduct such negotiations and sign
any treaty to be founded thereon, and to become responsible to Her
Majesty for their faithful performance by their respective Bands of
such obligations as shall be assumed by them, the said Indians have
thereupon named for that purpose, that is to say, representing the
Indians who make the treaty at Carlton, the several Chiefs and
Councillors who have subscribed hereto, and representing the
Indians who make the treaty at Fort Pitt, the several Chiefs and
Councillors who have subscribed hereto.</p>
                     <p>And thereupon, in open council, the different Bands having
presented their Chiefs to the said Commissioners as the Chiefs and
Headmen, for the purposes aforesaid, of the respective Bands of
Indians inhabiting the said district hereinafter described.</p>
                     <p>And whereas, the said Commissioners then and there received and
acknowledged the persons so presented as Chiefs and Headmen, for
the purposes aforesaid, of the respective Bands of Indians
inhabiting the said district hereinafter described.</p>
                     <p>And whereas, the said Commissioners have proceeded to negotiate
a treaty with the said Indians, and the same has been finally
agreed upon and concluded, as follows, that is to say:</p>
                     <p>The Plain and Wood Cree Tribes of Indians, and all other the
Indians inhabiting the district hereinafter described and defined,
do hereby cede, release, surrender and yield up to the Government
of the Dominion of Canada, for Her Majesty the Queen and Her
successors forever, all their rights, titles and privileges,
whatsoever, to the lands included within the following limits, that
is to say:</p>
                     <p>Commencing at the mouth of the river emptying into the
north-west angle of Cumberland Lake; thence westerly up the said
river to its source; thence on a straight line in a westerly
direction to the head of Green Lake; thence northerly to the elbow
in the Beaver River; thence down the said river northerly to a
point twenty miles from the said elbow; thence in a westerly
direction, keeping on a line generally parallel with the said
Beaver River (above the elbow), and about twenty miles distant
therefrom, to the source of the said river; thence northerly to the
north-easterly point of the south shore of Red Deer Lake,
continuing westerly along the said shore to the western limit
thereof; and thence due west to the Athabasca River; thence up the
said river, against the stream, to the Jaspar House, in the Rocky
Mountains; thence on a course south-easterly, following the
easterly range of the mountains, to the source of the main branch
of the Red Deer River; thence down the said river, with the stream,
to the junction therewith of the outlet of the river, being the
outlet of the Buffalo Lake; thence due east twenty miles; thence on
a straight line south-eastwardly to the mouth of the said Red Deer
River on the south branch of the Saskatchewan River; thence
eastwardly and northwardly, following on the boundaries of the
tracts conceded by the several treaties numbered four and five to
the place of beginning.</p>
                     <p>And also, all their rights, titles and privileges whatsoever to
all other lands wherever situated in the North-west Territories, or
in any other Province or portion of Her Majesty's Dominions,
situated and being within the Dominion of Canada.</p>
                     <p>The tract comprised within the lines above described embracing
an area of 121,000 square miles, be the same more or less.</p>
                     <p>To have and to hold the same to Her Majesty the Queen and Her
successors forever.</p>
                     <p>And Her Majesty the Queen hereby agrees and undertakes to lay
aside reserves for farming lands, due respect being had to lands at
present cultivated by the said Indians, and other reserves for the
benefit of the said Indians, to be administered and dealt with for
them by Her Majesty's Government of the Dominion of Canada;
provided, all such reserves shall not exceed in all one square mile
for each family of five, or in that proportion for larger or
smaller families, in manner following, that is to say: that the
Chief Superintendent of Indian Affairs shall depute and send a
suitable person to determine and set apart the reserves for each
band, after consulting with the Indians thereof as to the locality
which may be found to be most suitable for them.</p>
                     <p>Provided, however, that Her Majesty reserves the right to deal
with any settlers within the bounds of any lands reserved for any
Band as She shall deem fit, and also that the aforesaid reserves of
land, or any interest therein, may be sold or otherwise disposed of
by Her Majesty's Government for the use and benefit of the said
Indians entitled thereto, with their consent first had and
obtained; and with a view to show the satisfaction of Her Majesty
with the behaviour and good conduct of Her Indians, She hereby,
through Her Commissioners, makes them a present of twelve dollars
for each man, woman and child belonging to the Bands here
represented, in extinguishment of all claims heretofore
preferred.</p>
                     <p>And further, Her Majesty agrees to maintain schools for
instruction in such reserves hereby made as to Her Government of
the Dominion of Canada may seem advisable, whenever the Indians of
the reserve shall desire it.</p>
                     <p>Her Majesty further agrees with Her said Indians that within the
boundary of Indian reserves, until otherwise determined by Her
Government of the Dominion of Canada, no intoxicating liquor shall
be allowed to be introduced or sold, and all laws now in force, or
hereafter to be enacted, to preserve Her Indian subjects inhabiting
the reserves or living elsewhere within Her North-west Territories
from the evil influence of the use of intoxicating liquors, shall
be strictly enforced.</p>
                     <p>Her Majesty further agrees with Her said Indians that they, the
said Indians, shall have right to pursue their avocations of
hunting and fishing throughout the tract surrendered as
hereinbefore described, subject to such regulations as may from
time to time be made by Her Government of Her Dominion of Canada,
and saving and excepting such tracts as may from time to time be
required or taken up for settlement, mining, lumbering or other
purposes by Her said Government of the Dominion of Canada, or by
any of the subjects thereof duly authorized therefor by the said
Government.</p>
                     <p>It is further agreed between Her Majesty and Her said Indians,
that such sections of the reserves above indicated as may at any
time be required for public works or buildings, of what nature
soever, may be appropriated for that purpose by Her Majesty's
Government of the Dominion of Canada, due compensation being made
for the value of any improvements thereon.</p>
                     <p>And further, that Her Majesty's Commissioners shall, as soon as
possible after the execution of this treaty, cause to be taken an
accurate census of all the Indians inhabiting the tract above
described, distributing them in families, and shall, in every year
ensuing the date hereof, at some period in each year, to be duly
notified to the Indians, and at a place or places to be appointed
for that purpose within the territory ceded, pay to each Indian
person the sum of $5 per head yearly.</p>
                     <p>It is further agreed between Her Majesty and the said Indians,
that the sum of $1,500.00 per annum shall be yearly and every year
expended by Her Majesty in the purchase of ammunition, and twine
for nets, for the use of the said Indians, in manner following,
that is to say: In the reasonable discretion, as regards the
distribution thereof among the Indians inhabiting the several
reserves, or otherwise, included herein, of Her Majesty's Indian
Agent having the supervision of this treaty.</p>
                     <p>It is further agreed between Her Majesty and the said Indians,
that the following articles shall be supplied to any Band of the
said Indians who are now cultivating the soil, or who shall
hereafter commence to cultivate the land, that is to say: Four hoes
for every family actually cultivating; also, two spades per family
as aforesaid: one plough for every three families, as aforesaid;
one harrow for every three families, as aforesaid; two scythes and
one whetstone, and two hay forks and two reaping hooks, for every
family as aforesaid, and also two axes; and also one cross-cut saw,
one hand-saw, one pit-saw, the necessary files, one grindstone and
one auger for each Band; and also for each Chief for the use of his
Band, one chest of ordinary carpenter's tools; also, for each Band,
enough of wheat, barley, potatoes and oats to plant the land
actually broken up for cultivation by such Band; also for each Band
four oxen, one bull and six cows; also, one boar and two sows, and
one hand-mill when any Band shall raise sufficient grain therefor.
All the aforesaid articles to be given once and for all for the
encouragement of the practice of agriculture among the Indians.</p>
                     <p>It is further agreed between Her Majesty and the said Indians,
that each Chief, duly recognized as such, shall receive an annual
salary of twenty-five dollars per annum; and each subordinate
officer, not exceeding four for each Band, shall receive fifteen
dollars per annum; and each such Chief and subordinate officer, as
aforesaid, shall also receive once every three years, a suitable
suit of clothing, and each Chief shall receive, in recognition of
the closing of the treaty, a suitable flag and medal, and also as
soon as convenient, one horse, harness and waggon.</p>
                     <p>That in the event hereafter of the Indians comprised within this
treaty being overtaken by any pestilence, or by a general famine,
the Queen, on being satisfied and certified thereof by Her Indian
Agent or Agents, will grant to the Indians assistance of such
character and to such extent as Her Chief Superintendent of Indian
Affairs shall deem necessary and sufficient to relieve the Indians
from the calamity that shall have befallen them.</p>
                     <p>That during the next three years, after two or more of the
reserves hereby agreed to be set apart to the Indians shall have
been agreed upon and surveyed, there shall be granted to the
Indians included under the Chiefs adhering to the treaty at
Carlton, each spring, the sum of one thousand dollars, to be
expended for them by Her Majesty's Indian Agents, in the purchase
of provisions for the use of such of the Band as are actually
settled on the reserves and are engaged in cultivating the soil, to
assist them in such cultivation.</p>
                     <p>That a medicine chest shall be kept at the house of each Indian
Agent for the use and benefit of the Indians at the direction of
such agent.</p>
                     <p>That with regard to the Indians included under the Chiefs
adhering to the treaty at Fort Pitt, and to those under Chiefs
within the treaty limits who may hereafter give their adhesion
thereto (exclusively, however, of the Indians of the Carlton
region), there shall, during three years, after two or more
reserves shall have been agreed upon and surveyed be distributed
each spring among the Bands cultivating the soil on such reserves,
by Her Majesty's Chief Indian Agent for this treaty, in his
discretion, a sum not exceeding one thousand dollars, in the
purchase of provisions for the use of such members of the Band as
are actually settled on the reserves and engaged in the cultivation
of the soil, to assist and encourage them in such cultivation.</p>
                     <p>That in lieu of waggons, if they desire it and declare their
option to that effect, there shall be given to each of the Chiefs
adhering hereto at Fort Pitt or elsewhere hereafter (exclusively of
those in the Carlton district), in recognition of this treaty, as
soon as the same can be conveniently transported, two carts with
iron bushings and tires.</p>
                     <p>And the undersigned Chiefs on their own behalf and on behalf of
all other Indians inhabiting the tract within ceded, do hereby
solemnly promise and engage to strictly observe this treaty, and
also to conduct and behave themselves as good and loyal subjects of
Her Majesty the Queen.</p>
                     <p>They promise and engage that they will in all respects obey and
abide by the law, and they will maintain peace and good order
between each other, and also between themselves and other tribes of
Indians, and between themselves and others of Her Majesty's
subjects, whether Indians or whites, now inhabiting or hereafter to
inhabit any part of the said ceded tracts, and that they will not
molest the person or property of any inhabitant of such ceded
tracts, or the property of Her Majesty the Queen, or interfere with
or trouble any person passing or travelling through the said
tracts, or any part thereof, and that they will aid and assist the
officers of Her Majesty in bringing to justice and punishment any
Indian offending against the stipulations of this treaty, or
infringing the laws in force in the country so ceded.</p>
                     <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Her Majesty's said Commissioners and the
said Indian Chiefs have hereunto subscribed and set their hands at
or near Fort Carlton, on the days and year aforesaid, and near Fort
Pitt on the day above aforesaid.</p>
                     
<p>Signed by the Chiefs within named
<lb/>
in presence of the following wit<lb break="no"/>nesses, the same having been first<lb/>
read and explained by <persName ref="pers:ERAS1">Peter Eras<lb break="no"/>mus</persName>, <persName ref="pers:BALL4">Peter Ballendine</persName> and the
<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKA12">Rev. John McKay</persName>.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:JACK6">ALF. JACKES</persName>, M.D.,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WALK3">JAS. WALKER</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">N.W.M.P.</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCIL2">J. H. MCILLREE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">N.W.M.P.</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LEVA1">PIERRE LEVAILLER</persName>. his x mark.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DUMO1">ISADORE DUMOND</persName>, his x mark<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DUMO2">JEAN DUMOND</persName>, his x mark.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HOUR1">Peter HOURIE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">F. GINGRAS</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MITC4">J. B.
MITCHELL</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Staff Constable N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:PRIC2">E. H. PRICE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Hospital Steward N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LETA1">XAVIER LETANGER</persName>, his x mark.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SINC9">WILLIAM SINCLAIR</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:KENN4">A. R. KENNEDY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:PRIT1">R I. PRITCHARD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CLAR6">L. CLARK</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKA11">W.
MCKAY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:JARV1">W. D. JARVIS</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Inspector, N.W.M.P.</hi></p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:MORR1">ALEXANDER MORRIS</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">L. G. N.W.T.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKA4">JAMES MCKAY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Indian Commissioner</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CHRI3">W. J. CHRISTIE</persName> <hi rendition="simple:italic">do</hi>
</p>

<p>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Head Chiefs of the Carlton Indians.</hi></p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:MIST1">MIS-TO-WA-SIS</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:AHTU1">AH-TUK-UK-KOOP</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Chiefs.</hi></p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:PEEY1">PEE-YAHN-KAH-NICHK-OO-SIT</persName> his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:AHYA1">AH-YAH-TUS-KUM-IK-IM-AM</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KEET2">KEE-TOO-WA-HAW</persName>. his x mark.</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:CHAK1">Cha-Kas-Ta-Pay-Sin</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:SMIT13">JOHN SMITH</persName>. his x mark.</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:SMIT10">JAMES SMITH</persName> his x mark.</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:CHIP3">CHIP-EE-WAYAN</persName>. his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors of Mis-to-wa-sis</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MASS5">MASS-AX</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:CADI1">PIERRE CADIEN</persName>. his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KOOY1">KOO-YAH-TIK-WAH-PAHA</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MAHS1">MAHS-KEE-TO-TIM-AN</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors of Ah-tuk-uk-koop.</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:SAHS1">SAH-SAH-KOO-MOOS</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BENJ1">BENJAMIN</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MEEN1">MEE-NOW-AH-CHAHK-WAY</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KEES3">KEE-SIK-OW-AS-IS</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors of Pee-yahh-kah-nishk-oo-sit</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:PEET1">PEE-TOOK-AH-HAN
AP-EE-GIW-EW</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:PEEA1">PEE-AY-CHEW</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:TAHW1">TAH-WAH-JUSK
EE-KAHP-POW</persName>, his x mark<lb/></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:AHSK1">AHS-KOOS</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors of Kee-oo-wa-haw</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:PETE1">PET-E-QUA-CAY</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BAPT2">JEAN BAPTISTS</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:WOLF1">ISADORE
WOLFE</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KEEK1">KEE-KOO-HOOS</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors of Ah-yah-tus-kum-ik-im-um</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:OOSA1">Oo-SAHM US-KOO-NEE-KIK</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:YAYY1">YAY-YAH-TOO-WAY</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:LOOS1">LOO-SOU-AM-EE-KWAKN</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:NEES2">NEES-WAH-YAK-EE-NAH-KOOS</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors of Cha-kas-tay-pay-sin.</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KAHT2">KAH-TIP-IS-KOW-AHT</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KAHK2">KAH-KUN-EE-KNAHN-AHS-UM</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:NAHP1">NAH-PACH</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MUSI1">MUS-IN-AH-WE-KIM-AHER</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors of John Smith</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BADG1">WILLIAM
BADGER</persName>, </p>
<p><persName ref="pers:JOYF1">BENJAMIN
JOYFUL</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BADG2">JOHN BADGER</persName>,</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BEAR4">JAMES BEAR</persName>,</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors of James Smith</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:CONS3">BERNARD
CONSTANT</persName>,</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:SMIT11">HENRY
SMITH</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MATW2">MA-TWA-AHS-TIN-OO-WE-GIN</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MCLE12">JACOB
MCLEAN</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors of Chipee-wayun</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:NAAP1">NAA-POO-CHEE-CHEES</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:WAHW1">WAH-WIS</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KAHP1">KAH-PAH-PAH-MAH-CHATIK-WAY</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KEEY1">KEE-YEU-AH-TIAH-PIM-WAHT</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p>Signed by the Chiefs and Headmen of<lb/>
the Willow Indians near Fort Carlton,<lb/>
this 28th day of August, A.D. 1876, the<lb/>
same having been first read and ex<lb break="no"/>plained by the <persName ref="pers:MCKA4">Hon. Jas. McKay</persName> and<lb/>
by <persName ref="pers:ERAS1">Peter Erasmus</persName>, in the presence of<lb/>
the undersigned witnesses:</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:JACK6">A. G. JACKES</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">M.D</hi>.,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GENT1">JOSEPH GENTON</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:KERR2">JOHN A. KERR</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LAVE3">PIERRE X LAVEILLER</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:JARV1">W. D. JARVIS</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Ins. N.W.M.P.</hi></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:WAHW2">WAH-WEE-KAH-OO-TAH-MAH-HOTE</persName>, (TOTEM,)
(or
MEH-CHA-AW-ASIS), his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:SEES1">SEE-SEE-QUAN-ISH</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:WEET1">WEE-TEE-KOO-WEE-KAH-MAW-OO</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors.</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KAHM1">KAH-MEE-GIS-TOO-WAY-SIT</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KAHP2">KAH-PAY-YAK-WAHSK-OO-NUM</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:SEES2">SEE-SEE-KWAHN-IS</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Joint
Chiefs of
the
Willow Indians.</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KAHN3">KAH-NAH-LAH-SKOW-WAHT</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KAHA1">KAH-AH-TEE-KOO-WEN</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KAHN4">KAH-NAH-MAH-CHEW</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MOON1">MOON-ED-YAHS</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:OOMI1">OO-MIN-AH-KAW</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:OOTU1">Oo-TUK-KOO-PAH-KAH-MAY-TOW-WAY-YIT</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors
of
Willow Indians.</hi></p>

<p>Signed by Her Majesty's Commissioners and by the Chiefs and Headmen here-<lb/>
after subscribing hereto, the same having been first read and explained to the Indians<lb/>
by the Honourable <persName ref="pers:MCKA4">James McKay</persName> and <persName ref="pers:ERAS1">Peter Erasmus</persName>, near Fort Pitt , this 9th day<lb/>
of September, A.D. 1876, in the presence of the undersigned witnesses.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:JACK6">A.G. JACKES</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">MD.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCLE13">JAS. MCLEOD</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Commr. N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:VITA1">VITAL J</persName>., <hi rendition="simple:italic">Bishop St. Albert, O.M.I.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CLAR5">E. DALRYMPLE CLARK</persName>; <hi rendition="simple:italic">Adj. N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SCOL1">CONSTANTINE SCOLLEN</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Prst., O.M.I.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCDO19">JOHN MCDOUGALL</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Meth. Missionary.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCEL1">John MCELVEY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:JONE6">W.E. JONES</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:PAMB1">PETER C. PAMBRON</persName>, <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:KENN4">A.R. KENNEDY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ERAS1">PETER ERASMUS</persName>, <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKA6">THOMAS MCKAY</persName>, <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SIMP3">JAMES SIMPSON</persName>, <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HARD1">ELIZA HARDISTY</persName>, <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKA15">MARY MCKAY</persName>.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MORR1">ALEXANDER MORRIS</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">L.G., N.W.T.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKA4">JAMES MCKAY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Indian Commr.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CHRI3">W.J. CHRISTIE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Indian Commr.</hi></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:WEEK1">WEE-KAS-KOO-KEE-SAY-YIN</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:PEEY2">PEE-YAS-EE-WAH-KAH-WE-CHA-KOOT</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:SEEN1">JAMES SEENUM</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:OONA1">OO-NAH-TAH-MEE-NAH-HOOS</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:SEEK1">SEE-KAHS-KOOTCH</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:TUST2">TUS-TUK-EE-SKWAHS</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:PEEN1">PEE-NAY-SIS</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KEEY2">KEE-YE-WIN</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Cree Chiefs</hi>.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KINO1">KIN-OO-SAY-OO</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Chipewayan Chief</hi>.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:SEEW1">SEE-WAS-KWAN</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:WAYW2">WAY-WAY-SEE-POO-WE-YIN</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors
to Wee-kas-koo-ke-say-yin</hi>.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors to Pee-yas-ee-wa-cha-koot</hi>.</p>

<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">TIP-EE-SLOW-AH-CHAK</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:PAYP1">PAY-PAY-SEE-SEE-MOO</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors to See-kahs-kootch</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:OONO1">Oo-NOW-AK-EE-PAH-CHAS</persName></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MYOE1">MY-OE-WAY-SEES</persName></p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors to Tus-tuk-ee-skwans</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:OOSP1">OOS-PERAH-KHAN-IS</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:NEEY1">NEE-YE-PES-TAY-AS-EE-KAYSE</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors to Pee-way-sis</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MAHC1">MAH-CHAH-ME-WIS</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:CARD7">ISAAC CARDINAL</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors to Kim-oo-say-uo</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:XAVI1">ANTOINE
XAVIER</persName></p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors to James Seenum</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BULL1">WILLIAM BULL</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors to See-kahs-kootch</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:WAHK1">WAH-KEG-SEE-KOOT</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors to Kee-ye-win</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:CARD3">CHARLES CARDINAL</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:WAHB1">PIERRE
WAHBISKAW</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors to Wee-has-hoo-hee-say-yin</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KIYA1">KI-YAS-EE-KUN</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KAHK3">KAH-KEE-OO-PAH-TOW</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillor to Oo-ma-tak-mee-wa-koos</hi>/</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:CAKE1">CAKE-CAKE</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillor to James Seenum</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KAMO2">KAM-OO-WIN</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillor to See-kahs-kootch</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:AHSI1">AH-SISS</persName>, his x mark.</p>




                     <p>Recorded 24th February, 1877.<lb/>
Lib. 27, Fol. 352.</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:CATE1">L.A. CATELLIER</persName>,<lb/>
Deputy Registrar-General of Canada.</p>
             


<div type="section">

                  <head>Adhesion By Cree Indians</head>
                 

                     <p>We, the undersigned Chiefs and Headmen of the Cree and other
Bands of Indians, having had communication of the treaty, a copy of
which is printed in the report of the Minister of the Interior for
the year ending 30th June, 1876, concluded at Forts Carlton and
Pitt between the Indians inhabiting the country described in said
treaty, and Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, by
Her Commissioners, the Honourable Alexander Morris,
Lieutenant-Governor of Manitoba and the North-west Territories, the
Honourable W.J. Christie and the Honourable James McKay, but not
having been present when the negotiations were being conducted at
the above mentioned places, do hereby for ourselves, and the Bands
which we represent, agree to all the terms, conditions, covenants
and engagements of whatever kind enumerated in the said treaty and
accept the same as if we had been present, and had consented and
agreed to the same when the treaty was first signed and
executed.</p>
                     <p>Witness our hands at Fort Pitt, this ninth day of August, in the
year of Our Lord one thousand eight hundred and seventy-seven.</p>
 

<p>Signed by the Chief and Headman (hav<lb break="no"/>ing been first read and explained by<lb/>
Peter Erasmus) in the presence of:</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:ERAS1">PETER ERASMUS</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CAMP7">RODERICK CAMPBELL</persName>.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:DICK3">M. G. DICKIESON</persName>, Commisioner.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:PAYM1">PAY-MO-TAY-AH-SOO</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KAHS1">KAH-SEE-MUT-A-POO</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:AAHP1">AAH-PAY-SIS</persName>, his x mark.<lb/>
(KE-HI-WIN'S Headman.)</p>

<p>Signed at Edmonton this 21st day of<lb/>
August, in the year above written, by<lb/>
the undersigned Chiefs and Headmen,<lb/>
the whole having been first read and<lb/>
explained by Peter Erasmus, in the pre<lb break="no"/>sence of:</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HARD2">Ric. HARDISTY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LEDU1">H. LEDUC</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ERAS1">PETER ERASMUS</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:JARV1">W. D. JARVIS</persName>,<lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Inspector N.W.M.P.</hi></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KEES4">ALEXIS KEES-KEE-CHEE-CHI</persName>, his x mark. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief</hi>. </p>

<p><persName ref="pers:OOMU1">OO-MUS-IN-AH-SOO-WAW-SINEE</persName>, his x mark. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>. </p>

<p><persName ref="pers:CATC1">CATCHIS-TAH-WAY-SKUM</persName>, his x mark. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief</hi>. </p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KOOS1">KOO-SAH-WAN-AS-KAY-O</persName>, his x mark. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>. </p>

<p><persName ref="pers:PAHS1">PAHS-PAHS-CHASE</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:TAHK1">TAH-KOOTCH</persName>, his x mark.</p>

</div>


<div type="section">


<head>ADHESION BY CREE INDIANS</head>

                     <p>We, members of the Cree Tribe of Indians having had explained to
us the terms of the treaty made and concluded near Carlton on the
23rd day of August, and on the 28th day of said month respectively,
and near Fort Pitt on the 9th day of September, 1876, between Her
Majesty the Queen, by the Commissioners duly appointed to negotiate
the said treaty, and the Plain and Wood Cree and other Tribes of
Indians, inhabiting the country within the limits defined in said
treaty, but not having been present at the council at which the
articles of the said treaty were agreed upon, do now hereby for
ourselves and the Band which we represent, in consideration of the
provisions of the said treaty being extended to us and the Band
which we represent, transfer, surrender, and relinquish to Her
Majesty the Queen, Her heirs and successors, to and for the use of
the Government of the Dominion of Canada, all our right, title and
interest whatsoever, which we and the said Band which we represent
have held or enjoyed of, in and to the territory described, and
fully set out in the said treaty, also, all our right, title and
interest whatsoever to all other lands wherever situated, whether
within the limits of any other treaty heretofore made, or hereafter
to be made with Indians, or elsewhere in Her Majesty's territories,
to have and to hold the same unto and for the use of her Majesty
the Queen, Her heirs and successors forever.</p>
                     <p>And we hereby agree to accept the several benefits, payments and
reserves promised to the Indians under the Chiefs adhering to the
said treaty at Fort Pitt; and solemnly engage to abide by, carry
out and fulfil all the stipulations, obligations and conditions
therein contained, on the part of the Chiefs and Indians therein
named to be observed and performed, and in all things to conform to
the articles of the said treaty, as if we ourselves and the Band
which we represent had been originally contracting parties thereto,
and been present at the councils held near Fort Pitt, and had there
attached our signatures to the said treaty.</p>
                     <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Her Majesty's Lieutenant-Governor and Indian
Superintendent for the North-west Territories, and the Chief and
Councillors of the Band hereby giving their adhesion to the said
treaty, have hereunto subscribed and set theirs hand at the
Blackfoot Crossing of the Bow River, this twenty-fifth day of
September, in the year of Our Lord one thousand eight hundred and
seventy-seven.</p>

<p>Signed by the parties hereto, in the pre<lb break="no"/>sence of the undersigned witnesses,
the same having been first explained<lb/>
to the Indians by the Rev. J. Mc<lb break="no"/>Dougall.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MCLE13">JAMES F. MCLEOD</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut.-Col,<lb/>
Com. N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SCOL1">CONSTANTINE SCOLLEN</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCDO19">J. MCDOUGALL</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Missionary</hi>.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR4">DAVID LAIRD</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut.-Governor and<lb/>
Indian Superintendent of N.W.T.</hi></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KISK1">KISKAQUIN</persName>,  or BOB-TAIL, his x mark. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief</hi>.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MEMI1">MEMINOWATAW</persName>, or SOMETIMES GLAD. his x mark. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillor</hi>.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:TCHO1">TCHOWEK</persName> or Passingsound, his x mark. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillor</hi>.</p>

<p>Recorded 26th January, 1878.<lb/>
Lib. 27, Folio 519.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:CATE1">L. A. CATELLIER</persName>,<lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Deputy Registrar General of Canada</hi></p>

</div>


                     <div type="section">


<head>ADHESION BY CREE INDIANS</head>

                     <p>The undersigned Chiefs and Headmen of the Cree Nation having had
communication of the treaty concluded between Her Majesty the Queen
by Her Commissioners and certain Chiefs of the Cree Nation at Fort
Pitt on the 9th day of September, 1876, agree to surrender our
title to all the lands in the North-west Territories and to abide
by all the promises set forth in the said treaty, on condition that
all the payments, reserves of land, and promises named therein are
secured to us by Her Majesty.</p>
                     <p>And the undersigned Superintendent of Indian Affairs for the
North-west Territories on behalf of Her Majesty agrees that all the
payments, reserves and promises named in the said treaty to be made
to each Cree Chief and his Band shall be faithfully made and
carried out to the Chiefs who have subscribed to this memorandum
and to their people.</p>
                     <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, the undersigned Indian Superintendent and
the undersigned Chiefs and Headmen have hereto set our hands in
this nineteenth day of August, one thousand eight hundred and
seventy-eight.</p>


<p>Signed the day and year above written,<lb/>
after having been read and interpreted<lb/>
to the Chiefs and Headmen by Peter<lb/>
Erasmus, in the presence of:</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:FREN1">JOHN FRENCH</persName>,<lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Sub-Inspector, N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ERAS1">PETER ERASMUS</persName>.</p>


<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR4">DAVID LAIRD</persName>,</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:PUSK1">PUSKEE-YAH-KAY-WEE-YIN</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MAHK1">MAH-KAYO</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:ISAD1">ISADORE</persName>, his x mark.</p>


                     </div>

                     <div type="section">
<head>ADHESION BY STONY INDIANS</head>

                     <p>We, the undersigned Chief and Headmen of the Plain Stony Tribe
of Indians, having had communication of the treaty made and
concluded near Carlton on the twenty-third and twenty-eighth days
of August respectively, and near Fort Pitt on the ninth day of
September, one thousand eight hundred and seventy-six, between Her
Majesty the Queen by Her Commissioners, and the Plain and Wood
Crees and other Tribes of Indians, inhabitants of the country named
therein, hereby for ourselves and the Band which we represent, in
consideration of the provisions of the said treaty being extended
to our Band, cede, transfer, surrender and relinquish to Her
Majesty the Queen, Her heirs and successors, to and for the use of
the Government of the Dominion of Canada, all our right, title and
privileges whatsoever to all lands in the North-west Territories,
or elsewhere in Her Majesty's dominions, to have and to hold the
same unto and to the use of Her said Majesty the Queen, Her heirs
and successors forever.</p>
                     <p>And we hereby agree to accept the several provisions, payments
and reserves of the said treaty as therein stated, and solemnly
promise and engage to abide by and carry out all the stipulations
and obligations therein contained, on the part of said Chiefs and
Indians therein named to be observed and performed, and in all
things to conform to the articles of the said treaty, as if we
ourselves and our Band had originally been contracting parties
thereto.</p>
                     <p>And Her Majesty the Queen, by Her representative, the Honourable
David Laird, Indian Superintendent of the North-west Territories,
agrees that all the payments and provisions named in the said
treaty to be made to each Chief and his Band shall be faithfully
made and fulfilled to the aforesaid Chief and his Band.</p>
                     <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, we, the said Indian Superintendent of the
North-west Territories and the said Chief and Headmen of the Stony
Tribe of Indians, have hereto set our hands, at Battleford, this
twenty-ninth day of August, one thousand eight hundred and
seventy-eight.</p>

<p>Signed by the parties hereto in the pre<lb break="no"/>sence of the undersigned witnessses,
the same having been first explained <lb/>
to the Indians by Peter Ballendine:</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:WALK3">JAMES WALKER</persName>,<lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Inspector N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BALL4">P. BALLENDINE</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:REED1">HAYTER REED</persName>.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR4">DAVID LAIRD</persName>. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Indian
Superintendent</hi>.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:SUKE1">SU-KE-MAN</persName> or MISKETO, his x mark.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:ETAM1">ETA-ME-PE-TON</persName>, or USES BOTH ARMS. his x mark.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:NESO1">NESO-AU-ASIS</persName>, or Two CHILD, his x mark.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KAWA2">KA-WA-SA-SKO-TRE-PAH-IK</persName>, or LIGHTNING, his x mark.</p>

                     </div>

<div type="section">
<head>ADHESION BY CREE INDIANS</head>


                     <p>We, the undersigned Chiefs and Headmen of the Wood Cree Tribe of
Indians, having had communication of the treaty made and concluded
near Carlton on the twenty-third and twenty-eighth days of August,
respectively, and near Fort Pitt on the ninth day of September, one
thousand eight hundred and seventy-six, between Her Majesty the
Queen, by Her Commissioners, and the Plain and Wood Cree and other
Tribes of Indians, inhabitants of the country named therein, hereby
for ourselves and the Bands which we represent, in consideration of
the provisions of the said treaty being extended to our Bands,
cede, transfer, surrender and relinquish to Her Majesty the Queen,
Her heirs and successors, to and for the use of Her Government of
the Dominion of Canada, all our right, title and privileges
whatsoever to all lands in the North-west Territories or elsewhere
in Her Majesty's Dominions, to have and to hold the same unto and
to the use of Her said Majesty the Queen, Her heirs and successors
forever.</p>
                     <p>And we hereby agree to accept the several provisions, payments
and reserves of the said treaty as therein stated, and solemnly
promise and engage to abide by and carry out all the stipulations
and obligations therein contained, on the part of said Chiefs and
Indians therein named to be observed and performed, and in all
things to conform to the articles of the said treaty, as if we
ourselves and our Bands had originally been contracting parties
thereto.</p>
                     <p>And Her Majesty the Queen, by Her representative, the Honourable
David Laird, Indian Superintendent of the North-west Territories,
agrees that all the payments and provisions named in the said
treaty to be made to each Chief and his Band shall be faithfully
made and fulfilled to the aforesaid Chiefs and their Bands.</p>
                     <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, we, the said Indian Superintendent of the
North-west Territories and the said Chiefs and Headmen of the Wood
Cree Tribe of Indians, have hereto set our hands at Carlton this
third day of September, one thousand eight hundred and
seventy-eight.</p>


<p>Signed by the Chiefs and Councillors<lb/>
within named, in presence of the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing witnesses, the same having first<lb/>
been explained by Peter Ballendine:
</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:CLAR6">L. CLARKE</persName>.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FORG2">A. E. FORGET</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BALL4">P. BALLENDINE</persName>.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR4">DAVID LAIRD</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Indian Superintendent</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KOPA1">KO-PAH-A-WA-KE-MUM</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MARI2">BANYIEL MARISTYO</persName>, his x mark. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillor.</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:JAME1">JAMES</persName> (CHIEF SON) his x mark. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillor.</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:SASE1">SA-SE-WA-HUM</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KENE1">KENE-MO-TAY</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MASE1">MAS-E-NAS-CHOSE</persName>, his x mark.</p>

</div>

<div type="section">

<head>ADHESION BY CREE INDIANS</head>


                     <p>We, the undersigned Indian Chief and Headmen, having had
communication of the treaty made and concluded at Forts Carlton and
Pitt in the summer of 1876, but not having been present at the
conferences at which said treaty was negotiated, hereby agree to
accept the terms and conditions of the said treaty and to abide
thereby, in the same manner as if we had been present at the time
the said treaty was first signed.</p>


<p>As witness our hands this eighteenth day of September, 1878.</p>

<p>Signed by the Chief and Headmen after<lb/>
having been read and explained by</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:ERAS1">PETER ERASMUS</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:CALI1">MICHEL CALISTROIS</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:PAYP2">Louis PAY-PATSMAH-WAYO</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:SEE1">ACOO SEE</persName>, his x mark.</p>

</div>

                     <div type="section">
<head>ADHESION BY CREE INDIANS</head>


                     <p>Whereas, Min-a-he-quo-sis, or Little Pine, a Cree Chief, on
behalf of his Band and certain other Cree Indians, comprising
twenty lodges, inhabitants of the country covered by the treaty
commonly known as "Treaty No. 6," made between Her Majesty the
Queen, by Her Commissioners, the Honourable Alexander Morris, the
Honourable James McKay and the Honourable William Joseph Christie,
of the one part;</p>
                     <p>And the Plain and Wood Cree Tribes of Indians of the other part,
at Carlton, on the twenty-third and twenty-eighth days of August,
and near Fort Pitt on the ninth day of September, in the year of
Our Lord one thousand eight hundred and seventy-six, who have not
yet given in their adhesion to the said treaty, have presented
themselves to Edgar Dewdney, Esquire, Indian Commissioner for the
North-west Territories, and expressed a desire to join in the said
treaty. And whereas the said Commissioner has recognized the said
"Little Pine" as the Headman of his Band, and the said Band of
twenty lodges have selected and appointed Pap-a-way, "The Lucky
Man," one of their number as the Headman of their Band, and have
presented him as such to the said Commissioner, who has recognized
and accepted him as such Headman;</p>
                     <p>NOW, THIS INSTRUMENT WITNESSETH that the said "Little Pine" and
Pap-a-way or "the Lucky Man," for themselves and on behalf of the
Bands which they represent, do transfer, surrender and relinquish
to Her Majesty the Queen, Her heirs and successors, to and for the
use of Her Government of the Dominion of Canada, all their right,
title and interest whatsoever which they have held or enjoyed of,
in and to the territory described and fully set out in the said
treaty; also, all their right, title and interest whatsoever which
they have held or enjoyed of, in and to the territory described and
fully set out in the said treaty; also all their right, title and
interest whatsoever to all other lands wherever situated, whether
within the limits of any other treaty heretofore made or hereafter
to be made with Indians or elsewhere in Her Majesty's territories,
to have and to hold the same unto and for the use of Her Majesty,
the Queen, Her heirs and successors for ever. And do hereby agree
to accept the several benefits, payments and reserves promised to
the Indians adhering to the said treaty at Carlton and Fort Pitt on
the dates above mentioned; and further, do solemnly engage to abide
by, carry out and fulfil all the stipulations, obligations and
conditions contained on the part of the Indians therein named, to
be observed and performed, and in all things to conform to the
articles of the said treaty, as if the said "Little Pine" and
Pap-a-way or "the Lucky Man," and the Bands whom they represent had
been originally contracting parties thereto, and had been present
at the treaty at Carlton and Fort Pitt, and had there attached
their signatures to the said treaty.</p>
                     <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Edgar Dewdney, Indian Commissioner for the
North-west Territories, and the said "Little Pine" and Pap-a-way or
"the Lucky Man," Headmen of the said Bands, hereby giving their
adhesion to the said treaty, have hereunto subscribed and set their
hands at Fort Walsh, in the said North-west Territories, this
second day of July, in the year of Our Lord one thousand eight
hundred and seventy-nine.</p>


<p>
Signed by
by the
parties hereto,
in the<lb/>
presence of
the undersigned
wit<lb break="no"/>nesses, the same
having been ex<lb break="no"/>plained to the Indians by the said
Edgar Dewdney, Esq., Indian
Commr., through the interpreters,
Edwd. McKay and P. Leveille.</p>


<p><persName ref="pers:MCLE13">JAMES F. MCLEOD</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:IRVI3">A. G. IRVINE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Assistant Commissioner N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:NORM1">FRANK NORMAN</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Staff Constable .N.W.M.P.</hi></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:DEWD1">EDGAR DEWDNEY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Indian
Commissioner</hi>.</p>
<p>"<persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Little Pine</persName>." his x mark.</p>
<p>"<persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">THE LUCKY MAN</persName>." his x mark.</p>


                     </div>


                     <div type="section">
<head>ADHESION BY CREE INDIANS</head>


                     <p>WHEREAS, Big Bear, a Cree Chief, on behalf of his Band,
comprising thirty lodges, inhabitants of the country covered by the
treaty commonly known as "Treaty Number Six," made between Her
Majesty the Queen, by Her Commissioners the Honourable Alexander
Morris, the Honourable James McKay and the Honourable William
Joseph Christie, of the one part, and Plain and Wood Cree Tribe of
Indians of the other part at Carlton, on the twenty-third and
twenty-eighth days of August, and near Fort Pitt on the ninth day
of September, in the year of Our Lord one thousand eight hundred
and seventy-six, who have not yet given in their adhesion to the
said Treaty, have presented themselves to Allan Macdonald, Esq.,
Indian Agent of Treaty Number Four, and expressed a desire to join
in the same treaty; and whereas the said Indian Agent has
recognized the said "Big Bear" as the Chief of their Band.</p>
                     <p>NOW THIS INSTRUMENT WITNESSETH, that the said "Big Bear," for
himself and on behalf of the Band which he represents, does
transfer, surrender and relinquish to Her Majesty the Queen, Her
heirs and successors, to and for the use of Her Government of the
Dominion of Canada, all his right, title and interest whatsoever,
which he has held or enjoyed, of, in and to the territory described
and fully set out in the said treaty; also all his right, title and
interest whatsoever to all other lands wherever situated, whether
within the limits of any other treaty heretofore made or hereafter
to be made with Indians, or elsewhere in Her Majesty's territories.
To have and to hold the same unto and for the use of Her Majesty
the Queen, Her heirs and successors forever. And do hereby agree to
accept the several benefits, payments and reserves promised to the
Indians, adhering to the said treaty at Carlton and Fort Pitt on
the dates above mentioned; and further, do solemnly engage to abide
by, carry out and fulfil all the stipulations, obligations and
conditions contained on the part of the Indians therein named, to
be observed and performed, and in all things to conform to the
articles of the said treaty as if the said "Big Bear" and the Band
which he represents had been originally contracting parties
thereto, and had been present at the treaty at Carlton and Fort
Pitt, and had then attached his signature to the said treaty as
Chief of the said Band.</p>
                     <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Allan Mcdonald, Esquire, Indian Agent, and
the said "Big Bear," Chief of the said Band, hereby giving his
adhesion to the said treaty, have hereunto subscribed and set their
hands at Fort Walsh, in the said North-West Territories, this
eighth day of December, in the year of Our Lord one thousand eight
hundred and eighty-two.</p>
                    
<p>Signed by the parties hereto, in the pres<lb break="no"/>ence of the undersigned witnesses, the<lb/>
same having been explained to the<lb/>
Indians by the said Allan Macdonald,<lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Esq</hi>., Indian Agent, through the In<lb break="no"/>terpreter, Peter Hourie and Louis<lb/>
Leveillee.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:IRVI3">A.G. IRVINE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut.-Col., Com. N.WM.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:COTT1">JOHN COTTON</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Superintendent and Adjutant, N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:JAKE1">AUGUSTUS JAKES</persName>, M.B., F.S.C., Lond., <hi rendition="simple:italic">Surgeon, N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:NORM1">FRANK NORMAN</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Inspector, N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SHUR1">A. SHURTLIFF</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Superintendent, N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ABBO3">W.R. ABBOTT</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Sergeant-Major, N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ROUT1">W. ROUTLEDGE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Corporal, N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MACD18">ALLAN MACDONALD</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Indian Agent, Treaty No.</hi> 4.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BIGB1">Big Bear</persName>, his x mark, <hi rendition="simple:italic">(Chief.)</hi></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:TANN1">Joe Tanner</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:HOUR1">Peter Hourie</persName>,</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:LEVE2">Louis Leveillee</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:PIEA1">PIE A POT</persName>, his x mark, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief</hi>.</p>

                     </div>
                     <div type="section">
<head>ADHESION BY CREE INDIANS</head>


                     <p>We the undersigned Chiefs and Headmen, on behalf of ourselves
and the other members of the Wood Cree Tribe of Indians, having had
explained to us the terms of the treaty made and concluded near
Carlton, on the 23rd day of August and on 28th day of said month
respectively, and near Fort Pitt on the 9th day of September, 1876,
between Her Majesty the Queen, by the Commissioners duly appointed
to negotiate the said treaty, and the Plain and Wood Cree and other
Tribes of Indians inhabiting the country within the limits defined
in said treaty, but not having been present at the councils at
which the articles of the said treaty were agreed upon, do now
hereby for ourselves and the Bands which we represent, in
consideration of the provisions of the said treaty being extended
to us and the Bands which we represent, transfer, surrender, and
relinquish to Her Majesty the Queen, Her heirs and successors, to
and for the use of the Government of the Dominion of Canada, all
our right, title and interest whatsoever which we and the said
Bands which we represent hold and enjoy, or have held and enjoyed,
of, in and to the territory included within the following limits:
All and singular that portion or tract of land being the north part
of the Land District of Prince Albert, as shown on the maps
published by the Honourable the Minister of the Interior, dated at
Ottawa on the 31st day of August, 1885; the same tract being north
of the northerly limit of Treaty No.6, North-West Territory,
containing 11,066 square miles, be the same more or less, and more
particularly described as follows: Commencing at a point being the
north-west corner of projected Township No. 70, Range 10, west of
the Third Initial Meridian; thence easterly along the northern
boundaries of projected Townships Nos. 70 to the north-east corner
of projected Township No. 70, Range 13, west of the Second Initial
Meridian; thence southerly following the east boundary of said 13th
Range of projected Townships to the northern limits of Treaty No.
6. into the projected Township No. 60; thence westerly following
the northerly limit of Treaty No. 6 to the south-eastern shore of
Green Lake, being at the north-easterly part of projected Township
No. 58, Range 10, west of the Third Initial Meridian; thence
following the westerly shore of Green Lake to the main inlet
thereof known as Beaver River; thence up the right bank of Beaver
River to its intersection with the west boundary of projected
Township No. 62, Range 10, west of the Third Initial Meridian;
thence northerly following the west boundary of projected townships
of Range 10, west of the Third Initial Meridian, to the point of
commencement.</p>
                     <p>Also, all our right, title and interest whatsoever to all other
lands wherever situated, whether within the limits of any other
treaty heretofore made, or hereafter to be made with Indians, and
whether the said lands are situated in the North-West Territories
of elsewhere in Her Majesty's Dominion, to have and to hold the
same unto and for the use of Her Majesty the Queen, Her heirs and
successors forever.</p>
                     <p>And we hereby agree to accept the several benefits, payments and
reserves promised to the Indians adhering to the said treaty at
Fort Pitt or Carlton; with the proviso as regards the amount to be
expended annually for ammunition and twine, and as respects the
amount to be expended for three years annually in provisions for
the use of such Indians as are settled on reserves and are engaged
in cultivating the soil, to assist them in such cultivation, that
the expenditure on both of these items shall bear the same
proportion to the number of Indians now treated with as the amounts
for those two items as mentioned in Treaty No. 6 bore to the number
of Indians then treated with. And we solemnly engage to abide by,
carry out and fulfil all the stipulations, obligations and
conditions therein contained on the part of the Chiefs and Indians
therein named to be observed and performed, and we agree in all
things to conform to the articles of the said treaty, as if we
ourselves and the Bands which we represent had been originally
contracting parties thereto and had been present at the council
held near Fort Pitt or near Carlton and had there attached our
signatures to the said treaty.</p>
                     <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Her Majesty's special Commissioners and the
Chiefs and Councillors of the Bands hereby giving their adhesion to
the said treaty have hereunto subscribed and set their hands at
Montreal Lake this eleventh day of February, in the year of Our
Lord one thousand eight hundred and eighty-nine.</p>

<p>Signed by the parties hereto in the pre<lb break="no"/>sence of the undersigned witnesses,<lb/>
the same having been first explained<lb/>
to the Indians by the Venerable Arch<lb break="no"/>deacon Mackay:</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:IRVI3">A.G. Irvine</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lt.-Colonel, Commissioner</hi>.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GOUL1">R. GOULET</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner</hi>.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCNE2">A.J. MCNEILL</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Indian Department</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MOBE1">H.J. MOBERLY</persName>, C. F., H. B. Co.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ALEX2">H.H. ALEXANDER</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Sergt., N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ALLO1">C.V. ALLOWAY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MACK7">J.A. MACKAY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Archdeacon of Saskatchewan</hi>.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Chiefs</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:ROBE3">JAMES ROBERTS</persName>,</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR3">WILLIAM CHARLES</persName>, his x mark.</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Councillors of James Roberts' Band</hi>.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR4">AMOS CHARLES</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:CHAR5">JOSEPH CHARLES</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:ROBE4">ELIAS ROBERTS</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:COOK4">JOHN COOK</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD3">BENJAMIN BIRD</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD4">ISAAC BIRD</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD5">PATRICK BIRD</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD6">MOSES BIRD</persName>, his x mark.</p>

                     </div>

<div type="section">
                  <head>Adhesions to Treaty Number
Six</head>
                

                     <p>
                        WHEREAS we the undersigned Chiefs and Headmen
have had communication of the treaty commonly known as Treaty
Number Six made between Her Majesty Queen Victoria and certain
tribes of Indians at Carlton and Fort Pitt, in the year of Our Lord
one thousand eight hundred and seventy-six, and of the intention of
His Most Gracious Majesty King George VI, by the Grace of God of
Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond Seas, King,
Defender of the Faith, Emperor of India, to extend its provisions
to us through His Commissioners, Malcolm McCrimmon and John Lothrop
Grew, both of the City of Ottawa;</p>
                     <p>
                        NOW THEREFORE we the said Chiefs and Headmen
hereby for ourselves and the Indians whom we represent, in
consideration of the provisions of the said treaty being extended
to us and the Indians whom we represent, cede, transfer, surrender
and relinquish to His Majesty the King, His heirs and successors,
forever, all our right, title and privileges whatsoever to all
lands in His Majesty's Dominions;</p>
                     <p>
                     AND we hereby agree to accept the several
provisions, payments and reserves of the said treaty as therein
stated, and solemnly promise and engage to abide by and carry our
all the stipulations and obligations therein contained, to be
observed and performed by the Chiefs and Indians therein named, and
in all things to conform to the articles of the said treaty, as if
we ourselves and the Indians whom we represent had originally been
contracting parties thereto;</p>
                     <p>
                       AND His Majesty, the King, by His
representatives, aforesaid, agrees that all the payments and
provisions named in the said treaty to be made to each Chief and
his Band shall be faithfully made and fulfilled to the aforesaid
Chiefs and Headmen and the Indians whom they represent;</p>
                     <p>
                       IN WITNESS WHEREOF, His Majesty's Commissioners
and the said Chiefs and Headmen have set their hands as hereinafter
set forth.</p>
    
<p>Signed at Rocky Mountain House on the 25th<lb/>
day of May, 1944, by His Majesty's Commissioners<lb/>
and the Chief and Headmen representing the Band or<lb/>
group of Cree Indians comprising some<lb/>
families located by the Baptiste River, in the<lb/>
Province of Alberta, in the presence of the under<lb break="no"/>signed witnesses after having been first interpreted<lb/>
and explained.</p>

<p>Witnesses:</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:WHIT11">John R. White</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MILL8">RAM Miller</persName>. Esq<lb/>
R.C.M. Police<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:STEL1">Henry Stelfox</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MACK8">Rev. W.A. Mackenzie</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:PICH3">Rev. Rob R. Piche</persName> </p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCR3">M. McCrimmon</persName> <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GREW1">J.L. Grew</persName> <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:SUNC1">L. Sunchild</persName></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:NAPA1">Napaysis</persName> [in syllabic characters]</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:EYES2">J. Yellow Eyes</persName></p>

</div>

<div type="section">
<p>Signed at Rocky Mountain house on the 12th<lb/>
day of May, 1950, by His Majesty's Commissioner<lb/>
and the Indians of, the Band or group of Chippewa Indians<lb/>
located at Rocky Mountain House<lb/>
 in the Province of Alberta, in the presence of the<lb/>
undersigned witnesses after having been first interpreted<lb/>
and explained.</p>

<p>Witnesses:</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MCCR3">M. McCrimmon</persName> <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner</hi></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:GOOD4">G.K. Gooderham</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HALL3">John H. Hall</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:STEL1">Henry Stelfox</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCIR1">J.G. McIlroy</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BHAN1">B.A. Bhanz</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DONA1">Ed Donald</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MOOR4">Harold Moore</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GRAN8">N de Grandmaison</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:DAYC1">James Daychief</persName> his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:DAYC2">Thomas Daychief</persName> his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:STRA1">Simon Strawberry</persName> his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BEAV2">James Beaverbones</persName> his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:WHIT12">Alex Whitford</persName> his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:STRA2">Frank Strawberry</persName> his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:STRA3">Andrew Strawberry</persName> his x mark</p>

<p>Witnesses:</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:GOOD4">G. Kent Gooderham</persName>
<persName ref="pers:SORE1">L.H. Sorenson</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DESC2">Joe Deschamps</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BULM1">Sam S. Bulmer</persName>
<persName ref="pers:STEL1">Henry Stelfox</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:STEL1">Henry Stelfox</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:STEL1">Henry Stelfox</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:STEL1">Henry Stelfox</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ANDE4">Eva Macdonald Anderson</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCLE16">Ida Mae McLeod</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BRIM1">Joseph Brimmis</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:WAWA2">Wawakachin</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BRIM2">Thomas Brimmis</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:STRA4">Jimmie Strawberry</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:CHAK2">Chakasee</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MUSK1">John Muskeg</persName>, also called Barp[?] , his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MUSK2">No Case Muskeg</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:STRA5">Susie Strawberry</persName>, her x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:STRA6">Josie Strawberry</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MUSK3">John Muskeg</persName>

</p>

</div>

<div type="section">



            <head>Adhesion to Treaty Number Six</head>
                     

                     <p>WHEREAS we the undersigned Chief and Headmen have had
communication of the treaty commonly known as Treaty Number Six
made between Her Majesty Queen Victoria and certain tribes of
Indians at Carlton and Fort Pitt, in the year of Our Lord one
thousand eight hundred and seventy-six, and of the intention of His
Most Gracious Majesty the King George VI, by the Grace of God of
Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas,
King, Defender of the Faith, to extend its provisions to us through
His Commissioner, James Pember Brookbank Ostrander, of the City of
Regina;</p>
                     <p>NOW THEREFORE we the said Chief and Headmen hereby for ourselves
and the Indians whom we represent, in consideration of the
provisions of the said treaty being extended to us and the Indians
whom we represent, cede, transfer, surrender and relinquish to His
Majesty the King, His heirs and successors, forever, all our right,
title and privileges whatsoever to all lands in His Majesty's
Dominions;</p>
                     <p>AND we hereby agree to accept the several provisions, payments
and reserves of the said treaty as therein stated, and solemnly
promise and engage to abide by and carry out all the stipulations
and obligations therein contained, to be observed and performed by
the Chiefs and Indians therein named, and in all things to conform
to the articles of the said treaty, as if we ourselves and the
Indians whom we represent had originally been contracting parties
thereto;</p>
                     <p>AND His Majesty the King, by his representative, aforesaid,
agrees that all the payments and provisions named in the said
treaty to be made to each Chief and his Band shall be faithfully
made and fulfilled to the aforesaid Chief and Headmen and the
Indians whom they represent;</p>
                     <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, His Majesty's Commissioner and the said
Chief and Headmen have set their hands as hereinafter set
forth.</p>

<p>Signed at Witchekan Lake on the twenty-first<lb/>
day of November 1950, by His Majesty's <lb/>
Commissioner and the Chief and Headmen representing the<lb/>
Band or group of Cree Indians comprising some<lb/>
fourteen families located on the Witchekan Lake Indian Reserve in the Province of Saskatchewan, in the<lb/>
presence of the undersigned witnesses after having been<lb/>
first interpreted and explained.</p>

<p>Witnesses:</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MCLE15">A.J. McLeod</persName>. <persName ref="pers:WARD3">J.T. Warden</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:OSTR1">J.P.B. Ostrander</persName>, Commissioner</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:THOM12">Louis Thomas</persName>, his x mark.</p>


<p>Witnesses:</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:MCCR3">M. McCrimmon</persName> <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner</hi></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MCLE15">A.J. McLeod</persName>
<persName ref="pers:WARD3">J.T. Warden</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SUIE1">N.B. Suiers</persName>, M.D.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GRAN9">V.M. Gran</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCDO22">R.J. McDonald</persName>
<persName ref="pers:LIES1">C.J.W. Liesss</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:THOM11">Emma Thomas</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM12">Louie Thomas</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BEAR5">Jack Bear</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BEAR6">Pete Bear</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:JIM1">Shorty Jim</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:THOM13">George Thomas</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:THOM14">John Thomas</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p>Witnesses:</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BEAR8">Annie Bear</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WARD3">J.T. Warden</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:THOM15">Joe Thomas</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:BEAR7">Paddy Bear</persName>, his x mark</p>

</div>

<div type="section">
                       <head>Adhesion to Treaty Number Six</head>
               

                     <p>WHEREAS we the undersigned Indians have had communication of the
treaty commonly known as Treaty Number Six made between Her Majesty
Queen Victoria and certain tribes of Indians at Carlton and Fort
Pitt, in the year of Our Lord one thousand eight hundred and
seventy-six, and of the intention of Her Most Gracious Majesty
Queen Elizabeth the Second, by the Grace of God of the United
Kingdom, Canada and Her other Realms and Territories, Queen, Head
of the Commonwealth, Defender of the Faith, to extend its
provisions to us through His Commissioner, Malcom McCrimmon, of the
City of Ottawa;</p>
                     <p>NOW THEREFORE we the said Indians hereby in consideration of the
provisions of the said treaty being extended to us cede, transfer,
surrender and relinquish to Her Majesty the Queen, Her heirs and
successors, forever, all our right title and privileges whatsoever
to all lands in Canada;</p>
                     <p>AND we hereby agree to accept the several provisions, payments
and reserves of the said treaty as therein stated, and solemnly
promise and engage to abide by and carry out all the stipulations
and obligations therein contained, to be observed and performed by
the Chiefs and Indians therein named, and in all things to conform
to the articles of the said treaty, as if we ourselves had
originally been contracting parties thereto;</p>
                     <p>AND Her Majesty the Queen, by Her representative, aforesaid,
agrees that all the payments and provisions named in the said
treaty to be made to each Chief and his Band shall be faithfully
made and fulfilled to the aforesaid Indians.</p>
                     <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Her Majesty's Commissioner and the said
Indians have set their hands as hereinafter set forth.</p>

<p>Signed at Cochin on the 18th<lb/>
day of August 1954, by Her Majesty's<lb/>
Commissioner and the Indians of the Saulteaux Band<lb/>
comprising some families located on the<lb/>
Saulteaux Indian Reserve in the Province of Saskatchewan,<lb/>
in the presence of the undersigned witnesses after having<lb/>
been first interpreted and explained.</p>

<p>Witnesses:</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:MCCR3">M. McCrimmon</persName> <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner</hi></p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:BELL9">Harvey J. Bell</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:COCK6">Wm. Cockburn</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:COCK6">Wm. Cockburn</persName> <lb/>

<persName ref="pers:BELL9">H.J. Bell</persName> <lb/>

<persName ref="pers:BELL9">H.J. Bell</persName> <lb/>

<persName ref="pers:FRAS7">T. Fraser</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FRAS7">T. Fraser</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FRAS7">T. Fraser</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FRAS7">T. Fraser</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MART10">Alex Martell</persName></p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:KACH2">Alex Kacheech</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:WAHP3">George Wahpansee</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:NIGH1">John Night</persName></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:NIGH2">Jim Night</persName></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:NIGH3">Job Night</persName></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:THOM16">Harry Thomas</persName>, his x mark</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:GOPH1">Richard Gopher</persName>, his x mark.</p>
<p><persName ref="pers:KATC2">Joe Katcheech</persName></p>
<p><persName ref="pers:GOPH2">Bill Gopher</persName></p>

<p>
Witnesses:</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BELL15">A.S. Bell</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FRAS7">T Fraser</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BELL15">A.S. Bell</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MART10">Alex Martell</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FRAS7">T Fraser</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BELL15">A.S. Bell</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FRAS7">T Fraser</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:RAE2">A.G. Rae</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:RAE2">A.G. Rae</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:RAE2">A.G. Rae</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:COCK6">Wm. Cockburn</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BELL15">A.S. Bell</persName> <lb/>
</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:GOPH3">Clara Gopher</persName>, her x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KATC3">Helen Katcheech</persName>, her x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:NIGH4">Bill Night</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:IRON3">Joseph Ironbow</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:GOPH4">Alex Gopher</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MOCA1">Alex Mocassin</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:GOPH5">Annie Gopher</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:IRON4">Margaret Ironbow</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KACH3">Mary Kacheech</persName>, her x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KATC5">Francis Katchich</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:GOPH6">Jim Gopher</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:WEAG1">Archie Weaganase</persName> </p>

</div>

<div type="section">

<p>Signed at Cochin on the 15th day<lb/>
of May 1956, by the following members<lb/>
of the Saulteaux Indian Band in the Province of Saskatchewan<lb/>
in the presence of the undersigned witnesses, after having<lb/>
been first interpreted and explained.</p>

<p>Witnesses:</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BERG3">Cst. RW Berggren</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WARD3">J.T. Warden</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WARD3">J.T. Warden</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:COCK6">Wm. Cockburn</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MART9">Joe Martel</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MART9">Joe Martel</persName> </p>

<p><persName ref="pers:SWIM1">John Swimmer</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:SWIM2">Johnnie Swimmer</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KATC4">George Katchuch</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:SWIM3">Bennie Swimmer</persName></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MOCA2">Francis Mocassin</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MOCA3">Stan Mocassin</persName>, his x mark</p>


</div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
