<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="treaty_08"
     type="full">
<teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreaty">Treaty Document(s)</name>, <date when="1899-06-21">21 June 1899</date>, Treaty No. 8 and Adhesions, Reports, Etc.</title>
        

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName></respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion from HTML to TEI</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLM3">Martin Holmes</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">LAYOUT IS NOT EXACTLY LIKE ORIGINAL</hi></p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <title>Treaty No. 8</title>.
                    

          <date when="1966"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Roger Duhamel, F.R.S.C. Queen's Printer and Controller of Stationery</publisher>.
          
  <orgName>
               
                  <orgName xml:lang="en">Indigenous and Northern Affairs Canada</orgName>
               </orgName>
        
        </bibl>
 

            <list>
               <item>
                <ptr target="https://www.aadnc-aandc.gc.ca/eng/1100100028813/1100100028853"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-11-21">Transformed original HTML to TEI.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treaty">
         

               

                  <head>Order In Council Setting Up Commission
for Treaty 8</head>
            

                     <p>
                       P.C. No. 2749
                     </p>

                     <p>On a report dated 30th November, 1898, from the Superintendent
General of Indian Affairs, stating with reference to his report of
the 18th June, 1898, upon which was based the Minute of Council
approved on the 27th of the same month, authorizing the appointing
of Commissioners to negotiate a treaty with the Indians occupying
territory to the north of that already ceded and shown in pink on
the attached map, that in that report it was set forth that the
Commissioner of the North West Mounted Police had pointed out the
desirability of steps being taken for the making of a treaty with
the Indians occupying the proposed line of route from Edmonton to
Pelly River; that he had intimated that these Indians, as well as
the Beaver Indians of the Peace and Nelson Rivers, and the Sicamas
and Nihames Indians, were inclined to be turbulent and were liable
to give trouble to isolated parties of miners or traders who might
be regarded by the Indians as interfering with what they considered
their vested rights; and that he had stated that the situation was
made more difficult by the presence of the numerous travellers who
had come into the country and were scattered at various points
between Lesser Slave Lake and Peace River.</p>
                     <p>The Minister further states that the view of the Commissioner of
the North West Mounted Police as to the desirability of making a
treaty with these Indians being concurred in by the Indian
Commissioner, and the Minister being convinced that in the public
interest it was necessary to take at the earliest possible date the
suggested step, it was recommended that Commissioners be appointed
with full power to negotiate a treaty. An Order in Council as above
stated, issued accordingly; and the preliminary arrangements are
now being made.</p>
                     <p>The Minister, in this connection, draws attention to the fact
that part of the territory marked "A" on the plan attached is
within the boundaries of the Province of British Columbia, and that
in the past no treaties such as have been made with the Indians of
the North West have been made with any of the Indians whose habitat
is west of the Mountains. An arrangement was come to in 1876 under
which the British Columbia Government agreed to the setting aside
by a Commission subject to the approval of that Government, of land
which might be considered necessary for Indian reserves in
different parts of the Province, and later on the agreement was
varied so as to provide that the setting apart should be made by a
Commissioner appointed by the Dominion Government whose allotment
would be subject to the approval of the Commissioner of Lands and
Works of the Province.</p>
                     <p>As the Indians to the west of the Mountains are quite distinct
from those whose habitat is on the eastern side thereof, no
difficulty ever arose in consequence of the different methods of
dealing with the Indians on either side of the Mountains. But there
can be no doubt that had the division line between the Indians been
artificial instead of natural, such difference in treatment would
have been fraught with grave danger and have been the fruitful
source of much trouble to both the Dominion and the Provincial
Governments.</p>
                     <p>The Minister submits that it will neither be politic nor
practicable to exclude from the treaty Indians whose habitat is in
the territory lying between the height of land and the eastern
boundary of British Columbia, as they know nothing of the
artificial boundary, and, being allied to the Indians of Athabasca,
will look for the same treatment as is given to the Indians whose
habitat is in that district.</p>
                     <p>Although the rule has been laid down by the Judicial Committee
of the Privy Council that the Province benefitting by a surrender
of Indian title should bear the burdens incident to that surrender,
he the Minister after careful consideration does not think it
desirable that any demand should be made upon the Province of
British Columbia for any money payment in connection with the
proposed treaty.</p>
                     <p>That from the information in possession of the Department of
Indian Affairs it is not at present clear whether it will be
necessary to set apart any land for a reserve or reserves for
Indians in that part of the Province of British Columbia which will
be covered by the proposed treaty, but if the Commissioners should
find it necessary to agree to the setting apart of any reserve or
reserves in that territory, the Minister is of opinion that the
same may properly be set aside under the agreement of 1876 already
referred to.</p>
                     <p>As it is in the interest of the Province of British Columbia, as
well as in that of the Dominion, that the country to be treated for
should be thrown open to development and the lives and property of
those who may enter therein safeguarded by the making of provision
which will remove all hostile feeling from the minds of the Indians
and lead them to peacefully acquiesce in the changing conditions,
he the Minister would suggest that the Government of British
Columbia be apprised of the intention to negotiate the proposed
treaty; and as it is of the utmost importance that the
Commissioners should have full power to give such guarantees as may
be found necessary in regard to the setting apart of land for
reserves the Minister further recommends that the Government of
British Columbia be asked to formally acquiesce in the action taken
by Your Excellency's Government in the matter and to intimate its
readiness to confirm any reserves which it may be found necessary
to set apart within the portion of the Province already
described.</p>
                     <p>The Minister further recommends that a certified copy of this
Minute, if approved, and of the map attached hereto be transmitted
to the Lieutenant Governor of the Province of British Columbia for
the information of his Government.</p>
                     <p>The Committee submit the same for Your Excellency's
approval.</p>
                

                        <p>(sgd.) <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">R. W. SCOTT</persName>.</p>

<div type="section">

                  <head>Report of Commissioners for Treaty No.
8</head>
       

                        <p>WINNIPEG, MANITOBA, 22nd September, 1899.</p>
              

                     <p>The Honourable<lb/>
CLIFFORD SIFTON,<lb/>
Superintendent General of Indian Affairs,<lb/>
Ottawa.</p>
                     <p>SIR, --- We have the honour to transmit herewith the treaty
which, under the Commission issued to us on the 5th day of April
last, we have made with the Indians of the provisional district of
Athabasca and parts of the country adjacent thereto, as described
in the treaty and shown on the map attached.</p>
                     <p>The date fixed for meeting the Indians at Lesser Slave Lake was
the 8th of June, 1899. Owing, however, to unfavourable weather and
lack of boatmen, we did not reach the point until the 19th. But one
of the Commissioners Mr. Ross --- who went overland from Edmonton
to the Lake, was fortunately present when the Indians first
gathered. He was thus able to counteract the consequences of the
delay and to expedite the work of the Commission by preliminary
explanations of its objects.</p>
                     <p>We met the Indians on the 20th, and on the 21st the treaty was
signed.</p>
                     <p>As the discussions at the different points followed on much the
same lines, we shall confine ourselves to a general statement of
their import. There was a marked absence of the old Indian style of
oratory. Only among the Wood Crees were any formal speeches made,
and these were brief. The Beaver Indians are taciturn. The
Chipewyans confined themselves to asking questions and making brief
arguments. They appeared to be more adept at cross-examination than
at speech-making, and the Chief at Fort Chipewyan displayed
considerable keenness of intellect and much practical sense in
pressing the claims of his band. They all wanted as liberal, if not
more liberal terms, than were granted to the Indians of the plains.
Some expected to be fed by the Government after the making of
treaty, and all asked for assistance in season of distress and
urged that the old and indigent who were no longer able to hunt and
trap and were consequently often in distress should be cared for by
the Government. They requested that medicines be furnished. At
Vermilion, Chipewyan and Smith's Landing, an earnest appeal was
made for the services of a medical man. There was expressed at
every point the fear that the making of the treaty would be
followed by the curtailment of the hunting and fishing privileges,
and many were impressed with the notion that the treaty would lead
to taxation and enforced military service. They seemed desirous of
securing educational advantages for their children, but stipulated
that in the matter of schools there should be no interference with
their religious beliefs.</p>
                     <p>We pointed out that the Government could not undertake to
maintain Indians in idleness; that the same means of earning a
livelihood would continue after the treaty as existed before it,
and that the Indians would be expected to make use of them. We told
them that the Government was always ready to give relief in cases
of actual destitution, and that in seasons of distress they would
without any special stipulation in the treaty receive such
assistance as it was usual to give in order to prevent starvation
among Indians in any part of Canada; and we stated that the
attention of the Government would be called to the need of some
special provision being made for assisting the old and indigent who
were unable to work and dependent on charity for the means of
sustaining life. We promised that supplies of medicines would be
put in the charge of persons selected by the Government at
different points, and would be distributed free to those of the
Indians who might require them. We explained that it would be
practically impossible for the Government to arrange for regular
medical attendance upon Indians so widely scattered over such an
extensive territory. We assured them, however, that the Government
would always be ready to avail itself of any opportunity of
affording medical service just as it provided that the physician
attached to the Commission should give free attendance to all
Indians whom he might find in need of treatment as he passed
through the country.</p>
                     <p>Our chief difficulty was the apprehension that the hunting and
fishing privileges were to be curtailed. The provision in the
treaty under which ammunition and twine is to be furnished went far
in the direction of quieting the fears of the Indians, for they
admitted that it would be unreasonable to furnish the means of
hunting and fishing if laws were to be enacted which would make
hunting and fishing so restricted as to render it impossible to
make a livelihood by such pursuits. But over and above the
provision, we had to solemnly assure them that only such laws as to
hunting and fishing as were in the interest of the Indians and were
found necessary in order to protect the fish and fur-bearing
animals would be made, and that they would be as free to hunt and
fish after the treaty as they would be if they never entered into
it.</p>
                     <p>We assured them that the treaty would not lead to any forced
interference with their mode of life, that it did not open the way
to the imposition of any tax, and that there was no fear of
enforced military service. We showed them that, whether treaty was
made or not, they were subject to the law, bound to obey it, and
liable to punishment for any infringements of it. We pointed out
that the law was designed for the protection of all, and must be
respected by all the inhabitants of the country, irrespective of
colour or origin; and that, in requiring them to live at peace with
white men who came into the country, and not to molest them in
person or in property, it only required them to do what white men
were required to do as to the Indians.</p>
                     <p>As to education the Indians were assured that there was no need
of any special stipulation, as it was the policy of the Government
to provide in every part of the country, as far as circumstances
would permit, for the education of Indian children, and that the
law, which was as strong as a treaty, provided for non-interference
with the religion of the Indians in schools maintained or assisted
by the Government.</p>
                     <p>We should add that the chief of the Chipewyans of Fort Chipewyan
asked that the Government should undertake to have a railway built
into the country, as the cost of goods which the Indians require
would be thereby cheapened and the prosperity of the country
enhanced. He was told that the Commissioners had no authority to
make any statement in the matter further than to say that his
desire would be made known to the Government.</p>
                     <p>When we conferred, after the first meeting with the Indians at
Lesser Slave Lake, we came to the conclusion that it would be best
to make one treaty covering the whole of the territory ceded, and
to take adhesions thereto from the Indians to be met at the other
points rather than to make several separate treaties. The treaty
was therefore so drawn as to provide three ways in which assistance
is to be given to the Indians, in order to accord with the
conditions of the country and to meet the requirements of the
Indians in the different parts of the territory.</p>
                     <p>In addition to the annuity, which we found it necessary to fix
at the figures of Treaty Six, which covers adjacent territory, the
treaty stipulates that assistance in the form of seed and
implements and cattle will be given to those of the Indians who may
take to farming, in the way of cattle and mowers to those who may
devote themselves to cattle-raising, and that ammunition and twine
will be given to those who continue to fish and hunt. The
assistance in farming and ranching is only to be given when the
Indians actually take to these pursuits, and it is not likely that
for many years there will be a call for any considerable
expenditure under these heads. The only Indians of the territory
ceded who are likely to take to cattle-raising are those about
Lesser Slave Lake and along the Peace River, where there is quite
an extent of ranching country; and although there are stretches of
cultivable land in those parts of the country, it is not probable
that the Indians will, while present conditions obtain, engage in
farming further than the raising of roots in a small way, as is now
done to some extent. In the main the demand will be for ammunition
and twine, as the great majority of the Indians will continue to
hunt and fish for a livelihood. It does not appear likely that the
conditions of the country on either side of the Athabasca and Slave
Rivers or about Athabasca Lake will be so changed as to affect
hunting or trapping, and it is safe to say that so long as the
fur-bearing animals remain, the great bulk of the Indians will
continue to hunt and to trap.</p>
                     <p>The Indians are given the option of taking reserves or land in
severalty. As the extent of the country treated for made it
impossible to define reserves or holdings, and as the Indians were
not prepared to make selections, we confined ourselves to an
undertaking to have reserves and holdings set apart in the future,
and the Indians were satisfied with the promise that this would be
done when required. There is no immediate necessity for the general
laying out of reserves or the allotting of land. It will be quite
time enough to do this as advancing settlement makes necessary the
surveying of the land. Indeed, the Indians were generally averse to
being placed on reserves. It would have been impossible to have
made a treaty if we had not assured them that there was no
intention of confining them to reserves. We had to very clearly
explain to them that the provision for reserves and allotments of
land were made for their protection, and to secure to them in
perpetuity a fair portion of the land ceded, in the event of
settlement advancing.</p>
                     <p>After making the treaty at Lesser Slave Lake it was decided
that, in order to offset the delay already referred to, it would be
necessary for the Commission to divide. Mr. Ross and Mr. McKenna
accordingly set out for Fort St. John on the 22nd of June. The date
appointed for meeting the Indians there was the 21st. When the
decision to divide was come to, a special messenger was despatched
to the Fort with a message to the Indians explaining the delay,
advising them that Commissioners were travelling to meet them, and
requesting them to wait at the Fort. Unfortunately the Indians had
dispersed and gone to their hunting grounds before the messenger
arrived and weeks before the date originally fixed for the meeting,
and when the Commissioners got within some miles of St. John the
messenger met them with a letter from the Hudson's Bay Company's
officer there advising them that the Indians after consuming all
their provisions, set off on the 1st June in four different bands
and in as many different directions for the regular hunt; that
there was not a man at St. John who knew the country and could
carry word of the Commissioners' coming, and even if there were it
would take three weeks or a month to get the Indians in. Of course
there was nothing to do but return. It may be stated, however, that
what happened was not altogether unforeseen. We had grave doubts of
being able to get to St. John in time to meet the Indians, but as
they were reported to be rather disturbed and ill-disposed on
account of the actions of miners passing through their country, it
was thought that it would be well to show them that the
Commissioners were prepared to go into their country, and that they
had put forth every possible effort to keep the engagement made by
the Government.</p>
                     <p>The Commissioners on their return from St. John met the Beaver
Indians of Dunvegan on the 21st day of June and secured their
adhesion to the treaty. They then proceeded to Fort Chipewyan to
Smith's Landing on the Slave River and secured the adhesion of the
Cree and Chipewyan Indians at these points on the 13th and 17th
days of July respectively.</p>
                     <p>In the meantime Mr. Laird met the Cree and Beaver Indians at
Peace River Landing and Vermilion, and secured their adhesion on
the 1st and 8th days of July respectively. He then proceeded to
Fond du Lac on Lake Athabasca, and obtained the adhesion of the
Chipewyan Indians there on the 25th and 27th days of July.</p>
                     <p>After treating with the Indians at Smith, Mr. Ross and Mr.
McKenna found it necessary to separate in order to make sure of
meeting the Indians at Wabiscow on the date fixed. Mr. McKenna
accordingly went to Fort McMurray, where he secured the adhesion of
the Chipewyan and Cree Indians on the 4th day of August, and Mr.
Ross proceeded to Wabiscow, where he obtained the adhesion of the
Cree Indians on the 14th day of August.</p>
                     <p>The Indians with whom we treated differ in may respects from the
Indians of the organized territories. They indulge in neither paint
nor feathers, and never clothe themselves in blankets. Their dress
is of the ordinary style and many of them were well clothed. In the
summer they live in teepees, but many of them have log houses in
which they live in winter. The Cree language is the chief language
of trade, and some of the Beavers and Chipewyans speak it in
addition to their own tongues. All the Indians we met were with
rare exceptions professing Christians, and showed evidences of the
work which missionaries have carried on among them for many years.
A few of them have had their children avail themselves of the
advantages afforded by boarding schools established at different
missions. None of the tribes appear to have any very definite
organization. They are held together mainly by the language bond.
The chiefs and headmen are simply the most efficient hunters and
trappers. They are not law-makers and leaders in the sense that the
chiefs and headmen of the plains and of old Canada were. The tribes
have no very distinctive characteristics, and as far as we could
learn no traditions of any import. The Wood Crees are an off-shoot
of the Crees of the South. The Beaver Indians bear some resemblance
to the Indians west of the mountains. The Chipewyans are physically
the superior tribe. The Beavers have apparently suffered most from
scrofula and phthisis, and there are marks of these diseases more
or less among all the tribes.</p>
                     <p>Although in manners and dress the Indians of the North are much
further advanced in civilization than other Indians were when
treaties were made with them, they stand as much in need of the
protection afforded by the law to aborigines as do any other
Indians of the country, and are as fit subjects for the paternal
care of the Government.</p>
                     <p>It may be pointed out that hunting in the North differs from
hunting as it was on the plains in that the Indians hunt in a
wooded country and instead of moving in bands go individually or in
family groups.</p>
                     <p>Our journey from point to point was so hurried that we are not
in a position to give any description of the country ceded which
would be of value. But we may say that about Lesser Slave Lake
there are stretches of country which appear well suited for
ranching and mixed farming; that on both sides of the Peace River
there are extensive prairies and some well wooded country; that at
Vermilion, on the Peace, two settlers have successfully carried on
mixed farming on a pretty extensive scale for several years, and
that the appearance of the cultivated fields of the Mission there
in July showed that cereals and roots were as well advanced as in
any portion of the organized territories. The country along the
Athabasca River is well wooded and there are miles of tar-saturated
banks. But as far as our restricted view of the Lake Athabasca and
Slave River country enabled us to judge, its wealth, apart from
possible mineral development, consists exclusively in its fisheries
and furs.</p>
                     <p>In going from Peace River Crossing to St. John, the trail which
is being constructed under the supervision of the Territorial
Government from moneys provided by Parliament was passed over. It
was found to be well located. The grading and bridge work is of a
permanent character, and the road is sure to be an important factor
in the development of the country.</p>
                     <p>We desire to express our high appreciation of the valuable and
most willing service rendered by Inspector Snyder and the corps of
police under him, and at the same time to testify to the efficient
manner in which the members of our staff performed their several
duties. The presence of a medical man was much appreciated by the
Indians, and Dr. West, the physician to the Commission, was most
assiduous in attending to the great number of Indians who sought
his services. We would add that the Very Reverend Father Lacombe,
who was attached to the Commission, zealously assisted us in
treating with the Crees.</p>
                  
<p rendition="simple:centre">The actual number of Indians paid
was:----</p>
   <table><row><cell>7</cell><cell>Chiefs at
$32.............................................................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$ 224 00</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>23</cell>
                           <cell>Headmen at
$22........................................................</cell>
                           <cell rendition="simple:right">506 00</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>2,187</cell>
                           <cell>Indians at
$12............................................................</cell>
                           <cell rendition="simple:right">26,244 00</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell></cell>
                           <cell rendition="simple:right">Total:</cell>
                           <cell rendition="simple:right">$26,974 00</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>

                     <p>A detailed statement of the Indians treated with and of the
money paid is appended.</p>
              

                        <p>We have the honour to be, sir,</p>
                  

                           <p>Your obedient servants,</p>
                   

                              <p><persName ref="pers:LAIR4">DAVID LAIRD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ROSS11">J. H. ROSS</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKE8">J. A. J. McKENNA</persName></p>
               
                                 <p>Indian Treaty Commissioners.</p>
                              
                        
</div>

<div type="section">
                  <head>Statement of Indians Paid Annuity and
Gratuity Moneys in Treaty No. 8, during 1899</head>
                 
<p rendition="simple:centre"><hi rendition="simple:italic">REPORT OF COMMISSIONERS</hi></p>
<p rendition="simple:centre">STATEMENT of Indians paid Annuity and Gratuity Moneys in Treaty No. 8, during 1899.</p>
<table>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">----</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Chiefs.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Head<lb break="no"/>men.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Other<lb/> Indians.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Cash<lb/> Paid each<lb/> Band.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Total<lb/> Cash<lb/> Paid.</cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">LESSER SLAVE LAKE</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$ cts.</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$ cts.</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Keenoaxtayo's Band (Crees)</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Chiefs at $32...........................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">32 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Headmen at $22..................</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">4</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">88 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
   <row><cell>Other Indians at $12...............</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">211</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,892 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">3,012 00</cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">PEACE RIVER LANDING</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Duncan Tastawit's Band (Crees and Beavers)-</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell>Headmen......................</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">22 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Other Indians...............</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">46</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">552 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">574 00</cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">VERMILION</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Ambroise Tete-Noire's Band (Beavers)-</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell>Chiefs...........................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">32 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Headmen......................</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">22 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Other Indians...............</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">148</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,776 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,830 00</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Tall Cree Band (Crees)-</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell>Headmen......................</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">22 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Other Indians...............</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">64</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">768 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">790 00</cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">DUNVEGAN</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Beaver Band-</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell>Headmen......................</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">22 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Other Indians...............</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">33</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">396 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">418 00</cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">RED RIVER POST, PEACE RIVER</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Crees paid as part of Band-Cree Band at Vermilion</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell>Indians...............</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">65</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">792 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">792 00</cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">FORT CHIPEWYAN</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Chipewyan Band-</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell>Chief...........................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">32 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Headmen......................</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">44 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Other Indians...............</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">407</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">4,884 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">4,960 00</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Cree Band-</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell>Chief...........................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">32 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Headmen......................</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">44 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Other Indians...............</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">183</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,196 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,272 00</cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">SMITH'S LANDING</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Chipewyan Band-</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell>Chief...........................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">32 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Headmen......................</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">44 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Other Indians...............</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">280</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">3,360 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">3,436 00</cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">FOND DU LAC</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Chipewyan Band-</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell>Chief...........................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">32 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Headmen......................</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">44 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Other Indians...............</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">376</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">4,512 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">4,588 00</cell></row>
</table>

<p rendition="simple:centre"><hi rendition="simple:italic">TREATY No. 8</hi></p>
<p rendition="simple:centre">STATEMENT of Indians paid Annuity and Gratuity, &amp;c.,-<hi rendition="simple:italic">Concluded</hi></p>

<table>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">----</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Chiefs.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Head<lb break="no"/>men.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Other<lb/> Indians.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Cash<lb/> Paid each<lb/> Band.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Total<lb/> Cash<lb/> Paid.</cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">FORT McMURRAY</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$ cts.</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$ cts.</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Cree and Chipewyan Bands-</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell>Headmen......................</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">44 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Other Indians...............</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">130</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,560 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,604 00</cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">WABISCOW</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Cree Band-</hi></cell><cell></cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell>Chief...........................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">4</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">32 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Headmen......................</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell>191</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">88 00</cell><cell></cell></row>
<row><cell>Other Indians...............</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,292 00</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,412 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Total..................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">7</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">23</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,187</cell><cell>.......</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">26,974 00</cell></row></table>

<p rendition="simple:centre">SUMMARY.</p>
<table>
<row><cell rendition="simple:right">7</cell><cell>Chiefs at $32.......................$</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">224 00</cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:right">23</cell><cell>Headmen at $22.....................$</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">506 00</cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">2,187</hi></cell><cell>Other Indians at $12..............$</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">26,224 00</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell rendition="simple:right">2,217</cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$26,974 00</cell></row>
</table>

<p rendition="simple:centre">Certified correct,</p>
<p rendition="simple:right"><persName ref="pers:LAIR4">DAVID LAIRD</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ROSS11">J.H. ROSS</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKE8">J.A.J. McKENNA</persName>,<lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Indian Treaty Commissioners</hi></p>

</div>

<div type="section">
                  <head>Treaty No. 8</head>
       

                     <p>ARTICLES OF A TREATY made and concluded at the several dates
mentioned therein, in the year of Our Lord one thousand eight
hundred and ninety-nine, between Her most Gracious Majesty the
Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, by Her Commissioners the
Honourable David Laird, of Winnipeg, Manitoba, Indian Commissioner
for the said Province and the Northwest Territories; James Andrew
Joseph McKenna, of Ottawa, Ontario, Esquire, and the Honourable
James Hamilton Ross, of Regina, in the Northwest Territories, of
the one part; and the Cree, Beaver, Chipewyan and other Indians,
inhabitants of the territory within the limits hereinafter defined
and described, by their Chiefs and Headmen, hereunto subscribed, of
the other part:</p>
                     <p>WHEREAS, the Indians inhabiting the territory hereinafter
defined have, pursuant to notice given by the Honourable
Superintendent General of Indian Affairs in the year 1898, been
convened to meet a Commission representing Her Majesty's Government
of the Dominion of Canada at certain places in the said territory
in this present year 1899, to deliberate upon certain matters of
interest of Her Most Gracious Majesty, of the one part, and the
said Indians of the other.</p>
                     <p>AND WHEREAS, the said Indians have been notified and informed by
Her Majesty's said Commission that it is Her desire to open for
settlement, immigration, trade, travel, mining, lumbering and such
other purposes as to Her Majesty may seem meet, a tract of country
bounded and described as hereinafter mentioned, and to obtain the
consent thereto of Her Indian subjects inhabiting the said tract,
and to make a treaty, and arrange with them, so that there may be
peace and good will between them and Her Majesty's other subjects,
and that Her Indian people may know and be assured of what
allowances they are to count upon and receive from Her Majesty's
bounty and benevolence.</p>
                     <p>AND WHEREAS, the Indians of the said tract, duly convened in
council at the respective points named hereunder, and being
requested by Her Majesty's Commissioners to name certain Chiefs and
Headmen who should be authorized on their behalf to conduct such
negotiations and sign any treaty to be founded thereon, and to
become responsible to Her Majesty for the faithful performance by
their respective bands of such obligations as shall be assumed by
them, the said Indians have therefore acknowledged for that purpose
the several Chiefs and Headmen who have subscribed hereto.</p>
                     <p>AND WHEREAS, the said Commissioners have proceeded to negotiate
a treaty with the Cree, Beaver, Chipewyan and other Indians,
inhabiting the district hereinafter defined and described, and the
same has been agreed upon and concluded by the respective bands at
the dates mentioned hereunder, the said Indians DO HEREBY CEDE,
RELEASE, SURRENDER AND YIELD UP to the Government of the Dominion
of Canada, for Her Majesty the Queen and Her successors for ever,
all their rights, titles and privileges whatsoever, to the lands
included within the following limits, that is to say:</p>
                     <p>Commencing at the source of the main branch of the Red Deer
River in Alberta, thence due west to the central range of the Rocky
Mountains, thence northwesterly along the said range to the point
where it intersects the 60th parallel of north latitude, thence
east along said parallel to the point where it intersects Hay
River, thence northeasterly down said river to the south shore of
Great Slave Lake, thence along the said shore northeasterly (and
including such rights to the islands in said lakes as the Indians
mentioned in the treaty may possess), and thence easterly and
northeasterly along the south shores of Christie's Bay and McLeod's
Bay to old Fort Reliance near the mouth of Lockhart's River, thence
southeasterly in a straight line to and including Black Lake,
thence southwesterly up the stream from Cree Lake, thence including
said lake southwesterly along the height of land between the
Athabasca and Churchill Rivers to where it intersects the northern
boundary of Treaty Six, and along the said boundary easterly,
northerly and southwesterly, to the place of commencement .</p>
                     <p>AND ALSO the said Indian rights, titles and privileges
whatsoever to all other lands wherever situated in the Northwest
Territories, British Columbia, or in any other portion of the
Dominion of Canada.</p>
                     <p>TO HAVE AND TO HOLD the same to Her Majesty the Queen and Her
successors for ever.</p>
                     <p>And Her Majesty the Queen HEREBY AGREES with the said Indians
that they shall have right to pursue their usual vocations of
hunting, trapping and fishing throughout the tract surrendered as
heretofore described, subject to such regulations as may from time
to time be made by the Government of the country, acting under the
authority of Her Majesty, and saving and excepting such tracts as
may be required or taken up from time to time for settlement,
mining, lumbering, trading or other purposes.</p>
                     <p>And Her Majesty the Queen hereby agrees and undertakes to lay
aside reserves for such bands as desire reserves, the same not to
exceed in all one square mile for each family of five for such
number of families as may elect to reside on reserves, or in that
proportion for larger or smaller families; and for such families or
individual Indians as may prefer to live apart from band reserves,
Her Majesty undertakes to provide land in severalty to the extent
of 160 acres to each Indian, the land to be conveyed with a proviso
as to non-alienation without the consent of the Governor General in
Council of Canada, the selection of such reserves, and lands in
severalty, to be made in the manner following, namely, the
Superintendent General of Indian Affairs shall depute and send a
suitable person to determine and set apart such reserves and lands,
after consulting with the Indians concerned as to the locality
which may be found suitable and open for selection.</p>
                     <p>Provided, however, that Her Majesty reserves the right to deal
with any settlers within the bounds of any lands reserved for any
band as She may see fit; and also that the aforesaid reserves of
land, or any interest therein, may be sold or otherwise disposed of
by Her Majesty's Government for the use and benefit of the said
Indians entitled thereto, with their consent first had and
obtained.</p>
                     <p>It is further agreed between Her Majesty and Her said Indian
subjects that such portions of the reserves and lands above
indicated as may at any time be required for public works,
buildings, railways, or roads of whatsoever nature may be
appropriated for that purpose by Her Majesty's Government of the
Dominion of Canada, due compensation being made to the Indians for
the value of any improvements thereon, and an equivalent in land,
money or other consideration for the area of the reserve so
appropriated.</p>
                     <p>And with a view to show the satisfaction of Her Majesty with the
behaviour and good conduct of Her Indians, and in extinguishment of
all their past claims, She hereby, through Her Commissioners,
agrees to make each Chief a present of thirty-two dollars in cash,
to each Headman twenty-two dollars, and to every other Indian of
whatever age, of the families represented at the time and place of
payment, twelve dollars.</p>
                     <p>Her Majesty also agrees that next year, and annually afterwards
for ever, She will cause to be paid to the said Indians in cash, at
suitable places and dates, of which the said Indians shall be duly
notified, to each Chief twenty-five dollars, each Headman, not to
exceed four to a large Band and two to a small Band, fifteen
dollars, and to every other Indian, of whatever age, five dollars,
the same, unless there be some exceptional reason, to be paid only
to heads of families for those belonging thereto.</p>
                     <p>FURTHER, Her Majesty agrees that each Chief, after signing the
treaty, shall receive a silver medal and a suitable flag, and next
year, and every third year thereafter, each Chief and Headman shall
receive a suitable suit of clothing.</p>
                     <p>FURTHER, Her Majesty agrees to pay the salaries of such teachers
to instruct the children of said Indians as to Her Majesty's
Government of Canada may seem advisable.</p>
                     <p>FURTHER, Her Majesty agrees to supply each Chief of a Band that
selects a reserve, for the use of that Band, ten axes, five
hand-saws, five augers, one grindstone, and the necessary files and
whetstones.</p>
                     <p>FURTHER, Her Majesty agrees that each Band that elects to take a
reserve and cultivate the soil, shall, as soon as convenient after
such reserve is set aside and settled upon, and the Band has
signified its choice and is prepared to break up the soil, receive
two hoes, one spade, one scythe and two hay forks for every family
so settled, and for every three families one plough and one harrow,
and to the Chief, for the use of his Band, two horses or a yoke of
oxen, and for each Band potatoes, barley, oats and wheat (if such
seed be suited to the locality of the reserve), to plant the land
actually broken up, and provisions for one month in the spring for
several years while planting such seeds; and to every family one
cow, and every Chief one bull, and one mowing-machine and one
reaper for the use of his Band when it is ready for them; for such
families as prefer to raise stock instead of cultivating the soil,
every family of five persons, two cows, and every Chief two bulls
and two mowing-machines when ready for their use, and a like
proportion for smaller or larger families. The aforesaid articles,
machines and cattle to be given once for all for the encouragement
of agriculture and stock raising; and for such Bands as prefer to
continue hunting and fishing, as much ammunition and twine for
making nets annually as will amount in value to one dollar per head
of the families so engaged in hunting and fishing.</p>
                     <p>And the undersigned Cree, Beaver, Chipewyan and other Indian
Chiefs and Headmen, on their own behalf and on behalf of all the
Indians whom they represent, DO HEREBY SOLEMNLY PROMISE and engage
to strictly observe this Treaty, and also to conduct and behave
themselves as good and loyal subjects of Her Majesty the Queen.</p>
                     <p>THEY PROMISE AND ENGAGE that they will, in all respects, obey
and abide by the law; that they will maintain peace between each
other, and between themselves and other tribes of Indians, and
between themselves and others of Her Majesty's subjects, whether
Indians, half-breeds or whites, this year inhabiting and hereafter
to inhabit any part of the said ceded territory; and that they will
not molest the person or property of any inhabitant of such ceded
tract, or of any other district or country, or interfere with or
trouble any person passing or travelling through the said tract or
any part thereof, and that they will assist the officers of Her
Majesty in bringing to justice and punishment any Indian offending
against the stipulations of this Treaty or infringing the law in
force in the country so ceded.</p>
                     <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF Her Majesty's said Commissioners and the Cree
Chief and Headmen of Lesser Slave Lake and the adjacent territory,
HAVE HEREUNTO SET THEIR HANDS at Lesser Slave Lake on the
twenty-first day of June, in the year herein first above
written.</p>
                    

<p>Signed by the parties hereto, in the<lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit<lb break="no"/>nesses, the same having been first<lb/>
explained to the Indians by<lb/>
Albert Tate and Samuel Cun<lb break="no"/>ningham, Interpreters.<lb/>
</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:LACO1">FATHER A. LACOMBE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HOLM2">GEO. HOLMES</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GROU1">E. GROUARD</persName>, O.M.I.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WHIT16">W. G. WHITE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WALK3">JAMES WALKER</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:COTE4">J. ARTHUR COT</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SNYD1">A. E. SNYDER</persName>, Insp. N.W.M.P.,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ROUN1">H. B. ROUND</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:YOUN6">HARRISON S. YOUNG</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:PRUD1">J. F. PRUD'HOMME</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MART6">J. W. MARTIN</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MAIR1">C. MAIR</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CONR3">H. A. CONROY</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DESC1">PIERRE DESCHAMBEAULT</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:PICA2">J. H. PICARD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SECO1">RICHARD SECORD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCCA8">M. McCAULEY</persName>.</p>


                        <p><persName ref="pers:LAIR4">DAVID LAIRD</persName>, Treaty Commissioner,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKE8">J.A.J. McKENNA</persName>, Treaty Commissioner,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ROSS11">J. H. ROSS</persName>, Treaty Commissioner,<lb/>
                        </p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:KEEN1">KEE NOO SHAY OO</persName> Chief, his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:MOOS2">MOOSTOOS</persName> Headman, his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:GIRO1">FELIX GIROUX</persName> Headman, his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:WEEC1">WEE CHEE WAY SIS</persName> Headman, his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:NEES3">CHARLES NEE SUE TA SIS</persName> Headman, his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:CAPT2">CAPTAIN</persName> Headman, from Sturgeon Lake. his x mark</p>
              


                     <p>In witness whereof the Chairman of Her Majesty's Commissioners
and the Headman of the Indians of Peace River Landing and the
adjacent territory, in behalf of himself and the Indians whom he
represents, have hereunto set their hands at the said Peace River
Landing on the first day of July in the year of Our Lord one
thousand eight hundred and ninety-nine.</p>
                     

<p>Signed by the parties hereto, in the<lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit-<lb/>
nesses, the same having been first<lb/>
explained to the Indians by<lb/>
Father A. Lacombe and John<lb/>
Boucher, Interpreters.</p>


<p>
<persName ref="pers:LACO1">FATHER A. LACOMBE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GROU1">E. GROUARD</persName>, O.M.I., Ev. d'Ibora,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HOLM2">GEO. HOLMES</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCCO5">HENRY MCCORRISTER</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ANDE3">K. F. ANDERSON</persName>, SGT., N.W.M.P.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DESC1">PIERRE DESCHAMBEAULT</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CONR3">H. A. CONROY</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BRIC1">T.A. BRICK</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:YOUN6">HARRISON S. YOUNG</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MART6">J. W. MARTIN</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CURR3">DAVID CURRY</persName>.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:LAIR4">DAVID LAIRD</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chairman of Indian<lb/>
Treaty Commissioners</hi>,</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:TAST1">DUNCAN TASTAOOSTS</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman of Crees</hi> his x mark</p>

  

                     <p>In witness whereof the Chairman of Her Majesty's Commissioners
and the Chief and Headmen of the Beaver and Headman of the Crees
and other Indians of Vermilion and the adjacent territory, in
behalf of themselves and the Indians whom they represent, have
hereunto set their hands at Vermilion on the eighth day of July, in
the year of our Lord one thousand eight hundred and
ninety-nine.</p>
                  
<p>Signed by the parties hereto, in the<lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit<lb break="no"/>nesses, the same having been first<lb/>
explained to the Indians by<lb/>
Father A. Lacombe and John<lb/>
Boucher, Interpreters.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:LACO1">FATHER A. LACOMBE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GROU1">E. GROUARD</persName>, O.M.I., Ev. d'Ibora,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SCOT3">MALCOLM SCOTT</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WILS3">F.D. WILSON</persName>, H.B. Co.,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CONR3">H. A. CONROY</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DESC1">PIERRE DESCHAMBEAULT</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:YOUN6">HARRISON S. YOUNG</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MART6">J. W. MARTIN</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ANDE3">K. F. ANDERSON</persName>, SGT., N.W.M.P.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CLAR7">A.P. CLARKE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WADE1">CHAS. H. STUART WADE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ANDE3">K. F. ANDERSON</persName>, SGT., N.W.M.P.<lb/>
</p>

<p>
                       <persName ref="pers:LAIR4">DAVID LAIRD</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chairman of Indian Treaty
Coms.,</hi></p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:TETE1">AMBROSE TETE NOIRE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief Beaver Indians</hi>. his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:FOUR4">PIERROT FOURNIER</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman Beaver Indians</hi> his x mark</p>


<p>
<persName ref="pers:KUIS1">KUIS KUIS KOW CA POOHOO</persName> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Cree Indians</hi>. his x mark</p>



                     <p>In witness whereof the Chairman of Her Majesty's Treaty
Commissioners and the Chief and Headman of the Chipewyan Indians of
Fond du Lac (Lake Athabasca) and the adjacent territory, in behalf
of themselves and the Indians whom they represent, have hereunto
set their hands at the said Fond du Lac on the twenty-fifth and
twenty-seventh days of July, in the year of Our Lord one thousand
eight hundred and ninety-nine.</p>


<p>Signed by the parties hereto in the<lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit<lb break="no"/>nesses, the same having been first<lb/>
explained to the Indians by<lb/>
Pierre Deschambeault, Reverend<lb/>
Father Douceur and Louis Robil<lb break="no"/>lard, Interpreters.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:LAIR4">DAVID LAIRD</persName>,<lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Chairman of Indian Treaty Coms</hi>.,<lb/>
</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:DZIE1">LAURENT DZIEDDIN</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:TOUS1">TOUSSAINT</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p>(The number accepting treaty being larger than at first expected, a Chief<lb/>
was allowed, who signed the treaty on the 27th July before the same witnesses<lb/>
to signatures of the Commissioner and Headman on the 25th.)</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:BREY1">G. BREYNAT</persName>, O.M.I,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:YOUN6">HARRISON S. YOUNG</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DESC1">PIERRE DESCHAMBEAULT</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BURK1">WILLIAM HENRY BURKE</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:COOP1">BATHURST F. COOPER</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MERC1">GERMAIN MERCREDI</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ROBI6">LOUIS ROBILLARD</persName>, his x mark<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ANDE3">K.F. ANDERSON</persName>, Sgt., <hi rendition="simple:italic">N.W.M.P.</hi></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:PICH2">MAURICE PICHE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief of Band.</hi> his x mark</p>

<p>Witness, <persName ref="pers:YOUN6">H.S. YOUNG</persName>.</p>


         


                     <p>The Beaver Indians of Dunvegan having met on this sixth day of
July, in this present year 1899, Her Majesty's Commissioners, the
Honourable James Hamilton Ross and James Andrew Joseph McKenna,
Esquire, and having had explained to then the terms of the Treaty
unto which the Chief and Headmen of the Indians of Lesser Slave
Lake and adjacent country set their hands on the twenty-first day
of June, in the year herein first above written, do join in the
cession made by the said Treaty, and agree to adhere to the terms
thereof in consideration of the undertakings made therein.</p>
                     <p>In witness whereof Her Majesty's said Commissioners and the
Headman of the said Beaver Indians have hereunto set their hands at
Dunvegan on this sixth day of July, in the year herein first above
written.</p>
              

<p>Signed by the parties thereto in the <lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit<lb break="no"/>nesses, after the same had been<lb/>
read and explained to the Indians<lb/>
by the Reverend Joseph Le Treste<lb/>
and Peter Gunn, Interpreters.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:SNYD1">A.E. SNYDER</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Insp. N.W.M.P.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LETR1">J. LE TRESTE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GUNN4">PETER GUNN</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FITZ2">F.J. FITZGERALD</persName>.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:ROSS11">J.H. ROSS</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKE8">J.A.J. McKENNA</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioners,</hi></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:NATO3">NATOOSES</persName> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, his x mark</p>


                     <p>The Chipewyan Indians of Athabasca River, Birch River, Peace
River, Slave River and Gull River, and the Cree Indians of Gull
River and Deep Lake, having met at Fort Chipewyan on this
thirteenth day of July, in this present year 1899, Her Majesty's
Commissioners, the Honourable James Hamilton Ross and James Andrew
Joseph McKenna, Esquire, and having had explained to them the terms
of the Treaty unto which the Chief and Headmen of the Indians of
Lesser Slave Lake and adjacent country set their hands on the
twenty-first day of June, in the year herein first above written,
do join in the cession made by the said Treaty, and agree to adhere
to the terms thereof in consideration of the undertakings made
therein.</p>
                     <p>In witness whereof Her Majesty's said Commissioners and the
Chiefs and Headmen of the said Chipewyan and Cree Indians have
hereunto set their hands at Fort Chipewyan on this thirteenth day
of July, in the year herein first above written.</p>
        
<p>Signed by the parties thereto in the <lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit<lb break="no"/>nesses after the same had been<lb/>
read and explained to the Indians<lb/>
by Peter Mercredi, Chipewyan<lb/>
Interpreter, and George Drever,<lb/>
Cree Interpreter.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:SNYD1">A.E. SNYDER</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Insp., N.W.M.P.,</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MERC2">P. MERCREDI</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DREV1">GEO. DREVER</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LEDO1">L.M. LE DOUSSAL</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DECH2">A. DE CHAMBOUR</persName>, O.M.I.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ROUN1">H.B. ROUND</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BREY1">GABRIEL BREYNAT</persName>, O.M.I.,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FRAS6">COLIN FRASER</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FITZ2">F.J. FITZGERALD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:COOP1">B.F. COOPER</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCLA2">H.W. McLAREN</persName>,</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:ROSS11">J.H. ROSS</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKE8">J.A.J. McKENNA</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Treaty Commissioners,</hi></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:LAVI1">ALEX LAVIOLETTE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chipewyan Chief,</hi> his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:RATF1">JULIEN RATFAT</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:HEEZ1">SEPT. HEEZELL</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chipewyan Headman,</hi> his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MART7">JUSTIN MARTIN</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Cree Chief,</hi> his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:TACC1">ANT. TACCARROO</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p> <persName ref="pers:GIBB2">THOMAS GIBBOT</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Cree Headman</hi>. his x mark
</p>



                     <p>The Chipewyan Indians of Slave River and the country thereabouts
having met at Smith's Landing on this seventeenth day of July, in
this present year 1899, Her Majesty's Commissioners, the Honourable
James Hamilton Ross and James Andrew Joseph McKenna, Esquire, and
having had explained to them the terms of the Treaty unto which the
Chief and Headmen of the Indians of Lesser Slave Lake and adjacent
country, set their hands on the twenty-first day of June, in the
year herein first above written, do join in the cession made by the
said Treaty, and agree to adhere to the terms thereof in
consideration of the undertakings made therein.</p>
                     <p>In witness whereof Her Majesty's said Commissioners and the
Chief and Headmen of the said Chipewyan Indians have hereunto set
their hands at Smith's Landing, on this seventeenth day of July, in
the year herein first above written.</p>
 
<p>Signed by the parties thereto in the <lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit<lb break="no"/>nesses after the same had been<lb/>
read and explained to the Indians<lb/>
by John Trindle, Interpreter.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:SNYD1">A.E. SNYDER</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Insp. N.W.M.P.,</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ROUN1">H.B. ROUND</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:REID5">J.H. REID</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HALY1">JAS. HALY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:TRIN1">JOHN TRINDLE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FITZ2">F.J. FITZGERALD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCCL2">WM. McCLELLAND</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SUTH7">JOHN SUTHERLAND</persName>.</p>


<p><persName ref="pers:ROSS11">J.H. ROSS</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKE8">J.A.J. McKENNA</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Treaty Commissioners,</hi></p>

<p>PIERRE SQUIRREL, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p>MICHAEL MAMDRILLE, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, his x mark
</p>

<p>WILLIAM KISCORRAY, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, his x mark</p>


                     <p>The Chipewyan and Cree Indians of Fort McMurray and the country
thereabouts, having met at Fort McMurray, on this fourth day of
August, in this present year 1899, Her Majesty's Commissioner,
James Andrew Joseph McKenna, Esquire, and having had explained to
them the terms of the Treaty unto which the Chief and Headmen of
the Indians of Lesser Slave Lake and adjacent country set their
hands on the twenty-first day of June, in the year herein first
above written, do join in the cession made by the said Treaty and
agree to adhere to the terms thereof in consideration of the
undertakings made therein.</p>
                     <p>In witness whereof Her Majesty's said Commissioner and the
Headmen of the said Chipewyan and Cree Indians have hereunto set
their hands at Fort McMurray, on this fourth day of August, in the
year herein first above written.</p>
                 

<p>Signed by the parties thereto in the <lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit<lb break="no"/>nesses after the same had been<lb/>
read and explained to the Indians<lb/>
by the Rev. Father Lacombe and <lb/>
T.M. Clarke, Interpreters</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:LACO1">A. LACOMBE</persName>, O.M.I.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WARW1">ARTHUR J. WARWICK</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CLAR8">T.M. CLARKE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MART6">J.W. MARTIN</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FITZ2">F.J. FITZGERALD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:VERN1">M.J.H. VERNON</persName>.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:MCKE8">J.A.J. McKENNA</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Treaty Commissioner</hi>,</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:BOUC5">ADAM BOUCHER</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chipewyan Headman</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">SEAPOTAKINUM</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Cree Headman</hi>, his x mark

</p>




                     <p>The Indians of Wapiscow and the country thereabouts having met
at Wapiscow Lake on this fourteenth day of August, in this present
year 1899, Her Majesty's Commissioner, the Honourable James
Hamilton Ross, and having had explained to them the terms of the
Treaty unto which the Chief and Headmen of the Indians of Lesser
Slave Lake and adjacent country set their hands on the twenty-first
day of June in the year herein first above written, do join in the
cession made by the said Treaty and agree to adhere to the terms
thereof in consideration of the undertakings made therein.</p>
                     <p>In witness whereof Her Majesty's said Commissioner and the Chief
and Headmen of the Indians have hereunto set their hands at
Wapiscow Lake, on this fourteenth day of August, in the year herein
first above written.</p>


<p>Signed by the parties thereto in the <lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit<lb break="no"/>nesses after the same had been<lb/>
read and explained to the Indians<lb/>
by Alexander Kennedy.</p>


<p>
<persName ref="pers:SNYD1">A.E. SNYDER</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Insp. N.W.M.P.,</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WEAV1">CHARLES RILEY WEAVER</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GIRO2">J.B. HENRI GIROUX</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">O.M.I., P.M.,</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:JOHN9">MURDOCH JOHNSTON</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FALH1">C. FALHER</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">O.M.I.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:KENN5">ALEX KENNEDY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Interpreter</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CONR3">H.A. CONROY</persName>,<lb/>
(Signature in Cree character).<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCLE14">JOHN McLEOD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:JOHN9">M.R. JOHNSTON</persName>.
</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:ROSS11">J.H. ROSS</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Treaty Commissioner</hi>,</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:KAPU1">JOSEPH KAPUSEKONEW</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:ANSE1">JOSEPH ANSEY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:WAPO1">WAPOOSE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:ANSE2">MICHAEL ANSEY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:BEAV1">LOUISA BEAVER</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Headman</hi>, <choice><sic>his</sic><corr>her</corr></choice> x mark
</p>

</div>

<div type="section">

                  <head>Order In Council Ratifying Treaty No.
8</head>
               

                     <p>EXTRACT from a Report of the Committee of the Honourable the
Privy Council, approved by His Excellency on the 20th February,
1900.</p>
                     <p>On a Memorandum dated 8th February, 1900, from the
Superintendent General of Indian Affairs, submitting for Your
Excellency's consideration the accompanying Treaty made by the
Commissioners, the Honourable David Laird, James Andrew Joseph
McKenna, Esquire, and the Honourable James Hamilton Ross, who were
appointed to negotiate the same, with the Cree, Beaver, Chipewyan
and other Indians inhabiting the territory, --- as fully defined in
the Treaty --- lying within and adjacent to the Provisional
District of Athabasca.</p>
                     <p>The Minister recommends that the Treaty referred to be approved,
and that the duplicate thereof, which is also submitted herewith,
be kept of record in the Privy Council and the original returned to
the Department of Indian Affairs.</p>
                     <p>The Committee submit the same for Your Excellency's
approval.</p>
                     <p>
                   
<persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">JOHN J. McGEE</persName>,<lb/>
                        <lb/>
Clerk of the Privy Council.</p>
                     <p>The Honourable<lb/>
The Superintendent General of Indian Affairs.</p>
                
</div>

<div type="section">
                  <head>Report of Commissioner for Treaty No.
8</head>
          

                     <p>DEPARTMENT OF INDIAN AFFAIRS,</p>
       


                     <p>OTTAWA, December 11, 1900.</p>
            

                  <p>The Honourable<lb/>
The Superintendent General of Indian Affairs,<lb/>
Ottawa.</p>
                  <p>SIR, --- I beg to report having, in pursuance of the commissions
entrusted to me by you, visited the territory covered by Treaty No.
8, and all the posts from Fort St. John, on the Upper Peace River
in the west, to Fort Resolution on Great Slave lake in the north.
During that visit, acting as your commissioner for the purpose,
formal adhesions to treaty were taken from certain Indian
inhabitants of the ceded territory belonging to eight bands who
were not treated with last year, annuities were paid to all treaty
Indians, and business of a general character was transacted with
and for them; acting as a commissioner to receive and hear
half-breed claims, over three hundred and fifty cases were dealt
with; and acting magisterially as a commissioner of Dominion police
and a justice of the peace for the Territories, nineteen cases of
crime and misdemeanour were disposed of. Separate reports touching
upon half-breed claims, public order and minor Indian matters are
being submitted.</p>
                  <p>My commission to take adhesions to Treaty Eight was designed to
enable me to treat with the Indians of Fort St. John in the Upper
Peace river, and the various bands on Great Slave lake that trade
at Fort Resolution, to the end of bringing them into treaty
relations with Her Majesty's government.</p>
                  <p>There came to meet me, however, in addition to these, two bands
of Indians, undoubted inhabitants of the tract covered by Treaty
No. 8, with whom I was not empowered to deal, one of Crees from
Sturgeon lake and one of Slaves from the Upper Hay river. Both of
these desired to enter into treaty, and it became necessary to
decide whether they, after having come from distant points to meet
one whom they looked upon as a representative of the government,
were to be dismissed non-plussed and dissatisfied, or to be allowed
to give in their adhesions. It being impossible to communicate with
the department, and as the title of these people to the benefits of
the treaty was beyond question, the conclusion was unhesitatingly
adopted that it was my duty to assume responsibility and concede
those benefits to them. The instruments embodying their adhesions
are submitted herewith together with those I was empowered to take,
which contain the adhesions of certain of the Indians of Fort St.
John and the whole of those of Fort Resolution on Great Slave lake,
whose hunting grounds lie within treaty limits. It is hoped that
you will approve this assumption of responsibility, and that the
sanction of His Excellency in Council will be extended to all the
adhesions.</p>
                  <p>Last year 2,217 Indians were paid. This year 3,323 claimed the
annuity, an increase of 1,106, or almost fifty per cent. Of this
increased number 248 belong to or have now joined, bands treated
with in 1899, and 858 to the following bands which remained undealt
with in that year, namely, Crees of Sturgeon lake; Beavers of Fort
St. John; Slaves of Upper Hay river, who trade at Vermilion; and
the Dogribs, Yellowknives, Chipewyans and Slaves of Lower Hay
river, who trade at Fort Resolution. Some Caribooeaters, belonging
to the country east of Smith's Landing on Great Slave river, also
came into treaty, but they were incorporated with the Chipewyan
band of Smith's Landing, being allied thereto. Six new chiefs were
recognized.</p>
                  <p>As was reported by your commissioners last year, there is little
disposition on the part of most of the northern Indians to settle
down upon land or to ask to have reserves set apart. Dealing, under
your instructions, with demands for land, two small provisional
reserves were laid out at Lesser Slave Lake for Kinosayo's band,
and fifteen or sixteen applications were registered for land in
severalty by Indians who have already, to some extent, taken to
agriculture.</p>
                  <p>It appears that this disinclination to adopt agriculture as a
means of livelihood is not unwisely entertained, for the more
congenial occupations of hunting and fishing are still open, and
agriculture is not only arduous to those untrained to it, but in
many districts it as yet remains untried. A consequence of this
preference of old pursuits is that the government will not be
called upon for years to make those expenditures which are entailed
by the treaty when the Indians take to the soil for
subsistence.</p>
                  <p>The health of the Indians in the district seems to vary with the
times. When game is plentiful it is good; when scarce, it is bad.
The want of rabbits along the Peace and Hay rivers caused suffering
to the Beavers and Slaves in part of the western portion of the
territory last winter; but, in the eastern portion, the Chipewyans
were unusually well off, cariboo being plentiful. At Fond du Lac,
it was said, there was less disease than for many years. No such
loss of life from starvation as has often characterized northern
winters was reported, and the measures for relieving sick and
destitute Indians planned by the commissioners last year, operated
well and alleviated distress in many deserving cases. Dr. Edwards,
who accompanied me, gave advice and dispensed medicine to a large
number of Indians and vaccinated many. Great appreciation of his
services was manifested.</p>
                  <p>At nearly all the important points the chiefs and more
intelligent men who were present at the making of treaty last year,
asked for extended explanations of its terms, in order that those
of their bands who had failed to grasp its true meaning might be
enlightened, and that those who were coming into treaty for the
first time might fully understand what they were doing. In the
course of the councils held for this purpose, it was possible to
eradicate any little misunderstanding that had arisen in the minds
of the more intelligent, and great pains were taken to give such
explanations as seemed most likely to prevent any possibility of
misunderstandings in future.</p>
                  <p>Each of the many appointments made was punctually kept, a fact
which appeared to give great satisfaction to both the traders and
the Indians.</p>
                  <p>Appended is a summary of the bands paid, showing the admissions
to treaty permitted this year.</p>
                  <p>There yet remains a number of persons leading an Indian life in
the country north of Lesser Slave lake, who have not accepted
treaty as Indians, or scrip as half-breeds, but this is not so much
through indisposition to do so as because they live at points
distant from those visited, and are not pressed by want. The
Indians of all parts of the territory who have not yet been paid
annuity probably number about 500 exclusive of those in the extreme
northwestern portion, but as most, if not all, of this number
belong to bands that have already joined in the treaty, the Indian
title to the tract it covers may be fairly regarded as being
extinguished.</p>
                  <p>Most respectfully submitting this report,<lb/>
I have, &amp;c.,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MACR1">J. A. MACRAE</persName>,<lb/>
Commissioner.</p>
                  <p>Documents accompanying this report:<lb/>
No. 1. Adhesion of Sturgeon Lake band.<lb/>
No. 2. Adhesion of part of the Beavers of Fort St. John.<lb/>
No. 3. Adhesion of Slaves of Upper Hay River.<lb/>
No. 4. Adhesion of Dogribs of Great Slave Lake.<lb/>
Chipewyans of Great Slave Lake.<lb/>
Yellowknives of Great Slave Lake.<lb/>
Slaves of Lower Hay River or Great Slave Lake.<lb/>
                     <lb/>
No.5. Statement of the number of Indians admitted to treaty this
year (1900) .<lb/>
No. 6. Map showing the distribution of Indians in the territory
covered by Treaty No. 8, and the extent of that territory.</p>
                  <p>The Cree Indians, of Sturgeon Lake, and the country thereabouts,
having met at Lesser Slave Lake, on this eight day of June, in the
present year 1900, James Ansdell Macrae, Esquire, and having had
explained to them the terms of the treaty unto which the Chief and
Headmen of the Indians of Lesser Slave Lake and adjacent country
set their hands on the twenty-first day of June, in the year 1899,
do join in the cession made by the said treaty, and agree to the
terms thereof in consideration of the undertakings made
therein.</p>
                  <p>In witness whereof, the said James Ansdell Macrae, Esquire, and
the Headmen of the said Cree Indians, have hereunto set their hands
at Lesser Slave Lake, on this the eighth day of June in the year
first above written.</p>
           

<p>Signed by the parties thereto in the <lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit<lb break="no"/>nesses after the same had been<lb/>
read and explained to the Indians<lb/>
by Peter Gunn and Albert Tate,<lb/>
Interpreters.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:TATE1">ALBERT TATE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GUNN4">PETER GUNN</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HOLM2">GEO. HOLMES</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MACD19">MYLES O'C. MAC DERMOT</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ODON2">W.J. O'DONNEL</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CHEE2">A. CHEESBROUGH</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Const.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FIEL3">R. FIELD</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Const.</hi></p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:MACR1">J.A. MACRAE</persName>,</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:MEES1">MEE-SOO-KAM-IN-OO-KA-POW</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:PEEY3">WILLIAM PEE-YU-TAY-WEE-TUM</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:MOOS3">MEEK-COO MOOS-OS</persName>, his x mark
</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:PAPA4">ALEXIS PA-PASS-CHAY</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:CAPT2">THE CAPTAIN</persName>, his x mark</p>




                  <p>The Beaver Indians of the Upper Peace River and the country
thereabouts, having met at Fort St. John, on this thirtieth day of
May, in this present year 1900, Her Majesty's Commissioner, James
Ansdell Macrae, Esquire, and having had explained to them the terms
of the treaty unto which the Chief and Headmen of the Indians of
Lesser Slave Lake and adjacent country set their hands on the
twenty-first day of June, in the year 1899, do join in the cession
made by the said treaty, and agree to adhere to the terms thereof,
in consideration of the undertakings made therein.</p>
                  <p>In witness whereof, Her Majesty's said Commissioner, and the
following of the said Beaver Indians, have hereunto set their
hands, at Fort St. John, on this the thirtieth day of May, in the
year herein first above written.</p>
         
<p>Signed by the parties thereto in the <lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit<lb break="no"/>nesses after the same had been<lb/>
read and explained to the Indians<lb/>
by John Shaw, Interpreter.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:SHAW2">JOHN SHAW</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Interpreter</hi>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ODON2">W.J. O'DONNELL</persName>.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:MACR1">J.A. MACRAE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner</hi>,</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:MUCK2">MUCKITHAY</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:AGIN1">AGINAA</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:DISL1">DISLISICI</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:TACH2">TACHEA</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:APPA1">APPAN</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:ATTA1">ATTACHIE</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:ALLA3">ALLALIE</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:YATS1">YATSOOSE</persName>, his x mark</p>






                  <p>The Slave Indians of Hay river and the country thereabouts,
having met at Vermilion, on this twenty-third day of June, in this
present year 1900, Her Majesty's Commissioner, James Ansdell
Macrae, Esquire, and having explained to them the terms of the
treaty unto which the Chief and Headmen of the Indians of Lesser
Slave Lake and adjacent country set their hands on the twenty-first
day of June, in year 1899, do join in the cessions made by the said
treaty, and agree to adhere to the terms thereof in consideration
of the undertakings made therein.</p>
                  <p>In witness whereof, Her Majesty's said Commissioner and the
Chief and principal men of the said Slave Indians, have hereunto
set their hands, at Vermilion, on this twenty-third day of June, in
the year 1900.</p>
      


<p>Signed by the parties thereto in the <lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit<lb break="no"/>nesses after the same had been<lb/>
read and explained to the Indians<lb/>
by Louis Cardinal.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:CARD4">LOUIS CARDINAL</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Witness:</hi> G. ARTHUR BALL<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WHIT17">ALFRED SPEECHLY WHITE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GAGN3">ISAIE GAGNON</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:KNAP1">GEO. KNAPP</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LARO2">H.J. LAROQUE</persName>,</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:OUEL1">MARTIN OUELLETE</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Witnesses:</hi> <persName ref="pers:BALL5">G. ARTHUR BALL</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LETE2">WILLIAM LETENDRE</persName>.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:MACR1">J.A. MACRAE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner,</hi></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:TATA1">ALEXIA TATATECHAY</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:TCHA1">FRANCOIS TCHATEE</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:NAHD1">GIROUX NAHDAYYAH</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KOKA1">KOKA</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:KACH1">KACHWEESALA</persName>, his x mark</p>




                  <p>The Indians inhabiting the south shore of Great Slave Lake,
between the mouth of Hay river and old Fort Reliance, near the
mouth of Lockheart's river, and territory adjacent thereto, on the
mainland or on the islands of the said lake, having met at Fort
Resolution, on this twenty-fifth day of July, in the present year
1900, Her Majesty's Commissioner, James Ansdell Macrae, Esquire,
and having had explained to them the terms of the treaty unto which
the Chief and Headmen of the Indians of Lesser Slave Lake and
adjacent country set their hands on the twenty-first day of June,
1899, do join in the cession made by the said treaty, and agree to
adhere to the terms thereof, in consideration of the undertakings
made therein.</p>
                  <p>In witness whereof, Her Majesty's said Commissioner and the
Chief and Headmen of the said Indians have hereunto set their
hands, at Fort Resolution, on the twenty-fifth day of July, in the
year herein first above written.</p>
                  <p/>

<p>Signed by the parties thereto in the <lb/>
presence of the undersigned wit<lb break="no"/>nesses after the same had been<lb/>
read and explained to the Indians<lb/>
by Rev. Father Dupirer,<lb/>
W.R. Norn, A. Mercredi.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:DUPI1">L. Dupirer</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">O.M.I.,</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:NORN1">W.R. NORN</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MERC3">ALXANDER MERCREDI</persName> ,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MARS4">THOS. J. MARSH</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GAUD2">F.C. GAUDET</persName>,<lb/>
(The mark of <persName ref="pers:MAND1">Michel Mandeville</persName>),<lb/>
[Indian characters.]<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:NORN2">CHARLIE NORN</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FIEL4">RICHARD FIELD</persName>.
</p>

<p>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Witnesses:</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:RAE1">T.C. RAE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MERC4">OLIVER MERCREDI</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CAMS2">J.S. CAMSELL</persName>.</p>

<p>
<persName ref="pers:MACR1">J.A. MACRAE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Commissioner,</hi></p>



<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">For the Dog Ribs.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DRIE1">DRIED GEESE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief</hi>, his x mark

</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:WAYM1">WAY-MI-AH</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">H.M.</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:CRAP1">CRAP-WA-TEE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">H.M.</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">For the Yellow Knives.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SNUF1">SNUFF</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:TZIN1">TZIN-TU</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">H.M.</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:ATEE1">ATE-EE-ZEN</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">H.M.</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">For the Slaves of Hay River,</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SUNR1">SUNRISE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">H.M.</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:LAME1">LAMELISE</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">H.M.</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">For the Chipewyans.</hi><lb/>
<persName ref="pers:AHTH1">LOUISON AHTHAY</persName>, <hi rendition="simple:italic">Chief</hi>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:AJJE1">OLIVER AJJERICON</persName>, his x mark</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:LAMO2">VITAL LAMOLLE</persName>, his () sign</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:CHAN2">PAULETTE CHANDELLE</persName>, <choice><sic>his</sic><corr>her</corr></choice> () sign</p>


                  <p>STATEMENT showing the number of Indians who joined Treaty No. 8
in A.D. 1900 and received annuity and gratuity --- the bands
treated with for the first time being denoted by italics (annuities
paid to those dealt with in 1899 not shown).</p>
      
<table>
<row><cell rendition="simple:centre">Band.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Whereabouts.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Chiefs.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Head<lb break="no"/>men.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Indians.</cell><cell rendition="simple:centre">Cash paid.</cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$ cts.</cell></row>
<row><cell>Crees (Kinoosayo's).........</cell><cell>Lesser Slave Lake...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">10</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">120 00</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Crees</hi>...................</cell><cell>Sturgeon Lake...........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">93</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,170 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Crees (Testawit's).........</cell><cell>Peace River Crossing...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">20</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">240 00</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Beavers</hi>...................</cell><cell>Fort St. John...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">46</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">552 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Beavers...................</cell><cell>Fort Dunvegan...........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">74</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">920 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Beavers (Tete Noire's)...................</cell><cell>Fort Vermillion...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">18</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">216 00</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Slaves of Upper Hay River</hi>..........</cell><cell> " ...........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">175</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,176 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Crees (Tall Cree's)..............</cell><cell> " ...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">43</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">516 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Little Red River..............</cell><cell>Little Red River...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">9</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">108 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Chipewyans..............</cell><cell>Fort Chipewyan...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">12 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Crees..............</cell><cell> " ...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">12 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Chipewyans..............</cell><cell>Smith's Landing...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">35</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">452 00</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Chipewyans</hi>..............</cell><cell>Fort Resolution...........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">111</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,386 00</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Yellowknives</hi>..............</cell><cell> " ...........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">191</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,368 00</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Dogribs</hi>..............</cell><cell> " ...........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">119</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,504 00</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Slaves of Lower Hay River</hi>.........</cell><cell> " ...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">103</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,258 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Chipewyans (Maurice's)..........</cell><cell>Fond du Lac (Lake Athabasca)..</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">65</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">780 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Crees..............</cell><cell>Fort McMurray...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">30</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">360 00</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Stragglers</hi>..............</cell><cell> " ...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">17</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">204 00</cell></row>
<row><cell>Crees..............</cell><cell>Wabiscow...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">39</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">468 00</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Crees</hi>..............</cell><cell>Whitefish Lake...........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell>........</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">24 00</cell></row>
<row><cell><hi rendition="simple:italic">Crees</hi>..............</cell><cell>Trout Lake...........</cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:underline">........</hi></cell><cell><hi rendition="simple:underline">........</hi></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">1</hi></cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">12 00</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">6</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">10</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,203</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">14,858 00</cell></row>
</table>

<table>
<row><cell cols="2" rendition="simple:centre">SUMMARY.</cell></row>
<row><cell>Total admitted in 1899.......................................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">2,217</cell></row>
<row><cell> " 1900.......................................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,218</cell></row>
<row><cell>Total of Indian annuitants under Treaty No. 8................</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">3,323</cell></row>
</table>




                  <p>Certified correct,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MACR1">J.A. MACRAE</persName>,<lb/>
Commissioner.</p>
                 
</div>

<div type="section">
                  <head>Order In Council Ratifying Adhesions
to Treaty No. 8</head>
            

                     <p>EXTRACT from a Report of the Committee of the Honourable the
Privy Council approved His Excellency on January 3, 1901.</p>
                     <p>On a report dated December 22, 1900, from the Superintendent
General of Indian Affairs referring to the Order in Council of
February 20, 1900, approving of the Treaty known as Treaty No. 8,
made in 1899, with the Cree, Beaver, Chipewyan and other Indians
inhabiting the territory lying within and adjacent to the
Provisional District of Athabaska, and stating that as the
Commissioners who negotiated the treaty above mentioned, were
unable last year to meet the Indians of Fort St. John and Fort
Resolution, it was necessary to appoint a Commissioner during the
season of 1900 to take the adhesion of the Indians in those
localities and on March 2, 1900, James Ansdell Macrae, Esquire, was
commissioned by Order in Council to obtain such adhesions.</p>
                     <p>The Minister submits herewith the report of Mr. Commissioner
Macrae, accompanied by the following documents:</p>
                     <p>No. 1. Adhesion of Sturgeon Lake Band.<lb/>
No. 2. Adhesion of part of the Beavers of Fort St. John.<lb/>
No. 3. Adhesion of Slaves of Upper Hay River.<lb/>
No. 4. Adhesion of Dogribs of Great Slave Lake.<lb/>
Adhesion of Chipewyans of Great Slave Lake.<lb/>
Adhesion of Yellowknives of Great Slave Lake.<lb/>
Adhesion of Slaves of Lower Hay River or Great Slave Lake.<lb/>
No.5. Statement of the number of Indians admitted to Treaty this
year. (1900).</p>
                     <p>The Minister recommends that for the reasons stated in Mr.
Macrae's report, all the adhesions taken by him be approved by Your
Excellency in Council and that the original adhesions be returned
to the Department of Indian Affairs and the duplicates thereof kept
on record in the Privy Council Office.</p>
                     <p>The Committee submit the same for Your Excellency's
approval.</p>
                     <p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">JOHN J. McGEE</persName>,<lb/>
Clerk of the Privy Council.</p>
                     <p>The Honourable<lb/>
The Superintendent General of Indian Affairs.</p>
                  </div>
               

         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
