<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="treaty_04"
     type="full">
<teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
<titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreaty">Treaty Document(s)</name>, <date when="1874-09-15">15 September 1874</date>, Treaty No. 4.</title>
        

            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName></respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Conversion from HTML to TEI</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLM3">Martin Holmes</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">LAYOUT IS NOT EXACTLY LIKE ORIGINAL</hi></p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:treaty_4">
          
               <title>Treaty No. 4 between Her Majesty the Queen and the Cree and Saulteaux Tribes of Indians at the Qu'appelle and Fort Ellice</title>.
                    

          <date when="1966"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>ROGER DUHAMEL, F.R.S.C. QUEEN'S PRINTER AND CONTROLLER OF STATIONERY</publisher>.
          
  <orgName>
               
                  <orgName xml:lang="en">Indigenous and Northern Affairs Canada</orgName>
               </orgName>
        
        </bibl>
 

            <list>
               <item>
                 <ptr target="https://www.aadnc-aandc.gc.ca/eng/1100100028689/1100100028690"/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-11-21">Transformed original HTML to TEI.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="treaty">
      

                  <fw type="running">Treaty Texts - Treaty No. 4</fw>
                  <fw type="running">Treaty No. 4 between Her Majesty
the Queen and the Cree and Saulteaux Tribes of Indians at the
Qu'appelle and Fort Ellice</fw>
                  


<head>ORDER IN COUNCIL SETTING UP
COMMISSION<lb/>
FOR TREATY No. 4<lb/>
P.C. No. 944</head>


                  <p>On a Memorandum, dated 20th July 1874, from the Honorable the
Minister of the Interior, stating that he has had before him a
Minute of the Council of the North West of the 14th March last,
recommending that Treaties should this year be concluded with the
Tribes of Indians inhabiting the Territory therein indicated, lying
West of the Boundary of Treaty No. 2, and between the International
Boundary Line and the Saskatchewan.</p>
                  <p>That he has also had before him several Despatches from the
Lieutenant Governor of later date urging the necessity of these
Treaties.</p>
                  <p>That looking to these representations and to the fact that the
Mounted Police Force is now moving into the Territory in question
with a view of taking up their winter quarters at Fort Pelly, and
considering the operations of the Boundary Commission which are
continually moving westward into the Indian Country, and also the
steps which are being taken in connection with the proposed
Telegraph Line from Fort Garry westward, all which proceedings are
calculated to further unsettle and excite the Indian mind, already
in a disturbed condition; he recommends that three Commissioners be
appointed by His Excellency the Governor General for the purpose of
making Treaties during the current year with such of the Indians
Bands as they may find it expedient to deal with, inhabiting the
portion of the North West Territories which may be approximately
described as lying between the Westerly Boundary of Treaty No. 2
and the 110th degree of West Longitude, and bounded on the South by
the International Boundary Line, and on the North by Lake Winnipeg,
and by the Saskatchewan River, including a strip of country ten
miles north of that River to the Forks and thence following the
South branch of the said River until it meets the 110th degree of
West Longitude.</p>
                  <p>The Minister further recommends that the Commissioners to be
appointed for this purpose be instructed to confer with the
Lieutenant Governor of the North West Territories on the subject of
the Treaties, and that, in the event of permanent annuities being
granted to the Tribes with whom Treaties may be made, such
annuities should not be fixed at a higher rate than those
sanctioned by the Treaties already concluded with the Indians of
the North West.</p>
                  <p>The Committee submit the above recommendation for Your
Excellency's approval.</p>
                  <p>(sgd.) <persName ref="pers:HUNT2">L. S. HUNTINGDON</persName>.<lb/>
Approved<lb/>
23 July, 1874<lb/>
Dufferin<lb/>
                  </p>

     

<div type="section">
                        <head>APPROVAL OF TREATY No. 4<lb/>
                
P.C. No. 1332</head>
             

                  <p>On a Memorandum dated 29th October, 1874 from the Hon. Mr.
Mackenzie submitting for the consideration of Your Excellency in
Council Copies of a Treaty and supplementary Treaty with the Cree,
Saulteaux and other Indians inhabiting the Territory affected by
such Treaty, the former concluded on the 15th September last, and
the latter on the 21st September last, by His Honor the Lieutenant
Governor of the North West Territories, the Hon. the Minister of
the Interior, and W. J. Christie, Esquire, of Brockville, Ont., the
Commissioners specially appointed for that purpose, under Orders in
Council dated 23rd July and 26th August respectively.</p>
                  <p>Mr. Mackenzie states that the Territory covered by the Treaties
may be approximately described as lying between the Western
boundary of Treaty No.2 and the 1101/2 degree of West Longitude,
and bounded on the South by the International Boundary, and on the
North by the Red Deer River, and its Lakes, Red Deer and Etoimami,
to the source of its Western Branch thence in a straight line to
the source of the Northern Branch of the Qu'Appelle, thence along
and including said stream to the Forks near Long Lake; thence along
and including the Valley of the West Branch of the Qu'Appelle to
the South Saskatchewan, thence along and including said River to
the mouth of Maple Creek, thence along said Creek, to a point
opposite the Cypress Hills, thence due South to the Boundary Line,
and that the Area of the Territory above described comprises about
50,000 Square Miles.</p>
                  <p>That the terms of the Treaties are nearly identical with those
of the Treaty concluded last year at the North West Angle of the
Lake of the Woods.</p>
                  <p>That the principal conditions of the Treaties may be briefly
stated as follows:</p>
                  <list rend="bulleted">
                     <item>1st A Money present to each Chief of $25; to each Headman not
exceeding four in each Band $15 and to every other Indian, man,
woman and Child in the Band $12.</item>
                     <item>2nd An Annual payment in perpetuity, of the same sums to the
Chiefs and Headmen (not exceeding four in each Band) and $5 to
every other man, woman and Child in the Band.</item>
                     <item>3rd Certain trifling presents of clothing every third year, to
the Chiefs and Headmen.</item>
                     <item>4th A supply of Ammunition and twine every year to the value of
$750.</item>
                     <item>5th Presents of Agricultural implements, Cattle, grain,
Carpenter's tools, etc., proportioned to the number of families in
the Band actually engaged in farming.</item>
                     <item>6th Reserves to be selected of the same extent in proportion to
the numbers of the Bands, and on the same conditions as in the
previous Treaty.</item>
                     <item>7th Schools to be established on each Reserve as soon as the
Indians settle thereon.</item>
                     <item>8th Intoxicating liquors to be excluded from the Reserve.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Mr. Mackenzie states that the Treaties appear to him to be
satisfactory and he therefore recommends that they be approved by
Your Excellency in Council.</p>
                  <p>He further submits that he is of opinion that the satisfactory
conclusion of the Treaties is mainly due to patience, firmness,
tact and ability displayed by the Commissioners in the conduct of
the negotiations.</p>
                  <p>The Committee concur in the foregoing Report and recommend and
advise that the Treaties be approved and accepted and be enrolled
in the usual manner.</p>
                  <p>signed by: <persName ref="pers:MACK1">A. Mackenzie</persName>.<lb/>
Approved<lb/>
4th November 1876<lb/>
Dufferin.<lb/>
                  </p>
</div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>TREATY No. 4</head>
               

                  <p>ARTICLES OF A TREATY made and concluded this fifteenth day of
September, in the year of Our Lord one thousand eight hundred and
seventy-four, between Her Most Gracious Majesty the Queen of Great
Britain and Ireland, by Her Commissioners, the Honourable Alexander
Morris, Lieutenant Governor of the Province of Manitoba and the
North-West Territories; the Honourable David Laird, Minister of the
Interior, and William Joseph Christie, Esquire, of Brockville,
Ontario, of the one part; and the Cree, Saulteaux and other
Indians, inhabitants of the territory within the limits hereinafter
defined and described by their Chiefs and Headmen, chosen and named
as hereinafter mentioned, of the other part.</p>
                  <p>Whereas the Indians inhabiting the said territory have, pursuant
to an appointment made by the said Commissioners, been convened at
a meeting at the Qu'Appelle Lakes, to deliberate upon certain
matters of interest to Her Most Gracious Majesty, of the one part,
and the said Indians of the other.</p>
                  <p>And whereas the said Indians have been notified and informed by
Her Majesty's said Commissioners that it is the desire of Her
Majesty to open up for settlement, immigration, trade and such
other purposes as to Her Majesty may seem meet, a tract of country
bounded and described as hereinafter mentioned, and to obtain the
consent thereto of Her Indian subjects inhabiting the said tract,
and to make a treaty and arrange with them, so that there may be
peace and good will between them and Her Majesty and between them
and Her Majesty's other subjects, and that Her Indian people may
know and be assured of what allowance they are to count upon and
receive from Her Majesty's bounty and benevolence.</p>
                  <p>And whereas the Indians of the said tract, duly convened in
Council as aforesaid, and being requested by Her Majesty's said
Commissioners to name certain Chiefs and Headmen, who should be
authorized on their behalf to conduct such negotiations and sign
any treaty to be founded thereon, and to become responsible to Her
Majesty for their faithful performance by their respective bands of
such obligations as shall be assumed by them the said Indians, have
thereupon named the following persons for that purpose, that is to
say: Ka-ki-shi-way, or "Loud Voice," (Qu'Appelle River); Pis-qua,
or "The Plain" (Leech Lake); Ka-wey-ance, or "The Little Boy"
(Leech Lake); Ka-kee-na-wup, or "One that sits like an Eagle"
(Upper Qu'Appelle Lakes); Kus-kee-tew-mus-coo-mus-qua, or "Little
Black Bear" (Cypress Hills); Ka-ne-on-us-ka-tew, or "One that walks
on four claws" (Little Touchwood Hills); Cau-ah-ha-cha-pew, or
"Making ready the Bow" (South side of the South Branch of the
Saskatchewan); Kii-si-caw-ah-chuck, or "Day-Star" (South side of
the South Branch of the Saskatchewan); Ka-na-ca-toose, "The Poor
Man" (Touchwood Hills and Qu'Appelle Lakes); Ka-kii-wis-ta-haw, or
"Him that flies around" (towards the Cypress Hills); Cha-ca-chas
(Qu'Appelle River); Wah-pii-moose-too-siis, or "The White Calf" (or
Pus-coos) (Qu'Appelle River); Gabriel Cote, or Mee-may, or "The
Pigeon" (Fort Pelly).</p>
                  <p>And thereupon in open council the different bands, having
presented the men of their choice to the said Commissioners as the
Chiefs and Headmen, for the purpose aforesaid, of the respective
bands of Indians inhabiting the said district hereinafter
described.</p>
                  <p>And whereas the said Commissioners have proceeded to negotiate a
treaty with the said Indians, and the same has been finally agreed
upon and concluded as follows, that is to say:-</p>
                  <p>The Cree and Saulteaux Tribes of Indians, and all other the
Indians inhabiting the district hereinafter described and defined,
do hereby cede, release, surrender and yield up to the Government
of the Dominion of Canada, for Her Majesty the Queen, and Her
successors forever, all their rights, titles and privileges
whatsoever, to the lands included within the following limits, that
is to say:-</p>
                  <p>Commencing at a point on the United States frontier due south of
the northwestern point of the Moose Mountains; thence due north to
said point of said mountains: thence in a north-easterly course to
a point two miles due west of Fort Ellice; thence in a line
parallel with and two miles westward from the Assiniboine River to
the mouth of the Shell River; thence parallel to the said river and
two miles distant therefrom to its source; thence in a straight
line to a point on the western shore of Lake Winnipegosis, due west
from the most northern extremity of Waterhen Lake; thence east to
the centre of Lake Winnipegosis; thence northwardly, through the
middle of the said lake (including Birch Island), to the mouth of
Red Deer River; thence westwardly and southwestwardly along and
including the said Red Deer River and its lakes, Red Deer and
Etoimaini, to the source of its western branch; thence in a
straight line to the source of the northern branch of the
Qu'Appelle; thence along and including said stream to the forks
near Long Lake; thence along and including the valley of the west
branch of the Qu'Appelle to the South Saskatchewan; thence along
and including said river to the mouth of Maple Creek; thence
southwardly along said creek to a point opposite the western
extremity of the Cypress Hills; thence due south to the
international boundary; thence east along the said boundary to the
place of commencement. Also all their rights, titles and privileges
whatsoever to all other lands wheresoever situated within Her
Majesty's North-West Territories, or any of them. To have and to
hold the same to Her Majesty the Queen and Her successors for
ever.</p>
                  <p>And Her Majesty the Queen hereby agrees, through the said
Commissioners, to assign reserves for said Indians, such reserves
to be selected by officers of Her Majesty's Government of the
Dominion of Canada appointed for that purpose, after conference
with each band of the Indians, and to be of sufficient area to
allow one square mile for each family of five, or in that
proportion for larger or smaller families; provided, however, that
it be understood that, if at the time of the selection of any
reserves, as aforesaid, there are any settlers within the bounds of
the lands reserved for any band, Her Majesty retains the right to
deal with such settlers as She shall deem just, so as not to
diminish the extent of land allotted to the Indians; and provided,
further, that the aforesaid reserves of land, or any part thereof,
or any interest or right therein, or appurtenant thereto, may be
sold, leased or otherwise disposed of by the said Government for
the use and benefit of the said Indians, with the consent of the
Indians entitled thereto first had and obtained, but in no wise
shall the said Indians, or any of them, be entitled to sell or
otherwise alienate any of the lands allotted to them as
reserves.</p>
                  <p>In view of the satisfaction with which the Queen views the ready
response which Her Majesty's Indian subjects have accorded to the
invitation of Her said Commissioners to meet them on this occasion,
and also in token of their general good conduct and behaviour, She
hereby, through Her Commissioners, makes the Indians of the bands
here represented a present, for each Chief of twenty-five dollars
in cash, a coat and a Queen's silver medal; for each Headman, not
exceeding four in each band, fifteen dollars in cash and a coat;
and for every other man, woman and child twelve dollars in cash;
and for those here assembled some powder, shot, blankets, calicoes,
strouds and other articles.</p>
                  <p>As soon as possible after the execution of this treaty Her
Majesty shall cause a census to be taken of all the Indians
inhabiting the tract hereinbefore described, and shall, next year,
and annually afterwards for ever, cause to be paid in cash at some
suitable season to be duly notified to the Indians, and at a place
or places to be appointed for that purpose, within the territory
ceded, each Chief twenty-five dollars; each Headman not exceeding
four to a band, fifteen dollars; and to every other Indian man,
woman and child, five dollars per head; such payment to be made to
the heads of families for those belonging thereto, unless for some
special reason it be found objectionable.</p>
                  <p>Her Majesty also agrees that each Chief and each Headman, not to
exceed four in each band, once in every three years during the term
of their offices shall receive a suitable suit of clothing, and
that yearly and every year She will cause to be distributed among
the different bands included in the limits of this treaty powder,
shot, ball and twine, in all to the value of seven hundred and
fifty dollars; and each Chief shall receive hereafter, in
recognition of the closing of the treaty, a suitable flag.</p>
                  <p>It is further agreed between Her Majesty and the said Indians
that the following articles shall be supplied to any band thereof
who are now actually cultivating the soil, or who shall hereafter
settle on their reserves and commence to break up the land, that is
to say: two hoes, one spade, one scythe and one axe for every
family so actually cultivating, and enough seed wheat, barley, oats
and potatoes to plant such land as they have broken up; also one
plough and two harrows for every ten families so cultivating as
aforesaid, and also to each Chief for the use of his band as
aforesaid, one yoke of oxen, one bull, four cows, a chest of
ordinary carpenter's tools, five hand saws, five augers, one
cross-cut saw, one pit-saw, the necessary files and one grindstone,
all the aforesaid articles to be given, once for all, for the
encouragement of the practice of agriculture among the Indians.</p>
                  <p>Further, Her Majesty agrees to maintain a school in the reserve
allotted to each band as soon as they settle on said reserve and
are prepared for a teacher.</p>
                  <p>Further, Her Majesty agrees that within the boundary of the
Indian reserves, until otherwise determined by the Government of
the Dominion of Canada, no intoxicating liquor shall be allowed to
be introduced or sold, and all laws now in force, or hereafter to
be enacted, to preserve Her Indian subjects, inhabiting the
reserves, or living elsewhere within the North-West Territories,
from the evil effects of intoxicating liquor, shall be strictly
enforced.</p>
                  <p>And further, Her Majesty agrees that Her said Indians shall have
right to pursue their avocations of hunting, trapping and fishing
throughout the tract surrendered, subject to such regulations as
may from time to time be made by the Government of the country,
acting under the authority of Her Majesty, and saving and excepting
such tracts as may be required or taken up from time to time for
settlement, mining or other purposes, under grant or other right
given by Her Majesty's said Government.</p>
                  <p>It is further agreed between Her Majesty and Her said Indian
subjects that such sections of the reserves above indicated as may
at any time be required for public works or building of whatsoever
nature may be appropriated for that purpose by Her Majesty's
Government of the Dominion of Canada, due compensation being made
to the Indians for the value of any improvements thereon, and an
equivalent in land or money for the area of the reserve so
appropriated.</p>
                  <p>And the undersigned Chiefs and Headmen, on their own behalf and
on behalf of all other Indians inhabiting the tract within ceded,
do hereby solemnly promise and engage to strictly observe this
treaty, and also to conduct and behave themselves as good and loyal
subjects of Her Majesty the Queen. They promise and engage that
they will, in all respects, obey and abide by the law, that they
will maintain peace and good order between each other, and between
themselves and other tribes of Indians and between themselves and
others of Her Majesty's subjects, whether Indians, Half-breeds, or
whites, now inhabiting or hereafter to inhabit any part of the said
ceded tract; and that they will not molest the person or property
of any inhabitant of such ceded tract, or the property of Her
Majesty the Queen, or interfere with or trouble any person passing
or travelling through the said tract, or any part thereof, and that
they will assist the officers of Her Majesty in bringing to justice
and punishment any Indian offending against the stipulations of
this treaty, or infringing the laws in force in the country so
ceded.</p>
                  <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF Her Majesty's said Commissioners, and the
said Indian Chiefs and Headmen, have hereunto subscribed and set
their hands, at Qu'Appelle, this day and year herein first above
written.</p>
                  
                     
                        <p>Signed by the Chiefs and Headmen within named in
presence of the following witnesses, the same having been first
read and explained by <persName ref="pers:PRAT1">Charles Pratt</persName>:<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:SMIT12">W. OSBORNE SMITH</persName>, C.M.G.<lb/>
Lt.-Col. D.A.G. Commg.<lb/>
Dominion Forces in North-West.,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BREL1">PASCAL BRELAND</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKA7">EDWARD MCKAY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:PRAT1">CHARLES PRATT</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:POIT1">PIERRE POITRAS</persName> <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DAVI5">BAPTIST DAVIS</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DENO1">PIERRE DENOMME</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKA8">JOSEPH McKAY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCDO10">DONALD McDONALD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCDO16">A. McDONALD</persName>,<lb/>
Capt. Provl. Battn. Infantry,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:STRE2">GEO. W. STREET</persName>,<lb/>
Ens. Provl. Battn. Infantry,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CODD1">ALFRED CODD</persName>, M.D.,<lb/>
Surgeon Provl. Battn. Infantry,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HERC1">W. M. HERCHMER</persName>, Captain,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DECO2">C. DE COUYES</persName>, Ensign,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:POIT2">JOS. POITRON</persName>, x<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DICK3">M. G. DICKIESON</persName>,<lb/>
Private Secy. Min. of Interior,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LAPI1">PETER LAPIERRE</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCLE9">HELEN M. McLEAN</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:GARR2">FLORA GARRIOGH</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:COTT1">JOHN COTTON</persName>, Lt. Canadian Artillery<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ALLA2">JOHN ALLAN</persName>,<lb/>
Lt. Provl. Battn. Infantry<lb/>
                        </p>
                        <p><persName ref="pers:MORR1">ALEXANDER MORRIS</persName>,<lb/>
Lt.-Gov. North-West Territories,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LAIR4">DAVID LAIRD</persName>, Indian Commissioner,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CHRI3">WILLIAM J. CHRISTIE</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KAKI1">KA-KII-SHI-WAY</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:PISQ1">PIS-QUA</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KAWE1">KA-WEZAUCE</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KAKE3">KA-KEE-NA-WUP</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KUSK1">KUS-KEE-TEW-MUS-COO-MUS-QUA</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KANE1">KA-NE-ON-US-KA-TEW</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:CAUA1">CAN-AH-HA-CHA-PEU</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KIIS1">KII-SI-CAW-AH-CHUCK</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KAWA1">KA-WA-CA-TOOSE</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KAKI2">KA-KU-WIS-TA-HAW</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:CHAC1">CHA-CA-CHAS</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:WAHP1">WA-PII-MOOSE-TOO-SUS</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:MEEM1">GABRIEL COTÉ OR MEE-MAY</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark<lb/>
                        </p>
                     
                  
                  <p>We, members of the Saulteaux Tribe of Indians, having had
communication of the treaty hereto annexed, made on the 15th day of
September instant, between Her Majesty the Queen and the Cree and
Saulteaux Indians, and other Indians at Qu'Appelle lakes, but not
having been present at the councils held at Qu'Appelle lakes
between Her Majesty's Commissioners and the several Indian Chiefs,
and other therein named, at which the articles of the said treaty
were agreed upon, hereby for ourselves and the band which we
represent, in consideration of the provisions of the said treaty
being extended to us and the said band which we represent,
transfer, surrender and relinquish to Her Majesty the Queen, Her
heirs and successors, to and for the use of Her Government of Her
Dominion of Canada, all our right, title and privileges whatsoever
which we and the said band which we represent, have held or enjoy,
of, in and to the territory described and fully set out in the said
articles of treaty and every part thereof also all our right, title
and privilege whatsoever, to all other lands, wherever situated,
whether within the limits of any treaty formerly made or hereafter
to be made with the Saulteaux Tribe or any other tribe of Indians
inhabiting Her Majesty's North-West Territories, or any of them. To
have and to hold the same unto and to use of Her said Majesty the
Queen, Her heirs and successors forever.</p>
                  <p>And we hereby agree to accept the several provisions, payments
and reserves of the said treaty, signed at the Qu'Appelle lakes, as
therein stated, and solemnly promise and engage to abide by, carry
out and fulfil all the stipulations, obligations and conditions
therein contained on the part of said Chiefs and Indians therein
named to be observed and performed, and in all things to conform to
the articles of the said treaty, as if we ourselves, and the band
which we represent, had been originally contracting parties thereto
and had been present and attached our signatures to the said
treaty.</p>
                  <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF Her Majesty's said Commissioners and the said
Indian Chief and Headman have hereunto subscribed and set their
hands at Fort Ellice, this twenty-first day of September, in the
year of Our Lord one thousand eight hundred and seventy-four.</p>
                  
                     
                        <p>Signed by the parties hereto, in the presence of
the undersigned witnesses, the same having been first explained to
the Indians by <persName ref="pers:ROBI5">Joseph Robillard</persName>:<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCDO13">ARCH. McDONALD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FLET1">GEORGE FLETT</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MAXW1">A. MAXWELL</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ARMI1">DAVID ARMIT</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKA9">HENRY McKAY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCDO17">ELLEN McDONALD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:ARMI2">MARY ARMIT</persName>,<lb/>
                        </p>
                        <p><persName ref="pers:MORR1">ALEXANDER MORRIS</persName>,<lb/>
Lt.-Gov. North-West Territories.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:LAIR4">DAVID LAIRD</persName>, Indian Commissioner.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CHRI3">W. J. CHRISTIE</persName>, Indian Commissioner,</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:WAYW1">WAY-WA-SE-CA-POW</persName>, or the MAN PROUD OF STANDING UPRIGHT,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:OTAM1">OTA-MA-KOO-EWIN</persName>, or SHA-POUS-E-TUNG'S-FIRST SON, THE MAN WHO STANDS
ON THE EARTH,<lb/>
his x mark<lb/>
                        </p>
                     
                  
                  <p>We, members of the Cree, Saulteaux and Stonie Tribes of Indians,
having had communication of the treaty hereto annexed, made on the
15th day of September last between Her Majesty the Queen and the
Cree and Saulteaux Indians, and other Indians at Qu'Appelle Lakes,
but not having been present at the councils held at the Qu'Appelle
Lakes between Her Majesty's Commissioners and several Indian Chiefs
and others therein contained, at which the articles of the said
treaty were agreed upon, hereby, for ourselves and the bands which
we represent, in consideration of the provisions of the said treaty
having extended to us and the said bands which we represent,
transfer, surrender and relinquish to Her Majesty the Queen, Her
heirs and successors, to and for the use of Her Government of Her
Dominion of Canada, all our right, title and privileges whatsoever
which we and the said bands which we represent have held or enjoy,
of, in and to the territory described and fully set out in the said
articles of treaty and every part thereof; also, all our right,
title and privileges whatsoever to all other lands wherever
situated, whether within the limit of any treaty formerly made or
hereafter to be made with the Saulteaux Tribe or any other tribe of
Indians inhabiting Her Majesty's North-West Territories, or any of
them. To have and to hold the same unto and to the use of Her said
Majesty the Queen, Her heirs and successors forever.</p>
                  <p>And we hereby agree to accept the several provisions, payments
and reserves of the said treaty, signed at the Qu'Appelle Lakes, as
therein stated, and solemnly promise and engage to abide by, carry
out and fulfill all the stipulations, obligations and conditions
therein contained on the part of said Chiefs and Indians therein
named to be observed and performed, and in all things to conform to
the articles of the said treaty as if we, ourselves, and the bands
which we represent, had been originally contracting parties
thereto, and had been present and attached our signatures to the
said treaty.</p>
                  <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Her Majesty's Commissioners and the said
Indian Chiefs have hereunto subscribed and set their hands at
Qu'Appelle Lakes this eighth day of September, in the year or Our
Lord one thousand eight hundred and seventy-five.</p>
                  
                     
                        <p>Signed by the parties hereto in the presence of
the undersigned witnesses, the same having been first explained to
the Indians by <persName ref="pers:MCKA10">William the second McKay</persName>.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCKA10">WILLIAM S. McKAY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCDO13">ARCH. McDONALD</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BREL1">PASCAL BRELAND</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WAGN1">WILLIAM WAGNER</persName>.<lb/>
                        </p>
                        <p><persName ref="pers:CHRI3">W. J. CHRISTIE</persName>, Indian Commissioner,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DICK3">M. G. DICKIESON</persName>, Acting Ind'n Com'r.,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WRIG9">W. F. WRIGHT</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:CHEE1">CHEE x CUK</persName> <lb/>
his x mark<lb/>
                        </p>
                     
                  
                  <p>We, members of the Cree, Saulteaux and Stonie Tribes of Indians,
having had communication of the treaty hereto annexed, made on the
15th day of September last between Her Majesty the Queen and the
Cree and Saulteaux Indians and other Indians at the Qu'Appelle
Lakes, but not having been present at the councils held at the
Qu'Appelle Lakes, between Her Majesty's Commissioners and the
several Indian Chiefs and others therein named, at which the
articles of the said treaty were agreed upon, hereby for ourselves
and the bands which we represent, in consideration of the
provisions of the said treaty having extended to us, and the said
bands which we represent, transfer, surrender and relinquish to Her
Majesty the Queen, Her heirs and successors, to and for the use of
Her Government of Her Dominion of Canada, all our right, title and
privileges whatsoever which we and the said bands which we
represent have held or enjoy, of, in and to the territory described
and fully set out in the said articles of treaty, and every part
thereof; also, all our right, title, and privileges whatsoever to
all other lands wherever situated, whether within the limit of any
treaty formerly made, of hereafter to be made with the Saulteaux
Tribe or any other tribe of Indians inhabiting Her Majesty's
North-West Territories, or any of them. To have and to hold the
same unto and to the use of Her said Majesty the Queen, Her heirs
and successors forever.</p>
                  <p>And we hereby agree to accept the several provisions, payments
and reserves of the said treaty signed at the Qu'Appelle Lakes, as
therein stated, and solemnly promise and engage to abide by, carry
out and fulfil all the stipulations, obligations and conditions
therein contained on the part of said Chiefs and Indians therein
named to be observed and performed, and in all things to conform to
the articles of the said treaty as if we ourselves and the bands
which we represent had been originally contracting parties thereto
and had been present and attached our signatures to the said
treaty.</p>
                  <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Her Majesty's Commissioners and the said
Indian Chiefs have hereunto subscribed and set their hands at
Qu'Appelle Lakes this ninth day of September, in the year of Our
Lord one thousand eight hundred and seventy-five.</p>
                  
                     
                        <p>Signed by the parties hereto, in the presence of
the undersigned witnesses, the same having been first explained to
the Indians by <persName ref="pers:PRAT1">Charles Pratt</persName>.<lb/>
Witness <persName ref="pers:PRAT1">CHARLES PRATT</persName>,<lb/>
Witness <persName ref="pers:MCDO13">ARCH. McDONALD</persName>,<lb/>
Witness <persName ref="pers:READ2">JOSEPH READER</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BREL1">PASCAL BRELAND</persName>.<lb/>
                        </p>
                        <p><persName ref="pers:CHRI3">W. J. CHRISTIE</persName>, Ind. Comr.,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DICK3">M. G. DICKIESON</persName>, Ind. Comr.,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:WRIG9">W. F. WRIGHT</persName>,</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:WAHP2">WAH-PEE-MAKWA</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:WHIT15">THE WHITE BEAR</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:OKAN1">OKANES</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:PAYE1">PAYEPOT</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:LECR1">LE CROUP DE PHEASANT</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KITC3">KITCHI-KAH-ME-WIN</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark<lb/>
                        </p>
                     
                  
                  <p>We, members of the Cree and Saulteaux Tribes of Indians, having
had communication of the treaty made on the 15th day of September,
1874, between Her Majesty the Queen and the Cree and Saulteaux
Indians and other Indians at Qu'Appelle Lakes, but not having been
present at the councils held at Qu'Appelle Lakes between Her
Majesty's Commissioners and the several Indian Chiefs and others
therein named, at which the articles of the said treaty were agreed
upon, hereby for ourselves and the band which we represent, in
consideration of the provisions of the said treaty having extended
to us and the said band which we represent, transfer, surrender and
relinquish to Her Majesty the Queen, Her heirs and successors, to
and for the use of Her Government of Her Dominion of Canada, all
our right, title and privileges whatsoever which we and the said
band which we represent have held or enjoy, of, in and to the
territory described and fully set out in the said articles of
treaty and every part thereof; also our right, title and privileges
whatsoever to all other lands wherever situated, whether within the
limits of any treaty formerly made or hereafter to be made with the
Saulteaux Tribe or any other tribe of Indians inhabiting Her
Majesty's North-West Territories, or any of them. To have and to
hold the same unto and to the use of Her said Majesty the Queen,
Her heirs and successors for ever.</p>
                  <p>And we hereby agree to accept the several provisions, payment
and reserves of the said treaty signed at the Qu'Appelle Lakes as
therein stated, and solemnly promise and engage to abide by, carry
out and fulfil all the stipulations, obligations and conditions
therein contained, on the part of said Chiefs and Indians therein
named to be observed and performed, and in all things to conform to
the articles of the said treaty as if we ourselves and the band
which we represent had been originally contracting parties thereto,
and had been present and attached our signatures to the said
treaty.</p>
                  <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Her Majesty's Commissioners and the Indian
Chiefs have hereunto subscribed and set their hands at Swan Lake,
this twenty-fourth day of September, in the year of Our Lord one
thousand eight hundred and seventy-five.</p>
                  
                     
                        <p>Signed by the parties hereto, in the presence of the
undersigned witnesses, the same having been first explained to the
Indians by <persName ref="pers:BRAS1">George Brass</persName>.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCDO13">ARCH. McDONALD</persName>, Witness.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCDO10">DONALD McDONALD</persName>, Witness,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:BRAS1">GEORGE BRASS</persName>, Witness,<lb/>
his x mark<lb/>
                        </p>
                        <p><persName ref="pers:CHRI3">W. J. CHRISTIE</persName>, Indian Comr.,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:DICK3">M. G. DICKIESON</persName>, Acting Indian Comr.,</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:OWTA1">OW-TAH-PEE-KA-KAW</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KIIS2">KII-SHI-KOUSE</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark<lb/>
                        </p>
                     
                  
                  <p>We, members of the Saulteaux Tribe of Indians, having had
communication of the treaty hereto annexed, made on the 15th day of
September, A.D. 1874, between Her Majesty the Queen and the Cree
and Saulteaux Indians and other Indians at Qu'Appelle Lakes, but
not having been present at the councils held at the Qu'Appelle
Lakes between Her Majesty's Commissioners and the several Indian
Chiefs and others therein named, at which the articles of the said
treaty were agreed upon, hereby for ourselves and the band which we
represent, in consideration of the provisions of the said treaty
having extended to us and the said band which we represent,
transfer, surrender and relinquish to Her Majesty the Queen, Her
heirs and successors, to and for the use of Her Government of Her
Dominion of Canada, all our right, title and privileges whatsoever
which we and the said band which we represent have held or enjoy,
of, in and to the territory described and fully set out in the said
articles of treaty and every part thereof; also, all our right,
title and privileges whatsoever to all other lands wherever
situated, whether within the limit of any treaty formerly made or
hereafter to be made with the Saulteaux Tribe or any other tribe of
Indians inhabiting Her Majesty's North-West Territories, or any of
them. To have and to hold the same unto and to use of Her said
Majesty the Queen, Her heirs and successors forever.</p>
                  <p>And we hereby agree to accept the several provisions, payments
and reserves of the said treaty signed at the Qu'Appelle Lakes as
therein stated, and solemnly promise and engage to abide by, carry
out and fulfill all the stipulations, obligations and conditions
therein contained on the part of the said Chiefs and Indians
therein named to be observed and performed, and in all things to
conform to the articles of the said treaty as if we ourselves and
the band which we represent had been originally contracting parties
thereto, and had been present and attached our signatures to the
said treaty.</p>
                  <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Her Majesty's Commissioners and the said
Indian Chief and Headmen have hereunto subscribed and set their
hands at Fort Pelly, this twenty-fourth day of August, in the year
of Our Lord one thousand eight hundred and seventy-six.</p>
                  
                     
                        <p>Signed by the parties hereto in the presence of
the undersigned witnesses, the same having been first read and
explained by <persName ref="pers:MCKA2">A. McKAY</persName>:<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCDO14">AND. McDONALD</persName>.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:RUSS1">ALEX. LORD RUSSELL</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:FLET1">GEORGE FLETT</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCBE1">HUGH McBEATH</persName>.<lb/>
                        </p>
                        <p><persName ref="pers:MCKA2">A. McKAY</persName>,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:NAGL1">W. H. NAGLE</persName>,</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:OOZA2">OO-ZA-WASK-OO-QUIN-APE</persName>, (or YELLOW QUILL),<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:KENI1">KENISTIN</persName> (or CREE),<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:NEPI1">NE-PIN-AWA</persName> (or SUMMER FUR),<lb/>
his x mark<lb/>
                        </p>
                     
                  
                  <p>We, members of the Assiniboine Tribe of Indians, having had
communication of the treaty hereto annexed, made on the 15th day of
September, one thousand eight hundred and seventy-four, between Her
Majesty the Queen and the Cree Saulteaux Indians, and other Indians
at Qu'Appelle Lakes, but not having been present at the councils
held at Qu'Appelle Lakes between Her Majesty's Commissioners and
the several Indian Chiefs and others therein named, at which the
articles of the said treaty were agreed upon, hereby for ourselves,
and the band which we represent, in consideration of the provisions
of the treaty being extended to us and the said band which we
represent, transfer, surrender and relinquish to Her Majesty the
Queen, Her heirs and successors, to and for the use of Her
Government of Her Dominion of Canada, all our right, title and
privileges whatsoever which we and the bands which we represent
have held or enjoy, of, in and to the territory described and fully
set out in the said articles of treaty and every part thereof; also
our right, title and privileges whatsoever to all other lands
wherever situated, whether within the limit of any treaty formerly
made or hereafter to be made with the Assiniboine Tribe or any
other tribe of Indians inhabiting Her Majesty's North-West
Territories, or any of them. To have and to hold the same unto and
to the use of Her said Majesty the Queen, Her Heirs and successors
forever.</p>
                  <p>And we hereby agree to accept the several provisions and the
payment in the following manner, viz.: That those who have not
already received payment receive this year the sums of twelve
dollars for the year 1876, which shall be considered their first
year of payment, and five dollars for the year 1877, making
together the sum of seventeen dollars apiece to those who have
never been paid, and five dollars per annum for every subsequent
year, and also the reserves of the said treaty signed at Qu'Appelle
Lakes, as therein stated, and solemnly promise and agree to abide
by, carry out and fulfil all the stipulations, obligations and
conditions therein contained on the part of the said Chiefs and
Indians therein named to be observed and performed, and in all
things to conform to the articles of the said treaty as if we
ourselves and the band which we represent had been originally
contracting parties thereto and had been present and attached our
signatures to the said treaty.</p>
                  <p>IN WITNESS WHEREOF, Major James M. Walsh, Inspector of
North-West Mounted Police, in command at Forth Walsh, and the said
Indian Chiefs and Headmen, have hereunto set their hands at Fort
Walsh, this twenty-fifth day of September, in the year of Our Lord
one thousand eight hundred and seventy-seven.</p>
                  
                     
                        <p>Signed by the parties hereto in the presence of
the undersigned witnesses, the same having been first explained by
<persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Constant Provost</persName> to the Indians.<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:MCIL2">J. H. McILLREE</persName>,<lb/>
Sub-Inspector,<lb/>
<persName ref="pers:NEAL1">PERCY REGINALD NEALE</persName>,<lb/>
Sub-Inspector, N.W.M.P.<lb/>
                        </p>
                        <p><persName ref="pers:WALS5">J. M. WALSH</persName>,</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:LONG3">LONG LODGE TEPEE HOSKA</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:ONET1">THE ONE THAT FETCHED THE COAT</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:WICH1">WICH-A-WOS-TAKA</persName>.<lb/>
his x mark</p>
<p>
<persName ref="pers:POOR1">THE POOR MAN</persName>,<lb/>
his x mark<lb/>
                        </p>
                     


</div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
