<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgBCLC_1870-03-24"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgBCLCoun">British Columbia Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1870-03-24">24 March 1870</date>, Province of BC, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          <editor>W.S. Sebright Green</editor>
          
         
               <title>Legislative Council, Debate on the Subject of Confederation with Canada</title>.
                    

          <date when="1912"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Victoria, B.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>William H. Cullin</publisher>.
                    
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="150"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_142.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_143.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_144.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_145.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_146.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_147.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_148.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_149.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_150.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-22">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-22">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-25">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_142">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_142.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_143">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_143.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_144">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_144.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_145">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_145.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_146">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_146.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_147">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_147.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_148">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_148.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_149">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_149.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_150">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_150.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="142" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_142.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">142</fw> <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
<!-- GL, 2017-03-22, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->

<!--<p>
     Hon. MR. BARNARD—And turn people out of the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. DR. HELMCKEN—You keep them in. You send out $100,000 a quarter for goods, 
     <lb/>
     which ought to be spent here. That $100,000 ought to be invested in mines and in building up 
     <lb/>
     the country. Now, you want this country to be a garden and a manufactory. The people must 
     <lb/>
     do it, and it is the only way in which they can do it. Put your productions into competition 
     <lb/>
     with the whole world and you will ruin the producers throughout the whole Colony. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER—Another question is, up to what point are you to protect? 
     <lb/>
     What is the use of protecting produce if you protect colonists out of the country? I put this 
     <lb/>
     as an abstract proposition. There is no more moot point than the difference between free trade 
     <lb/>
     and protection. I see the Canadian tariff protects these things, and I don't feel inclined to ask 
     <lb/>
     for more. Under the Canadian tariff agricultural products are almost free, but manufactures 
     <lb/>
    are protected. I don't intend to assume that the tariff will be taken off—that protection is to 
     <lb/>be taken away from manufacturers, for, if so, it will be against the arguments of the members 
     <lb/>from British Columbia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     Hon. MR. ROBSON-Some members are growing protection mad. They want to build a 
     <lb/>
     wall around the Colony and keep out the entire world. You must come down to first principles. 
     <lb/>
     When honourable members talk about protection, I suppose we intend to protect that which we 
     <lb/>
     can produce. Are we to protect so as to force people into branches of industry unthought of 
     <lb/>
     before? Some honourable members have run to the extent of protecting population out of 
     <lb/>
     the Colony; another favours protection in order to keep prices low, and thus to secure our 
     <lb/>
     population. I maintain that protection has run too far, and the agriculturists have not 
     <lb/>
     benefited by it. ["No, no "—Mr. DeCosmos.] They tell me that the demand is so small that 
     <lb/>
     prices are less. I am not in favour of withdrawing protection from farmers, but let us see 
     <lb/>
     that it does not go too far. . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. WOOD-Might I not turn the tables by judging some honourable members are 
     <lb/>
     free trade mad. No one ever dreamt of such high taxation.  So far from sweeping oft popula<lb break="no"/>tion we secure it; and in England free trade is intended to benefit the manufacturer, and it 
     <lb/>
     does so. It struck a blow at agriculture, and if they had not gone into raising and spending 
     <lb/>
     more money it would have been an utter failure. High price for corn is now unknown, but free 
     <lb/>
     trade by way of dogma is absurd.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. DECOSMOS—There is a distinction between a tariff for protection and a prohibi<lb break="no"/>tory tariff. The Hon. Collector of Customs will set me right, if I am mistaken, but I believe 
     <lb/>
     the importation of arms from foreign countries  into a Colony is prohibited. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. COLLECTOR OF  CUSTOMS—Prohibited, I believe, altogether. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. DECOSMOS—Precisely so; that the defence of the Colony may never depend on 
     <lb/>
     foreign aid. The Hon. Chief Commissioner asked the extent of the protection. I say during the 
     <lb/>
     infancy of the Colony. When we are able to run alone, protection will be necessary. With 
     <lb/>
     regard to farmers wanting free trade, I deny it emphatically. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. DR. HELMCKEN—No doubt the Canadian Government will like this amendment of 
     <lb/>
     the tariff. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL—I shall vote against it because it says it is expedient to 
     <lb/>
     arrange it in the terms. If the Hon. Member alters the wording it would then become on the 
     <lb/>
     same footing as the last recommendation.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. DECOSMOS altered the wording accordingly, and on vote the motion was lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The motion of Hon. Dr. Helmcken was put and carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head>
     THURSDAY, 24TH March, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   

            <p> On the House going into Committee of the Whole on the Confederation Resolution, <lb/>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DECOSMOS</persName> moved the following resolution :—" That in the
                  opinion of this Council <lb/> it is expedient, in order to foster commerce, to
                  admit, duty free, into this Colony or some <lb/> portions thereof, certain
                  articles of foreign merchandise not produced in the Dominion or this <lb/>Colony,
                  and that provision for the admission of the same be made in the terms of Union
                  with <lb/>Canada." In reply to a question the Hon. mover said it would be
                  impossible to name all the <lb/>articles; but a few of them might be instanced,
                  such as tropical fruits, silks, and English dry <lb/>
                  <pb n="143" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_143.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">143</fw> goods; he thought this the proper time to bring these
                  matters to the attention of the Dominion <lb/> Government, believing that they
                  would listen to them. Some discussion ensued as to the mode <lb/> in which the
                  different recommendations and resolutions were to be taken up. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> called Hon. Members' attention to
                  the fact, that it had <lb/> been agreed by the House that an expression of opinion
                  on these general principles, namely, as <lb/> to the protection of agriculture, of
                  manufactures, and of commerce, should be taken, and that, <lb/> as had been very
                  properly suggested by the Member for Victoria District, a general resolution <lb/>
                  should be framed on these abstract views. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I shall offer an amendment, because I think
                  the question of free port <lb/> and protection should not be dealt with together.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —The proposition of the Hon. Member for
                  Victoria District <lb/> is as to what shall he admitted free; the Hon. Member for
                  New Westminster proposes to <lb/> suspend the whole tariff. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I stated one reason why I thought it not
                  desirable to put the two <lb/> together. You cannot get the control of the tariff.
                  I say we want free trade in certain articles, <lb/> and I say we must have the
                  tariff entirely re—modelled as to these articles. My difficulty is that <lb/> we
                  were last evening discussing protection, and how far we should have the power to
                  deal with <lb/> it. I moved an amendment which was, I think, the only
                  constitutional way of dealing with the <lb/> question, and in answering certain
                  propositions of Hon. gentlemen yesterday, I endeavoured to <lb/> deal with
                  protection, <hi rendition="simple:italic">per se</hi>. I listened with interest to
                  what fell from the Hon. Commissioner <lb/> of Customs, and I do not like to set my
                  opinion against his on matters of this kind, on which <lb/> I know he is an
                  authority, especially when I find him backed by the Hon. Attorney-General and
                  <lb/> Chief Commissioner of Lands and Works. I instanced the United States of
                  America, and said <lb/> that they are a living instance of non-separation of
                  tariff. The Hon. Commissioner of Customs <lb/> did not go so far as to say we
                  could frame a tariff for ourselves, but that the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"
                  />ment would frame it for us. Now, Sir, I say that we must not run away with any
                  such idea. <lb/> If we were allowed to have a different scheme of revenue,
                  Newfoundland would ask the same; <lb/> New Brunswick, Prince Edward Island and
                  other Provinces would all ask for exceptional tariffs, <lb/> and the Federal
                  fiscal policy would be broken up and destroyed. Depend upon it we ought not <lb/>
                  to run away with such an idea. The Dominion Government cannot admit of exceptional
                  or <lb/> differential tariffs any more than the United States can do so. Some Hon.
                  Members say that <lb/> we are not under the Organic Act, and need not be under it,
                  unless we choose; that there is a <lb/> distinction between the relations of the
                  Provinces that were Confederated under the Act and <lb/> those that may hereafter
                  come in, and that we can change the Organic Act if we think proper. <lb/> I admit
                  that any Province not prepared to come in under the Organic Act can stay out. The
                  <lb/> Act is not binding on us now, but it will be if we go into the Dominion. I
                  am surprised to <lb/> hear some Hon. Members speaking lightly of a reciprocity
                  treaty. Look at the single item of <lb/> coal. We at present only send 18,000 tons
                  per annum to San Francisco. I have no doubt that <lb/> under a reciprocity treaty,
                  we should supply them with 50,000 tons a year at least, to say nothing <lb/> of
                  anthracite coal. In the course of a few years, allowing time for trade to develop
                  itself, this <lb/> would bring in $900,000 or, say, one million dollars a year
                  into the Colony. Mr. Chairman, we <lb/> are now speaking of a single item, and
                  that, I believe, not the largest, which would bring in one <lb/> million a year,
                  and that calculation is based upon the present consumption of coal in San <lb/>
                  Francisco, and the consumption will no doubt increase. In addition to this, look
                  at the quantity <lb/> of shipping, and the cheap commodities which these ships
                  bring in, which could hardly be brought <lb/> as a measure of commerce. There are
                  objectors to reciprocity. No doubt it would be very nice <lb/> if we could open
                  the United States ports to our goods, and close our ports to their goods. But
                  <lb/> this would not be reciprocity. There is, in my opinion, only one answer to
                  be given. I say, <lb/> give the farmers good roads, and this will be protection
                  for them. Now, Sir, what does the <lb/> development of our coal interests mean? It
                  means extension of labour, and circulation of <lb/> money. Farmers have at once a
                  full demand for their produce. Apply the same argument to <lb/> lumber. Its
                  development would cause more money to be expended in the Colony. Every ton <lb/>
                  of coal brought to the bank, and every tree cut down, means spending of money.
                  There, then, <lb/> is another field opened up for what farmers have to sell. Give
                  the farmers this development <lb/> and good roads, and they would soon find out
                  that reciprocity would be like the handle of a jug, <lb/> on the side of British
                  Columbia. Depend upon it we will come in under the reciprocity treaty, <lb/> and
                  the advantages will be so great on our side that it will hardly be reciprocity.
                  Nothing can <lb/> be more unfair than to suppose we are to have a free market in
                  the United States and they <lb/> have none here. <lb/>
               </p>


            <pb n="144" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_144.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">144</fw> <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HAML1">Hon. COLLECTOR OF CUSTOMS</persName> asked if Hon. Mr. Robson had any
                  resolution to propose. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> said that at present he was replying to
                  remarks that had been made <lb/> by other Hon. gentlemen. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> said that the course that the Hon.
                  gentleman was pursuing <lb/> was embarrassing, and would tend to complicate the
                  question before the House, and proceeded <lb/> to correct a statement which he
                  understood Hon. Mr. Robson to have made as to what had fallen <lb/> from the Hon.
                  Chief Commissioner, Hon. Mr. Hamley, and himself on a previous occasion as to
                  <lb/> the right to control tariff being in the Provinces after Union. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —Anyone who knows the history of the United
                  States knows that if <lb/> any question of dealing with the tariff law in any
                  manner other than Federal could arise, it <lb/> would be in reference to groups of
                  States instead of single States. I say, then, that we must <lb/> consider this as
                  a group of Provinces of the Dominion. Many years will probably not elapse <lb/>
                  before we see groups of States distinguished as Pacific and Atlantic, or East and
                  West, and <lb/> North and South, in the neighbouring Republic. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon MR. ROBSON</persName> —I rise to move a resolution. It is the same
                  as that proposed at the <lb/> Yale Convention by the Hon. Member for Victoria
                  District, in 1867. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> and <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>
                  —What Convention? We know of no <lb/> Convention. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I have a perfect right to allude to what
                  took place at the little <lb/> Parliament at Yale. I believe this to be the proper
                  way to approach the subject. The resolution <lb/> which I propose is as follows :—
                  <lb/>
               </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" That a respectful Address be presented to His Excellency the Governor recommending that 
     <lb/>
     the following may be included in the conditions of the proposed terms of Union with Canada: 
     <lb/>
     ' If at any time after the admission, the Legislature of British Columbia shall pass an Address 
     <lb/>
     to the Govenor-General of Canada declaring that it is expedient to establish a free port on the 
     <lb/>
     Pacific in order to advance the interests of British commerce in the North Pacific, the Parliament 
     <lb/>
     of the Dominion to make provision for the establishment of the same.' " 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     It is astonishing to find what a change has come over the Hon. Mr. DeCosmos since he 
     <lb/>
     changed his city seat for a rural seat. He is becoming less capable of taking a statesmanlike 
     <lb/>
     view of these things than he was two years ago. 1 think by providing that if the new Council 
     <lb/>
     shall, after due deliberation, find it desirable, that a free port shall be established in this Colony 
     <lb/>
     is, after all, the proper way. I cannot think that this House, with the small representative 
     <lb/>
     element that it has, should be asked to decide this point. I say that the tendency of the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian policy is in the direction of free trade. [No, no, from the Hon. Mr. DeCosmos.]  I 
     <lb/>
     say it is, and there is a speech of Sir G. E. Cartier recently published, in which he says that 
     <lb/>
     the tendency of Canadian policy is towards free trade. Now, I believe, that a great British 
     <lb/>
     Empire is to be established on this Continent,—the Greater Britain ; and I believe that all 
     <lb/>
     British manufactures will be admitted free. If Great Britain takes her true part in pushing 
     <lb/>
     forward this Empire, she will naturally expect some advantages ; she will naturally look for 
     <lb/>
     some immediate financial result. Every unproductive labourer in England is a tax upon the 
     <lb/>
     others ; but transfer them to the Dominion and they will become producers and consumers.   I 
     <lb/>
     believe it to be of the first importance that there should be a free port here. By a free port 
     <lb/>
     I do not mean that everything should necessarily be admitted free. There is no reason why 
     <lb/>
     local industries. and especially agricultural interests, should not continue to enjoy substantial 
     <lb/>
     protection. I believe the Canadian Government will readily realize the advantages of the 
     <lb/>
     policy of having a free port on the Pacific. There could be no local jealousies growing out of it. 
     <lb/>
     The Provinces on the Atlantic could not object. Our free port would attract commerce and 
     <lb/>
     wealth to the nation which they could not possibly  attract, and thus enrich the nation and 
     <lb/>
     reflexly benefit all. I maintain that while the larger advantages would be local, the general 
     <lb/>
     advantages would be very considerable. I was gratified in reading a leading article in the 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Ottawa Times</hi>, the organ of the Dominion Government, in which the theory of a free port for 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion on the Pacific is strongly and ably advocated ; and this article forms a complete 
     <lb/>
     answer to those who allege that the Canadian statesmen would never listen to any such propo<lb break="no"/>sition. If it should be decided that a free port would conduce to the interest of the Province 
     <lb/>
     and, consequently, to the interest of the Dominion, why should not we have it? Why should 
     <lb/>
     we object? What more glorious idea can there be than that of a British Empire extending 
     <lb/>
     across the Continent, with its back to the North Pole, with its face looking Southward. I will 
     <lb/>
     not venture to say how far ; with one foot planted on the Atlantic and the other on the Pacific, 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="145" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_145.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">145</fw>
           

     stretching out one hand to Europe and the other to Asia, and inviting the commerce of both 
     <lb/>
     hemispheres to enter its wide open portals, free as the wind that fills the canvas. Depend upon 
     <lb/>
     it, Sir, if this is to be the true north-west passage, the gates must be thrown open. Let us not 
     <lb/>
     repel commerce, but woo it. I venture to think that the resolution which I have the honour to 
     <lb/>
     offer proposes to deal with the matter in the most statesmanlike way; and I trust it will com<lb break="no"/>mend itself to the judgment, and receive the support, of all parties in the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. MR. HOLBROOK</persName>, whilst believing that the establishment of
                  a free port at Victoria <lb/> might be beneficial to the interests of the Lower
                  Fraser, did not think it would be for the general <lb/> good of the Colony. In his
                  opinion the agricultural interests wanted protection. For the present <lb/> he
                  must vote against the Hon. Member for New Westminster. He thought that such
                  questions <lb/> ought to be left to the Dominion Government. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —After the very, I will not say unusual,
                  but unexpected, remarks in <lb/> reference to myself, I must crave the indulgence
                  of the House whilst I say a few words to set <lb/> myself right. Sir, I had
                  something to do with the Yale Convention, and I am not ashamed of <lb/> my
                  connection with it; my political standard was unfurled then as it is to-day. When
                  I first <lb/> entered upon politics in this country I established a high political
                  standard, which would take <lb/> the measure of a political trickster as well as
                  that of a statesman. There is nothing,r in the <lb/> conduct of the hon. member
                  for New Westminster either here or at Yale to entitle him to the <lb/> name of
                  statesman. I say, Sir, that I am as free as I was at Yale to vote for that clause,
                  and <lb/> if it can be got into the terms I will vote for it. I brought the
                  question up at Yale because I <lb/> knew that there was a party in Victoria
                  favourable to free port, and I wished to see the question <lb/> fought out after
                  Confederation, not before. The Hon. gentleman was defeated; he could not get <lb/>
                  the Yale Convention to endorse the retaining of the Assay Office at New
                  Westminster, and he <lb/> took his defeat very much to heart. [Hon. Mr.
                  Robson—Untrue, untrue.] The Hon. Member <lb/> for Yale came to me and said :—" You
                  concede this point as to the Assay Office and I will yield <lb/> the free port. We
                  don't want Mr. Robson to leave." That's how it came to be in the Yale resolu<lb
                     break="no"/>tions. Since to this Colony I came, I have never swerved from
                  protection. In the first article I <lb/> wrote for a newspaper in this Colony the
                  word "protection" occurs. I want to see the Canadian <lb/> revenue laws extended
                  here; I want to see power in the Local Government to protect the indus<lb
                     break="no"/>trial interests of the Colony. I would like to know who has changed
                  the Hon. gentleman's <lb/> opinions. I spent my time and money in getting
                  protection. I challenged a gentleman on the <lb/> floor of this House to retire,
                  and I did retire; I hoisted the flag of protection and won. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —I wish to state that what the Hon.
                  gentleman said was true, except <lb/> that he mistook the Hon. Mr. Robson for Hon.
                  Mr. Holbrook. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR.HELMCKEN</persName> —We are here to remedy evils likely to occur
                  from Confederation, <lb/> evils which are admitted by every member of this
                  Council. That there is an evil even the <lb/> Hon. Member for New Westminster has
                  admitted. [Hon. Mr. Robson—No.] The Hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man makes his net
                  so wide that he slips through; but he said in effect that the difficulty was <lb/>
                  irremediable, and to get out of it he proposes not general free trade, but free
                  trade in certain <lb/> special articles. If the Canadian Government can agree to
                  one they can to the other. I believe <lb/> that if we show the Canadian Government
                  that the Canadian tariff would be an evil they will <lb/> find means to remove the
                  evil. l believe a tariff fair and suitable to this Colony will be made. <lb/> I
                  believe we have gone so far right; we have resolved that our agriculture shall be
                  protected. <lb/> Now comes the question as to commerce. We want articles of
                  commerce as cheap as possible; <lb/> our trade is chiefly retail, nevertheless it
                  is important, and should be fostered. I think that <lb/> everything we can do to
                  increase the population of this country is of importance. I therefore <lb/>
                  propose this resolution :— <lb/>
               </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" That in the opinion of this Council it is advisable that after Union foreign manufactured 
     <lb/>
     "articles in which trade can be carried on with neighbouring countries shall be admitted into 
     <lb/>
     "this Colony at a low nominal rate of duty, and generally the tariff should be made to suit 
     <lb/>
     "the commercial condition of the Colony." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     I think free trade in Vancouver Island would be beneficial with protection to agricultur<lb break="no"/>alists, but I do not think it desirable, except in a limited way. Does any one imagine that if 
     <lb/>
     free port was restored to Victoria her prosperity would return? In more early days, when she 
     <lb/>
     enjoyed free port, there were not the obstructions to free trade with the neighbouring country 
     <lb/>
     that there are at present. Now there are Custom House oflicers to prevent smuggling, and a 
     <lb/>
     great deal of illicit trade is checked. With regard to free trade: In former days we were far 
     <lb/>


            <pb n="146" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_146.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">146</fw> <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> 
    

     more advanced than the people on the Sound ; to-day, on the Sound, trade has so far increased 
     <lb/>
     as to be almost equally as good, and I am told you can buy goods almost as cheaply as in 
     <lb/>
     Victoria, so I do not believe free port would restore our pristine prosperity. Under free trade 
     <lb/>
     it is pposed that large stocks of goods will come by Panama. or by long sea route. But look 
     <lb/>
     at the altered condition of things resulting from the Pacific Railway, and the railway to 
     <lb/>
     Columbia River, and probably on to Puget Sound. Do you imagine anyone will send large 
     <lb/>
     stocks of goods to lie here? and will not people telegraph for whatever they may require, and 
     <lb/>
     bring them across the continent by railway? I say that the same prosperity and trade that 
     <lb/>
     we enjoyed before would not come back. We are told that when the railway is made Asiatic 
     <lb/>
     trade will come across, but I doubt the railway being made in our time, and, if it is, ships 
     <lb/>
     will go wherever the railway terminus is and that will not be here. It would be an advan<lb break="no"/>tage to have some articles free, silks, tric tracs, &amp;c. Make Victoria the Paris of the Coast 
     <lb/>
     and we may do something. And this brings me to the observation of my Hon. friend on my 
     <lb/>
     right, that more frequent steam communication with the Sound would be productive of much 
     <lb/>
     good to trade. What I want to say is that the persons going to negotiate these terms ought 
     <lb/>
     to be able to state that this Colony requires restrictions in the tariff. I do not intend to be 
     <lb/>
     factious, but I do intend to show to the Canadian Government what we consider best for this 
     <lb/>
     country, and that without certain terms we believe Confederation will be bad. What use is it 
     <lb/>
     to attempt to deceive Canada? She knows what is being done, and if not, there are those here 
     <lb/>
     who would tell her. It is our duty to show the Canadian Government that there are things 
     <lb/>
     we desire. Of what use is the country to Canada unless it is populated? She wants people, 
     <lb/>
     not terms. We must show what will be the advantages of Confederation. If the tariff of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion must come here it will be unsuitable to us—an admitted evil. If this cannot be 
     <lb/>
     remedied, Confederation is likely to be put off for years. I merely mean to elicit the feeling of 
     <lb/>
     this House on the subject of whether we can take off certain duties. If commerce can be 
     <lb/>
     protected in the way we desire, as we shall see when the persons who go to arrange the terms 
     <lb/>
     come back, then it will be no use to oppose Confederation. If the evil is still to exist, then 
     <lb/>
     there will be opposition. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName> —I shall vote against the Resolution. With
                  regard to free port, I <lb/> do not say 1 am opposed to it or in favour of it ;
                  but I do say that the Canadians will say if <lb/> we pass this Resolution, "What
                  kind of people are these that passed a Resolution yesterday <lb/> in favour of
                  protection, and to-day desire free port?" The Hon. Member for Victoria City <lb/>
                  proved forcibly, I will not say conclusively, that free port would not be
                  beneficial. His reason<lb break="no"/>ing is consistent ; and it is eminently
                  characteristic of the honourable gentleman. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I desire to explain the terms of my
                  Resolution—the latter part. <lb/> If the Canadian tariff rules our farmers are
                  ruined. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName> —Vancouver Island can never be an
                  agricultural country. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —Bring the Canadian tariff here and you
                  take away protection <lb/> and tax the farmers for all they consume. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HAML1">Hon. COMMISSIONER OF CUSTOMS</persName> —A free port is an
                  impossibility. unless the English <lb/> Parliament repeal the Act of Union. This
                  Act enacts that British Columbia tariff laws shall <lb/> prevail. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I believe a free port could be carried on
                  if, you could wall in <lb/> an acre or two of this city. and not do any injury to
                  manufacturing interests, or any other <lb/> interests. I mean to say that upon
                  that acre people might expose their goods—make it one <lb/> large bonded
                  warehouse. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName> —We have heard of the pernicious effects in
                  prospective of the Canadian <lb/> tariff. I maintain that it will protect the
                  principal, that is the pastoral, interests better than <lb/> what is proposed by
                  some honourable members. The admission of cereals free will be counter<lb
                     break="no"/>balanced by the additional protection afforded to the farmers'
                  horses and cattle, and the <lb/> cheaper rate for goods. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Hon. ATTORNEY—GENERAL</persName> —I wished to gather the opinion of the
                  House before express<lb break="no"/>ing my opinion on this question. I regret
                  much, and am sure that this House will join me <lb/> in a feeling of regret. that
                  my honourable colleague, the Chief Commissioner of Lands and <lb/> Works, is,
                  unfortunately, absent from his place on account of indisposition, for I am aware
                  that <lb/> this is a subject to which he has given much consideration, and I would
                  have been glad that <lb/> the House should have had the benefit of his opinion on
                  this very serious question, for it is <lb/>
                  <pb n="147" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_147.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">147</fw> impossible to approach the subject without feeling its
                  vital importance; and I think it would <lb/> tax our united will and energy to
                  their utmost limits, if we had the power to frame a tariff <lb/> which would be
                  suitable; therefore, I see, wisely, in all the Resolutions a wide generality.
                  <lb/> Upon this question of tariff we must especially avoid attempting to commit
                  the Dominion <lb/> Government to any fixed principle. The tariff cannot be part of
                  the terms, but it is. undoubt <lb/> edly. a matter of consideration to be urged on
                  the Canadian Government. Though we have <lb/> assented to the Organic Act. we have
                  not shut ourselves out from going to the Dominion <lb/> Parliament to ask for
                  remedies which they can give to us, and to us; them to find a remedy <lb/> which
                  will make Confederation acceptable 'to this Colony. Therefore. I think, with the
                     Honour<lb break="no"/>able Chief Commissioner, that one general Resolution upon
                  this subject, after dealing with. <lb/> the three separate Resolutions or abstract
                  principles, may, with advantage, be passed by this <lb/> House. I think also, with
                  that honourable gentleman, Mr. Chairman, that Canadian statesmen <lb/> who will
                  have to deal with this matter. will do so with wisdom. They, in considering the
                  <lb/> terms when other Provinces have entered the Confederation, must have
                  experienced some of <lb/> these difficulties which now come to us for the first
                  time. No doubt many honourable members <lb/> of this House have given great
                  consideration to this question. yet I think that Canadian <lb/> experience will
                  help us. Much has been said on free port—much for and against. My own <lb/>
                  tendencies, since first I had a seat on this floor, in another Assembly, have been
                  in favour of <lb/> free port. I voted for it then, but I feel that I am obliged to
                  vote against it now. The <lb/> Imperial Government will not sanction anything
                  which is in effect a differential duty in the <lb/> same tariff; but this is
                  distinct from the question of a separate tariff for British Columbia. <lb/> Other
                  considerations will naturally strike Canada, and I think if free port was made a
                     <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua <lb/> non</hi> she would refuse
                  Confederation altogether. as she would not like to run the risk of entering <lb/>
                  into difficulties and disputes of a fiscal character with her great and powerful
                  neighbour. which <lb/> might possibly arise out of smuggling. Another difficulty
                  in dealing with this matter that we <lb/> have to encounter is, that we have
                  intorniation that a reconstruction of the Canadian tariff is <lb/> at present
                  going on, and there is some chance of a reciprocity treaty being arranged,
                  therefore <lb/> we cannot put forward any fixed principles. The main objections of
                  the Dominion to a separate <lb/> tariff, it strikes me, will be found to be:
                  first, that they are afraid of infringing principle: and, <lb/> second, the
                  formation of a precedent for a special tariff, which might cause Newfoundland,
                  <lb/> New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, and other Provinces to ask for special tariffs
                  to suit their par<lb break="no"/>ticular circumstances, and to avoid the
                  inconvenience of possible hostile tariffs. There are <lb/> certainly many
                  plausible reasons to be found in favour of a special tariff for British Columbia.
                  <lb/> Such as the difficulty of communication. The want of either road or railway,
                  and the security <lb/> against smuggling into Canada. But the probability is, that
                  protection to commerce would be <lb/> secured by the reconstruction of the
                  Canadian tariff, and I regard the framing of a tariff now <lb/> which would apply
                  satisfactorily to our altered circumstances, under such a thorough change as <lb/>
                  Confederation would bring, a matter of impossibility. Formerly, when there was a
                  free <lb/> port at Victoria, it was always in danger, and the Hon. Senior Member
                  for Victoria City, <lb/> then the Speaker of the Vancouver Island House of
                  Assembly, was always afraid of. every <lb/> little impost on stock or produce lest
                  it should infringe upon the principle of free trade. and at <lb/> last it was so
                  loaded with dues and charges that before the Union the principle of free port
                  <lb/> was destroyed. But I see no reason why, when we are going into a
                  partnership, we should <lb/> not arrange the best terms we can; and I think that
                  the differences could be altered in <lb/> favour of this Colony. and in favour of
                  Confederation generally. We have no power ourselves; <lb/> that is the reason this
                  question is not brought up in the terms. We must see what eltect <lb/> Union will
                  have on this Colony first; we must see how the thing works before we decide <lb/>
                  finally. At the same time. we must take care that we protect such important
                  interests as <lb/> agriculture and commerce from haste or injurious delay. I will,
                  therefore, as soon as the <lb/> terms are settled. propose a resolution which will
                  meet this difficulty and give  time to see <lb/> what change, if any, the country
                  may require. In sending our resolutions to the Canadian <lb/> Government, we must
                  not suppose that we have exhausted the subject. Many points must <lb/> arise when
                  the Canadian Commissioners come here, or ours go there—if the matter take that
                  <lb/> turn; but we should be careful not to overload the terms, lest we should
                  endanger the cause <lb/> of Confederation altogether. We must have some faith in
                  the Dominion Government—in <lb/> Canada and Canadian stalteslnen. We must not
                  forget that their own interests would be ours. <lb/> I say nothing with regard to
                  the latter part of the resolution of the Hon. Member for Victoria <lb/>
                  <pb n="148" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_148.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">148</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> City, except that it does not accord
                  with his usual startesmanlike views. I shall offer no <lb/> opposition to the
                  latter part of the resolution of the Hon. Member, but I cannot support the <lb/>
                  whole. If anyone will move an amendment to leave out the latter part, I will
                  support it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p> 
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—We have three propositions now before the
                  House—my own, and <lb/> those of the Hon. Members for Victoria and New
                  Westminster. The former divides the subject. <lb/> I think they would both act
                  judiciously if they withdrew the question of free port. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName> moved an amendment to strike out the latter
                  part of the resolution <lb/> of the Hon. Member for Victoria. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName> suggested that the amendment should be
                  deferred. These amendments <lb/> so qualify the general principles that I must
                  decline voting for any one of them. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName> —Sir, I do not intend to express my opinion on
                  free trade or protection, <lb/> but I intend to vote; and I think my Hon. friend
                  (Mr. Ring) might consider that he is not. <lb/> pledged to any particular course
                  by his vote. I give my vote in order that the question may <lb/>he brought before
                  the Canadian Government, and ultimately before the people of this Colony. <lb/>
               </p>

    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName> —I have great respect for the opinion of the
                  Hon. and learned gentleman; <lb/> but the resolution of the Hon. Member for New
                  Westminster pledges us to the Organic Act, <lb/> whicn I decline to endorse. We
                  are entitled to our own free port and to the regulation of <lb/> our own tariff.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName> — I hope the Hon. Member will remain while I
                  set him right. My <lb/> resolution only asks that a Representative Council here,
                  after due deliberation, shall have <lb/> power to decide upon this question. I
                  consider that the name of free port is attractive; this, <lb/> under the
                  resolution of the Hon. Member for Victoria District, we should lose, We must not
                  <lb/> regard the Canadian tariff entirely unprotective. It is wrong. it is untrue,
                  to state that the <lb/> Canadian tariff is such a great evil, and I maintain that
                  it would not he an evil, but an actual <lb/> good; but that is no reason we should
                  not seek to make it a greater good. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The Clerk read the resolution of Hon. DeCosmos, the amendment of Hon. Robson, the 
     <lb/>
     amendment of Hon. Dr. Helmcken, and the amendment of Hon. Dr. Carrall. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     By the leave of the Committee. the amendment of the Hon. Mr. Robson was withdrawn, 
     <lb/>
     in order that it might be brought up as a substantive motion. . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On a division, the motion of Hon. Dr. Carrall was carried, and the original resolution of 
     <lb/>
     Mr. DeCosmos was lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Hon. Mr. Robson then moved his resolution, to which the Hon. Mr. Humphrey's moved 
     <lb/>
     an amendment, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Amendment and resolution were lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName> —Sir, I rise to more this resolution on Excise
                  :- <lb/>
               </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"That in the opinion of this Council. the duties of excise levied upon maltstel's and 
     <lb/>
     "brewers under the Excise Laws of Canada would be detrimental if made applicable to British 
     <lb/>
     "Columbia. and that His Excellency he requested to take such steps as he may deem advisable 
     <lb/>
     " [or the interest of this Colony, and further to take care that no export duties shall be charged 
     <lb/>
     " on spars exported from British Columbia." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     And I would remark, in doing so, that excise as levied under the Canadian system, is 
     <lb/>
     very hoary indeed; there is duty. licence, and excise. The result would he to the brewing 
     <lb/>
     interests. in all probability, total extinction; for on an increasing trade the duty would he so 
     <lb/>
     high as to check trade in this direction. The other part of the resolution is in respect to logs, 
     <lb/>
     the duty on which is $1 per thousand on saw-legs; but whether a spur or a mast, it is regarded 
     <lb/>
     still as a log. Thus the Canadian tariff would seriously interfere with our industry, and inter<lb break="no"/>fere with getting out masks and spars. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRAL</persName> —I think the Hon. and learned Member for
                  Victoria City is under <lb/> a misapprehension when he includes spurs with logs.
                  If "logs" refers simply to saw-logs, I <lb/> cannot see that the spar husin ss
                  would he affected. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> —I must confess, Sir, that I do not see
                  the object of this <lb/> clause, I don't think there is any need for alarm. I have
                  lived for some years in Canada, <lb/> and when I think of the Canadian statesmen.
                  who will look at British Columbia without <lb/> regard to party politics such men.
                  for instance, Sir J, A, Macdonald, Sir Francis Hincks, <lb/> Sir A. T. Galt, Mr,
                  George Brown. and the various statesmen accustomed to deal with these <lb/>
                  things—I feel confident that we are safe in their hands; therefore, I hope that
                  the Hon, and <lb/>learned Member will not imagine that, in voting.r against this
                  motion, we are voting against <lb/>the interests he so properly wishes to protect.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <pb n="149" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_149.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">149</fw>
            

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName> —The Hon. Attorney-General seems to think that
                  these honourable men <lb/> may live forever. He forgets that in the progress of
                  time other men will take the lead in <lb/> public affairs. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —lt is a most important question. The
                  Canadian Government <lb/> ought to know what we think of it. The brewing interest
                  would disappear, and it is large <lb/> in proportion to our population, and to
                  ruin it would be doing an injury. I hope the Hon. <lb/> Attorney-General will
                  withdraw his opposition and let this recommendation go with the others <lb/> to
                  the Governor, that he may forward it with them to the Canadian Government. At the
                  <lb/> time the Organic Act was made it related to contiguous Provinces. The Hon.
                  Attorney-General <lb/> says they may not put it in force here for ten, twenty, or
                  thirty years. Granted, but it may <lb/> also he put in force immediately. I say,
                  then, let the Canadian Government he made aware <lb/> that the application of the
                  excise laws to this Colony will be detrimental to its interests. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName> —I think the Hon, Member loses sight of one
                  fact He is terribly <lb/> afraid of the Canadian tariff, but he loses sight of the
                  fact that barley comes in duty free. <lb/> I believe the whole system will be
                  carefully revised, and it is absurd to hamper the terms of <lb/> the resolution
                  for such a petty question. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName> —1n reply, I think our duty in coming here is
                  to protect the interests <lb/> of the Colony. We ask the Dominion Government to
                  consider these things. We do not insist <lb/> on terms being inserted. I do not
                  ask for this only; I desire to draw the attention of the <lb/> Canadian Government
                  to these interests that they may not be overlooked. As to these interests <lb/>
                  being petty and small, that is our misfortune; but let us not lose sight of them
                  for that reason. <lb/> As for Americans coming here to cut down our legs, I say
                  let them come. If I can alter my <lb/> resolution to suit the Attorney-General, I
                  will do it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —If I thought the interests of the
                  Colony would suffer, I <lb/> would consent to bring the subject before the
                  Canadian Government, but I think we have nothing <lb/> to fear. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName> —If you ruin the threwing interest, you
                  inflict much harm in other <lb/> ways Brewers consume one million pounds of harloy
                  yearly. This is 700 acres of land which <lb/> must be cultivated. To ruin this
                  will throw out of employment at large number of people and <lb/> close up our
                  breweries. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —I see no objection to sending this up, but
                  not to make it a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine <lb/> qua non</hi>. I believe
                  the Canadian Government will protect all these interests. Brewing is <lb/> not of
                  sufficient magnitude to kill Confederation. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I must oppose it logs are left in. l think
                  it may be our duty to <lb/> protect spars and logs. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName> —Then I will strike out logs and leave spars.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The Clerk then read Hon. Mr, Drake's motion, as altered. Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> — There are other things to he considered.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —I think it is now competent for me to
                  more the resolution <lb/> proposed by the Hon. Chief Commissioner. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —It is intended that this shall swamp all the
                  others? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> —No; it relates only to tariff :- <lb/>
               </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That this Council respectfully represent to I is Excellency the Governor that, 
     <lb/>
     "in negotiating the terms of union of British Columbia with Canada, it is of the first import<lb break="no"/>"ance to point out to the Government of the Dominion that the circumstances of this Colony 
     <lb/>
     " are in many respects so different from those of the Eastern Provinces that the application of 
     <lb/>
     " the present Canadian Tariff to this Colony, while reducing the aggregate burden of taxation, 
     <lb/>
     "would injuriousiy affect the agricultural and commercial interests of this community, and 
     <lb/>
     " that it he therefore urgently impressed upon that Government that it is absolutely necessary 
     <lb/>
     "to our wellbeing under Confederation that special rates of Customs duties and special 
     <lb/>
     "Customs regulations be arranged for this Colony in such name' as may be found practically 
     <lb/>
     " most advisable, so as to secure, while our requirements in this respect remain as at present, 
     <lb/>
     " an equal measure of protection to our agricultural products and of facility to commerce, as 
     <lb/>
     "are provided under the existing British Columbia Tariff." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     The resolution was carried unanimously.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The original motion of the Hon. Mr. DeCosmos, on the Orders of the Day, was read, and 
     <lb/>
    by leave withdrawn. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="150" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-24_Page_150.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">150</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            

<p>
     Hon. Mr. Drake's motion was also withdrawn. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Holbrook's motion was put and lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Robson's motion was put and lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS</persName> moved :- <lb/>
               </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"That in the consideration of the subsidies to be given by Canada to this Colony, due 
     <lb/>
     "weight shall be given to the advisability of abolishing the present road tolls on the Yale-<lb break="yes"/>" Cariboo road, and also to make provision for funds to keep the same in repair." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     I put this in consequence of the suggestions thrown out by the Hon. Chief Commissioner. 
     <lb/>
     I think these road tolls have done more towards making bankrupts than any over-trading. 
     <lb/>
     They are main trunk roads, and I think they ought to be kept up by the Dominion Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —I am not aware that that is the result
                  of a suggestion <lb/> of the Hon. Chief Commissioner, I am aware of his views, and
                  I believe he has doubts as to <lb/> whether roads can he maintained by a
                  Government so far removed as Canada. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —I would suggest that this be laid over till
                  the Hon. Chief Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner be here <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —The Hon. Chief Commissioner would not
                  object to any <lb/> conclusion of the House on this matter, But I caution Hon.
                  Members not, by the addition of <lb/> these suggestions, so to overload the
                  resolutions as to break down the whole of them <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —I move that the Committee rise and report
                  progress, in order that <lb/> the matter may he laid over until the Hon. Chief
                  Commissioner is in his place. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Committee rose and reported progress. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<!-- GL, 2017-03-22, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


            <!--<p>
     FRIDAY, MARCH 25TH, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On Mr. Humphreys' motion on roads being read, the Hon. Attorney-General said :<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <p>I regret to say that my honourable colleague, the Chief Commissioner of Lands and Works, 
     <lb/>
     is still too much indisposed to attend to his place in this House. I would, therefore, suggest 
     <lb/>
     that the Honourable Member should postpone his notice until he is present. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR, HUMPHREYS—I have no objection to defer it, on the understanding that it 
     <lb/>
     comes up on Monday.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL—On Monday, or this day, if: the Committee get through with 
     <lb/>
     their other motions on Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR RING—l desire to introduce a motion with regard to free port, but I do not 
     <lb/>
     intend to inflict upon the House a speech. I move that His Excellency he respectfully requested 
     <lb/>
     to place in the terms a clause to restore to Victoria the system of free port antecedent to 
     <lb/>
     Confederation. The Honourable Member for New Westminster was indignant with me yester<lb break="no"/>day for not supporting his resolution. I only say that his proposition was hypercritieal. I 
     <lb/>
     ask that we may have free port restored before Confederation. We have now the right to 
     <lb/>
     legislate for ourselves on this point. Hereafter we shall he at the mercy of the, Canadian 
     <lb/>
     Parliament at Ottawa. i would make free port one of the conditions of Confederation; but 
     <lb/>
     first restore free port. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the Clerk reading the first words of the resolution,<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. DR. CARRALL—I rise to a point of order. I say that this question has been already 
     <lb/>
     decided.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     CHAIRMAN—I think 'the Hon Member for Nanaimo is not out of order on that point. 
     <lb/>
     The question of free port yesterdav related to free port after Confederation. The resolution 
     <lb/>
     of the Hon, Member for Nanaiino is in reference to free port antecedent to Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. COSMOS—The Hon, Member is surely out of order, this Committee having 
     <lb/>
     met to consider Confederate resolutions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     CHAIRMAN— I rule that the Hon. Mr. Ring is in order, as his resolution refers to the 
     <lb/>
     terms of Confederation now before this Committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the Hon. Mr. Ring's motion being but to vote, it was lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>