<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgBCLC_1870-03-23" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgBCLC">British Columbia Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1870-03-23">23 March 1870</date>, Province of BC, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgBCLC">
          

         <editor>W.S. Sebright Green</editor>
          
         
               <title>Legislative Council, Debate on the Subject of Confederation with Canada</title>.
                    

          <date when="1912"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Victoria, B.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>William H. Cullin</publisher>.
                   
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="132" to="142"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_132.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_133.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_134.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_135.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_136.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_137.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_138.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_139.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_140.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_141.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_142.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-22">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-22">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-25">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_132">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_132.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_133">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_133.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_134">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_134.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_135">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_135.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_136">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_136.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_137">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_137.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_138">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_138.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_139">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_139.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_140">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_140.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_141">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_141.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_142">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_142.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="132" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_132.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">132</fw> <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
<div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">

     WEDNESDAY, 23RD MARCH, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </head>


            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName> rose to resume the debate on Tariff, and said
                  :—Mr. Chairman, in speak<lb break="no"/>ing to the motions now before the House,
                  it will hardly be necessary for me to say that I think <lb/> this question of
                  Tariff the most important of all that have been introduced during this debate.
                  <lb/> My object is, as I have said, to reduce to the utmost, in the event of
                  Confederation with Canada, <lb/> the chance of difference with the Dominion ; my
                  objection to Confederation being that, however <lb/> much it may apparently and at
                  first tend to confer upon the Colony material benefits, yet there <lb/> is every
                  fear of consequent reaction and disaffection. In dealing with the matter it will
                  be <lb/> necessary to see whether the subject of Tariff now before us will have
                  the effect of raising a <lb/> direct question and difference between this Colony
                  and Canada. Tariff is not simply a mode of <lb/> collecting taxes; it is a system
                  with a double object. The object of obtaining revenue, and in <lb/> the obtainingr
                  of that revenue the further object of promoting domestic and home industries <lb/>
                  by a just discrimination between the subject-matter on which taxation is levied.
                  The question <lb/> of Tariff directly tends to promote or depress domestic
                  productions and domestic trade; conse<lb break="no"/>quently, the chances of
                  difference and reaction depend on whether our interests are identical <lb/> with
                  those of Canada, or whether there is a conflict. The intended future Dominion of
                  Canada <lb/> is obviously divided, so far as this question is concerned, into two
                  parts, that which is to the <lb/> east and that which is to the west of the Rocky
                  Mountains—the Atlantic   and Pacific portions of <lb/> that Dominion; and to these
                  several divisions there appertain distinct and several industrial <lb/> interests,
                  agricultural, manufacturing, and commercial. Let us run through in our own minds
                  our <lb/> own, the Pacific, interests, so to say,—the interests, in fact, of this
                  present Colony. First. we <lb/> have the agricultural interests. This is a
                  material interest, as 1' trust it always will be con<lb break="no"/>sidered in
                  every Colony; it is an industry which a Government cannot well avoid materially to
                  <lb/> assist. I don't say "protect," but "assist," and this whether agricultural
                  produce be a staple <lb/> of the Colony or not. I may here remark that I use the
                  word "staple" in what I understand <lb/> to be the received acceptation of the
                  word—produce, exportable produce, raised in a Colony with <lb/> advantage and at a
                  remunerative rate to the producer, and capable of being exchanged with <lb/>
                  advantage for the produce of other countries in the markets of the world. Our next
                  material <lb/> interests are our own staples, properly so-called as above
                  defined—such, for instance, as the <lb/> wool of Australia, gold anywhere, or
                  fisheries, as in Newfoundland. Our particular staples are <lb/> our fisheries, our
                  forests, and our minerals, to say nothing of certain aptitudes for shipbuilding
                  <lb/> and the repairing of ships. Next, we must take trade and commerce; our local
                  and geographical <lb/> position being such as to give us some advantage in the
                  distribution of goods, and, as such, is to <lb/> be regarded as an element of
                  wealth and one of our material interests. Let us now turn to <lb/> Canada. Canada
                  has manufactures, but not by way of staples, because she cannot undersell <lb/>
                  the Old World in manufactured goods; but with a population of, I suppose, over
                  three millions <lb/> she can produce sufficient manufactures of certain
                  descriptions for her own use. Then her <lb/> staples are agriculture, produce,
                  lumber, and a certain amount of minerals, and perhaps horns <lb/> and tallow.
                  Agricultural produce is a staple in Canada; she exports it; therefore it requires
                  no <lb/> protection; it would be no good to inpose a tariff upon it. In
                  manufactures there is such a <lb/> tariff as will slightly protect manufactures,
                  as with us we give the same turn of the market <lb/> to the farmer by a slight
                  tariff on agricultural produce. Following the common law of self- <lb break="yes"/> interest, British Columbia is bound to protect her own interests, and Canada
                  the same. Let us <lb/> see whether or not there is a manifest tendency to
                  protection in the Dominion Legislature. It <lb/> has been stated in this debate
                  that Canada is adverse to protection, that she wants to follow <lb/> England and
                  the Old World in the direction of free trade. I say that those who make the
                     asser<lb break="no"/>tion must prove it. [" Hear, hear," from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DeCosmos</persName>."] <supplied><persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName></supplied> I
                  say that my sources of information <lb/> tend to show that it is untrue that
                  Canada favours free trade; she desires to protect her own <lb/> manufactures.
                  Right or wrong as a political theory, new countries will be found, as soon <lb/>
                  as manufactures are possible, desirous to protect their own native industries,
                  whereas it suits <lb/> old countries to have free trade. In England manufactured
                  goods are in reality her staples. <lb/> England can compete with the world in most
                  classes of manufacturing goods, from her manifest <lb/> advantages in having coal
                  and iron in close proximity, moderately cheap labour, and established <lb/>
                  industries, to say nothing of the commercial energy of her people. Some of the
                  writers say that <lb/>America and many of the Colonies of Great Britain suffer
                  from protection. I say that, suffer <lb/>
                  <pb n="133" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_133.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">133</fw> or not suffer, they insist upon it. I say nothing now of
                  my convictions. I think, however, that <lb/> the theory of free trade goes too
                  far. " Free trade " is quoted as if it were a golden rule. I <lb/> believe that
                  free trade is an exceedingly elastic idea; there is no orthodoxy in it. It is not
                  a <lb/> law of physics, like the law of gravitation, or some abstruse and
                  elaborate theory like Sturn's <lb/> problem, or the stability of the eccentricity
                  of the planetary orbits, to which there is no exception. <lb/> It is elastic, and
                  suits one country and not another ; it suits old countries and not new ; it suits
                  <lb/> England for the reasons I have stated. Her manufactures are her staples. She
                  can undersell <lb/> the world. People may say that free trade is applicable
                  equally to other places and to all <lb/> classes of industries. As to this, I have
                  my own opinions. But so far as this discussion is con<lb break="no"/>cerned, I
                  deal with the world as I find it. New countries desire protection. Why? No matter
                  <lb/> why—they do desire it. Dealing with protection in a moderate way, I think it
                  may be <lb/> reasonably conceded that a moderate protection, in the way of customs
                  duties at <lb/> least, may he applied to staple productions and agriculture. But
                  whether the opinion <lb/> be sound or not, colonial experience shows us that this
                  is the line of argument <lb/> pursued and acted on. Taking it for granted, as
                  admitted by some political writers <lb/> of eminence, that we may reasonably
                  protect staples until they can support themselves, <lb/> let us see what
                  legitimate protection may be afforded to existing interests in this Colony. <lb/>
                  Agriculture may be protected, or rather fostered, in numbers of ways—by facilities
                  for the <lb/> acquisition of land, by roads, by immigration of farm hands, by the
                  admission of implements <lb/> free, and by a moderate tariff 'on produce.
                  Agriculture, it must be remembered, is not only the <lb/> cultivation of the land
                  ; it is bound up with local interests, and carries with it a local population
                  <lb/> attached to the soil. If you want population localized you must encourage
                  agricultural interests. <lb/> Besides this, it must not be lost sight of that it
                  is a practical remedy against poverty. If a man <lb/> has certain faculties for
                  acquiring or being employed as a labourer on land, he need never go to <lb/> the
                  poor—house ; it humanizes men. It is the duty of every politician to protect
                  agricultural <lb/> interests in a new country, to the best of his power. Now, with
                  regard to staples: I say they <lb/> may reasonably be protected and fostered in
                  their infancy, because they are the real wealth of <lb/> the nation. It is said
                  that at first the wool interest of Australia was carried on at a loss; and <lb/>
                  for a country like this, that can produce without limit, fish, lumber, and coals,
                  to say nothing of <lb/> gold, we must give all the facilities in our power to
                  induce industry in these walks of life. Take <lb/> the gold miner: We might give
                  him his gold license cheap, and make the acquisition of claims <lb/> easy; provide
                  him with roads and trails; and in this way we might "protect" the miner and <lb/>
                  encourage mining interests. Fisheries—how are they to be protected? By the
                  promotion of <lb/> information as to markets for fish; by pushing those markets;
                  by local knowledge of the haunts <lb/> of fish; by cheap implements, and by cheap
                  salt. To promote the lumber interest, we might <lb/> give cheap machiney, so far
                  as we can, by admitting it free, and let persons acquire land easily. <lb/>
                  Shipwrights might also be legitimately protected and encouraged by making
                  implements and <lb/> materials cheap, and by giving encouragement to docks. Let us
                  do everything to promote the <lb/> interests of ships. Where there are such
                  natural inlets as ours, with coal at hand, and facilities <lb/> for the
                  importation of iron and steel for building ships, we could build cheaper than
                  anywhere <lb/> on this coast; not, of course, so cheaply as on the Clyde, but
                  still we might attract some ship<lb break="no"/>builders. Now as to trade—export
                  trade. This is surely an item, though possibly a small item, <lb/> in our wealth;
                  yet still, if we export only to Puget Sound, we might encourage such commerce.
                  <lb/> It is an industry and a source of wealth; it causes foreign ships to come,
                  and causes an expendi<lb break="no"/>ture of money in our ports; it adds to the
                  number of merchants, drays, and labourers, and <lb/> increases general business; a
                  vitality is given by it which makes it an element of wealth; it <lb/> seems to
                  have been beneficial here, and certain it is that it is estimated in this Colony
                  as a <lb/> material interest. How is this export trade to be protected? Some say
                  by free port, that <lb/> is to say, no Customs duties; others say: "Reduce
                  taxation to a minimum on goods in which <lb/> there is a tangible export trade."
                  Within these limits of what we may call moderate protection, <lb/> we may
                  reasonably suppose the Colonists of British Columbia to be desirous to legislate;
                  and <lb/> suppose we desire to have implements of labour and machinery, and some
                  goods cheap and <lb/> free, and put ten per cent. on imported agricultural
                  produce. This is the reverse of Canadian <lb/> policy. As regards machinery, I
                  believe the Canadian tariff gives fifteen per cent. on manu<lb break="no"/>factured machinery at least. There is nothing to prevent the Canadian tariff
                  from being <lb/> increased. Protection may run rampant in the Dominion. You have
                  no guarantee. I say <lb/> that in these fiscal questions we are at issue as
                  affects some of our most important elements of <lb/>
                  <pb n="134" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_134.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">134</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> national wealth. There would be a
                  conflict, not only between the tariffs of British Columbia <lb/> and Canada, but
                  between the protective policy of each Province. How is this cause of discon<lb break="no"/>tent and conflict of interest to be removed? Why, by a British
                  Columbia tariff for British <lb/> Columbia. This place has no commercial
                  connection with Canada. Canada attords us no <lb/> market. There is no frontier to
                  cause a difficulty with Custom House Officers. Why not have <lb/> different
                  tariffs? In the event of reciprocity with the United States we might be compelled
                  to <lb/> sacrifice the farmer, but possibly he might be in a condition to support
                  himself by produce for <lb/> which we have some special aptitude. Assuredly we
                  shall have discontent, or worse, if the <lb/> tariff is made oppressive, if we
                  have for it to suffer the extinction, or the disadvantage, of our <lb/> own
                  industries. I have said hastily, give us our own tariff and I am almost in favour
                  of Con<lb break="no"/>federation. I think I must take that expression of opinion
                  back. There are so many other <lb/> matters, so many points of differences between
                  us and Canada, that under any circumstances <lb/> there would be a continual
                  struggle with the other Provinces. But, however this may be, if <lb/> you wish not
                  to provoke and keep up a sore question, have a separate tariff. Give to Canada
                  <lb/> and Canadian interests a tariff framed to meet their wants, and give to
                  British Columbia its <lb/> own especial tariff. If the tariff of Canada is to
                  rule, I fear it will never be altered, for the <lb/> feeble voice of our eight
                  members would never be listened to in the Parliament of Ottawa, and <lb/> the
                  Canadian tariff, framed for the support and maintenance of Canadian interests,
                  would <lb/> assuredly prevail. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">The Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> said:—Sir. after the very able
                  abstract review of the <lb/> whole question of tariff, customs, and taxation of
                  the honourable gentleman who has just sat <lb/> down, I will not add anything by
                  way of dissertation. But I must recall the House to the <lb/> practical
                  consideration of the subject. I acknowledge the ability of the honourable and
                  learned <lb/> member, and quite agree with him that this is one of the most
                  important matters connected <lb/> with Confederation. Then why, it might be asked,
                  was it not touched upon in the terms? <lb/> Not because it has not been fully
                  considered, but because the Organic Act puts it virtually <lb/> out of the power
                  of the Colony to prescribe what form of tariff we should have under Confed<lb break="no"/>eration. The scheme, as has been already pointed out by the Hon.
                  Commissioner of Customs, <lb/> is based on the transfer of the control of our
                  Customs to Canada; therefore, it is not within <lb/> our province, under the
                  scheme submitted, to impose on the Dominion, or even to propose any <lb/> special
                  tariff for this Colony; but this is a matter which is left open for the
                  consideration of <lb/> this Colony on its merits, and is left open, as the Hon.
                  Member for Victoria has told you, for <lb/> this Council to make suggestions as to
                  what tariff may be desirable under Confederation. I <lb/> take this opportunity to
                  set right the impression which seems to prevail as to the liberty of <lb/>
                  Government Members upon this question. It is not left open to us to complicate the
                  terms by <lb/> inserting any condition as to make it in fact a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi>; but it is left open for this
                  Council <lb/> to suggest what tariff would be suitable for this Colony. The Hon.
                  Mr. Wood has discussed this <lb/> matter on its abstract merits, as if it was in
                  our power to dictate to Canada what tariff we <lb/> should have; he has laid
                  before this House very ably the pros and cons of tariff and free port. <lb/> It is
                  for us to consider what tariff would best suit us in or out of Confederation; but
                  it is not <lb/> allowed to us to prescribe to the Dominion what form of Customs
                  duties they shall adopt in <lb/> this Colony, or in this Province, as it will be.
                  We have placed the control of the matter out <lb/> of our hands. [No, no,—<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hons.
                  Helmcken</persName> and <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Wood</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:TRUT1">The Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName></supplied> Well, Sir,, I believe we have; I say <lb/> that view is
                  imposed upon us by the terms, and I think it is better that it should be so; and
                  for <lb/> this reason: We, as being acquainted with the wants of the place, are
                  best able to point out <lb/> in what respect we need protection, and where our
                  interests are likely to suffer from the tariff <lb/> of the Eastern Provinces. But
                  I believe, Sir, that there are those in the Dominion whose <lb/> larger
                  experience, and mature views, will render them much better able than us to supply
                  such <lb/> remedy as will be most beneficial. I am perfectly willing to explain my
                  views on the subject <lb/> of tariff and free port in the abstract, and the
                  Government invite the freest discussion on <lb/> the point, both as regards
                  protection to agriculture and manufactures, and free port. But I <lb/> believe it
                  will be better for the Colony to leave the decision and the remedy for the evils
                  to <lb/> those who will have the care of this Province, as well as the Eastern
                  Provinces. I think it <lb/> will be to the interest of statesmen in the Dominion
                  to treat this Colony well. Instead of <lb/> feeling any want of confidence in
                  those statesmen, I feel sure that every possible measure to <lb/> promote the
                  interests of this Colony will be well considered. They are in a better position to
                  <lb/> decide what will be most beneficial to this Colony, even in regard to
                  tariff. I would rather hear <lb/>
                  <pb n="135" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_135.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">135</fw> more opinions expressed before I offer a suggestion. It is
                  my intention to offer a resolution in <lb/> general terms so as to suggest to the
                  Dominion Government that our agricultural interests must <lb/> be protected, and
                  that certain things are required, and to ask the Dominion for such special <lb/>
                  provisions in regard to tariff as we think we require. We are not in a position,
                  after having <lb/> endorsed the scheme of the Government, and after having handed
                  over the sole control of the <lb/> Customs to Canada, to prescribe what tariff we
                  shall have, or to impose conditions as to our <lb/> local tariff. <lb/>
               </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName>—Mr. Chairman, while I consider the question of
                  tariff one of very <lb/>great importance, it does not appear to me that it
                  necessarily forms any part of the terms. It <lb/>is, in my opinion, futile to
                  imagine that we shall obtain power, under Confederation, to frame <lb/>and
                  regulate our own tariff. 'l'he Customs tariff is essentially a Federal measure,
                  and the <lb/>Dominion Government cannot very well permit a Province to make its
                  own tariff. To do so <lb/>would, in my opinion, be to admit a principle which
                  would ultimately break up the whole Con<lb break="no"/>federation. If such a
                  concession were made to British Columbia every other Province in the <lb/>Dominion
                  would forthwith clamour for it. The Dominion tariff is of necessity a Federal
                  matter, <lb/>to be dealt with by the Federal Parliament, and it is unreasonable to
                  expect that such an <lb/>exception will be made in our favour. The Customs tariff
                  is the main source of Federal <lb/>revenue; and if any Province were permitted to
                  tinker with it, the Federal revenue would, <lb/>indeed, be precarious. History
                  does not encourage us to hope for such a power. Taking the <lb/>United States
                  which, in this respect, presents conditions not dissimilar to those of the
                  Dominion, <lb/>we find that the Customs tariff has ever been a Federal question.
                  To no State or Territory <lb/>has it been conceded to deal with its own tariff. If
                  the strongest reasons had not existed for <lb/>this, we should certainly have
                  found exceptions made in favour of Pacific States and Territories. <lb/>Hon.
                  Members will recollect the bitter complaints made in earlier times on this Coast
                  against <lb/>Federal tariffs; yet the people, while complaining, were never
                  foolish enough to claim or expect <lb/>the right to regulate their own tariff.
                  They knew perfectly well that such a power was wholly <lb/>incompatible with
                  Union. It is as well that we should not cling to any such hope as that of
                  <lb/>being permitted to make and regulate our own tariff under Confederation. I
                  quite concur with <lb/>the Hon. the Chief Commissioner in the view that,
                  notwithstanding the difference in existing <lb/>conditions on this side of the
                  continent, and on the Atlantic side of it there are many questions, <lb/>even of
                  tariff, which would be more successfully dealt with at Ottawa, and that our
                     repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives would be listened to, and would have their due
                  weight upon such questions. Probably <lb/>through their influence the tariff
                  would, in some respects, be made more conformable to our <lb/>circumstances and
                  interests; but the Dominion tariff must be altered and maintained by the
                  <lb/>Federal Parliament, and not by any Provincial authority. We occupy a very
                  exceptional <lb/>position, and shall do so for years, in regard to such questions,
                  and this might justify us in <lb/>asserting that the tariff of Canada, as a whole,
                  is not applicable to British Columbia at present. <lb/>But, Sir, permit me to say
                  that this question, like most others, has two sides to it, and has not <lb/>been
                  approached with that fairness and candour which its great importance demands. We
                  are <lb/>very apt to estimate protection above its real value—to forget the price
                  we pay for it. Even <lb/>our farmers sometimes pay more for protection than it is
                  in reality worth to them. Under <lb/>free trade the products of this part of the
                  Colony commanded a much more ready market, and <lb/>higher prices, than they do
                  now after three years of protection. I am willing to admit that a <lb/>few farmers
                  have thriven, partly, perhaps, on protection, but partly, too, I am apt to think,
                  at <lb/>the expense of other classes and other interests in the Colony. Let us
                  remember that protec<lb break="no"/>tion is not an unmixed good, and that it
                  sometimes costs more than it is really worth. It should <lb/>also be remembered
                  that the importance of protection is somewhat localized in its application.
                  <lb/>Nature has given ample protection to the interior of the Colony; and it is,
                  in reality, only <lb/>on this Island and the Lower Fraser that artificial
                  protection can be desirable. I venture to <lb/>think that there is a great future
                  before Vancouver Island, but I do not believe that it will <lb/>ever owe its
                  greatness to agricultural development. I believe that its commercial, maritime,
                  <lb/>mineral, and manufacturing industries will far outweigh its farming
                  interests, and I do not <lb/>think, therefore, that we would be justified in
                  refusing Confederation upon fair and equitable <lb/>terms, simply because we could
                  not have power to regulate the Customs tariff. I regret that I <lb/>am unable to
                  agree with any one of the recommendations now before the Committee. The
                  <lb/>wisest course, in my opinion, will be to ask the Dominion Govermnent to
                  withhold the applica<lb break="no"/>tion of the Federal tariff of Customs to
                  British Columbia for a fixed period, say, until railway <lb/>  <pb n="136" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_136.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">136</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> communication shall have been
                  established through the Dominion to the Pacific. Until that <lb/> takes place
                  British Columbia must continue to occupy a position so isolated, and so
                  exceptional, <lb/> as to render the general tariff, however well adapted to the
                  Provinces to the eastward of the <lb/> Rocky Mountains, scarcely suited to us. But
                  with the opening of continuous railway com<lb break="no"/>munication these
                  exceptional conditions will, for the most part, disappear. Look, for instance,
                  <lb/> at California. What a complete revolution the railway has wrought in the
                  condition of that <lb/> State. The moment the railway was opened, California was
                  no longer separated from the great <lb/> commercial centres of the Eastern States
                  by thousands of miles of sage-bush and desert. It <lb/> was practically set down
                  alongside of them; or, to use the words of another, time and space <lb/> were
                  annihilated, and California became, for the first time, a fitting subject of a
                  common tariff <lb/> framed at Washington, and enforced throughout the
                  widespreading Union. Similar results <lb/> will be realized in our own case. Upon
                  the opening of the Canadian Pacific Railway British <lb/> Columbia will
                  practically be set down alongside ot the Atlantic Provinces. We get over all <lb/>
                  constitutional difficulties by approaching the subject in this way. I do not say
                  that the <lb/> Dominion Government will assent to the proposition to postpone the
                  application of their tariff <lb/> to this Colony until railway communication shall
                  have been established; but we will approach <lb/> them with a much greater show of
                  reason and success in this way than in the other. I shall, <lb/> therefore,
                  propose an amendment, or a recommendation, asking that the Customs tariff of the
                  <lb/> Dominion be not extended over the Colony of British Columbia until railway
                  communication <lb/> therewith shall have been established. Should this be agreed
                  to on the part of the Canadian <lb/> Government, it would then become our duty,
                  upon entering the Dominion, to remodel our <lb/> tariff with a view to protecting
                  local industries on the one hand, and building up our commercial <lb/> and
                  maritime interests on the other. Canada might, possibly, sacrifice a little
                  revenue in the <lb/> first instance, but it would come back to her a hundred fold
                  in the greatly enlarged prosperity <lb/> certain to follow. In this way, also,
                  would be presented a living recognition of the necessity <lb/> for railway
                  communication, it not an incentive for the speedy consummation of that great <lb/>
                  desideratum. The course which I propose will more fully meet the local necessities
                  of the <lb/> country, while it will be more acceptable to the people, and, I feel
                  assured, more likely to meet <lb/> with the concurrence of the authorities at
                  Ottawa. It possesses the advantage of accomplishing <lb/> more good than can
                  possibly be attained in the way proposed either by the Hon. Member for <lb/>
                  Victoria District, or that proposed by another Hon. Member, and, at the same time,
                  of steering <lb/> clear of constitutional difficulties. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. Mr. DECOSMOS</persName>—Sir, we have heard some very good and
                  eloquent speeches. I intend <lb/> to say a few words, and will begin with first
                  principles. When the Confederation Delegates <lb/> first met, they proposed to
                  adopt a tariff similar to that of the United States; that the Federal <lb/>
                  Government alone should have the right to impose customs duties; that there should
                  be no sub<lb break="no"/>sidies, and that each Province should raise its own
                  revenue by direct taxation; but it was found <lb/> that Local Governments were not
                  favourable to direct taxation. At the Conference at West<lb break="no"/>minster it
                  was at first proposed to give local legislatures power to make laws and impose
                  direct <lb/> taxation, but when the Organic Act was prepared that part was dropped
                  out. I have desired to <lb/> harmonize with the Organic Act. Whatever we may do we
                  should harmonize with the Organic <lb/> Act; by so doing we shall meet with less
                  objection at Ottawa. In looking at this question I may <lb/> come to the
                  conclusion that there is a possibility for the Local Government to raise taxes,
                  but if <lb/> it was referred to the Privy Council they might say it clashed. I
                  will illustrate my meaning: I <lb/> think the Legislature of Ontario voted an
                  additional sum to one of the Judges; the Privy Council <lb/> said it was
                  unconstitutional to do so. So it might be if the Local Government imposed a tax
                  <lb/> upon foreign produce and manufactures. But we must not clash with the
                  Dominion Government. <lb/> In case the Dominion enacted customs laws lower than
                  our own, we would have the privilege <lb/> to put direct taxes on those articles
                  so as to give protection to them. Turning to the Year <lb/> Book, I find that in
                  New Brunswick the export dues on lumber amounts to $70,000. This is <lb/> an
                  export revenue for a source of revenue. If the Government of New Brunswick was
                  able to <lb/> except this item from the operation of the Dominion tariff, why
                  should we not be able to get <lb/> the same sort of difference? The Canadian
                  Revenue will not suffer; every article will have to <lb/> pay the Canadian tariff,
                  and Canada will benefit by any prosperity that we enjoy. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. Dr. CARRALL</persName>—For how long do you propose to suspend the
                  operation of the Dominion <lb/> tariff? <lb/>
               </p>
            <pb n="137" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_137.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">137</fw>
            

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—I have said indefinitely—possibly for ten
                  or twelve years. We may <lb/> have the Railway completed by that time. The Hon.
                  Mr. Wood put the question properly. <lb/> The tariff is a thing that is
                  changeable—it rises and falls. Suppose that Canada has to raise six <lb/> millions
                  for a guarantee for the Railway, they might have to raise the tariff. I think the
                  tariff <lb/> will probably rise for a long time. But this is aside the issue. My
                  object in making this propo<lb break="no"/>sition is to prevent clashing between
                  our Local Government and the Dominion. I include produce <lb/> in my
                  rccommendation,—which means stock, cereals, and vegetables. If a provision of that
                  sort <lb/> were added we would be in a position to get a certain degree of
                  protection, and the largest <lb/> interest, that is the agricultural interest,
                  would be satisfied. But I maintain that beyond this we <lb/> ought to protect
                  certain rude manufactures; and in going into the Dominion we should go with <lb/>
                  as little friction as possible; there must be some friction, but we must keep
                  things as smooth as <lb/> possible. There will be, as I have said before, a
                  revolution in labour and value. Now, we do <lb/> not want too much protection. Let
                  our agricultural interests be satisfied, and if those engaged <lb/> in rude
                  manufactures are protected the people will be satisfied. There are also a class
                  engaged <lb/> in trade who believe in protection; you will find them the
                  agricultural interest, the manufacturing <lb/> interest, and believers in
                  protection, who will form a strong band of opponents to Confederation. <lb/> Take
                  away this subject of friction and you have the whole thing easier. If they are not
                     con<lb break="no"/>sidered there will be opposition before Confederation, and
                  more after. If Hon. Members desire <lb/> to keep up a feeling of loyalty towards
                  Canada after Confederation, they will protect these <lb/> interests. With respect
                  to the Hon. Member for New Westminster, his argument is no stronger <lb/> than his
                  weakest point, which is—[<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. Helmcken</persName> — His resolution]. <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName></supplied> Well, perhaps this is
                  <lb/> the weak point. He admits the whole point. I do not intend to follow the
                  Hon. Member. I <lb/> ask the Hon. Members to consider this question so as to
                  consider industries and manufactures, <lb/> so that the union may be lasting. I
                  hope both sides will unite heartily in shaping our institutions <lb/> with this
                  end in view. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName> —Mr. Chairman, I only desire to drop a few
                  hints. I say that the Organic <lb/> Act is wholly inapplicable to this Colony.
                  Does the Hon. Member for New Westminster mean <lb/> to hand us over under this
                  Organic Act to swell the coffers of the Dominion? I hail any <lb/> approach to
                  free trade; I believe in it; free trade should have as free a course as the wind.
                  <lb/> Now, Sir, with regard to what has been said about protection to commerce;
                  there are natural <lb/> and artificial protections. I am for protecting the farmer
                  by natural protections. Any attempt <lb/> to shut out the surplus produce of
                  another country must fail. The attempt to protect farmers <lb/> by imposing a tax
                  on flour and such articles, is a mistake. Any protection beyond harbour and <lb/>
                  pilot dues is a vicious system. Then, say others: free port is abolished, would
                  you go back to <lb/> direct taxation? I say, how can we ascertain what the people
                  can pay by taxing income and <lb/> property. The revenue would be smaller, but it
                  is not fictitious. We must curtail expenditure, <lb/> and having done so, I would
                  abolish customs altogether as a source of revenue. I agree entirely <lb/> with the
                  proposition of the Hon. Member for New Westminster, that the tariff of the
                  Dominion <lb/> is a Federal matter. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —Mr. Chairman, I rise to support the
                  recommendation of the <lb/> Hon. Member for Victoria District. I have listened
                  carefully to the lofty arguments of the <lb/> Government appointees on this
                  question. It appears to me that the mistakes which the English <lb/> generally
                  make are attributable to their reading and studying great English writers too
                  much, <lb/> instead of considering what is practically applicable to a new
                  country. Old countries are, in <lb/> this respect, very different to new. Free
                  trade may suit England and other old countries, whilst <lb/> it may act very
                  perniciously in a new one. Even in old countries a large proportion of the <lb/>
                  people whom free trade is calculated to benefit are against it. But in new
                  countries protection <lb/> is absolutely necessary. It is said by some Hon.
                  gentlemen that the farming interests in the <lb/> upper country needed no greater
                  protection than nature had given them. I can mention an <lb/> instance to the
                  contrary. Flour was imported last year from California and sold in Cariboo <lb/>
                  at prices with which the upper country farmers could not compete. There ought to
                  be some <lb/> way of protecting the upper country farmers without clashing with
                  the interests of the <lb/> Dominion. I think it but just and right to protect the
                  farmers above all other interests. I <lb/> look upon this question as next to
                  Responsible Government, and that I regard as the most <lb/> important question in
                  the Resolutions which are before the Council; all others sink into <lb/>
                  insignificance besides these two conditions. <lb/>
               </p>

            <pb n="138" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_138.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">138</fw> <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
           

 <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The Hon. COMMISSIONER OF CUSTOMS</persName> —Notwithstanding that the
                  Local Legislature <lb/> after Confederation may not have a right to frame its own
                  tariff, what we hope is, that the <lb/> Canadian Parliament will deem it
                  desirable, for their own interests, that a special tariff should <lb/> be framed
                  for this part of the Dominion. There is no law against this. It would not be a
                  <lb/> differential duty; it cannot be objected to on this ground. Differential
                  duties are where the <lb/> same articles from two different countries are charged
                  differently. If the Canadian tariff was <lb/> applied here taxation would he
                  lessened. We must not lose sight of that fact. It would prob<lb break="no"/>ably
                  be lessened to the extent of $100,000 a year. I have estimated the difference upon
                  one <lb/> quarter's revenue, and I believe the difference to be at least $20,000
                  for the quarter. For all <lb/> that, I think the tariff should be changed. A
                  special tariff is required. I mentioned yesterday <lb/> horses and cattle. I think
                  the $15 on a horse and $10 on cattle would be a great hardship on <lb/> this
                  Colony; it would amount to a prohibition. Last year 1,700 head of cattle were
                  imported <lb/> into this city; are we prepared for the difference that the
                  Canadian tariff would make in this <lb/> item? I think this large duty would be
                  most objectionable. With a tariff made especially to <lb/> protect the farmers,
                  over 40,000 pounds of butter were last year imported. If the Canadian <lb/> tariff
                  of four cents a pound were applied, 1 do not know that much more could come in. I
                  <lb/> think that the farmers must have sold all they had. I think that advocates
                  of protection do <lb/> not apply the principles of protection to farmers of the
                  upper country, but those of Vancouver <lb/> Island. The farmers will feel the
                  weight of the protecting tariff without receiving any of its <lb/> benefits. They
                  will not feel the difference in the duty upon butter. I think that there will be
                  <lb/> a Treaty of Reciprocity between the United States and Canada, and I hope
                  this Colony will <lb/> participate in it. It would be a great advantage. [Hear,
                  hear.] I think the opening of the <lb/> United States' markets to our lumber would
                  more than counterbalance the loss of protection <lb/> on produce. I don't care for
                  coal; they take as much as we can supply. I would suggest that <lb/> this Council
                  should send forward to Government a recommendation that we believe a special <lb/>
                  tariff desirable, nay, almost imperative. I do not believe that our eight members
                  in the House <lb/> of Commons, and four in the Senate, of Ottawa, will have no
                  weight; if so, they had better come <lb/> back. What in God's name good will they
                  do? I think the question may be safely left to the <lb/> Canadian Government and
                  our representatives at Ottawa. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —With a view of bringing this to a vote, I
                  will propose this recom<lb break="no"/>mendation: " That, in the opinion of this
                  Council, it is highly desirable that the agricultural, <lb/> horticultural, and
                  dairy interests of British Columbia be protected." And I do this in order <lb/> to
                  divide the question into two parts. One Hon. Member wants the power of suiting the
                  tariff <lb/> to our convenience; and more than one Hon. Member has said that
                  Confederation must come. <lb/> I deny it. There is no necessity that it should
                  come now. If the people vote against Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion when the terms
                  come before them, His Excellency will inform Her Majesty's Government. <lb/> that
                  the people don't want it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —We have always said so. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —I have so stated fifty times
                  already. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I am glad it is so understood. The Hon.
                  gentlemen must be very <lb/> careful to make the terms suit; for if the terms
                  don't suit the people we shall not have Con<lb break="no"/>federation. I say that
                  the people have been seriously told that Confederation was to be the <lb/> destiny
                  of this Colony. ["No, no,' from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Messrs. DeCosmos</persName> and <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Barnard</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> Efforts have been
                  <lb/> made to impress on the Colony that we must have Confederation on any terms.
                  I do not con<lb break="no"/>sider that it is necessary for us to go in under the
                  Organic Act. We did not expect to do it. To <lb/> the Hon. Collector of Customs I
                  would say, that much stress is laid upon the fact that under the <lb/> Canadian
                  tariff the people will save $100,000; that is, because the customs lose, the
                  people save. <lb/> I say this does not follow. Canadian goods don't come here now
                  because they cannot compete. <lb/> The only reason they will be used is, they will
                  come in free, whilst others pay tariff. Possibly <lb/> then the difference in
                  price between Canadian goods and our goods may be very little; the <lb/>
                  Government may lose, but the people won't gain. Do you understand that? ["No, no,"
                  from <lb/> <persName ref="pers:HAML1">Hamley</persName> and <persName ref="pers:ANON1">others</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> People may have to pay as much for Canadian goods
                  as for American <lb/> goods now. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Hon. COMMISSIONER OF CUSTOMS</persName> —American goods would come in
                  less the duty now <lb/> paid. Don't you see? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName> —The difference of transport would prevent
                  Canadian manufactures from <lb/> coming here cheaper. <lb/>
               </p>

            <pb n="139" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_139.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">139</fw>
            

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I say the tariff would be almost the same
                  on these American goods <lb/> then as now. I grant there will be a loss on
                  agricultural produce Hon. gentlemen say they <lb/> may send agricultural produce.
                  Butter, I believe, comes from cows; it costs money to buy a <lb/> cow; there is
                  the difference between raising agricultural produce and cattle. If butter could
                  <lb/> be grown from the ground I don't suppose that forty tons would have been
                  imported. Farmers <lb/> are poor; they have not money to buy stock. Keep up
                  protection and they will have money <lb/> bye and bye to purchase cattle.
                  Experience of the agriculturalists in this Colony has taught me <lb/> that farmers
                  with capital come out at the wrong end of the stick, whilst those who have gone
                  <lb/> in to work for themselves have made money. I know most of the farmers on
                  Vancouver Island, <lb/> and I find that those who began with nothing are doing
                  well. The Hon. Collector of Customs <lb/> said that farmers in the upper country
                  don't require a tariff. I went into that question <lb/> yesterday. I think they
                  will want it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hons. CARRALL</persName> and <persName ref="pers:BARN1">BARNARD</persName>—Prices are
                  getting too high now. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —It is exceeding easy and pleasant for us
                  who want to eat to say <lb/> prices are too high, but let any man go to work on a
                  farm and he will have experience of the <lb/> difficulties. The Hon. Collector of
                  Customs says a treaty of reciprocity would be of great benefit, <lb/> and that we
                  might give up the farming. interests of this Colony for it. Now, Sir, this Council
                  <lb/> said last year, almost unanimously, that agricultural interests must be
                  protected. Why should <lb/> Hon. Members think that we should require anything
                  different under Confederation? The Hon. <lb/> Member for Victoria District almost
                  led me the way in saying that irritation would arise which <lb/> would lead to a
                  desire for annexation if the agricultural interests were not protected. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —The interests we want to protect
                  would be annihilated <lb/> under Confederation. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I say what we want now is what we want
                  under Confederation. <lb/> Now, Sir, what have we been trying for? What has been
                  our policy? Why, to protect industry. <lb/> I am told that the Dominion Government
                  will not admit any alteration in our tariff; and the <lb/> example of the United
                  States is cited. It has been said that California wanted to alter her <lb/>
                  tariff, and was not allowed to do so. I say, in reply, that California was one and
                  a part of <lb/> the United States. British Columbia is not yet Confederated, so we
                  are still in a position to <lb/> make terms. California would have made terms if
                  she could, but could not; and it was for <lb/> a time a question whether she
                  should not secede. It was only large subsidies and steam <lb/> communication that
                  kept California in the Union. There is this peculiarity in the Organic Act, <lb/>
                  section 95 enables Canada to make different laws as to agriculture in each
                  different Province. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —I don't think that section applies
                  to the tariff; it does not <lb/> sound like it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —Perhaps it does not, but I say that
                  anything advantageous to the <lb/> Colony may be enacted by the Local Government.
                  We can ask for a separate tariff, and Canada <lb/> has power to make different
                  laws as to agriculture in each Province. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —No, that is a mistake. The 95th
                  section weakens the Hon. <lb/> Member's argument. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName> —I say it strengthens my argument. It does
                  not mean merely that <lb/> people may clean thistles out of their land. The simple
                  issue is: Shall agricultural interests <lb/> be protected or not? It is quite
                  possible that those who regulate the treaty, when brought into <lb/> contact with
                  Canadian statesmen, may devise some means whereby this result may be effected.
                  <lb/> I do not mean to give up to Canadian statesmen that they know more than
                  ourselves about our <lb/> local affairs; but I do think we may utilize their
                  experience. I do not think that people, when <lb/> they know that Confederation
                  will not be forced upon them, will accept Confederation. The <lb/> question for
                  the farmers will be: Shall agriculture be protected or not? I ask again. is <lb/>
                  agriculture protected by the resolution or not? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY—GENERAL</persName> —It is not a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi>. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —I think the idea to take a vote on
                  protection to agriculture <lb/> a good one, and I would rather that the resolution
                  stopped there. Then I would propose a <lb/> further resolution, pointing out the
                  difficulties and ills we labour under. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I accept that alteration. We shall by it
                  procure an expression of <lb/> the opinion of the Council upon this point. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —I go further than that resolution. I stand
                  here as a protectionist, <lb/> and I want to see the manufacturing interests
                  protected as well as the agricultural interests. <lb/>
               </p>

            <pb n="140" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_140.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">140</fw> <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            

<p>
     Protection will be a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi> with my constituents. If the Hon. senior Member for Victoria 
     <lb/>
     will divide the question into agricultural interests, manufacturing interests, and trade, I will 
     <lb/>
     withdraw my recommendation. I say that we want this question settled before Confederation. 
     <lb/>
     As for reciprocity it has, in my opinion, to be based on existing industry. The most important 
     <lb/>
     treaty of reciprocity was between England and Portugal, under which English goods were 
     <lb/>
     admitted into Portugal and wines into England. Reciprocity to be successful must be based 
     <lb/>
     on existing industries. If we enter into a treaty of reciprocity with the United States, we must 
     <lb/>
     build up our industries, such as coal. I take it that what our coal has to contend with is foreign 
     <lb/>
     and native coal in the San Francisco and Portland markets. Unless there is an extended market 
     <lb/>
     for coal it is impossible to increase the trade in it. Reciprocity would destroy the most per<lb break="no"/>manent interests; that, for instance, of agriculture, and we would gain nothing by it. I say if 
     <lb/>
     Canada thinks proper to negotiate a treaty of reciprocity with the United States, we should be 
     <lb/>
     at liberty to negotiate a separate treaty, or to insert special clauses in the treaty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —Let us clear the ground by getting
                  the Chairman to put <lb/> this resolution as an abstract proposition. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman then read the resolution as an abstract proposition for the vote of the 
     <lb/>
     Council :— <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" That in the opinion of this Council it is necessary that the agricultural, horticultural, and 
     <lb/>
     "dairy interests of British Columbia be protected." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —Mr. Chairman, I am prepared to vote
                  for that proposition, <lb/> but I do not go quite to the extent of beliving it
                  necessary, although I think it very desirable. I <lb/> don't think it of such
                  importance as the Hon. Members for Victoria City and District, as to make <lb/> it
                  a vital question or a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi> of
                  Confederation. I think it is desirable to continue <lb/> protection under
                  Confederation, and I do not see why we cannot. I think that the Dominion <lb/>
                  Government may, perhaps, be better able to provide the ways and means to effect
                  that object <lb/> than ourselves. We may not be able to provide a remedy, but we
                  may advise. The protection <lb/> that we ask for only partially affects the
                  community. It is patent that it only affects Vancouver <lb/> Island and the Lower
                  Fraser at this time. ["No, no," from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DeCosmos</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName></supplied> I say that the <lb/> farmers
                  of the Interior have a geographical protection. The time is so distant when
                  agricultural <lb/> produce can come into the upper parts of British Columbia, or
                  when the produce of the Upper <lb/> Country can come into competition with the
                  produce of the Island and of the Lower Fraser in <lb/> these markets, without
                  feeling the cost of transport as equivalent to a protective duty, that <lb/>
                  before that time arrives the tariff may be amended again and again. With regard to
                  what has <lb/> been said about the closer union with a foreign country. I said,
                  and I repeat it, that if the <lb/> interests of the farmers would be prejudiced
                  under Confederation, they would be utterly <lb/> annihilated under Annexation. I
                  believe that if we were brought under the Dominion tariff <lb/> they would be
                  injured. I did not say that the Dominion would not give us separate tariff <lb/>
                  regulations. I think they will do so, but I say we have put ourselves out of a
                  position to <lb/> prescribe. We have put before them a scheme, and we have left
                  the tariff out of the scheme. <lb/> We can now point out that we want, protection,
                  and leave it for the Dominion Government to <lb/> point out the means. We have
                  virtually put it out of our hands to dictate the means approved <lb/> by this
                  Council. I cannot agree in thinking that clause 91 leaves us free to impose our
                  own <lb/> tariff. I say we have made the British North America Act apply under the
                  scheme which we <lb/> have adopted under clause 16. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName> —I differ from that. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —That is the whole strength of my
                  argument. We have <lb/> virtually given up the power over the tariff to Canada,
                  but it is open to us, and the Council <lb/> are invited to state what is wanted.
                  It must he remembered that those terms are only memor<lb break="no"/>anda for
                  Confederation. Different terms may be sent back, and it will be left for the new
                  <lb/> Council to decide upon them; and I, for one, am ready to suggest to the
                  Canadian Government <lb/> that we should have protection, although there are
                  objections, for if you protect one interest <lb/> another must suffer. We pay for
                  the protection of produce in the increased price of the articles <lb/> we consume.
                  I go to the length of thinking it desirable to recommend the Canadian Government
                  <lb/> to protect our agricultural interests. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —I will ask the honourable mover of
                  this recommendation <lb/> whether he insists on the word "necessary"? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I say this is one of those things that
                  under Confederation will be <lb/> necessary. <lb/>
               </p>

            <pb n="141" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_141.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">141</fw>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —Will the Hon. Member alter the word
                  "necessary" to <lb/> " very desirable "? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —If you retain that word I must vote
                  against it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I retain the word. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —" Highly desirable " would suit my views
                  better. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —I think the word ought to be retained.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ALST1">Hon. MR. ALSTON</persName> —I believe all restrictions are false in
                  principle, and Governments have <lb/> no right to travel out of their path to
                  dictate principles. It has rightly been said that protection <lb/> to agriculture
                  is at the expense of other things, and it is simply ridiculous to say that
                     agricul<lb break="no"/>tural interests are the only interests in the Colony.
                  Vancouver Island cannot be looked upon <lb/> as an agricultural country. I would
                  vote for protection temporarily, but as soon as good roads <lb/> are made the
                  farmer needs no protection; and, although free trade may be injurious to one <lb/>
                  interest, I believe it to be the correct principle. It strikes me that the Organic
                  Act is a treaty <lb/> of partnership between four countries, and where the terms
                  are silent we can alter the Organic <lb/> Act. If it be that we may make the laws,
                  Canada still takes the revenue; and unless the <lb/> resolution is altered I
                  cannot vote for it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —I may clear the ground if I make a
                  suggestion. I think <lb/> it would be better to take the subjects separately, and
                  then I would embody the whole matter <lb/> in one Resolution to His Excellency.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName> —It would be desirable to have as unanimous a
                  vote as possible. The Hon. <lb/> Chief Commissioner and the Hon. Mr. Alston have
                  said that a tax on produce would he likely <lb/> to prove injurious. I say that
                  protection is only to be extended until our agriculturalists can <lb/> compete
                  with the farmers on the opposite shore. If reciprocity eventually arise, I do not
                  pledge <lb/> myself to support protection. It may be necessary then to make some
                  compensation to farmers, <lb/> but I cannot say I would support it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —We want a positive guarantee for
                  protection. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> moved an amendment to change the word
                  "necessary" to <lb/> " highly desirable." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The recommendation, as amended, was carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> moved a Resolution, " That it is highly
                  desirable that manufactured <lb/> articles should be protected." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —I would ask the Hon. Member to
                  define "manufactured <lb/> articles." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —I would name boots and shoes. Now, in
                  event of any reciprocity <lb/> treaty, I should like to see our interests
                  protected. A reciprocity treaty may exert a stimulating <lb/> influence for a
                  time, or it may be detrimental. We have confectionery and many other things; <lb/>
                  for instance, there is a proposition to erect a woollen manufactory. Furniture, at
                  present, all <lb/> comes from the United States. Our cabinet-makers could
                  manufacture it here if they could <lb/> import the raw material free. The same
                  could be said of wheelwrights. If we are to have <lb/> large public works we must
                  have these interests protected. Harness may be brought in cheap <lb/> under
                  reciprocity; leather and soap likewise. I start out on this principle: if we can
                  keep our <lb/> manufactures at home we are doing our duty. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —The Canadian tariff applies to all the
                  articles mentioned by the <lb/> Hon. gentleman. I am mystified in regard to this
                  protection. He says he wants protection <lb/> for leather, and boots, and harness.
                  Twenty per cent. is our tariff on waggons, and yet no <lb/> class of waggons, such
                  as is wanted, can be made here. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —We shall never have producing
                  manufacturers if we do not protect <lb/> them. With regard to waggon building:
                  parties now engaged in the business were about to <lb/> leave until the tariff was
                  introduced. Competition lowers the price of home-manufactured <lb/> articles.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I shall support this Resolution; the
                  Canadian tariff to some <lb/> measure meets it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —I shall ask to have the words altered.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —Presently we shall have to protect British
                  Columbian interests <lb/> against Canadian interests. If the farmer and boot-maker
                  are protected, other local manufac<lb break="no"/>tures must be protected also.
                  Where you do not produce things admit them free. It is our <lb/> duty to protect
                  our own interests. <lb/>
               </p>

            <pb n="142" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-23_Page_142.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">142</fw> <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —And turn people out of the country. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —You keep them in. You send out $100,000 a
                  quarter for goods, <lb/> which ought to be spent here. That $100,000 ought to be
                  invested in mines and in building up <lb/> the country. Now, you want this country
                  to be a garden and a manufactory. The people must <lb/> do it, and it is the only
                  way in which they can do it. Put your productions into competition <lb/> with the
                  whole world and you will ruin the producers throughout the whole Colony. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —Another question is, up to what
                  point are you to protect? <lb/> What is the use of protecting produce if you
                  protect colonists out of the country? I put this <lb/> as an abstract proposition.
                  There is no more moot point than the difference between free trade <lb/> and
                  protection. I see the Canadian tariff protects these things, and I don't feel
                  inclined to ask <lb/> for more. Under the Canadian tariff agricultural products
                  are almost free, but manufactures <lb/> are protected. I don't intend to assume
                  that the tariff will be taken off—that protection is to <lb/>be taken away from
                  manufacturers, for, if so, it will be against the arguments of the members
                  <lb/>from British Columbia. <lb/>
               </p>

    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —Some members are growing protection mad.
                  They want to build a <lb/> wall around the Colony and keep out the entire world.
                  You must come down to first principles. <lb/> When honourable members talk about
                  protection, I suppose we intend to protect that which we <lb/> can produce. Are we
                  to protect so as to force people into branches of industry unthought of <lb/>
                  before? Some honourable members have run to the extent of protecting population
                  out of <lb/> the Colony; another favours protection in order to keep prices low,
                  and thus to secure our <lb/> population. I maintain that protection has run too
                  far, and the agriculturists have not <lb/> benefited by it. ["No, no "—<persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr.
                  DeCosmos</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName></supplied> They tell me that the demand is so small that <lb/> prices are less. I
                  am not in favour of withdrawing protection from farmers, but let us see <lb/> that
                  it does not go too far. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName> —Might I not turn the tables by judging some
                  honourable members are <lb/> free trade mad. No one ever dreamt of such high
                  taxation. So far from sweeping oft popula<lb break="no"/>tion we secure it; and in
                  England free trade is intended to benefit the manufacturer, and it <lb/> does so.
                  It struck a blow at agriculture, and if they had not gone into raising and
                  spending <lb/> more money it would have been an utter failure. High price for corn
                  is now unknown, but free <lb/> trade by way of dogma is absurd. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —There is a distinction between a tariff
                  for protection and a prohibi<lb break="no"/>tory tariff. The Hon. Collector of
                  Customs will set me right, if I am mistaken, but I believe <lb/> the importation
                  of arms from foreign countries into a Colony is prohibited. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Hon. COLLECTOR OF CUSTOMS</persName> —Prohibited, I believe, altogether.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —Precisely so; that the defence of the
                  Colony may never depend on <lb/> foreign aid. The Hon. Chief Commissioner asked
                  the extent of the protection. I say during the <lb/> infancy of the Colony. When
                  we are able to run alone, protection will be necessary. With <lb/> regard to
                  farmers wanting free trade, I deny it emphatically. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —No doubt the Canadian Government will like
                  this amendment of <lb/> the tariff. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —I shall vote against it because it
                  says it is expedient to <lb/> arrange it in the terms. If the Hon. Member alters
                  the wording it would then become on the <lb/> same footing as the last
                  recommendation. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> altered the wording accordingly, and on
                  vote the motion was lost. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The motion of Hon. Dr. Helmcken was put and carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


   <!-- GL, 2017-03-22, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p>
     THURSDAY, 24TH March, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On the House going into Committee of the Whole on the Confederation Resolution, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. DECOSMOS  moved the following resolution :—" That in the opinion of this Council 
     <lb/>
     it is expedient, in order to foster commerce, to admit, duty free, into this Colony or some 
     <lb/>
    portions thereof, certain articles of foreign merchandise not produced in the Dominion or this 
     <lb/>Colony, and that provision for the admission of the same be made in the terms of Union with 
     <lb/>Canada." In reply to a question the Hon. mover said it would be impossible to name all the 
     <lb/>articles; but a few of them might be instanced, such as tropical fruits, silks, and English dry 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>