<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgBCLC_1870-03-25" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgBCLC">British Columbia Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1870-03-25">25 March 1870</date>, Province of BC, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgBCLC">
         
         <editor>W.S. Sebright Green</editor>
          
         
               <title>Legislative Council, Debate on the Subject of Confederation with Canada</title>.
                    

          <date when="1912"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Victoria, B.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>William H. Cullin</publisher>.
                   
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="150" to="157"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_150.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_151.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_152.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_153.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_154.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_155.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_156.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_157.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-22">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-22">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-25">Marked-up people.</change> 
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_150">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_150.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_151">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_151.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_152">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_152.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_153">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_153.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_154">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_154.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_155">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_155.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_156">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_156.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_157">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_157.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="150" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_150.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">150</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
<!-- GL, 2017-03-22, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 


<!--<p>
     Hon. Mr. Drake's motion was also withdrawn. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. I-Iolbrook's motion was put and lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Robson's motion was put and lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS moved :<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <p>"That in the consideration of the subsidies to be given by Canada to this Colony, due 
     <lb/>
     "weight shall be given to the advisability of abolishing the present road tolls on the Yale<lb break="no"/>" Cariboo road, and also to make provision for funds to keep the same in repair." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I put this in consequence of the suggestions thrown out by the Hon. Chief Commissioner. 
     <lb/>
     I think these road tolls have done more towards making bankrupts than any over-trading. 
     <lb/>
     They are main trunk roads, and I think they ought to be kept up by the Dominion Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL—l am not aware that that is the result of a suggestion 
     <lb/>
     of the Hon. Chief Commissioner, I am aware of his views, and I believe he has doubts as to 
     <lb/>
     whether roads can he maintained by a Government so far removed as Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. BARNARD—I would suggest that this be laid over till the Hon. Chief Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner be here 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon, ATTORNEY-GENERAL—The Hon. Chief Commissioner would not object to any 
     <lb/>
     conclusion of the House on this matter, But I caution Hon. Members not, by the addition of 
     <lb/>
     these suggestions, so to overload the resolutions as to break down the whole of them 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. BARNARD—l move that the Committee rise and report progress, in order that 
     <lb/>
     the matter may he laid over until the Hon. Chief Commissioner is in his place. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Committee rose and reported progress. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     FRIDAY, MARCH 25TH, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     On Mr. Humphreys' motion on roads being read, the Hon. Attorney-General said :- <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I regret to say that my honourable colleague, the Chief Commissioner of Lands and Works, 
     <lb/>
     is still too much indisposed to attend to his place in this House. I would, therefore, suggest 
     <lb/>
     that the Honourable Member should postpone his notice until he is present. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —I have no
                                          objection to defer it, on the understanding that it <lb/>
                                          comes up on Monday.   <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —On Monday, or
                                          this day, if: the Committee get through with <lb/> their
                                          other motions on Confederation. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName> —I desire to introduce
                                          a motion with regard to free port, but I do not <lb/>
                                          intend to inflict upon the House a speech. I move that His
                                          Excellency he respectfully requested <lb/> to place in the
                                          terms a clause to restore to Victoria the system of free
                                          port antecedent to <lb/> Confederation. The Honourable
                                          Member for New Westminster was indignant with me yester<lb break="no"/>day for not supporting his resolution.
                                          I only say that his proposition was hypercritieal. I <lb/>
                                          ask that we may have free port restored before
                                          Confederation. We have now the right to <lb/> legislate
                                          for ourselves on this point. Hereafter we shall he at the
                                          mercy of the, Canadian <lb/> Parliament at Ottawa. i would
                                          make free port one of the conditions of Confederation; but
                                          <lb/> first restore free port. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     On the Clerk reading the first words of the resolution,- <lb/>
            </p>


            <p><persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName> —I rise to a point of order. I say that this
                                          question has been already <lb/> decided.  <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">CHAIRMAN</persName> —I think the Hon Member for
                                          Nanaimo is not out of order on that point. <lb/> The
                                          question of free port yesterdav related to free port after
                                          Confederation. The resolution <lb/> of the Hon, Member for
                                          Nanaiino is in reference to free port antecedent to
                                          Confederation. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —The Hon, Member is
                                          surely out of order, this Committee having <lb/> met to
                                          consider Confederate resolutions. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">CHAIRMAN</persName> — I rule that the Hon. Mr.
                                          Ring is in order, as his resolution refers to the <lb/>
                                          terms of Confederation now before this Committee. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     On the Hon. Mr. Ring's motion being but to vote, it was lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="151" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_151.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">151</fw>
            

<p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. MR. HOLBROOK</persName> —I have very great
                                          pleasure in bringing this resolution forward <lb/> with
                                          reference to the Indian tribes. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —I ask the
                                          indulgence of the Hon. Member whilst I interpose <lb/> a
                                          few words. On a former occasion a very evil impression was
                                          introduced in the Indian mind <lb/> on the occasion of Sir
                                          James Douglas' retirement. I ask the Hon. gentleman to be
                                          cautious, <lb/> for Indians do get information of what is
                                          going on. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. MR. HOLBROOK</persName> —My motion is to
                                          ask for protection for them under the change <lb/> of
                                          Government, The Indians number four to one white man, and
                                          they ought to be considered. <lb/> They should receive
                                          protection. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> —These are the
                                          words that do harm. I would ask the Hon. <lb/> Magisterial
                                          Member for New Westminster to consider <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK</persName> —I say they shall
                                          be protected. I speak of Indians of my own <lb/>
                                          neighbourhood on the Lower Fraser. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I rise to a point of
                                          privilege. I think that the warning of the Hon. <lb/>
                                          Attorney-General is necessary This is the sort of
                                          discussion which does harm. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —Don't report it.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. MR. HOLBROOK</persName> —I do not view it
                                          in that way. I say that the Indians of the <lb/> Lower
                                          Fraser are intelligent, good settlers. I ask that they
                                          receive the same protection under <lb/> Confederation as
                                          now. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —I would ask what
                                          protection they have now? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. MR. HOLBROOK</persName> —They have
                                          protection in being allowed to occupy land, and they <lb/>
                                          enjoy equally with white people the protection of the law,
                                          and I ask the House to keep them <lb/> in the same
                                          position. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —If the Indians
                                          had no better protectors than the Hon. <lb/> Magistrate
                                          from New Westminster, I should not envy them their
                                          protection. The Hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man must have
                                          forgotten the directions of the Imperial Government to His
                                          Excellency the <lb/> Governor, in Lord Granville's
                                          despatch. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —The Hon. Mr.
                                          Holbrook has told you that he speaks in behalf of <lb/>
                                          40,000 Indians. I speak in the name of 65,000. I am
                                          inclined to think we should not pass <lb/> this matter
                                          over entirely; we ought to point out our desire that the
                                          Indians should be cared <lb/> for. Now, the Canadian
                                          Indian policy has been characterized as good, even by
                                          American <lb/> statesmen. Our own policy is not worth the
                                          name. I consider it to be a blot on the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. I will. therefore, propose as an
                                          amendment the following :- <lb/>
                                   </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" That the Indian policy of Canada shall be extended to this Colony immediately upon its 
     <lb/>
     " admission into the Dominion, and that the necessary agencies and appliances for an efficient 
     <lb/>
    "administration of Indian affairs may be at once established." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

    

            <p>
     The Canadian Government occupies the position of guardians to Indians. They are treated 
     <lb/>
     as minors. There is a perfect network of Indian Agents in Canada, and through them the 
     <lb/>
     Indians are made presents of agricultural implements, seeds, and stock. Now, if we let it 
     <lb/>
     go forth to the Indians that their interests are being considered, and that this will be greatly 
     <lb/>
     to their advantage. I say, by making the Indians feel all this, there will be less danger of 
     <lb/>
     exciting any unpleasant feeling among them. We should set the Indian mind at rest and let 
     <lb/>
     them feel that Confederation will be a greater boon to thorn than to the white population. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName> —I rise to state my
                                          intention of voting against the resolution and <lb/> the
                                          amendment We have the full assurance in Lord Granville's
                                          despatch that the Indians <lb/> must be protected, I do
                                          think the Hon. gentlemen are only heaping up resolutions
                                          trusting <lb/> to overload the whole system. The Hon.
                                          Member for New Westminster has affirmed how <lb/> good the
                                          Canadian system is. The goodness of that system is in
                                          itself sufficient to render the <lb/> resolution needless.
                                          I shall, therefore, vote against it and the amendment,
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. MR. HOLBROOK</persName> —I must vote
                                          against the amendment <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR HUMPHREYS</persName> —I disapprove of
                                          what both the Hon. Members stated. These <lb/> gentlemen
                                          know nothing of the question. I will show you why. Take
                                          away the Indians from <lb/> New Westminster, Lillooet.
                                          Lytton. Clinton, and these towns would he nowhere. I say
                                          the <lb/> Indians are not treated fairly by us, and all
                                          they want is fair dealing from the white popula<lb break="no"/>tion. At Lillooet I was told there were
                                          upwards of 16,000; and $17,000 gold dust was purchased
                                          <lb/> from Indians. Take away this trade and the towns
                                          must sink. I say, send them out to <lb/> reservations and
                                          you destroy trade; and if the Indians are driven out we
                                          had all best go too. <lb/>
                                   </p>


            <pb n="152" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_152.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">152</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
           

 <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —The Hon. Member for
                                          Lillooet says that the Canadian policy will <lb/> ruin the
                                          country and the Indians. I say. then, to be consistent, he
                                          must move an amendment <lb/> that it shall not apply. To
                                          say that the Canadian policy will ruin the country shows
                                          simply <lb/> ignorance. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —I am convinced that
                                          the Hon. Attorney-General is right. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ALST1">Hon. MR. ALSTON</persName> —I must support the
                                          Hon. Member for New Westminster. I say there <lb/> is no
                                          Indian policy here, and I am sure that the Canadian policy
                                          is good. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I was induced to put
                                          an amendment because there is a resolution; <lb/>
                                          otherwise I would not have interfered. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —My esteemed
                                          colleague the Hon. Registrar-General says <lb/> we have no
                                          Indian policy. I say our policy has been, let the Indians
                                          alone. [<persName ref="pers:ALST1">Hon Mr. Alston</persName> <lb/> —" No, no!"] <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —The reason I ask
                                          for the withdrawal of the resolution is that we <lb/>
                                          cannot keep back from the Indians anything that happens
                                          here, and it will have a bad effect. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —As these words
                                          may go forth, I wish to state on behalf of <lb/> the
                                          Government that the care of the Indians will be the first
                                          care of the Imperial Government <lb/> and of the Local
                                          Government. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —I do not
                                          apprehend any danger from any discussion in this <lb/>
                                          House. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ALST1">Hon. MR. ALSTON</persName> —I suggest the
                                          withdrawal of the resolution. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName> —I say that the
                                          Canadian policy has caused them to grow and prosper. <lb/>
                                          I am at a loss to understand why Honourable Members should
                                          be afraid to trust to it. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —The Honourable
                                          Member for Cariboo seems to find it difficult to <lb/>
                                          understand my position. I think it right to endeavour to
                                          get the best terms we can, and to point <lb/> out
                                          difficulties. It is the duty of every man to do so. I am
                                          perfectly willing to sit here and <lb/> make the best
                                          terms possible. When they come back from Canada it will be
                                          time enough for me <lb/> to decide whether or not I shall
                                          support Confederation. I am now anti-Confederate, but I
                                          may <lb/> become Confederate if the terms are good. I say
                                          it the Indians are to he stuck on Reservations <lb/> there
                                          will be a disturbance. I think, Sir, that it will be well
                                          that there should be some <lb/> opposition.   <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I wish to state I will withdraw my amendment if
                                          the Honourable <lb/> Member will withdraw his motion.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. MR. HOLBROOK</persName> cannot do so
                                          consistently with my duty. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     The amendment was withdrawn. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The resolution of the Hon. Mr. Holbrook was lost by a vote of 20 to 1. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> moved that an Address
                                          be presented to His Excellency the Governor, <lb/> asking
                                          that Canada shall cause a Geological Survey of this Colony
                                          to be made, commencing <lb/> within one year after Union.
                                          He said that a fund of $100,000 had been set apart by the
                                          <lb/> Canadian Government for the specific object of
                                          carrying out a systematic Geological Survey; <lb/> that
                                          sum to be spread over a period of five years. Canada had
                                          the good fortune to possess a very <lb/> efficient
                                          Geological staff. The Red River country had received the
                                          first year's survey under that <lb/> arrangement, and
                                          would probably receive the second this year. British
                                          Columbia will possess a <lb/> greater mineral interest
                                          than any other Province, and a thorough Geological Survey
                                          will be of <lb/> the utmost importance to her, and
                                          reflexly to Canada, and it was not too much to expect such
                                          <lb/> a survey to follow close upon Union. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —I am sure no
                                          one can have the slightest objection to support <lb/> a
                                          motion for a survey. I assure you it has not escaped the
                                          notice of the Government, but I <lb/> regard it as a
                                          matter of certainty that British Columbia will come in for
                                          her share. I do not <lb/> object to the consideration of
                                          the question between this Government and that of Canada,
                                          but <lb/> I do object to inserting it in the terms. I
                                          think it may lead to the danger of the Canadian <lb/>
                                          Government saying, when other things come to be
                                          considered: " You don't want this, it is not <lb/>
                                          mentioned in the terms; had you really required this it
                                          would scarcely have been omitted in <lb/> terms so full as
                                          these." <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —In reply, I say that
                                          the Government has inserted a number of special <lb/>
                                          things in the terms; and with reference to the Geological
                                          Survey, I believe Newfoundland got <lb/> this very matter
                                          inserted under the direction of Governor Musgrave. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <pb n="153" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_153.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">153</fw> 
            

<p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —I rise to support
                                          the motion. I cannot understand the opposition. <lb/> [<persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon
                                          Attorney-General</persName>—I don't oppose; divide. divide, divide] <supplied><persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName></supplied> I
                                          desire to Show the necessity <lb/> for a Geological
                                          Survey. We are now eleven years old as a Colony, and
                                          nothing is hardly known <lb/> of the country. We are
                                          behind our neighbours of the United States. In California
                                          there is a <lb/> Geological Surveyor, who has to explore
                                          and publish the result of his survey. We should have <lb/>
                                          something of the sort here, and, in addition, a record of
                                          the number of available acres of land <lb/> in the Colony.
                                          If or 30 farmers arrived here I would undertake to affirm
                                          they could not get <lb/> any information from the Land
                                          Office as to where they could settle down. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I should not like
                                          that statement to get abroad uncontradictcd. <lb/> I think
                                          these assertions should not be made; they are likely to do
                                          much harm. I should like <lb/> to see the 25 or 30 farmers
                                          come; let them go to the mouth of the Fraser. There may be
                                          some <lb/> difficulty in getting land in any part or
                                          locality, but it is absurd to bring up this fuss about the
                                          <lb/> Land Office. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     The resolution was put to the vote and carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> moved, "That it is
                                          desirable that the Dominion Government shall <lb/>
                                          maintain telegraphic communication with this Colony."
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —It is absolutely
                                          necessary that there should be some telegraphic <lb/>
                                          communication with the outer world. It is palpable that we
                                          must have it with the seat of <lb/> Government. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —It will be in the
                                          recollection of some of the Hon. Members that, <lb/> some
                                          years ago. a question was sent out for discussion from the
                                          Secretary of State as to the <lb/> payment by Vancouver
                                          Island of a subsidy towards the Trans-Continental Line of
                                          Telegraph. <lb/> She could not afford it. Canada has the
                                          wire now taken over from the Hudson Bay Company. <lb/> I
                                          shall support the resolution. I do not regard it as a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi>, but
                                          very essential. I have <lb/> no doubt Canada will do it.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I understood the
                                          Hon. Member for Victoria City intended to ask the <lb/>
                                          Canadian Government to maintain the existing telegraph
                                          line, which runs through a foreign <lb/> country. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —From the
                                          general wording of the resolution I am at a <lb/> loss to
                                          know what is meant. I think this is a matter which had
                                          best the left out, or we shall <lb/> be overloading the
                                          terms. If I vote against it, it is because we have fully
                                          too much on the <lb/> terms. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —Why did not the
                                          terms come down to us more perfect? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName> —I am sorry the
                                          resolutions did not come down more perfect, but <lb/> if
                                          they had been ever so perfect Hon. Members would have
                                          found fault. I look upon the <lb/> conduct of Hon. Members
                                          in bringing forward the additional resolutions as being
                                          inimical to <lb/> Confederation. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName> —I shall support the
                                          resolution. I think our care will enhance our value <lb/>
                                          in the estimation of Canada. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —It is admitted
                                          that if we are to have union we must have telegraphic
                                          <lb/> communication. Why it was left out I don't know. it
                                          must have slipped out, for it was before <lb/> the
                                          Executive. Surely Hon. Members will not have the idea that
                                          $3,000 or $4,000 inserted here <lb/> will stop
                                          Confederation. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —3,000 or 4000
                                          dollars? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —At present, yes.
                                          The only means of communication is through <lb/> America.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —I thought this was
                                          a trans-continental telegraph. I am sorry I <lb/> said
                                          anything about it. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman then put the motion, which, on division, was lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —When I first rose
                                          to address this House on the question of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, I made some passing allusions to
                                          nation-making. Now, Sir, I believe we are engaged <lb/> in
                                          that great work. Our posterity will, I believe, control
                                          the northern end of this continent <lb/> for a thousand
                                          generations. We find the American continent in the
                                          possession of two nations. <lb/> The northern part in the
                                          possession of the Anglo-Saxon race, and the southern part
                                          in the <lb/> possession of the Spanish race. Then again we
                                          find the Anglo-Saxon race in the north divided <lb/> into
                                          two nations. with a great mission before them. The first
                                          object of the great nation to <lb/> the south of us may,
                                          perhaps, be said to be the acquisition of territory, and
                                          they have a <lb/>
                                          <pb n="154" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_154.jpg"/>
                                          <fw type="num">154</fw>
                                          <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> united piece
                                          of territory from our boundary to Mexico. With regard to
                                          the northern Anglo- <lb break="yes"/> Saxon race—to which
                                          we belong—we find that they possess all the north except
                                          Alaska. If <lb/> the United States have a single and
                                          compact piece of territory to the south, we want the same
                                          <lb/> in the north. Look at history as regards the
                                          acquisition of territory by nations: Lorraine by <lb/>
                                          France, Poland by Russia, Scotland by England, Texas and
                                          Alaska by the United States. How <lb/> has this been
                                          brought about but by a national policy. For hundreds of
                                          years it was the policy <lb/> of France to acquire
                                          Lorraine; so it was with Russia and Poland. It has been
                                          said that republics <lb/> cannot have a national policy as
                                          monarchies can; I say that they have a policy with regard
                                          to <lb/> land, And I say that we should have a policy of
                                          the same kind. Let us lay down this principle, <lb/> that
                                          we intend to create a great nation, and intending to do
                                          so, we should have all territory north <lb/> of the United
                                          States. I have no objection to the United States gaining
                                          territory to the south, <lb/> but I do object to her
                                          coming north or holding Alaska. Let us glance at Alaska
                                          for one moment. <lb/> The country is similar to our own.
                                          It has coal. fish, and lumber, as we have, and its
                                          contiguity <lb/> to our country ought to induce us to
                                          believe that there is a natural alliance between us. We
                                          <lb/> all know how much the purchase of this piece of
                                          territory cost the United States in hard cash. <lb/> Then
                                          its annual cost is nearly two million dollars. or forty
                                          millions to support it as a United <lb/> States Territory
                                          for twenty-five years, Then look at the population, a mere
                                          nothing; and its <lb/> revenue, hardly worth taking into
                                          account. It is said by many that America is sick of her
                                          <lb/> bargain, and that Russia sold the United States. I
                                          think this is a favourable time to bring it <lb/> up.
                                          Canada can well afford to pay for an extended frontier on
                                          the Pacific Coast. If we <lb/> purchased Alaska the
                                          Americans could still come in to fish and gather furs; so.
                                          commercially, <lb/> there need be no difficulty. I believe
                                          we could get along smoothly; therefore, I have to move
                                          <lb/> this resolution :- <lb/>
                                   </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"That Canada shall purchase the Territory of Alaska, if possible." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     I hope, Sir, in all our relations for the future we shall remain international, not national. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName> —I rise to support
                                          the resolution of the Hon. Mr. DeCosmos. The <lb/> only
                                          objection I can see is, that perhaps it is a little
                                          premature. That Canada will ultimately <lb/> acquire it, I
                                          can have no doubt. In supposing that the acquisition of
                                          this Territory, and the <lb/> consequent hemming in of
                                          British Columbia would have the effect of leading the
                                          people of Canada <lb/> to believe in the ultimate destiny
                                          of the British American possessions being drawn into
                                                 annexa<lb break="no"/>tion, or absorption, the Hon.
                                          W. H. Seward made an egregious blunder; he did it in his
                                          ignorance <lb/> of the Canadian character. It is not
                                          necessary for Canadians to get up and show their loyalty
                                          <lb/> daily, they are ready and able to occupy their
                                          position of <hi rendition="simple:italic">imperium in
                                                 imperio</hi>. There may be <lb/> some people in
                                          Canada who do not like the Government. In what country are
                                          there not some <lb/> uneasy spirits? The United States has
                                          them, and England is not free from them. I shall <lb/>
                                          decidedly support the Hon. member. although, I think, he
                                          is, perhaps, a little in advance of <lb/> American
                                          statesmen as to the acquisition of territory. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —I think Mr,
                                          Seward understood what he was about when he <lb/> effected
                                          the purchase of Alaska. I feel convinced that the
                                          Government of the United States <lb/> will not consent to
                                          let us have it. I have a strong feeling in favour of the
                                          United States, and <lb/> am satisfied that they should
                                          have Alaska. I don't think Canada can afford to repurchase
                                          the <lb/> Territory; nor do I think she has men to pit
                                          against the intellectual giants of America. I think <lb/>
                                          the Hon. Member for Victoria Disirict has perpetrated a
                                          joke on this Council; I shall, however, <lb/> support his
                                          motion. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName> —I rise to support the
                                          motion of the Hon. Member for Victoria District. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I think this a
                                          subject of too great importance to be disposed of hastily.
                                          <lb/> It ought to be fully discussed. I agree with the
                                          Hon. Member for Victoria District that such <lb/> is
                                          desirable, but I also agree with the Hon. Member for
                                          Cariboo that it is somewhat premature. <lb/> I think the
                                          people of the United States would like to get rid of it;
                                          would be rather glad to back <lb/> out of it. "their
                                          policy is to let it " paddle its own canoe." If we wait it
                                          will probably fall <lb/> into our hands. If we are to make
                                          a suggestion as to the acquisition of territory we should
                                          <lb/> not confine ourselves to Alaska only, Let us have
                                          Maine also. It impinges upon Canada on the <lb/>Atlantic;
                                          and it is a portion of land out of which England allowed
                                          herself to be cheated. It is<lb/>well known that Maine is
                                          most important, as giving an open winter seaboard to
                                          Canada ; a <lb/>large portion of Canadian trade has had to
                                          pass through Maine in bond. I believe the Dominion<lb/>of
                                          Canada will eventually utterly absorb America. (Laughter.)
                                          Some may laugh, but that is my<lb/>conviction. The United
                                          States have made great progress, but the Constitution is
                                          very defective.<lb/>
                                   </p>


            <pb n="155" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_155.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">155</fw>
            

<p>
     It cannot hear the creation of another nation, especially one of such a liberal and enlightened 
     <lb/>
     constitution as the Dominion of Canada. alongside of it. One of two things is perfectly certain 
     <lb/>
     to my mind: That the Dominion will absorb the United States, or that they will meet as one 
     <lb/>
     nation, each giving up something. I think it is contrary to nature that they should continue 
     <lb/>
     separate. I believe that so great will be the success of the new British North American Empire. 
     <lb/>
     that it will absorb all the English-speaking people on this continent. The people of Maine desire 
     <lb/>
     to belong to Canada, and have done so for years. If, on the Pacific. the Dominion acquires 
     <lb/>
     Alaska, and the State of Maine on the Atlantic, I assert that the great destiny of the Empire 
     <lb/>
     is assured. I move that the State of Maine be included. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —All we lack now
                                          is a Leech or Douglas Jerrold. I think we <lb/> shall
                                          ininiortalize ourselves; probably we shall appear in <hi rendition="simple:italic">Punch</hi>. I think Mr.
                                          Seward won't <lb/> blame us. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I must move an
                                          amendment. We shall be absorbed before this <lb/>
                                          absorption can take place. I shall move to leave out the
                                          words " if possible." I think the frog <lb/> has swollen
                                          to the size of an ox. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —These debates should
                                          be carried on with becoming gravity. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> — think so, too.
                                          and I think it would he the duty of any Leech <lb/>
                                          amongst us to secure a correct sketch of the movers of the
                                          resolution and amendments. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —I think the Hon.
                                          the Attorney General should give his opinion. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     The words "if possible." on vote, were struck out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —Shall the words "
                                          State of Maine " be included? <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Several Members</persName> —Yes, yes. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     The motion "That Canada shall purchase the Territory of Alaska and the State of Maine" 
     <lb/>
     was carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —Mr. Chairman, as
                                          there is no further resolution before the <lb/> Committee,
                                          except my own upon roads, I shall, without further words,
                                          move its adoption. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon MR. BARNARD</persName> —I think it unwise to
                                          hamper these conditions, but I consider this <lb/> an
                                          important question. I am here to protest on behalf of
                                          persons who pay road tolls. The <lb/> excuse made for this
                                          imposition is that the Colony is indebted for the
                                          construction of these <lb/> roads. People have looked to
                                          Confederation to relieve them of the $4 per barrel duty
                                          upon <lb/> flour, which they have been paying for so long.
                                          I desire to move an amendment to strike out <lb/> the
                                          Douglas Road, as I believe it to be unnecessary. I know
                                          that the Upper Country people <lb/> will raise their
                                          voices against the continuance of the road tolls.   <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —The question was
                                          alluded to by myself when the terms were under <lb/>
                                          discussion. I think the roads. if not national, ought to
                                          be local. I think the matter ought <lb/> to be approached
                                          differently in dealing with this road. I think that
                                          shortly this plank in the <lb/> platform of terms will be
                                          useless, because the railway will span the distance if
                                          Confederation <lb/> is granted on the terms proposed;
                                          therefore, I do not see the wisdom of handing them over
                                          <lb/> to Canada. I. think it desirable that road tolls
                                          should be abolished, and that we must have <lb/> something
                                          to compensate us for giving them up. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —I cannot
                                          assent to either the original motion or the amend<lb break="no"/>ment. I promise by saying the matter
                                          has received considerable consideration The original <lb/>
                                          resolution, which was suggested by the Hon. Chief
                                          Commissioner of Lands and Works, tool; <lb/> up this whole
                                          matter. I am sorry the House has not adjourned to give him
                                          an opportunity <lb/> to explain his views upon this
                                          question. His opinion is that the road from Yale to
                                          Cariboo <lb/> would not be so well managed by the
                                          Government at Ottawa as by the Local Government, The <lb/>
                                          Hon. Member for Yale ' that there are no reasons for road
                                          tolls. There is one. as stated <lb/> by the Hon. Chief
                                          Commissioner. It is being continually improved, therefore
                                          a road of that <lb/> description ought to carry with it a
                                          road toll for its construction and maintenance as a matter
                                          <lb/> of principle, even after the original cost is paid.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName>, with the consent
                                          of the House, withdrew his resolution in order <lb/> to
                                          make some verbal alterations in it. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —I shall move the
                                          same amendment as I moved to the former <lb/> resolution.
                                          I will read it:- <lb/>
                                   </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" That the Government be requested to insert in the Terms of Confederation to be proposed 
     <lb/>
     " to Canada some such clause as the following: All public roads and property of British Colum<lb break="no"/>"bia at the time of admission to belong to British Columbia, except such public works and 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="156" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_156.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">156</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
           

     "property as shall properly belong to the Dominion under the 'British North America Act,' and 
     <lb/>
     "such portions of the Main Trunk Line through British Columbia, or other roads then con<lb break="no"/>" structed, as may be necessary to complete a continuous line of coach road from a point at or 
     <lb/>
     " below Yale to a point at the fool: of the eastern slope of the Rocky Mountains, and that the 
     <lb/>
     " same shall be free of toll of any kind whatever." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName> —I agree that some road
                                          tolls ought to be kept up. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —My only object is
                                          to bring this matter before the Executive. I <lb/> cannot
                                          agree with the Hon. Member for Yale. I have not opposed
                                          any proposition of any man <lb/> from personal motives.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —I oppose the motion
                                          of the Hon. Member for Lillooet. I think it <lb/> does not
                                          meet the question. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY—GENERAL</persName> —The objection
                                          to the whole matter in shape of a resolution <lb/> is that
                                          by talking of road tolls we raise expectations we cannot
                                          probably fulfil. I had hoped <lb/> Hon. members would not
                                          press the subject. I assure the Hon. gentlemen that the
                                          petitions sent <lb/> up have been the subject of earnest
                                          consideration. I attach weight to what the Hon. Member
                                          <lb/> for Yale says in this House, and regret that such a
                                          feeling should go abroad. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName> —I, as Member for
                                          Cariboo, should say something upon this matter. <lb/> I
                                          have some doubt upon it. I would say this much, as a
                                          member of the Government, that is, <lb/> that many of the
                                          resolutions brought up here and vetoed will probably form
                                          the subject of <lb/> negotiation with the delegation in
                                          settling the terms. They will be a sort of substratum. I
                                          <lb/> regard the taxing of those who use the roads as the
                                          proper means for the keeping up the road, <lb/> and,
                                          furthermore, I fear to overload the terms. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. MR. HOLBROOK</persName> —For such roads as
                                          were made on the petition of the people tolls <lb/> are
                                          justifiable, but tolls should not be kept up after the
                                          debt is defrayed. No doubt when this <lb/> road comes
                                          under the rule of Canada she will construct turnpikes. Our
                                          road tolls are too high. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I regret the absence
                                          of the Hon. Chief Commissioner. I think that <lb/> he has
                                          an impression that some such resolution as this is
                                          necessary. I regret that the matter <lb/> was brought up
                                          to-day at all. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> —I proposed
                                          that the matter should be left open until <lb/> Monday.  
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —Then let it he left
                                          open. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —I have pointed
                                          out the Hon. Chief Commissioner's objections. <lb/> He
                                          says that the road can be better kept up by the Local than
                                          the Dominion Government. I <lb/> regret the absence of the
                                          Hon. Chief Commissioner. He did not state to me any
                                          certain impres<lb break="no"/>sion, but I am sure he would
                                          have been glad to have joined in the discussion. It has, I
                                          have no <lb/> objection to state, been discussed in
                                          Executive Council and this discussion will do no good.
                                          <lb/> I must oppose such resolutions going up to the
                                          Governor. for it may create expectations which, <lb/> when
                                          the terms go to the polls, cannot be fulfilled. , <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —I have no doubt
                                          when the terms come to the polls there will be one <lb/>
                                          howl of discontent at the financial part of them from
                                          Carihoo to New Westminster. I wish to <lb/> see road tolls
                                          free but I do not wish to see the Dominion Government
                                          taking charge of our local <lb/> interests, such as tolls.
                                          With regard totcrms, I say that the financial terms will
                                          kill Con<lb break="no"/>federation when it comes to the
                                          polls. The people from Cariboo to New Westminster want
                                          these <lb/> road tolls abolished. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —The Attorney-General
                                          suggests, on behalf of the Hon. Chief Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner, that we shall lose the revenue; but this is a
                                          gain if we get free from the maintenance <lb/> of the
                                          roads. The Government should consider themselves part of
                                          the people, and endeavour <lb/> to relax taxes. Another
                                          objection is, that under this arrangement roads would not
                                          be kept <lb/> in repair so well as at present. I say,
                                          under Confederation, the Chief Commissioner of Lands <lb/>
                                          and Works would have control of roads. The Dominion
                                          Government is less likely to bc penuri<lb break="no"/>ous
                                          than a Local Government. The Hon. Chief Connnissioner
                                          spoke to me after making that <lb/> objection. and my
                                          distinct impression is that the Hon. gentleman would
                                          support some such <lb/> proposition as this. We ask what
                                          is in perfect harmony with reason. We may just as well ask
                                          <lb/> Canada to do the whole thing, and to maintain the
                                          whole road. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName> —It astonishes me that
                                          Hon. gentlemen are connecting revenue with these <lb/>
                                          tolls. It can only be justifiable to keep tolls for the
                                          repair of roads. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I am on the horns
                                          of a dilemma. If I vote for road tolls being <lb/>
                                          taxable, I shall be told I want to make the terms too
                                          heavy; it against them, I should be told <lb/> I am
                                          against Confederation. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <pb n="157" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-25_Page_157.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">157</fw>
            

<p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:WALK1">Hon. MR. WALKEM</persName> —Sir, I have made few
                                          speeches during this debate, but this is a <lb/> question
                                          on which I must ask leave to say a few words. Session
                                          after Session the question has <lb/> been brought down We
                                          have had always a large Victoria element, and this
                                          question has. <lb/> unfortunately, always taken a Victoria
                                          and Mainland issue. I have studied this matter care<lb break="no"/>fully. With regard to the Acts
                                          themselves they are very strong; they commence with
                                          preambles <lb/> as to construction, maintenance, and
                                          repair. The toll was not mentioned as to continue merely
                                          <lb/> until the debt was extinguished, therefore I think
                                          the vote should be taken on another view. <lb/> The
                                          benefits accrue equally to Victoria and the Upper Country;
                                          probably the farmer gets the <lb/> lion's share; I know
                                          the Upper Country pretty well: formerly the miner used
                                          nothing outside <lb/> of bacon and flour. This should not
                                          he made an Island and Mainland question. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName> —I do not regard
                                          the subject as a joke. We have paid $60,000 for <lb/>
                                          roads on Vancouver Island—roads not one-twentieth the
                                          length of those on the Mainland. <lb/> Victoria gets more
                                          kicks than halfpence. Victoria pays the greater part of
                                          the tolls. I belong <lb/> to a company who pay a large
                                          proportion. What do they propose in place of a road toll?
                                          <lb/> Some one must pay it. Thirty thousand dollars per
                                          annum is required to keep roads in repair. <lb/> I say
                                          Victoria and Vancouver Island are more concerned with What
                                          is for the good of the <lb/> Colony, generally, than any
                                          part of the Mainland. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —I rise to bear
                                          testimoin to the fairness of the Hon. Members for <lb/>
                                          Vancouver Island in whatever concerns the Mainland. I have
                                          always seen a desire on the part <lb/> of Vancouver Island
                                          Members to legislate for the whole, and not for a part, of
                                          the Colony. <lb/> I am as tired of this bickering as any
                                          Member of the Mainland. I consider it our duty to be <lb/>
                                          more united. It the Hon. Members for New Westminster and
                                          Yale would talk less about <lb/> injustice to the Mainland
                                          it would be better. I regret the action of the Hon. Member
                                          for <lb/> Yale; it is factions. <lb/>
                                   </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —Vancouver Island has always made practical
                                          jokes of any questions <lb/>from the Mainland. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> rose to order.
                                          <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —I referred to the
                                          Hon. gentleman for Victoria City. There are no <lb/> road
                                          tolls on Vancouver Island. [Yes a road tax! —<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr.
                                          Helmcken</persName>] <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> As soon as the roads <lb/> are paid for the
                                          people or the Mainland will, to a man, refuse to pay any
                                          more road tolls. Every <lb/> item has been used as a
                                          threat against Confederation. I do not offer any such
                                          threat. I believe <lb/> the Upper Country would accept
                                          Confederation on the terms proposed; but if the Government
                                          <lb/> expect that they will be able to collect this
                                          $60,000 from the population of the Upper Country <lb/>
                                          they are mistaken.   <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —The Hon. Member
                                          for Yale is unjust to Vancouver Islanders. The <lb/> Whole
                                          of this Colony is paying large sums of money for interest
                                          on debt on roads. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —I did not say what
                                          I did with reference to Vancouver Island <lb/> Members
                                          without consideration. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I hope that
                                          Government Members. in view of the absence of the Hon.
                                          <lb/> Chief Commissioner, will vote so as to allow this
                                          resolution to go forward. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
                                          <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> —I must express
                                          a contrary hope. <lb/>
                                   </p>

            <p>
     The amendment of Hon. Mr. Barnard was carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Committee rose and reported the resolutions complete. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Council resumed. and the resolutions passed in Committee were adopted, except those with 
     <lb/>
     regard to the purchase of Alaska and the State of Maine. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<!-- GL, 2017-03-22, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p>
     WEDNESDAY, 6TH APRIL, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Hon. Attorney-General. in the absence of the Hon. Colonial Secretary, Presiding 
     <lb/>
     Member. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On motion, the House resolved itself' into Committee of the Whole, to take into consideration 
     <lb/>
     the Message of His Excellency the Governor respecting the provision to be made for the sending. 
     <lb/>
     of Delegates to Ottawa. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Ball in the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>