<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgBCLC_1870-03-18" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgBCLC">British Columbia Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1870-03-18">18 March 1870</date>, Province of BC, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          <editor>W.S. Sebright Green</editor>
          
         
               <title>Legislative Council, Debate on the Subject of Confederation with Canada</title>.
                    

          <date when="1912"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Victoria, B.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>William H. Cullin</publisher>.
                    

          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="95" to="105"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_095.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_096.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_097.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_098.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_099.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_100.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_101.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_102.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_103.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_104.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_105.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-24">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_095">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_095.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_096">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_096.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_097">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_097.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_098">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_098.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_099">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_099.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_100">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_100.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_101">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_101.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_102">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_102.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_103">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_103.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_104">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_104.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_105">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_105.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="95" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_095.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">95</fw>
            
<!-- GL, 2017-03-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 


<!--<p>
     Hon. MR. DECOSMOS—l think we ought to fix a minimum number and keep to it, and 
     <lb/>
     a date, because I think that when the distrust wears away, British Columbia may be content 
     <lb/>
     with three in the Senate, and six in the House of Commons. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman put the recommendation of the Hon. Mr. Drake, to fill up the blank with 
     <lb/>
     the figures "91." Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman put the recommendation of the Hon. Mr. Wood—"That the number of 
     <lb/>
     members to the Commons should never be less than 8, and to the Senate never less than 4." 
     <lb/>
     Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Clause 13 was then passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Committee rose, and reported progress, and obtained leave to sit again on Friday at 
     <lb/>
     one o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     FRIDAY, MARCH 18TH, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">The Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I rise to move the adoption of
                  clause 14:- <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>"14. The Union shall take efffect on such day as Her Majesty by Order in Council (on 
     <lb/>
     "an Address to that effect, in terms of the 146th Section of 'The British North America 
     <lb/>
     " Act, 1867,') may direct: and British Columbia may, in such Address, specify the Districts, 
     <lb/>
     "Counties, or Divisions, if any, for which any of the four Senators to whom the Colony shall 
     <lb/>
     "be entitled shall be named, the Electoral Districts for which—and the time within which- <lb/> "the first Election of Members to serve in the House of Commons shall take place." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     These terms, or rather the terms which come back from Canada, will of necessity come 
     <lb/>
     before the new electoral body, whose existence His Excellency has shadowed forth, and the 
     <lb/>
     particulars as to the division into districts  must be left for the decision of that House. It is 
     <lb/>
     impossible at present to specify the time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. Mr. DECOSMOS</persName>—Cannot an approximate time be named?
                  Besides there are other <lb/> things upon which the country will want information;
                  such, for instance, as whether the <lb/> voting for members will be by ballot, and
                  what is to be the qualification of voters. I think it <lb/> ought to be fixed. The
                  Dominion law is more liberal than that to which the people of this <lb/> country
                  have been accustomed. I believe in the ballot, but it will be better to leave it
                  to the <lb/> constituencies. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—This clause has been left general,
                  that it may be settled <lb/> by the newly-constituted Council. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName>—If there is a qualification for the House
                  of Commons it must be <lb/> general for the whole Dominion. At present I believe
                  the qualification is that existing in the <lb/> Provinces before union. Ultimately
                  there must be a qualification for the whole Dominion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName>—There is no general law for qualification.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS</persName>—The clause is indefinite and dangerous.
                  The Dominion qualifica<lb break="no"/>tion will virtually disfranchise half the
                  British settlers in British Columbia. We are legislating <lb/> in the interests of
                  the people; this ought to be determined at once. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—I believe in British subjects, having a
                  fixed residence, and of a <lb/> certain age, voting in British Columbia. It should
                  be a residential manhood suffrage. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName>—We cannot deal with the subject now. It is
                  impossible to divide <lb/> the Colony into districts until we know how many
                  Senators we are to have. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK</persName>—Mr. Chairman, I move a recommendation to
                  strike out the words <lb/> "if any." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName>—I think the words ought to stand. The Organic
                  Act says that Senators <lb/> shall be selected for districts; but it may be
                  desirable that Senators should be appointed for <lb/> the whole Colony. They are
                  nominated, and nominated because they are the best men that <lb/> the Governor can
                  obtain. [No no, no—<persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. DeCosmos</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName></supplied> I believe the Executive are in the <lb/> best
                  position to know whether the principle of appointing Senators is best or whether
                  they <lb/> should go for the whole Colony. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName>—As this stands it throws the whole power
                  into the hands of the <lb/> Canadians. The Lieutenant-Governor will be a Canadian
                  and will name Canadians. We ought <lb/> to know by whom these appointments are to
                  be made. <lb/>
               </p>
            <pb n="96" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_096.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">96</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName>—It is a great pity that these sectional
                  differences should be allowed <lb/> to prevail. We ought to consider ourselves
                  British Colombians. The Governor-General, with <lb/> the consent of 'his Council,
                  appoints the Lieutenant-Governor, and the Lieutenant-Governor, <lb/> with the
                  advice of his Cabinet, recommends the Senators. [No, no—<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. Helmcken</persName>.] <lb/>
                  <supplied><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName></supplied> Yes, it is so. He recommends to the Governor-General, who appoints. It is a great
                  pity to <lb/> raise these disputes about Englishmen and Canadians. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS</persName>—It is all very well to talk that way. I
                  maintain that the English<lb break="no"/>men sitting at this table have said less
                  as to nationality than the Canadians. We want to be <lb/> governed by British
                  Columbians. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName>—We had better drop these nationalities.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName>—The Hon. Member for New Westminster should not
                  be angry because <lb/> we want to provide against the possibility of ill-feeling
                  by timely precaution. " Safe bind, safe <lb/> find." When the Governor-General
                  appoints Senators, it i understand it right, he appoints <lb/> the political
                  friends of his Cabinet. If we are to have Responsible Government there will <lb/>
                  always be some check; if not we may be in the position of having members selected
                  by the <lb/> Lieutenant-Governor without the assistance of any responsible
                  Cabinet. [Hear, hear—Hon. <lb/> <persName ref="pers:DECO1">DeCosmos</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName></supplied> A Canadian Lieutenant-Governor will act
                  with the same sort of feeling that the <lb/> English Government will. Senators
                  will be selected by favouritism, and supporters of Confed<lb break="no"/>eration
                  will doubtless be selected in this Colony, unless we have Responsible Government
                  and <lb/> Representative Institutions in full vigor. Canadian interests will
                  doubtless be very prominent <lb/> in this Colony, and power acts injuriously on
                  the human mind—it is one of the corruptors of <lb/> the mind. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I should be very sorry to see the words
                  " if any " struck out ; <lb/> their retention leaves the matter open. Hon. Members
                  seem to have forgotten that Senators <lb/> must be residents of British Columbia.
                  Probably they may be selected on the ground of their <lb/> having an appreciation
                  of the whole country, instead of a section only. It may be that Senators <lb/>
                  will be appointed for the whole Colony. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK</persName>—After hearing the explanations of the Hon.
                  Attorney-General, <lb/> I feel more desirous to press my recommendations, to show
                  that we from the Mainland desire <lb/> to have our fair share of representation. I
                  think the words most objectionable. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. Mr. DECOSMOS</persName>—I find by the Resolutions passed at the
                  Conference of Delegates. <lb/> in London, that Senators were to be taken from the
                  Legislative Council. We are told by the <lb/> Government that we are to go into
                  Confederation without Responsible Government; then we <lb/> ought to have a
                  guarantee that the first Senators shall be representative men, and that they <lb/>
                  shall not be chosen by the Governor and put into office for life without reference
                  to the people. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS</persName>—I shall move a recommendation that the
                  first Senators shall be <lb/> nominated by the Legislature.   <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName>—The position will be worth $600. The
                  difficulty will be to get <lb/> anyone to go there. People are chary of going into
                  the Legislative Council now, and they will <lb/> not be very anxious to go to
                  Canada. As to choosing Senators from one place, it is out of the <lb/> question.
                  And it is equally out of the question to appoint them by the Legislative Council.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS</persName>—We are here as the agents of the people,
                  delegates in point <lb/> of fact, and we are bound to legislate in accordance with
                  the well understood wishes of the <lb/> people. In reference to having these
                  Senators appointed, we are bound to see what they are <lb/> and whether the people
                  are likely to approve of our acts. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—Hon. Members must remember that these
                  Resolutions will <lb/> be submitted to the people, a much-abused term, as the Hon.
                  Member for Victoria District has <lb/> truly said, and our common object must be
                  to make the terms acceptable to the people. They <lb/> will have to pass upon them
                  in the last resort, and to say we will or we will not have them. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:PEMB1">Hon. Mr. PEMBERTON</persName>—The objection seems to me to be to
                  dividing British Columbia <lb/> into districts. It is a qualification for Senators
                  that they must reside in their districts; there<lb break="no"/>fore, I think it
                  will not be desirable to divide the Colony into districts. 1 think the clause
                  <lb/> should stand as it is. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—One matter deserves attention in connection
                  with this item. I believe <lb/> that the indemnity to Senators is $600 in a lump
                  sum, without travelling expenses. I think <lb/> it is now commuted, and this would
                  place British Columbia Senators at a disadvantage with <lb/> other It is no
                  hardship to other Provinces, but would be most unfair to British Columbia. <lb/>
                  Travelling expenses both ways should be allowed. <lb/>
               </p>
            <pb n="97" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_097.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">97</fw>
            

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—My conviction is that mileage is now
                  allowed. If I am <lb/> right, ten cents a mile both ways is allowed. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName>—It is the prerogative of the Governor; we
                  had better vote for the <lb/> repeal of the Organic Act, <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—Under the proposed constitution Senators
                  would be chosen by an <lb/> irresponsible Governor, on the advice of an
                  irresponsible Minister. Those who own this country <lb/> do not want such a state
                  of things to be.   <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName>—It is better to bear in mind that the Organic
                  Act applies to three, or <lb/> at the most four, Provinces: Canada East, Canada
                  West, and the Maritime Provinces. Here <lb/> we want exceptional terms. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—Hon. Members seem to assume that we are going
                  to enter Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion without Responsible Government. This I
                  repudiate. I say we shall enter with privileges <lb/> equal to other Provinces I
                  decline to assume anything else, With regard to the appointment <lb/> of Senators
                  by the Legislative Council, I would ask by what Council? By this or by the new
                  <lb/> House? It would not satisfy the people that a Council nominated by the
                  Governor should <lb/> appoint; and it is yet to be seen that the new House, as
                  shadowed forth by the Governor, <lb/> would be less objectionable than this one.
                  We are entirely in the dark. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName>—As I understand it, these Senators are to
                  be appointed after <lb/> Confederation, and consequently the recommendation refers
                  to the new Council. His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency that he will give a majority to
                  the popular members, and I have no doubt he means <lb/> what he says. I believe
                  him to be a most estimable gentleman; but I have a feeling that he <lb/> has been
                  misled. It is not likely that in a few weeks' travel he could understand the wants
                  <lb/> and feelings of the people. You must eat, drink, and sleep among them to
                  understand a people. <lb/> If I were a great Government contractor I would support
                  the Government. I ask some reason <lb/> of rank. It would be very easy to give us
                  a majority of two or three popular members; but <lb/> unless we have a large
                  majority of representative members the Government might still get <lb/> their own
                  way. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>-I desire, Mr. Chairman, to answer two points.
                  I believe we shall <lb/> fight for and have Responsible Government. In referring
                  to the Governor's speech, the Hon. <lb/> Member for Lillooet says the new Council
                  will be just similar to this; that it will still be <lb/> unrepresentative. I
                  cannot see why there should be this doubt about the constitution of the <lb/> new
                  Council. If there were to be only a majority of two or three the Council would
                  still be <lb/> unrepresentative; and the people will not be contented with such a
                  form of Government. The <lb/> argument of the Hon. Member for Lillooet refutes
                  itself in the most conclusive way. The people <lb/> do not want an
                  unrepresentative House not having their confidence to elect their Senators. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName>—What have we to do with the Organic Act? Why
                  should we put ourselves <lb/> under the iron points of the Organic Act, and be
                  dragged under a barrow all the days of our <lb/> lives? If the Act is wrong it
                  must be repealed. Now is the time to express our opinion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman put the recommendation of Mr. Humphreys, which on division was lost, and 
     <lb/>
     of Mr. Robson, which on division was lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Clause 14 passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY—GENERAL</persName>—Sir, I rise to move the adoption of
                  clause fifteen, which <lb/> is as follows:- <lb/>
               </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"15. The constitution of the Executive authority and of the Legislature of British Columbia, 
     <lb/>"shall, subject to 'The British North America Act, 1867,' continue as existing at the time of 
     <lb/>"union, until altered under the authority of the Act." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     And before touching upon the merits of the Resolution itself. I wish to explain that the 
     <lb/>
     time which must necessarily elapse before Confederation will allow ample opportunity to 
     <lb/>
     procure a change in the Constitution and I desire to impress upon Hon. Members that this 
     <lb/>
     question of alteration in the form of Government is not necessarily connected with the Resolu<lb break="no"/>tion now before the House. I make these observations in consequence of observing a notice of 
     <lb/>
     the Hon. Member for Lillooet, on the subject of Responsible Government, on the Orders of the 
     <lb/>
     Day. On behalf of the Government, I desire to say that there is no desire whatever to shirk 
     <lb/>
     the full discussion of the question of Responsible Government. I throw the door open and 
     <lb/>
     invite the fullest discussion; but, as the question of the change of the Constitution of this 
     <lb/>
     Colony is one that lies between this Colony and the imperial Government, it does not form an 
     <lb/>
     item in these Resolutions. Therefore, I would ask Hon. Members to postpone the consideration 
     <lb/>
           

          
            <pb n="98" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_098.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">98</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
          

     of Responsible Government and pass these Resolutions. On a question of such importance, 
     <lb/>
     a special day, irrespective of these Resolutions, should be set apart for discussion. There is 
     <lb/>
     no desire whatever on the part of the Government to shirk the question. The matter of 
     <lb/>
     the Constitution is under negotiation between this Colony and the Imperial Government at 
     <lb/>
     this moment. Supposing these Resolutions are passed, other negotiations must take place. 
     <lb/>
     First, Canada has to accept them; then there is reference back to British Columbia to submit 
     <lb/>
     to the popular vote, so that there will be full time allowed for the new institutions to be 
     <lb/>
     inaugurated. If the people say that they do not want the terms, but that they want Responsible 
     <lb/>
     Government, they will undoubtedly get it. I cannot conceive our going into Confederation 
     <lb/>
     with a Crown Council; we must expect to go in with fuller Representative Institutions. If 
     <lb/>
     we do not have Confederation under these terms, we shall, nevertheless, have Representative 
     <lb/>
     Institutions; and a majority, under the Imperial Act, will have the power to change and get 
     <lb/>
     Responsible Government,— that is, party government. My point is, that it is unnecessary to 
     <lb/>
     drag in Responsible Government now; it is not necessary to mix it up with these Resolutions. 
     <lb/>
     Our vote on this Resolution need not be decided on Responsible Government, or party govern<lb break="no"/>ment. We shall still be open to send any other Resolution on the subject of party government 
     <lb/>
     to the Governor. I, therefore, throw out the invitation to discuss it more fully on a future 
     <lb/>
     day. I feel sure that it this course is adopted the discussion will be more free. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName>—I think, Sir, that His Excellency's message, it
                  I may so call these <lb/> Resolutions, invites us to discuss Responsible
                  Government. Sir, we have been in former days <lb/> favoured with Representative
                  Institutions, and have been defrauded by them. I desire to <lb/> know what we have
                  gained by the Irresponsible Government that has for some years past <lb/>
                  oppressed us. What, I ask, has been done about the various questions that have
                  come up- <lb/> the Sisters' Rocks, the Court of Appeal? The answer has been no
                  funds. Where do the funds <lb/> come from? From the people. If the Governor heard
                  the views of the people, he might, <lb/> perhaps, change his views. I ask Hon.
                  Members here, who have lived under Responsible <lb/> Government in Great Britain,
                  [Hear, hear, from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DeCosmos</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName></supplied> not to be recreant to their <lb/> country. Hon.
                  Members on the other side may say they are against Responsible Government <lb/>
                  and refer to a former House of Assembly of Vancouver Island. This is no argument.
                  I trust <lb/> that Hon. Members loving British institutions will be true to their
                  country. Because there are <lb/> defects in some Assemblies, do not let us run
                  into the abject error of saying we are not fit for <lb/> self-government. We have
                  borne this too long. Do not let us hand over to Canada our consent <lb/> to submit
                  to this degradation. Let us not say that we are not fit; that we surrender the
                  <lb/> question of self-government. Who, I ask, has examined the people? Who has
                  tried them and <lb/> discovered whether or not they are competent to exercise the
                  privileges of Responsible Govern <lb/> ment? There are many points in this clause
                  which demand discussion, but I am not going to <lb/> exhaust myself. I say,
                  however, that the question of Responsible Government must be con<lb break="no"/>sidered. I throw the gauntlet down. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName>—Mr. Chairman, as mover of the Resolution
                  on Responsible <lb/> Government, I do not think it necessary to take up the time
                  of the House. I am perfectly <lb/> satisfied in my own mind that the official
                  members are convinced that the people are in favour <lb/> of Responsible
                  Government. As a student of history, young as I am, I begin to realize this <lb/>
                  truth: that all liberty and improvement has been infused into communities by the
                  shock of <lb/> revolution. or violent agitation. There is no hope of political
                  improvement in time of tran<lb break="no"/>quillity and without agitation. The
                  official members of this Council are remarkable for their <lb/> profound
                  indifference to right and wrong. It is in their interest to postpone the
                  settlement <lb/> of this question of Responsible Government. I hold that there is
                  a great necessity for this <lb/> Resolution. The question ought to be settled now
                  and for ever. Why should we be com<lb break="no"/>pelled, year after year, to
                  fight those battles for reform over and over again? Let this question <lb/> be
                  settled so that we may have leisure for other things. Hon. gentlemen say the
                  people are not <lb/> in favour of Responsible Government. Time will show. I say
                  that they will almost as a unit <lb/> insist upon it, and I lay down this
                  proposition—no Responsible Government, no Confederation; <lb/> no Confederation,
                  no pensions. Instead of t liteniug the Governmental reins they should be <lb/>
                  slackened. If Responsible Government is not granted these officials will still
                  lose their power; <lb/> for then, in all probability, a mightier nation than
                  Canada will take charge of us. I am in <lb/> favour of Confederation if it gives
                  us permanent advantages, not otherwise. We must have a <lb/> free constitution. My
                  conscience tells me that my votes on these Resolutions are not prompted <lb/>
                  <pb n="99" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_099.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">99</fw> by selfish motives. If the people get Responsible
                  Government I am satisfied. His Excellency <lb/> admits that he would not like to
                  extend the liberal form of Government to this Colony. My <lb/> opinion is that
                  there is no community unfit to govern themselves. Government is not a com<lb break="no"/>plicated machine, There is very little difference between carrying
                  on a Government and carrying <lb/> on a business. One-half of the depression in
                  this Colony is, in my opinion, attributable to the <lb/> despotic form of
                  government. Just fancy the head of a mercantile house allowing his clerks to <lb/>
                  carry on the whole business of the firm as they pleased. [Hear, hear, from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr.
                  DeCosmos</persName>.] <lb/> <supplied><persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName></supplied> without Responsible Government you will lose Confederation. It is
                  not necessary to say any <lb/> more. Let us have something like the Government of
                  Ontario. Those whom I have the honour <lb/> to represent sent me here to advocate
                  Responsible Government. I will read from a petition now <lb/> in my hands. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—This is out of order. I rise to call
                  the Hon. Member to <lb/> order. This is not the time to present a petition. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—The Hon. Member has a right to read from it.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">CHAIRMAN</persName>—The Hon. Member cannot read from a petition which
                  has not been presented <lb/> to and received by this House. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—Mr. Chairman, I request that you will be
                  careful in ruling on this <lb/> matter. Hon. Members have the right to read from
                  documents to show the views of their <lb/> constituents. It is alluded to as the
                  best means of acquainting the House with the views of <lb/> the constituency which
                  the Hon. Member represents. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—On the other hand, I would say that the
                  right of petitioners <lb/> must be respected; and if Hon. Members are allowed to
                  read petitions, then petitions can be got <lb/> in by a side wind. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—In my opinion the Hon. Member has a right to
                  read from a document <lb/> of this kind.   <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName>—Having looked at this document I see it is
                  not a petition to this <lb/> House, and may therefore be quoted. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The CHAIRMAN</persName>, having looked at the document, decided that it
                  might be quoted. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> then read a portion of the prayer of the
                  petition, which purported <lb/> to be to Her Majesty the Queen. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—The Honourable and learned Attorney-General
                  has appealed to those <lb/> Honourable Members who are in favour of Responsible
                  Government to postpone the question for <lb/> the present. I should be glad to
                  accede to the request it the Honourable and learned gentleman <lb/> will meet the
                  objections that present themselves to my mind as to that course. In my opinion,
                  <lb/> to vote for this section now will preclude the possibility of our bringing
                  on the subject of <lb/> Responsible Government in the House this Session. We shall
                  be met with the assertion that <lb/> it has been already discussed and decided for
                  this Session. I am quite sure the Honourable and <lb/> learned Attorney-General
                  does not wish to catch us in a trap. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—Certainly not. As Honourable Members
                  have insisted upon <lb/> opening the question, I now propose to go on with the
                  discussion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName>—I am most anxious to meet the views of the
                  Government in this matter, <lb/> it possible; but, we are asked to vote aye or no
                  upon this clause, I say that in voting for it <lb/> we shall be casting our votes
                  in direct opposition to Responsible Government. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—The discussion must go on now. You have
                  begun; it is too <lb/> late to withdraw. The lists are closed, and the gang of
                  battle down. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—Mr. Chairman, I will address myself to the
                  question before the House, <lb/> which I feel to be the most important clause in
                  these terms; a question, in fact, which underlies <lb/> the peace. prosperity, and
                  happiness of British Columbia; a question which, if carelessly or <lb/> improperly
                  treated now, may eventuate in the most serious consequences to the Colony; for I
                  <lb/> believe the people are as ready now as in earlier days to fight for freedom,
                  and to shed their <lb/> blood in defence of their political rights. It becomes us,
                  then, to be candid with ourselves and <lb/> with each other—very serious, firm,
                  and dispassionate in discussing this clause, as it might <lb/> result in most
                  disastrous consequences. As I read the clause, it places it beyond the power <lb/>
                  of the colonists to obtain the form of Government which they, I believe, really
                  want; and <lb/> it we pass it we shall obtain no more than that slightly more
                  liberal form which is fore<lb break="no"/>shadowed in His Excellency's Speech,
                  under the cover of Representative Government. Pro<lb break="no"/>foundly impressed
                  as I am with the gravity of the subject we are now called upon to consider, <lb/>
                  <pb n="100" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_100.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">100</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> any remarks I may be enabled to
                  offer will proceed rather from a sense of duty to my con<lb break="no"/>stituents
                  and to my country than from any hope of changing the views or influencing the vote
                  of <lb/> any Honourable Member. What is Responsible Government? I have been led to
                  believe that <lb/> considerable confusion of ideas exists upon this point; and I
                  was the more impressed with this <lb/> upon listening to the remarks ot the
                  Honourable Member for Cariboo, a few days ago. That <lb/> Honourable gentleman
                  compared the introduction of Responsible Government into this Colony <lb/> to
                  applying the machinery of the Great Eastern to a dairy churn. Now, Sir,
                  Responsible <lb/> Government is not a quantity; it is a principle; and as such it
                  is applicable to the Great Eastern   <lb/> or to a dairy churn,—capable of being
                  applied to a tiny lady's watch. It is a principle <lb/> admirably adapted to the
                  largest communities in the Old World. It is a principle admirably <lb/> adapted to
                  the smallest communities in the New World. It is a principle that may be worked
                  <lb/> out in a cabinet of a hundred. It is a principle which may be successfully
                  worked out in <lb/> a cabinet of three. Without it no Government can, in the true
                  sense, be called a people's <lb/> Government. All true Governments derive their
                  power from the people. All true Govern<lb break="no"/>ments must be responsible to
                  the people. Responsible Government is, then, a principle which <lb/> may be
                  adapted to, and successfully worked out in, this community. If this proposition is
                  <lb/> incontrovertible, which I maintain it is. who can say that British Columbia
                  is not large <lb/> enough for Responsible Government? There are men here of
                  ability to form a Cabinet. The <lb/> Cabinet of the day is, under the responsible
                  system, the Government, just so long as it has the <lb/> confidence of a majority
                  of the representatives of the people in the House. In the event of <lb/> that
                  confidence being lost. one of two courses is open: The Ministers place their
                  resignation <lb/> in the hands of the Governor who commonly calls upon a prominent
                  member of the opposition <lb/> to form a Ministry; or, it they believe that the
                  House does not truly represent the people <lb/> upon the question at issue, they
                  advise a dissolution and an appeal to the country. What <lb/> would Responsible
                  Government have to do here? In dealing with this question I, of course, <lb/>
                  assume British Columbia to be a Province of the Dominion; and, I confess, that
                  were it <lb/> otherwise, were it proposed to remain a separate Colony, the case
                  would be different. I do <lb/> not say that even then I would not advocate the
                  introduction of Responsible Government, <lb/> but that advocacy might be less
                  hearty and less firm. Regarding British Columbia as a <lb/> Province of the
                  Dominion, the chief objections are removed by the removal to Ottawa of all <lb/>
                  those larger and more complex questions of legislation which might threaten to
                  crack the brain <lb/> of our embryo statesmen. The Local Government would alone
                  have to deal with local questions, <lb/> and thus it would have very simple duties
                  to discharge—scarcely more difficult, in fact, than <lb/> those falling within the
                  functions of a large municipality in Canada. Are the people in British <lb/>
                  Columbia fit for it? And here I would express my sincere regret that the
                  representative of <lb/> Her Majesty in this Colony has felt it to be his duty to
                  pronounce an adverse opinion. I will <lb/> yield to no one, either in this House
                  or out of it, in entertaining a high respect for His Excellency, <lb/> for his
                  talent, experience, and honesty of purpose; but I do say,—and I say it with
                  respect, <lb/> more in sorrow than in anger—that I cannot think his knowledge of
                  the people of this Colony <lb/> was such as to justify him in so early pronouncing
                  upon their fitness for self-government. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> — The Honourable Member for New
                  Westminster will, I am <lb/> sure. pardon the interruption but I feel it to be my
                  duty to deny that the Governor ever said, <lb/> or that any member of the
                  Government has said or thought. that the people of British Columbia <lb/> are
                  unfit for self-government. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—I thank the honourable and learned
                  Attorney-General, and I appreciate <lb/> his motives. There is no one less
                  disposed than myself to speak or write one word calculated <lb/> to weaken the
                  hands of the Government, or cause the well-deserved popularity of His Excellency
                  <lb/> to wane; but yet I cannot conceal from myself the fact that a mere play upon
                  words will not <lb/> mend matters. Whether it is the Colony or its inhabitants
                  that has been pronounced unfit for <lb/> self-government, the practical results
                  remain the same: and it is with these we alone are con<lb break="no"/>cerned. From
                  my own knowledge of the people. and it is the result of eleven years' contact
                  <lb/> with them, I have no hesitation in saying they are pre-eminently fitted for
                  self-government. <lb/> There are scores of men in this country with calloused
                  palms and patched garments, well fitted <lb/> by natural endowments, education,
                  and practical experience in the working of Responsible <lb/> Government in other
                  Colonies, to occupy seats either in the Legislative Assmbly or in the <lb/>
                  Cabinet of British Columbia. He who would judge of the intelligence and mental
                  acquirements <lb/> of men in this Colony by outward appearance and by present
                  occupation, certainly would not   <lb/> judge righteous judgment. The opinion of
                  His Excellency the Governor to the contrary not<lb break="no"/><pb n="101" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_101.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">101</fw>withstanding, I boldly assert that the people of British
                  Columbia are fit for Responsible <lb/> Government. Do they want it? Doubtless
                  there are those in this House, possibly even in <lb/> the unofficial ranks, who
                  will deny that the people of British Columbia really desire to have <lb/>
                  Responsible Government under Confederation. It is sometimes difficult to account
                  for diver<lb break="no"/>gence of opinion; but I venture to think that I have the
                  weight of both argument and evidence <lb/> on my side when I assert, as I do, that
                  the great body of the people—certainly an overwhelming <lb/> majority—do earnestly
                  and intelligently desire that form of government. It is difficult to believe <lb/>
                  that any man who has given due thought to the subject can possibly hesitate. Look
                  at the <lb/> position this Colony would occupy under Confederation, without the
                  full control of its own <lb/> affairs—a condition alone attainable by means of
                  Responsible Government While the other <lb/> Provinces only surrender Federal
                  questions to the Central Government, we would surrender <hi rendition="simple:italic">all</hi>. <lb/> While the other Provinces with which
                  it is proposed to confederate upon equal and equitable <lb/> terms retain the
                  fullest power to manage all Provincial matters, British Columbia would <lb/>
                  surrender that power. Her local as well as her national affairs would virtually be
                  managed <lb/> at Ottawa. Could a union so unequal be a happy and enduring one? The
                  compact we are <lb/> about to form is for <hi rendition="simple:italic">life</hi>.
                  Shall we take into it the germ of discord and disruption? The <lb/> people desire
                  change; but they have no desire to exchange the Imperial heel for the Canadian
                  <lb/> heel. They desire political manumission. I stand here, and, in the name of
                  my ancestors, <lb/> protest before Heaven against the surrender of constitutional
                  rights purchased by the best <lb/> blood of our race—a priceless legacy we have no
                  right to barter away, even if we would. We <lb/> owe it to our ancestors to
                  preserve entire those rights which they have delivered to our care. <lb/> We owe
                  it to posterity not to suffer their dearest inheritance to be destroyed But, if it
                  were <lb/> possible for us to be insensible of these sacred claims, there is yet
                  an obligation binding upon <lb/> ourselves, from which nothing can acquit us; a
                  personal interest which we cannot surrender. <lb/> To alienate even our own rights
                  would he a crime as much more enormous than suicide, as a <lb/> life of civil
                  security and political freedom is superior to a condition of serfdom; and if life
                  be <lb/> the bounty of Heaven, we scornfully reject the noblest part of the gift
                  if we consent to surrender <lb/> that certain rule of living, and those
                  constitutional rights, without which the condition of human <lb/> nature is not
                  only miserable but contemptible. I know but too well that the people of this <lb/>
                  Colony have, during these years past, been unjustly and unconstitutionally
                  deprived of their <lb/> rights; but the perpetration of a wrong in the past can
                  constitute no argument for perpetrating <lb/> that wrong in the future; and it
                  would appear a most fitting moment, when a new constitution <lb/> is about to be
                  offered, to demand the full restoration of political rights of which we have been
                  <lb/> for some time so unjustly deprived. A word about the constitution which the
                  Governor proposes <lb/> to confer upon this Colony. Regarding it in the dim light
                  shed upon it by the Executive, it <lb/> is not unfair to assume that there will be
                  one more popular Member taken into the Executive, <lb/> and that the people will
                  have a majority of two in the Legislature. Let us suppose that the <lb/>
                  Legislative Council has 20 Members, 11 elected by the people and 9 appointed by
                  the Governor. <lb/> Three are taken from the 11 into the mysterious chamber of the
                  Executive, where they become <lb/> —I will not say corrupted—manipulated; educated
                  to see things somewhat differently from what <lb/> they saw them before. In a
                  House so constituted, is it unfair, is it uncharitable to conclude <lb/>   that,
                  on all Government measures at least, the Government would command a majority? Take
                  <lb/> 3 from 11, and 8 remain. Take 8 from 20, and how many remain to the
                  Government? Is <lb/> it not 12? Where, then, is the people's majority under the
                  proposed constitution? And yet I <lb/> am constantly told that this is not the
                  proper time to ask for Responsible Govermnent—that <lb/> if the people want it
                  they will possess, under the new constitution, the ready means of obtaining <lb/>
                  it. Sir. I do not see the matter in that light. I see in the proposed constitution
                  a condition of <lb/> things which promises a five years', possibly a ten years',
                  agitation for what the people are <lb/> prepared for now, desire now, are entitled
                  to now. All Governments are naturally conservative. <lb/> All persons holding
                  positions of honour, power. or emolument, are conservative. Think you <lb/> those
                  holding office by appointment will favour or promote a change which would make
                  them <lb/> responsible to the people—exchange their commission from the Crown for
                  the more brittle <lb/> tenure of "public opinion "? On the contrary, we should
                  find those in power opposed to the <lb/> people in their struggle for Responsible
                  Government; and how long the struggle might last, it <lb/> would be idle to
                  predict. Besides, the people of Canada do not desire to see British Columbia <lb/>
                  occupying any such false position. They know too well the value of free
                  institutions, and their <lb/> adaptation to new countries, to think of withholding
                  them from us. These institutions were <lb/> not won without a long and bloody
                  struggle, even in Canada; and the prosperity and content<lb break="no"/><pb n="102" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_102.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">102</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>ment of that people date from the
                  inauguration of Responsible Government. The failure of <lb/> representative
                  institutions, formerly enjoyed upon this Island, is frequently cited as an
                  argument <lb/> against Responsible Government being introduced here. I admit the
                  partial failure of these <lb/> institutions. That failure was not, however, on
                  account of the institutions being " representa<lb break="no"/>tive," but because
                  they were not "responsible" The essential principle was wanting. There <lb/> was
                  no constitutional connecting link—no bond of sympathy between those who sat by the
                  will <lb/> of the people and those who sat contrary to, and in defiance of, that
                  will. The system, painted, <lb/> though it was, in popular dress, was rotten at
                  the core—proved a delusion and a sham. The <lb/> people, sometimes in indifference
                  and contempt, permitted unsuitable men to be elected, and the <lb/> whole thing,
                  came to rack and ruin. It is to avoid a repetition of that unseemly farce that the
                  <lb/> people demand that any new constitution which may be conferred upon this
                  Colony shall be <lb/> based upon the only true principle of responsibility. This
                  question should be finally settled. <lb/> The Colony desires political rest. To
                  inaugurate a fresh political agitation with Union is most <lb/> undesirable, and
                  might lead to disastrous results. The possible consequences of a refusal to <lb/>
                  grant Responsible Government coincident with Confederation, is a part of the
                  subject I almost <lb/> hesitate to touch. I would neither prophecy, predict, nor
                  threaten; but I would ask the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to read well and
                  carefully the lessons written in blood in other countries Human nature <lb/> is
                  much the same on both sides of this great continent. Has the Anglo-Saxon race
                  become so <lb/> utterly degenerate here that it is prepared to barter away for
                  mere money subsidies those rights <lb/> which were purchased with so much blood
                  elsewhere? I utterly refuse to think so meanly of <lb/> this people. We have seen
                  that even the half-breeds at Red River have too much of the old <lb/> blood in
                  their veins to permit a fancied political wrong. I am not going to predict a
                  rebellion <lb/> here. Heaven grant there may be none. But I do feel it my duty to
                  warn the Government <lb/> against unnecessarily provoking such a possible
                  contingency. Why should there be such an <lb/> unaccountable antipathy to
                  investing the people of British Columbia with those political powers <lb/> enjoyed
                  under the British Constitution? Why is the present form of Government so unpopular
                  <lb/> with the people? I will tell you why. It is just because it is not a
                  people's Government. They <lb/> had no hand in making it. They had none in working
                  it. They can have none in unmaking it. <lb/> Only let the people have a hand in
                  forming the Government, in selecting men of their own choice <lb/> to rule over
                  them, and we would find a popular Government, a strong Government, strong in <lb/>
                  the heart and confidence of the people. The very same gentlemen who are unpopular
                  now, <lb/> because ruling without the consent of the people, would be popular
                  then, because ruling by <lb/> the act and with the consent of the people. The
                  people of British Columbia are naturally a <lb/> conservative people. Restore to
                  them their political rights, and no Government would need to <lb/> fear an undue
                  desire for change. The people know best how to manage their own local affairs.
                  <lb/> Depend upon it, Sir, the people are seldom wrong in their opinions; in their
                  sentiments they <lb/> are never mistaken. Those now in power have a great
                  responsibility resting upon them. Upon <lb/> the manner in which they acquit
                  themselves in regard to this very question may hang the most <lb/> momentous
                  consequences. Will they promote everlasting wellbeing, or precipitate untold evil?
                  <lb/> Heaven grant that they may do the right! I stand here today to advise and
                  warn, not to <lb/> threaten and predict. The Government has a very grave
                  responsibility in this matter, and may <lb/> well take a lesson from other
                  countries. The possible consequence of a refusal to grant a   <lb/> reasonable
                  request may be a repetition of the Red River trouble. Let not the Government <lb/>
                  make a fatal mistake, or they may find themselves in a state of political
                  agitation that may <lb/> lead to the most serious consequences. I believe that,
                  under circumstances analogous to what <lb/> occurred in the Red River Territory,
                  the Imperial Government would treat the inhabitants of <lb/> this Colony with even
                  more consideration. It would not be a question of bayonets and fleets <lb/> to
                  coerce this Colony, but it would be a question of what concessions ought to be
                  made. I say <lb/> that the Government have an opportunity now not only of shunning
                  evil, but of doing a great <lb/> work. Oh! let not the Government make the fatal
                  mistake of saying the people shall not <lb/> manage their own affairs Do not let
                  them make the fatal mistake of compelling the people <lb/> to reject these
                  conditions at the polls. Now I have discharged a duty; I have said all I feel
                  <lb/> called upon to say at this stage. I have stated my own views and, I venture
                  to think, those <lb/> of an overwhelming majority of the people of British
                  Columbia, as well as of my own con<lb break="no"/>stituents. I trust the
                  Government will take care how they force a vote on this question, which <lb/>
                  affects this whole community , [" Hear, hear."] This is, in a sense, distinct from
                  the conditions, <lb/> and it is probable that the Governor must obtain what we are
                  now asking from a different <lb/> quarter. But, obtain it from where he will, it
                     <hi rendition="simple:italic">must</hi>, I say, be obtained. <lb/>
               </p>
   
           
            <pb n="103" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_103.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">103</fw>
            <p>
     I beg to move the following amendment, as meeting the case more fully than the resolution 
     <lb/>
     offered by the Hon. Member for Lillooet :- <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"Whereas no union can be either acceptable or satisfactory which does not confer upon the 
     <lb/>
     people of British Columbia as full control over their own local affairs as is enjoyed in the other 
     <lb/>
     Provinces with which it is proposed to confederate; therefore, be it 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Resolved, That an humble address be presented to His Excellency the Governor, earnestly 
     <lb/>
     recommending that a Constitution based upon the principle of Responsible Government, as 
     <lb/>
     existing in the Province of Ontario, may be conferred upon this Colony, coincident with its 
     <lb/>
     admission into the Dominion of Canada." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—Allow me to observe on this, that the
                  Hon. Member is asking <lb/> the Government to grant what it has no power to give.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—The Governor has promised to seek the power
                  to grant us a new <lb/> Constitution. We only ask that in that new Constitution we
                  may have Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—Mr. Chairman I do not intend to occupy the
                  House for many <lb/> minutes. I agree with the Hon. Member for Lillooet, and I
                  disagree with the Hon. Member <lb/> for New Westminster. I think, Sir, that we
                  ought to have representative institutions and <lb/> Responsible Government,
                  irrespective of Confederation. The Hon. Member for New West<lb break="no"/>minster's proposition unites it with Confederation. I think this is a mistake;
                  but it is of no <lb/> matter, so long as we get it. I look upon British Columbia
                  as a municipality under the British <lb/> Crown. Under Canada it will be a
                  municipality with less power. Anyone who knows anything <lb/> of municipal law
                  knows that it is based upon three principles: territory, authority, and respon<lb break="no"/>sibility. This Colony has the first two, and we are now asking for
                  the third. and the terms <lb/> sent down to the Council do not contain the
                  elements of responsibility of the Executive to the <lb/> people. Everything is
                  tending to this point. Without responsibility, no matter how elective <lb/> the
                  new Council is, it will be a failure. The people want Responsible Government and
                     repre<lb break="no"/>sentative institutions under 'any circumstances. I think
                  the people would be traitors to <lb/> themselves if they accepted any form of
                  Government which had not the element of respon<lb break="no"/>sibility. I would
                  rebel if there were enough like me in the Colony, and arrest every member <lb/> of
                  the Government that I thought was robbing me of my rights. I would go to a further
                  <lb/> extreme. However, I shall not trouble the House with a long speech on this
                  matter, as I <lb/> consider it of little use. This question ended, I am contented
                  to leave this Council and go to <lb/> my constituents, <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName>—Mr. Chairman, I should like to ask what all
                  this breeze is about? <lb/> It is perfectly clear to all that as soon as we enter
                  the Confederacy the people of this country <lb/> can have any form of Government
                  they desire. I refuse to take up the issue without Con<lb break="no"/>federation,
                  in a state of isolation. We are dealing with Confederation. I am, equally with
                  <lb/> the Hon. Member for New Westminster, aware of the priceless boon of
                  responsibility which <lb/> exists in England, which may fairly be called the
                  standard-bearer of nations, and I am equally <lb/> aware that the same
                  responsibility does not exist in the Unitcd States. During the late war <lb/> I
                  was in the United States army. Stanton, the then Secretary of War, was a most
                  unpopular <lb/> man. They wanted to get rid of him, but he could not be removed.
                  When I took the ground <lb/> that Responsible Government was not expedient. it was
                  not because I did not approve of the <lb/> system. It is I say, the wisest and
                  best form of Government, but it is too cumbrous for this <lb/> Colony. I will
                  repeat my objections: The Council contains no men of influence, the con<lb break="no"/>stituencies are too remote, and the inhabitants are all engaged in
                  bread-seeking; there are few <lb/> men of independent means who would take part in
                  Responsible Government, and, consequently, <lb/> the direction of public affairs
                  would fall into the hands of men who are not fitted, or qualified <lb/> to govern
                  the country, or otherwise into the hands of Victorians; neither of which I, for
                  one, <lb/> wish to see. How unfortunate it would be for Caribooites if the Hon.
                  senior Member for <lb/> Victoria (Dr. Helmcken) were elected for Cariboo. I say,
                  then. that it must fall into bad <lb/> hands. or into the hands of Victorians. I
                  offer that argument as a British Columbian. The <lb/> Executive Council do not
                  care one fig what sort of Government the people take. The Executive <lb/> say the
                  question is one for the people to decide. We have a measure of responsib y now.
                  <lb/> The Hon. Member for New Westminster says that His Excellency will do certain
                  things. I <lb/> take his speech as it reads, and I have no doubt that a majority
                  of the people's representatives <lb/> will sit round the board; none know how
                  great the majority will be. [<persName ref="pers:CREA1">Attorney-General</persName>—"Hear, <lb/>
                  <pb n="104" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_104.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">104</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> hear."] <supplied><persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName></supplied> Responsible Government has
                  never been made a distinct issue throughout the Colony. <lb/> [" It has "—<persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr.
                  DeCosmos</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName></supplied> The Hon. Member says that it has; I say it has not. It has <lb/> been
                  named with Confederation, but not by itself; and until it is made a separate
                  question, <lb/> my advice to the Governor will be not to grant it. The Governor
                  has left you to choose any <lb/> Government you deem best. Do you think it would
                  be better to have as permanent heads of <lb/> departments two or three gentlemen
                  who are familiar with the wants of the Colony, or a <lb/> moveable Ministry going
                  out on a question of repairs to Cowichan Road, or something of that. <lb/> kind?
                  These are amongst the things that you have to consider, and if, after due
                  consideration, <lb/> the people desire Responsible Government, they will have it.
                  I am here to state that His <lb/> Excellency the Governor has no wish or desire to
                  keep back Responsible Government; if he had <lb/> any such desire, is it likely
                  that he would have reconstituted his Executive Council so as to <lb/> make it
                  elective? I apprehend that people do not consider what they are talking about when
                  <lb/>they'ask for Responsible Government; they have not probably considered the
                  failures that have <lb/>been made in respect of Responsible Government There have
                  been some failures, as, for <lb/>instance, in Jamaica and in Victoria. A class of
                  people get into power under Responsible <lb/>Government whom no person would like
                  to have as rulers. There are petty interests mixed <lb/>up with politics in small
                  communities, which prevent the system working so well in them as <lb/>in large
                  countries like Great Britain, where there is a healthy tone and a vast population,
                  and, <lb/>consequently, great questions of national importance. I maintain that
                  after Confederation the <lb/>questions connected with local affairs will be so
                  small, and so entirely connected with particular <lb/>localities, that a staff of
                  permanent heads of departments will be far better for the Colony than
                  <lb/>Responsible Government. I make this statement from conviction. I am perfectly
                  free to take <lb/>any course I like, notwithstanding I am an Executive Councillor.
                  My position has not in any <lb/>way curtailed my views. I could have advised
                  Responsible Government if I had thought proper, <lb/>and would have done so if I
                  had thought it desirable for this Colony. If anyone believes that <lb/>the Organic
                  Act does not allow Responsible Government to be obtained at any time, let him
                  <lb/>move to make clause 19 specially applicable to this Colony. <lb/>
               </p>

    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName>—It is in the terms already, only it is not
                  specially named. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName>—Well, name it specially and put it in; I
                  will support it if anyone <lb/> proposes it. We know what His Excellency's
                  intention is with regard to giving representation <lb/> in the new Council, but we
                  do not know the measure of it. If there is an overwhelming <lb/> majority for
                  Responsible Government in all districts, electors will take care to send
                  Responsible <lb/> Government Members to the next Council. If the people are
                  determined to have this " priceless <lb/> boon," let them send men who will say
                  they will have it. I feel impelled to administer a soft <lb/> and gentle rebuke to
                  the Hon. Member for New Westminster, who has, I must confess, won <lb/> my esteem
                  by his manly, straightforward support of these Resolutions; but I must take <lb/>
                  exception to his language: it has been too emphatic—unintentionally, of
                  course—because led <lb/> away by the subject. He has used inflammatory language
                  which he had better not have <lb/> uttered, language which was not exactly in
                  accordance with what I conceive to be correct. <lb/> That clause in the Governor's
                  speech which speaks of our not being fit to govern ourselves: <lb/> Governor
                  Musgrave has never said so; if he had, I should have taken it as a personal
                  insult. <lb/> I say, as a British Columbian, I am capable of governing myself ;
                  and if we can, individually, <lb/> govern ourselves, it is fair to suppose that
                  the Colony, as a whole, can govern itself. It you <lb/> had the whole population
                  comeatable altogether, so that they could be parallel like an army, <lb/> and you
                  could make them give expression to their views, and out of that get a Government,
                  it <lb/> might be practicable; but instead of that, here we are with a scattered
                  population, isolated <lb/> centres separatcd from each other. The majority are
                  here for the sole purpose of making <lb/> money, and they don't feel that anxiety
                  that has been represented about Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment; they want
                  to be governed as cheaply as possible. If I am wrong, if it turns out at <lb/> the
                  polls that even a trifling majority are in favour of Responsible Government, they
                  can have <lb/> it. The iron heel of Canada is all nonsense. Governor Musgrave is
                  the man we have to deal <lb/> with, and I say that Responsible Government is a
                  relief to any Governor, for it comes between <lb/> him and the people. Governor
                  Musgrave says that it is (I paraphrase) " my duty, with my <lb/> "experience, to
                  give fair and frank advice to the people; to tell them what I think is for their
                  <lb/> "good. If they determine differently to my advice, the fault is with them."
                  Supposing that <lb/> Governor Musgrave had put Responsible Government in as a
                  condition, and had thrust it upon <lb/> the people, would not the respectable
                  minority who are against it have said—or possibly, and <lb/>
                  <pb n="105" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-18_Page_105.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>                                    
                  <fw type="num">105</fw> 

as I think, probably, have said—His Excellency had acted unwisely?
                  This question has been <lb/> before the people; they would have been justified in
                  jumping at the gilded bait of Responsible <lb/> Government if the Government had
                  not proposed a new system; but as he has done so, the <lb/> people will do well to
                  consider before they swallowed the barbed hook that lies under the bait. <lb/> I
                  desire to disclaim speaking in the interest of oflicials; their position would, so
                  far as I <lb/> believe, not be injured in any way by the introduction of
                  Responsible Government. Those <lb/> among them who were commissioned in England (I
                  mean the heads of departments) will be <lb/> rendered so independent that they
                  will be above fighting after their own interests. I think <lb/> it unlikely that
                  they will remain here. As to the balance of officials, if Canada is as liberal
                  <lb/> now as of old, or as liberal as Australia, they will be well provided for,
                  whether we have <lb/> Responsible Government or not. Probably they will be
                  "utilized," since that is the term we <lb/> are to use. I claim for the system
                  which His Excellency has foreshadowed, that it is more <lb/> suitable to the
                  present circumstances of this Colony than any other system which can be given
                  <lb/> us. Responsible Government has acted well in large communities, but in small
                  ones I doubt <lb/> its efficiency. It is like a painted ship on a painted ocean.
                  If it were obtained in a small <lb/> Colony like this, there would be a constant
                  game of battledore and shuttlecock going on—in <lb/> to-day and out to-morrow.
                  Fancy the Honourable Member for Victoria City presiding at the <lb/> Lands and
                  Works Department one day, and I, having paid him all the compliments I could,
                  <lb/> come over another day to have an interview with the Chief, and find that
                  there has been a <lb/> change of Ministry, there is another man in. My ideas may
                  be wrong; if so, they can be <lb/> corrected at the polls. If I were a man of
                  property, with a large stake in the Colony, I should <lb/> decidedly object to
                  Responsible Government. I have given my opinion candidly and honestly. <lb/> I may
                  never sit at this Council Board again. I have given my advice to His Excellency,
                  to <lb/> this Board, and to my constituents. conscientiously. If I am wrong, the
                  people will correct me. <lb/> I speak from conviction. No doubt there is talent in
                  British Columbia; no doubt there is plenty <lb/> of administrative ability; there
                  are many better men than myself, I am very sure, and that <lb/> is one reason that
                  I oppose Responsible Government. [Laughter.] But the main difficulty is <lb/> that
                  the best men won't come here; the chaff is blown here, the wheat remains behind.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>     On motion of Hon. Mr. Drake, the debate was adjourned to Monday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-03-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


            <!--<milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     MONDAY, March 21st,   1870. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr RING rose to assume the debate, and said:— Mr. Chairman, I feel assured that 
     <lb/>
     the House will accord me leave to say a few words. There have been submitted for the 
     <lb/>
     consideration of this House two amendments. and in the observations of the movers, two points 
     <lb/>
     of argument have been adduced,—the first founded on supposed reasoning, and the second in 
     <lb/>
     the way of threats and military argument, grounded on the possibility of the Government 
     <lb/>
     refusing to insert this condition. I desire to disengage myself from this latter argument. 
     <lb/>
     When I hear anything tantamount to a threat from the people against the Executive, I desire 
     <lb/>
     to repudiate it. Hon. Members who put such a picture of warfare before us talk bunkum. I 
     <lb/>
     address my humble petition to His Excellency, but if his judgment is against us I say to him, 
     <lb/>
     stand to your point and do not give way to threats; listen to no arguments as to what may 
     <lb/>
     happen in the nature of threats; stand to your points. I  say to Executive Members, don't yield 
     <lb/>
     to threats; don't be moved by them. I support the principle of Responsible Government, but I 
     <lb/>
     do so constitutionally. I say to Executive Members, I trust you will yield to reason and 
     <lb/>
     argument, but not to threats. I say we can ask for Responsible Government without the leave 
     <lb/>
     of the Organic Act; but I say let us repudiate all connection with Canada until we have secured 
     <lb/>
     Responsible Government; let us not wait till we are surrounded by Canadians. With regard to the 
     <lb/>
     railway, I say that in the life of the youngest amongst us we shall not get it; but we must 
     <lb/>
     make this the main Resolution : without Responsible Government let us have no Confederation. 
     <lb/>
     Better bear the ills we have than fly to others that we know not of. Let us not run the risk 
     <lb/>
     of having to ask Canada for Responsible Government.  Make it the emphatic sine qua non that 
     <lb/>
     we must have Responsible Government or no Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>