<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="lgBCLC_1870-03-09" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgBCLC">British Columbia Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1870-03-09">9 March 1870</date>, Province of BC, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 1<date when="2015-12-30"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 6<date when="2015-12-30"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 7<date when="2015-12-30"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 8<date when="2016-01-02"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 9<date when="2016-01-03"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 10<date when="2016-01-03"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 11<date when="2016-01-03"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 12<date when="2016-01-03"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 13<date when="2016-01-03"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 14<date when="2016-01-07"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 15<date when="2016-01-07"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 16<date when="2016-01-07"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 17<date when="2016-01-07"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 18<date when="2016-01-07"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgBCLC">

<editor>W.S. Sebright Green</editor>
          
               <title>Legislative Council, Debate on the Subject of Confederation with Canada</title>.
                    

          <date when="1912"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Victoria, B.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>William H. Cullin</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="1"/>.
 <biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="18"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_001.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_006.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_007.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_008.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_009.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_010.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_011.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_012.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_013.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_014.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_015.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_016.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_017.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_018.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-24">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_001">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_006">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_006.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_007">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_007.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_008">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_008.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_009">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_009.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_010">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_010.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_011">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_011.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_012">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_012.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_013">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_013.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_014">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_014.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_015">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_015.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_016">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_016.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_017">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_017.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_018">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_018.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_001.jpg"/>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL</head>

<head rendition="simple:centre">DEBATE ON THE SUBJECT OF CONFEDERATION WITH CANADA.</head>



<head rendition="simple:centre">WEDNESDAY, 9TH MARCH, 1870.</head> 
                 
               
            
         
            
            <p>
               The <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL CREASE</persName> opened the debate on Confederation, as 
                  <lb/>
               follows :— , 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
                  Mr. President—I rise to move that this Council do now resolve
                  itself into Committee of <lb/> the Whole, to take into consideration the terms
                  proposed for the Confederation of the Colony <lb/> of British Columbia with the
                  Dominion of Canada, in His Excellency's Message to this Council. <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            
            
            
            <p>
               In doing so, I am deeply impressed with the momentous character of the discussion into 
                  
               which we are about to enter, the grave importance of a decision by which the fate of this our 
                  <lb/>
               adopted country of British Columbia must be influenced for better, for worse, for all time to<lb/>come. And I earnestly hope that our minds and best energies may be bent to a task which <lb/>will tax all our patriotism, all our forbearance, all our abnegation of self, and selfish aims, to 
                  <lb/>
               combine all our individual powers into one great, united effort for the common good. 
                  <lb/>
               
               <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               May He who holds the fate of Nations in thehollow of His hand, and crowns with success, 
                  <lb/>
               or brings to nought, the counsels of men, guide all our deliberations to such an issue as shall 
                  <lb/>
               promote the peace, honour, and welfare of our Most Gracious Sovereign, and of this and all 
                  <lb/>
               other portions of Her extended realm. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>And now, Mr. President, I must dwell a few moments on the exact practical import of
                  the <lb/> motion before the House, and the issue which is involved in the "Aye" or
                  " No " which each <lb/> Honourable Member will be called upon to cast upon the
                  question which you, Mr. President, <lb/> will put to the House in that familiar
                  Parliamentary phrase " That I do now leave the Chair?" <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            <p>
               This issue is, Confederation or no Confederation?  
                  
               
            <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p>The motion assumes that the principle of Confederation has been already fully adopted
                  <lb/> by this House—and having so assumed, asks you now to go into Committee of
                  the Whole to <lb/> discuss the Terms on which the Colony would be content to be
                  confederated with the Dominion. <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            <p>Your question, therefore, Mr. President, "That I do now leave the Chair?" means—Will
                  you refuse Confederation at any price? or, Will you have it on favourable terms?
                  That is the <lb/> issue before us now. <lb/>
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            <p>Now, therefore, is the time for those Honourable Members who, notwithstanding the
                  <lb/> previous Resolutions of this House so frequently affirming the principle
                  ["No, no," from <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. <lb/> Helmcken</persName>], <supplied><persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL CREASE</persName></supplied> still conscientiously object to the
                  principles of Confederation, to come forward and <lb/> explain to this Honourable
                  body, and to the country at large, their views,—why they still refuse <lb/> to aid
                  in the consolidation of British interests on the North American Continent, by the
                     Con<lb break="no"/>federation of this Colony with the Dominion, and the
                  creation of one homogeneous nationality <lb/> from sea to sea. <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Some Honourable gentlemen say "No, no " to my statement that the House has affirmed 
                  <lb/>
               the principle of Confederation. But I appeal to the Journals of this House, in proof of what 
                  <lb/>
               I state. I well remember, on the 19th March, 1867, when the "British North America Act, 
                  <lb/>
               1867," was being framed by the Imperial Parliament, this Council, anxious to be embraced 
                  <lb/>
               within the purview of its provisions, passed by an unanimous vote the following Resolution :-<lb/>
            </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">" <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That this Council is of opinion that at this juncture of affairs in British North 
                  <lb/>
               America. east of the Rocky Mountains, it is very desirable that His 'Excellency be respectfully 
                  <lb/>
               requested to take such steps, without delay, as may be deemed by him best adapted to insure the 
                  <lb/>
               admission of British Columbia into the Confederation on fair and equitable terms, this Council being 
                  <lb/>
               confident that in advising; this step they are expressing the views of the 'Colonists generally." 
                  <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
                  
            <pb n="6" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_006.jpg"/>
            
      <fw type="num">6</fw> <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.<lb/> </fw>
                  
     
            
            <p>
               And more than that, this Resolution was followed up by a deputation of individual members 
                  <lb/>
               to Governor Seymour, who at their instance telegraphed to the Secretary of State the purport 
                  <lb/>
               of that Resolution; and on the 22nd March, the following Message was sent down to the Council 
                  <lb/>
               on the subject :-<lb/>
            </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">" The Governor has received the Resolution of the Legislative Council, dated the 18th instant, in 
                  <lb/>
               favour of the admission of British Columbia with the proposed Confederation of the Eastern British 
                  <lb/>
               Colonies of North America. He will place himself in communication on the subject with the Secretary 
                  <lb/>
               of State, with Viscount Monck. Governor-General of Canada, and with Sir Edmund Head, Governor 
                  <lb/>
               of the Hudson's Bay Company." 
                  <lb/>
               
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               Whatever construction may be put upon this Resolution by Honourable Members who have 
                  <lb/>
               said "No, no," one thing is certain, it affirmed, in the most distinct manner, by this Council, 
                  <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">the principle of Confederation</hi>, the advisability of our joining at some time or other the Dominion 
                  <lb/>
               of Canada. That principle has during every subsequent session, down to the present day, been 
                  <lb/>
               confirmed, either directly or indirectly, by a specific Resolution of this House ["No, no," from 
                  <lb/>
               <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. Helmcken</persName> and <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Mr. Wood</persName>]. <supplied><persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL CREASE</persName></supplied> Thus, on the 28th April, 1868, a Resolution was passed by this 
                  <lb/>
               Council confirming the previous Resolution, in the following terms :-<lb/>
            </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">"That 'this Council, while confirming the vote of last Session in favour of the general principle 
                  <lb/>
               of the desirability of the Union of this Colony with the Dominion of Canada, to accomplish the 
                  <lb/>
               consolidation of British interests and institutions in North America, are still without sufficient 
                  <lb/>
               information and experience of the practical working of Confederation in the North American 
                  
               Provinces, to admit of their defining the terms on which such an Union would be advantageous 'to 
                  <lb/>
               the local interests of British Columbia." 
                  <lb/>
               
         
            </quote>
            
            
            <p>
               What is that but a confirmation of the principle? Now let us look to the Journals of 1869, 
                  <lb/>
               There I see that, on the 17th February, 1869), when, owing to the position of other political 
                  <lb/>
               issues then current in the Colony, it would have been easy, had it been so desired, to procure 
                  <lb/>
               an adverse verdict on the principle of Confederation, the House, though invited to do so, refused 
                  <lb/>
               to go any further than to request Her Majesty's Government (while the North-West Territory 
                  <lb/>
               was still out of the Dominion) not to press the <hi rendition="simple:italic">present</hi> consummation of Union. The word 
                  <lb/>
               "present" was an express amendment of my Honourable colleague opposite (Mr. Trutch) and 
                  <lb/>
               myself, so as to preserve the principle, and bide our time. The House, therefore, I take it, 
                  <lb/>
               has thoroughly and uniformly committed itself to the principle of Confederation, and may 
                  <lb/>
               very properly be invited now, setting aside all causes of difference, for the common good, 
                  <lb/>
               calmly, frankly, and cordially to enter upon a discussion of the terms. But if any Honourable 
                  <lb/>
               Members think the principle has not been decided. now is the time and now the hour to settle 
                  <lb/>
               that point (as far as this Session and this present Council is concerned) once and forever. 
                  <lb/>
               They are bound, in support of their views, to lay before the Council the reasons for the faith 
                  <lb/>
               that is in them, and to explain why we should not consolidate counsels with the Dominion. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               And here, Mr. President, let me say a few words upon the position the Official Members of 
                  <lb/>
               this Council have occupied throughout the whole of this matter 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Their action has been much misunderstood—I will not say misconstrued―both in England 
                  <lb/>
               and at Ottawa. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Until the receipt of Earl Granville's Confederation Despatch of 14th August, 1869, they 
                  <lb/>
               did not feel themselves at liberty to go further in the direction of Confederation than to affirm 
                  <lb/>
               the general principle of its propriety, carefully abstaining from the expression of opinion on the 
                  <lb/>
               merits of any particular mode, details, or time of carrying that principle into practical effect. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               That, they considered, could most effectually be done by Her Majesty's Government, and 
                  <lb/>
               Executive peculiarly qualified for the task, this Legislature, and the People of this Colony all 
                  <lb/>
               acting in concert together, as it is now proposed to do. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I do not at present intend to enter into the details of what particular terms would or would 
                  <lb/>
               not be most advantageous to this Country in any proposal for Confederation. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               That will be a question for the House to settle when, if ever, we get into Committee on the 
                  <lb/>
               subject; but, inasmuch, as the principle of Confederation means the advisability of consolidat<lb break="no"/>ing British interests on the North American Continent, it is impossible to lose sight altogether, 
                  <lb/>
               in a debate upon the principle, of the general advantages to be derived by British Columbia 
                  <lb/>
               from a participation in that great scheme. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            <p>
               I readily confess that there are drawbacks to material union, such as distance, lack of communication,  and, to some extent, want of identity of interest, which can only—but yet which<lb/>
               <lb/>can—be removed, either wholly or in a very great degree, by suitable conditions of Union. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>

            

                  
            <pb n="7" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_007.jpg"/>
         <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            <fw type="num"> 7<lb/></fw>
            
       
            
            <p>
               It is for us to determine those conditions in this House, and, after negotiation upon them 
                  <lb/>
               with Canada, to submit them to the decision of the popular vote, the people being the parties 
                  <lb/>
               principally affected by the change, who will have to pass in the last resort, once and forever, 
                  <lb/>
               upon the whole question. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The circumstances, political, geographical, and social, under which we are at present placed, <lb/>compel us to political movement in one direction or another, and the question is now—In what 
                  <lb/>
               direction shall we go? 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We are sandwiched between United States Territory to the north and south―indeed on 
                  <lb/>
               all sides but one, and that one opening towards Canada. Our only option is between remaining; 
                  <lb/>
               a petty, isolated community 15,000 miles from home, ekeing out a miserable existence on the 
                  <lb/>
               crumbs of prosperity our powerful and active Republican neighbours choose to allow us, or, 
                  <lb/>
               by taking our place among the comity of nations, become the prosperous western outlet on the 
                  <lb/>
               North Pacific of a young and vigorous people, the eastern boundary of whose possessions is 
                  <lb/>
               washed by the Atlantic. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               This is the only option left to faithful subjects of the British Crown. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Now look at our condition as a Colony, with a climate far finer than any other in the 
                  <lb/>
               world, with magnificent harbours, rivers, seas, and waters for inland navigation, with unrivalled 
                  <lb/>
               resources of almost every description you can name—coal, lumber, spars, fish, and furs— <lb/>mines of gold, silver, copper, lead, cinnabar, tin, and almost every other mineral throughout 
                  <lb/>
               the land; with a soil and climate admirably adapted to pastoral and agricultural pursuits—  
                  <lb/>
               with almost every natural advantage which the lavish hand of Nature can bestow upon a  
                  <lb/>
               country—the undoubted fact remains :—  
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We are not prosperous. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Population does not increase. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Trade and commerce languish; coal mining does not advance; agriculture, though pro<lb break="no"/>gressive, does not go forward as it might. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The settlement of the country, though increasing, yet falls short of just expectations. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               No public works for opening the country are on hand, and a general lack of progress (that 
                  <lb/>
               is, proportioned to the extraordinary resources of the Colony) is everywhere apparent. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               And why is this? 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It is not, as some allege, because of the particular form of Government we at present enjoy 
                  <lb/>
               (if it were, Confederation in that would effect a change). 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It has among other things a Public Debt altogether disproportioned to our means. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Our close proximity to an active and powerful neighbour whose interests are foreign to our 
                  <lb/>
               own. [" Hear, hear," from <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. Helmcken</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL CREASE</persName></supplied> But the chief reason of all is that policy of isola<lb break="no"/>tion which has kept us aloof from the assistance and sympathy of a kindred race, and left us 
                  <lb/>
               in the infant state of one of England's youngest Colonies, to support the burdens and responsi<lb break="no"/>bilities of a thickly peopled and long settled land. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Do Honourable Members ask what would Confederation do for us? 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It would at once relieve us from the most if not all the present ills from which we suffer, 
                  <lb/>
               if properly arranged. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               For Confederation in some sense means terms. It would assume our Public Debt. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Greatly increase our Public Credit, and thereby aid in the utilization of our varied resources. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            
            
            <p>
               It would leave us a <hi rendition="simple:italic">good balance</hi> in our Exchequer to carry on all local works and open 
                  <lb/>
               out the country.<lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>It would give us a Railroad across the Continent. and a quick and easy access to Ottawa<lb/>New York, and London. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
            
            <p>
               It would cement and strengthen, instead of weaken, our connection with the Mother-land, 
                  <lb/>
               and ensure the protection of her Fleet and Army. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It would attract population, over tending in a continuous wave towards the West. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It would promote the settlement of our Public Lands, and the development of Agriculture. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Under it Trade and Commerce would take a fresh start. It would enlarge, not contract, 
                  <lb/>
               our political horizon, and it would infuse new hope and life blood into the whole system of the 
                  <lb/>
               Colony, and not leave us a more detached Municipality, as some suppose, any more than Scotland  
                  <lb/>
               is separate from the rest of Great Britain, or the County of Kent from England.  
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I leave to others to dilate upon the advantages which Canada would derive from the con<lb break="no"/>nection, the possession of a Far West (Canada's great want) into which her rapidly increasing 
                  <lb/>
               population may pour, instead of going to swell the bulk of the adjoining States. 
                  <lb/>
            </p> 
       
            
            <pb n="8" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_008.jpg"/>
      <fw type="num">8</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.<lb/></fw>
            
       
            
            <p>
               Those gentlemen will be able to show that the ultimate importance—nay possible existence 
                  <lb/>
               —of the Dominion as a Nation may hereafter, in some measure, depend upon her Union with 
                  <lb/>
               ourselves.  
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               To them, also, I leave the task of dwelling on the healing of old internal feuds of race and 
                  <lb/>
               language of which Confederation is the only cure. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               If we watch the progress of events, they all point to the same end, to the growth of a new 
                  <lb/>
               universal sentiment of nationality in British America. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It is clear that events all gravitate in that direction. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               [<persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DeCosmos</persName>—" In the direction of Confederation or Nationality?"] 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               <supplied><persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL CREASE</persName></supplied> I say, Sir, that the current of events points to Confederation and ultimately to Nationality. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Confederation is evidently our ultimate destiny—Our own interests—Canadian aspirations <lb/>—and Imperial policy, as enunciated in the Secretary of State's Despatch, all point the same 
                  <lb/>
               way. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We shall, therefore, best consult the real interests of the Colony, the sooner bring on a 
                  <lb/>
               new era of progress and prosperity in this favoured land, by not delaying to debate and consider 
                  <lb/>
               over the advisability of the principle itself, but at once to go into Committee of the Whole, and 
                  <lb/>
               there combine all our energies upon the best scheme to be submitted in the last resort to the 
                  <lb/>
               decision of the people, for carrying out the principle of Confederation, under God's blessing, 
                  <lb/>
               successfully into practical effect. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The motion was seconded by the <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. the Chief Commissioner of Lands and Works</persName>, who 
                  <lb/>
               was excused from speaking at this stage of the debate on the ground of indisposition, under 
                  <lb/>
               which he was manifestly suffering. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p> The <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName> said:―The subject of Confederation was
                  introduced by His <lb/> Excellency the Governor in his Speech, in the following
                  terms :-<lb/>
               </p>
            <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"The community is already acquainted with the Despatch which I have recently received from 
                  <lb/>
               Her Majesty's Secretary of State on this subject: and the careful consideration of it cannot longer 
                  <lb/>
               be deferred with courtesy to Her Majesty's Government, or advantage to the Colony. I commend it 
                  <lb/>
               to your earnest thought. For my own part I am convinced that on certain terms, which I believe it 
                  <lb/>
               would not be difficult to arrange, this Colony may derive substantial benefit from such an Union. 
                  <lb/>
               But the only manner in which it can be ascertained whether Canada will agree to such arrange<lb break="no"/>ments as will suit us, is to propose such as we would be ready to accept. With the assistance of 
                  <lb/>
               my Council, I have prepared a scheme which I shall cause to be laid before you. Resolutions framed 
                  <lb/>
               upon that basis will enable me to communicate with the Government of Canada and ascertain whether 
                  <lb/>
               they will be willing to accede to our propositions. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               While the views of Her Majesty's Government have been clearly. and forcibly expressed upon this- 
                  <lb break="yes"/>
               question, I am sure there is no desire to urge the Union, except in accordance with its general 
                  <lb/>
               acceptance by British subjects in the Colony. I do not, therefore, propose that any terms agreed upon 
                  <lb/>
               by the Government of Canada should be finally accepted, until ratified by the general verdict of the 
                  <lb/>
               community, so far as that can be ascertained through another Council, of which the Unofficial Members 
                  <lb/>
               shall have been reelected." 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p></quote>
            

            
            <p>
               Before proceeding to the consideration of the subject, I will reply in a very few words to 
                  <lb/>
               the speech of the Hon. Attorney-General. The Hon. gentleman laid great stress upon the 
                  <lb/>
               consolidation of British interests on this coast. but I say, Sir, that however much we are in<lb/>favour of consolidating British interests, our own interests must come first; Imperial interests 
                  <lb/>
               can well afford to wait. We are invited to settle this question now and for ever, but I say 
                  <lb/>
               that we are not called upon to do so; the matter will come before the people after the proposed 
                  <lb/>
               terms have been submitted to the Dominion Government, and it will very likely happen that, 
                  <lb/>
               if these terms are rejected and others of a mean nature substituted by the Government of 
                  <lb/>
               Canada for the consideration of the people of this Colony, other issues may come up at the<lb/>polls, and amongst them, the question whether there is no other place to which this Colony 
                  <lb/>
               can go but Canada; whatever may be the result of the present vote, it is impossible to deny 
                  <lb/>
               the probability of the less being absorbed by the greater; and it cannot be regarded as improbable 
                  <lb/>
               that ultimately, not only this Colony, but the whole of the Dominion of Canada will be absorbed 
                  <lb/>
               by the United States. The Hon. Attorney-General has not attempted to prove the advantages 
                  <lb/>
               which will result from Confederation; he has contented himself with vague assertions of 
                  <lb/>
               advantages. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The question is only brought down by the Governor in consequence of the Despatch of 
                  <lb/>
               Lord Granville; all we have to do is to agree to a series of resolutions. It is not pretended 
                  <lb/>
               
       
            
            <pb n="9" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_009.jpg"/>
       <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            <fw type="num">9<lb/></fw>
            
   
               that it is the voice of the people, or the voice of this Council. It is well understood that it is 
                  <lb/>
               a Government measure. And we all know what that means—it means that this series of 
                  <lb/>
               resolutions is to be passed. And we have it from the Governor that he desires to send these 
                  <lb/>
               resolutions to Canada; they will not go, they are not intended to go, as the opinion of the 
                  <lb/>
               people, but when certain terms have been agreed upon between the Government of this Colony 
                  <lb/>
               and the Dominion Parliament, they will come back to the people for ratification. It remains 
                  <lb/>
               then for the people to organize, so as to be ready at the proper time to give their verdict, for 
                  <lb/>
               the responsibilities will ultimately rest with the people, and it is for them to say whether they 
                  <lb/>
               will have Confederation or not. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I do think, Sir, that the question ought to have been an open one. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Her Majesty's Government ought not to have interfered; they are not justified in interfering 
                  <lb/>
               in business which we could very well manage for ourselves. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I feel certain that His Excellency will act uprightly, fairly, honestly, and generously, by, 
                  <lb/>
               and for, the Colony [hear, hear]; and, Sir, I fully believe that if these terms are declined now, 
                  <lb/>
               in any future negotiations that may take place, if the people support the Governor, no terms 
                  <lb/>
               will be accepted, or ever proposed, which would lead to this Colony being sacrificed to Canada, 
                  <lb/>
               and that the people will have every opportunity afforded them to organize for the final vote 
                  <lb/>
               when the time arrives for the settlement of this question "finally and forever," as the Honour<lb break="no"/>able Gentleman has put it. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I see no reason, Sir, why Her Majesty's Government should interfere with our affairs; there 
                  <lb/>
               is no reason that the Members of this Council shall be coerced. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The desire of Her Majesty's Government is in reality a command to the Executive. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               A new election ought to have been called before this question was brought on; but there 
                  <lb/>
               is one satisfaction left us, it is that Her Majesty's Government have left the terms to the Colony. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It is for the people to use that power rightly, wisely, and well, to see that Confederation 
                  <lb/>
               means the welfare and progress of the Colony. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Now, Sir, in the first place, it is necessary for the people to see that Confederation must 
                  <lb/>
               be for the general good of the Colony. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I am opposed to this question being brought down now. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I believe it to be most inopportune. It is believed by most people that this Colony is on 
                  <lb/>
               the verge of great changes. That the new gold discoveries will bring a large population to 
                  <lb/>
               this Colony, and that the slight despondency which now exists will be swept away, and that 
                  <lb/>
               this Colony will once more enter upon an era of prosperity not inferior to that which belonged 
                  <lb/>
               to it a few years ago. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I say, Sir, that this is an inopportune period to bring this question up, because when that 
                  <lb/>
               population which is expected arrives, our position to negotiate for terms will be much better, 
                  <lb/>
               because with a larger population and greater prosperity, we may demand far better terms than 
                  <lb/>
               now; and, Sir, it is my firm conviction that if prosperity comes shortly the people of this 
                  <lb/>
               Colony will not desire to change certainty for uncertainty. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Another reason there is that we ought to wait until after 1871. In that year Canada has 
                  <lb/>
               to take a census of the population, and when that is taken we shall know the amount of the 
                  <lb/>
               debt per head. I have no doubt it is greater now than when Confederation was first inaugu<lb break="no"/>rated, It is increasing, and I believe that instead of 22 cents per head it will now be 25 cents. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I should like, then, to wait until after 1871, because we shall then have a better opportunity 
                  <lb/>
               of knowing the financial condition of those with whom we would connect ourselves 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It is inopportune, also, for the reason that the present difficulties in the Red River Settle<lb break="no"/>ment: are sufficient to cause us great anxiety: I will not take up the time of this House by 
                  <lb/>
               inquiring whether the people of that Territory are right or wrong. I know not, and shall not 
                  <lb/>
               discuss the question; but this I do know, that if they induce the Indians to join them it will 
                  <lb/>
               cause a great delay in the settlement of that country; and we do not even yet know that the 
                  <lb/>
               Red River Settlement will prove so inviting to emigration as is reported. Again, Sir, I may 
                  <lb/>
               state that Confederation, so far as it has at present gone, is but a mere experiment. It is 
                  <lb/>
               nothing more or less than an experiment. And I believe that considerable dissatisfaction has 
                  <lb/>
               resulted from it. If we wait a little longer before seeking to enter within its pale ourselves, 
                  <lb/>
               we shall know better about the faults of its machinery, and perhaps be able to learn what are 
                  <lb/>
               its drawbacks, and how we can best avoid them. These, Sir, are good and sufficient reasons 
                  <lb/>
               for delay. It is absurd to attempt to ally ourselves with a people 3,000 miles away, without 
                  <lb/>
               

            
     
            
            <pb n="10" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_010.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">10</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.<lb/></fw>
            
        
               any settlement of the intervening country, with no communication except through the United<lb/>States, and with no telegraphic communication. Canada is for all practical purposes further 
                  <lb/>
               removed from us to-day than England; we know less about her. When we asked for a copy 
                  <lb/>
               of the Canadian Tariff we were told that there was no copy to be had. [" Yes, yes," from <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Hon. 
                  <lb/>
               Members</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> No official copy then. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               This, then, shows forcibly the intimate nature of the relations subsisting between us. 
                  <lb/>
               When we desire to refer to the Canadian Year Book, a most useful work, which during the 
                  <lb/>
               present discussion ought to be in the hands of every member, we find but two copies. This, 
                  <lb/>
               again, shows the extent of our communication with Canada. Her Majesty's Government seem 
                  <lb/>
               to think that they know best what is for our interest, and it seems much as if they said to us 
                  <lb/>
               " You are a Crown Colony, and you ought to remain one. You are not fit to govern yourselves ; 
                  <lb/>
               we do not want you ; we will hand you over to Canada." I would rather that we were governed 
                  <lb/>
               from Downing Street. It is not, in my opinion, necessary or desirable that this Colony should 
                  <lb/>
               be Confederated with Canada. And now, Sir, let us glance at this Colony. I need not dilate 
                  <lb/>
               upon what is known to all. I maintain, Sir, that this Colony is one of the richest portions of 
                  <lb/>
               the world's surface ; that it has unlimited supplies of lumber and spars ; that it possesses coal, 
                  <lb/>
               gold, and other minerals in abundance ; that her waters teem with fish ; that it is rich in every<lb break="no"/>thing. Take the climate ; it is far better than that of England, far more temperate, far more 
                  <lb/>
               bright and sunny, and, I may fairly add, far more healthy. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We are asked by the Honourable the Attorney-General why the country does not get on ; 
                  <lb/>
               and I will now proceed to tell you, Sir, why the country has not prospered as it ought to have 
                  <lb/>
               done. It is because the Government has paid too little attention to the acquisition of population. 
                  <lb/>
               One very great drawback to its progress and the settlement of its land, is its proximity to the 
                  <lb/>
               United States. That proximity is one of the chief reasons that it has not been peopled as it 
                  <lb/>
               would have been. When we look at the energy and enterprise there, and at the field which the 
                  <lb/>
               United States offers for emigrants and the enterprising of all nations, how can we wonder that 
                  <lb/>
               that country is preferred to ours, and that people when they become dissatisfied here should 
                  <lb/>
               leave for the United States. The United States hem us in on every side ; it is the Nation by 
                  <lb/>
               which we exist ; it is the Nation which has made this Colony what it is ; but, nevertheless, it 
                  <lb/>
               is one of our greatest drawbacks. We do not enjoy her advantages, nor do we profit much by 
                  <lb/>
               them ; we do not share her prosperity, and we are far too small to be her rival. The effect 
                  <lb/>
               of a large body and a small body being brought into contact, is, that the larger will attract the 
                  <lb/>
               smaller, and ultimately absorb it. [" Yes, yes," and " No, no."] 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               [<persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Hon. Member for Kootenay</persName>—How about Switzerland?] 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> I say more, Sir. I say that the United States will probably ultimately absorb both this 
                  <lb/>
               Colony and the Dominion of Canada. [" No, no, no," from <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Mr. Trutch</persName>, <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Mr. Crease</persName>, and <persName ref="pers:ANON1">others</persName>.] 
                  <lb/>
               <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> Canada will in all probability find it quite as much to her advantage to join her ultimately. 
                  <lb/>
               as we do now to join the Dominion. I say, Sir, that one cause of our want of prosperity has 
                  <lb/>
               been the neglect of acquisition of population, and particularly of agricultural population. The 
                  <lb/>
               next cause is that we have driven people out of the Colony. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I need only allude to our having deposed the Free Trade system. That deposition took 
                  <lb/>
               population out of the Colony which has never been replaced. There was a depopulation of the 
                  <lb/>
               cities without any attempt having been made to obtain a substitute rural population. We are 
                  <lb/>
               now asked to undergo another revolution which will ruin our farmers, and do no sort of good to 
                  <lb/>
               those engaged in commercial pursuits. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I do not intend, Sir, to follow the details of the proposed terms at present, but there seem 
                  <lb/>
               items which I must notice. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            <p>
               I hold in my hands the published returns of the Custom House receipts for last year, and 
                  <lb/>
               this document shows plainly, that no less than half a million of dollars are sent out of the 
                  <lb/>
               Colony every year for the purchase of agricultural productions—wheat, barley, flour, and cattle <lb/>―all of which, considering the fertility of our soil, its abundance, the magnificent, salubrious, 
                  <lb/>
               healthy, sunny, and more than temperate climate, we ought to produce ourselves. This Colony 
                  <lb/>
               probably raises another half million's worth. If we adopt the Canadian Tariff we shall throw<lb/>away this million of dollars; that is, the half million which we raise, and the half million 
                  <lb/>
               which can be raised—and for what? For the sake of problematical benefits which some think 
                  <lb/>
               likely to arise from Confederation. If Confederation should come and bring with it the Tariff 
                  <lb/>
               of Canada, and it will do so, the great inducements which we now have to attract population, 
                  <lb/>
               


            
            <pb n="11" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_011.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            <fw type="num">11<lb/></fw>
            
      
 
               will be taken away. So far from Confederation benefiting the commercial community, I say it  
                  <lb/>
               is much rather calculated to do them harm. No doubt if public works are undertaken, as we 
                  <lb/>
               are told will be the case under Confederation, employment will be given for a time, but the 
                  <lb/>
               supplies required will come from the United States, and our public works will actually be of 
                  <lb/>
               more benefit to the United States, during their construction, than to this Colony. What we want, 
                  <lb/>
               is an enlarged outlet for our resources. We want markets for our coal and lumber ; we want 
                  <lb/>
               our local industries fostered ; and all of these can be obtained by a judicious arrangement of our 
                  <lb/>
               own Tariff. Next, we want agricultural population, and any increase of this kind of population 
                  <lb/>
               must depend upon the encouragement given. If our agricultural interests are left without 
                  <lb/>
               encouragement, we shall not get an increased agricultural population ; and, therefore, the 
                  <lb/>
               country will not reap so much benefit from public works, as the supplies will come from the 
                  <lb/>
               United States. 
                  
               
            <lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We shall find it difficult, Sir, to get a Tariff from Canada that will suit us, and I think 
                  <lb/>
               that I shall be able to show you, Sir, that Confederation will not produce population Anything 
                  <lb/>
               that deprives this Colony of the power of protecting the local industries and interests of the 
                  <lb/>
               Colony, and of regulating and fostering its commerce and trade, cannot be otherwise than 
                  <lb/>
               dangerous and injurious to the country. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I feel perfectly sure, Sir, that if Confederation should come, bringing with it the Tariff of<lb/>Canada, not only will the farmers be ruined, but our independence will be taken away. It will 
                  <lb/>
               deprive our local industries of the protection now afforded them, and will inflict other burdens 
                  <lb/>
               upon them. It will not free trade and commerce from the shackles which now bind them, and 
                  <lb/>
               will deprive the Government of the power of regulating and encouraging those interests upon 
                  <lb/>
               which the prosperity of the Colony depends. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            
            
            <p>
               There can be no permanent or lasting union with Canada, unless terms be made to promote<lb/>and foster the material and pecuniary interests of this Colony. The only link which binds this 
                  <lb/>
               Colony to Canada is Imperial. The people must be better off under Confederation than alone, 
                  <lb/>
               or they will not put up with it. We are told, Sir, that public works are to be undertaken. 
                  <lb/>
               I answer that they may do good to some, but the supplies both of food and raiment will come 
                  <lb/>
               from the United States, who will in reality reap the lion's share of the benefit ; and, what is 
                  <lb/>
               more, as soon as the money was expended the people would begin to consider whether they 
                  <lb/>
               were equally well off under Confederation, as they might be under another Government ; and 
                  <lb/>
               if a change should be desired, it is perfectly plain that Canada cannot use force to keep the 
                  <lb/>
               people of this Colony within the Dominion. They must he better off under Confederation than 
                  <lb/>
               alone, or they will not stop in the Confederacy. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Our true course, Sir, judging from the statistics, is not to look to Canada, but to seek to 
                  <lb/>
               extend our markets for our natural productions, and to obtain an agricultural productive 
                  <lb/>
               population. I say, Sir, that there is no necessity for us to join Canada ; we can get on very 
                  <lb/>
               well by ourselves at present. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Hon. Attorney-General says Canada will take over our debts ; but I say, Sir, that our<lb/>debt in proportion to our population is very little more per head than that of Canada. When <lb/>I state this, I mean that Indians are very large consumers and producers, and ought to be 
                  <lb/>
               reckoned with the population. Our expenses will soon be much smaller. What I mean, Sir, is 
                  <lb/>
               that at the end of 1871 this Colony will save $50,000, for one of the loans will have expired, 
                  <lb/>
               thus saving as $36,000, and floating loans will be funded, and we shall save ten or twelve 
                  <lb/>
               thousand by that. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I shall not go into the question of Canada being able to defend this Colony ; I do not 
                  <lb/>
               believe, Sir, that Canada is able to defend itself. Great Britain has taken away her standing 
                  <lb/>
               army. Canada will very soon be required to pay for the few troops that are left, and in the 
                  <lb/>
               next place they will be asked to contribute to the expense of keeping up the navy. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Confederation would make the Dominion territorially greater, but would, in case of war, 
                  <lb/>
               be a source of weakness. It is people, not territory, that makes a country strong and powerful. 
                  <lb/>
               To be strong, the union must be of people, and in my opinion that condition is wanting. I feel 
                  <lb/>
               certain that Her Majesty's Government has no wish to be put to the expense of defending the 
                  <lb/>
               country ; no wish to be involved in quarrels with the United States ; no wish to keep Canada 
                  <lb/>
               depending upon her support, but rather a wish to force her into independence—to get rid of 
                  <lb/>
               her altogether. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I am opposed to Confederation, because it will not serve to promote the industrial interests 
                  <lb/>
               of this Colony, but, on the contrary, it will serve to ruin many, and thus be detrimental to the 
                  <lb/>
               
            
                  
            <pb n="12" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_012.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">12</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.<lb/></fw>
            
       
               interest and progress of the country. I say that Confederation will be injurious to the farmers, <lb/>because protection is necessary to enable them to compete with farmers of the United States. 
                  <lb/>
               The Tariff and Excise Laws do not supply that. They will be inimical to brewers. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
                   Inimical to the Spar Trade ; 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
                   Inimical to Fisheries ; 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
                   Inimical to Whaling Pursuits ; 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
                   Inimical to Spar and Lumber Business. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            
            
            <p>
               Turn to the Canadian Tariff and you will find grain admitted free. I maintain that if the 
                  <lb/>
               tariff now imposed upon certain cereals and agricultural produce be taken away, farmers of this<lb/>Colony will be brought into competition with the farmers of the United States, and will succumb <lb/>[<persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DeCosmos</persName>—Lower Country Farmers]  <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> Yes, and here the Resolutions are silent where they 
                  <lb/>
               ought to be loudest. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            
            
            <p>
               I shall not attempt to prove that farmers did not prosper under Free Trade ; be that as it 
                  <lb/>
               may, they are now prosperous and becoming rich. There is no better advertisement for popula<lb break="no"/>tion than the fact of the present prosperity of the farmers. Take away that prosperity, and 
                  <lb/>
               you do away with the chief inducement which you have for agricultural population. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            <p>I go on to brewers, and these interests, though in point of fact small, are in proportion as 
                  <lb/>
               large with us, as larger interests would be to a larger population ; moreover, we, having so small 
                  <lb/>
               a population, cannot afford to risk a change, because we cannot recuperate quickly. Under the 
                  <lb/>
               Canadian law a brewer must take out a brewer's and maltster's license, and has to pay one cent 
                  <lb/>
               per pound on all malt made, and as there is an average amount of 1,248,000 pounds of malt 
                  <lb/>
               consumed in the year, the average duty would amount to $12,680 per annum, in addition to 
                  <lb/>
               which they will have to pay a maltster's and brewer's license. The duty upon that amount of 
                  <lb/>
               malt now is $3,750. Confederation therefore will increase the malt duty by nearly $9,000. 
                  <lb/>
               Brewers would probably buy all their malt from abroad or cease to brew, especially when we 
                  <lb/>
               take into consideration the annoyances connected with the bonding system. You will see, Sir, 
                  <lb/>
               that this quantity of malt would take 500 acres of land to raise it, so that in addition to 
                  <lb/>
               injuring the brewers, the farmers are also injured. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Under the Canadian Law, salmon must not be taken at the mouth of any river when they 
                  <lb/>
               are going up for the purpose of spawning. We all know that they must be taken. If we are 
                  <lb/>
               not allowed to catch them as they go up, we should never get them at all. They never come 
                  <lb/>
               down again ; they go up to die. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Again, according to Canadian Law, whales must not be taken by means of bombs or fire<lb break="no"/>arms; and I am told they cannot be taken without firearms in these waters, so that under 
                  <lb/>
               Confederation whales would be free to spout as they pleased. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Under Canadian Law, tobacco cannot be grown without excise duty ; it has to be bonded, 
                  <lb/>
               and its cultivation would be abandoned. Alkaline soil suits the tobacco plant, and I have very 
                  <lb/>
               little doubt that tobacco could be grown profitably in many parts of British Columbia [<persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. 
                  <lb/>
               Holbrook</persName>—It is grown] ; <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> but the excise duty. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               When we come to lumber we find that there is an export duty on logs of $1 per 1,000 feet ; 
                  <lb/>
               this will affect the spar business. [<persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. Barnard</persName>—No, it will not affect spars ; the duty is 
                  <lb/>
               upon logs only, which is cut into lumber, and is a protection to Canadian Lumber Mills.] 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            
            
            <p>
              <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> I have now, Sir, given you reasons why the general interests of the Colony will not be<lb/>promoted. Farmers, Brewers, the Lumber Trade, and the Fisheries will not be benefited ; who 
                  <lb/>
               will? Canada will take no coal nor lumber from us, and will not increase our trade at all ; 
                  <lb/>
               but they will take our money, and much of that money derived from the very fact that we 
                  <lb/>
               have to pay more for Canadian manufactures than the Eastern Provinces, or rather we are 
                  <lb/>
               obliged to pay duties upon foreign articles, simply because we cannot obtain Canadian, and 
                  <lb/>
               yet we are told that Confederation will reduce our taxation. Our Tariff is as low as that of 
                  <lb/>
               Canada, save upon spirits and tobacco. 
                  
               
            <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It would be absurd for us to sacrifice our interests in order that laws may be made for us 
                  <lb/>
               by a people who know little of our condition and wants, and who in fact must necessarily 
                  <lb/>
               legislate for the greater number―the people of the Atlantic Provinces. It is dangerous to place 
                  <lb/>
               ourselves at the disposal of superior numbers. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I believe, Sir, that we are quite capable of making laws for ourselves. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            
            
            <p>
               If we are united, or rather absorbed, everything will centralize in Canada, and the whole<lb/>country will be tributary to Canada. The number of Representatives sent to Ottawa from 
                  <lb/>
               other places would overwhelm the number sent from British Columbia. Even in the matter of 
                  <lb/>
        
            
            <pb n="13" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_013.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            <fw type="num"> 13</fw>
            
        
               appropriations, where the scramble always is, this Colony would be overborne ; we should be 
                  <lb/>
               laughed at by the victors for our pretensions. It is the case in all other Colonies, and would 
                  <lb/>
               be here. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It is absurd to suppose that the same laws, whether civil, commercial, or industrial will be 
                  <lb/>
               found equally advantageous to all parts of this great Continent. It manifestly cannot be so ; 
                  <lb/>
               the conditions are different. We know what is best for ourselves, and are able to legislate to 
                  <lb/>
               effect that. We have no wish to pay Canada to do our legislation. 
                  
               
            <lb/>
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               No union between this Colony and Canada can permanently exist, unless it be to the material 
                  <lb/>
               and pecuniary advantage of this Colony to remain in the union. The sum of the interests of 
                  <lb/>
               the inhabitants is the interest of the Colony. The people of this Colony have, generally speak<lb break="no"/>ing, no love for Canada ; they care, as a rule, little or nothing about the creation of another 
                  <lb/>
               Empire, Kingdom, or Republic ; they have but little sentimentality, and care little about the 
                  <lb/>
               distinctions between the form of Government of Canada and the United States. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            <p>
               Therefore no union on account of love need be looked for. The only bond of union outside 
                  <lb/>
               of force―and force the Dominion has not—will be the material advantage of the country and 
                  <lb/>
               pecuniary benefit of the inhabitants. Love for Canada has to be acquired by the prosperity of<lb/>the country, and from our children.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 
                  
               I say, Sir, it is absurd for us to ally ourselves with a people with whom we have, and 
                  <lb/>
               can have, no communication. The Tariff and Excise Laws of Canada will ruin the dominant<lb/>interests of this Colony, and we are told that those laws must rule accordingly to the conditions 
                  <lb/>
               of "The British North America Act." A Tariff perhaps excellent to the Eastern Provinces, is 
                  <lb/>
               ruin to British Columbia. Our Tariff imposes a large duty on spirits, and a duty on agricul<lb break="no"/>tural produce. The Canadian Tariff imposes none on agricultural produce, and a small duty 
                  <lb/>
               on spirits. <lb/>
                  
          
            </p>

  
            
            
            <p>
               If we are Confederated with Canada we become its tributary, and in all that concerns us 
                  <lb/>
               chiefly Canada has to act for us. In all our chief concerns, commerce, shipping, and mercantile 
                  <lb/>
               laws, agriculture, trade, navigation, fisheries, currency, banking—Canada rules. She may tax 
                  <lb/>
               us to any extent, and in any manner she pleases, so that it is quite possible we may have export 
                  <lb/>
               duties on gold and coal. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               All such things as require money for their performance are left for the Colony to provide ; 
                  <lb/>
               those that require intellect are supplied by Canada. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The expense to Canada is constantly decreasing, her revenue constantly increasing. The 
                  <lb/>
               expense of the Local Government on the other hand, is constantly increasing, and out of propor<lb break="no"/>tion to any increase of its revenue. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Is it necessary that we should pay for the intellect of Canada? Is our own not as good? 
                  <lb/>
               Do we not know what is best for ourselves? Cannot we do all as well as they? Cannot we pay 
                  <lb/>
               our Colonial intellect to do our business well, instead of theirs to do it badly? 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The very means by which we ought to make our roads are taken from us, so that, as time 
                  <lb/>
               rolls on, we shall have to provide other taxes, and raise loans for the purpose. The other 
                  <lb/>
               countries have gone into Confederation with roads ready made, and large loans and large debts. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It is not fair to put this country upon a footing of its present population ; on its present 
                  <lb/>
               income ; a future income ought to be calculated upon. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I do not think it wise to ruin the present population for the sake of the future. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Remember that to have a population, that population must be able to live. Confederation 
                  <lb/>
               will ruin the farmer, and destroy at once the greatest inducement to immigration ; will ruin the 
                  <lb/>
               brewer and the fisheries ; do no good to commerce ; afford no larger market for lumber, coal, or 
                  <lb/>
               anything else ; in fact do a great deal of harm and no good, save that which is problematical 
                  <lb/>
               and fanciful. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               In conclusion, I have to say that I sincerely trust that our deliberations may result in good, 
                  <lb/>
               and that whatever may be the issue of this debate, it may be for the good of the Colony. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>I accord most heartily with the learned Attorney-General in the belief that― 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
         
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
               " There's a Divinity that shapes our ends, 
                  <lb/>
               Rough hew them how we may,"<lb/>
          
              
               
            </quote>

            
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">The Hon. Mr. DRAKE</persName>, Member for Victoria City, rose and
                  said:—Sir, I will move an amend<lb break="no"/>ment to the Resolution of the Hon.
                  Attorney General―" That the consideration of this question <lb/> be postponed for
                  six months." I need not state, Sir, that I have always been opposed to Con<lb break="no"/>federation. I have consistently opposed Confederation on any terms
                  up to the present time, and <lb/>
                  <pb n="14" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_014.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">14</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> I do not see any reason now to
                  change my opinion. I do not say that Confederation must be<lb/>bad for all time,
                  the time may come when it will be a benefit or a necessity ; but at present, I
                  <lb/> do not believe that Confederation would be a benefit to British Columbia.
                  The time has not <lb/> yet arrived for it. I was sent to this Council as an
                  opponent of Confederation. I oppose it <lb/> from conviction, and I shall still
                  continue to oppose it. <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The question of Confederation has been advocated by certain parties for some years past, 
                  <lb/>
               and why? Because there has been a general feeling of dissatisfaction throughout the Colony, 
                  <lb/>
               a general feeling of pressure from heavy taxation on a daily diminishing basis. The people 
                  <lb/>
               have been suffering under a desire for change ; that is what is at the bottom of this discussion. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Confederation has been discussed outside, in the public press, and in other places, and now, 
                  <lb/>
               after years of agitation, by secret and unknown partizans, it has cropped up in this Council as 
                  <lb/>
               a Government measure. I know, Sir, that I have no chance of carrying this amendment. I 
                  <lb/>
               have not the slightest hope of carrying it, but I move it with the view of bringing the question 
                  <lb/>
               fairly before the public. I should deeply regret that this Council should be able to bind the 
                  <lb/>
               Colony for ever. The question is one of the greatest magnitude, greater by for than any other 
                  <lb/>
               which has ever come before this Legislature. I am glad that it must hereafter be referred to 
                  <lb/>
               another Council, the majority of whose members will have to come before the people for election 
                  <lb/>
               I think, however, that it is waste of time to bring this measure before this Council. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            
            
            <p>
               There are some points in Confederation, I admit, which are worthy of consideration, or 
                  <lb/>
               would be under different circumstances. The idea of consolidating the British Possessions on 
                  <lb/>
               this Continent, is an idea which is likely to carry people away. The idea of assisting to found 
                  <lb/>
               a large and wide-spreading country might be dazzling to some. But if we are to be turned 
                  <lb/>
               over to Canada with no change in our form of Government, no alteration in the management 
                  <lb/>
               of our political affairs, where is the advantage of any change. It will simply be a change from<lb/>" King Stork" to " King Log." The Officials will be chosen by the Dominion Government instead 
                  <lb/>
               of the Crown ; we should be transferred from the rule of Statesman at Downing Street to that 
                  <lb/>
               of Politicians at Ottawa. ["No, no." from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DeCosmos</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DRAK1">The Hon. Mr. DRAKE</persName></supplied> All our political rights will be 
                  <lb/>
               taken away, the whole of the legislation will pass out of our hands into that of the Dominion 
                  <lb/>
               at Ottawa ; those laws upon which we shall be entitled to pass an opinion, will be much of the 
                  <lb/>
               same nature as those upon which a municipality  or vestry may vote ; but which are beneath the 
                  <lb/>
               dignity of a Colony. All power of raising taxes, except as the Hon. Member for the District 
                  <lb/>
               reminds me, for provincial purposes, we shall be subject to the provisions of the Organic Act, 
                  <lb/>
               which we have no power to change. Any terms which we can impose, must be subject to the 
                  <lb/>
               provisions of " The British North America Act." My position, therefore, is correct, when I say 
                  <lb/>
               that our power will not exceed that of a municipality. We are told that we are not fit for 
                  <lb/>
               Representative Institutions or Responsible Government. Then we shall go into the Dominion 
                  <lb/>
               as a Crown Colony—bound hand and foot. The few Members that will represent us at Ottawa, 
                  <lb/>
               will not have the power to do anything for us. I do not trust the Politicians of Ottawa. I do 
                  <lb/>
               not desire to give them the power to raise money upon our vast and rich territory, whilst we 
                  <lb/>
               should get nothing from Canada in return. I would rather remain as we are, with some change 
                  <lb/>
               and modification in our Government. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I admit that Confederation offers great advantages to those Provinces which are contiguous 
                  <lb/>
               to Canada ; there they have a mutuality of interests ; they are able to use the products of the 
                  <lb/>
               Dominion ; they have community of interests ; and there is no extent of wild, unsettled country 
                  <lb/>
               between them and the seat of Government. We are divided by upwards of 4,000 miles from 
                  <lb/>
               Halifax, 2,000 of which is an unknown wilderness. Some explorers who have travelled by that 
                  <lb/>
               route say, that the greater part of the country is alkaline and unfit for settlement. There is, 
                  <lb/>
               no doubt, a large tract of fertile land in the valley of the Saskatchewan, but much of the inter<lb break="no"/>vening territory is unknown. I ask, Sir, is not our position as a territory of Great Britain, far 
                  <lb/>
               in advance of what it would be as a Province of the Dominion? Will not the change operate 
                  <lb/>
               disadvantageously? 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We know that our interests can hardly conflict with those of Great Britain ; can we say the 
                  <lb/>
               same as regards the Dominion. Canada is hampered by her vast territory, and the larger that 
                  <lb/>
               territory becomes, the greater her weakness will be. But, Sir, I ask of what use is this vast 
                  <lb/>
               territory, unpeopled and uncultivated. Canada wants population and capital ; this Colony wants 
                  <lb/>
               the same. Upon looking at the returns of population, I find that two-thirds of the emigrants 
                  <lb/>
               go over the border to the United States, and many native-born Canadians go to the United 
                  <lb/>
               States, because they find there a more genial climate, and more work to do. If Canada teemed 
                  <lb/>
      
            
                  
            <pb n="15" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_015.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            <fw type="num">15<lb/></fw>
            
        
               with population like England, where people cannot find work for their hands to do, I could 
                  <lb/>
               conceive it likely that we might acquire population through Canada, but I cannot see how we 
                  <lb/>
               can gain population unless a Railway were not only commenced, but in such a state of progress 
                  <lb/>
               as to be a means and inducement for population to come into the country, and this is not likely, 
                  <lb/>
               in my opinion, to be the case. I have listened to what my Honourable colleague has said about 
                  <lb/>
               the agricultural interests, and I entirely coincide with him. Our farmers cannot compete with 
                  <lb/>
               the farmers of the United States under the Canadian Tariff. In the United States, farmers 
                  <lb/>
               are able to get everything that they want within their own country, whilst here everything 
                  <lb/>
               comes from abroad. Until the farmers of this Colony can make everything that they require 
                  <lb/>
               for their own use, they cannot compete with those of the United States. We can always import 
                  <lb/>
               American goods, even under a heavy duty, cheaper than Canadian goods, and this, Sir, will put 
                  <lb/>
               this Province under a different condition as compared with other Provinces. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Let us then suppose this Confederation scheme carried out; we will consider the sacrifice 
                  <lb/>
               completed, the victim decorated with the conditions which have been graciously accorded by 
                  <lb/>
               the more powerful contracting party. What will become of our farmers? I refer more 
                  <lb/>
               particularly to the farmers of the Island and of the Lower Fraser. This class I look upon 
                  <lb/>
               as the bone and sinew of the country. They, Sir, I say, will be driven out of their own market 
                  <lb/>
               by the cheaper productions of the States. And, I would ask, what industry it is supposed will 
                  <lb/>
               take the place of agriculture? Moreover, Sir, I would ask it we be confederated upon these 
                  <lb/>
               terms, what guarantee has the Colony that the terms will be carried out? We all know that 
                  <lb/>
               when compacts are made between a large and a small power, the larger can break the treaty 
                  <lb/>
               with impunity when an emergency arises. Would Canada hesitate, in the event of having to 
                  <lb/>
               repel a Fenian invasion, to abandon the Railway? We have no guarantee that the Dominion 
                  <lb/>
               will carry out: the terms to which her statesmen may agree. We may be abandoned at any 
                  <lb/>
               time. The benefits of the larger Provinces of Canada will always take precedence of those 
                  <lb/>
               of British Columbia, whose representatives will be in a small minority. And I would never 
                  <lb/>
               consent to Confederation on any terms without an Imperial guarantee that the terms would 
                  <lb/>
               he observed and kept. History tells us that in a compact between a larger and smaller country, 
                  <lb/>
               the smaller must go to the wall. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I sum up my objections to Confederation in a few words: 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               At the present time, I think that any terms will be inimical to this Colony, on account of 
                  <lb/>
               our distance from Canada; on account of, the smallness of our population, for we never can have 
                  <lb/>
               an equal vote in the Dominion Parliament with other Provinces; on account of the danger of 
                  <lb/>
               our farming interests being killed and crushed; and on account of the unsettled state of the 
                  <lb/>
               intervening territory; and even it the North-West Territory were confederated, what advantage 
                  <lb/>
               would it be to us? 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Our Confederation would be a source of weakness to Canada, and to ourselves. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We are so far separated from Canada, that she can only communicate with us by telegraph 
                  <lb/>
               through the United States, and by ships round the southern extremity of the American Continent. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We are told that Confederation is an Imperial necessity. We have nothing to do with this. 
                  <lb/>
               We must look to our own interests. Confederation is a political idea; it may be part of the 
                  <lb/>
               Imperial policy, but what of that? We are told that Great Britain desires to get rid of all 
                  <lb/>
               her Colonies. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               These are serious matters for consideration, and this question ought not to be dealt with 
                  <lb/>
               as a party measure. I offer these remarks in the hope that any legislation which may result 
                  <lb/>
               from this debate, after it has received popular sanction, may be enduring and of advantage to 
                  <lb/>
               the Colony. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
       
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">The Hon. Mr. RING</persName>, Member for Nanaimo, said :—Mr. President,
                  I rise to second the amend<lb break="no"/>ment of the Hon. Member for Victoria,
                  and in doing so I abstain from dealing with the merits <lb/> of the question. It
                  appears that the Governor wishes to have a popular vote upon the question <lb/> of
                  Confederation. I say, then, let there be an extended suffrage given, so that the
                  voice of the <lb/> people may be heard in this House. I hope that the people will
                  have the opportunity of <lb/> expressing their opinion, Aye or No, whether they
                  will have Confederation. The people should <lb/> not be bound by what occurs in a
                  Council constituted as this is. <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I say, Sir, that the material question for decision is not that of terms. The Government, 
                  <lb/>
               it this amendment is carried, will have the opportunity of hearing the voice of the people. On 
                  <lb/>
               behalf of my constituents, I say they do not want Confederation; they believe that it is undesir<lb break="no"/> <pb n="16" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_016.jpg"/><fw type="num">16</fw><fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>able at present. The proper way to find out the opinion of the country is for the Governor 
                  <lb/>
               to give us the enlarged representation promised. Let the question come before the people in a 
                  <lb/>
               fair way. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I do not desire to go into the general question of terms of Confederation upon this occasion. 
                  <lb/>
               But I must say, Sir, that these resolutions are not based upon the minds of the people. I 
                  <lb/>
               protest, Sir, against the people's name being mixed up with those resolutions. I reserve what 
                  <lb/>
               I have to say on the question of terms, and support the amendment of the Hon. Member for 
                  <lb/>
               Victoria, in order that the people may have an opportunity of passing their vote upon the 
                  <lb/>
               question of Confederation. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">The Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS</persName>, Member for Lillooet, moved the
                  adjournment of the debate. <lb/> Withdrawn. <lb/>
               </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">The Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName>, Member for New Westminster, rose and
                  said :—Sir, I had intended <lb/> to reserve any remarks that I intended to offer
                  until the terms submitted by the Government <lb/> were under debate in Committee,
                  but I have an objection to the adjournment of the debate at <lb/> this early hour.
                  I cannot, however, allow certain expressions which have fallen from the <lb/>
                  Honourable the senior Member for Victoria City to pass unnoticed. I believe the
                  question for <lb/> us to consider is,—Shall we have Confederation, and upon what
                  terms? <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I believe this House is ready to say Aye to the first question, and to go into Committee of 
                  <lb/>
               the Whole on the second. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I am surprised to find an Honourable Member of this House, who is a Cabinet Minister, 
                  <lb/>
               expressing his regret that this measure has come down to this Council as a Government 
                  <lb/>
               measure. I think that the freedom of his remarks contradicts the idea that it is a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment measure, in the sense that Government Members must vote for it. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I was also surprised to hear the Honourable Member, who is a Cabinet Minister, say that 
                  <lb/>
               Confederation would not be the only issue at the polls, but that there was another place besides 
                  <lb/>
               Ottawa to which we could go. "I had hoped that all allusion to this matter would have been 
                  <lb/>
               kept out of this debate; for I say, Sir, that this vague language can have but one meaning, 
                  <lb/>
               particularly when it is added that the United States will ultimately absorb British Columbia, 
                  <lb/>
               and Canada as well. The Honourable Member evidently means—Shall we have Confederation, 
                  <lb/>
               or accept, as an alternative, Annexation? As everything that comes from the Honourable 
                  <lb/>
               Member is entitled to great weight, and especially as he is a Member of the Government, I <lb/>think we have a right to know whether that is really the issue or not. I had hoped that 
                  <lb/>
               this debate would have been carried through without the necessity of making use of the word 
                  <lb/>
               "Annexation"; but as the subject has been dragged in by a Member of the Government, I trust 
                  <lb/>
               I shall be pardoned for alluding to it. I say, Sir, that if the Government really means to ask 
                  <lb/>
               whether the people desire Confederation or another union, let us know it. ["No, no," from 
                  <lb/>
               the <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Attorney—General</persName> and <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Mr. Trutch</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">The Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName></supplied> I am at a loss to understand the position of the 
                  <lb/>
               Honourable Member for Victoria. I am anxious to have it explained. If he has not repre<lb break="no"/>sented Cabinet views correctly, this House should be set right. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Waiving these matters, and assuming that the Honourable Member will be able to explain 
                  <lb/>
               the apparent paradox, I pass on to the objections raised. I find the Honourable Member 
                  <lb/>
               distinctly setting himself in opposition to Confederation. I will not follow him for the purpose 
                  <lb/>
               of rebutting so-called arguments against Confederation. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            <p>
               The Honourable gentleman tells us that confederation is unnecessary, that this Colony is 
                  <lb/>
               one of the richest spots on the face of the earth, with a climate inferior to no part of the 
                  <lb/>
               world—why should it not go on alone? And he tells us that this view of the question is taken<lb/>by the majority of the people of the Colony. Why, Sir, the Colony has had all this opportunity 
                  <lb/>
               for fifteen years; and what is the fact? Ten years ago the Colony had a very much larger 
                  <lb/>
               population than now, and very much larger commerce. Are we, then, under these circum<lb break="no"/>stances, to ask the people to wait and work out their own salvation? But, Sir, in addition, we 
                  <lb/>
               are told in a State paper that we are not to be allowed to hang on the skirts of Great 
                  <lb/>
               Britain, like a mendicant's child. I can hardy reconcile the position of manly independence 
                  <lb/>
               with the position of hanging on to unwilling Imperial skirts. Rather than that, I would ask 
                  <lb/>
               for union with the Sandwich Islands, or with Hindostan. British Columbia has tried long 
                  <lb/>
               enough to get on by herself. After fifteen years hard struggle, she finds herself worse off than 
                  <lb/>
               she was at the beginning. Her progress has been like that of the crab—backward. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
            <pb n="17" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_017.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            <fw type="num">17</fw>
            
            
            <p>
               She might make progress, but, unfortunately, her form of Government has rendered progress <lb/>impossible. I believe that the illiberal form of Government has had much to do with keeping 
                  <lb/>
               away population—with <hi rendition="simple:italic">driving</hi> away population,—and with destroying the spirit of manly 
                  <lb/>
               enterprise of those who are here. Apart from its being the policy of the British Government 
                  <lb/>
               to unite all the British American Colonies in one great Confederation, if we persist in remain- <lb/>ing alone we shall be told by the Imperial Government that we are not fit for liberal institutions, 
                  <lb/>
               and not prepared for self-government. We should get no amelioration. Downing Street officials 
                  <lb/>
               would say that we are not fit for Responsible Government, and that we ought to confederate. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               There is no difficulty in showing that Confederation will be beneficial to British Columbia; 
                  <lb/>
               that is to say, Confederation on proper terms. I do not say that Confederation would be entirely 
                  <lb/>
               satisfactory on the terms proposed in the Government programme. The terms, although 
                  <lb/>
               excellent, do not go far enough; but I can hardly understand any man taking the position that 
                  <lb/>
               under those terms, even as they are, Confederation would not be beneficial. The public works 
                  <lb/>
               proposed would make the population of the Colony double what it is now. No man can conceal  
                  <lb/>
               from himself, looking at the question dispassionately, that the construction of the Railway 
                  <lb/>
               alone would bring a very great increase to our labouring and productive population. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We are told that the tariff of the Dominion would crush our farming and industrial 
                  <lb/>
               interests. Why, Sir, that tariff is a little more than a third lighter than ours, and would 
                  <lb/>
               relieve us of that one-third of present taxation; and our Customs duties, it must be borne in 
                  <lb/>
               mind, are taken by the Dominion Government. Although, in its present form, the tariff would 
                  <lb/>
               be ill-adapted to some of our local interests which we desire to protect, it should be remembered 
                  <lb/>
               that the Canadian tariff is now under revision, as regards the free admission of American 
                  <lb/>
               productions; and under Confederation we shall in all probability have a treaty of reciprocity; 
                  <lb/>
               or, if not, certainly a revised tariff which would meet American productions, which now find a 
                  <lb/>
               free market in the Dominion, with a protective duty. The argument  of the Honourable 
                  <lb/>
               Member with regard to tariff and farming interests is then swept away by that fact. [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. 
                  <lb/>
               Helmcken</persName>—" Is it a fact?"] 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            
            
            <p>
              <supplied><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">The Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName></supplied> This subject is one of the greatest importance. All other questions are overshadowed by<lb/>it. It is the most important one ever debated on the British Pacific. It has been justly said 
                  <lb/>
               it is a step for life, for better for worse. The question must be approached in a fair spirit, and 
                  <lb/>
               in dealing with it we ought to be thoroughly honest with ourselves; and in dealing with facts, 
                  <lb/>
               I hope that allowance will be made for what has been said, for I believe that much of the 
                  <lb/>
               present opposition arises out of ancient prejudices. Why do we find an Honourable gentleman 
                  <lb/>
               who has grown grey in the service of his country, and for whom we have respect amounting 
                  <lb/>
               to veneration, talking of centralization of every interest under Confederation at Ottawa? Does 
                  <lb/>
               the union of Washington Territory and Oregon with other States of the Great Republic mean 
                  <lb/>
               centralization at Washington? [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr Helmcken</persName> "Yes."] 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               <supplied><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">The Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName></supplied> Then, Sir, where would be the advantage of union in that other direction that has been 
                  <lb/>
               alluded to? Certain persons are fond of talking about the advantages of Annexation; all 
                  <lb/>
               arguments in its favour can be brought with redoubled force in favour of Confederation. 
                  <lb/>
               British Columbia as a member of the Union would have a Pacific frontage, but only in common 
                  <lb/>
               with other countries of the Union. As a part of the Dominion she would have more, for she 
                  <lb/>
               would be the only outlet of the British Confederacy on the Pacific Coast.  
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Exception has been taken by the Honourable gentleman to the fishery laws of the Dominion; 
                  <lb/>
               and it is said that the whales and salmon will cry out for Confederation to protect them. If 
                  <lb/>
               the Canadian fishery laws were enforced in their present form, it is possible that the salmon 
                  <lb/>
               might escape, and the whales might spout with impunity; but we have a right to expect that 
                  <lb/>
               the Dominion Parliament will adapt these laws to this Colony, on the representations of the 
                  <lb/>
               Members from this Province. It would be absurd to suppose that, if the fishery laws of the 
                  <lb/>
               Dominion were inimical to British Columbia, they would be enforced; the nature of the union 
                  <lb/>
               will be such as to make the interests of this part of the Dominion identical with other parts. 
                  <lb/>
               We cannot suppose that the Dominion Parliament would seek to injure this Province. A man 
                  <lb/>
               would not wantonly injure the smallest member of his body. He could not do so without 
                  <lb/>
               feeling it. No man can neglect or injure any member of his own body with impunity. If one 
                  <lb/>
               member, however humble, suffers, all the members will suffer with it. Community of interest 
                  <lb/>
               is the best guarantee for fair play to every section. The Dominion is made up of Provinces, 
                  <lb/>
               and the prosperity of the Dominion means the prosperity of the Provinces of which it is <lb/>composed. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
      
            
            <pb n="18" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-09_Page_018.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">18</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATE DEBATE.</fw>
            
           
            
            <p>
               If we could believe that the Government of the Dominion were composed of men of so 
                  <lb/>
               little wisdom as the opponents of Confederation seem to think, I would say, do not let us join 
                  <lb/>
               them. But I believe, Sir, and the Imperial Government believes, and British Columbia believes, 
                  <lb/>
               that the Government of the Dominion is composed of statesmen. And I say, Sir, that since 
                  <lb/>
               these statesmen have grasped the great idea of Confederation, they have proved themselves 
                  <lb/>
               fit to govern an empire. I am surprised to find any Honourable Member venturing to suggest 
                  <lb/>
               that Canada either could not, or would not, fulfil her pledges. The Dominion Government is 
                  <lb/>
               one and the same in this matter with the Imperial Government. The Imperial Government 
                  <lb/>
               stands at the hack of the Dominion Government, and will be equally concerned in the fulfilment 
                  <lb/>
               of the stipulations in their integrity. It will be time to impugn the honour of Canada when she 
                  <lb/>
               refuses to keep the terms. With regard to Nova Scotia, a departure was made from the terms 
                  <lb/>
               of union. The Imperial Government, and the Canadian Government, considered that certain 
                  <lb/>
               concessions ought to be made, and they were made, but only to add to the terms in favour of 
                  <lb/>
               Nova Scotia. British Columbia places herself in a false position before Canada, and before 
                  <lb/>
               the world, in saying that there is any doubt as to whether the Dominion would fulfil the 
                  <lb/>
               terms 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               With regard, again, to the tariff. I think that the only arguments against Confederation 
                  <lb/>
               worthy of consideration, are against the present Canadian Tariff. The Customs Tariff is a 
                  <lb/>
               federal matter, and I confess that the arguments against the applicability of the present scale 
                  <lb/>
               to British Columbia are entitled to notice; but, Sir, as I said before, I think these arguments 
                  <lb/>
               are to a great extent met by the fact that we shall have an amended tariff, or a reciprocity 
                  <lb/>
               treaty. But if we could hit upon some scheme that, Without infringing the Dominion preroga<lb break="no"/>tives, would meet our requirements, it would be most desirable, and shall have my hearty 
                  <lb/>
               support:  
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               In conclusion, Sir, the Government measure shall meet with my hearty support, so far as 
                  <lb/>
               it goes. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It affords me unspeakable gratification to find that Government has sent down a measure  
                  <lb/>
               for Confederation which can hardly be cavilled at. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               While feeling pleasure in giving a hearty general support to this measure, I shall reserve 
                  <lb/>
               to myself the right to suggest that other items shall be placed in the list now before the House. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I believe there are terms of the greatest importance which ought to be added. But anything 
                  <lb/>
               that can be added will not meet the wishes of the people of this Colony, unless the fundamental 
                  <lb/>
               principle of self-government accompanies them. I believe that the Canadians are a great, a 
                  <lb/>
               wise, and a conservative people; but I conceive we should be doing a great wrong to ourselves,  
                  <lb/>
               to our children, and to those who are to come after us, if we left out Responsible Government. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Suppose, Sir, the case of three persons forming a partnership; if the third partner, coming 
                  <lb/>
               in subsequently, should consent to leave the management of his private affairs to the firm, 
                  <lb/>
               he would not only be giving up his own rights, but he would be throwing into the partnership 
                  <lb/>
               a great element of discord. I say, then, that while Canada necessarily and properly asks us 
                  <lb/>
               to surrender the larger questions, she does not ask us to relinquish our smaller and local 
                  <lb/>
               rights, and if we give them up we shall be doing a wanton thing and a great wrong. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               In promising my support, therefore, I make this reservation: That, if this Colony is to 
                  <lb/>
               become a Province of Canada, the people of British Columbia shall have the right to manage 
                  <lb/>
               their own local affairs, as fully as every other Province has. For, while I agree with the 
                  <lb/>
               Honourable Junior Member for Victoria, that the change from Downing Street to Ottawa would 
                  <lb/>
               be useless without a change in the system of Government, I say that it would be most 
                  <lb/>
               injurious to go into Confederation upon terms which might inaugurate a fresh era of political 
                  <lb/>
               agitation, which would probably continue for a series of years.  
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon MR. HELMCKEN</persName>—Sir, I rise for the purpose of explaining.
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I deny that I uttered any such thing as that the choice would be put to the people by the 
                  <lb/>
               Government between two issues of Confederation and any other union. But that if the 
                  <lb/>
               Canadian Government refuses to agree to terms equivalent to these, but chooses to offer some 
                  <lb/>
               mean terms for consideration, when it comes to the polls the people themselves will raise the 
                  <lb/>
               issue between Confederation and the only other change which offers itself for consideration. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The debate was here adjourned until Thursday, at 1 o'clock. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
           
            
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>