<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgBCLC_1870-03-16" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgBCLC">British Columbia Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1870-03-16">16 March 1870</date>, Province of BC, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgBCLC">
          

         <editor>W.S. Sebright Green</editor>
          
         
               <title>Legislative Council, Debate on the Subject of Confederation with Canada</title>.
                    

          <date when="1912"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Victoria, B.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>William H. Cullin</publisher>.
                    
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="68" to="82"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_068.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_069.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_070.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_071.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_072.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_073.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_074.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_075.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_076.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_077.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_078.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_079.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_080.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_081.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_082.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-17">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-21">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_068">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_068.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_069">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_069.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_070">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_070.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_071">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_071.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_072">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_072.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_073">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_073.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_074">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_074.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_075">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_075.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_076">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_076.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_077">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_077.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_078">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_078.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_079">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_079.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_080">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_080.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_081">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_081.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_082">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_082.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="68" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_068.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">68</fw> <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>


<!-- GL, 2017-03-17, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

 <!--<p>
     the House of Commons will give us, as has been suggested, almost the balance of power between 
     <lb/>
     parties: eight, standing firmly together, will have great influence ; but what would be our 
     <lb/>
     influence with two? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After a few words from Hon. Mr. Humphreys in support of the basis of population, as 
     <lb/>
     disclosed in the scheme of the Hon. Mr. DeCosmos. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The several recommendations of the Hon. Messrs. DeCosmos, Drake, and Robson were read 
     <lb/>
     by the Clerk. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Some discussion ensued as to how the vote was to be taken, and the Chairman decided to 
     <lb/>
     put the recommendations of Hon. Mr. DeCosmos first, by itself, and then the recommendation 
     <lb/>
     of Hon. Mr. Drake, which was an amendment on the recommendation of Hon. Mr. Robson. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The recommendation of the Hon. Mr. DeCosmos, on a division, was lost. Ayes 5, Noes 14. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The recommendation of the Hon. Mr. Drake, as an amendment to that of the Hon. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Robson, on a division, was carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Clauses 2 and 3 were then passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On motion, the Committee rose. and asked leave to sit again. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. DeCosmos voted against the Report of the Committee being adopted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     House adjourned at 6 p.m. until 1 o'clock on Wednesday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     WEDNESDAY, 16th MARCH, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>
     Committee sat at a quarter-past one. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CREA1">The Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> moved the adoption of Clause 4:-
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            <p>"4. The Dominion shall guarantee Interest at the rate of 5 per centum per annum on 
     <lb/>
     "such sum, not exceeding £100,000, as may he required for the construction of a first-class 
     <lb/>
     " Graving Dock at Esquimalt." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     He said :—It is pretty generally known that a company was started for the construction 
     <lb/>
     of a Graving Dock at Esquimalt, and that negotiations with that object in view had taken 
     <lb/>
     place under a former administration; but although both the Admirals and Governor Seymour 
     <lb/>
     had reported in favour of it, the thing had fallen through. owing to the inability of the company 
     <lb/>
     to obtain the necessary funds. They were, only able to get a small loan in aid from the 
     <lb/>
     Admiralty. The Dominion guarantee of 5 per cent. on £100,000 sterling, with a prospect of 
     <lb/>
     ultimate profits from the undertaking itself, will, it is believed, secure the whole amount of 
     <lb/>
     capital required, which has been variously estimated ; but from preliminary surveys and investi<lb break="no"/>gations which have been made, the sum of £100,000 is deemed sufficient, and there is little 
     <lb/>
     doubt that if a company can get a guarantee for that amount, they can carry out the under<lb break="no"/>taking on the largest practicable scale. I am aware that some opposition has been expressed 
     <lb/>
     to the locality ; but it is to be supported on general grounds. It will be general to the whole 
     <lb/>
     Colony. £100,000 cannot be spent in any part of the Colony without benefiting the rest of 
     <lb/>
     it. The Navy are at Esquimalt. Esquimalt is the first port which ocean ships reach when 
     <lb/>
     they want repair. and the last point they leave when they receive sailing orders. Captain 
     <lb/>
     Richards, and all the Admiral from first to last, have reported in favour of Esquimalt for a 
     <lb/>
     dock. Without Admiralty patronage and aid the thing could not succeed. Another advantage 
     <lb/>
     in a dock would be, that it would enable us to utilize our great white elephant, the dredger. 
     <lb/>
     As to any opposition to the locality for Burrard Inlet and New Westminster, though as much 
     <lb/>
     interested as any Hon. Member round this Board in those places, I must say that they already 
     <lb/>
     have the larger share of benefit from the terms ; for in my opinion the Overland Railway must 
     <lb/>
     follow down the main artery of the Colony. Fraser River. and have its terminus either at New 
     <lb/>
     Westminster or Burrard Inlet. Therefore, on public grounds, and because I believe that it will 
     <lb/>
     be a public benefit. I support the establishment of a Graving Dock at Esquimalt. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">The Hon. MR. HOLBROOK</persName>—Sir, I rise to oppose this clause,
                  because I deem it too <lb/> sectional; all sectional views should be set aside. 1
                  think the locality should certainly be left <lb/> out, and the question decided
                  hereafter. I have no objection to getting all the money we can <lb/> from Canada.
                  but I am not sure that there is any present necessity for a dock, I believe that
                  <lb/> for some time to come it will be cheaper to send ships to San Francisco.
                  What is wanted is <lb/>
                  <pb n="69" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_069.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">69</fw> one of Clarke's Patent Slips. We shall, before long, have
                  plenty of ships at Burrard Inlet, <lb/> and when the community requires it we
                  shall have plenty of private parties ready to come <lb/> forward to construct
                  them. Both at Burrard Inlet and New Westminster there is so great <lb/> a rise and
                  fall in the tide that they would be good places. I have been asked to support the
                  <lb/> substitution of Burrard Inlet for Esquimalt in the terms, but I will not do
                  so ; I would prefer <lb/> striking out the name altogether. We ought, I say, to
                  let go sectional ideas. and go in for the <lb/> public good. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> said:—Sir, I am at a loss to understand
                  any opposition to this <lb/> clause. Any such guarantee, if it lead to the
                  expenditure of so much money in any part of <lb/> the Colony, will be an advantage
                  to the whole community. It is an easily understood benefit. <lb/> It will not, in
                  my opinion, make much difference where it is built ; perhaps it would be better
                  <lb/> to leave the selection of the locality to a Committee, who might indicate to
                  the Canadian <lb/> Government the best locality. I am of opinion that we want a
                  Graving Dock ; we don't want <lb/> ships to go to San Francisco. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>, Member for New Westminster, said:—I may,
                  perhaps, be expected <lb/> to oppose this clause, and ask for New Westminster to
                  be inserted. but I shall not do so. I have <lb/> no sectiona1 feelings in
                  supporting Confederation. I think the word Esquimalt is perfectly <lb/> harmless,
                  although, like my Hon. friend (Mr. Holbrook), I should have preferred that no
                  <lb/> locality had been named. I do not think that naming the spot will, of
                  itself, decide the question. <lb/> The Dock will, no doubt, be built in the most
                  suitable place. As the Word is in, let it remain. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName> said:—Sir, I agree with what has fallen from
                  Hon. Members who object <lb/> to the naming of the locality, and I shall move that
                  the word "Esquimalt" be struck out, <lb/> and the words "such place as the
                  Dominion Government shall appoint" be inserted. I desire, <lb/> if we are to have
                  this organic change, that we should be free of sectional and local feelings <lb/>
                  of irritation The naming of Esquimalt as the locality for the Dock seems to me to
                  be an <lb/> endeavour to purchase the good-will of Victoria, whose population is
                  known to be anti- <lb break="yes"/> confederate ["No, no," from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DeCosmos</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName></supplied> —of
                  Victoria, which stood the test of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion at the last
                  election, and whose Members sit here pledged against Confederation. This is <lb/>
                  bidding for the favour of the Victoria constituency. ["No, no," from <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hons.
                  Attorney-General</persName> <lb/> and <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Chief Commissioner</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName></supplied> I judge of the effect which it is
                  likely to have upon others by the <lb/> effect it has upon me. I own some small
                  portion of land at Esquimalt, at Constance Cove, <lb/> near the probable site of
                  the Docks, and that, I confess, has a softening effect upon me ; and <lb/> though
                  I do not allow it to influence my vote, it does influence my mind. [Laughter.]
                     Con<lb break="no"/>federation, as the Hon. Member for Victoria (Mr. Helmcken)
                  has said, means a Railway, <lb/> Docks, and money ; it means to each person the
                  possibility of getting $1,000 at the end of two <lb/> years, or $100 a month in
                  rents. I do not believe that these terms will be submitted to, and <lb/> if the
                  inducements are taken away, I say the people will not have Confederation. If they
                  do <lb/> accept it under the inducement of material benefits, I fear that we shall
                  very shortly see a <lb/> strong feeling of reaction. Why should we name Esquimalt?
                  What right have we to do so, <lb/> if it is not intended to have effect on the
                  Victorian interest? Why not leave it open? If <lb/> Esquimalt is named, it seems
                  to me to tie down the Dominion Government to a locality of <lb/> which they may
                  not approve, and may be disadvantageous to the negotiation. The more that <lb/> is
                  left to the Dominion Government, the better is the chance of carrying out the
                  negotiations <lb/> successfully. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> - What is the estimated cost of
                  constructing the Docks? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—£100,000 <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—I think, Mr. Chairman, that it is
                  much to be regretted <lb/> that the Hon. Mr. Wood has attributed not very
                  creditable motives to the Government. <lb/> [" Hear, hear."] I am sorry to have to
                  say so. I am sorry I cannot congratulate him on <lb/> statesmanlike qualities when
                  he says he might have been influenced. I have never taken <lb/> this view. I
                  believe the influence of a vote never occurred to any Member of the Executive
                  <lb/> Council. I protest against such insinuations. I congratulate the Hon. Member
                  for New <lb/> Westminster upon the course he has taken, and on his support of: the
                  Government without <lb/> reference to any sectional views. I feel bound to explain
                  why Esquimalt has been named <lb/> by the Government. The main object in asking
                  for a Graving Dock there is to secure the <lb/> headquarters of the Navy on the
                  Pacific Coast within the Colony. When you come to remember <lb/> that Esquimalt is
                  the Naval Station, and has been for years, and when you come to consider <lb/>
                  <pb n="70" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_070.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">70</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> that assistance is offered by the
                  Imperial Government, it will not be difficult to discern that <lb/> there was
                  reason on our side. I could give you good commercial reasons, but it is sufficient
                  <lb/> to say that the Government named Esquimalt especially with a view to the
                  retention of <lb/> the Fleet. Both the late Admiral and the late Governor agreed
                  in reporting in favour of <lb/> Esquimalt. We should, therefore, have been remiss
                  in not pointing it out. I think it hard <lb/> that the Government should be
                  twitted with the intention of catching votes. [" Hear, hear," <lb/> from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr.
                  DeCosmos</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName></supplied> I scout the idea. There is an Imperial Act, which only allows the <lb/>
                  Admiralty to lend a limited sum to Colonial Docks—the Act, of 28 and 29 Victoria,
                  Cap. 206. <lb/> This Act allows a loan of £20,000 from the Admiralty upon certain
                  terms; it is a loan of so <lb/> much money that is contemplated, and not a
                  guarantee of interest. Last year I stated to this <lb/> Council that the Admiralty
                  had offered to lend £20,000, at 4 per cent. The Company did not <lb/> think it
                  sufficient inducement. We hope to get Imperial assistance still; that is one
                  reason <lb/> for the locality being named. I stand here to say that Esquimalt is
                  the place. I am surprised <lb/> that a Member from the Mainland should bring an
                  accusation of sectional proclivities against <lb/> the Government in this matter,
                  for the Railway will specially benefit the Mainland. I believe <lb/> and hope it
                  will follow down the Valley of the Fraser, and immediately benefit the district
                  from <lb/> which the Hon. Member comes. Fraser River is the main artery and the
                  probable course of <lb/> the Railway. I did not, therefore. expect to hear of any
                  sectional prejudice in the Resolutions <lb/> from any Member from the Mainland,
                  when, if there is any immediate benefit to any special <lb/> locality, it will be
                  to the Mainland of British Columbia. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. Mr. RING</persName>, Member for Nanaimo, said :—Sir, I am prepared
                  to support the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment upon this clause. Why should we set
                  ourselves up in opposition to the opinion of the <lb/> successive Admirals who
                  have been upon this station, and who can have no prejudices? I <lb/> think it is a
                  waste of public time to impute motives. Esquimalt has been pronounced by <lb/>
                  engineers to be the proper place. I am not one of those who, like certain Hon.
                  Members <lb/> here, would constantly "pin their conscience on their sleeves for
                  daws to peck at." Such <lb/> motives as are suggested could never have entered
                  into the minds of the Executive. They <lb/> have been repelled by the Hon. Chief
                  Commissioner, and why should we be accused of giving <lb/> personal votes? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName>— No personal motives are imputed. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName>—It seems like such an imputation. I think the
                  Hon. Member should <lb/> withdraw his motion. Consider how such a principle as
                  that suggested by the Hon. Mr. Wood <lb/> would work. It in effect amounts to
                  this: "Because you have a local interest, you must refrain <lb/> from supporting
                  by your vote what you conscientiously approve of as beneficial to the <lb/>
                  community." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName>—I must correct my Hon. friend (Mr. Ring). I do
                  not attribute personal <lb/> motives in any improper sense; but I say, is there a
                  butcher, or baker, or any other man, who <lb/> will, in these days of pressure,
                  fail to vote as his pocket will be influenced? The material <lb/> benefit to the
                  individual is an influence at all elections, and rightly so. I can see, in my
                  <lb/> mind's eye, banners floating at the next general election, and can imagine
                  placards posted <lb/> with the inscription in the largest type: "Vote for DeCosmos
                  and the Esquimalt Dock." <lb/> This object may not be intentional, but yet can it
                  be otherwise? What is it? Intending <lb/> without intending? I deny that I impure
                  any dishonest motive in the Executive, but it is <lb/> clear that the Dock at
                  Esquinialt will influence many votes, and I confess I gave them credit <lb/> for
                  foreseeing so obvious a consequence. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—I say this, Sir, that if any such
                  motives had guided <lb/> the Executive Council; if any considerations, such as
                  have been suggested, had swayed them; <lb/> if the object had been a different
                  one, we could have prepared a much more palatable dish; we <lb/> could have shown
                  you pecuniary advantages. If we had had the intention to get votes, we <lb/> could
                  have framed the Resolutions very differently. But they were framed with no such
                  views. <lb/> It was the intention of the Government to prepare terms on a fair and
                  proper basis to be <lb/> submitted to the people. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName>—As a Member of the Executive Council, Sir,
                  I confess that I <lb/> was pleased to see Esquimalt mentioned as the site for the
                  Docks. I will meet the Hon. Mr. <lb/> Wood on this isue, and say that supposing
                  this is put in for the sake of gaining the vote of <lb/> the Victoria people, what
                  is Confederation? Confederation moans union to benefit every part <lb/> of the
                  Colony. To follow out the Hon. Member's reasoning, there should have been no
                  public <lb/>
                  <pb n="71" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_071.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">71</fw> works at all named in the conditions. I state that the
                  insertion of Esquimalt in the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment Resolutions was not
                  governed by sectional prejudices. The Executive Council took the <lb/> broad view
                  that is was for the interest of the Canadian Government to build this Dock,
                  because <lb/> if Victoria prospers under Confederation, it will be so much better
                  for the Dominion revenue. <lb/> If the work is a benefit to Victoria, through
                  bringing labourers, it will benefit the whole Colony, <lb/> and our position will
                  be improved, and therefore we shall become a more important part of the <lb/>
                  Dominion. If it pleases the people of Victoria, if they consider it a sufficient
                  inducement to <lb/> go into Confederation, let them do so. The people of Victoria
                  are here to make money, and <lb/> not to found empires; their children may perhaps
                  make the kingdoms and empires. If the <lb/> people like Confederation on these
                  terms, I say let them vote for it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. MR. CARRALL</persName>, Member for Cariboo—" It may not be
                  intentional, but it is so," were <lb/> the concluding words of the Hon. Mr. Wood.
                  I say yes, so far as this: that the whole of the <lb/> conditions of this scheme
                  were intended to benefit the whole of the Colony. As a Member of <lb/> the
                  Executive Council, I repudiate entirely the narrow motives which have been
                  suggested by <lb/> the Hon Mr. Wood. The Executive Council were actuated by no
                  sectional views; their object <lb/> was to make the whole of the Resolutions not
                  only palatable, but beneficial, to the Colony. The <lb/> merits of Esquimalt as a
                  site for the Docks are in themselves a sufficient reason to advance in <lb/>
                  favour of the Executive opinion being correct. I shall vote for the clause as it
                  stands. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—I am one of those who think it proper to
                  have the locality for <lb/> the Docks named; and I think the Government would have
                  made a blunder if they had left <lb/> out the word "Esquimalt." It would have been
                  wrong, in my opinion, if the Government <lb/> had framed the Resolutions with any
                  sectional views. But it appears to me whilst they are <lb/> likely to do the
                  Colony good generally, they have been framed with a tendency to create the <lb/>
                  popular vote, and I do not see much harm in that. The point which I want to hear
                  about is, <lb/> whether £100,000 will be sufficient to construct a good Dock, and
                  what sort of a Dock it is to <lb/> be? It is possible that a large Stone Dock may
                  not be of so much use as a Patent Slip. I <lb/> have visited the Floating Docks in
                  the Arsenals of the United States, to take such observa<lb break="no"/>tions as
                  would serve an unprofessional man; and I confess that if it is to be a Stone
                  Graving <lb/> Dock in Constance Cove, to admit of one vessel at a time, I am
                  inclined to the opinion that it <lb/> would not be as good, nor as much public
                  utility, as a Patent Slip. I shall support the item, <lb/> or a larger sum than
                  £100,000. I believe that a Dock, or a Patent Slip, at Esquimalt, will <lb/>
                  attract ships from Puget Sound. It is a step in the right direction. There is a
                  feeling abroad <lb/> that the Colony would have to construct this Dock. This would
                  be a mistake; but to get <lb/> Canada to endorse the scheme, by giving a guarantee
                  for the interest, is, in my opinion, the <lb/> right course to pursue. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. MR. TRUTCH</persName>—That is the intention; that a private company
                  should undertake the <lb/> work, the Dominion giving a guarantee. it will be left
                  for the company to choose. Probably <lb/> Clarke's Patent Slip, with hydraulic
                  lift, would be the easiest worked, as it would be the <lb/> cheapest. It could
                  probably be erected for £75,000, whereas a cut stone Graving Dock would <lb/> cost
                  more. One of the advantages of the latter would be that there would be more money
                  <lb/> expended in the Colony during its construction, whereas the principal cost
                  of a Patent Slip <lb/> would be expended elsewhere for machinery. I cannot say if
                  £100,000 would be enough for <lb/> the construction of a cut stone Dock or not. I
                  think that a guarantee of 5 per cent. on <lb/> £100,000 will be a sufficient
                  inducement for any company to take the matter up. I am con<lb break="no"/>vinced
                  that £100,000 will not build a stone Dock of sufficient capacity to take in such a
                  ship <lb/> as the Zealous. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName>—If the people of Victoria desire the terms, why
                  should not they vote <lb/> for Union? My desire is, if we are to be united. to see
                  a union which shall be lasting. I say <lb/> that these terms are not lasting. They
                  are in the nature of direct and immediate pecuniary <lb/> advantage. Reaction will
                  set in after the Railway and Dock are built. Show me in these <lb/> terms
                  continuing and abiding benefit, and I am satisfied. Let the people of Victoria
                  choose, <lb/> but I ask Hon. Members, who understand human nature, whether the
                  people would not choose <lb/> direct benefit in preference to prospective and
                  continuing advantages. Mankind will choose <lb/> direct present pecuniary benefit,
                  rather than. that benefit which is to be lasting and remote. <lb/> I fear
                  reaction. I look upon this place as my home, and shall complain, I think with
                  justice, <lb/> if ten years hence I find a great reaction of the present hasty
                  action. <lb/>
               </p>
            <pb n="72" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_072.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">72</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName>—Would it be better to have Confederation
                  with no terms at all, <lb/> or with terms equal to these? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName>—I ask for different terms; power to impose our
                  own tariff, for instance. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName>—The objections of the Hon. Member are not
                  correct. When the <lb/> Dock and Railway are built, I admit that some source of
                  labour, and consequent interest, <lb/> will be gone, but then we must look for
                  other interests to arise. I admit that discontent may <lb/> arise; it has
                  frequently been so in England, when a large number of labourers have been <lb/>
                  thrown out of employment; but I say that the Dominion and Local Governments will
                  have the <lb/> power and the sense to remedy any such evils as they occur. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I cannot fancy anything more calculated
                  to promote perma<lb break="no"/>nent benefit than the establishment of Graving
                  Docks. Every ship that comes in would spend <lb/> money, would be a benefit to the
                  town, and a continuing benefit; and not to the town only, <lb/> but to some extent
                  to the whole Colony. It the Colony goes on and increases, so must the work <lb/>
                  to be done in the Docks go on increasing. I regret that the Hon. Mr. Wood should
                  have taken <lb/> the ground that the Executive are influenced by any sectional
                  motives. I do not see why the <lb/> Hon. Member should refuse benefits which come
                  under Confederation. He would surely not <lb/> prefer to go in without terms.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. Mr. DRAKE</persName>—I doubt whether the amount named is large
                  enough. I have informa<lb break="no"/>tion from good authority that double that
                  amount will be required. Canada is only asked to <lb/> guarantee the interest. I
                  shall, therefore, move an amendment, in the shape of a recommendzv <lb/> tion to
                  His Excellency, that the sum of £100,000 be increased to £150,000 in the
                  conditions I <lb/> am of opinion that the terms should be put in as favourable a
                  light as possible for this Colony. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:PEMB1">Hon. MR. PEMBERTON</persName>—I would ask the Chief Commissioner of
                  Lands and Works <lb/> whether it would be possible to connect the supply of water
                  with the Docks? London is <lb/> supplied by a large fresh water reservoir, and it
                  is possible that the same course might be <lb/> adopted as regards this city. If
                  the course of the water in the valley of Victoria Arm were <lb/> stopped, the
                  Gorge being a natural valley, if it were possible to exclude the salt water from
                  <lb/> the whole of Victoria Harbour, a vast natural reservoir of fresh water might
                  be formed, which <lb/> would supply the whole city with water. Being no engineer,
                  I feel some diffidence in putting <lb/> it forward. I only put it as a suggestion
                  to the Chief Commissioner, with the view of inquir<lb break="no"/>ing whether it
                  could be done. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—It is impossible for me to offer an
                  opinion upon the <lb/> suggestion of the Hon. Mr. Pemberton. The supply of water
                  upon the supposed plan, would <lb/> contemplate the expenditure of much more money
                  than the sum required for Graving Docks. <lb/> Besides the proposed place is too
                  low, and would necessitate the water being pumped up to a <lb/> second reservoir.
                  Moreover, I am of opinion that the supply of water is too much of a local <lb/>
                  matter to be worthy of mention in the terms. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK</persName>— My amendment is, that the word "Esquimalt"
                  be struck out, on <lb/> the ground that it is too sectional. I believe that any
                  Company which is formed will erect <lb/> a Patent Slip instead of a Dock. It has
                  been shown in practice to be more useful. I move <lb/> that the word "Esquinialt "
                  be struck out. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p> Hon. Mr. Wood's reconnuendation to strike out the word "Esquimalt," and to insert
                  <lb/> "such place as the Dominion Government shall appoint," on division was lost,
                  two only voting <lb/> in favour of it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Drake's reconnuendution "That the sum of £150,000 be named," on division was 
     <lb/>
     lost, eight voting in favour of the recommendation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Clause 4 was then passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman then read section 5:- <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" 5. In addition to the other provisions of this Resolution, Canada shall assume and defray 
     <lb/>
     " the charges of the following Services:- <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"(<hi rendition="simple:italic">a</hi>.) Salary and allowances of the Lieutenant-Governor: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "(<hi rendition="simple:italic">b</hi>.) Salaries and Allowances of the Judges and Officers of the Supreme Court, and 
     <lb/>
     " of the County Courts: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "(<hi rendition="simple:italic">c</hi>.) The charges in respect of the Department of Customs: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "(<hi rendition="simple:italic">d</hi>.) The Postal Department: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="73" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_073.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE</fw> <fw type="num">73</fw>

<p>
     "(<hi rendition="simple:italic">e</hi>.) Lighthouses, Buoys, Beacons, and Lightships, and such further charges as may 
     <lb/>
     "be incident to and connected with the services which by 'The British North 
     <lb/>
     "America Act. 1867,' appertain to the General Government, and as are or may be 
     <lb/>
     "allowed to the other Provinces." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

   <p> The <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> moved the adoption of this
                  Clause, which he said <lb/> was taken from "The British North America Act, 1867,"
                  and would relieve the Colony of the <lb/> payment of a certain amount annually in
                  the shape of Salaries. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPRHEYS</persName>—I shall move a recommendation that the
                  maintenance of the <lb/> Roads by the Dominion Government, be included in this
                  Clause. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—This seems to be a made up clause, it is
                  provided for in "The <lb/> British North America Act," and the insertion of the
                  clause in these Resolutions looks like <lb/> setting it before the country for the
                  object of educating them up to what they are expected to <lb/> ask for. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—It is an essential part of the whole
                  scheme. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. MR. TRUTCH</persName>—I think it is partly provided for by "The
                  British North America <lb/> Act; " yet it is included in the Terms of the proposed
                  admission of Newfoundland. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> - And of all the other Provinces. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—I do not agree with the Hon. Member for
                  Victoria District. I think <lb/> the Act of British North America applies to
                  original Provinces, and provision is made for the <lb/> admission of others. They
                  might be presumed to apply to us, but I think it is proper to ask <lb/> in an
                  address that these charges should be put in, and that it is as necessary to insert
                  these <lb/> as it is to insert any clauses. We should make it plain that we desire
                  to have these terms <lb/> applied to us. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—There is no provision in paragraph (<hi rendition="simple:italic">b</hi>) for payment of salaries of <lb/> Judges of
                  Admiralty or District Courts. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName>—I move to strike out these paragraphs; they are
                  mere verbiage. One <lb/> word with respect to the Admiralty Court, which ought to
                  be included if the Supreme Court <lb/> is inserted. ' <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—We have no power, as a Council, to deal
                  with the constitu<lb break="no"/>tion of the Admiralty Court; nor is this the
                  proper time to enter into any discussion respecting <lb/> it. <lb/>
               </p>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName> - I say we have every power, and I take this
                  opportunity of saying that <lb/> the Admiralty Court is badly managed. I have
                  heard it insinuated that the Judges of the <lb/> Admiralty Courts in this Colony
                  have been influenced by fees to prolong the business of the <lb/> Court and drag
                  out Admiralty business to its utmost length, instead of pushing it through, as
                  <lb/> the business of the Common Law Courts is pushed through. There ought to be
                  no fees. <lb/> Admiralty practice in this Colony is likely, in case of war, to
                  assume enormous proportions. I <lb/> do not see why a condition should not be
                  insorted to provide us with an Admiralty Court with <lb/> Judges to be paid by
                  fees. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—Does the Hon. the Attorney-General intend
                  to insert Admiralty <lb/> Court? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—We must not arrogate to ourselves
                  powers which we have <lb/> not; and the insertion of such a clause in the
                  Resolutions which we are now discussing would <lb/> be entirely out of place, and
                  I would suggest to Hon. Members not to introduce this Resolution <lb/> now, but
                  let it be brought up as a substantive measure. It cannot be brought up again, if
                  it <lb/> is decided now. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName>—I said, and I repeat it, that if the Imperial
                  Government were properly <lb/> approached this thingr might be done, just as if
                  the Crown were properly approached, the <lb/> Crown Salaries Act might be
                  repealed. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—I think some action ought to be taken. I
                  wish to call attention <lb/> to the fact that the Canadian Parliament have power
                  to fix the salaries of the Judges in <lb/> Admiralty, where they are paid by
                  salaries. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—-Then bring the matter up separately.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName>—I would draw the Attorney-General's attention
                  to section 100 of the <lb/> British North America Act, which includes Admiralty
                  Courts where the Judges are paid by <lb/> salaries and pensions. It is expressly
                  stated that the terms of the British North America Act <lb/> shall apply to this
                  Colony; then why not insert it in the words} of the Act? Though we are <lb/>
                  <pb n="74" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_074.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">74</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> aware that these Resolutions have to
                  be carried, there is no reason that we should not add <lb/> recommendations. I
                  think section 100 of the Act is better than our clause. I will move the <lb/>
                  addition of the word "pensions" <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName>—I cannot see that the application of section
                  100 would meet the <lb/> case. It would be ineffectual because our Judges of the
                  Admiralty Court are not paid by <lb/> salaries; therefore it would be inoperative
                  as regards British Columbia. Whilst I deem it quite <lb/> desirable to make the
                  change suggested, I do not think this is the time to make it. I should <lb/>
                  suggest postponing the discussion of the question as to the Admiralty Court until
                  these Resolu<lb break="no"/>tions are settled. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. Mr. TRUTCH</persName>—Why complicate the question? Why not bring it
                  up in open <lb/> House and discuss it? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName>—It could be done in three or four months. The
                  Judges of the <lb/> Admiralty Courts could be put upon salaries, and section 100
                  would then be applicable. We <lb/> are upon the question of Judges, and why not
                  decide it at once? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. Mr. TRUTCH</persName>—I am not prepared to discuss this question,
                  as to the Admiralty <lb/> Court, now. It proper notice is given of its being
                  brought up, I shall then be prepared to go <lb/> fully into its merits. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName>—The principle is bad to pay Judges by fees.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. Mr. RING</persName>—The question is: are the Judges of the
                  Admiralty Court, Judges? <lb/> Why should we not say clearly and unmistakeably
                  what we mean? I shall support the recom<lb break="no"/>mendation of the Hon. Mr.
                  Wood, and I hope the members of the Government will pause <lb/> before they oppose
                  it. Let them consider whether it is desirable to admit the principle that <lb/>
                  any person exercising the office of a Judge should be paid by fees. I say that the
                  question is <lb/> properly before us now, and the recommendation comes fairly and
                  correctly in this place. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ALST1">Hon. Mr. ALSTON</persName>—I agree with the Hon. Mr. Wood, as to the
                  Constitution of the <lb/> Admiralty Court, but should vote against the
                  recommendation, and for the Resolution, because <lb/> i do not think that this
                  recommendation, or amendment, for it virtually amounts to that, if <lb/> acted
                  upon by the Executive, would effect the cure; the Judges would still take tees.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I shall be obliged to vote against this
                  recommendation, <lb/> if it is pressed, on account of the way in which it is
                  brought up here. The friends of the <lb/> alteration are those who are refusing to
                  join in bringing it forward at this inopportune time. <lb/> A vote taken now,
                  would prevent free discussion of the subject. I recommend the Hon. <lb/> Member to
                  withdraw his amendment, and I invite full and free discussion of the subject of
                  the <lb/> Admiralty Courts upon a special day to be fixed. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. Mr. TRUTCH</persName>—This discussion is inapporpriate at this
                  time. If this side of the House <lb/> were against the consideration of the
                  payment of Admiralty Judges by fees, they could let it <lb/> pass in Committee,
                  and kill it in the House; then. under our Standing Orders, it could not be <lb/>
                  brought up again, but we do not intend to do so. I shall vote against it <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The Hon. Mr. Wood, with the permission of the Council, withdrew his recommendation, 
     <lb/>
     on the understanding that it was to he brought up at a future day as a distinct motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Hon. Mr. Drake's recommendation as to Pensions was put, and lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName>—It is treating the
                  reconnnendations of non-official members with con<lb break="no"/>tempt and
                  disrespct to find the Government Members voting them down. ["No, no," from <lb/>
               the <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Attorney-General</persName>]. ["Yes, yes," from <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Mr. Drake</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName></supplied> Let us
                  have an opportunity of <lb/> putting our opinion upon record. This Government vote
                  operates as a wet blanket upon all <lb/> occasions. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—It is the common sense of the House,
                  which says that <lb/> recommendations which are against the basis of the
                  Resolutions should not pass. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS</persName>—If what we do is not to meet the eye of
                  the Executive, it is <lb/> of no use being here. I never felt so mean. Our
                  position in this Council is nugatory; utterly <lb/> futile and contemptible. If
                  all the elected members felt as I do, we should leave the Council <lb/> in a body.
                  and have nothing more to do with it. ["Hear. hear," from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DeCosmos</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS</persName></supplied> I find
                  <lb/> it difficult to speak of the Government conduct of business in this House
                  with patience. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. Mr. TRUTCH</persName>—I should really like to know what this is all
                  about. One Hon. <lb/> Member that the course is disrespectful, because the sense
                  of the Council was against him. <lb/> The Hon. Member for Lillooet indulges in a
                  species of harangue which is peculiar to him; when <lb/> he is at a loss for an
                  argument he shakes the red flag of officialdom before him, lowers his head, <lb/>
                  <pb n="75" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_075.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">75</fw> and charges at it madly. With regard to disrespect, I think
                  we treat them with respect by <lb/> discussing them here at all. We might allow
                  them to pass here, and vote them down in the <lb/> Executive; but instead of that,
                  the Executive Members enter freely into the discussion here, <lb/> and declare
                  what their views are fully. As to voting recommendations of Hon. Members <lb/>
                  down, when a suggestion is made to substitute one Scheme for another, it would be
                  strange if <lb/> the Government Members should not unite in voting it down. With
                  regard to the recom<lb break="no"/>mendations for adding to the terms and
                  conditions, they ought to be carefully made. or their <lb/> insertion may create
                  great disappointment in the public mind by leading people to expect more <lb/>
                  than will he acceded. Hon. Members should weigh their votes well. I, for one, will
                  not vote <lb/> for what I cannot recommend to His Excellency in the Executive
                  Council. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS</persName>—I am not in the habit of holding my head
                  down, I always <lb/> hold it up. I agree with the Hon. Mr. Wood, that all that we
                  are likely to do for the public <lb/> benefit is crushed by the official vote.  
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. MR. CARRALL</persName>—The Hon. Mr. Wood has stated that the
                  recommendations of the <lb/> Elected Members would be treated with contempt. He is
                  not a Member of the Executive <lb/> Council. I, as a Member of that Council, can
                  tell him that they are always treated with the <lb/> greatest respect. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName>—What I say is that the recommendations of
                  Independent Members do <lb/> not reach, and will not reach, the head of the
                  Executive. We want them to reach. We all <lb/> believe that the Members of the
                  Executive will mention them, but that is not what we want. <lb/> We desire that
                  these recommendations should meet the eye of the Executive. 1 disdain to <lb/>
                  consider that the Executive rules this Colony. They do not; they administer the
                  Government, <lb/> and l consider it to be the duty of the Executive to sink their
                  own views, when they do not <lb/> accord with the popular will. It is quite
                  possible that the Executive may be wrong and the <lb/> Popular Members right
                  occasionally <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. Mr. TRUTCH</persName>—I do not think the position of the Hon. Mr.
                  Wood is correct. <lb/> There are now three Resolutions of, so-called, Popular
                  Members before the Executive; why <lb/> are so many of their recommendations
                  carried if there is any desire to treat them with dis» <lb/> respect? The
                  difficulty is, that the Hon. gentleman persisted in trying to force a vote upon
                  <lb/> his Resolution about the Admiralty Court. I, if pressed to give an opinion
                  at an inapposite <lb/> time, would vote against it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DeCOSMOS</persName>—The conviction in and out of this House is,
                  that the Elected <lb/> Members are useless, being outnumbered by the official
                  vote. The only reason why I would <lb/> endeavour to be elected to a seat, in a
                  Council so constituted, is to prevent evils that might <lb/> happen. The
                  Government might get tools to go in and vote as they liked. The Government <lb/>
                  might get some one to be elected, and then call it the popular vote. The mistake
                  has been in <lb/> interpreting recommendations into amendments. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—Mr. Chairman, I think that nothing can be
                  more unfair, nothing <lb/> more ungenerous, than the position taken by some Hon.
                  Members towards the Government. <lb/> This scheme was brought down to the House by
                  the Government. and we were invited by the <lb/> Hon. Attorney-Genera and other
                  Members of the Government, to make any recommendations <lb/> or suggestions that
                  we thought proper, and they would receive every consideration at the hands <lb/>
                  of the Executive. I fail to see one single act or vote at variance with that
                  position. I have seen <lb/> leading Members of the Government vote different ways;
                  and this I take to be an evidence <lb/> of their sincerity. There seems to be a
                  disposition to run away with the impression that the <lb/> unofficial members are
                  treated with disrespect. To me. Sir, such a position is undignified and <lb/>
                  absurd. Because I have moved a recommendation. and the House has voted it down, am
                  I <lb/> treated with disrespect? Why, follow this up and an adverse vote would be
                  in every case an <lb/> insult to the minority, and legislation would become an
                  impossibility. I am grateful to the <lb/> Government for what I consider a great
                  scheme; grateful for having the opportunity of voting <lb/> upon it, and I join
                  the Hon. Chief Commissioner in warning the House against voting altera<lb break="no"/>tions in the Terms. lest such a course should create hopes to be
                  afterwards disappointed, and <lb/> lead to a reaction which might result in the
                  defeat of the whole scheme at the polls. 1' would <lb/> also caution Hon. Members
                  to avoid attempting to induce the Government to insert terms <lb/> which would
                  imperil the scheme with the Dominion Government. I shall set aside any par<lb break="no"/>ticular views and suggestions I should like to make, to avoid that
                  result. I can understand <lb/>
                  <pb n="76" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_076.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">76</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> enemies of the cause rushing in
                  resolutions calculated to raise extravagant hopes, and so pro<lb break="no"/>duce
                  disappointment and fatal reaction, but not friends of the caus.. In recommending
                     altera<lb break="no"/>tions to Government our reason and judgment should be
                  fairly and calmly exercised. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Clause 5 was put to the Committee by the Chairman, and passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman read Clause 6:- <lb/>
            </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"6. Suitable Pensions, such as shall be approved of by Her Majesty's Government, shall 
     <lb/>
     "be provided by the Government of the Dominion for those of Her Majesty's Servants in the 
     <lb/>
     "Colony, whose position and emoluments derived therefrom would be affected by political 
     <lb/>
     "changes on the admission of this Colony into the Dominion of Canada," 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CREA1">The Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> said :—In proposing the adoption of
                  this clause, it is only <lb/> necessary for me to state to the House that it is
                  inserted in accordance with Lord Granville's <lb/>   despatch. Confederation will,
                  in all probability, affect the positions of certain officials, and the <lb/>
                  despatch advises that provision should he made, hence this clause. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS</persName>—I do not approve of the principle of
                  pensions, and I cannot under<lb break="no"/>stand why pensions should be given to
                  men who came out to this Colony, as I came out, as needy <lb/> adventurers. The
                  people of this country do not approve of pensions. If Hon. Members had been <lb/>
                  induced to come out from England to assume positions under Government for life, I
                  could under<lb break="no"/>stand their being provided for with pensions on the
                  positions being abolished. I was once a <lb/> Government Officer in this Colony
                  myself, and should of course have liked to get a pension; <lb/> but in my opinion
                  the present Government officials have drawn very good pay for doing very <lb/>
                  little work, for long enough; and before a pension is given, it should he shown
                  that the person <lb/> to whom it is given has done the State some service. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DeCOSMOS</persName>—We have now, Sir, arrived at the.
                  Government's "wisdom" in <lb/> delaying Confederation in 1868, and subsequently,
                  and of which we heard from the Hon. Chief <lb/> Commissioner of Lands and Works
                  The Hon. gentlemen who own this Colony—for the Governor <lb/> and Executive
                  virtually own the country—are now ready to execute a quit claim deed of this <lb/>
                  colony to Canada, for a pension to each, and it may be the cheapest mode of
                  getting rid of them. <lb/> Pensions are a modern discovery. The Romans granted
                  triumpth entries as a reward to their <lb/> most distinguished citizens; and the
                  Greeks crowned those whom they would honour with lanrels; <lb/> but now pensions
                  are the fashion. How much more substantial! The whole secret of the <lb/>
                  opposition of the Government to Confederation lay in the question of pensions.
                  ["No, no."] <lb/> ["Yes, yes."] Still I shall vote for the clause, as I believe
                  this to be the cheapest way of <lb/> buying out the present possessors, the
                  virtual owners of the Colony, I think it ought to be <lb/> pensions or
                  compensation, but I will move no amendment: <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK</persName>—I am prepared to support this clause. It
                  shows that Great Britain <lb/> does not forget her public servants, It is a good
                  and proper clause, and a usual one. This is <lb/> following out what is done in
                  every other British Colony. I shall support the clause. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName>—I shall support this clause. It stands out in
                  strong contrast to the action <lb/> of the Imperial Government, in their treatment
                  of public officers upon the occasion of another <lb/> union. I am glad to see this
                  clause inserted, as representing a principle that ought always to <lb/> he
                  recognized.   <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName>—The Hon. Member for Victoria District is
                  attributing motives again. <lb/> If he throws dirt on others, he must expect to
                  have it thrown back on himself, and it might as <lb/> well be said that Hon.
                  Representative Members who vote for Confederation only vote for it for <lb/> the
                  sake of the loaves and fishes. [No, no," from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">DeCosmos</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> This is a question for
                  the <lb/> Canadian Government. not for us. Government officials are entitled to
                  some compensation for <lb/> loss of offices, and the Canadian Government will
                  think so too To them I leave it. They will, <lb/> I believe, settle the question
                  honourably. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName>— I challenge any man to say that I ever
                  asked to have any Govern<lb break="no"/>ment post or appointment. I have lived
                  half a century, and three-fourths of that time I have <lb/> earned my own bread
                  and spent my own money. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMOKEN</persName>— I don't accuse the Hon. Member of seeking
                  office. I say the <lb/> argument might be used; and if gentlemen will throw dirt,
                  they must expect. to get it thrown <lb/> on them. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName>—The remarks I made were as to times past. As
                  to dirt, I never use <lb/> it. I deal in facts. I know men, however, who have for
                  themselves and friends stuck closely to <lb/> the loaves and fishes; and I could
                  name some public men who did their best and succeeded in <lb/>
                  <pb n="77" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_077.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION</fw>
                  <fw type="running">DEBATE. 77</fw> depriving the Colony of Vancouver Island of
                  half a million of dollars, that the Duke of New<lb break="no"/>castle, as Colonial
                  Secretary, said belonged to it. [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon Mr. Helmcken</persName> —"Name."] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> No, I will <lb/> not
                  mention names. I say, again, that the chief reason for this question not being
                  taken up in <lb/> 1868, was because pensions were not provided. Now, Sir, I am
                  glad the Hon. senior Member <lb/> for Victoria City has afforded me an opportunity
                  to explain the part that I took in pressing <lb/> Confederation on the Council in
                  1868. I first endeavoured, with the Hon. Member for New <lb/> Westminster, to
                  enlist Governor Seymour in the matter,—get him to take it up as a Government <lb/>
                  measure,—and open negotiations with the Canadian Government. But he refused to
                  interfere <lb/> in it, and said the Council might deal with it. Without the
                  support of the Governor, in a Council <lb/> so constituted, there was no hope for
                  the measure. It then became a question whether any <lb/> Resolution on it ought to
                  be brought forward in the Council. Some Confederates urged that it <lb/> would not
                  do to have a Resolution defeated. 0n the other hand, I thought it best to make
                  some <lb/> proposition, merely to elicit an expression of the Council's opinion,
                  and show the country its <lb/> attitude on the question. For in agitating the
                  question, unless it could be proved incontestably <lb/> that the Council and
                  Executive were opposed, the people could not be aroused to take action. <lb/> I,
                  therefore, brought it up in a series of Resolutions before the House, and not in
                  Committee of <lb/> the Whole. If I had had the least hope that it would have
                  passed, I would have had it con<lb break="no"/>sidered in Committee of the
                  Whole,—the proper place to settle such an important matter, after <lb/> the terms
                  had been settled between the two Governments. As a matter of course, the Resolu<lb break="no"/>tions were defeated. But subsequently, when it was urged upon the
                  Governor, at the instance <lb/> of the Collector of Customs, that the Council be
                  allowed to take action, he said "No; let the <lb/> people act." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. MR. CARRALL</persName>—I shall vote in favour of this clause, and I
                  only desire to offer three <lb/> remarks. The Council have had two objects mainly
                  in view: first, to bring in a scheme which <lb/> should bring general prosperity;
                  and, secondly, that no vested interests should be affected by <lb/> the act of
                  Confederation. The positions held by official gentlemen are, I contend, vested
                  <lb/> interests, and as such, entitled to protection. As regards the way in which
                  members have <lb/> been treated in other Colonies, there are numbers who are now
                  receiving pensions. I may <lb/> instance two notable members of the Imperial
                  Government—the Right Hons. Robert Lowe and <lb/> H. C. E. Childers. I desire to
                  put it upon record that I vote for this clause with as much <lb/> pleasure as I
                  support any clause of the Resolutions. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Clause 6 was then read by the Chairman, and passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               The <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> proposed the adoption of Clause 7:- <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"> " 7. The Dominion Government shall supply an efficient and
                  regular fortnightly steam <lb/> "communication between Victoria and San Francisco,
                  by steamers adapted and giving facilities <lb/> "for the conveyance of passengers
                  and cargo." <lb/>
               </quote>

            <p>
     This clause speaks for itself, and it is unnecessary for me to say anything in support of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—l regard this paragraph of the Resolutions
                  as a make-weight, nothing <lb/> more nor less. It is a mistake to make it one of
                  the essential conditions. The time may come <lb/> when we don't want this steam
                  communication. The Railway may come to Puget Sound, and <lb/> then this clause
                  will be unnecessary. People will say, at first, that this is a splendid thing; but
                  <lb/> it is all included in the British North America Act <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—The Hon. Member refers, I suppose, to
                  clause (<hi rendition="simple:italic">b</hi>) of <lb/> Section 92, which excepts
                  "Lines of steamships between the Province and any British or <lb/> foreign
                  country" from the "Local works and undertakings" which are declared to be subjects
                  <lb/> of exclusive Provincial legislation. The Dominion Government would have to
                  make provision <lb/> for mail steamers. This clause provides for regular
                  communication. When we have com<lb break="no"/>munication with Canada by railway,
                  such a clause as this would be unnecessary; but now, if <lb/> confederated, we
                  shall need, more than ever, regular and more frequent communication with <lb/> San
                  Francisco, which is the chain of communication with Canada. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—There seems to be a spirit of distrust in
                  this and other clauses <lb/> of those Resolutions, a desire to have everything in
                  writing. I believe that we should have <lb/> a steamship line without this clause.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName>—The Hon. Member says it is of no use. If
                  the clause was not there, <lb/> the Dominion Government need not give us this
                  communication. Postal communication it must <lb/> give; but that means only
                  communication with Olympia <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—I do not think that this implies distrust any
                  more than asking a man <lb/> to give a note for a debt implies distrust. In the
                  conditions framed on the admission into the <lb/>
                  <pb n="78" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_078.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">78</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE</fw> Confederation of Prince Edward Island
                  and Newfoundland, these matters are set out with great <lb/> minuteness. I
                  perfectly agree that we might trust the Canadian Government, but we are not <lb/>
                  in Canada, and we are asked to name specific terms. Surely we ought to do so. It
                  would be <lb/> very unbusiness-like to say to the Dominion, we will leave it all
                  to you. The Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would say, let it be prepared in
                  black and white, so that we may say whether we can <lb/> perform it or not. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman read Clause 7. Passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               The <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> proposed the adoption of Clause 8:- <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
                  <p>" 8. Inasmuch as no real Union can subsist between this Colony and Canada
                     without the <lb/> "speedy establishment of communication across the Rocky
                     Mountains by Coach Road and <lb/> " Railway, the Dominion shall, within three
                     years from the date of Union, construct and open <lb/> "for traffic such Coach
                     Road, from some point on the line of the Main Trunk Road of this <lb/> " Colony
                     to Fort Garry, of similar character to the said Main Trunk Road; and shall
                     further <lb/> " engage to use all means in her power to complete such Railway
                     communication at the <lb/> "earliest practicable date, and that surveys to
                     determine the proper line for such Railway <lb/> " shall be at once commenced;
                     and that a sum of not less than One Million Dollars shall be <lb/> "expended in
                     every year, from and after three years from the date of Union, in actually
                        con<lb break="no"/>"structing the initial sections of such Railway from the
                     seaboard of British Columbia, to <lb/> "connect with the Railway system of
                     Canada." <lb/>
                  </p>
               </quote>

            <p>
     I move this Resolution, Mr. Chairman, as being the practical bond of Union between the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion and this Colony. I leave it to other members to discuss the details. I merely say 
     <lb/>
     that three years is the time deemed necessary to make preliminary surveys, and the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture of a sum of $1,000,000 is the best practical guarantee that the work will be done. The 
     <lb/>
     Dominion would not submit to the expenditure of such an amount if they did not intend to 
     <lb/>
     push the work forward as quickly as possible. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—Sir, I do not claim any honour in
                  connection with the Resolu<lb break="no"/>tion respecting the Railway. I am
                  perfectly willing to accord the praise that is due to the <lb/> originator of this
                  clause, but think a portion of it a great mistake. I do not altogether like <lb/>
                  the way in which these Resolutions are got up. I don't like the preamble as to
                  "real union." <lb/> In all these Govermnont Resolutions there is something of a
                  "catching" character; little <lb/> hooks to catch the popular vote. Material union
                  can exist without railroads. Look at the real <lb/> union between this Colony and
                  Great Britain. People who were here in 1859 may recollect <lb/> how safe they felt
                  during the San Juan difficulty, and subsequently during the Trent affair. <lb/>
                  There was then a physical union; we felt that we should be protected by force if
                  necessary. <lb/> I believe that I was amongst the first or second of those who
                  moved in the matter of the trans<lb break="no"/>continental coach road. But whilst
                  on this Subject I will take occasion to do justice to the <lb/> memory of the
                  gentleman who proposed the Overland Railway through British America. <lb/> It was
                  during the administration of Sir Robert Peel, in 1844 or 1845, that A. W. Godfrey,
                  a <lb/> bookseller in Halifax, addressed letters to Sir Robert Peel, about a
                  Railway from Halifax to <lb/> Vancouver Island. Previously, Whitney had proposed
                  his scheme for a Railroad from Texas <lb/> to the Pacific. Our worthy old citizen,
                  Mr. Waddington, has been distinguished among those <lb/> who have taken active
                  measures in favour of the Railway. Till Lord Granville's despatch <lb/> arrived,
                  none of the railway agitators seemed to have made much headway. At the Conference
                  <lb/> of Delegates from British North America in London, an Overland Railway was
                  considered and <lb/> described as "a subject of the highest importance, and one to
                  be promoted at the earliest stage <lb/> that the finances of the country would
                  admit of" The proposition before us shows how great a <lb/> stride has been made
                  in this matter since 1867, I have no wish to claim any honour or to <lb/> detract
                  from that which is due to others, but we must recollect that $1,000,000 a year is
                  not <lb/> a Railway across the Rocky Mountains. I have, however, year after year,
                  looked upon Rail<lb break="no"/>way communication as the only means to settle up
                  the interior of British Columbia. I never <lb/> could see how British Columbia
                  could be settled up without a Railway to connect Fraser <lb/> River with Kamloops.
                  I think, Sir, that a different course ought to be pursued by the <lb/> Government
                  with the Dominion than that proposed. Assuming that the Coach Road may be <lb/>
                  open in three years,—for I am ready to admit that proposition,—when people settle
                  the <lb/> country from Thompson River to Osoyoos Lake the farmers must have the
                  means of transport <lb/> for their various productions. How are they to get them
                  out? I maintain that the true <lb/> course for the development of the resources of
                  the country is to make a line of Railway from <lb/>
                  <pb n="79" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_079.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">70</fw> some navigable spot on the Fraser to Lake Kamloops, I claim
                  for this that it might be <lb/> regarded as a part of the transcontinental line,
                  and in my opinion it would do more to build <lb/> up the country than anything
                  else that could be conceived, and I believe it to be thoroughly <lb/> practicable.
                  I, therefore, move a recommendation to His Excellency that the construction of
                  <lb/> a Railway from steamboat navigation on the Fraser River to Kaniloops Lake be
                  inserted in <lb/> the terms, instead of commending from the initial sections on
                  the seaboard of British Columbia. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon, CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—Sir, I approach the consideration of
                  this clause with <lb/> a great sense of the magnitude of the work which we propose
                  to the Government of, that <lb/> Dominion with which we propose to be
                  confederated. My mind seems somewhat to shrink <lb/> before the contemplation of
                  its magnitude; and it is only when the reflection is gradually <lb/> forced upon
                  me, that the union can never be a reality until the Railway is commenced in our
                  <lb/> own territory, and that it is necessary, that I can bring myself to believe
                  that it should be <lb/> done. That it is practicable is undeniable, and needs no
                  argument. From all information I <lb/> have been able to obtain, and comparing it
                  with the difficulties which have been overcome on <lb/> the Pacific line, I
                  believe the proportion of cost of the proposed line of Railway from the <lb/>
                  seaboard of British Columbia to Canada to be not more than two-thirds of the cost
                  of the line <lb/> already built from California across the Sierra Nevada. There
                  will, of course, be difficulties <lb/> to overcome, which may influence the choice
                  of the best line of route I believe we are justi<lb break="no"/>fied in asking for
                  the construction of the Railway, and I am satisfied, I may say I know, that <lb/>
                  there is a great desire on the part of those now in power in Canada to construct
                  this Railroad, <lb/> and if it be in their power to do it it will be done. To go
                  to the terms: objections have been <lb/> made to the time of commencement I would
                  ask the House to consider what an amount of <lb/> prospecting and survey will have
                  to be done before any commencement can possibly be made <lb/> in the work. I do
                  not think that there is any delay suggested by fixing the time of three <lb/>
                  years. I think it is the shortest time that could be named. The proper line could
                  hardly be <lb/> determined sooner. We do not presume to suggest the scheme, or the
                  means. My opinion is <lb/> that the Railway will be built by private enterprise,
                  under a guarantee. As the Imperial <lb/> Government have shown a desire to
                  encourage Confederation, I think we have a right to <lb/> expect that they will
                  render seine assistance in the building of the Railway. especially after <lb/>
                  Lord Granville's despatch. [Hear, hear] I hope that the Canadian Government will
                  have <lb/> the assistance of the Imperial Government in carrying out this scheme,
                  It will be some time <lb/> before the scheme can be developed, and then atleast
                  two seasons must elapse, as an immense <lb/> amount of reconuoitring and surveying
                  will be necessary. Three years is not too much. The <lb/> Hour Member for Victoria
                  District (Mr. DeCosmos) objects to the framing of this Resolution <lb/> as too
                  catching. I think his objection is unfounded, I believe that the benefits will be
                  real <lb/> and substantial. The reason that so small a sum as $1,000,000 is asked
                  for is that it is only <lb/> intended to be an earnest. so to speak, on the part
                  of the Dominion Government that the <lb/> Railway will be made. I believe that the
                  expenditure of $1,000,000 upon the first twenty <lb/> miles will bring an
                  accession of from 5,000 to 10,000 to our population. We have a right to <lb/> ask
                  that the Railway should be commenced here. It is desirable that it should be made
                  here. <lb/> It will be found that when once it is commenced here a nucleus of,
                  population will be formed <lb/> which will add considerably to the prosperity of
                  the Colony. It has been argued that no <lb/> profit can arise from the expenditure
                  of the vast amount of capital that will be required to <lb/> build this Railway.
                  It will cost probably $20,000,000, and therefore is not likely to be <lb/>
                  profitable for years to come. We cannot, in my opinion. expect any pecuniary
                  return for <lb/> years. It believes the Dominion Government, if they desire the
                  prosperity of this part of the <lb/> Empire, to develop the resources of the
                  estate which we are handing over. If they value it as <lb/> we. do, and as we
                  believe that they do. they will endeavour to realize the advantages at the <lb/>
                  earliest possible date. This Railway will do so. when it is completed across the
                  Rocky <lb/> Mountains, and in my opinion not till then shall we have a population.
                  Before concluding, I <lb/> desire to say that it is intended, although it is not
                  so stated in the terms, to give an assurance <lb/> to the Dominion Government that
                  any amount of land which they think reasonable will be <lb/> given. This will be
                  made a part of the scheme for the construction of the Railway, if thought <lb/>
                  desirable. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon, MR. HUMPHREYS</persName>—Sir, I look upon this clause as most
                  important. I am one <lb/> of those who believe that there can be no real
                  Confederation without a Railroad. Government <lb/> has made a mistake in naming
                  the sum of $1,000,000 to be expended on the seaboard. There <lb/>
                  <pb n="80" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_080.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">80</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> is no necessity to put this in. This
                  would only bring a floating population, which we do not <lb/> want. I agree with
                  the Hon. Member for Victoria District, that the Railway ought to be <lb/>
                  commenced in the agricultural districts of the Mainland. so as to connect them
                  with the head <lb/> of navigation on the Fraser. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—It does not become us, I think, to
                  dictate in what <lb/> way the work should be done, or to describe the details of
                  the scheme to Canada. I feel con<lb break="no"/>fident that if this plan is really
                  taken up it will be done much more quickly than if only <lb/> $1,000,000 a year
                  were spent. I think that several millions a year will be expended, and if so <lb/>
                  I have little doubt that the Railway from the seaboard to the agricultural
                  districts will be <lb/> made in five years. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName>—What is the seaboard? Does it mean Barclay
                  Sound? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—That is what we have purposely left
                  open. The line <lb/> may come down the valley of the Fraser, as in my opinion will
                  be best, or it may come through <lb/> to Bute Inlet or Bentinck Arm. We have
                  purposely generalized and left it for those who <lb/> undertake the work to
                  determine for themselves. It is not desirable for us to cramp this <lb/>
                  Resolution by defining the locality for the line or terminus. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">The Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—Sir, l conceive that we have now come to
                  the most vital part of <lb/> the whole scheme. I quite concur in the opinion that
                  no real union can take place without a <lb/> Railway. Did I believe that the
                  Overland Railway would not be made. I should hesitate very <lb/> much about
                  Confederation, because l should he apprehensive that the whole scheme would fall
                  <lb/> to pieces. I think that great haste must he used to build up an
                  English-speaking nation along<lb break="no"/>side of another existing
                  English-speaking country. To accomplish this end, I think that the <lb/> Overland
                  Railway is necessary, and must: be pushed through to speedy completion to be an
                  <lb/> immediate success. In ten years' time, without an Overland Railway, I do not
                  believe that we <lb/> should have any British Territory here at all. The great
                  work must be undertaken with the <lb/> assistance of both the Canadian and
                  Imperial Governments, and pushed through to a speedy <lb/> success. It is true
                  that a sort of union might exist without a Railway, such as the union <lb/>
                  between British Columbia and Great Britain.   But we propose to establish a union
                  that will <lb/> endure and that will render an Overland Railway just as necessary
                  as the arteries in the <lb/> human body are necessary to circulate the blood and
                  to keep up life. I believe that $1,000,000 <lb/> is a mere nominal sum, as
                  explained by the Hon. Chief Commissioner, a tangible security that <lb/> the work
                  will be completed The expenditure of the first million will be a guarantee that
                  any <lb/> company or Government undertaking it will carry it through. Every
                  reflecting mind will see <lb/> that if any company spend $1,000,000 a year, they
                  must spend more, and that it will he to <lb/> their interest to push it through.
                  To say that because we only name a sum of $1,000,000, <lb/> that it will be a
                  matter of 100 years is absurd; my reply to this, I cannot call it an argument,
                  <lb/> is that capitalists could not be found in the world so silly as to spread
                  the construction over <lb/> one hundred, or fifty, or twenty, or even ten years. I
                  cannot support the amendment of the <lb/> Hon Member for Victoria District; we
                  must carefully avoid committing ourselves to the route, <lb/> or terms of
                  building. I think this may be safely left in the bands of the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. It is useless to argue that it is of vital importance to them
                  to have be best route. The <lb/> Railway must pass through the Colony, and benefit
                  the Colony. no matter where the terminus; <lb/> it must be in British Columbia.
                  and consequently a benefit to the whole Colony. I cannot see <lb/> that it would
                  be better to begin in the middle. I look upon it as an absolute necessity that the
                  <lb/> Railway should commence at the seaboard: moving the material is the great
                  expense that has <lb/> to be contended against, and the advantage of being able to
                  land the material and lay it down <lb/> at once on the road, will be incalculable.
                  If the Railway were to be constructed from a given <lb/> point ten miles from the
                  seaboard, it would probably pay the contractors to build that piece of <lb/> the
                  line. Unless Hon. Members can show us that the material can be brought to the line
                  by <lb/> way of the Rocky Mountains, don't let us stultify ourselves by asking
                  them to begin in the <lb/> middle. It is right that the work should be commenced
                  simultaneously on the Atlantic and <lb/> Pacific sides. I fancy that, as a matter
                  of policy and economy, any company undertaking the <lb/> work would so commence,
                  without it being named in the terms, as it would undoubtedly be <lb/> more
                  economical to carry on the work by sea from the westward in British Columbia, and
                  by <lb/> land from the East. As for the amount named in the conditions. as I have
                  said. I look upon <lb/> it as a tangible assurance to the people that the thing
                  will be done, rather than as the specific <lb/> statement of a sum with the
                  expenditure of which this Colony will be satisfied. I have some <lb/>
                  <pb n="81" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_081.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">81</fw> doubts about the clause requiring the Dominion Government
                  to make a Coach Road. The age <lb/> for Coach Roads has almost passed away. Such a
                  road would not meet the requirements of <lb/> the present day. I would prefer
                  removing this condition, and require the work to be com<lb break="no"/>menced
                  within two years, or seek compensation in some other way as an equivalent for the
                  <lb/> supposed advantage of the road. The sooner we do our little part towards
                  convincing the <lb/> Dominion Government that this is necessary, the better, Not
                  only is the Railway a national <lb/> necessity for the Dominion, but for every
                  fractional part of British North America. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">The Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName>—I reiterate that Confederation means
                  terms. What feeling <lb/> now exists in favour of Confederation has been brought
                  about by the assertion that Canada <lb/> will do certain things for the Colony,
                  amongst others, that she will build a Railway. If the <lb/> people are deceived in
                  this matter; if Canada does not accede to this portion of the conditions, <lb/>
                  she need not ask the people of this Colony to be united. I would ask the people to
                  hand them <lb/> selves together to demand that the terms shall be verified, and I
                  hope they will take that stand. <lb/> And I will ask that the promises made by the
                  Dominion Government will be strictly performed. <lb/> ["Hear, hear," from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr.
                  DeCosmos</persName> and <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Mr. Wood</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">The Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> This Colony would be just as much <lb/> isolated as ever
                  after a paper union, without a Railway as one of the conditions. I acknowledge
                  <lb/> that we might have such union as exists with England now, with a Railway. We
                  are a Colony <lb/> of England, and I don't know that many people object to being a
                  Colony of England; but I say <lb/> that verv many would object to becoming a
                  Colony of Canada. As a Colony of England we <lb/> have the right to legislate for
                  ourselves; if we become a Colony of Canada, that power is taken <lb/> away. ["No,
                  no," from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DeCosmos</persName>] [<persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon Mr. Robson</persName>, it will give us more power] <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">The Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> I <lb/> say
                  that the power of regulating our own commerce is taken away, and the only power
                  left to <lb/> us is that of raising taxes for Municipal purposes That is the
                  difference between being a <lb/> Colony of Canada, and a Colony of England. The
                  distance is so great between this Colony <lb/> and Ottawa without any Railway and
                  without any Telegraphic communication, that laws might <lb/> be passed there,
                  which would ruin British Columbia, without our having any notice of them. <lb/> I
                  do not consider that Canada expects or intends to attempt to make this Railway a
                  paying <lb/> institution of itself. There are a great many institutions in this
                  Colony which are not paying <lb/> institutions. Canada takes the view that the
                  Railway is necessary to complete the British line <lb/> of communication between
                  England and her Asiatic possessions, in order that the English people <lb/> may
                  share in the carrying trade to China and the East Indies with our American
                  neighbours. <lb/> Canada expects to influence Great Britain to guarantee the loan
                  for the formation of the Rail<lb break="no"/>way. Great Britain may guarantee the
                  loan for the purpose of having a check on the American <lb/> line of Railway, but,
                  she would never guarantee it for Canadian purposes only. The people of <lb/>
                  England would not tolerate it. I consider this an essential condition. Without it
                  Confederation <lb/> must not take place. This is one of those things which will he
                  a vast benefit to this Colony and <lb/> to Canada, and therefore I regard it as a
                  necessary condition. Why should this Colony join <lb/> Canada except for the
                  benefit of both? We should be better off without Canada if we have no <lb/>
                  Railway. I say that this Colony had better stand alone than risk everything
                  without a Railway. <lb/> What benefit can Canada expect from Confederation with
                  British Columbia without a Railway? <lb/> Is she afraid of, British Columbia being
                  handed over to America? If Canada thinks she can hold <lb/> British Columbia for
                  her own purposes, and use it when she pleases, and takes her own time to <lb/> do
                  what she likes with it, she is mistaken. The Railway has been made a lever for
                     Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, by Canada, I ask that Canada he now made to
                  promise faithfully that a Railway shall <lb/> be made. With regard to the
                  expenditure of $1,000,000, there should he a forfeit of ten per cent <lb/> payable
                  to this Colony if it is not spent; I am not so much afraid about the Canadian
                     Govern<lb break="no"/>ment not carrying out the terms as I am of our own
                  people. I believe that there is more danger <lb/> from our own people than from
                  the Canadian Government. British Columbia may cheat herself, <lb/> and it is our
                  duty, man for man, to take care that we don't cheat this Colony; that we don't
                  <lb/> in fact cheat ourselves. I think that the Coach Road may be useful; it will
                  take some time <lb/> to build a Railroad, and it will be necessary to have
                  communication. The road might be used <lb/> for Immigration purposes, and for
                  drving cattle, but will he of no use commercially; such an <lb/> idea would have
                  suited people who lived some years ago. Speaking of commerce in which the <lb/>
                  Dominion is to take part, I do not myself believe that the Asiatic traffic will
                  come this way; but <lb/> still we must not lose sight of the idea that it may
                  eventually be partially diverted to this route. <lb/> These Resolutions do not
                  afford practically any immediate benefit. ["Hear, hear," from <lb/> <persName ref="pers:DECO1">DeCosmos</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">The Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> If
                  the Colony was united to the Dominion to-morrow, there would be no immediate <lb/>
                  <pb n="82" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-16_Page_082.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">82</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> benefit to result even from the
                  Railway. This is one of the points on which the people may be <lb/> deceived. If
                  they imagine that with Confederation will come immediate prosperity. I shall be
                  <lb/> glad if anyone will point out how it is to come. If it were made inland it
                  might be more <lb/> beneficial to agricultural interests in a short space of time,
                  than if commenced on the sea coast. <lb/> Public works in this Colony should help
                  to develop the resources, and one thing should he made <lb/> to work with another,
                  so as to be mutually beneficial; each should be for the benefit of the <lb/>
                  whole, and the whole for the benefit of each. Suppose a Railway were commenced
                  tomorrow <lb/> at Fraser River, how much benefit would it be? It might be some,
                  but if these public works <lb/> were made subservient to the interests of settling
                  up the Colony, they would be more likely to <lb/> be beneficial. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. MR. CARRALL</persName>—Sir, I have only a few words to say, and
                  have no intention of detain<lb break="no"/>ing the House at this late hour, but I
                  must be allowed to express the satisfaction which I <lb/>feel in observing a
                  change in the sentiments of the Hon. Member for Victoria City (Mr. <lb/>Helmcken),
                  a change which does honour to his head and heart. He has begun to show some
                  <lb/>faith in the Canadian Government at last. He may be called the pattern of the
                  distrustful <lb/>party, and I augur favourably from his conversion. With regard to
                  the local advantages of a <lb/>Railway, I would point to the construction of the
                  Intercolonial Railway Property in Halifax <lb/>has gone up 40 per cent. since it
                  was built. I fully admit the desirability and necessity of a <lb/>Railway, but I
                  cannot admit that Union cannot exist without it; look at the Union which
                  <lb/>existed for so many years between California and the Eastern States of
                  America without a <lb/>Railway. I believe that Canada, for Imperial reasons,
                  intends to undertake the construction <lb/>of this Railway. As for the length of
                  time allowed for the commencement, I think it could <lb/>not be well less than
                  three years. I believe with the Hon. Chief Commissioner, that the work <lb/>will
                  be undertaken by a private company, under guarantee. If so, it would be hampering
                  the <lb/>Government of the Dominion to make them commence earlier. It might compel
                  them to close <lb/>with parties not in all respects eligible. It would put them in
                  a false position. If the Colony <lb/>had charge of her own Crown lands, there
                  should be a power given to Canada to promise <lb/>Crown lands in connection with
                  the construction of the Railway. I regret that this has not <lb/>been put in the
                  Resolutions, but no doubt the omission can be remedied hereafter. <lb/>
               </p>

    

    

            <p>
     On the motion of <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. Mr. Drake</persName>, the Committee rose, reported the passing of Clauses 5, 
     <lb/>
     6, and 7, and obtained leave to sit again at one o'clock the 17th instant. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Report adopted, and Clauses 5, 6, and 7, passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-03-17, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
   
            <!--<p>
     THURSDAY, 17TH MARCH, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. MR. DeCOSMOS—Mr. Chairman, judging from the statements made by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, this Railway is not likely to be completed in so short a period as I had hoped. The 
     <lb/>
     indefinite nature of the clause is unsatisfactory. It contemplates nothing more than the 
     <lb/>
     expenditure of $1,000,000 per annum, which would no doubt be a great boon, and would 
     <lb/>
     stimulate various branches of industry but that is almost all that can be said of it. The way 
     <lb/>
     that it has been put to the Colony heretofore, was that the Canadian Government would 
     <lb/>
     construct the road. It now turns out, from the statements of the Hon. Chief Commissioner of 
     <lb/>
     Lands and Works, that in all probability the Canadian Government will get some private com<lb break="no"/>pany to carry out the work; and he adds " that we may" get a guarantee with grants of land 
     <lb/>
     in aid of, the undertaking. Now, Sir, from the first I have always been careful not to bring 
     <lb/>
     forward the question of the Railway in connection with Confederation. The London Conference 
     <lb/>
     favoured it only when the financial position of the Dominion admitted it. It must be quite a 
     <lb/>
     long time before connection by rail with the Canadian Railway system can take place. I never 
     <lb/>
     believed the Canadian Government would contract a debt for this purpose at the present. 
     <lb/>
     They are already, in my opinion, too deeply in debt, and are taxed too high, to allow them to 
     <lb/>
     do so. According to my calculation, it will cost $150,000,000 to complete the Railway from 
     <lb/>
     this Colony to Montreal. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK—You mean to the head of the water communication of Lake 
     <lb/>
     Superior? 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>