<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgBCLC_1870-03-11"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgBCLCoun">British Columbia Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1870-03-11">11 March 1870</date>, Province of BC, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

         
          
         
               <title>Legislative Council, Debate on the Subject of Confederation with Canada</title>.
                    

          <date when="1912"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Victoria, B.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>William H. Cullin</publisher>.
                    
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="53"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_038.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_039.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_040.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_041.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_042.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_043.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_044.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_045.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_046.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_047.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_048.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_049.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_050.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_051.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_052.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_053.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_038">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_038.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_039">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_039.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_040">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_040.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_041">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_041.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_042">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_042.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_043">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_043.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_044">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_044.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_045">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_045.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_046">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_046.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_047">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_047.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_048">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_048.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_049">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_049.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_050">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_050.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_051">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_051.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_052">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_052.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_053">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_053.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="38" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_038.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">38</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
    
<!-- GL, 2017-03-15, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
        
            <!--<p>
               [Hon Mr. Wood―" Let us have it in black and white."] 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Why, let the Act be repealed and down go the terms. The sovereign power is in the 
               <lb/>
               Parliament of England. It made the Act, and if it is violated without redress, it can repeal 
               <lb/>
               it, and the power of Canada ceases. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Honourable and learned Member for Victoria City has referred to the possibility of 
               <lb/>
               a Fenian invasion, and said what will become of the Railway in such an event. I believe, Sir, 
               <lb/>
               on such an extraordinary occasion, such as invasion, each one in the Colony would be patriotic 
               <lb/>
               enough to do without a few miles of Railway, until the invasion may be put down. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It has been asked what is the gain under Confederation. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               At present we have no surplus revenue. But with Confederation on equitable terms, there 
               <lb/>
               will be a clear gain of $384,000 annually from subsidies and reduction of tariff; therefore, as 
               <lb/>
               $384,000 is to nothing, so is Confederation to Isolation. There are a great many points to 
               <lb/>
               which I could allude were I disposed to trespass longer on the time of the Council; but I reserve 
               <lb/>
               them until we go into Committee. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               There are, however, some few things to which I will passingly allude. It is important to 
               <lb/>
               British Columbia to know what will be the qualification of Members to the Dominion Parliament 
               <lb/>
               [Hear, hear, from Dr Helmcken] and the qualification of electors. And with reference to 
               <lb/>
               the Local Constitution, it may be necessary for us to know whether our Governors cannot be 
               <lb/>
               elected as in the United States. instead of being appointed on the English principle; and 
               <lb/>
               whether we may not acquire the right to pass local laws over the veto of the Governor, by a 
               <lb/>
               two-third vote of the Legislature. The usury laws, imprisonment for debt, and many other 
               <lb/>
               matters will require careful consideration and attention. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               With respect to the main principle, I am in favour of Confederation, provided the financial 
               <lb/>
               terms are right in amount, and if the other terms will contribute to the advancement and 
               <lb/>
               protection of our industry. If we cannot get favourable terms, which I believe we can, it will 
               <lb/>
               then be for the people of this country to say whether we shall remain in isolation or seek some<lb/>
               other more favourable union. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The debate was here adjourned until Friday, at 1 o'clock. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>-->
            
        <div type="section"> 
            
            <head>
               FRIDAY, 11th MARCH, 1870. 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The debate was resumed by the Hon. Mr. RING, who on rising was greeted with cries of 
               <lb/>
               " Spoke, spoke." 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Ring said:—Sir, I have only spoken to the amendment, and have a right to speak 
               <lb/>
               to the original motion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Doubts were expressed as to the Hon. gentleman's right to speak a second time, but the 
               <lb/>
               Presiding Member was not called upon to decide, and Mr. Ring proceeded :- <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Sir. the Hon. Member for Victoria District commenced by congratulating the Council on 
               <lb/>
               having the grand question of Confederation now before them. He congratulated them on the 
               <lb/>
               great advantage of being able to grapple with a great question like this. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I cannot compliment him on the way in which he introduced his subject. I admire his 
               <lb/>
               perseverance and confess that on many subjects he enlightens Members on both sides of the 
               <lb/>
               House. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I lament to find that having alluded to the opening speech of the Attorney-General, he 
               <lb/>
               thought fit to cast unwarrantable imputations upon that gentleman and the members of the 
               <lb/>
               Government. He suddenly turned aside and quoted a text, which he applied to the Official 
               <lb/>
               Members of this Council, He likened one of them to a woman who forgets her modesty and 
               <lb/>
               shame and goes after lovers for broad; to her who has a harlot's forehead, and refuses to 
               <lb/>
               be ashamed. Sir, I deprecate such allusions; they throw no light upon the subject. I think 
               <lb/>
               that an Honourable and grave body like this, on hearing such charges, should have at once 
               <lb/>
               risen to express their indignation rather than have condoned it by their silence. Nothing is 
               <lb/>
               more easy than to take any one act of a man, or of a body of men, and apply it to a sinister 
               <lb/>
               motive, when it is capable of an honourable one, Sir. I was very glad that the Hon. Attorney. 
               <lb/>
               General had the courage to follow the example of the English House of Commons. He, finding 
               <lb/>
               
            
            <pb n="39" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_039.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">39</fw>
            
            

               no Chaplain to this House, supplied the defect by invoking the blessing of God, which was 
               <lb/>
               met by a sneer. I say I admire his courage in fronting a godless age, by the invocation of<lb/>
               the blessing of Him in whom we live and move and have our being. He was not ashamed 
               <lb/>
               to acknowledge the controlling power of Heaven over the destinies of this fallen Colony. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Now, Sir, the Attorney-General descanted at great length on the advantages of Union. 
               <lb/>
               He put that as the basis of the Government proposition. There is nothing like Union he 
               <lb/>
               says; this is a noble sentiment which all must join in. Everyone would welcome that compre<lb break="no"/>hensive brotherhood which embraces all civilized Nations. I am sure that when the Hon. 
               <lb/>
               Member for Victoria alluded to the possibility of a prospective union with other Powers, he 
               <lb/>
               did not do so in the idea of this Colony abandoning its allegiance to the Crown; because 
               <lb/>
               he expressed a wish to see the desire of general union spreading, is no reason that he should 
               <lb/>
               desire to shake off his connection with the Mother Country. Had it been otherwise, I should 
               <lb/>
               have deplored the Hon. gentleman's loss, of loyalty. Some surprise has existed at the Hon. 
               <lb/>
               Member for Victoria offering suggestions as to the possibility of any other union, Why so? 
               <lb/>
               The Hon. Attorney―General himself gracefully introduced it. Why should not the English<lb break="no"/>speaking race live in peace and form one nation? The people of the United States spring 
               <lb/>
               from one common stock with ourselves. I long to see the time when all national sectarianism 
               <lb/>
               shall be swept away, 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               My position as Member for Nanaimo has been assailed in a cowardly way by what is 
               <lb/>
               called the Press. I have been accused of shrinking from my duty to my constituents at 
               <lb/>
               Nanaimo, because I echoed their sentiments against Confederation. I ask the indulgence of 
               <lb/>
               the House whilst I allude to what occurred at Nanaimo at the last election. At that time the 
               <lb/>
               question of Confederation was rife throughout the Colony; people's minds were agitated; the 
               <lb/>
               people of Nanaimo were almost unanimous against it. In what I said to them during the 
               <lb/>
               progress of the election, and also on the hustings, I told them that I agreed with their views 
               <lb/>
               against Confederation, but that when it came before the Council I should give it my best 
               <lb/>
               attention. It was not made a test question at my election. The people of Nanaimo are still of 
               <lb/>
               their original opinion; and, therefore, I express their opinion now, against this measure; and 
               <lb/>
               say that their convictions are against Confederation, notwithstanding the " No, noes " of certain 
               <lb/>
               Hon. Members. There may be some amongst them, Canadians by birth and principle, who 
               <lb/>
               desire Confederation, who, though they are here, can say with the poet :- <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" Where ere I roam, whatever realms I see, 
               <lb/>
               My heart untravelled fondly turns to thee." <lb/>
            </p></quote>



            <p>Thus much for Nanainio. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
            
            <p>
               Now, I say. Sir, that the question of Confederation ought to be fully and amply discussed 
               <lb/>
               in this House, and to do this there should be a full House. I deny that it is the desire of 
               <lb/>
               the people to have Confederation, but I say let the people have an opportunity of expressing 
               <lb/>
               their opinions in this House. Let the disfranchised districts have first restored to them the 
               <lb/>
               rights of which they have been defrauded. The Governor has been betrayed into supposing 
               <lb/>
               that the people want Confederation, and assuming this to be true, he says I shall now give 
               <lb/>
               the people an opportunity to discuss the terms. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               But let the Franchise be restored, then let the general question of Confederation come 
               <lb/>
               before an enlarged representation; and I say that Confederation should be put alone, aye or 
               <lb/>
               no. Shall we have Confederation; and not upon what terms shall we have it. The proper 
               <lb/>
               course is to dissolve the House, issue new writs, and let the people say whether they want 
               <lb/>
               Confederation; and after they have said yes, then descend into the particulars of it. A Govern<lb break="no"/>ment measure is now proposed, we are bound hand and foot, and handed over to Ottawa I say, 
               <lb/>
               Sir, that being so handed over, we ought to let our masters settle the terms for us. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I, therefore, venture again, Mr. President, to repeat that if it is to go abroad that the 
               <lb/>
               people desire Confederation. then the House should be dissolved, and a fair vote taken. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Hon. Member for Victoria District puts it as if the voice of the people had been heard. 
               <lb/>
               I ask how? Through newspapers? Conventions? Speeches? I say this is not the proper way. 
               <lb/>
               Let the people speak in this House, through a full body of Representatives of their own choosing. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The question has been amply ventilated in this Council. The Hon. Member for Victoria 
               <lb/>
               City has gone fully into what he considers the difficulties. He has been met on the other side 
               <lb/>
               in a manly and able reply by the Hon. Chief Commissioner of Lands and Works, who has been 
               <lb/>
               again met by the Hon. Mr. Wood. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <pb n="40" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_040.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">40</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>


            <p>It is not for me to go into the question of terms now; but I deny emphatically that<lb/>
Confederation is desired by the people. My own constituents 
               are against it; many other<lb/>
constituents are, as I believe, against it also. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>I ask, then, why should the Government attempt to force these Resolutions upon us, by<lb/>
means of the Official Members, who are only supreme in numbers? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            
            
            
            <p>
               The people have had no opportunity to express their wish. Difficulties have been presented 
               <lb/>
               by an Hon. Member, arising from the space between British Columbia and Canada—difficulties 
               <lb/>
               arising from the means of transit, and from the means of communication being cut off—diff<lb break="no"/>culties arising from what is at present called the rebellion in the North―West Provmces; that 
               <lb/>
               strife, as I am informed, gathering strength day by day. ["No, no." from Mr. DeCosmos.] 
               <lb/>
               Hon, Members say "No, no." I am so informed I hope it is not so, but if it be, then under 
               <lb/>
               the name of Union we are called upon to take part in this internecine war. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I long for union as much as any man. In union of good there is strength and victory, 
               <lb/>
               but in union of evil there is defeat and disaster. I shall not occupy the time of this Council: 
               <lb/>
               in adverting to matters which have been amply discussed; in expressing my conscientious 
               <lb/>
               opinion I do my duty. The Hon. Mr. Wood has told us that he counts professional honours 
               <lb/>
               as nought. I say nothing of prior claims to professional honours which I have lost, from, at 
               <lb/>
               all times, conscientiously supporting what I conceived to be right. His Excellency says that 
               <lb/>
               we are not fit for Responsible Government. I want to know on what local data he says so? 
               <lb/>
               Who has tried the people? On the scope of whose mind is it said they are not fit? Who has 
               <lb/>
               examined them? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Hon. Member for Victoria District has properly said, if Hon. Members were paid for 
               <lb/>
               their attendance in the House you would soon see whether men were capable or not to enter 
               <lb/>
               upon and fulfil the duties of Responsible Government. Then we should see whether the gentle<lb break="no"/>men disguised in mean apparel—Graduates of Oxford, Cambridge, and other Universities who 
               <lb/>
               have cast; their lot in this Colony, but are unable to defray their travelling expenses from remote 
               <lb/>
               places to the Capital. We should see, I say, whether they were capable, or not, of enlightening 
               <lb/>
               and controlling by their wisdom the feeble powers of Governmental diplomacy. Sir, by enlarged 
               <lb/>
               representation we shall discover such men. We had one foot forward in the direction of 
               <lb/>
               freedom, it has been forced back. The franchise has been taken away. Sir, I have very feebly 
               <lb/>
               endeavoured to touch upon these subjects. In line, I affirm that the matter has not been, 
               <lb/>
               discussed fairly. There must he an enlarged representation, that the people may tell the 
               <lb/>
               Government what they want. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Hon. Members who have supported Confederation have failed in showing that this is the 
               <lb/>
               time for it. They are afraid to ask the people. They have refused to do so. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Much has been said; more will be said. I have listened, and have heard high―sounding 
               <lb/>
               words, and inflated tautology of this and that Hon. Member, which reminds me of soap―bubbles, 
               <lb/>
               which, though beautiful by the reflection of the sun's prismatic colours, are equally remarkable 
               <lb/>
               for their rotundity and their emptiness. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The Hon. MR. BARNARD said:―Sir, in rising to support the motion of the Hon. and 
               <lb/>
               learned Attorney—General, I can but express my feelings of pleasure in being permitted to take 
               <lb/>
               a part in the great work in hand-that of hewing off the rough corners of the block which 
               <lb/>
               has come to us from the hands of the Executive, and which, after receiving the finishing 
               <lb/>
               touch at the bands of the people, will become the key-stone of the great Confederation arch 
               <lb/>
               which will, ere twelve months, extend from ocean to ocean. The terms as sent down by His 
               <lb/>
               Excellency are, I consider, a fair subject of congratulation The manner in which they have 
               <lb/>
               been received by this House and the people is another subject of congratulation; and the paucity 
               <lb/>
               and utter idleness of the arguments used by the opposition, represented in this House as it is 
               <lb/>
               by the talent of the opposing party in the country, are also subjects of congratulation to His 
               <lb/>
               Excellency, this House, and the country. It is wrong, Mr. President, to Charge the desire for 
               <lb/>
               Confederation on the part of its promoters to a desire for change. So far as my constituency 
               <lb/>
               and the adjoining ones on the Mainland are concerned, I may say safely that such was not the 
               <lb/>
               case—we accepted the Organic Act constituting this Council, and agreed to work it out to its 
               <lb/>
               legitimate end; and we have not countenanced nor have we been subjected to the many changes 
               <lb/>
               which other parts of this Colony have. I desire, before going further, to allude to a charge 
               <lb/>
               commonly made against my countrymen—often offensively put—but yesterday put by the Hon.<lb/>
               
          
            
            <pb n="41" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_041.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">41</fw>
           

     Mr. Wood, in his usual gentlemanly way. It is that of "Canadian proclivity" As a native- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     born Canadian, in common with others, I love the land of my birth. We admire her institutions 
     <lb/>
     and revere her laws; but we never forget the land of our adoption, and we would no more 
     <lb/>
     consent to see her wronged by Canada than would the tens of thousands of Englishmen who 
     <lb/>
     have made Canada their home, permit a wrong to he done her by England. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is also wrong and contrary to fact that, "so anxious are we for Confederation that we 
     <lb/>
     would accede to any terms proposed." During the past three years, I have been one of the 
     <lb/>
     foremost in advocating the cause of Confederation; and, in so doing, throughout the interior 
     <lb/>
     of the Colony, I am free to confess I never uttered such a sentiment; and, in justice to my 
     <lb/>
     fellow-countrymen in particular, and the advocates of this cause in general, I will say that 
     <lb/>
     I never heard any one express a desire that this Colony should be confederated, except on 
     <lb/>
     such terms as might, on investigation, be found to be just and beneficial. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We desire Confederation with Canada, because we believe that it will be to the interest 
     <lb/>
     of this Colony to unite with the progressive Colonies to the east. That they are progressive 
     <lb/>
     I assert, and as proof I point to the fact that, previous to Confederation, Canada proper had 
     <lb/>
     expended $184,000,000 on public works, principally in building canals. Up to 1869, $170,000,000 
     <lb/>
     had been expended in railways. She pays to-day $300,000 yearly for her ocean steam mail 
     <lb/>
     service alone, and her enterprise is followed by her people. Her manufactures are increasing 
     <lb/>
     yearly, and even now she is exporting cloths to England, and competing there with cheap 
     <lb/>
     labour. One firm alone, composed of men who landed in Canada penniloss, now has $9,000,000 
     <lb/>
     invested in ocean steamers, employing 4500 men, and thus sustaining 22,000 persons. Among 
     <lb/>
     the objections urged by Hon. Members against Confederation is our proximity to the United 
     <lb/>
     States. This, I hold, is no objection. Canadians are not taught to fear competition with the 
     <lb/>
     United States. The general feeling there is that we can hold our own (except in point of 
     <lb/>
     numbers) with her in any direction whatever. It is to her we look for a great portion of our 
     <lb/>
     trade, and the advantages of such trade are mutual.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The question is often asked: "What are the immediate advantages to be derived by us 
     <lb/>
     from Confederation? " My reply is that, in addition to the amount paid us by way of subsidies, 
     <lb/>
     we will save by a reduction in the tariff and by importing Canadian manufactures, a very 
     <lb/>
     considerable sum, thus reducing our taxation. Next, the terms propose that $1,000,000 be spent 
     <lb/>
     on a waggon-road to be commenced immediately and completed in three years, thus causing 
     <lb/>
     over $300,000 a year to be spent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. gentlemen will recollect that in 1801. 1862, and 1863, immigration poured in on us, 
     <lb/>
     caused by the report of rich discoveries in Cariboo, and by a knowledge on the part of those 
     <lb/>
     coming that the Government was spending large sums on public works, and that those who 
     <lb/>
     failed in the mines might     fall back on the roads to replenish their purses; and many who are 
     <lb/>
     now permanent settlers in the interior acknowledge that they made their " farm stake " there. 
     <lb/>
     How much more is this likely to be the case if the larger works contemplated in the terms are 
     <lb/>
     carried out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then, Sir, look at the construction of a Railway. You may judge of the magnitude of the 
     <lb/>
     work by the following figures. There were employed on the Central Pacific at one time 25,000 
     <lb/>
     men and 6,000 teams; 600 tons of material were forwarded daily to the point of construction; 
     <lb/>
     30 vessels in harbour at one time, loaded with material; the wharves at San Francisco and 
     <lb/>
     Sacramento loaded with railway iron; 70 locomotives landed, and 700 cars built to carry on 
     <lb/>
     the work on construction account; no less than 30 sawmills in operation at one point at one 
     <lb/>
     time. The enterprise that set this enormous trade in motion is not one of greater magnitude 
     <lb/>
     than will be the work undertaken on this side, and if our farmers and population generally do 
     <lb/>
     not profit, and that immediately, by the carrying on of such enterprises as these let them 
     <lb/>
     succumb, for I know of no state of prosperity that can help them. I contend the benefits 
     <lb/>
     of Confederation, in these respects at least, will be immediate. But Hon. Members have said 
     <lb/>
     "the United States will derive the benefit." If that argument holds good, why not tell the 
     <lb/>
     merchants of Wharf Street to close their doors because foreign manufacturers reap a part of 
     <lb/>
     the benefit of their trade. Better, a great deal, for the opponents of this cause to advise the 
     <lb/>
     farmers to cultivate every inch of their farms and garner up their crops, for the day assuredly 
     <lb/>
     will come when they will have ample market for all they can raise. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It has been urged here that Canada cannot retain her population, much less the immigra<lb break="no"/>tion that comes to her shores, In this, Sir, there is considerable truth, although the Hon. and 
     <lb/>
         
            <pb n="42" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_042.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            <fw type="num">42</fw>


     learned Member for Victoria has not put the matter fairly before this House. In giving the 
     <lb/>
     number of passengers going from Canada to the United States, he has omitted to give you the 
     <lb/>
     number of those passing from the States into Canada. One reason why Canada has not retained 
     <lb/>
     the whole number of emigrants landed on her shores, is that they find greater attractions in 
     <lb/>
     the treeless prairies of the Western States than in the heavily timbered lands of Canada. 
     <lb/>
     This, Sir, has ever been a serious drawback to her. But now the case is different. Having 
     <lb/>
     acquired the vast territories of the great North-West, she will open them to settlement, and 
     <lb/>
     then she will have inducements to offer such as cannot be boasted of by any other country in 
     <lb/>
     the world. Open those millions of acres to the settler, and you will see such a rush of immi<lb break="no"/>gration—not only from the older countries of Europe, but from the United States—as will 
     <lb/>
     astonish the world, and stand unparalleled in the history of immigration. Canada's hardy sons 
     <lb/>
     who have left their homes for the Western States—allured by the advantages of prairie over 
     <lb/>
     wooded lands—will join in swelling the numbers, and once more plant their feet on British 
     <lb/>
     soil. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The difficulties of defence have been spoken of as a formidable obstacle. Sir, she never 
     <lb/>
     regarded them in any such light. Canada has no fears in that direction. She relies on the 
     <lb/>
     thorough good understanding that has existed between herself and the United States for so 
     <lb/>
     long a period, as a guarantee for the future. Their interests are so identical that they cannot 
     <lb/>
     afford to quarrel. The troubles between them heretofore have been on England's account, and 
     <lb/>
     not Canada's, as witness the Trent affair, and the more recent Fenian invasion, which was 
     <lb/>
     rather a stab at England than an attack on Canada. During the recent fratricidal war in 
     <lb/>
     the United States, Canada had a difficult part to play in maintaining strict neutrality, yet she 
     <lb/>
     came out unscathed. It must be remembered, also, that Canada possesses in her canal system 
     <lb/>
     a powerful lever—a guarantee for peace—vastly more potent than fortifications. The great 
     <lb/>
     bulk of the produce of the Western States finds its way to the ocean through Canadian channels, 
     <lb/>
     which could be closed at any moment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As to that "other issue" (I will not use the word that has been so freely used outside), I 
     <lb/>
     have no tears for Canada or this Colony either. It used to be fashionable here, in early days, 
     <lb/>
     to associate the name of Canada with rebellion. It was the result of prejudice and ignorance, 
     <lb/>
     and was a great mistake. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I recently read, Sir, an account of a meeting held in one of our principal Canadian cities, 
     <lb/>
     on the occasion of a Sabbath school convention. An American gentleman was engaged in 
     <lb/>
     addressing the house, filled to its utmost capacity. In the course of his remarks, having 
     <lb/>
     occasion to refer to Her Most Gracious Majesty the Queen, he added:—"American though I 
     <lb/>
     am, I can with all my heart say, ' God bless the Queen.' " Immediately, Sir, without any pre<lb break="no"/>concerted action, the. entire audience of men, women, and children rose to their feet and sung 
     <lb/>
     the National Anthem. That gentleman said, that such a spontaneous, hearty, and unanimous 
     <lb/>
     outburst of loyalty was probably never heard before. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Such, Sir, is the kind of loyalty we were taught in Canada; such is the kind that is 
     <lb/>
     being taught to the rising generation of the new Dominion to-day; and I leave it to you as to 
     <lb/>
     whether there is room for that "other issue " or not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Before concluding. Sir, I would wish to remark with reference to the charge made by the 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Member for Victoria District against the Hon. Attorney-General, that his conversion to 
     <lb/>
     Confederation was late. Iknow that it is impossible to make some Honourable Members 
     <lb/>
     believe anything good of Officials, whether in respect of Confederation or anything else. But I 
     <lb/>
     simply desire to relate this fact. I had occasion to go into the Hon. Attorney-General's office 
     <lb/>
     in 1867, and he then showed me a letter, written by himself, in favour of Confederation; and 
     <lb/>
     after perusing that letter I felt convinced that when, in his estimation, the proper time arrived, 
     <lb/>
     the cause, would have a warm and sincere advocate in the Attorney-General. I mention this 
     <lb/>
     in order to show that the Hon. Member for Victoria District has no right to arrogate to 
     <lb/>
     himself that he was the only man who was far-seeing enough to recognize the advantages of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation three years ago, and as a reproof to him for finding fault with the position taken 
     <lb/>
     by Hon. Official Members on this question now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To sum up, Sir, I say that amongst the statesmen of Canada we may safely look for men 
     <lb/>
     fully competent to control the affairs of a young nation. They are men of as much ambition 
     <lb/>
     and grasp of thought as are the rulers in the adjoining States; and, depend upon it, nothing 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="43" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_043.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">43</fw>
          

     will be left undone to advance the prosperity and well-being of every portion of their vast 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. We may safely repose full confidence in them. England has done so, or she would 
     <lb/>
     never have committed the well-being of four millions of her subjects to their care. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     They can steer the good ship "Dominion" and hold her on her way. She will receive 
     <lb/>
     many a shock, "but 'twill be of the waves, and not the rock." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS, Member for Lillooet, said :—Mr. President, It is not my 
     <lb/>
     intention to occupy the attention of the House at any great length. I shall pass in review 
     <lb/>
     rapidly the arguments for and against Confederation, as they have been used by Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Members who have spoken during the progress of this debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It seems to me, Sir, that the people and their interests have been entirely ignored through<lb break="no"/>out the discussion of this question, and perhaps intentionally. I refer to the subject of 
     <lb/>
     Responsible Government ["Hear, hear," from Mr DeCosmos], which has up to this stage been 
     <lb/>
     all but lost sight of. l, Sir, am one of those men who believe in the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I remember that in opening; this debate, the Hon. Attorney-General invoked the Divine 
     <lb/>
     blessing upon the work upon which we were then entering. This was high-sounding, and a 
     <lb/>
     very nice picture to look at, but it does not wear well without that strict attention to the 
     <lb/>
     divine rights of the people, which is inalienable from true political economy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have a distinct recollection of most Hon. Members now occupying an official position at 
     <lb/>
     this Council Board, and of the positions which they occupied when first they came to this 
     <lb/>
     Colony. I have often asked myself what entitles these Hon. Members to govern this Colony; 
     <lb/>
     but I have never been able to answer myself satisfactorily, I am perfectly ready to admit the 
     <lb/>
     ability of Executive Members as individuals. The learned eloquence of the Hon. Attorney- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     General has always, since 1 have had the honour to sit at this Council Board, impressed me 
     <lb/>
     with a deep sense of the advantage of thorough forensic training; and the power and force of 
     <lb/>
     the reply of the lion, the Chief Commissioner has ever and again made me feel with especial 
     <lb/>
     force the utter hopelessness of combating stern official reticence with even the most brilliant 
     <lb/>
     powers of oratory. Yet, Sir, whatever our admiration for individual excellence, however great 
     <lb/>
     our estimation of personal worth, the question has still remained unanswered, and, in my 
     <lb/>
     opinion, unanswerable. What is there in the collective wisdom of these Honourable Official 
     <lb/>
     Members that entitled them to arrogate to themselves the right to rule? Are they, I ask, the 
     <lb/>
     dominant race, and are the people serfs? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We have heard a great deal about absorption, and the danger of the larger body swallow<lb break="no"/>ing up the smaller. I think about as much of that danger as I do of the other evil threatened 
     <lb/>
     in such earnest and thrilling language by the Hon. Member for Victoria, namely, that our 
     <lb/>
     salmon would be under Confederation, and the protection from salmon nets that would be 
     <lb/>
     extended to them, increase and multiply to such an extent that they would absorb all the 
     <lb/>
     smaller fish. I, however, to speak seriously, doubt very much if the Hon. Member can cite 
     <lb/>
     a single example in history of the larger absorbing the lesser. unless the larger possessed 
     <lb/>
     better qualifications, as in the case of the absorption by British Columbia of Vancouver Island. 
     <lb/>
     Sir, we must give up all personal prejudices, and we must bend our minds to the establishment 
     <lb/>
     of a great British Empire upon this Pacific Coast. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Lord Macaulay says that "Governments are made for the people, and not the people for 
     <lb/>
     the Governments." Yet, Sir, how different seems to he the course of reasoning in this Colony. 
     <lb/>
     Here we have a strange compound of sickly representation and unpoular officialdom. The want 
     <lb/>
     of Responsible Government has become intolerable; the people have ceased to respect the 
     <lb/>
     Government, and the Government seem to be doing their best to educate the people up to hating 
     <lb/>
     the officials. There is to my mind, Sir, no necessity for the continuance of such a state of 
     <lb/>
     things; only let the people's voice be heard, and there will be a change. The overwhelming 
     <lb/>
     preponderance of the official element in this Council, and the presence in the Legislative body 
     <lb/>
     of officials who are paid by the people, and yet are not responsible to them, is the real cause 
     <lb/>
     of the alienation of the hearts of the people from the Government. The votes of these Hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen must always oscillate between their own interests and what their own consciences 
     <lb/>
     dictate to them as for the good of the country. It is our duty, Sir, to bring back the hearts 
     <lb/>
     of the people. We must have a Government by and for the people. This is what I believe the 
     <lb/>
     people really require, and this and more. if necessary, the Government must be prepared to 
     <lb/>
     give them. The people of this Colony will consent to no arrangement which has not for its 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="44" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_044.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">44</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
         

     
     foundation—Responsible Government. We must be prepared to pull down and demolish the 
     <lb/>
     old structure, in order to rear up one that shall endure—as a Government secure in the 
     <lb/>
     affections of the people only can endure. I warn Hon. gentlemen that they must endeavour 
     <lb/>
     to recover the wills of the people; then, and not till then, will return that prosperity which we 
     <lb/>
     all desire to see.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I hope, Sir, that the Executive will not attempt to make any arrangement with the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Government which does not include popular self-government. The people will never 
     <lb/>
     accept Confederation without Responsible Government.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We must first get the tree-Responsible Govermnent—and we may afterwards, with some 
     <lb/>
     reason, hope to get the fruit. I say, Sir, that it is a gross libel upon the intelligence of the 
     <lb/>
     people of this Colony, to say that we are not fitted for self-government. In no country can 
     <lb/>
     you find men better capable of governing themselves, and of managing their own affairs, than 
     <lb/>
     in this Colony. I hold, Sir, that the greatest enemies of the people are those who always 
     <lb/>
     endeavour to blazon forth their learning. I am proud to say that I am of the people. My 
     <lb/>
     education, if not of so high a culture as that of some Hon. Members of this House, has at 
     <lb/>
     least enabled me, up to this time, to make my own way in the world, unaided by official pay 
     <lb/>
     and without the assistance of official favour or influence. And when I hear Hon. Members 
     <lb/>
     speaking of the people as a class unfit for self-government. I find it difficult to believe that 
     <lb/>
     such a set of men are the same as have been speaking before, in this House and outside, on 
     <lb/>
     Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In conclusion, Sir, I say fearlessly that Responsible Government is a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi> in the 
     <lb/>
     terms of Confederation. Place what conditions you will before the people, without the condition 
     <lb/>
     of Responsible Government, and Confederation is killed.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Confederation means to Official Members a pension; to the people it means self-government; 
     <lb/>
     and I say, Sir, that above all things, we must keep in view the absolute necessity of keeping 
     <lb/>
     control of our own local affairs, otherwise Confederation would be useless to the country; 
     <lb/>
     and I warn Hon. Members at the other side of the House, that to exclude Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment from the terms is to ensure defeat for the whole Confederation scheme when it comes 
     <lb/>
     before the people at the polls. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Hon. MR. CARRALL, Member for Cariboo, said :—Mr. President, I did not intend to 
     <lb/>
     open my lips during this debate; indeed, I am left with very little to say by the Honourable 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen who have preceded me. I have taken notes with a view, it those assertions which 
     <lb/>
     were put forth were not answered, of replying to them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     For three days I have sat at this Board and heard discussions <hi rendition="simple:italic">pro</hi> and <hi rendition="simple:italic">con</hi>. I have heard 
     <lb/>
     nearly every word; certainly every argument which Honourable Members on both sides have 
     <lb/>
     adduced ; especially have I listened to every argument of those who are in opposition, and I 
     <lb/>
     believe that nothing remains unanswered—in fact, but a few crumbs are left for me. Another 
     <lb/>
     reason why I did not desire to make a speech is that my principles are pretty thoroughly 
     <lb/>
     known, and I deem it almost a work of supererogation to reiterate my sentiments. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     But as this debate as to whether we should go into Committee or not has taken such a 
     <lb/>
     serious turn, I think it right and proper to say a few words. Whoever knows me through this 
     <lb/>
     Colony, or through British North America, knows that my principles have never changed on 
     <lb/>
     this great Confederation question.  I have always  maintained that the fragments of 
     <lb/>
     empire lying loose, so to speak, in British North America, east and west of the Rocky 
     <lb/>
     Mountains, should be united and consolidated under one Government. The question of the 
     <lb/>
     Confederation of the whole Colonial Empire of Great Britain is one that has always appeared 
     <lb/>
     to me to be replete with the greatest interest, and I trust that I may be spared to see this 
     <lb/>
     consolidation consummated. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With regard to the advantages that Confederation will bring to British Columbia, it is 
     <lb/>
     almost forbidden, ground, for the advantages are in reality part of the Resolutions. If I allude 
     <lb/>
     to them I am forestalling the debate on terms; and as I should not be in a position to prove 
     <lb/>
     anything which is in futurity, I had perhaps better abstain from touching upon the subject. 
     <lb/>
     However, this much I will say, that, after sentiment and loyalty are disposed of, it becomes a 
     <lb/>
     question of advantage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The terms sent down to this House, in my opinion, warrant our acceptance of them in 
     <lb/>
     their entirety; but if the House think otherwise, I may, I am sure, go so far as to say that 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="45" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_045.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">45</fw>
          

     the Executive are open to receive suggestions, and that there will be no objection to adopt 
     <lb/>
     any suggestions which will not be likely to jeopardize the success of the whole scheme. In this 
     <lb/>
     conviction, I do not propose to go over the ground that has already been taken up. But I 
     <lb/>
     must allude to what I cannot help calling the feeling of over-care and caution which has been 
     <lb/>
     displayed throughout this debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I believe, Mr. President, that you are an Englishman, and as a nation I think you express 
     <lb/>
     too much caution, fear, and anxiety with respect to the course which Canada might pursue. 
     <lb/>
     I do not speak personally, but such appears to me to be the characteristic  quality of English<lb break="no"/>men, and it has especially cropped out during this debate. I say that I believe we are treating 
     <lb/>
     with a far-seeing, fair-dealing set of men who would never forfeit their word, statesmen who 
     <lb/>
     would be incapable of offering "mean conditions," even if we of British Columbia would accept 
     <lb/>
     them. They will give us terms to make us happy and contented. Another reason for our feel<lb break="no"/>ing confidence in the future is that we shall have under these terms, as the Hon. Member for 
     <lb/>
     Victoria District says, an enormous proportion of Representatives at Ottawa, and I presume 
     <lb/>
     that each of these Representatives will have a voice and the gift of speech. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is fair to augur that the Dominion statesmen will give us what will make us contented 
     <lb/>
     and prosperous. In touching upon this point, I should like to make an historical allusion, and 
     <lb/>
     for example I would refer to the present condition of the Union between Great Britain and 
     <lb/>
     Ireland. ["hear, hear," from Dr. Helmcken.] When Hon. gentlemen say "Hear, hear." they 
     <lb/>
     may think I have given an unapt illustration. We, however, know that the number of Ireland's 
     <lb/>
     representatives, amounting to something over one hundred, have enabled the Irish members of 
     <lb/>
     the British  House of Commons to hold the balance of power and the bulk of patronage between 
     <lb/>
     the great contending political parties, and by swaying between the Gladstones and Disraelis, or 
     <lb/>
     other leaders of the day, they have frequently been able. to turn the scale so as to obtain what 
     <lb/>
     they desired. and to secure  a liberal share of the patronage to office. I maintain, Sir, in this 
     <lb/>
     connection, that if British  Columbia found that by reason of her small  representation-large 
     <lb/>
     in comparison with the representation of the different States in the Congress of America—I 
     <lb/>
     say, that if British Columbian Members found that there was any disposition to tyrannize in 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion House of Commons, which I do not for one moment fear, they could make common 
     <lb/>
     cause with other small maritime Provinces against Canada proper. To quote the words of the 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Chief Commissioner, I believe that British Columbia will be a pet Province of the Con<lb break="no"/>federacy. I try, Sir, to avoid speech-making; the time for that will be in Committee. I do 
     <lb/>
     not hope to sway a single vote by any remarks that I make. I believe that every Hon. Member 
     <lb/>
     came here previously prepared to vote one way or the other, and I do not think any eloquent 
     <lb/>
     orators, and much less any feeble words of mine, will cause one of them to change his opinion. 
     <lb/>
     But I make a speech in order that a record may be taken of it, and my constituents may be 
     <lb/>
     able to see that I was not dumb. I believe, I say, that all Hon. Members came down with their 
     <lb/>
     opinions formed, as to whether the amendment of the Hon. and learned Member for Victoria, 
     <lb/>
     or the proposition of the Hon. and learned Attorney-General, which was so ably put before us, 
     <lb/>
     should be carried. I sincerely hope, however, that Hon. Members will join me in voting down 
     <lb/>
     the amendment and in supporting the motion of the Hon. Attorney-General. This is emphatic<lb break="no"/>ally, the question of the day and the policy of the Government should meet with a liberal and 
     <lb/>
     warm support from every Member of this Council, in order that: the question may be fairly 
     <lb/>
     brought before the people for final decision. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And here, Sir, with the permission of the House, I will say one word upon the course 
     <lb/>
     pursued by the Government. The Executive Council have been actuated by motives of duty 
     <lb/>
     only. They have brought down these   Resolutions, based on a broad view of the whole subject, 
     <lb/>
     and they ask you to make suggestions and additions. [Dr. Helmcken- "No, they don't"] Yes, 
     <lb/>
     Sir, I maintain that the Executive do so, and I will maintain it with my last breath. The 
     <lb/>
     Executive are prepared to consider, and it possible give effect to, every amendment or suggestion 
     <lb/>
     of this Council, provided it does not jeopardize the success of the scheme with the Canadian 
     <lb/>
     Government. The final verdict must: come from the people, and I can safely maintain that 
     <lb/>
     nothing could be fairer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Among things brought up in the course of this debate, the questions of Tariff and Respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government occupy prominent positions. I think the Hon. Member for Victoria District 
     <lb/>
     has taken right ground, when he said that it was competent for the Dominion Government to 
     <lb/>
     alter and amend the tariff so as to protect every vested interest in this Colony. I am no lawyer, 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="46" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_046.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">46</fw>  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> 
     

     but I believe the Canadian statesmen are sufficiently far-seeing to take care that not an interest 
     <lb/>
     in this Colony shall suffer by the Resolutions which we are about passing. With regard to the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Tariff, people thought that the abrogation of the Reciprocity Treaty was the death- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     knell of the independence of Canada. I have lived, however, to see her more prosperous by that 
     <lb/>
     abrogation. It has taught her to develop her own resources, and to become self-reliant. After 
     <lb/>
     she was prevented from going to the United States, by that abrogation, she turned her attention 
     <lb/>
     to her own resources, and I believe she is now going to be one of the most progressive nations 
     <lb/>
     upon the earth. Undoubtedly, she is determined to progress westward, until she reaches British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia and the Pacific; and with all her progressive tendency she will not abate one jot of 
     <lb/>
     the loyalty for which, now as ever, she is distinguished. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, with regard to Responsible Government. {"Hear, hear," from Mr. DeCosmos.] I 
     <lb/>
     desire to touch lightly upon this subject in passing, because I have been told that my popularity 
     <lb/>
     has suffered by some remarks to which I gave utterance in this House upon a previous occasion. 
     <lb/>
     Much as I value popularity, I must on this question express my honest and conscientious opinion 
     <lb/>
     as an individual. I believe that I was the first to break ground on the question of Responsible 
     <lb/>
     Government, in connection with Confederation. I did it, not hastily or thoughtlessly, but on 
     <lb/>
     conviction; and I maintain that so long as I do it honestly, I am free to say what I please, as 
     <lb/>
     an individual, upon this matter. I do not believe, Sir, that, with our present population, with our 
     <lb/>
     people scattered over a vast extent of thinly populated country, and having regard to the various 
     <lb/>
     conflicting interests consequent on remoteness from the centre, the principle of Responsible 
     <lb/>
     Government cannot be satisfactorily applied to this community at present. I believe entirely 
     <lb/>
     in the ability and fitness of the Anglo-Saxon race to govern themselves; but I say that the time 
     <lb/>
     has not yet arrived under which that particular form of government, generally known as Respon<lb break="no"/>sible, can be satisfactorily worked in this Colony. I believe that the scheme foreshadowed by 
     <lb/>
     the Governor for Representative Govermnent will be the best that, under present circumstances, 
     <lb/>
     the Colony can have. The popular members under that system will have a clear majority, and, 
     <lb/>
     consequently, the people will have the control of the  purse-strings. I do not speak these words 
     <lb/>
     as a member of the Executive Council, but as the expression of my own deliberate opinion. Sir, 
     <lb/>
     I was not sent here pledged to any particular platform. My constituents had confidence in me, 
     <lb/>
     and were content that I should act on my own judgment. Speaking officially, I say that Respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government is not a question of Union. The Act of Union gives us the exclusive right to 
     <lb/>
     alter our own laws with respect to everything connected with the internal and local Government 
     <lb/>
     of the Province, so long as the Federal prerogative, if I may so call it, is not infringed. If the 
     <lb/>
     majority of the people want Responsible Government after Confederation, neither Governor 
     <lb/>
     Musgrave nor any other power on earth can prevent their having it. It is unfounded, unfair, 
     <lb/>
     and unjust, on the part of those who are opposed to the Government on the question of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, to endeavour to put any other complexion upon the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With respect, Mr. President, to the remarks  about Cabinet Ministers and Executive Coun<lb break="no"/>cillors, which have fallen from certain Hon. Members, I will only refer to the work that the 
     <lb/>
     Executive have laid before this House. From the general approbation which has been tendered, 
     <lb/>
     both in this House and on the outside, to the terms of Confederation which have been sent down 
     <lb/>
     by the Executive, I think that I am fairly entitled to assume that our labour has not been in 
     <lb/>
     vain, and that it has given   satisfaction. I thank this Council for the words of encouragement 
     <lb/>
     and approbation with which they have accepted these conditions, especially those who have 
     <lb/>
     endorsed   them. No one—not even the Hon. Member for Victoria City—can say that it is not 
     <lb/>
     the wish of the people that this question should be discussed, and ultimately dealt with by 
     <lb/>
     the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A charge has been preferred by the Hon. Member for Victoria District, against the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Attorney—General and the Hon. Chief Commissioner,  to the effect that they had turned their 
     <lb/>
     coats and changed since they had given votes upon Confederation in this House upon a former 
     <lb/>
     occasion.  If they have changed, I maintain that upon conviction they are not to be blamed for 
     <lb/>
     doing so. It was well known that the Hon. gentleman had stated, or at all events I have always 
     <lb/>
     so understood it, had a telegram, or some other information from head-quarters,  more than a 
     <lb/>
     year ago, to the effect that the Dominion Government were not prepared to negotiate terms of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation with this Colony, until after the settlement of the Red River question, which was 
     <lb/>
     then pending with the Hudson's Bay Company. The Hon. Attorney-General and the Hon. Chief 
     <lb/>
     Commissioner took this same ground last year. They were of opinion that nothing could be 
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="47" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_047.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>   <fw type="num">47</fw>
          

     done to further Confederation satisfactorily, until the sovereignty of the Dominion was estab<lb break="no"/>lished in the North-West Territory. Both assured me privately that they were in favour of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation, and I say that they entered into the consideration of the scheme without mention 
     <lb/>
     of pensions being secured to them. Who, I ask, are Confederates? The people most unquestion<lb break="no"/>ably; and could we, the people of this Colony, ever have made Confederation a successful issue 
     <lb/>
     unless it had been taken up by Government? His Excellency Governor Musgrave has done 
     <lb/>
     nothing but what Prime Ministers do every day, in making this a Government question. On 
     <lb/>
     the part of the Government, I cordially invite the assistance, co-oporation, and earnest delibera<lb break="no"/>tion of all Members of the Council to the scheme—a good one—and after we have done our best 
     <lb/>
     with it, we must leave it to the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Before I close my remarks. Sir, I must allude to what fell from the Hon. Member for 
     <lb/>
     Victoria City, whose opinion and lightest remarks are always received and listened to by this 
     <lb/>
     House with the greatest deference and respect, and every wrinkle of whose brow is a notch 
     <lb/>
     in the calendar of a well―spent life, for whose character as an individual I have the highest 
     <lb/>
     reverence and esteem. I cannot but say, however, that in my opinion, and I believe in the 
     <lb/>
     opinion of this House, what the Hon. gentleman did say about another possible issue was ill- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     timed, inopportune, and unhappy; and, Sir, I deem it my duty as a Member of the Executive 
     <lb/>
     Council to say, that if he did intend to foreshadow the idea that the other union, to which he 
     <lb/>
     made ill―timed allusion, could ever be an issue in this Colony, he entirely misrepresented the 
     <lb/>
     views of the Executive Council. In this connection I desire to say that, in common with the 
     <lb/>
     Chief Commissioner, I feel a great respect for our neighbours of the Great Republic. I honour 
     <lb/>
     the country and its institutions; particularly I esteem the people of America in the exercise of 
     <lb/>
     national and domestic relations. They are true Anglo-Saxons. They are at this moment lavish<lb break="no"/>ing an amount of hospitality on Prince Arthur, which would do honour to any nation. But, 
     <lb/>
     whilst professing great respect for the people and for the Government of the United States, I 
     <lb/>
     confess that I do not like their political institutions. I have many friends in America, and 
     <lb/>
     I have spent some time there myself, in their military service, but I left America a greater 
     <lb/>
     Canadian than ever. And I say, Sir, that I deem the action taken by certain foreigners here, 
     <lb/>
     in getting up a petition, which has perhaps been brought into more prominent notice than it 
     <lb/>
     was entitled to, exceedingly unhappy, and I know that I speak the sentiments of my constituents 
     <lb/>
     when I say so. These foreigners have received every hospitality, and have been treated with 
     <lb/>
     respect and liberality in this Colony. They enjoyed all the rights and privileges to which they 
     <lb/>
     would have been entitled in their own country, and perhaps more; they have acted foolishly 
     <lb/>
     towards the flag that sheltered them, and have abused the hospitality which has been extended 
     <lb/>
     to them in getting up this petition. If any British subjects signed it, I consider them unworthy 
     <lb/>
     of the name; they would be better in the chain―gang. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I must refer once again to the Hon. Member for Victoria City. He said that patriotism was 
     <lb/>
     dead in this Colony; that interest and self-interest was paramount, and that the dollar was 
     <lb/>
     supreme, and was the only patriotism. [Dr. Helmcken—" What? what? I said nothing of the 
     <lb/>
     kind."] I maintain that the words were used, and I say that the Hon. Member misunderstood 
     <lb/>
     or misrepresented the feelings of the people of this Colour in saying so. It is, perhaps, 
     <lb/>
     unbecoming in me, who have not the stake in the country, and who have not the status, 
     <lb/>
     domestic, monetary, or political, of most other gentlemen round this Council Board, and who 
     <lb/>
     have, comparatively speaking, but lately come to the Colony, to express an opinion; but never<lb break="no"/>theless I do say that patriotism is not dead in this Colony, and that the people are as patriotic, 
     <lb/>
     noble, and generous―hearted as any other people in the world. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr Helmcken—Sir, I rise to a question of privilege. I cannot allow the Hon. Member 
     <lb/>
     to make a speech about something I did not say without correcting him. I said that this Colony 
     <lb/>
     had no love for Canada; the bargain for love could not be; it can only be the advancement of 
     <lb/>
     material interests which will lend to union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Carrall—I maintain, Sir, that I have not in any wayexaggerated what the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman did say; and I conclude by saying that the people of British Columbia are loyal, 
     <lb/>
     honourable, and true, and when they give their adhesion to the Dominion they will uphold the 
     <lb/>
     British flag,  they always have upheld— <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" The flag that has braved a thousand years 
     <lb/>
     The battle and the breeze." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <pb n="48" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_048.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">48</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            

<p>
     The Hon. Mr ALSTON, Registrar—General, said :—Sir, I should not have risen to attempt 
     <lb/>
     to make a speech at this late hour, had it not been from the peculiar position which I occupy in 
     <lb/>
     this Council, and I feel that I ought to apologise for detaining the House, even for a few minutes, 
     <lb/>
     after the very exhaustive arguments on both sides have been heard with such patient attention. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As I am neither one of the Executive, nor a Representative Member of this House, I have 
     <lb/>
     to satisfy my own conscience, and as it is probable I may not have another opportunity of 
     <lb/>
     expressing my opinion on the principle of Confederation with Canada, I must beg leave to say 
     <lb/>
     a few words. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It will be unnecessary to follow up the subject at any length, as I believe that the principle 
     <lb/>
     of Confederation has been virtually conceded. I give the Hon. Member for Victoria District all 
     <lb/>
     the credit that may be due for the consistent way in which he has agitated this question for 
     <lb/>
     years past, and probably the reason why the matter was not earlier brought to a successful issue 
     <lb/>
     through that agitation, was that either he did the right thing in the wrong way, or that he lived 
     <lb/>
     before his time. From 1867 to the present time, the question has been discussed in successive 
     <lb/>
     sessions of the Council, and it has been declared in effect that, at some future time, Confederation 
     <lb/>
     would be of advantage to this Colony. The Imperial Government have now spoken out unmis<lb break="no"/>takeably in the matter, and have decided that Confederation shall take place. It seems that 
     <lb/>
     those who have the power to shape the destinies of this Colony have decided that it is to take 
     <lb/>
     a part in the great scheme of Confederation of the British North American Colonies, and have 
     <lb/>
     not hesitated to throw the whole weight of their enormous influence in the scale to effect this 
     <lb/>
     object; the Canadian Parliament manifestly urge this matter as a necessary part of the scheme; 
     <lb/>
     and last, though not least, a large portion of the people of this Colony cry aloud for it as a 
     <lb/>
     panacea for all their ills. Downing Street has not hesitated to guide and control the opinions 
     <lb/>
     of Her Majesty's servants in this Colony. Whether this be wise or prudent on the part of the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary of State for the Colonies, in view of the present constitution of this Colony, it is not 
     <lb/>
     for me to say, but it is of no use blinding our eyes to the fact that they who have the power 
     <lb/>
     will—and for aught I know should—exercise it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It was fitting, then, that the Executive of this Colony should take the initiative and under<lb break="no"/>take the responsibility of placing the matter before the countrv in a tangible shape, I rejoice 
     <lb/>
     that they have done so, and that the working out of the basis of arrangements has fallen into 
     <lb/>
     so able hands, for what other party have the power to do so? If they had not preoccupied the 
     <lb/>
     ground, who is there? What part is there in this small community commanding sufficient 
     <lb/>
     general respect that could have undertaken this important duty, with any chance of success? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Now, Sir, the Resolutions before us form no final measure, no unavoidable and perfected 
     <lb/>
     conditions I look upon them simply as the basis of arrangement—the initial step in the 
     <lb/>
     negotiation of the business. If it had been otherwise—if these were proposed as final conditions. 
     <lb/>
     upon which the people of the Colony would he allowed to pass no vote, over which they would 
     <lb/>
     exercise no control; if the Government had said to this Council, you shall have these terms or 
     <lb/>
     none. I would have voted against them or retired from this Assembly. But the Governor has 
     <lb/>
     declared that they shall be submitted to a popular vote, and ratified by a really representative 
     <lb/>
     and reconstructed Council. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That being so, I can give them my conscientious support, not only because I deem it to be 
     <lb/>
     my duty to support every well—considered Government measure, but because I believe them to 
     <lb/>
     be, as far as they go, reasonable, fair, and advantageous. Before now, a Government measure 
     <lb/>
     has claimed a support, but a reluctant one; in this case it is not so, I trust I may be allowed 
     <lb/>
     to render my small tribute of thanks to the Hon. Member for Victoria City, who with great 
     <lb/>
     self—denial has undertaken an unenviable position, one which, of necessity, would lay himself 
     <lb/>
     open to attack and misrepresentation; but one in which he has done and can do great service 
     <lb/>
     to his country. I think I can see, in the Resolutions before me, evidences of this service; traces 
     <lb/>
     of his handiwork; and although he cannot give the measure his support, I feel sure, though I 
     <lb/>
     desire not to penetrate the secrets of that mysterious chamber, that he has done all in his power 
     <lb/>
     to render them as beneficial, or rather, as the Hon. Member himself would say, as little hurtful 
     <lb/>
     as he could to the best interests of the Colony. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When this subject came up for discussion, in the last Session of this Council, I joined those 
     <lb/>
     who were supposed to form the Confederate party, and moved the following Resolution :— <lb/>
            </p>
            

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>" That however desirable Confederation with Canada may hereafter become, this Council believes 
     <lb/>
     that until the great Territory intervening between this Colony and the Dominionis transferred to the 
     <lb/>
     Crown, and contains a larger and more settled population, it would be premature to express any 
     <lb/>
     definite opinion on the subject." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <pb n="49" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_049.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">49</fw>
            

<p>
     It is unnecessary for me to say anything in favour of the principle of Confederation. It is 
     <lb/>
     admitted in the Resolution which I have just read. I take it, Sir, that the obstacle there referred 
     <lb/>
     to will be speedily removed; that the small band of disaffected spirits will soon disperse, and 
     <lb/>
     that the machinery of Government will shortly be put in motion; and though I do not take 
     <lb/>
     pleasure, like the Hon. Member on my left, in revolution, political hatred, agitation, and blood 
     <lb/>
     and thunder generally, I am not disposed to regret the occurrence of the difficulty in the Red 
     <lb/>
     River, for it will teach the Canadian Government, and the Imperial Government, and all Govern<lb break="no"/>ments, that though you may buy and sell territories, you cannot transfer the human beings 
     <lb/>
     therein, like so many serfs and chattels, to a fresh allegiance with impunity; that the consent 
     <lb/>
     of the people must be first obtained; and that though the soil may be sold, the soul is free. 
     <lb/>
     This measure was, to a certain extent, forced upon the Government by the people of this Colony. 
     <lb/>
     It is said that the people clamour for a change in the Government. Why, Sir, we have had 
     <lb/>
     changes enough during that time I have been in the Colony, to ruin any country; changes 
     <lb/>
     generally for the worse. [" No, no," from Mr. DeCosmosJ But whether Confederation comes 
     <lb/>
     or not, there is one change more which I hope to see before this year expires, and that is a 
     <lb/>
     change in the Constitution of this Council. I desire to see all the Members, save the Executive 
     <lb/>
     Officers, elected by the people; and this change is promised by the Governor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I hope, also, that the Colony will so prosper, and the population so increase, that before 
     <lb/>
     many years another change will come, that is to say Responsible Government. At present, 
     <lb/>
     I believe we are not fitted for it; it is practically impossible, and the Governor has had the 
     <lb/>
     courage to declare it. I would gladly believe that the cry for this panacea for all evil does 
     <lb/>
     not come from those who would fain jump into vacant places, and enjoy what they are pleased 
     <lb/>
     to term bloated idleness. Such pharisaic patriotism was so well exposed by my much-abused 
     <lb/>
     friend at the bottom of the table (Dr. Helmcken), that I will not further allude to it. But 
     <lb/>
     I say, Sir, that if they can find public servants who will perform their duties better and more 
     <lb/>
     perfectly, let them in God's name come on. I am content, for one, to give place to better men. 
     <lb/>
     Now is the opportunity offered. But, Sir, I am rejoiced that this measure has come down 
     <lb/>
     from the Executive; it will, when accomplished, give us rest I hope from this everlasting change. 
     <lb/>
     The farmer, the artizan, the capitalist, and the merchant will know what to expect, and will 
     <lb/>
     make their plans accordingly. Years ago, the farmer naturally expected that the Free Port 
     <lb/>
     system was settled and approved of. Agitation commenced, the farmer and the merchant could 
     <lb/>
     not carry on their pursuits without anxiety, and the Colony suffered. The Free Port was 
     <lb/>
     abolished—that grand political mistake—Union with British Columbia was effected, and a heavy 
     <lb/>
     tariff imposed, and business calculations were confounded again. But this Colony and the 
     <lb/>
     people have such elastic force, that they are again beginning to settle themselves down to the 
     <lb/>
     new order of things. Business went on, it is true, but, nevertheless, it suffered; and for the last 
     <lb/>
     two years agitation has again been at work. The farmer is alarmed; he is prosperous at 
     <lb/>
     present, but he dreads (unnecessarily I think) what will be virtually to him the Free Port 
     <lb/>
     system again; and so alarm, and change, and unquietness are for ever distracting this small 
     <lb/>
     and struggling Colony, which., unless it had immense vital energy, and enormous latent strength, 
     <lb/>
     would long ago have succumbed. I see, however, in the prospect before us, a sign of better 
     <lb/>
     things—a more hopeful future—a state which when consummated will, I believe, secure a more 
     <lb/>
     settled life to the Colony. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I do not fear for the agricultural interest, for I believe the only protection which the 
     <lb/>
     farmer requires, is the protection of good roads, good laws, and an easy communication with 
     <lb/>
     the markets where he may best dispose of his produce. Self-interest, if no other reason, will 
     <lb/>
     induce the Canadian Government so to modify the Tariff as to endanger as little as possible 
     <lb/>
     the various interests, agricultural and otherwise of the Colony. I firmly believe that Canada 
     <lb/>
     will deal justly with us; at any rate, it is our duty to deal frankly and in a friendly spirit with 
     <lb/>
     the Canadians, until we see signs of a contrary spirit animating them. I am ready to shake 
     <lb/>
     hands across the Rocky Mountains with our Canadian brethren; let us not open negotiations 
     <lb/>
     with clenched fists.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As regards the paucity of representation allowed to us in the Dominion Parliament, after 
     <lb/>
     what has been shown so clearly to us by the Hon. Member for Victoria District of the analogous 
     <lb/>
     right of representation enjoyed by the Pacific States of the American Union, I think we cannot 
     <lb/>
     rightly expect more. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

          
            <pb n="50" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_050.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">50</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
<p>
     My Hon. friend on my right (Mr. Wood), who certainly has placed the objections and 
     <lb/>
     arguments against Confederation forcibly before the House, says that Confederation means 
     <lb/>
     an union of equal States self—governed, and is equivalent to absorption. I doubt whether this 
     <lb/>
     is historically correct. But, Sir, whether that be so or not is beside the question, for the 
     <lb/>
     Resolutions which are before us are in fact Resolutions for the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Union</hi> of this Colony with 
     <lb/>
     Canada. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Union</hi> is the term used in the Organic Act, and the term Confederation never once 
     <lb/>
     occurs. It is <hi rendition="simple:italic">Union</hi> we are seeking, not Confederation. The American States are States of 
     <lb/>
     the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Union</hi>, not of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Confederation</hi>, and it has been conclusively shown that in that country 
     <lb/>
     the separate States are not absorbed, although united. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And again, Sir, we were told that we are selling our independence, and transferring our 
     <lb/>
     loyalty. Not a bit of it. If the people of this Colony pass the measure, surely their verdict 
     <lb/>
     is not one of slavery, unless they be slaves themselves, and yet they are free to act. This 
     <lb/>
     measure will not pass unless the people of this Colony are willing that it should, and declare 
     <lb/>
     unmistakeably that it is for their benefit. Whatever I may individually think, I shall bow to 
     <lb/>
     the free popular decision, and be prepared to believe that the <hi rendition="simple:italic">vox populi</hi> is the <hi rendition="simple:italic">vox dei</hi>. In so 
     <lb/>
     great a measure, I trust the people may be guided to a right conclusion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As to loyalty, I need add no more than has already been said so forcibly by the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Attorney—General and the Hon. Chief Commissioner of Lands and Works. Hemmed in to the 
     <lb/>
     north and south by a people owing a different allegiance to our own; forced back to the sea 
     <lb/>
     to west, the only direction in which loyal hearts can turn is to the rising people of the east, 
     <lb/>
     who ask us to unite in a friendly spirit with them, to form a great Nation. May that union 
     <lb/>
     prove a source of strength to us and them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I shall give to the Government measure a hearty support, reserving, however, to myself 
     <lb/>
     the right of suggesting any amendment or improvements, or of supporting any recommendations 
     <lb/>
     which may appear to me to be necessary or desirable. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     From the position which I hold in this Council as an officer of the Government, I have 
     <lb/>
     deemed it right to make this statement of the course which I propose to follow in this great 
     <lb/>
     and momentous subject, and I maintain it to be perfectly conscientious and perfectly consistent 
     <lb/>
     with my previous conduct. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
       
            <p>
     The Hon. MR. DEWDNEY, Member for Kootenay, rose and said :—Mr. President, I have 
     <lb/>
     purposely waited until this late stage of the debate in order to avail myself of the opportunity 
     <lb/>
     of listening to the arguments that have been adduced both for and against the scheme of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation as sent down for our consideration by His Excellency the Governor, and particu<lb break="no"/>larly for the reason that I have not been in a position (from my longer absence in the Upper 
     <lb/>
     Country) of making myself acquainted with the subject as I should like to have done. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     As the debate progressed, I felt more and more that I had been right in so doing, as I 
     <lb/>
     have now the benefit of the well—considered opinions and arguments of so many Honourable 
     <lb/>
     Members; and upon these able arguments l have in a great measure been guided in coming 
     <lb/>
     to the conclusion which I propose to explain. ' 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And now, Mr. President, I think it s incumbent on me to state the course I intend to take 
     <lb/>
     with regard to the subject.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I feel I have a most responsible duty to perform, not only to my constituents, but to myself 
     <lb/>
     and the country generally. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With regard to my constituents. I feel that I am placed in a rather peculiar position, and 
     <lb/>
     I regret that I have had no opportunity of communicatng with them since Confederation has 
     <lb/>
     assumed the phase it now does. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     You are aware, I presume, Mr. President, that I was selected, unsolicited on my part, to 
     <lb/>
     represent the Kootmay District in this Council. At that election Confederation was made the 
     <lb/>
     test question, and I can assure you that at that time the feeling of the majority of my 
     <lb/>
     constituents was opposed to Confederation with the Dominion of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     At a subsequent period—only a few months ago—a petition, concocted in this city, was 
     <lb/>
     dispatched to Kootenay for the purpose of obtaining signatures in favour of Confederation. 
     <lb/>
     It was, however, unfavourably received, the party circulating it was roughly handled, and the 
     <lb/>
     petition returned a blank. I mention this to show you that up to a late period my constituents 
     <lb/>
     held the same views with regard to Confederation that they did some eighteen months ago. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="51" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_051.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">51</fw>


            <p>
     Shortly after this petition had been dispatched to Kootenay, as just mentioned, I wrote 
     <lb/>
     to my constituents. requesting them to advise me fully with regard to their wants and wishes; 
     <lb/>
     and, in reply, I received a communication setting forth what they specially desired that I 
     <lb/>
     should assist in obtaining for them, but not one word on the subject of Confederation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have now before me the terms submitted by His Excellency the Governor at the opening 
     <lb/>
     of this Council, as well as the paragraph in His Excellency's Speech referring to those terms ; 
     <lb/>
     and I must say that had i resided as near my constituents as the Honourable Members for 
     <lb/>
     Victoria and Nanaimo Cities do to their I should most certainly have south an opportunity 
     <lb/>
     of meeting them and obtaining some expr .ion of their opinions on the now altered position 
     <lb/>
     of this question. But as the remoteness of my District has rendered such a course impossible, 
     <lb/>
     it is only left for me to exercise my own judgment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I wish to cast no reflections on the Hon. Members referred to, and with regard to the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     senior Member for Victoria. I consider the action he has taken on this question only forces 
     <lb/>
     stronger and stronger on my mind, and i believe on the minds of the people. that any matter 
     <lb/>
     entrusted to his care will alw be dealt with conscientiously, and with due regard to the 
     <lb/>
     feelings which he believes his constituents entertain, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Had I had an opportunity of submitting to my constituents the question of Confederation 
     <lb/>
     in the light that it now bears, I do believe that their opinions would he in unison with that of 
     <lb/>
     the country generally, in favour of Confederation on the terms now proposed, and being of that 
     <lb/>
     impression I intend to support the motion of the Hon. Attorney-General I feel assured that 
     <lb/>
     the vote which I am about to give will meet with the approval of my constituents. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I should feel some hesitation in supporting the motion of the Hon, Attorney-General, were 
     <lb/>
     it not for the assurance : ven in His Excelleiicy's Speech, that the action we may now take 
     <lb/>
     will not be final until ratified by the general verdict of the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I trust I have now stated openlv and fairly the position in which I stand, and the course 
     <lb/>
     I intend to pursue. l propose, Mr. I resident, to support Confederation with terms, and I believe 
     <lb/>
     that is the stand that will be taken by all the Hon. Members who support Confederation at all. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With regard to the terms proposed for our consideration, it will be open for me to discuss 
     <lb/>
     them more particularly in Committee ; but I may here state generally, that I Consider they are 
     <lb/>
     only what the country is fairly entitled to demand, and I shall support them probably as they 
     <lb/>
     stand; and, at the same time, shall be ready to give my vote to any address that may be 
     <lb/>
     forwarded to His Excellency, recommending the insertion of other terms that I believe may 
     <lb/>
     be advantageous to the Colony. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. President I must now thank you for the kind attention you have shewn me in listening 
     <lb/>
     to the few remarks I have felt bound to make; and I have now only to say, that as soon 
     <lb/>
     as the terms are decided upon by this Honourable Council, and placed in the hands of His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency, I, for one, shall feel perfectly confident that future negotiations will be brought to 
     <lb/>
     a successful issue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have acted conscientiously in this matter, and I am sure I shall not regret the action I 
     <lb/>
     have taken as long as I live. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Hon, Mr. HELMCKEN, Member for Victoria, in reply, said:—Mr. President, every 
     <lb/>
     word that I spoke I am willing to abide by, but I have no wish to be misrepresented. I never 
     <lb/>
     said that patriotism was dead in ibis Colony ; and I have not yet advocated that closer union 
     <lb/>
     with another country, to which allusion has been made, as the other issue to come before the 
     <lb/>
     people ; but a strong feeling does exist in favour of that other union, and it is just as well that 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion Government should know that there are very many people in this Colony who 
     <lb/>
     think that Annexation would be far more advantageous than Confederation, and who have no 
     <lb/>
     love for Canada. I maintain that the people of this Colony do not desire Confederation ; they 
     <lb/>
     desire these glittering terms; take away or reduce the terms, and the people don't want Con<lb break="no"/>federation—will not have it. I have never seen any programme proposed by the Confederation 
     <lb/>
     party, and it is certainly to the credit of the Government that it has sent one down [hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear,] which has taken even the Confederationists by surprise. I once saw a scheme brought 
     <lb/>
     before this House, which included no Railway, no Dry Dock, a small Subsidy, and the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion Tariff, objectionable as it is acknowledged now to be. It was defeated. The new scheme 
     <lb/>
     asks more, and so the country has gained by the delay. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_052.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">52</fw>
<fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            

            <p>
     But, Sir, the Hon, Members of this Council have been arguing as though these terms had 
     <lb/>
     been obtained—aerial castle building.  I say they are only propositions. I have not heard one 
     <lb/>
     Member say those terms must be had, or no Confederation, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     [HON. Mr. DeCosmos, - I stated yesterday, that if certain terms were not granted I should 
     <lb/>
     oppose Confederation.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I expect to see you an opponent of Confederation before long ; probably we shall change 
     <lb/>
     sides [Laughter] ; but until these terms, or terms that will be satisfactory to the country, are 
     <lb/>
     arranged I shall not cease my opposition to Confederation. I think it necessary to say a few 
     <lb/>
     words in explanation of my position. I do stand here a Member of the Executive Council. 
     <lb/>
     Whether I gave in my resignation or not, is not for the Hon. Member for Victoria District to 
     <lb/>
     know ; I shall not gratify his curiosity ; he should recollect, however, that party Government 
     <lb/>
     does not exist here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have opposed the Government on Confederation. I think it probable that when the 
     <lb/>
     terms come back from Canada they will bear but little resemblance to themselves; so until the 
     <lb/>
     country is satisfied I will oppose Confederation. It is sufficient that the ultimate issue now 
     <lb/>
     rests with the people themselves ; and I hope they will band themselves together to demand 
     <lb/>
     these or better terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Thus far the question is lost to me in this Council. I am: beaten by the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, by the Canadian Government, by Lord Granville's despatch, but more than all by the 
     <lb/>
     alluring terms and a Government majority,—by no one else. In this Council, the Executive 
     <lb/>
     Council has repeated itself. I intend now to offer no factious opposition to the conditions, but 
     <lb/>
     it will be my duty to point out what I consider faults, and though 1 will support the terms as 
     <lb/>
     they are, or nearly so, others must go in. I will not attempt to introduce anything which 
     <lb/>
     Canada cannot concede ; so that on the one hand, (hinada may have no excuse to refuse to 
     <lb/>
     accept the terms, and on the other, if Confederation does come it may come accompanied with 
     <lb/>
     conditions that will be beneficial to the material interests of the Colony. I now bide my time; 
     <lb/>
     when the terms as agreed to by Canada return, the people may find them changed, and not so 
     <lb/>
     attractive and enticing as they now appear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In going into the Executive Council, I did so at a loss to myself. [Hear, hear, from the 
     <lb/>
     Hons. Attorney-General and Chief Commissioner.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After all, the Supreme Power hath made of one blood all the nations of the earth, and 
     <lb/>
     hath determined beforehand the bounds of their habitations. We are but instrmnents in carry<lb break="no"/>ing out this design, whatever it may be. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In the position which I now occupy, I have sacrificed no principle, forfeited no pledge, 
     <lb/>
     maintained my own honour, have done my duty, and I hope some good, to this Colony. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Hon. ATTORNEY—GENERAL said : — Sir, in rising to reply, I have to acknowledge 
     <lb/>
     and thank the members of this House for the care and attention which they have bestowed 
     <lb/>
     upon this great and momentous question, which I have had the honour to introduce to their 
     <lb/>
     notice. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With regard to the very decent, flattering, and personal remarks towards myself, in which 
     <lb/>
     the Hon, Member for Victoria District (Mr. DeCosmos) has been in the habit of' indulging for 
     <lb/>
     several years past, the House is so familiar with that gentleman's habit towards all his political 
     <lb/>
     opponents in that respect  that it has learnt to estimate them at their proper value. I will not, 
     <lb/>
     therefore. waste the time of the House by any further comment on them. I will not con<lb break="no"/>descend to notice them [Hear, hear, hear, hear,] but proceed to subjects of mor general interest. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I maintain, Sir. that liberal Representative Institutions for this Colony are not dependent 
     <lb/>
     on the success of the scheme of Confederation; they are in no way connected with it, Confed<lb break="no"/>eration is, however, the easiest and quietest way of getting Responsible Government, should 
     <lb/>
     that be found after deliberation to be really desired ,(l so ardently by the whole community as 
     <lb/>
     some Hon. Members aver. To those who conscientiously believe in Responsible Government, 
     <lb/>
     and that the real desire of the country is for it, or as the Hon. Member for Victoria District 
     <lb/>
     says is a "unit" for it, I say fling in your voice with us; these Resolutions will most speedily 
     <lb/>
     assure the result you desire. If the people, after careful deliberation and full information on 
     <lb/>
     the subject, whether we be confederated with Canada or not, really desire Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, they will have it. Their voice will be heard on this particular question, as on all others 
     <lb/>
     connected with Confederation. But it is the hollowest pretence to assert that Confederation 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="53" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-11_Page_053.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>     <fw type="num">53</fw>
           
           

     should be stopped till the Governor can send down a scheme for Responsible Government. If 
     <lb/>
     we do not get Confederation we shall still have our own Representative Institutions. and once 
     <lb/>
     possessed of Representative Institutions under the Imperial Statute of Victoria, the Colony 
     <lb/>
     will, if it be such a unit as described, be able at once to get Responsible or Party Government. 
     <lb/>
     Now, I earnestly deprecate, on the part of the Government, the unfair allegation which one 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Member has so improperly insinuated that the Government or Government Officials con<lb break="no"/>sidered the <hi rendition="simple:italic">people</hi>  of British Columbia unfit for self-government. Why, Sir, neither the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor nor any member of the Government, or any other official, ever said or thought that the 
     <lb/>
     people of this Colony were individually or collectively unfit for Responsible Government. The 
     <lb/>
     utmost that has ever been said on this side of the House has been that, under the present <hi rendition="simple:italic">cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances of the Colony</hi>, it would be unwise, excessively costly—nay impracticable. As I 
     <lb/>
     have said before, and again repeat, the Governor has no power of himself to alter the Consti<lb break="no"/>tution. He can only refer it where it has already gone, to the decision of the Queen in 
     <lb/>
     Council, which we ought in common justice to await before bringing forward any Resolution 
     <lb/>
     for Responsible Government. Now, how would the country, if a unit on this point, get 
     <lb/>
     Responsible Government after Confederation? After Confederation the people can have 
     <lb/>
     Responsible Government, if they desire it, under clause 92 of the "British North America 
     <lb/>
     Act, 1867," by which power is given for the Provinces to change their own Constitution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Hon. Member for Victoria City (Dr. Helmcken) has alluded to the Hon. Member for 
     <lb/>
     Victoria District having prepared a scheme for Confederation, now on the Journals of this 
     <lb/>
     House, which did not contain any reference to Responsible Government, or the Overland 
     <lb/>
     Railway, possibly in view of this very section 92 of the Organic Act. The Hon. Member for 
     <lb/>
     Victoria District may have considered that Confederation would, as a natural consequence 
     <lb/>
     after Union, bring Responsible Government. If so, I trust he will vote with us now [Hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear, hear], and leave a matter of such importance to be settled, not by a House constituted 
     <lb/>
     as this is, but by a House containing a majority of Representative Members elected by the 
     <lb/>
     country, after the question of party Government has been specially submitted to the polls. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I ask the House to deal with this subject on its merits, apart from all side issues, such as 
     <lb/>
     the special form of the Government which is to subsist at the time of Union, which is really 
     <lb/>
     not now before us. I ask them to place a generous trust in Canada. I acknowledge the 
     <lb/>
     encouraging manner in which the Council has dealt with this question, and sincerely trust that 
     <lb/>
     all parties and sections in the House, setting aside all prejudices and sectional issues, will 
     <lb/>
     unite cordially, frankly, and unanimously in giving a generous support to the Government, 
     <lb/>
     and thus strengthen their hands for the country's good in all future negotiations. [Hear, hear, 
     <lb/>
     heal.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Hon. Mr. Drake, junior Member for Victoria. asked permission to withdraw his 
     <lb/>
     amendment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Leave having been granted, the amendment was withdrawn. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The motion of the Hon. Attorney-General to go into Committee was then put, and carried 
     <lb/>
     unanimously. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The House then went into Committee of the Whole on the Confederation Resolutions, and 
     <lb/>
     immediately rose, reported progress, and asked leave to sit again. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Leave was granted to sit again on Monday, at one o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<!-- GL, 2017-03-15, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


            <!--<p>
                                                          -\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\- <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
                                               IN COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
                                                                           -\-\-\-\-\-\-\- <lb/>                                               MONDAY, 14th MARCH, 1870. 
     <lb/>                                                                   -\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\- <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The House having resolved itself into Committee of the Whole on the Confederation 
     <lb/>
     Resolutions, as arranged by His Excellency the Governor of British Columbia, the Hon. Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Ball in the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the motion of the Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL, the Chairman read the Resolutions 
     <lb/>
     through. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>