<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgBCLC_1870-03-17"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgBCLC">British Columbia Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1870-03-17">17 March 1870</date>, Province of BC, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          
          <editor>W.S. Sebright Green</editor>
         
         
               <title>Legislative Council, Debate on the Subject of Confederation with Canada</title>.
                    

          <date when="1912"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Victoria, B.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>William H. Cullin</publisher>.
                    
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="82" to="95"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_082.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_083.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_084.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_085.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_086.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_087.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_088.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_089.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_090.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_091.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_092.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_093.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_094.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_095.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-24">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_082">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_082.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_083">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_083.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_084">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_084.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_085">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_085.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_086">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_086.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_087">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_087.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_088">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_088.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_089">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_089.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_090">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_090.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_091">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_091.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_092">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_092.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_093">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_093.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_094">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_094.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_095">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_095.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="82" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_082.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">82</fw> <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            

<!-- GL, 2017-03-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
<!--<p>
     benefit to result even from the Railway. This is one of the points on which the people may be 
     <lb/>
     deceived. If they imagine that with Confederation will come immediate prosperity. I shall be 
     <lb/>
     glad if anyone will point out how it is to come. If it were made inland it might be more 
     <lb/>
     beneficial to agricultural interests in a short space of time, than if commenced on the sea coast. 
     <lb/>
     Public works in this Colony should help to develop the resources, and one thing should he made 
     <lb/>
     to work with another, so as to be mutually beneficial; each should be for the benefit of the 
     <lb/>
     whole, and the whole for the benefit of each. Suppose a Railway were commenced tomorrow 
     <lb/>
     at Fraser River, how much benefit would it be? It might be some, but if these public works 
     <lb/>
     were made subservient to the interests of settling up the Colony, they would be more likely to 
     <lb/>
     be beneficial. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. CARRALL—Sir, I have only a few words to say, and have no intention of detain<lb break="no"/>ing the House at this late hour, but I must be allowed to express the satisfaction which I 
     <lb/>feel in observing a change in the sentiments of the Hon. Member for Victoria City (Mr. 
     <lb/>Helmcken), a change which does honour to his head and heart. He has begun to show some 
     <lb/>faith in the Canadian Government at last. He may be called the pattern of the distrustful 
     <lb/>party, and I augur favourably from his conversion. With regard to the local advantages of a 
     <lb/>Railway, I would point to the construction of the Intercolonial Railway Property in Halifax 
     <lb/>has gone up 40 per cent. since it was built. I fully admit the desirability and necessity of a 
     <lb/>Railway, but I cannot admit that Union cannot exist without it; look at the Union which 
     <lb/>existed for so many years between California and the Eastern States of America without a 
     <lb/>Railway. I believe that Canada, for Imperial reasons, intends to undertake the construction 
     <lb/>of this Railway. As for the length of time allowed for the commencement, I think it could 
     <lb/>not be well less than three years. I believe with the Hon. Chief Commissioner, that the work 
     <lb/>will be undertaken by a private company, under guarantee. If so, it would be hampering the 
     <lb/>Government of the Dominion to make them commence earlier. It might compel them to close 
     <lb/>with parties not in all respects eligible. It would put them in a false position. If the Colony 
     <lb/>had charge of her own Crown lands, there should be a power given to Canada to promise 
     <lb/>Crown lands in connection with the construction of the Railway. I regret that this has not 
     <lb/>been put in the Resolutions, but no doubt the omission can be remedied hereafter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     On the motion of Hon. Mr. Drake, the Committee rose, reported the passing of Clauses 5, 
     <lb/>
     6, and 7, and obtained leave to sit again at one o'clock the 17th instant. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Report adopted, and Clauses 5, G, and 7, passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     THURSDAY, 17TH MARCH, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DeCOSMOS</persName>—Mr. Chairman, judging from the statements
                  made by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, this Railway is not likely to be completed
                  in so short a period as I had hoped. The <lb/> indefinite nature of the clause is
                  unsatisfactory. It contemplates nothing more than the <lb/> expenditure of
                  $1,000,000 per annum, which would no doubt be a great boon, and would <lb/>
                  stimulate various branches of industry but that is almost all that can be said of
                  it. The way <lb/> that it has been put to the Colony heretofore, was that the
                  Canadian Government would <lb/> construct the road. It now turns out, from the
                  statements of the Hon. Chief Commissioner of <lb/> Lands and Works, that in all
                  probability the Canadian Government will get some private com<lb break="no"/>pany
                  to carry out the work; and he adds " that we may" get a guarantee with grants of
                  land <lb/> in aid of, the undertaking. Now, Sir, from the first I have always been
                  careful not to bring <lb/> forward the question of the Railway in connection with
                  Confederation. The London Conference <lb/> favoured it only when the financial
                  position of the Dominion admitted it. It must be quite a <lb/> long time before
                  connection by rail with the Canadian Railway system can take place. I never <lb/>
                  believed the Canadian Government would contract a debt for this purpose at the
                  present. <lb/> They are already, in my opinion, too deeply in debt, and are taxed
                  too high, to allow them to <lb/> do so. According to my calculation, it will cost
                  $150,000,000 to complete the Railway from <lb/> this Colony to Montreal. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK</persName>—You mean to the head of the water
                  communication of Lake <lb/> Superior? <lb/>
               </p>
            <pb n="83" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_083.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">83</fw>
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—NO! that gets frozen up and cannot be
                  utilized for several months <lb/> in the year. It must go to Montreal, on the
                  north side of Lakes Superior and Huron. It will <lb/> cost $100,000,000 to
                  construct it to Lake Superior from Victoria. Now a four per cent. guar<lb
                     break="no"/>antee on $100,000,000 will require Canada to impose additional
                  taxation of $4,000,000 a year. <lb/> Then you must remember that the wear and tear
                  of the Railway would not be met by the <lb/> returns. Besides that, there are
                  running expenses to be provided for. The United States <lb/> Trans-continental
                  Railway pays from the way stations in the populous districts through which <lb/>
                  it passes; we should have none, except a few people at the Red River and in
                  British Columbia. <lb/> A four per cent. guarantee would be adding one-third to
                  the annual taxation of the Dominion. <lb/> Then for the portion of Railway they
                  will have to make from the west end of Lake Superior <lb/> to Montreal, there
                  would be required $50,000,000 more at four per cent. To meet these sums, <lb/>
                  therefore, there would have to be raised an annual sum of $6,000,000 by Canada; in
                  other <lb/> words they would have to add nearly fifty per cent. to the present
                  taxation of Canada. Do you <lb/> think, Sir, they will ever do this, or that any
                  Finance Minister would dare attempt it in the <lb/> present state of Canadian
                  finances? I call attention to this view of the subject in order to <lb/> prevent
                  false impressions getting abroad, and the creation of false hopes, which will only
                  lead <lb/> to disappointment. With all due deference to his professional
                  knowledge, I deny the correctness <lb/> of the estimate of the Chief Commissioner
                  that this Railway will cost only two'thirds of the <lb/> United States
                  Trans-continental line. This is a more difficult line in my opinion, not an easier
                  <lb/> one, than the line over the Sierra Nevada. Perhaps part of the year we might
                  get communi<lb break="no"/>cation, partly by steamboat and partly by railway, but
                  for several months in the winter the <lb/> water portion of the route would be
                  closed up. In the temper of this House and the temper <lb/> of the Government, I
                  do not expect "this Resolution of mine to go up to the Government. Now, <lb/> I
                  want to utilize our money, and to utilize our time. I estimate that a Railway from
                  Fraser <lb/> River to Kamloops would cost $50,000 a mile. According to the plan of
                  the Chief Commissioner, <lb/> with the expenditure of only $1,000,000 a year, at
                  the end of five years, it we started at Burrard <lb/> Inlet, we should get to Yale
                  only, for which the water communication at present existing would <lb/> suffice,
                  and consequently that time would be lost Possibly it might be opened to the Rocky
                  <lb/> Mountains in ten years, if begun at New Westminster as this scheme proposes
                  It is our duty <lb/> to open the interior country—Osoyoos, Okanagan, Kanlloops,
                  Similkameen, and other districts. <lb/> Bring the interior into communication with
                  the seaboard, that would settle up the best portion <lb/> of the interior, provide
                  an outlet for produce, and keep the money that is new sent abroad <lb/> within our
                  own borders. The Government plan will injure, it not delay, the development of the
                  <lb/> country. I have no hope that my recommendation will pass, but still I have
                  the satisfaction <lb/> of feeling that I have done my duty. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. MR. HOLBROOK</persName>—Sir, I rise to support the recommendation
                  of the Hon. Member for <lb/> Victoria District (Mr. DeCosmos). I quite agree with
                  that Hon. gentleman that a Railway <lb/> starting from the head of steamboat
                  navigation, would he more useful than any other, If we <lb/> have a Company
                  spending $1,000,000 a year in building a Railway which will open up the <lb/>
                  farming districts, we shall be able to raise cereals and compete with our American
                  neighbours, <lb/> and by commencing at the head of navigation we shall'reap the
                  advantage in our lifetime. It <lb/> will develope the Mainland. Agricultural land
                  would be turned into profitable use, and the <lb/> mining section from Big Bend to
                  Kootenay. which contains. I believe, most valuable mines of <lb/> gold and silver
                  will be opened up. If the recommendation of the Hon. Member is adopted, we <lb/>
                  shall find almost immediate benefit From the opening up of the inland trade. It
                  will bring us <lb/> population, and will build up this City and New Westminster,
                  and other towns through the <lb/> Colony. I do hope it will receive the support of
                  the Executive Council. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon MR. RING</persName>—Sir, I thought we were discussing the necessity
                  of a Railway, but I did not <lb/> come prepared to discuss engineering questions
                  as to route; it is wasting words to discuss the <lb/> topography. That must be
                  decided by competent surveyors. Our business, as it appears to me, <lb/> is to
                  insist upon having a through Railway. And it is highly desirable that the
                  construction <lb/> should be commenced simultaneously at both ends as well as the
                  survey. I shall thoroughly and <lb/> cordially support the Government upon this
                  clause. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—Sir. I thought I had made the
                  Government views on this <lb/> clause sufficiently clear yesterday, in supporting
                  the Hon. the Attorney-General's motion; if not, <lb/> my words could not have
                  thoroughly expressed my meaning. The Government have not inserted <lb/> the
                  construction of a Railway into these Resolutions on the principle of local
                  advantages. The <lb/>
                  <pb n="84" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_084.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">84</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> Hon. Member for Victoria District
                  (Mr. DeCosmos) seems to argue that we inserted it in order <lb/> to secure the
                  advantages which would accrue to special localities from way traffic. But I can
                  <lb/> assure the House that the Executive Council entertained no such idea in
                  adjusting the details <lb/> of this great scheme; they have endeavoured to secure
                  the utmost advantages to the whole <lb/> Colony. You will observe, Sir, that the
                  clause is most general in its. terms, and it was <lb/> purposely made so. It does
                  not attempt to define the line the road should take; it may have n <lb/> terminus,
                  as I distinctly stated before, at any place on the coast most convenient—at
                  Bentinck <lb/> Arm, Bute Inlet, or Burrard Inlet, or even by crossing the fiords
                  between Vancouver Island and <lb/> the Mainland, it may come to Victoria or
                  Esquimalt. These details must be left to the parties <lb/> constructing the line.
                  The Executive Council have avoided all through all sectional and local <lb/>
                  considerations. I stated yesterday, and I repeat it again. that I hoped the
                  Railway would <lb/> follow down the valley of the Fraser River to the seaboard;
                  but the Government have purposely <lb/> avoided any definition of any particular
                  line, and have made it as general as possible I also <lb/> said that I did not
                  think that the Dominion Government would make the line; and I said so <lb/>
                  because I am well aware that this is not the way in which great works of this
                  character are <lb/> generally undertaken in these times. I believe that a private
                  company, with the assistance of <lb/> the Dominion Government, and I hope the
                  Imperial Government also, will construct the line. <lb/> But this is merely
                  surmise. I know no more on my own actual knowledge than other Members <lb/> round
                  this board But I come to this conclusion because I know that it is not considered
                  <lb/> feasible for Governments to undertake such works It has been found to be a
                  great mistake. <lb/> Then why discuss the suggestions of the Hon. Member for
                  constructing a Railway from Yale <lb/> to Kamloops, or try to fix details which
                  the spirit of the whole Resolution avoids, when we <lb/> don't even say the line
                  shall pass Yale or Kamloops at all? It is a vast undertaking, and if <lb/>
                  undertaken at all, it will not be with a view to profit, but with a view to the
                  future, and as <lb/> part of' the great responsibility of the Canadian Government
                  in contracting alliance with this <lb/> country. The strenuous desire of the
                  Canadian Government is to make such a line. I think <lb/> they are able to do it,
                  and we know for certain that they will do it if they can. I do not agree <lb/>
                  with the Hon. Member for Victoria City (Dr. Helmcken), that Confederation means a
                  Railway; <lb/> the Government do not say that there shall he no Confederation
                  without a Railway. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName>—No; that is my opinion, and I do not put it
                  forward as the opinion <lb/> of the Government. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—I am glad to have that set right. The
                  Government <lb/> believe that the Railway will be made, but they do not make it a
                     <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi>; but if, on a <lb/> calm view
                  of the whole subject in negotiating with Canada, it is found impracticable for
                  Canada <lb/> to commence to make the Railway at once, then I see alternative
                  terms, which will not only <lb/> suit Canada but the people of this Colony, who,
                  you must remember, will have to pass upon <lb/> them when they come back from
                  Canada. It has been stated the public mind is impressed with <lb/> the idea that
                  the insertion of so paltry a sum as $1,000,000 will lend to the postponement of
                  <lb/> the completion of the Railway for fifty years I can assure them it is a
                  fallacy Why, Sir, as <lb/> well put by the Hon. Member for New Westminster
                  yesterday. common sense shows that it <lb/> would be against the interest of the
                  part . making,r the line to prolong the work over a number <lb/> of years. It can
                  only he carried on quic to secure any real profit. I again repeat what the <lb/>
                  Government Members stated yesterday so distinctly, that the one million a year is
                  not nearly <lb/> the sum which will have to be spent; the amount stated is only
                  intended to serve as a guarantee <lb/> or an earnest that the work will be done.
                  If we had said make it in so many years time, they <lb/> could not have acceded to
                  it. Certainly in three years'   time the Dominion Government will he in <lb/> a
                  position to determine the line. The suggestion oi the Hon. Member is. in my
                  opinion, wholly <lb/> inapplicable   to this scheme. If admitted it would entirely
                  remodel the Government clause, which <lb/> is general.   The suggestion is. that
                  the first section should be made at some place on Fraser <lb/> River , I said
                  before, we cannot tell whether the Railway will come down the valley of the <lb/>
                  Fraser River at all. Those who spend the money have a right to choose their line.
                  As far as <lb/> my own opinion goes, I should say that the Canadian Government
                  will determine the basis of <lb/> the scheme on engineering considerations of the
                  port best suited for pouring in supplies, and for <lb/> the cheapest construction
                  of the road. Do not let us hamper so great a scheme by such minute <lb/> details;
                  let us leave it for those who have to construct the line to select their own
                  route. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—The Hon. the Chief Commissioner has left very
                  little for me to say <lb/> upon this clause, but there is one point to which I
                  would direct attention, The Hon. Member <lb/>
                  <pb n="85" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_085.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">85</fw> for Victoria District has not sufficiently considered, it
                  seems to me, how the material for the <lb/> construction of the Railway would he
                  most easily moved to the line from the sea coast. If <lb/> the road is to be
                  commenced at Yale, all the vast material and rolling stock would have to be <lb/>
                  shipped from the port in small steamers up the Fraser River, to a point at which
                  the line, <lb/> according to the Hon. Member's scheme, would start. The extra
                  expense would be ruinous; <lb/> and besides, it must be remembered that during a
                  considerable portion of the year the naviga<lb break="no"/>tion of the river is
                  closed to steamers; and not only is this the case, but these boats cannot <lb/>
                  take up the engines and cars, but can only carry on the ordinary traffic when the
                  population <lb/> increases. No; the real, the only proper, course will be to
                  commence to lay the track from the <lb/> ships to where the material will have to
                  be laid. That alone puts out of the question the <lb/> commencement of any initial
                  section at Yale, or anywhere else than on the seaboard. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName>—Mr. Chairman, I am glad to hear from Hon.
                  Members that this clause <lb/> is the pivot of the whole scheme. I hope it will
                  now be well understood that the Railway is <lb/>
                  <hi rendition="simple:italic">the</hi> condition in Hon. Members' minds upon which
                  Confederation or no Confederation hangs. <lb/> I hope that this will be remembered
                  hereafter. This Railway is a gigantic undertaking. I <lb/> look upon it as merely
                  impracticable. I believe this Railway will cost more than the whole <lb/> debt of
                  Canada, ["Hear, hear," from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hons. DeCosmos</persName> and <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Robson</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName></supplied> The Government tells <lb/>
                  us that this Railway is to be a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi>.
                  ["No"—<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. Helmcken</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName></supplied> Why, my colleague, <lb/> the Hon. Member for Victoria, who is a
                  Privy Councillor, says no. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName>—The Government does not say so; I say no.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. Mr. DRAKE</persName>—Well, certain Hon. Members say so. Now, this
                  is what will happen: <lb/> Canada will agree to a Railway to get Confederation,
                  and Confederation takes place, Canadian <lb/> officials rule here, and Canadian
                  laws prevail. Three years elapse, and Canada may find it <lb/> inconvenient or
                  impossible to carry out the Railway. I say that we require a guarantee for <lb/>
                  the making of the Railway. On Confederation how can we enforce this condition?
                  This <lb/> difficulty underlies the whole scheme. I ask how we are to get out of
                  it. guard against it, or <lb/> surmount it? Leave the Confederation? That means
                  rebellion, which is not to be thought of <lb/> by any law-loving persons. We can't
                  float ourselves out when once in; then we are bound hand <lb/> and foot from now
                  to eternity. There should be a penalty of $50,000 for every year in which <lb/>
                  Canada fails to expend the one million. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY—GENERAL</persName>—How do you propose to secure the
                  $50,000? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. Mr. DRAKE</persName>—By Imperial guarantee. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ANON1">An Hon. MEMBER</persName>—How would the guarantee of the President of
                  the United States do? <lb/> [Laughter.]   <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. Mr. DRAKE</persName>— I shall be quite satisfied if the President of
                  the United States indorses <lb/> the bill. [Laughter.] I consider the Railway the
                  primary and essential condition of Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation, and I think that
                  Canada is too poor to guarantee such a work as this. She had to go to <lb/> the
                  Imperial Government to guarantee the payment of the £300,000 to buy out Canadian
                  interests <lb/> in the Red River Settlements, and I maintain that we are on the
                  right course to ask for an <lb/> Imperial guarantee now. When we get into
                  Confederation we cannot help ourselves. If Canada <lb/> is unable or unwilling to
                  pay the $1,000,000 a year, as soon as it appears necessary to her to <lb/> throw
                  over the conditions, over they will be thrown. One Hon. Member tells us that
                  Canadian <lb/> statesmen are " men of unbounded ambition." Now, men of unbounded
                  ambition will not scruple <lb/> at anything to gain their ends; that is all they
                  look to. Until a guarantee is obtained, I shall <lb/> oppose this Resolution. I
                  don't care whether it is the guarantee of the President of the United <lb/> States
                  or any other that will do. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—I have listened with profound astonishment to
                  the remarks of the <lb/> Hon. Member who has just sat down, upon Canada and
                  Canadian statesmen. I shall not <lb/> coudescend to reply to the asperasions.
                  Canada can support herself against all this kind of <lb/> thing. She is great
                  enough to do so. Such attacks can only come from those who know <lb/> nothing
                  about those whom they malign, I am a Canadian, and am proud of being one; but in
                  <lb/> this matter of making terms of union, I shall be as exacting as any
                  reasonable Member of this <lb/> Council can be. I would have all the conditions
                  well understood, and would have them put in <lb/> black and white, but I would ask
                  no endorsement from any other source. When this agree<lb break="no"/>ment is
                  completed between British Columbia and Canada, we shall have the best possible of
                  <lb/> guarantees. We shall have the guarantee of the imperial Government, and of
                  Her Majesty <lb/> the Queen, from first to last. We shall have the endorsement of
                  the Queen's Proclamation, <lb/>
                  <pb n="86" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_086.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">86</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> which lies at the root of these
                  conditions. Can we have or desire better security? ["Hear, <lb/> hear," from <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Mr.
                  Trutch</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName></supplied> Hon. Members say we cannot get out, and that Canada may <lb/> repudiate.
                  I say, nothing of the kind. Canada would never be allowed by the Imperial <lb/>
                  Government to coerce this Colony to remain in Confederation for the fulfilment of
                  one side <lb/> of a contract of partnership, the terms of which Canada herself has
                  trodden under foot. To <lb/> entertain such a supposition is, if I may be allowed
                  the expression, an outrage on common <lb/> sense too absurd to be for a moment
                  seriously entertained. Would the Imperial Government <lb/> stand by and let Canada
                  send a force of soldiers to compel British Columbia to remain in Con<lb break="no"
                  />federation under such circumstances? The Canadian Government never broke faith
                  yet, and <lb/> the Imperial Government never broke faith yet, and both are pledged
                  to the fulfilment of this <lb/> condition. Canada has hitherto gone in advance of
                  her word. The distrustful views of the <lb/> Hon. junior Member for Victoria (Mr.
                  Drake) are so manifestly unjust that, as it is impossible <lb/> that they can
                  arise from ignorance, I may be pardoned for attributing them to wilfulness, to
                  <lb/> a rabid sense of opposition, and a chronic feeling of distrust. To ask the
                  President of the <lb/> United States to endorse a scheme which emanates from the
                  Imperial Government, I look <lb/> upon as a monstrous ill-timed joke, against
                  which reason and argument are powerless. I <lb/> cannot—we cannot discuss it. Now,
                  to go to the ways and means. Why, Sir, it is well <lb/> known that Canada is rich.
                  Does the Hon. Member know that Ontario and Quebec have <lb/> $4,000,000 lying idle
                  at this moment, carrying low interest. There is plenty of capital in <lb/> Canada
                  at this moment to build the Pacific Railway. The reason why Canada uses the <lb/>
                  Imperial guarantee for the £300.000 is this: She can borrow cheaper through the
                  Imperial <lb/> Government, with their guarantee, than without it. Canada
                  frequently borrows money for <lb/> public works. It pays her to do so. It is
                  simply a beneficial financial operation, <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName>—I rise for the purpose of explaining that I
                  make no reflections upon <lb/> Canadian statesmen, but I treat this solely as a
                  matter of business; and as in other ordinary <lb/> business, I prefer having an
                  endorsed note to a simple obligation. In the 145th section of the <lb/> British
                  North America Act, an Imperial guarantee for a loan of three millions sterling for
                  a <lb/> Railway is specified. I think we are justified in making a similar
                  request. Mine is a business <lb/> condition. I am willing to trust Canada, but I
                  say we are entitled to ask for an endorser. <lb/> The Hon. Member's remarks have
                  not disturbed my position.  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName>—I am obliged, Sir, in the few remarks that I
                  intend to offer, to treat <lb/> of all the amendments and suggestions together. To
                  my mind, this condition which requires <lb/> the construction of the Overland
                  Railway is one of the most important of all the terms. <lb/> A great deal has been
                  said about the incorruptibility of Canadian statesmen. No doubt <lb/> Canadian
                  statesmen are very like all others. Canada acts through her Ministers. Those now
                  <lb/> in power are, so far as we know, favourable to this scheme. But, without
                  imputing motives, it <lb/> must be admitted that it is very possible that a
                  Canadian Ministry, some three or four years <lb/> hence, possibly of the
                  anti-Confederate party, or cold upon the subject of Confederation, when <lb/>
                  pressed by circumstances, may be disinclined to carry out the terms, and with
                  perfect consist<lb break="no"/>ency of political conduct, desire to obtain relief
                  from carrying them out, and their first effort <lb/> would be to get a vote of the
                  Provincial Legislature to relieve them from the burthen. In <lb/> the event of
                  Confederation, I should consider this country a Colony of Canada. [<persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon Mr. <lb/>
                  DeCosmos</persName>—"No, an integral part of it."] <supplied><persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName></supplied> I say a Canadian Colony, because, as I
                  believe, <lb/> neither Responsible Govermnent nor full representative institutions
                  are to be granted under <lb/> Confederation; at all events, they are not included
                  in these terms. And under such a consti<lb break="no"/>tution as we have now, the
                  Canadian Government could easily get a vote of this Legislature <lb/> to cancel
                  the terms. I repudiate chronic opposition, but I consider it to be my duty to
                  oppose <lb/> the course that is being taken by some Hon. Members here. I believe
                  there are some Hon. <lb/> Members of this House who desire Confederation on any,
                  or without any, terms. ["Name, <lb/> name," from <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hons. Carrall</persName> and <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Robson</persName>; " No,
                  no," from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DeCosmos</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName></supplied> The very gentlemen <lb/> who speak, if I may judge from
                  their votes. ["No, no."] If I was in favour of Confederation <lb/> at all; if I
                  did not think that reaction would follow; if I thought that Lord Granville's
                  argument <lb/> was sound. I should say, "Let us be confederated at once." This
                  brings me to a difference of <lb/> opinion that exists. Some of us consider the
                  Railway a necessary point in the terms. Many <lb/> of us. including Lord
                  Granville, consider it essential, The Hon. Chief Commissioner says it <lb/> is not
                  essential. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—I never said the Railway was not
                  essential. <lb/>
               </p>


            <pb n="87" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_087.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">87</fw>
            

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName>—I understood the Hon. Member to say that
                  Government did not consider <lb/> it essential. I fear that it is delusive to hope
                  that the Imperial Government would give a <lb/> guarantee for this Railway. They
                  could only do so on military grounds; but I am convinced <lb/> they would never
                  guarantee three thousand miles of an exposed line of Railway within a few <lb/>
                  miles of the territorial boundary, a thing which courts assault and would be so
                  perilous to <lb/> maintain, seeing that it could he cut in two in a hundred places
                  by hostile forces from <lb/> the United States. It requires little reflection to
                  see that Colonial undertakings are seldom <lb/> guaranteed now. Canada's interest
                  in the Railway, on the other hand. is purely commercial. <lb/> For such a Railway
                  to pay, it must pass through populous districts—places like Omaha and <lb/> the
                  United States towns. It is monstrous to suppose that England would supply the
                  capital <lb/> for such a scheme. No capitalists in the world would advance their
                  money for such an under<lb break="no"/>taking. The matter has been talked
                  threadbare in the public prints. It is out of the question <lb/> to suppose that
                  there would be any material trade in bulky goods this way. [Hear, hear, <lb/>
                  hear, hear] Canada, finding the thing difficult, will refuse the terms. ["No, no,"
                  from <lb/> <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Dr. Carrall</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName></supplied> I say the money will not be spent. I back my knowledge
                  of: the world and <lb/> experience of men and things against the "No, no " of the
                  Hon. Member, and I believe the <lb/> result will be that the Canadian Government
                  will refuse this item; and in refusing will say, <lb/> "We do the best we can; it
                  is our interest to do the thing. but it is impossible to get the <lb/> guarantee
                  through Parliament." I believe the Canadian statesmen who have the conduct of
                  <lb/> this matter will sav to our Delegates, or to His Excellency, "Don't you
                  think you can do <lb/> without this Railway ? You must take our desire to do it
                  for the deed itself. By and bye, <lb/> perhaps, it can be accomplished, and by no
                  means so effectually as by becoming a part of our <lb/> Dominion." And so a quiet
                  go-by will be given to the Railway, and the terms will come back <lb/> again shorn
                  of this item. If, as the Hon. Chief Commissioner says, these terms are to come
                  <lb/> before the people—mind I say the people alone—I believe there is a feeling
                  that Confederation <lb/> is a movement which promises something, and this feeling
                  will lead to these terms being <lb/> passed. So weak are commercial and
                  agricultural interests in this Colony at the present time, <lb/> so small is the
                  population, and the mass of the people are doing so badly and are so dissatisfied
                  <lb/> thnlt, in my opinion, they will vote for anything that will give change and
                  a chance of bettering <lb/> themselves. I intend, Sir, to move an amendment, with
                  the view of making this Railway a <lb/> test question :—"That without a
                  substantial guarantee for an Overland Railway, Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion
                  should be rejected by the Delegates from this Colony." It is obvious that this
                  motion <lb/> will be defeated, but I am desirous to test the opinions of the
                  representative members of this <lb/> Council on so literal a point as this, The
                  Hon. Chief Commissioner says that these terms <lb/> are to be decided, eventually.
                  by the representative members alone—of course, without the <lb/> official vote.
                  And here I may ask, are the official members, in the event of its ultimate <lb/>
                  discussion, to retire from the Council, and leave the question to the
                  representative members <lb/> alone? If we are fit for representative institutions.
                  why not give them to us now? Having <lb/> promised the Colony terms, I think the
                  Executive are bound to present terms which are good, <lb/> in the sense of being
                  productive of permanent good and quiet enjoyment. I cannot forbear to <lb/> say
                  that in place of terms simply providing for pecuniary benefit, I should have
                  preferred to <lb/> have seen inserted cmislitutional powers, and powers of
                  self-government. [" Hear, hear," from <lb/> <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hons. DeCosmos</persName>, <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Robson</persName>, and
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Humphreys</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName></supplied> I should have desired 'to embody these in the <lb/> conditions; and,
                  in particular, I should hav desired to retain full power over the Tariff. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName>—The Tariff is an open question. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName>—Give us reasonable powers of self-government,
                  and I will accept Con<lb break="no"/>federation to-morrow. If we cannot settle our
                  local matters. there will be trouble. If the <lb/> Tariff is left an open
                  question. it is at least one step in the right direction. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName>—It is an open question on agricultural
                  matters. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. Mr. CARRALL</persName>—I shall not attempt to answer the discursive
                  remarks of the Hon. <lb/> Mr. Wood. It would require an <hi
                     rendition="simple:italic">ignis fatuus</hi> to do so. for he is here, there,
                  and everywhere <lb/> in no time; but I cannot suffer some of his remarks to pass
                  unnoticed l have sat in this <lb/> Council for two sessions, and have endeavoured
                  to conduct myself with propriety; but I find <lb/> certain Hon. gentlemen in this
                  Council who, by inuendo and implication, directly and indirectly, <lb/> have
                  endeavoured to cast slurs upon Canada, and to slander and belittle the statesmen
                  of <lb/> that country, which I am proud to call my own. I have, hitherto.
                  refrained from answering, <lb/> because I thought my country occupied too high a
                  place in the roll of England's Colonies to <lb/>
                  <pb n="88" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_088.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">88</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> be affected by such conduct. The
                  position of Canada is so great, beyond cavil and dispute, as <lb/> not to, require
                  any defender in this Council. Such remarks only recoil upon those who make <lb/>
                  them. The versatility of spleen displayed by the Hon. gentleman who has just sat
                  down, only <lb/> shows the bitterness of the mind that conceived the remarks. The
                  question now before us is <lb/> as to Clause 8, and upon the discussion of this
                  clause another question has arisen, or rather <lb/> has been dragged in, namely,
                  that of the ability of Canada to fulfil the condition of this <lb/> particular
                  clause, and it is said that this is to be made a test question. With regard to the
                  <lb/> idea of any future Canadian Ministry repudiating this condition, I wish, Mr.
                  Chairman, to <lb/> refer you to English history, and to ask whether you have ever
                  known an instance of an <lb/> incoming Ministry. whether Whig, Radical, or Tory,
                  repudiating the plighted troth of their <lb/> predecessors in office? Such a thing
                  is never done to my knowledge, and so far as my <lb/> experience of history goes,
                  never has been done. [" Hear, hear," from <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. Attorney-General</persName>.] <lb/> <supplied><persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. Mr. CARRALL</persName></supplied> I have yet
                  to learn an instance where a loan guaranteed, or anything else undertaken by any
                  <lb/> Government, has been repudiated by an incoming Ministry. We might just as
                  well suppose <lb/> that the guarantee for the loan for the Inter-colonial Railway
                  might be withdrawn by Gladstone, <lb/> because it was given by the late Ministry,
                  as that any future party in Canada might entertain <lb/> the idea of going back
                  from the promises of the present Government. History forbids such an <lb/> idea.
                  The Hon. and learned Member for Victoria (Mr. Drake) says he wants a guarantee.
                  <lb/> Well, let him want it. I am perfectly willing that he should want it. For my
                  part, I look <lb/> upon the Queen's Proclamation as the guarantee which will make
                  the whole thing inviolable. <lb/> I point to the fact, that every compact entered
                  into with the Maritime Provinces is being <lb/> fulfiled. Can anyone point to any
                  act of repudiation? No, Sir, Canada has gone beyond her <lb/> promises. I
                  repudiate, on behalf of myself and others, the assertion that any member of the
                  <lb/> confederate party has stated that he would accept Confederation without
                  conditions. I never <lb/> heard the Hon. Member for Victoria District, or the Hon.
                  Member for New Westminster, who <lb/> have taken a prominent part in this great
                  question, make any such statement. I have the <lb/> honour of being one of the
                  Executive Council who framed these Resolutions, and I believe <lb/> the terms will
                  be acceptable to a large majority of the people. Those who say that there can
                  <lb/> be no Union without a Railway, speak a fallacy. Railways follow. Look at San
                  Francisco <lb/> and the Eastern States of America. Look at Scotland and England. I
                  am well aware that <lb/> British Columbia wants a Railway, and I know that Canada
                  wants it. I am sanguine enough <lb/> to believe that it will be made. I am assured
                  that the money is ready, if the desired guarantees <lb/> can be obtained. The Hon.
                  Mr. Wood. in his discursive remarks, flew around like a humming<lb break="no"
                  />bird buzzing round a rose, and amongst other things touched on the assailability
                  of the Railroad. <lb/> I say that the American people have Railways of their own,
                  and we do not intend to have from <lb/> henceforth daily warfare. With regard to
                  the course of the Railway, the Hon. Chief Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner has told
                  you that the advantages of the line are greater than those of the existing Pacific
                  <lb/> line. It is well known that the American Pacific Railway, after passing
                  Omaha, passes through <lb/> a wild and most desolate country, through miles of
                  wilds and sage-brush. [" No, no." from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. <lb/> DeCosmos</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. Mr. CARRALL</persName></supplied> The North-West
                  Territory is more fertile than any portion of the route of the <lb/> American
                  Pacific Railway. The Hon. Mr. Wood says he will make this a test question. I say
                  <lb/> the whole terms are a test question, and no one part of them more than
                  another. The Canadian <lb/> Government are to be asked what they will do, and the
                  final test will be for the decision of <lb/> British subjects of this Colony. No
                  one thing is a test more than another. The people have the <lb/> sole right to say
                  whether they are willing to take the terms as finally offered, or not. I have
                  <lb/> already spoken twice with regard to Representative Institutions, which the
                  Hon. Mr. Wood <lb/> regrets are not made a condition. Either l must fail to put my
                  ideas clearly, or Hon. Members <lb/> misunderstand me. I have said, over and over
                  again, that the people must decide this question. <lb/> His Excellency says that
                  if the newly constituted Council asks for Responsible Government, <lb/> under the
                  Organic Act, they will get it. What need is there to drag in the question into
                  these <lb/> Resolutions? The Hon. Mr. ' Wood cannot, dare not, say that the
                  majority of the British subjects <lb/> in British Columbia are in favour of
                  Responsible Government. I may be found in the minority <lb/> upon this question
                  when it comes before the people, but I speak from conviction; and, moreover, <lb/>
                  I say that when once we are in the Dominion, if the people desire Responsible
                  Government, no <lb/> power on earth can prevent them from having it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName>—I heartily concur with the Hon. Mr, Wood, in
                  his views on Responsible <lb/> Government. <lb/>
               </p>

            <pb n="89" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_089.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">89</fw>
            

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName>—I never said I was in favour of Responsible
                  Government. I say that <lb/> the Governor asks for the ratification of the people,
                  and at the same time denies that we are <lb/> fit for self-government. I have
                  never pledged myself to Responsible Government. ["Oh! oh! <lb/> oh!"] <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName>—I must oppose the amendment of the Hon. and
                  learned member; <lb/> first, because it raises invidious distinctions, and might
                  lead to the inference that we were <lb/> indifferent to the other portion of the
                  terms; secondly, because it asks this House to do what <lb/> it cannot, and, even
                  if it had the power, ought not to do. This Council is not the proper body <lb/> to
                  dictate final terms. This Council is only a quasi-representative body, and does
                  not fairly <lb/> represent the people. With a House constituted as this is,
                  containing some Members who <lb/> professedly only represent their own individual
                  opinions, it would, in my opinion, be an insult <lb/> to the people to make any
                  condition a test of union, in the sense proposed. Suppose Canada <lb/> sends back
                  the terms without the Railway, it is for the people to accept or reject them; that
                  <lb/> is a right belonging to the people, who have not yet been consulted. The
                  Hon. Mr. Wood has <lb/> said that there are Hon. Members in this House who would
                  go in for Confederation on any terms. <lb/> I, for one, have never done so;
                  nothing is more foreign to my desires. [" Hear, hear," from <lb/> the
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Attorney-General</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName></supplied> Though I am a Canadian, and am proud of my country, I am also a
                  <lb/> British Colombian; and upon this question my first and last thought has
                  been, is, and will be, for <lb/> British Columbia. [" Hear, hear," from the
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Attorney-General</persName>.] <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ALST1">Hon. Mr. ALSTON</persName>—As a test question, I must say I cannot vote
                  for this amendment <lb/> If I am in this Council when the final votes upon
                  Confederation are to be taken, I shall be <lb/> prepared to vote against
                  Confederation, unless a Railway is included in the terms—unless, <lb/> that is to
                  say, my sentiments undergo some change which I do not foresee. I do not see how,
                  <lb/> if this were made a test question, the Government could carry out their
                  instructions, first to <lb/> submit the Resolutions to Canada. and then to submit
                  the Canadian terms to the people. <lb/> This is not the time to submit a test
                  question, neither can we arrogate to ourselves the power <lb/> to do so; it must
                  be left to the popular vote. Therefore, although I fully concur in the senti<lb
                     break="no"/>ment that we must have a Railway some time or other, I must vote
                  against this amendment. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName>—Mr. Chairman, the sooner we get back to
                  business the better. The <lb/> discussion has become too wide. Some Hon. Members
                  seem to think that Canada can't do it, <lb/> that too much money is required. What
                  is the fact? We merely ask the Canadian Government <lb/> to spend one million a
                  year. What is the interest on that sum, at 4 per cent? $40,000. and the <lb/> next
                  year $80,000. I don't know how long it will take to get to the Rocky Mountains We
                  want <lb/> the Railway for our own purposes. [" Hear, hear, hear," from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hons.
                  DeCosmos</persName>, <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Holbrook</persName>, and <lb/> <persName ref="pers:ANON1">others</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName></supplied> We shall derive benefit from the
                  expenditure of a million dollars a year in the Colony, <lb/> and be getting a
                  Railway at the same time. Every one seems to think that the Railway will <lb/>
                  unite the country; so it will; but it is not simply a Railway or a Telegraph that
                  will unite <lb/> Canada and British Columbia. The only true basis of Union is that
                  people should have the <lb/> same interests, the same feelings, and the same
                  desire to make this a prosperous country. <lb/> If Canada gives us terms
                  sufficiently good to show that it is her intention to do all she can <lb/> to
                  develop our resources and advance our interests. then she will gain the affections
                  of the <lb/> people of this Colony, and then there will be an union which no
                  Railway can give, a material <lb/> Union which nothing can disturb, and we shall
                  find hereafter that Kingdoms and Nations will <lb/> spring out of this Union. We
                  are told by the Hon. Mr. Wood that the Officials must vote for <lb/> these terms,
                  as they have been settled by the Governor. This is not so, for before any terms
                  <lb/> can be concluded some one must go to Canada from here, or come from Canada
                  to this place, <lb/> to arrange conditions. I believe in what His Excellency has
                  said. I place more reliance on him <lb/> than on any one else. I believe he will
                  act fairly and justly in this matter, nor do I think <lb/> there is so much to
                  fear from Canada as there is from the danger of the people of this Colony <lb/>
                  cheating themselves; you can make the people believe anything. I do not agree that
                  the <lb/> country is in 'such a depressed condition. I know that Victoria, the
                  chief city, is in rather <lb/> a depressed condition, and perhaps New Westminster
                  also, but outside it is otherwise. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName>—Is the gold mining interest prosperous? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mn. HELMCKEN</persName>—The Hon. Member asks if the gold mining
                  interest is prosperous. <lb/> I say that this Colony has no business to depend
                  upon its gold mining interests. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName>—What else has she got? <lb/>
               </p>

            <pb n="90" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_090.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">90</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
           

 <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. HELMCKEN</persName>-She has agricultural interests. coal.
                  lumber, and fisheries. What <lb/> do you send away half a million of dollars for
                  each year? We want a more industrious popula<lb break="no"/>tion, a productive
                  population. But to return to the Railway: the sooner we get through this <lb/>
                  Railway the better; it opens so many avenues for discussion. I think it is the
                  most essential <lb/> part of this document. It is essential to Canada; through it
                  she hopes to make a country of <lb/> this Colony; and it is essential to us, as
                  bringing us prosperity. I believe the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will
                  make the Railway in the interior. We are told that they have four millions lying
                  <lb/> idle; they cannot have a better investment for it than to build a Railroad
                  from Fraser River <lb/> to Kamloops. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DeCOSMOS</persName>—I remark. Mr. Chairman, that there is a
                  considerable contrast <lb/> between the views of two Hon. Members of the Executive
                  Council. I mean the Hon. Chief <lb/> Commissioner (Mr. Trutch) and the Hon. Member
                  for Victoria City (Dr. Helmcken). The <lb/> former says that it is not proposed to
                  construct a railway with reference to local interests. <lb/> He says to advocate
                  our own local interests is simply inapposite. I think differently. I think <lb/>
                  that we should deal with it locally as well as nationally. I presume it is put in
                  the terms <lb/> because it is expected that it will benefit the Colony. We don't
                  care so much for its benefiting <lb/> the people of Montreal as for benefiting
                  ourselves; we look at it from a British Columbian <lb/> point of view. I say with
                  the Hon. Member for Victoria City (Dr. Helmcken), that we should <lb/> deal with
                  it with reference to British Columbion interests. After the discussion of
                  yesterday, <lb/> I confess my surprise. I thought from the tenor of the
                  Resolutions that the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would construct the line.
                  Now, we are informed by the Hon. Chief Commissioner that <lb/> it will be
                  undertaken by a private company. Then, he says if we cannot get a Railway we <lb/>
                  must have an equivalent. If this clause is not a fixed principle in the terms,
                  then, I ask, <lb/> what do the Government propose as an equivalent? With regard to
                  Railway communication <lb/> through British Columbia, we ought, in my opinion, to
                  connect Kamloops and the adjacent <lb/> country with the seaboard. That is,
                  commencing at navigable water on Fraser River and ending <lb/> at Savona's Ferry,
                  Kamloops Lake. This line, at the utmost, is only 150 miles long. The <lb/> expense
                  of its construction, at $50,000 per mile, would be $7,500,000. We might safely
                  approach <lb/> the Canadian Government upon this, irrespective of the terms of
                  Union, under the constitutional <lb/> provision authorizing the Dominion
                  Government to construct public works of this character. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—I say again that the scheme of this
                  Railway, on which <lb/> this clause is based, hangs on the construction of the
                  line from the seaboard. I never said. and <lb/> never intended to say, that we had
                  no right to take into consideration whether or not local <lb/> interests would be
                  benefited. I say that I would not dare to stand up here and advocate a <lb/>
                  special link of a special line. I should think if I did so that I was doing what
                  the Canadian <lb/> Government could not listen to. But in a great scheme which
                  contemplates a line of Railway <lb/> from the seaboard of British Columbia to
                  Canada, I consider that the Dominion Government <lb/> may take a broad View and
                  strain a point to get it. This clause has been drawn without pre<lb break="no"
                  />tending to define the route. I did not say that it was proposed that the line
                  should be built <lb/> by a private company. I said that it suggested itself to my
                  mind that the line would be built <lb/> by a private company. not that it was so
                  proposed. I do not disregard local interests I look <lb/> upon this Railway as a
                  necessity of the position—a means to the end. I do not advocate it on <lb/> its
                  merits as to local interest, but as a grand scheme of Transcontinental Railway.
                  Why, Sir, <lb/> some say that the terminus should be brought to Esquimalt or
                  Nanaimo. A Railway is wanted <lb/> in the interests of the Confederacy, but the
                  locality has been generalized as much as possible <lb/> by the Government. This
                  brings me to another point: though I look upon the Railway as a <lb/> necessity of
                  the position, in view of the approach of Confederation, I would not pledge myself
                  <lb/> to bind the Dominion Government to the special terms of this clause. I think
                  it possible that <lb/> terms may be suggested; instead of this condition, which
                  may be found to be acceptable to the <lb/> people of this Colony, to whom, as you
                  know. His Excellency says the matter must he referred. <lb/> I do not look upon
                  the Railway as unessential. I say it is essential; for without unity of <lb/>
                  interests Confederation cannot endure. If I did not think that under Confederation
                  we should <lb/> be governed satisfaclorily and to our advantage, I would oppose
                  Confederation, and would <lb/> advise its abandonment. I do not say and I am not
                  going to bind myself, that unless that <lb/> clause is granted by Canada I shall
                  not vote for Confederation, although I think it essential <lb/> to the position.
                  <lb/>
               </p>


            <pb n="91" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_091.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">91</fw>
            

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WALK1">Hon. Mr. WALKEM</persName>— Chairman, having been unfortunately absent
                  during the early <lb/> part of this debate, I have not been able, hitherto, to
                  take part in it. I adopt the principle <lb/> laid down by the Hon. Chief
                  Commissioner with regard to this clause, but I think the clause <lb/> is not
                  general enough. It is true, that it is suiliciently general as to a part, but not
                  as to <lb/> the whole. Enough has been said about the spending of $1,000,000 to
                  show what it means. I <lb/> would leave out the one million. It would be enough,
                  in my opinion, to say that it shall be <lb/> constructed within a reasonable time.
                  This would mean not an indefinite, but a reasonable, <lb/> time; it would he so
                  interpreted by the Law Courts I would leave out the definition of time, <lb/> and
                  I would leave out the one million. I think it 'will do us injury with Canadian
                  statesmen; <lb/> they will say that this is the measure of our desire to he
                  contederated, There is another point <lb/> to which I would call attention. The
                  language of the clause does not, in my opinion, imply <lb/> that one million must
                  necessarily be expended within the Colony. I conclude, after hearing <lb/> the
                  explanations of Hon. Members, that it is intended that the one million shall he
                  spent here; <lb/> but in my opinion it might, under these words, be expended on
                  any part of the line. I thought <lb/> that was the intention; it was so thought in
                  San Francisco. There were newspaper articles <lb/> upon it, and the idea of a
                  million a year being spent upon the Railway for a hundred years <lb/> was laughed
                  at on all sides. I would suggest an alteration in the words. I am ready to leave
                  <lb/> the construction of the English to any schoolmaster. I say that they do not
                  mean " in the <lb/> Colony." With regard to the remarks of the Hon. Member for
                  Victoria District, I would remark <lb/> that this is not really a final contract,
                  and I agree with the Hon. Chief Commissioner that the <lb/> clause ought to be
                  general. The Canadian statesmen, with whom we are about to deal, are not <lb/>
                  mere tyros; and I say that the mention of this one million leaves it open to
                  Canada to keep the <lb/> time open. If they expend that sum upon any portion of
                  the line, they will be able to prolong <lb/> the building of the road as long
                  as-they please. And, although it may be said that Canada will <lb/> take care of
                  us, I say we ought to take care of ourselves. Let us get as good terms as
                  possible, <lb/> not trusting to the Canadians, but looking after our own
                  interests. We should, in my opinion, <lb/> abstain from all mention of one million
                  dollars, or any other sum; otherwise the Canadian <lb/> Government may say that on
                  payment or expenditure of that sum they will have completed <lb/> their bargain.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I rise, Sir, to defend my English. This
                  clause was settled <lb/> after much consideration, in the first place emanating
                  from the Hon. Chief Commissioner of <lb/> Lands and Works. I conceive that the
                  'words—"and that a sum of not less than $1,000,000 <lb/> "shall be expended in
                  every year, from and after three years from the date of Union, in <lb/> "actualy
                  constructing the initial sections of such Railway from the Seaboard of British
                  <lb/> "Columbia. to connect with the Railway system of Canada," fully convey the
                  meaning that <lb/> it was intended they should. The language means that the
                  expenditure should be within this <lb/> Colony, and it can mean nothing else. The
                  schoolmaster cannot have been where the Hon. <lb/> Member has just visited, or he
                  would not have so misconstrued this clause. I may confirm <lb/> what the Hon.
                  Chief Commissioner says, that if in communication with the Canadian Govern<lb
                     break="no"/>ment it is found that they will not consent to the Railway, it is
                  thought that we may obtain <lb/> some equivalent. I must vote against the
                  amendment of the Hon. Member for Victoria <lb/> District (Mr. DeCosmos). as it
                  proposes to enter into details affecting particular localities. I <lb/> regret
                  that the Hon. Member, who usually takes such large and extended views, should in
                  this <lb/> instance have taken so small and sectional a view of so large a scheme.
                  The whole country <lb/> will he just as much benefited by the Railway as any one
                  part of it, The Hon. and learned <lb/> Member for Victoria City proposes a
                  guarantee and a penalty, but he has not shown how he <lb/> could enforce the
                  penalty if, we cannot compel the fulfilment of the terms. I think that the <lb/>
                  self-interests of Canada will be so identified with those of British Columbia that
                  we shall <lb/> require no further guarantee. If more is required, as the Hon.
                  Member for New Westminster <lb/> says, we have the assurance of the Imperial
                  Government—the Queen's proclamation. I cannot <lb/> say that I think that the
                  Canadian interests are purely commercial, I have lived in Canada <lb/> for several
                  years. and while there did not regret to see the country divided against itself.
                  Now, <lb/> there is a national feeling growing up in that promising young country;
                  her inhabitants are <lb/> becoming more British in their feeling; I believe that
                  Canada will, as she has heretofore done, <lb/> carry out the terms she makes in
                  honour and good faith. It will he to her interest to do so; <lb/> it will be to
                  her interest to satisfy the interests of British Columbia. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS</persName>—The question of the Railway should be put
                  in a practical form. <lb/> The people want a Railway from the head of navigation
                  into the interior. Unless we get <lb/>
                  <pb n="92" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_092.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">92</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> immediate benefit, I hold we had
                  better have no Railway at all [laughter]. The resolution of <lb/> my Hon.
                  colleague (Mr. DeCosmos) will give us immediate prosperity. "Unless we get
                  immediate <lb/> advantage it is very little use at all. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName>—There is one word in the Hon. Attorney
                  General's speech that I <lb/> desire to reply to. He said that my recommendation
                  goes too much into matters of detail. I <lb/> find as much detail in the Organic
                  Act with reference to Railway communication to Halifax. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. Mn. ROBSON</persName>—I have a recommendation to move, hearing on
                  the Coach Road, as <lb/> follows:- <lb/>
               </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"That a respectful Address he presented to His Excellency, recommending that Clause 8 
     <lb/>
     "may he so altered as to include the section of the main trunk road of the Colony lying between 
     <lb/>
     " Yale and New Westminster, in the Coach Road which the Dominion Government is to he asked 
     <lb/>
     " to construct within three years from the date of Union." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     I think, Sir, that it is obvious that if Canada is to he asked to construct a grand trunk 
     <lb/>
     road it is equally important that she should add a connecting link which is wanting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. MR. HOLBROOK</persName>—If we can get the Dominion Government to
                  make this communicat<lb break="no"/>ing link it will he a benefit to the whole
                  Mainland.   <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. Dr. CARRALL</persName>—I shall support the recommendation of the
                  Hon. Member for New <lb/> Westminster. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—Tlis recommendation is open to the same
                  objection as the <lb/> proposal of the Hon. Member for Victoria District: I must
                  oppose it on principle. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—It was intended to add the words "and
                  maintain" after <lb/> "construct and open for traffic." The words have
                  inadverently been omitted. I propose to <lb/> remedy the mistake, and I therefore
                  move a respectful address to His Excellency suggesting that <lb/> the words " and
                  maintain " he added between the words " such " and " traffic," in the fourth line
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman put the recommendation of the Hon. Mr. Robson, which was carried; then 
     <lb/>
     the recommendation of the Hon. Chief Commissioner, which was carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The recommendations of the Hon. Mr. Wood and of the Hon. Mr. DeCosmos, were put 
     <lb/>
     and lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Clause 8 was then passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Clause 9 was next read hy the Chairman :- <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" 9. The Dominion shall erect and maintain, at Victoria, a Marine Hospital and a Lunatic 
     <lb/>
     "Asylum, either attached to the Hospital, or separateas may be considered most convenient. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "The Dominion shall also erect and maintain a Penitentiary, or other principal Prison, at 
     <lb/>
     "such place in the Colony as she may consider most suitable for that purpose." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     The Hon. Attorney-General moved the adoption of this clause. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">The Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName> said :—Sir, upon this clause I have to
                  move a recommendation <lb/> that the Penitentiary shall be at New Westminster. I
                  think that it will be admitted, on all <lb/> hands, that the Penitentiary ought to
                  he at New Westminster. Victoria and Esquimalt are <lb/> named as sites for
                  particular things. and why not New Westminster? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK</persName>—I second the recommendation of the Hon.
                  Member for New <lb/> Westminster. 1 think the Mainland ought to he considered; it
                  is of course a matter of some <lb/> consequence.   <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS</persName>—As a memher from the Mainland I shall
                  oppose the recommenda<lb break="no"/>tion, I am in favour of centralizing
                  buildings. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName>—Hon Members seem to lose sight of the words
                  "or principal <lb/> Prison." This does not mean exactly a Penitentiary, or other
                  principal Prison for reforming <lb/> criminals; the existing prisons are too small
                  for the purpose, and this really means a prison <lb/> for the detention of
                  prisoners, <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName>—The Dominion Government are bound, under
                  the Organic Act, <lb/> to provide a Penitentiary. This, I suppose, means more than
                  the Organic Act contemplates; <lb/> it means a Prison.   <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName>—Yes, that is the meaning; it means more
                  than the Organic Act <lb/> Contemplates. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName>—I think the Penitentiary ought to be in the
                  best and most central place; <lb/> wherever the prison can be best maintained. 1
                  would leave it to the Dominion Government <lb/> to decide the place. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK</persName>—Why should not Victoria be struck out of
                  this clause altogether? <lb/>
               </p>

            <pb n="93" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_093.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">93</fw>
            

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—I did not suggest New Westminster in any
                  local or sectional spirit. <lb/> I rather did it to divest the clause of local and
                  sectional spirit; though, at present, population <lb/> and other things point to
                  Victoria as the proper place for a Marine Hospital and Lunatic <lb/> Asylum; but
                  we must look to the future, the population must ultimately be largest on the <lb/>
                  Mainland. [<persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon Mr. Ring</persName> —" No, no."] <supplied><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName></supplied> Surely the Hon. Member for Nanaimo will not
                  assert <lb/> that the population or the Island will in time to come exceed that of
                  the Mainland. I have no <lb/> desire to give any sectional complexion to the
                  Resolutions. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—Sir, I desire to say that in my
                  opinion the Penitentiary <lb/> will ultimately be on the Mainland, perhaps at New
                  Westminster or Burrard Inlet, where <lb/> it is probable the Railway will come. I
                  can easily believe that the Hon. Member for New <lb/> Westminster does not
                  advocate New Westminster from local motives, but I must defend the <lb/>
                  Resolution as it stands. I think it better to leave it to the people who find the
                  money to <lb/> select the place. The position is not the same as regards the
                  Marine Hospital. It should be <lb/> at Victoria or Esquimalt, or at some
                  intermediate place, on account of this being the head <lb/> quarters of the Navy;
                  just as I think Esquinmlt is the proper place for the Dock. I believe <lb/> that
                  New Westminster will he the place, but I cannot, on principle, vote for the
                  recommendation. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman put the recommendation of the Hon. Mr. Robson to the Committee—Lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Clause 9 was then passed as read.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">The Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I move the adoption of Clause 10,
                  which reads thus :- <lb/>
               </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" 10. Efficient Coast Mail Steam Service, in connection with the Post Office, shall he estab<lb break="no"/>"lished and maintained by the Government of the Dominion, between Victoria and New West<lb break="no"/>"minster, Nanaimo, and such other places as may require such services." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>
     Until we have roads within the Colony, these services must he carried on for some time 
     <lb/>
     to come by water. I consider it to be a very proper item. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName>—I suggest the addition of Puget Sound.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon.  ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I object to such an addition, because
                  Puget Sound does <lb/> not come within Coast Mail Service. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK</persName>—Then are we to suppose there are to he no
                  other Ports of Entry, <lb/> other than Victoria? ["no, no, no," from <persName ref="pers:ANON1">all sides</persName>]
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman put the recommendation of the Hon. Mr. DeCosmos, which was lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Clause 10 was then passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">The Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I move the adoption of Clause 11,
                  which is a general <lb/> proposition, which will, I hope, meet with the
                  approbation of the House; it is as follows :- <lb/>
               </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" 11. Whatever encouragement, advantages, and protection are afforded by the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     "Government to the Fisheries of any of its Provinces, shall be extended in similar proportion 
     <lb/>
     "to British Columbia, according to its requirements for the time being." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Clause 11 was passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">The Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I move the adoption of Clause 12,
                  which reads thus :- <lb/>
               </p>
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"12. British Columbia shall participate. in fair proportion, in any measures which may be 
     <lb/>
     "adopted and Funds which may be appropriated by the Dominion for the encouragement of 
     <lb/>
     " Immigration." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     Passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I now more the adoption of Clause 13.
                  The working of <lb/> this clause is familiar to this Council from the debate which
                  has already taken place. The basis <lb/> is the population of 120.000 up to the
                  date, which is left blank. The clause is this :- <lb/>
               </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" 13. British Columbia shall be entitled to he represented in the Senate by Four Members, 
     <lb/>
     "and by Eight Members in the House of Commons, until the year 18 , and thereafter the 
     <lb/>
     "Representation in the Senate and the House of Commons shall be increased. subject to the 
     <lb/>
     "provisions of 'Thc British North America Act, 1867."  
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. Mr. DRAKE</persName>—Mr Chairman, there seems to be a diffliculty.
                  The Organic Act. section <lb/> 51, provides for the re-adjustment of the
                  representation after the census of 1871; and that the <lb/> representation shall
                  be based on the proportion of 65—the number that Quebec now has—to the <lb/>
                  population of Quebec. It ought to exist at this number until 1881, or 1891. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—1 would remark that in my opinion
                  Clause 51 does not <lb/> apply; we come in under Clause 146. The Hon. Members now
                  representing Victoria City and <lb/> District (Messrs. Helmcken and DcCosmos),
                  when they proposed to telegraph were a little late. <lb/> However if we now fix
                  the date, for which a blank is purposely left, that will settle the matter <lb/>
                  beyond any doubt. <lb/>
               </p>

            <pb n="94" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_094.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">94</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>—In my opinion, Sir, we are better off
                  than if we were <lb/> included. The only thing we have to do is to fix a date. If
                  we put the date back to a remote <lb/> period, we might be doing ourselves an
                  injustice; for we might be entitled to more. I would <lb/> put if off for 20
                  years, filling up the date by inserting 1801. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK</persName>—I think ten years quite enough, we shall
                  have more than 120,000 <lb/> in that time, and be entitled to increased
                  representation. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. Mr. DECOSMOS</persName>— Mr. Chairman, during the previous debate
                  an Hon. Member referred <lb/> to 120,000 as the basis of representation. as well
                  as the basis of population. We find this <lb/> echoed by others, last, but not
                  least. by the Hon. Attorney-General himself. I am surprised <lb/> to find the Hon.
                  and learned gentleman setting this up as a basis. For the basis of represen<lb
                     break="no"/>tation under the Organic Act was the basis of representation
                  allowed to Quebec, that is, <lb/> one member for every 20,000. It is proposed
                  that we shall have eight members; then the popu<lb break="no"/>lation ought to be
                  160,000; but it is only set up as 120,000, which number would only entitle <lb/>
                  us to six members. Now, Sir, I have no objection to getting eight members for the
                  House of <lb/> Commons, and four for the Senate; but I do object to Hon. Members
                  and newspapers spreading <lb/> abroad statements which have no foundation in fact.
                  I think our population has been over <lb/> estimated. It is going abroad that
                  120,000 is the proper foundation for representation; I say <lb/> it is not so. The
                  honest straightforward and manly course is for our Government to say <lb/> to the
                  Dominion Government, that it is necessary for us to have a larger representation
                  on <lb/> territorial grounds. The whole thing resolves itself into expediency;
                  beyond expediency I say <lb/> that no one can find a fulcrum for the assertion. I
                  would cheerfully support twelve and six <lb/> so far as it goes. But I do denounce
                  that want of principle and want of truth that surrounds <lb/> this basis. There is
                  another question about the representation to which due attention does <lb/> not
                  seem to have been given; it is this: the electoral qualification in Canada is too
                  high, and <lb/> it will be most objectionable to have the same qualification
                  thrust upon us. The qualification <lb/> of members may safely be left to the
                  Dominion Government. But that of electors is too high, <lb/> and will be a source
                  of irritation, which the Government should endeavour to remove now. I <lb/> should
                  have moved a recommendation as to this, but from the treatment which my amendments
                  <lb/> have received in this House, I am inclined to let it pass, and I shall move
                  my amendments before <lb/> my constituents. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     On motion of the Hon. Mr. Dewdney, the Committee rose, reported progress, and asked 
     <lb/>
     leave to sit again. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Several Members having left the House, on motion of the Hon. Mr. Robson the Committee 
     <lb/>
     sat again. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName>—Mr. Chairman, I find the average of
                  representation in the Dominion <lb/> Parliament is one member to 15,000. That, on
                  the basis of 120,000, gives eight members. Nova <lb/> Scotia has 19 members for
                  39,000, New Brunswick has 12, Newfoundland has 8 members. All <lb/> we have to do
                  is to take care that we are not included in the census of 1871. Our number <lb/>
                  cannot be diminished, so we may put it at 1881 safely. As for fictitious numbers,
                  it is useless <lb/> to talk about it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. MR. CARRALL</persName>— I move that the date " 1881 " be inserted.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName>-I do not see that of necessity the
                  number cannot be <lb/> decreased. I would name a more distant date. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—I would not take a more distant date, because
                  I think we shall have <lb/> a larger population in 1881. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName>—From Section 61 of the Organic Act, I think
                  our number might be <lb/> reduced. I think it improbable we shall have a
                  population of 120.000 in 1881. And if we <lb/> have not that number then, I think
                  it possible that we may be reduced. I shall therefore vote <lb/> for 1801.   <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I shall support the date 1801. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName>-I move a recommendation to insert the words
                  "not less than," before <lb/> "4 and 8," and after the word " eighteen" to insert
                  "91." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I cannot see the use or necessity for
                  the words "no less." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—I think the words are important. We might in
                  1881 be entitled to <lb/> more or less. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR DRAKE</persName>-I hold to 91, because I think it likely we
                  might be reduced if we fix <lb/> the date at 81. <lb/>
               </p>
   
         
            <pb n="95" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-17_Page_095.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">95</fw>
          

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—I think we ought to fix a minimum number
                  and keep to it, and <lb/> a date, because I think that when the distrust wears
                  away, British Columbia may be content <lb/> with three in the Senate, and six in
                  the House of Commons. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman put the recommendation of the Hon. Mr. Drake, to fill up the blank with 
     <lb/>
     the figures "91." Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Chairman put the recommendation of the Hon. Mr. Wood—"That the number of 
     <lb/>
     members to the Commons should never be less than 8, and to the Senate never less than 4." 
     <lb/>
     Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Clause 13 was then passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Committee rose, and reported progress, and obtained leave to sit again on Friday at 
     <lb/>
     one o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2017-03-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

   
            <!--<p>
     FRIDAY, MARCH 18TH, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL—I rise to move the adoption of clause 14:<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <p>"14. The Union shall take efffect on such day as Her Majesty by Order in Council (on 
     <lb/>
     "an Address to that effect, in terms of the 146th Section of 'The British North America 
     <lb/>
     " Act, 1867,') may direct: and British Columbia may, in such Address, specify the Districts, 
     <lb/>
     "Counties, or Divisions, if any, for which any of the four Senators to whom the Colony shall 
     <lb/>
     "be entitled shall be named, the Electoral Districts for which—and the time within which<lb break="no"/>"the first Election of Members to serve in the House of Commons shall take place." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     These terms, or rather the terms which come back from Canada, will of necessity come 
     <lb/>
     before the new electoral body, whose existence His Excellency has shadowed forth, and the 
     <lb/>
     particulars as to the division into districts  must be left for the decision of that House. It is 
     <lb/>
     impossible at present to specify the time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. DECOSMOS—Cannot an approximate time be named? Besides there are other 
     <lb/>
     things upon which the country will want information; such, for instance, as whether the 
     <lb/>
     voting for members will be by ballot, and what is to be the qualification of voters. I think it 
     <lb/>
     ought to be fixed. The Dominion law is more liberal than that to which the people of this 
     <lb/>
     country have been accustomed. I believe in the ballot, but it will be better to leave it to the 
     <lb/>
     constituencies. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER—This clause has been left general, that it may be settled 
     <lb/>
     by the newly-constituted Council. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. DR. HELMCKEN—If there is a qualification for the House of Commons it must be 
     <lb/>
     general for the whole Dominion. At present I believe the qualification is that existing in the 
     <lb/>
     Provinces before union. Ultimately there must be a qualification for the whole Dominion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. DR. CARRALL—There is no general law for qualification. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. HUMPHREYS—The clause is indefinite and dangerous. The Dominion qualifica<lb break="no"/>tion will virtually disfranchise half the British settlers in British Columbia. We are legislating 
     <lb/>
     in the interests of the people; this ought to be determined at once. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. DECOSMOS—I believe in British subjects, having a fixed residence, and of a 
     <lb/>
     certain age, voting in British Columbia. It should be a residential manhood suffrage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. DR. HELMCKEN—We cannot deal with the subject now. It is impossible to divide 
     <lb/>
     the Colony into districts until we know how many Senators we are to have. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK—Mr. Chairman, I move a recommendation to strike out the words 
     <lb/>
     "if any." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. WOOD—I think the words ought to stand. The Organic Act says that Senators 
     <lb/>
     shall be selected for districts; but it may be desirable that Senators should be appointed for 
     <lb/>
     the whole Colony. They are nominated, and nominated because they are the best men that 
     <lb/>
     the Governor can obtain. [No no, no—Hon. DeCosmos I believe the Executive are in the 
     <lb/>
     best position to know whether the principle of appointing Senators is best or whether they 
     <lb/>
     should go for the whole Colony. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS—As this stands it throws the whole power into the hands of the 
     <lb/>
     Canadians. The Lieutenant-Governor will be a Canadian and will name Canadians. We ought 
     <lb/>
     to know by whom these appointments are to be made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
     </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>