<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgBCLC_1870-03-22" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgBCLC">British Columbia Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1870-03-22">22 March 1870</date>, Province of BC, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          <editor>W.S. Sebright Green</editor>
          
         
               <title>Legislative Council, Debate on the Subject of Confederation with Canada</title>.
                    

          <date when="1912"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Victoria, B.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>William H. Cullin</publisher>.
                    

          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="120" to="131"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_120.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_121.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_122.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_123.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_124.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_125.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_126.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_127.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_128.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_129.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_130.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_131.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-22">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-22">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-25">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_120">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_120.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_121">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_121.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_122">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_122.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_123">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_123.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_124">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_124.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_125">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_125.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_126">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_126.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_127">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_127.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_128">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_128.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_129">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_129.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_130">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_130.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_131">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_131.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="120" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_120.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">120</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
<!-- GL, 2017-03-22, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

<!--<p>
     had; therefore Confederation is out of the question. I have thus, Sir, given my opinion on 
     <lb/>
     a point which is sure to meet with popular disfavour, but I am proud to support the Executive 
     <lb/>
     when I think it is right; and I would share the responsibility of a measure which would make 
     <lb/>
     that Executive obnoxious to blame. I have no chronic feeling of opposition to Government. 
     <lb/>
     I have no objection to individuals, nor do I impute to them sordid motives, but in the matter 
     <lb/>     
    of Confederation the Executive of this Colony are in a false position; they act primarily, 
     <lb/>not for the good of the Colony, but for the good, or supposed good, of Great Britain; and 
     <lb/>they exercise the power of Government in a matter in which the interests of the Colony 
     <lb/>are mainly at stake to carry out, and effect an organic change of great importance to local 
     <lb/>interests. It is somewhat unfair to me to say I impute motives to the Executive. 1 only 
     <lb/>quarrel with them when they place themselves in a false position, as in the question of 
     <lb/>education; and in this, as in education, I say they oppose their own views to the views of, 
     <lb/>the,well understood wishes of all classes of the community; and here the carry through a 
     <lb/>scheme of Confederation; they start the stone, and it is hard to see how or where it will roll. 
     <lb/>I sincerely feel for their position. The Colony will demand representative institutions, and they 
     <lb/>will be forced to yield them or back out of the position they have undertaken. The answer of 
     <lb/>the Executive Government to this is as given by the Hon. Attorney-General. The Attorney- 
     <lb break="yes"/>General says that after Confederation we are bound to have what we require—Responsible 
     <lb/>Government. This is taking the matter for granted. It may be attained, but with a struggle. 
     <lb/>It is impossible to doubt that the Executive of the new Province will oppose representative 
     <lb/>Government or any diminution of their own rights or their own power. He says it is inoppor<lb break="no"/>tune and beside the question. The Hon. Member for Cariboo (Dr. Carrall) says: "If the 
     <lb/>people of British Columbia want Responsible Government no power on earth can prevent their 
     <lb/>having it." This is but a promise for the future. The Hon. Chief Commissioner says the 
     <lb/>community is not fit for Responsible Government, but the matter is to be left to the new 
     <lb/>Council. Responsible Government will assuredly come with Confederation. The Hon. Member 
     <lb/>for Victoria (Dr. Helmcken) says: "This is the argument of the Government. But something 
     <lb/>must counterbalance Canada, otherwise with a working majority in the House the Dominion 
     <lb/>Government will keep things as they are when we are a Province of Canada." 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     TUESDAY, MARCH 22ND, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. MR. HOLBROOK</persName>—Mr. Chairman, I rise with some diffidence
                  to give my opinion <lb/> as to whether we are fitted for Responsible Government or
                  not, after the able speeches that <lb/> have been delivered by Hon. Members on the
                  subject. The Hon. and learned Member for <lb/> Victoria City (Mr. Drake) has
                  affirmed that Responsible Government would give the real <lb/> government of the
                  Colony to Victoria. This I believe is true, and if such were the case what <lb/>
                  injury it would inflict on New Westminster and the Mainland generally. I feel that
                  we are <lb/> not yet fit for Responsible Government; but nevertheless, I think
                  that the extent of the popu<lb break="no"/>lation is very much under-estimated. It
                  has been stated that after the most careful calculation <lb/> that can be made the
                  white population cannot be calculated at over 5,000 adults; but I think <lb/> this
                  is wrong, and no doubt it has been taken from the Government Accounts, which do
                  not <lb/> include Kootenay, Big Bend, or the settlements around New Westminster;
                  and I would make <lb/> the adult white population to be 10,000, besides 40,000
                  Indians; and these Indians ought not <lb/> to be ignored. If they are not
                  represented will it not be difficult to make them contented with <lb/> the change
                  from the Imperial Government to Canada? And it is for this reason that I have
                  <lb/> given a notice of motion in this House to show them that they are not
                  forgotten, and that they <lb/> may go on with their settlements and improvements
                  in safety. But if we are to have Respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government I will not
                  be answerable for the consequences. We are told the question is <lb/> to be
                  submitted to the people. I say let us wait for their decision. I have confidence
                  in <lb/> Canada, and am content to take my chance of being well governed by the
                  Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, rather than try something of the working of
                  which we know nothing. I have no doubt <lb/> that great agitation on the subject
                  of Responsible Government will be got up by the press, and <lb/> that many members
                  will gain their elections by confusing the questions of Confederation and <lb/>
                  <pb n="121" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_121.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="running">CONDEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">121</fw> Responsible Government. I entirely concur with the lion.
                  Mr. Wood in believing that more <lb/> liberal representation will do much more for
                  the good of the Colony than Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. I believe in a
                  good franchise being given, as foreshadowed by the Governor's Speech ; <lb/> and I
                  think twelve elected and eight nominated members would give satisfaction and work
                  <lb/> well, although report makes the change more liberal than this. We are now on
                  the eve of <lb/> prosperity. Our quartz mining is still to be commenced, and we
                  only want good roads to <lb/> Kootenay, by way of Eagle Pass, to open our
                  resources in this respect. I do not intend to <lb/> enter upon the question of
                  Responsible Government. I believe it would be bad for us and is <lb/> not required
                  by the people. I shall support the Government in the clause now under discussion.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—Mr. Chairman, I had not expected to say
                  anything more on this <lb/> subject ; but, on more mature reflection, I am
                  satisfied that it is my duty to do so. The more <lb/> the matter is argued, and
                  the more the remarks of Government members are heard, the more <lb/> I believe we
                  are being asked to take a leap in the dark ; for all I can learn is that the new
                  <lb/> House is to be partly nominative and partly elective—and not responsible.
                  The proportions <lb/> are not stated. It has also cropped out that there will be a
                  qualification for members. and <lb/> also for electors. If the Government refer
                  this matter to the people to know whether such a <lb/> Constitution will suit
                  them, I believe the people, to almost a unit, will reject it. The mass <lb/> are
                  opposed to Confederation altogether unless they can get a more liberal
                  representation than <lb/> that proposed by the Government. At the outset I
                  proposed a Committee of all parties to <lb/> consider and report upon the whole
                  matter; but the hasty judgment of the House, as I think, <lb/> deferred the
                  question. Now, Sir, I think if the Committee had met and suggested, for the <lb/>
                  protection of the property element, that one-third of the Members of the Council
                  should be <lb/> elected for a longer period and hold property qualifications, the
                  country would have been <lb/> satisfied. I can conceive on some such proposition
                  as that being laid before the House, it <lb/> would have been eminently
                  successful; as it nor stands it is matter of opinion. I think the <lb/> Governor
                  has been led into error if the utterances that occasionally drop from members of
                  this <lb/> House mean anything. I cannot conceive that the people will accept such
                  a Constitution. I <lb/> should prefer that we should go into Confederation as a
                  unit. I have made these few remarks <lb/> to set my mind at rest, and to save
                  myself trouble with my constituents if I should offer myself <lb/> as a candidate
                  again. I state that I believe the Government will jeopardise Confederation on
                  <lb/> this point. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Hon. MR. DEWDNEY</persName>—Sir, the question now under consideration
                  has been so fully gone <lb/> into by Hon, Members of the Council, that I feel it
                  will be useless for me to take up the time <lb/> of this House to any great
                  length. At the commencement of this debate I had several argu<lb break="no"/>ments
                  which I proposed to bring before your notice against Responsible Government, but I
                  <lb/> find that these have been ably handled by other Hon. gentlemen far more ably
                  than I could <lb/> have hoped to do ; and should I not have been convinced at the
                  earlier stages of this debate, <lb/> other arguments have been adduced which now
                  completely set my mind at rest on the subject. <lb/> I am opposed to the
                  recommendations of both the Hon. Members for New Westminster and <lb/> Lillooet,
                  particularly the latter, and in opposing them I do not feel I am injuring the
                  cause of <lb/> Confederation. But while I feel, Mr. Chairman, that it is
                  unnecessary for me to enter into <lb/> the question of Responsible Government, I
                  think I should not be doing my duty were I to <lb/> remain silent upon one matter
                  connected with this debate—one upon which I consider I am as <lb/> capable of
                  giving an opinion as any Hon. Member of this Council—namely, the feelings of <lb/>
                  the inhabitants of the Mainland generally with regard to Responsible Government. I
                  have <lb/> travelled through this country as much as any Hon. Member of this
                  Council, and I have been <lb/> brought in contact with all classes, and have mixed
                  with all classes. and I have yet to meet the <lb/> first individual who has
                  expressed to me his desire for Responsible Government. Now. Mr. <lb/> Chairman, do
                  you believe, does this Council believe, that the cry throughout this Colony is—
                  <lb/> down with the present form of Government, let us have Responsible
                  Government? Hon. <lb/> Members of this House are aware, I presume, that my
                  avocations for some years past, in fact <lb/> as long as I have been in the
                  Colony, have necessarily brought me in contact with all classes, <lb/> and should
                  this have been the cry, do you think I should not have heard it? I say distinctly
                  <lb/> again, I have yet to meet the first individual who has expressed to me his
                  desire for Respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government, The feeling of my constituents
                  is not in favour of Responsible Government; <lb/> on the contrary, it was
                  distinctly expressed to me that they do not desire any change in the <lb/> present
                  form of Government. All they want is money to keep their trails in order and a <lb/>
                  <pb n="122" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_122.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">122</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> resident Magistrate to administer
                  and carry out the laws I believe that some Hon. Members <lb/> of this House have
                  mistaken the feelings of the country on this matter. Any dissatisfaction <lb/>
                  that exists is not with the present system of government but with the expense of
                  carrying,r the <lb/> system out. We all feel that, and we all know that. it cannot
                  be avoided, for reasons which <lb/> have been given over and over again in this
                  House, namely, the smallness of population; <lb/> scattered as it is over so vast
                  an area. I have not heard during the debate any arguments that <lb/> will prove to
                  me or to this House that under Responsible Government we could have a cheaper
                  <lb/> form of government. I for one could not be convinced that we should. I
                  believe that the <lb/> public moneys would be wasted. peculation and dishonesty
                  would be the order of the day. We <lb/> are told by the Hon. Member for Yale we
                  must have a beginning. I am aware of that fact. <lb/> and for one shall assist to
                  put off the evil day. I prefer for a time—until our population <lb/> increases—to
                  live under the present form of Government, one under which, I am proud to say,
                  <lb/> I have lived for eleven years without seeing the faults of maladministration
                  and other evil <lb/> accusations that have been hurled at it by the Hon. Member
                  for Lillooet. I am aware that <lb/> that Hon. gentleman was himself in some
                  subordinate position under the Government; he may <lb/> of his own personal
                  knowledge, while in that capacity, be aware of some malpractice, but I <lb/> defy
                  him to point out a single instance brought before the notice of the Government
                  that did <lb/> not receive the strictest investigation and in which the individual
                  complained of, if the charges <lb/> were proved, was not discharged. In
                  conclusion, Mr. Chairman. I shall take this opportunity <lb/> of expressing my
                  appreciation of the officers generally that have carried on the Government of
                  <lb/> this Colony during the eleven years that I have lived here; and I challenge
                  any Hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man to prove by the records of Her Majesty's
                  Colonies, that in any Colony or Dependency of <lb/> the British Crown laws have
                  been more justly administered, life and property better protected, <lb/> or the
                  affairs of the. Colony carried on with greater rectitude than in the one in which
                  we are <lb/> now living. Holding these views, I must decline to support either of
                  the recommendations <lb/> before the Committee. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ALST1">Hon. Mr. ALSTON</persName>—Sir. I am in favour of Responsible
                  Government, but not the form <lb/> that has been discussed in this House at so
                  great a length I believe all representative Govern<lb break="no"/>ments are
                  responsible. The Hon. and learned Member for Victoria District has quoted John
                  <lb/> Stuart Mill I believe. Sir, that the words Responsible Government do not
                  occur in his book; <lb/> he shows that the form applicable to one country will not
                  do for another. We have heard <lb/> enough in this Council to make me believe that
                  'the people do not want Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment; I believe that a
                  representative form of Government is the only form that will suit this <lb/>
                  Colony It has been well shown by the Hon. Mix Wood, that from the difficulty of
                  getting <lb/> districts represented, this Colony is not adapted for purely
                  representative institutions. I think <lb/> it most desirable that Executive
                  Members should have seats in this Council, and I think that <lb/> a partially
                  elective House would best represent the interests of the entire community. The
                  <lb/> American form of Government is in a certain sense responsible, executive
                  officers being elected <lb/> for a term of four years. England possesses a
                  different form, and Canada diifers again from <lb/> England. The Colony from
                  which Governor Musgrave came is the last that has received <lb/> Responsible
                  Government; thus we may fairly trust to His Excellency to judge for us as to the
                  <lb/> probability of its working well here. The smallest Colony po 'ing
                  Responsible Government <lb/> is Prime Edward's Island: and we who do not possess a
                  popula on one-twelfth the size of that <lb/> of Newfoundland. are a use for
                  Responsible Govermnent. The lion. and learned Member <lb/> for Victoria City (Mr.
                  Drake). who seems to uphold Responsible Government against his own <lb/>
                  convictions. admits that all power would be held in Victoria; and he says that
                  there would be <lb/> no harm in such centralisation. I think, Sir, that he has
                  read John Stuart Mill to little <lb/> purpose if such be his conviction. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. Mr. Humphreys</persName> —Sir. I am more impressed than ever with
                  the absolute need <lb/> of Responsible Government. I think the Hon. Chief
                  Commissioner particularly, and the Hon. <lb/> Member for Victoria Citv, have
                  proved conclusively that two-thirds of the people representing <lb/> property are
                  determined to have Responsible Government. The Hon. Member for the City <lb/> told
                  us the people were not in favour of Responsible Government. and in the same
                  sentence he <lb/> tells us that if Confederation were set before the people with
                  Responsible Government mixed <lb/> up with it, the people would take Responsible
                  Government to the exclusion of material interests. <lb/> I have said, and say
                  again, I am in favour of Confederation, and I earnestly hope that it will <lb/> be
                  for the benefit of the Colony. I sometimes think that some Hon. Members at the
                  other end <lb/>
                  <pb n="123" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_123.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">123</fw> of the House intend to defeat Confederation. I may he
                  called an extremist—an agitator; I <lb/> admit I am. I desire to see the people
                  having a share in the Government, instead of being <lb/> under a despotism, or
                  what is equivalent to it. I have been in this Colony nearly eleven years; <lb/> I
                  am satisfied that the people want Responsible Government. Hon. Members say there
                  are <lb/> different forms of Responsible Government; admitted. I am not sure that
                  it would be advisable <lb/> to introduce any one system in its entirety here. Hon.
                  Members have been quoting writers <lb/> upon this subject; I will quote Lord
                  Macaulay, he says: "Government, like a good coat, is fit <lb/> for the body for
                  which it is made." I say if we cannot live on Responsible Goverinnont, we <lb/>
                  cannot live on irresponsible Government. I do not know what is shadowed forth in
                  His <lb/> Excellency's speech; I confess I cannot understand it. If the Governor
                  had promised a two <lb/> thirds elective House, with heads of department sitting
                  to give information without voting, <lb/> then I think the question of Responsible
                  Government would never have been considered. I <lb/> ask Hon. Members to endeavour
                  to approximate, and if they cannot agree to full Responsible <lb/> Government,
                  then to give us as liberal a form as they can. If you withhold Responsible <lb/>
                  Government you lose Confederation. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName>—Mr. Chairman, in rising to reply to what has
                  fallen from Hon. <lb/> gentlemen in opposition to Responsible Government, I crave
                  the kind indulgence of this House; <lb/> and should I, in the course of my
                  remarks, appear unduly harsh or unkind, I beg Hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men to
                  attribute it to earnestness in advocating a great cause, rather than to a desire
                  to wound <lb/> the feelings of any. The Hon. Member for Cariboo, who is also a
                  Member of the Executive, <lb/> made a very convenient, yet, to my mind, singularly
                  ineffective, reply to one point in my <lb/> speech of Friday. I had, or fancied I
                  had, with considerable force and elaborateness, pointed <lb/> out the difficulties
                  that might naturally be presumed to lie in the way of obtaining Responsible <lb/>
                  Government under the new constitution proposed to be conferred upon this Colony;
                  and the <lb/> only answer is that the Organic Act makes the necessary provision. 1
                  was as well aware of <lb/> the provision made in that Act before the Hon gentleman
                  spoke as after; but no attempt has <lb/> been made to meet the difficulties I
                  suggested. The Hon. gentleman, with that facetiousness, <lb/> poetry and ready wit
                  for which he is so justly celebrated, proceeded to point out the undesir<lb break="no"/>ableness of Responsible Government in this Colony. Under it, he
                  told us, Cabinets would be <lb/> too versatile. In fact, he described the working
                  of such institutions as a sort of dissolving <lb/> views, a thimble-rigging
                  operation, "now you see it, now you don't," in such quick succession <lb/> would
                  the changes be rung. The Chief Commissioner would, it appeared from his
                  description, <lb/> be much like Lincoln's celebrated flea. Now, Sir, where did the
                  Hon. gentleman acquire his <lb/> experience of the working of Responsible
                  Government? Was it not in Canada? What do <lb/> we find to be the experience of
                  that country? Certainly it does not in any way warrant the <lb/> conclusions
                  arrived at by my Hon. friend. On the contrary, we find a change of Ministry to
                  <lb/> be of very rare occurrence. The present Premier of Canada has, with one.
                  unimportant inter<lb break="no"/>mission, been at the head of the Government for
                  some twelve or fourteen years! As I stated <lb/> on a former occasion, the people
                  of British Columbia are not politicians, nor are they fond of <lb/> change. They
                  are naturally conservative. Give them a people's Government, and in no part <lb/>
                  of her Majesty's Colonial Empire will a less versatile, a more conservative and
                  loyal people be <lb/> found. The Honourable gentleman said Responsible Government
                  would blow the chaff into this <lb/> House. Now, although I listened with
                  pleasure, as I always do, to that gentleman's oratory and <lb/> humour. I could
                  not but experience a feeling of regret to find him on the wrong side of a great
                  <lb/> question, taking a false step. It is sad to witness the early mistakes of a
                  young man of such <lb/> talents, ambition, and promise; and when I hear such words
                  coming from my Hon. friend, I begin <lb/> to fear that the bright future, the
                  brilliant political career I had marked out for him may never <lb/> be realized.
                  Sir, a certain proportion of chaff may be blown into this House, under Respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government, as is the case now; but, depend upon it, under
                  the form of government we <lb/> seek, the chaff would quickly be blown out at the
                  back door, before the breath of public opinion. <lb/> The people can always
                  discriminate between wheat and chaff, and Responsible Government <lb/> supplies
                  the most effective winnowing-fan with which to separate the two. We were reminded
                  <lb/> by that Hon. gentleman that Responsible Govarmncnt had its failures as well
                  as its successes; <lb/> and he referred to Victoria, Australia, and to Jamaica, as
                  instances of failure. Now, I cannot <lb/> but think the Hon. gentleman has been
                  singularly unfortunate in going to these Colonies to <lb/> prove his proposition.
                  The former ranks amongst the most flourishing, progressive, and <lb/> wealthy of
                  all Her Majesty's Colonial possessions. Doubtless very grave political
                  difficulties <lb/>
                  <pb n="124" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_124.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">124</fw>                                                          
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> 
were encountered, and many mistakes characterized
                  the earlier working of Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in that fine Colony
                  ; but it would be most unfair to charge all these to the possession of <lb/> such
                  institutions. Nay, most of them had their origin in a different political system.
                  As for <lb/> Jamaica, Hon. gentlemen must be aware that it never possessed
                  Responsible Government. A <lb/> mixed representative system it had ; and the chief
                  cause of failure was the absence of responsi<lb break="no"/>bility. It was just
                  because those who administered the affairs of that unfortunate Colony were <lb/>
                  not responsible to the people that the opposition, led by the ill-fated Gordon—a
                  man of <lb/> unquestionable ability, although, perhaps, somewhat deficient in
                  judgment—was induced finally <lb/> to assume the extreme attitude which resulted
                  so fatally. The Hon. and learned Attorney- <lb break="yes"/> General made an
                  effort, not altogether warranted by facts, to force the advocates of Responsible
                  <lb/> Government into a false and disadvantageous position, in relation to the
                  Government pro<lb break="no"/>gramme ; but Hon. gentlemen will recollect how
                  anxious I was, at the beginning of this debate, <lb/> to meet the views and adopt
                  the suggestions of that Hon. and learned gentleman, in respect to <lb/> the
                  particular time and mode of approaching this question. My desire to give the
                  Government <lb/> a general and strong support upon the great question of
                  Confederation is no secret in this <lb/> House; and I think I can speak with equal
                  confidence in regard to the views and intentions <lb/> of my Hon. friend on my
                  left (the Member for Yale). But enough has already been said upon <lb/> this point
                  ; and I have only to add that I utterly refuse to occupy the position in which the
                  <lb/> Hon. and learned Attorney-General appears desirous of placing me. That Hon,
                  gentleman <lb/> was content to give the same answer to the main objection as that
                  given all round the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment end of the table, viz. that the
                  Organic Act provides the necessary and ready means of <lb/> obtaining what we
                  seek; and he further tells us that, inasmuch as Responsible Government <lb/>
                  relieves Governors of responsibility, a Governor would naturally be ready to make
                  the conces<lb break="no"/>sion. Such, however, is not the accustomed working of
                  human nature. Such is not the lesson <lb/> of history. The ruler hugs power as the
                  miser does his gold, nor parts with it only as it is <lb/> extorted piecemeal by
                  the people. I am charged with having used threats—threats of blood! <lb/> Now,
                  Sir, I must plead " not guilty" to this charge, While carefully avoiding
                  everything in <lb/> the nature of threat and prediction, I asked the Government to
                  read carefully those lessons <lb/> written in blood around us, and implored them
                  to take warning from the errors and profit by <lb/> the successes of others. We
                  were told by the Hon. and learned Attorney-General that the <lb/> Governor is
                  powerless to grant what the Resolution asks; but might not the same objection be
                  <lb/> raised to almost every recommendation passed in connection with
                  Confederation? His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency in asking Her Majesty's Government
                  for power to give us a new Constitution. The <lb/> Resolution merely suggests a
                  more liberal Constitution than His Excellency proposes. There <lb/> is therefore,
                  no weight in this objection. The Honourable gentleman next tells us that the <lb/>
                  Resolution implies want of confidence in the Canadian Government ; that they will
                  not listen <lb/> to the cry ot the people for Responsible Government. Now, the
                  Hon. gentleman must be <lb/> aware that Canada can only listen to our cry when it
                  is heard in the particular form prescribed <lb/> by the Constitution. The people
                  can only cry through the Government it is proposed to give <lb/> them under the
                  Constitution foreshadowed in His Excellency's opening message ; and I have <lb/>
                  already endeavoured to point out the probability that the new Government might
                  refuse to <lb/> utter a cry in that direction at the desire of the people. There
                  is no such expression of want <lb/> of confidence in the resolution. The Canadian
                  Government could not interfere—would have <lb/> no power to give us Responsible
                  Government—until asked by our Local Government to do so. <lb/> Such objections I
                  must, therefore, regard as frivolous, and utterly unworthy of the Hon. and <lb/>
                  learned Attorney-General. The Hon. Chief Commisioner followed with his accustomed
                  ability, <lb/> but, I venture to think, without his usual discretion, That Hon.
                  gentleman set out by telling <lb/> us that he quite understood it to be necessary
                  for certain members, in order to be consistent <lb/> with pen and speech outside
                  of this House, to bring forward this subject; that it was a logical <lb/>
                  necessity, inexorable fate. Now, Sir, I cannot see into that Hon, gentleman's
                  heart, any more <lb/> than I can into the mysterious Executive Chamber. l will
                  not, therefore, permit myself to <lb/> impute motives to that Hon. gentleman in
                  his opposition to Responsible Government; but he <lb/> must permit me to be the
                  best judge of those motives which have impelled me, with some <lb/> degree of
                  reluctance, to take a stand in opposition to the Government upon this question. lt
                  <lb/> may appear necessary, in order to be consistent with word and pen, that I
                  should advocate in <lb/> this House great principles which I have advocated
                  elsewhere; but it may be permitted me to <lb/> say that, whether here or
                  elsewhere, I advocate Responsible Government under Confederation, <lb/>
                  <pb n="125" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_125.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">125</fw> because I conceive it not only to be the right of the
                  people. but their interest also. We are <lb/> constantly told that we should not
                  have mixed this question up with the terms. We have not <lb/> mixed it up with the
                  terms; but the Government has mixed the terms up with it; and if there <lb/> is
                  any blame, any responsibility in this connection. it mus rest with the Government,
                  and not <lb/> with the Opposition The Hon. gentleman tells us that it is
                  impossible to work Responsible <lb/> Government with a population so scattered;
                  and in the same breath he tells us that we have <lb/> Responsible Government
                  now,—that the officials are responsible to the Governor, and he to the <lb/>
                  Queen. Well, certainly. this is a sort of responsibility; but it is not precisely
                  the kind we want. <lb/> The responsibility now existing takes the wrong direction.
                  It is not responsibility to the people, <lb/> but to the supreme power. In this
                  sense the most despotic form of government in the world <lb/> may be termed
                  Responsible Government. The members of the Government of the Czar of <lb/> Russia
                  are responsible to him, and he is responsible to the Great Ruler of all; ergo,
                  Russia has <lb/> Responsible Government! The Hon. gentleman must see the absurdity
                  of his startling propo<lb break="no"/>sition. Ile next tells us that if the people
                  desire Responsible Government it is because they <lb/> have been educated up to it
                  by the press. There is more truth than argument in this. Doubt<lb break="no"/>less
                  the press is in this, as in other civilized countries. the great educator of the
                  people, especially <lb/> in matters political. Have not the people of England been
                  similarly educated up to every great <lb/> political reform? Such constitutes a
                  legitimate and important function of the press. But the <lb/> honourable gentleman
                  goes further and tells us that if the present Government is unpopular <lb/> with
                  the people the responsibility resls with the press. which has by misrepresentation
                  created <lb/> prejudice in the public mind. This proposition I beg most.
                  unqualifiedly to deny. The honour<lb break="no"/>able gentleman has confounded
                  cause and effect. The press has opposed the Government because <lb/> it is
                  unpopular; and the Government is unpopular because it is not. a people's
                  Government— <lb/> because it does not possess the principle of responsibility to
                  the people. it must be remembered <lb/> that the press subsists on popular favour;
                  and in order lo subsist it must oppose an unpopular <lb/> form of Government. The
                  press of this Colony has acted rather as the exponent than the <lb/> moulder and
                  leader of public opinion in its opposition to the present form of Government. As
                  <lb/> I have repeatedly said, it is not the officials that are unpopular. so much
                  as the system under <lb/> which th administer. No officials can be popular under
                  such a system. it places them in <lb/> a false position. The press is, therefore,
                  not to blame; it is the faithful exponent of public <lb/> opinion. The honourable
                  gentleman on my left [<persName ref="pers:HOLB1">MR. Holbrook</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName></supplied> dissents from this view. It is <lb/> the habit
                  of some honourable gentlemen to affect to sneer at the press 0t this Colony. They
                  <lb/> admit that the pre s of England is all I claim for it; but they allude
                  sneeringly to the press <lb/> of this Colony. Now, I am free to admit that the
                  leading journal of this Colony would lose <lb/> by a comparison with the leading
                  journal of England. It is smaller, and, perhaps, less ability <lb/> is displayed
                  in its editorial columns. But would not such a comparison be unfair? Apply this
                  <lb/> rule to other institutions of the Colony and what would be the result?
                  Taking the press of <lb/> this Colony with all its imperfections, and l boldly
                  assert that it will compare favourably with <lb/> that of any other country of
                  like age and population. That is the way to institute the com<lb break="no"/>parison; and it is the only true way. When I hear honourable gentlemen indulging
                  in sneers <lb/> at the press invariably all ye at one conclusion: and I will not
                  tell you what that conclusion <lb/> is. It will not be necessary for me to again
                  allude to the improper use made of what I said <lb/> about the hornv-hunded class,
                  especially as the Hon. Mr. Walkem fully vindicated me. One more <lb/> point and I
                  have done with the honourable the Chief Commissioner. That gentleman repeated
                  <lb/> the now stereotyped argument that the Dominion Govormnent. being based on
                  liberal institu<lb break="no"/>tions. would not withhold Responsible Government if
                  desired by the people of: British Columbia. <lb/> That argument has been so often
                  met that I was surprised to hear it repeated by that honour<lb break="no"/>able
                  gentleman. Need I say. for the twentieth time, that it is not the prerogative of
                  the <lb/> Canadian Government to give, unless asked by our local Government. and
                  that our local Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will, from its organic nature, be averse
                  to ask anything of the hind? Surely I am entitled <lb/> to regard the constant
                  iteration of those exploded arguments as evidence of the weakness of <lb/> the
                  Government cause. Passing to the specch of the Honourable Mr. Walkem, my task is
                  an <lb/> easy one; for although that honourable gentleman spoke. with his
                  accustomed eloquence and <lb/> agreeable in of word and manner. all must have felt
                  lhat his effort had about it an air of <lb/> special pleading in a bad can. The
                  principal objection that gentleman brought against the <lb/> position 1 took on
                  Friday was, that Responsible Government is not a principle, but a form. <lb/> Now,
                  I think it may be regarded as either or both, and I am not disposed to quarrel
                  about mere <lb/>
                  <pb n="126" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_126.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">126</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> words. What I contend for is
                  Responsible Government. That honourable gentleman tells us <lb/> that Canada did
                  not get Responsible Government till her population reached about two millions.
                  <lb/> Now, while that gentleman is greatly astray in his figures, I cannot
                  discover in his facts any <lb/> evidence in support of the proposition he wishes
                  to establish They may prove that Responsible <lb/> Government was long wrongfully
                  withheld from Canada. I now come to my honourable friend <lb/> the senior member
                  for Victoria City. That honourable gentleman started out by telling us <lb/> that
                  he intended to support the Government scheme, and to support it strongly; but he
                  added <lb/> that he would not say much about Responsible Govermnent. Would that he
                  had adhered to <lb/> the latter resolution. It was but natural that, feeling
                  himself on the wrong side of a great <lb/> principle, he should be disposed to say
                  little. But, unfortunately for himself, he has said much, <lb/> a great deal too
                  much. He said some things which it would have been much better to have left <lb/>
                  unsaid. He told us that Government for, by, and from the people means Government
                  for, by, <lb/> and with the politicians. But he does not stop there. He tells this
                  House that the advocates <lb/> of Responsible Government will he willing to
                  surrender all the other conditions in order to <lb/> obtain that form of
                  Government as a means of securing office, power, pickings! Now, Sir, let <lb/> us
                  look at the political history, and position of the honourable gentleman who
                  presumes, with <lb/> so much boldness, to judge of other people's motives I
                  recollect when, some two years ago, <lb/> that honourable gentleman was the most
                  ardent of all Confederationists; when he desired to <lb/> rush into an
                  unconditional and blind union; when he urged the then Governor to negotiate union
                  <lb/> by telegraph, At that time I was doubtful about the policy of <hi rendition="simple:italic">immediate</hi> union, regarding such   <lb/> a step
                  as somewhat premature and unreal, so long as the immense intervening territory
                  remained <lb/> an unorganized and unopen waste. Holding these views I proposed to
                  strike the word 'imme<lb break="no"/>diate' out of the resolution which had been
                  moved by the Honourable Mr. DeCosmos; but so <lb/> enthusiastic, so fanatical. was
                  the honourable the senior member for Victoria City that he <lb/> longed for' a
                  stronger word than 'immediate.' Subsequently we saw that honourable gentleman
                  <lb/> the most ultra, the most rabid Anti-Confederate. We saw him opposing it in
                  every way, both <lb/> in the House and out of it, denouncing Canada as a most
                  undesirable connection. Now, what <lb/> do we see? We see the Anti-Confederate
                  Lion rampant suddenly metamorphosed into the <lb/> Canadian Lamb passant. with his
                  longing eyes fixed on Ottawa! Such has been the magic <lb/> influence of the
                  mysterious Executive Chamber. I do not, for one, regret the transformation; <lb/>
                  but I do object to that gentleman turning round so suddenly and denouncing the
                  motives by <lb/> which others are actuated. Does not that honourable gentleman
                  live in a 'glass house' in <lb/> that sense which peculiarly disentitles him to
                  throw stones? Is not he guilty of measuring <lb/> other people's corn in his own
                  bushel? Did not be cast all his political principles to the winds <lb/> and bolt
                  in at the very first opening to place and power that presented itself? And who
                  knows <lb/> but there may be at this moment a mission to Ottawa dangling
                  temptingly before his eager <lb/> eyes? ls this the man who is entitled to turn
                  round and, looking down from his pinnacle of <lb/> temporary power, judge others?
                  strutting his hour of brief authority, he taunts us with seek<lb break="no"/>ing
                  Responsible Government as a stepping-stone to power and pickings. I hurl back,
                  with scorn <lb/> and contempt, the accusation in his teeth! To pass, however, to
                  the so-called arguments put <lb/> forward by that honourable gentleman. he tells
                  us that the resolution asks for a Government <lb/> like that of Ontario,—that we
                  should require 40 or 30 members. Now. Sir, it is difficult to give <lb/> him
                  credit (or sincerity, as ever honourable member must see that the resolution asks
                  nothing <lb/> of the kind. It asks fo' a constitution based upon the principle of
                  Responsible Government as <lb/> existing in Ontario. That honourable gentleman has
                  attempted to make me inconsistent with <lb/> myself in saying that we shall be
                  under the heel of Canada without Responsible Government, <lb/> and that Canada
                  desires that we should have such institutions. Now, I see nothing inconsistent
                  <lb/> in this. Canada does desire that the people of British Columbia should
                  possess as full powers <lb/> of managing their own local affairs as the people of
                  the other Provinces possess; but Canada <lb/> will have no power to grant these
                  institutions until asked to do so in a constitutional way <lb/> through and by our
                  Local Govermnent; and the weight of my objection lies in the reasonable <lb/>
                  belief that, however desirous the people may be, the Local Government will be
                  naturally averse <lb/> to a change calculated to lessen its power, and weaken the
                  tenure by which its members hold <lb/> office. Again, we are told that the
                  Governor would not be disposed to withhold institutions <lb/> which would relieve
                  him of responsibility. However plausible this proposition may appear in <lb/>
                  theory, it is scarcely borne out by experience. As I have already stated, in reply
                  to the honour<lb break="no"/>able and learned Attorney-General, history presents
                  rulers in a different light. We are asked <lb/>
                  <pb n="127" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_127.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>                                    
                   <fw type="num">127</fw> 
what measures of importance have been introduced that have not been
                  introduced by the <lb/> Government? By this the honourable gentleman wishes, I
                  presume, to convey the idea that <lb/> the Government so fully meets the wants of
                  the people as to leave nothing for representative <lb/> members to do. In what
                  singular contrast is this with his utterances during past sessions. <lb/> Here,
                  again, we have the kindly bleating of the docile Confederation Lamb, instead of
                  the <lb/> terrific roar of the Anti-Confederate Lion of the past. Verily, the
                  mysterious influences of the <lb/> Executive Chamber must be potent. The
                  honourable gentleman tells us that if we couple the <lb/> question of Responsible
                  Government with the conditions of union, the people will be willing <lb/> to
                  accept poorer terms in their eagerness to obtain it. Surely, if language means
                  anything, this <lb/> is an inadvertent admission of what the honourable gentleman
                  has been so stoutly denying, <lb/> viz. : that the people desire Responsible
                  Govermnent. Leaving the honourable gentleman to <lb/> the lashings of his own
                  conscience, and to the seductive influences of the mysterious Executive <lb/>
                  Chamber, we next come to deal with the Honourable the Registrar of Titles. The
                  Honourable <lb/> Mr. Alston announces himself in favour of Responsible Government,
                  but not the kind that would <lb/> make the heads of Departments go in and out. He
                  holds all Representative Government to <lb/> be Responsible Government. The
                  honourable gentleman may be entitled to hold a theory pecu<lb break="no"/>liarly
                  his own ; but it is scarcely the fitting time to announce personal theories. We
                  are now <lb/> dealing with the question of Responsible Government, as understood
                  by political economists, not <lb/> as understood by the honourable gentleman who
                  has just propounded a political paradox. He <lb/> has been reading John Stuart
                  Mill, and he tells us that writer never mentions Responsible <lb/> Government. I
                  have not read Mill's theory, but I have read enough to know that he goes even
                  <lb/> further than I am prepared to go in the direction of responsibility. We have
                  next the honour<lb break="no"/>able gentleman for Kootenay telling this House that
                  with all his experience in the Colony he <lb/> never heard a man express a desire
                  for Responsible Government, and that his own constituents <lb/> were distinctly
                  opposed to it. Now, so far as that honourable gentleman's constituents are con<lb break="no"/>cerned, I am prepared to think that his opportunities of learning
                  their views upon that or any <lb/> other subject have scarcely been such as to
                  entitle him to express a very positive opinion; but <lb/> when he tells this House
                  that in all his experience in this Colony he has never heard a desire <lb/> for
                  Responsible Government expressed, I can only say that I am surprised. The
                  honourable <lb/> gentleman cannot but know, if he has not turned a deaf ear to
                  politics altogether, that the <lb/> question of Responsible Government has been a
                  prominent issue at more than one election, <lb/> and that it has been used as one
                  of the chief reasons for Confederation from one end of the <lb/> Colony to the
                  other. But, Sir, I fear I have already wearied the House. Permit me to say, <lb/>
                  however, that throughout this protracted debate the efforts on the Government side
                  of the <lb/> House have been characterized by a want of argument, and by a sort of
                  special pleading, a <lb/> begging of the question almost painful to listen to.
                  Every effort has been made to raise false <lb/> issues and to misconstrue remarks
                  coming from this side of the House, and a most unfair <lb/> attempt has been made
                  to, place the whole question in a false and disadvantageous position; <lb/> yet
                  this is scarcely surprising. It was not to be expected that the unrepresentative
                  members <lb/> would approve the measure I feel, however, quite inditterent about
                  their votes. We have a <lb/> large majority of the representative members with us,
                  and their vote must virtually carry the <lb/> measure. The great proposition I
                  desire to impress upon honourable members is this: The <lb/> Colony is about to
                  become a Province of the Dominion of Canada. No union can be equitable <lb/> and
                  just which does not give this Colony equal political power—equal control over
                  their own <lb/> local affairs with that possessed by the people at the Provinces
                  with which it is proposed to <lb/> unite. I care not how good the other conditions
                  may be: it the people of British Columbia are <lb/> placed in a false political
                  position they will not be content. and the inauguration of such a <lb/> union will
                  only prove the beginning of new political discontent and agitation. Mistakes will
                  <lb/> doubtless result from the first workings of Responsible Government, but
                  these mistakes were <lb/> better made now than years hence, when the consequences
                  might be more serious The period <lb/> of lisping, stammering infancy must, be
                  passed. Surely it is better to pass it now. while the <lb/> political questions
                  are few and simple, and the interests comparatively small, than to wait for <lb/>
                  great development. Almost every speaker on the Government side has accused me of
                  want of <lb/> confidence in the Dominion Government. 1 have no want of confidence
                  in that Government. <lb/> I know the men who compose it too well for that. I know
                  them as honourable, liberal, large- <lb break="yes"/> minded statesmen. But it is
                  our Local Govermnent under the new Constitution. proposed in <lb/> terms so vague
                  in His Excellency's opening message, that I doubt. The Canadian Government <lb/>
                  <pb n="128" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_128.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">128</fw>                                                          
                                                                <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION
                     DEBATE.</fw> will possess no constitutional power to grant us political relief
                  until asked to do so by our <lb/> Local Government ; and it is the hesitation, the
                  disinclination of the Local Government to <lb/> move in that direction which I
                  dread. I would again warn the Government against endanger<lb break="no"/>ing the
                  whole scheme by having it submitted to the people unaccompanied by "Responsible
                  <lb/> Government." <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CARR1">Hon. DR. CARRALL</persName>—Sir, on Friday last the honourable member
                  for New Westminster <lb/> spoke at some length upon this subject, and I replied as
                  best I could, and it is in accordance <lb/> with the eternal fitness of things
                  that I should make a very few remarks. It is one of those <lb/> happy things in
                  nature that where the poison is there is the antidote always near. (Laughter.)
                  <lb/> I propose to give the antidote. I laid down two principles: First, that the
                  Government did <lb/> not believe that Responsible Government, as it is maintained
                  in England, was applicable to this <lb/> Colony. I hold to that. I maintain that
                  no one has controverted this proposition ; no one has <lb/> proved that it could
                  be adapted to the requirements of this Colony; there has been burning <lb/>
                  eloquence and all that sort of thing, but no proof. But I say, Sir, that even now
                  there is a <lb/> measure of responsibility in this Government. I am responsible to
                  my constituents, and if there <lb/> is such an overwhelming force in favour of
                  Responsible Government can I ever return here <lb/> The utmost that the honourable
                  member for New Westminster has proved is, that under Con<lb break="no"/>federation
                  it would take a great deal of time and much agitation to get Responsible
                  Government, <lb/> a minimum of five years and a maximum of ten years, and that as
                  it would take that time it <lb/> was better that we should have it at once. I say
                  if one proposition is correct the other must <lb/> be incorrect. If there is such
                  an overwhelming desire on the part of the people for it, they <lb/> will get it.
                  If the majority even are in favour of Responsible Government there is no con<lb break="no"/>stitutional power to prevent their getting it. There is' no desire
                  on the part of the Government <lb/> to withhold it. I say it is a want of
                  responsibility of the Executive that has rendered them <lb/> unpopular ; but the
                  people have never been asked to contrast the present form of Government <lb/> with
                  that shadowed out by His Excellency ; and I say that heads of Departments under
                  that <lb/> system will be, to a certain extent, responsible. The present system is
                  bad, but the officers are <lb/> good I say that the requirements of the Colony
                  will be met by the system proposed by His <lb/> Excellency. If it is not, then let
                  the people say so, and get Responsible Government. The <lb/> honourable member for
                  New Westminster allows that it is only a question of time under the <lb/> Organic
                  Act. If it should take five years, then my point that there is not such a strong
                  desire <lb/> for it is proved. I said, and I say again, that in Jamaica they could
                  not work Responsible <lb/> Government, or even representative institutions, and in
                  Victoria it remains to this day a <lb/> monument of stupidity and mismanagement.
                  With regard to the assertion of the honourable <lb/> member for New Westminster, I
                  say that if speaking and voting from conviction are false steps, <lb/> and a bar
                  to advancement in political life, then I don't want to advance a step-further in
                  that <lb/> direction. I say that Responsible Government has not been made a
                  distinct issue in elections. <lb/> The Government of the people was to be one of
                  the consequences of Confederation ; I hope we <lb/> shall get a people's
                  Government before it. The present Executive Council is one-third unofficial ;
                  <lb/> the work; they have done has brought a shapeless, formless phantom into one
                  harmonious whole, <lb/> and they propose to precede Confederation with a form of
                  Government which will enable the <lb/> people to decide what form of Government
                  they will have. I coincide with the Honourable <lb/> Chief Commissioner of Lands
                  and Works, that it was not necessary to introduce this subject <lb/> into the
                  Confederation Resolution. I am sorry that it was brought up at all in connection
                  with <lb/> our scheme. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName>—Sir, I wish to say in reply to the remarks
                  of the honourable member <lb/> for New Westminster, that I support the Government
                  from conviction. I do not shirk my respon<lb break="no"/>sibility. I said that the
                  one great thing the supporters of Responsible Government are afraid <lb/> of is,
                  that it shall he set alongside of Representative Government. Honourable members
                  may <lb/> find when the resolutions return from Canada that I have still something
                  to say upon them. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The recommendation of the Honourable Mr. Humphreys was put by the Chair, and on 
     <lb/>
     division was lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The recommendation of Honourable Mr. Robson was put by the Chair, and on division 
     <lb/>
     was lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Clause fifteen then passed  read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CREA1">The Honourable ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> introduced clause sixteen: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

           <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"> <p>
     "16. The provisions in 'The British North America Act, 1867,' shall (except those parts 
     <lb/>
     "thereof which are in terms made, or by reasonable intendment may be held to be specially 
     <lb/>
           

            <pb n="129" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_129.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">129</fw>
          

     "applicable to and only affect one, and not the whole, of the Provinces now comprising the 
     <lb/>
     "Dominion, and except so far as the same may be varied by this resolution) be applicable to 
     <lb/>
     "British Columbia in the same way, and to the like extent, as they apply to the other Provinces 
     <lb/>
     "of the Dominion, and as if the Colony of British Columbia had been one of the Provinces 
     <lb/>
     "originally united by the said Act." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Honourable Dr. Helmcken</persName> and <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Honourable Mr. Drake</persName> objected to this clause on the ground 
     <lb/>
     that its passing would kill the notices already on the paper. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CREA1">The Honourable ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> gave an assurance that the resolutions of which 
     <lb/>
     notice had been given should be discharged, and the opposition was withdrawn. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Clause sixteen passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "With reference to defences:- <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">A</hi>. That it shall be an understanding with the Dominion that their influence will be used 
     <lb/>
     "to the fullest extent to procure the continued maintenance of the Naval Station at Esquimalt. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "<hi rendition="simple:italic">B</hi>. Encouragement to be given to develop the efficiency and organization of the Volunteer 
     <lb/>
     "force in British Columbia." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     On clause <hi rendition="simple:italic">A</hi> being read by the Chairman, Honourable Mr. Holbrook objected to Esquimalt 
     <lb/>
     being named, on the ground that it was only fair to New Westminster that one gunboat should 
     <lb/>
     be stationed there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Honourable ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—I should have been very sorry to
                  have this clause <lb/> inserted if I thought it would give us only two or three
                  gunboats. <lb/>
               </p>

   <p><persName ref="pers:HANK1">Honourable COLONIAL SECRETARY</persName> (Mr. Hankin) —Because the Naval Station is
                  at <lb/> Esquimalt it does not follow that every ship will remain there. The
                  commanding officer can send <lb/> ships where he pleases. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Clause <hi rendition="simple:italic">A</hi> passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR.  HUMPHREYS</persName> asked what 'encouragement' meant in
                  clause <hi rendition="simple:italic">B</hi>. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName>—At present there is no means of
                  ascertaining What encour<lb break="no"/>agement can be given; I suppose arms and
                  money. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     Clause <hi rendition="simple:italic">B</hi> passed as read. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName>—Mr. Chairman, I gave notice of my intention
                  to bring up a clause <lb/> with regard to provision being made to protect the
                  agricultural produce of this Colony. It has <lb/> been said by the honourable
                  Executive Member for Victoria City that this differential tariff is <lb/> quite a
                  new thing to me. If he will take the trouble to refer to the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Colonist</hi> of the 15th May, <lb/> 1868, he will
                  find that in an article written by myself I touched on this matter; it is not new
                  to <lb/> me. I am thoroughly persuaded that the disti ct which I represent will be
                  a unit against Con<lb break="no"/>federation without a provision to keep up
                  protection. From Comox to Sooke the opinion on this <lb/> point is as that of one
                  man, and I believe I maysay that it is the same thing as regards the whole <lb/>
                  of the agricultural districts on the Mainland, from Soda Creek to Kamloops. I
                  hold, with respect <lb/> to protection, that when farmers shall be able to produce
                  farm produce in sufficient quantity to <lb/> enable them to reduce their prices as
                  low as the prices obtained by the farmers of Oregon and <lb/> Washington
                  Territory; then protection is not essential, for this great and sufficient reason
                  that if <lb/> we can produce as good an article at home as we can get abroad,
                  which we can put down at the <lb/> same price, the cost of transport will be a
                  sufficient protection. Our farmers will have a natural <lb/> protection. With
                  regard to manufactures, I am one of those who believe that our manufactures <lb/>
                  ought to be protected. If we go into public works we must have waggons and
                  machinery, and the <lb/> waggon-builders should have protection; then, again,
                  farming implements should be made in the <lb/> Colony, and encouragement should be
                  given to the manufacturer of these things. Again, there are <lb/> the bootmaker
                  and tailor, and the soapmaker and others, even the brewer, for whom we require
                  <lb/> protection. I ask from the Executive the insertion of this principle: "That
                  British Columbia <lb/> shall be entitled to levy and collect any tax, or taxes, on
                  the sales of foreign produce and <lb/> manufactures entered for home consumption
                  equal in amount to the duties of Customs now <lb/> levied and collected on the
                  same under the 'Customs Ordinance, 1867,' provided, always, that <lb/> British
                  Columbia shall not be entitled to levy and collect any such tax, or taxes, as
                  aforesaid, <lb/> if the duties of Customs of Canada extended and applied to
                  British Columbia at the time of and <lb/> after Union on such foreign produce and
                  manufactures shall be as high as the duties of <lb/> Customs now levied and
                  collected on the same under the 'Customs Ordinance, 1867,' and <lb/> provided
                  always, that such foreign produce and manufactures shall be construed to mean no
                  <lb/> more and none other than such foreign produce and manufactures as may enter
                  into competition <lb/>
                  <pb n="130" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_130.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">130</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> with the produce and manufactures of
                  British Columbia." I don't care how it is put in, our <lb/> manufactures would
                  come into competition with goods from Canada. That is a natural evil <lb/> which
                  we cannot avoid. There will be other advantages arising out of Confederation which
                  will <lb/> counterbalance this. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I have nothing to do with the honourable
                  gentleman's newspaper <lb/> articles. I can only say that differential duties are
                  contrary to the views of Her Majesty's <lb/> Government. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName> — The honourable member's explanation is
                  different from the clause itself. <lb/> I suppose from the explanation that it is
                  intended to apply to all foreign produce and manufactures <lb/> tin-es imported. I
                  think it will be better that I should move my motion as an amendment to <lb/> his,
                  so as to confine the protection to agricultural produce. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> — I don't expect any resolution of mine to
                  pass. If it should pass I <lb/> shall be quite surprised ; but as I hold this to
                  be the very keystone, and of more consequence than <lb/> Responsible Government, I
                  deem it my duty to bring it forward. But to confine the protection <lb/>to
                  agricultural produce will not reach the issue. it would not touch our rude
                  manufactures. <lb/>
               </p>

    

    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —This is left an open question by the
                  Government. I wish it to <lb/> be distinctly understood that this question of the
                  agriculture of the country is an open question. <lb/> I think I shall be found on
                  the side of these honourable gentlemen. I think with the honourable <lb/> member
                  for Victoria District that this is the most important question comprised in these
                     resolu<lb break="no"/>tions. If the terms do not contain a clause giving
                  protection to agricultural interests, I will <lb/> answer for it there will he no
                  Confederation. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —I would ask the honourable member to
                  define how far <lb/> this is left an open question? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —I mean that every member of the Government
                  is free to vote as <lb/> he pleases upon this question of encouragement to the
                  agricultural interests of the Colony. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. MR. WOOD</persName> —Then it is free for official members to vote
                  these recommendations? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —Certainly it is, and it is right that it
                  should be so ; for I consider, <lb/> Sir, that we have come to a most important
                  question, one that concerns our own country. Con<lb break="no"/>federation must
                  not come like an eclipse, it must not produce a darkness and then leave us to
                  <lb/> recover. I say that if these terms are left to pass as they are, and return
                  from Canada, and are <lb/> passed by the people, they will produce great ills. I
                  say that the agricultural interests are most <lb/> important ; when we come to
                  manufacturing interests it is different, they have made but little <lb/> progress.
                  Manufacturers will meet with competition from Canada, and the Dominion would not
                  <lb/> stand it ; we cannot have protection for manufactures but with regard to
                  farm produce it is <lb/> different. I say that the farmers could not exist without
                  protection ; you will depopulate the <lb/> country by bringing Confederation
                  without protection. I have stated that this Colony affords <lb/> more inducement
                  to people to settle than any other Colony I know of ; yet we do not raise <lb/>
                  sufficient stock for ourselves. Look at the statistics: $111,447 is the value of
                  agricultural pro<lb break="no"/>duce—barley. flour, malt, wheat, and
                  oats—imported. Of barley. there is nearly one million <lb/> pounds imported, and
                  this would take about 450 acres to grow in ; of malt about 4,500 bushels, which
                  <lb/> would require ninety acres to grow in ; of flour and wheat about 87.000
                  bushels. which would <lb/> require about 2,500 acres to grow in ; of oats, about
                  2.364 bushels, which would require about sixty <lb/> acres to grow in ; altogether
                  about 3.080 acres. More land must be in cultivation to produce the <lb/> quantity
                  of cereals which I have enumerated as being imported annually. and this number of
                  <lb/> acres, supposing a man to cultivate fifty acres, would give employment to
                  123 men ; so that 123 <lb/> men will save the Colony $111,447, or $900 each,
                  besides growing what they want for their <lb/> own consumption. In relation to
                  this it must be recollected that mills would be at work to grind, <lb/> machinery
                  would be required, and labour of other kinds would he required. such, for
                  instance, as <lb/> brewers. In addition to this comes in pigs. There were 508 of
                  these animals imported last year ; <lb/> less by 28 than in the preceding year.
                  This is on improvement, when we consider that the amount <lb/> of bacon and hams
                  imported is 61.740 pounds less than last year. To make this bacon about 500 <lb/>
                  hogs are required ; so you will see that nearly the whole amount of bacon is made
                  by and from <lb/> foreign hogs. Take butter—82.000 pounds, or forty tons, were
                  imported last year. It will take <lb/> 400 more cows, yielding 200 pounds each per
                  annum, to produce this amount, and it would save the <lb/> Colony $31.588 per
                  annum. One thousand seven hundred head of beef cattle would save annually <lb/>
                  $96,949 but it repurposes 6,800 more cows at least. Now, then. to supply ourselves
                  with beef <lb/> and mutton, and cheese, 8,000 more cows are required ; but it
                  takes four years to produce beef. <lb/> We import 7,000 sheep. Surely no one will
                  tell us that we have no room for 7,000 sheep or <lb/>
                  <pb n="131" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-22_Page_131.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">131</fw> 3,000 cows. Why, it only means 20,000 acres, or thirty-six
                  miles of land; six miles will supply <lb/> the cereals—thirty-six miles in all.
                  Why, the flats at the Fraser would yield it all. The cattle <lb/> business
                  certainly requires capital, but the capital will produce great results, and
                  recollect the good <lb/> it would do the country, the amount of labour employed
                  and land cultn ted for the purpose; wool, <lb/> hides, and bones for house use or
                  export. What I wish to impress upon you, Sir, is the profit <lb/> that might be
                  derived from the introduction of a couple of hundred families. What an immense
                  <lb/> loss the Colony would sustain if this were thrown open to the Americans.
                  What a magnificent <lb/> field for immigration, particularly when we consider how
                  much more of agricultural produce will <lb/> he required when public works are
                  carried on. The market is good now; how much better it <lb/> would he then. I
                  think it would be doing those farmers who had commenced farming under a <lb/>
                  protective tariff a great injustice to withdraw protection from them now. We must
                  have an <lb/> agricultural population. It Confederation comes, and brings the
                  Canadian tariff, we destroy the <lb/> agricultural interests altogether, and the
                  country will become a wilderness. Confederation with<lb break="no"/>out those
                  terms will not, in my opinion, be accepted. Leave them out and Confederation will
                  <lb/> most assuredly fail . Farmers in the Upper Country have a natural protection
                  from the difficulty of <lb/> transport. The day will come, and pretty quickly,
                  when they will raise more there than they have <lb/> a market for. They must find
                  an outlet, which must be where the consumers are. If the duty <lb/> is not
                  maintained, how can they send their produce down? If the railway should be built,
                  the <lb/> cost of transporting goods from the interior will be diminished. and
                  farms of the Upper Country <lb/> will then find the tariff of more consequence to
                  them than to the people of the Lower Country. <lb/> I say Confederation will not
                  go down without protection. The agricultural interest will prefer <lb/> living in
                  comfort with protection. and without Confederation, than in a perpetual struggle
                  for <lb/> livelihood under Confederation. I am in favour of protecting our farming
                  interests; but if we <lb/> had a lower scale upon some other goods I should think
                  it an advantage. I support protection <lb/> to the agricultural interest, and the
                  throwing open of our ports to other things. The latter part <lb/> is, I fear, not
                  an open question. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HAML1">COMMISSIONER OF Customes</persName>—(Mr. Hamley) —It is difficult to
                  tell which resolu<lb break="no"/>tion the Hon. Member is speaking in favour of. It
                  is quite true that protection may he too <lb/> little on some things and too much
                  on others; for instance. I consider the duty on horses too <lb/> high. I will tell
                  Hon. gentlemen that a revision of the tariff was considered last year by a <lb/>
                  Committee appointed by the late Governor, and a majority of that Committee, who
                  were all <lb/> business men. reported in favour of lowering the duties on
                  agricultural produce, and there was <lb/> a special report in favour of making
                  Victoria almost a free port. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. Mr. DeCosmos</persName> that was the bogus Council, I suppose. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HAML1">Hon. MR. HAMLEY</persName> —They were a Committee of gentlemen whom the
                  late Governor thought <lb/> fit to appoint. I think the tariff must be altered to
                  suit this Colony but I believe it must he left <lb/> to the Canadian Parliament to
                  alter. What will our representat members do sitting in the <lb/> Canadian
                  Parliament, except they look after our interests? There is no obstacle that I know
                  <lb/> of to there being a diiferont tariff to suit the interests of this or any
                  particular Province of the <lb/> Dominion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK</persName> is no reason that there should he a similar
                  tariff all over, <lb/> but I think it must be altered by the Canadian Parliament.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName>—I do not think that it is necessary that
                  one tariff should prevail all over the Dominion <lb/> over the Dominion. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HAML1">Hon. Mr. Hamley</persName>— Not at all, not at all. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN</persName> —But there can be no differential duties;
                  that is forbidden by English <lb/> statutes. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HAML1">Hon. MR. HAMLEY</persName>—No; not by statute; in nstructions. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName>— So far from leaving it to the Canadian
                  Parliament, I say we <lb/> must go in with it altered. How absurd for eight
                  members to attempt to revise the tariff of <lb/> British Columbia in the Dominion
                  Parliament. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. MR. TRUTCH</persName> don't see it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HAML1">Hon. Mr. HAMLEY</persName>— Nor do I. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. DR. HELMCKEN</persName> —Why. look how ridiculous it is to come to
                  this House to propose <lb/> any alteration in the tariff. How much more so in the
                  Dominion Parliament. where so many <lb/> would be on the other side? If at all, it
                  must he done. by ourselves. The Canadian Government <lb/> must agree to it before
                  we go into Confederation. The other interests are subsidiary to it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     On motion of <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. Mr. Ring</persName>, the debate was adjourned to Wednesday, the 23rd. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>