<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="lgBCLC_1870-03-10" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgBCLC">British Columbia Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1870-03-10">10 March 1870</date>, Province of BC, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         
<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 19<date when="2016-01-07"/></resp>
   <persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 20<date when="2016-01-25"/></resp>
   <persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 21<date when="2016-01-25"/></resp>
   <persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 22<date when="2016-01-25"/></resp>
   <persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 23<date when="2016-01-25"/></resp>
   <persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 24<date when="2016-01-25"/></resp>
   <persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 25<date when="2016-03-16"/></resp>
   <persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 26<date when="2016-03-16"/></resp>
   <persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 27<date when="2016-03-16"/></resp>
   <persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 28<date when="2016-03-16"/></resp>
   <persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 29<date when="2016-03-16"/></resp>
   <persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 30<date when="2016-04-28"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 31<date when="2016-04-28"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 32<date when="2016-04-28"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 33<date when="2016-04-28"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 34<date when="2016-04-28"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 35<date when="2016-04-28"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 36<date when="2016-04-28"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 37<date when="2016-04-29"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>

<respStmt>
<resp>Proofing/correction p. 38<date when="2016-04-29"/></resp>
<persName>Lauren Chancellor</persName>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgBCLC">
          

          <editor>W.S. Sebright Green</editor>
          
         
               <title>Legislative Council, Debate on the Subject of Confederation with Canada</title>.
                    

          <date when="1912"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Victoria, B.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>William H. Cullin</publisher>.
                    

          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="19" to="38"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_019.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_020.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_021.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_022.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_023.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_024.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_025.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_026.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_027.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_028.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_029.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_030.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_031.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_032.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_033.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_034.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_035.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_036.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_037.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_038.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-14">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-21">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_019">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_019.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_020">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_020.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_021">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_021.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_022">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_022.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_023">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_023.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_024">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_024.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_025">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_025.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_026">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_026.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_027">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_027.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_028">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_028.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_029">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_029.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_030">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_030.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_031">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_031.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_032">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_032.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_033">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_033.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_034">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_034.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_035">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_035.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_036">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_036.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_037">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_037.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_038">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_038.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="19" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_019.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">19</fw>
            
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               THURSDAY, 10TH MARCH, 1870. 
            </head>
            
         
      
            <p> The debate was resumed by the <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. Mr. TRUTCH</persName>, Chief
                  Commissioner of Lands and <lb/> Works, who said:—Mr. President, in rising to renew
                  the debate on the question which has <lb/> been brought before the House by the
                  Honourable the Attorney―General. I desire to express <lb/> my regret that I was
                  prevented yesterday, by indisposition, from speaking in support of the <lb/>
                  motion which I had the honour to second, because I fear that by the delay I may
                  have laid <lb/> myself open to the charge of waiting to reply to objections that
                  might be urged against this <lb/> motion, instead of at once supporting it upon
                  positive and substantial grounds, as I hold it to <lb/> be incumbent on those to
                  do who advocate so important a measure. I must also ask the <lb/> indulgence of
                  the House if I find it necessary to follow the Honourable the Attorney-General
                  over <lb/> ground already so fully and ably occupied by him, as, rather than leave
                  out anything in the <lb/> history of this question which is pertinent to my
                  argument, I will run the risk of laying myself <lb/> open to the charge of
                  plagiarism. In the first place, then, I must ask you, Sir, to allow me <lb/> to
                  trace the history of Confederation in this Council, as shown in the debates which
                  have taken <lb/> place on the subject. You will find, Sir, that this subject was
                  first introduced into this'Council <lb/> on the 29th of March, 1867, when a
                  Resolution in favour of the abstract principle of the Con<lb break="no"/>federation of the British Provinces in North America, and expressing the desire
                  that this Colony <lb/> should be allowed the opportunity of entering the Dominion
                  upon fair and equitable terms, <lb/> at some future time, was unanimously agreed
                  to. I do not quite take the view of the Honourable <lb/> the Attorney-General with
                  respect to the discussions that have taken place on this question; <lb/> for, Sir,
                  I think that the question is now for the first time brought before this House and
                  the <lb/> country in a practical shape, for a full and deliberate expression of
                  opinion. The vote which <lb/> was taken in 1867, according to my understanding of
                  it at that time, went no further than <lb/> to express a desire on the part of the
                  Colony to be confederated with Canada, when a favourable <lb/> occasion should
                  arrive, and the result of that vote was, I believe, the insertion of the clause in
                  <lb/> the "British North America Act," on which the measure we are now discussing
                  is based. Again, <lb/> in 1868, when the Honourable Member for District No. 2
                  introduced a series of Resolutions <lb/> setting forth terms on which this Colony
                  should be united with Canada, the sense of the House, <lb/> as then expressed, was
                  that we were not possessed of sufficient information to enable us to <lb/> come to
                  any practical resolution on the subject; and, Sir, when the terms and conditions
                  then <lb/> proposed for the consideration of the House are compared with those now
                  submitted for your <lb/> adoption, no words are needed to show that the conclusion
                  then arrived at was judicious. <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Last year, again, the subject was introduced by the Hon. Dr. Davie, to a reluctant House. 
                  <lb/>
               We all felt that there were circumstances which rendered its discussion then in this Council 
                  <lb/>
               inexpedient, although the question of Confederation was even then occupying public attention 
                  <lb/>
               to an absorbing extent, and had in fact been the test question at the elections a short time 
                  <lb/>
               previously in the Districts in this part of the Colony. But certain remarks of the Honourable 
                  <lb/>
               Member for Cariboo, in reference to the position of Government Members on this question, 
                  <lb/>
               compelled the expression of the views of the Council on the subject at that time, in a Resolution 
                  <lb/>
               pointing out the practical impossibility of the union of this Colony with Canada, until the North- 
                  <lb break="yes"/>
               West Territory was amalgamated with the Dominion. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               But now circumstances are entirely changed. The Hudson Bay Company's rights in that 
                  <lb/>
               region, known as the North-West Territory, are determined by purchase, and that country is 
                  <lb/>
               practically part of the Dominion of Canada; for the temporary opposition from a certain class 
                  <lb/>
               of the population of the Red River Settlement, to the assumption of the Government by the 
                  <lb/>
               Canadian authorities, is passing away, if not by the present moment virtually at an end. And 
                  <lb/>
               treating that ebullition of feeling resulting from misapprehension of the real intention of the 
                  <lb/>
               Dominion Government as passed away, I regard it as an established fact that, as stated in Lord 
                  <lb/>
               Granville's despatch, our boundaries are now conterminous with those of Canada. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               But not only is Union with Canada now practicable, but, Sir, I regard the present as a most 
                  <lb/>
               opportune moment for its consummation. I entirely agree with Honourable Members who say 
                  <lb/>
               that this Colony requires a change. In its present depressed state, the Colony needs assistance 
                  <lb/>
               and fresh impetus. There are many causes which combine to contribute to the depression now 
                  <lb/>
               observable in the country. It has been attributed to the present form of Government. Take 
                  <lb/>
               that as one cause, if you please; but, Sir, I believe it has had very little effect, if any, in pro<lb break="no"/><pb n="20" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_020.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">20</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>ducing this result, and you will find many other and mightier reasons to account for it. Chiefiy, 
                  <lb/>
               I believe, with the Honourable Attorney-General, that this depression is attributable to the 
                  <lb/>
               isolated position of the Colony, and to the cold shade thrown over us by the neighbourhood of 
                  <lb/>
               the Territories of the United States, from whom we can never hope for aid in advancing the 
                  <lb/>
               interests of this Colony whilst under the British Flag. The desire for some change is urgent, 
                  <lb/>
               and if we wait for more prosperous times, under which to claim better financial terms, we may 
                  <lb/>
               realize the old proverb of the "Horse starving whilst the grass is growing." Besides, Sir, on 
                  <lb/>
               reference to the terms now proposed for the consideration of this House by the Government, 
                  <lb/>
               it will be found that they are based not altogether on the present condition of the Colony, but 
                  <lb/>
               somewhat on an anticipated increase of population and prosperity; and I suppose we might 
                  <lb/>
               wait many years before such a measure of prosperity would accrue to us, as to entitle us to 
                  <lb/>
               ask better financial terms than are included in these Resolutions. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I believe the time, then, to be opportune, and I think that there is every reason to suppose 
                  <lb/>
               that the present Government of the Dominion is now desirous and ready to grant us fair and 
                  <lb/>
               liberal terms. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I believe, Sir, the Canadian Government are favourably disposed towards us, and prepared 
                  <lb/>
               to go to the utmost of their ability in all reasonable matters to enable us to joint the Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. The policy and wishes of the Imperial Government, too, in the same direction are clearly 
                  <lb/>
               enunciated in Earl Granville's despatch; and we are fortunate in having now at the head of 
                  <lb/>
               the Executive a Governor admirably adapted by his ability and experience to take charge, on 
                  <lb/>
               our behalf, of negotiations for our union with the Dominion, and to whom the interests of the 
                  <lb/>
               community may confidently be entrusted. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               And that brings me, Sir, to this point: That in its first introduction into this Council, this 
                  <lb/>
               measure must necessarily be a Government measure. The constitution of this House renders 
                  <lb/>
               it imperative that the initiatory steps should he taken by the Government, although the final 
                  <lb/>
               acceptance of the terms will properly rest with the people. The policy of the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment has been clearly stated: It encourages us to amalgamate our interests with Canada, and 
                  <lb/>
               points out the advantages to be thus obtained, and nothing that I could add would enunciate 
                  <lb/>
               more clearly than that document the grounds on which Her Majesty's Government, on behalf 
                  <lb/>
               of this Colony, favour Confederation. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               This leads me to remark on the part that has been taken in reference to this question by 
                  <lb/>
               the Official Members of this House, especially by the Executive Officers. Our position has been 
                  <lb/>
               misapprehended—or it not misapprehended, it has been misrepresented—and I feel it my duty to 
                  <lb/>
               allude to the false impressions which have been spread abroad on this subject. It has been 
                  <lb/>
               stated that the Official Members have been obstructive to Confederation, with regard to their 
                  <lb/>
               own official positions and interests. But this is not the fact. On a matter so clearly involving 
                  <lb/>
               a question of Imperial policy, we were not at liberty to anticipate the views of the Home 
                  <lb/>
               Government, which have now for the first time been distinctly made public. The Hon. Attorney- 
                  <lb break="yes"/>
               General and myself have consistently affirmed the principle of Confederation; and we have 
                  <lb/>
               always felt that we could safely confide our personal interests to the care of the Imperial 
                  <lb/>
               Government, whose servants we are. To Her Majesty's Government those interests are entrusted 
                  <lb/>
               by the Resolutions proposed for your adoption; and, Sir, we are well satisfied that this question 
                  <lb/>
               as it affects us personally should so depend. We have been right, Sir, I believe, in not antici<lb break="no"/>pating the views of the Imperial Government, for the terms of union now submitted for your 
                  <lb/>
               adoption prove the wisdom of the course which we have pursued; and in the exercise of caution 
                  <lb/>
               we have shewn ourselves the truest friends of the Colony, even though we have not appeared 
                  <lb/>
               to be the most enthusiastic advocates of Confederation. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               This, then, is a Government measure, as the Honourable the senior Member for Victoria 
                  <lb/>
               has told you; and as I hold it is of necessity a Government measure. This scheme is propounded 
                  <lb/>
               by the Government, as the guardians of the interests of this infant Colony; and I stand here 
                  <lb/>
               as a member of the Government to support the Resolutions which are now before you, and I 
                  <lb/>
               sincerely trust that they will be adopted by this Council. But His Excellency has told us that 
                  <lb/>
               the ultimate acceptance or rejection of the terms of union with Canada, after they have been 
                  <lb/>
               submitted to the Dominion Government, shall be left to the popular voice of this country. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I will now. Sir, come to the consideration of what Confederation is in the abstract, as I 
                  <lb/>
               understand it. It is the union and consolidation of British interests in British Territory on 
                  <lb/>
               this continent, for the security and advancement of each Province individually, and of the 
                  <lb/>
               
           
            <pb n="21" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_021.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">21</fw>
            
           
               whole collectively, under the continued support of the British Flag. A great idea of great 
                  <lb/>
               minds, which have thus given a practical refutation to that doctrine of "America for the 
                  <lb/>
               United States," known as the "Munro doctrine," held by leading politicians of the States 
                  <lb/>
               south of us; and on this account, if on no other grounds, the principle of Confederation deserves 
                  <lb/>
               the support of every British heart in the Colony. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I am now brought to a subject which I should not have known how to approach, but for the 
                  <lb/>
               bridge thrown over for me by the Honourable Member for Victoria yesterday. By that Honour<lb break="no"/>able Member the suggestion of a closer union with another country—with the United States, in 
                  <lb/>
               fact—and the possibility that at the next General Election such an union might be presented as 
                  <lb/>
               an alternative to Confederation with Canada, was introduced in so palpable a manner, that I 
                  <lb/>
               should feel myself derelict to my duty as a Member of the Executive and as a Member of this 
                  <lb/>
               Council if I did not refer to it. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Mr. President, I should do violence to my best feelings were I to refrain from availing 
                  <lb/>
               myself of this opportunity of paying my humble tribute of respect and esteem for the people 
                  <lb/>
               of that great Republic. ["Hear, hear," from <persName ref="pers:ANON1">all sides</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. Mr. TRUTCH</persName></supplied> No one can better appreciate than I 
                  <lb/>
               do the high and eminent qualities which characterise that great Nation, and especially that 
                  <lb/>
               national feeling—that love of country, so worthy of our imitation―for which they have made 
                  <lb/>
               such sacrifices. It has been my fortune to pass several years in the United States, and to have 
                  <lb/>
               formed there some of the most valued friendships of my life, so that my acquaintance with 
                  <lb/>
               Americans has led me to form a most appreciative estimate of their social and domestic 
                  <lb/>
               relations, of which I can not speak in terms of too much praise. But my experience of the 
                  <lb/>
               political institutions of that country only led me to prize our own more highly, and made me 
                  <lb/>
               more than ever an Englishman; and I rejoice at the opportunity now afforded me of raising my 
                  <lb/>
               voice against any movement tending in the direction of incorporating this country with the 
                  <lb/>
               United States. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I must now make passing allusion to a petition gotten up in some mysterious way, looked 
                  <lb/>
               upon here at first as a mere joke; so insignificant that it would not be worthy of notice but 
                  <lb/>
               for the use made of it elsewhere. It has been represented in other quarters as expressing the 
                  <lb/>
               views of a great portion of this community. It has been so represented in very high quarters, 
                  <lb/>
               and I therefore notice it; and in doing so I feel compelled to state that, so far as I could learn, 
                  <lb/>
               it was signed by a very small number of people―forty-two, I believe, in all—many of whom were 
                  <lb/>
               aliens, and most of whom were foreign-born subjects, and who appear to have been generally 
                  <lb/>
               actuated by prejudice, based upon a lack of information respecting Canada and the Canadians, 
                  <lb/>
               and not by any regard for the permanent benefit of the community. But as this petition has 
                  <lb/>
               been followed up by the publication of letters and by a discussion in the newspapers, which we 
                  <lb/>
               cannot blink, as to what has been termed the Annexation of this Colony to the United States; 
                  <lb/>
               and as allusion was made to it, by an innuendo at all events, in this Council yesterday, I feel 
                  <lb/>
               bound to express my opinion of what our position would be under any such union as has been 
                  <lb/>
               hinted at. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               If British Columbia were placed in the same position as Washington Territory, we should 
                  <lb/>
               be absolutely without representation―for that Territory has one representative in Congress, it 
                  <lb/>
               is true, but he has no vote—and all our officials would come from Washington. Annexation to 
                  <lb/>
               the United States would also entail on us largely increased taxation, and would most materially 
                  <lb/>
               affect an interest which the Honourable Member for Victoria told you would suffer most 
                  <lb/>
               from Confederation. Why, Sir, under the union suggested, our farmers would be brought into 
                  <lb/>
               direct competition with the farmers of Washington Territory and Oregon, and then our agri<lb break="no"/>cultural interests would be indeed annihilated. Again, it this country were American Territory 
                  <lb/>
               you would have the whole influence of San Francisco brought to bear against the mercantile 
                  <lb/>
               interests of Victoria; no hope could we have of building up a port here to rival San Francisco; 
                  <lb/>
               no, Sir, you would never see a foreign vessel in these waters. I see no advantages in the 
                  <lb/>
               suggestion; I have heard none pointed out, unless it be the questionable expectation that 
                  <lb/>
               American capital might buy up the real estate in and around Victoria, and so give the present 
                  <lb/>
               holders the opportunity of realizing their property into money and then leave the country to 
                  <lb/>
               its fate. But in this hope, Sir, I believe they would be egregiously disappointed. I will not 
                  <lb/>
               pursue the subject any further. Annexation is entirely out of the question, and I should not  
                  <lb/>
               have dared to allude to it, but for the introduction of the subject by another Honourable Member 
                  <lb/>
               yesterday. What do these foreign petitioners propose to transfer? Themselves? Their own 
                  <lb/>
               
         
            <pb n="22" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_022.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">22</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
          
               property? No; not themselves, nor that which belongs to them, but the whole Colony, the soil 
                  <lb/>
               of this vast domain which belongs to the Crown and the people of England. This I regard as 
                  <lb/>
               treasonable. In supporting Confederation I support the flag I serve. I say that loyalty is no 
                  <lb/>
               exploded idea; call it a sentiment if you will; life is nothing without sentiment. Every one whose 
                  <lb/>
               soul is not dead must cling to love of country and attachment to her flag, as one of the most <lb/>cherished sentiments of the heart, and I regard loyalty as one of the most deep-rooted and 
                  <lb/>
               highly prized treasures of the human breast. [" Hear, hear," from <persName ref="pers:ANON1">all sides</persName>] 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               <supplied><persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. Mr. TRUTCH</persName></supplied> Bear with me, Sir, while I tell you now what I think Confederation is not. I don't think 
                  <lb/>
               it necessarily means Responsible Government, or, as an Honourable Member at the other end 
                  <lb/>
               of the House has put it, that it means getting rid of Government Officials. If that Honourable 
                  <lb/>
               Member's desire is to be rid of the present incumbents of office so that others may take their 
                  <lb/>
               place, I think it probable that his wishes in this respect may be gratified through Confederation; 
                  <lb/>
               and in that case I could only hope that the change would be beneficial to the Colony, But I 
                  <lb/>
               doubt much if this measure would receive support from this Council on these grounds; and at 
                  <lb/>
               all events the Honourable Gentleman cannot expect much sympathy on that score from this side 
                  <lb/>
               of the House. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Again, Confederation does not, to my mind, mean Responsible Government, as some Honour<lb break="no"/>able Members hold. British Columbia will assuredly get Responsible Government as soon as 
                  <lb/>
               the proper time arrives, as soon, that is to say, as the community is sufficiently advanced in 
                  <lb/>
               population, and in other respects, to render such a form of Government practically workable; 
                  <lb/>
               sooner, probably, through Confederation than by any other means, and the sooner the better, I 
                  <lb/>
               say. But I do not think it desirable to fetter or cumber the proposed terms of union with 
                  <lb/>
               anything about Responsible Government, and specially for the reason that we should find it 
                  <lb/>
               very difficult to arrive at any conclusion in favour of it. Great difference of opinion exists 
                  <lb/>
               upon the subject even around this Council Board, and I am by no means sure that the strongest 
                  <lb/>
               opposition to Responsible Government would come from the Government side of the House. It 
                  <lb/>
               is easier to change the constitution after Confederation than before. ["No, no."] Under the 
                  <lb/>
               Organic Act, this Colony could get Responsible Government. In fact, it is the special prerogative 
                  <lb/>
               under this Act of each Province to regulate the constitution of its own Executive Government 
                  <lb/>
               and Legislature; and whence this desire to act so prematurely now in this respect? 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Another Honourable Member has told you that in his opinion Confederation means the 
                  <lb/>
               terms―means a Railway; but I take it, Sir, that the terms proposed result from Confederation, 
                  <lb/>
               and that the Railway is a means to the end, for we cannot have real Confederation without a 
                  <lb/>
               Railway, But, Sir, I advocate Confederation on principle; and I believe the terms to be the 
                  <lb/>
               natural result of Confederation. They flow from it as a natural consequence, as the effect 
                  <lb/>
               proceeds from the cause. I believe that by Confederation we are to gain those advantages 
                  <lb/>
               which are set forth in the terms. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               If it could be shown that by acceptance of these terms we should in any way sacrifice our 
                  <lb/>
               honour―lose any political status that: we now enjoy—I would not support Confederation it it 
                  <lb/>
               brought a dozen railroads. But I believe that each member of this community will be raised 
                  <lb/>
               by the change. We shall have a distinct and very respectable representation in the House of 
                  <lb/>
               Commons and Senate. We shall have as representatives there men whose voice will be heard, 
                  <lb/>
               men whose duty it will be to speak for us Far from entertaining the views expressed by the 
                  <lb/>
               two Honourable Members for Victoria, I am inclined to think with the Honourable Member for 
                  <lb/>
               New Westminster, that this Colony will have its due weight and influence in the Dominion, that 
                  <lb/>
               its representatives will be heard and listened to in the Canadian Parliament, and that this will 
                  <lb/>
               be a favoured portion of the Confederation, when admitted, on account of its position as the 
                  <lb/>
               outlet of Canada on the Pacific. I do not, then, advocate Confederation specially on account 
                  <lb/>
               of the terms I find in its general merits ample grounds for support, and I consider, as I have 
                  <lb/>
               said, that the terms follow as a matter of course. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Honourable Member for Victoria has said that we are bound to prove the benefits. It 
                  <lb/>
               is difficult to prove anything to some minds. The benefits of Confederation are among those 
                  <lb/>
               things which, being in futurity, we cannot prove. I cannot prove that which has not happened. 
                  <lb/>
               We can only rely on human judgment and experience, and argue that such and such things will 
                  <lb/>
               occur, as certain causes will produce certain effects. I, and other Official Members of this 
                  <lb/>
               Colony, have a considerable interest in this Colony; I have, to a certain extent, identified myself 
                  <lb/>
               with it and its concerns for some years past, and speaking as an individual Member of this 
                  <lb/>
               
        
            
            <pb n="23" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_023.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">23</fw>
            
           
               Council, if I did not believe that Confederation would prove advantageous to this Colony, and 
                  <lb/>
               redound to the benefit of our local interests, I should not support it by my voice. I might as 
                  <lb/>
               a Government servant vote for it as a Government measure, but I should not be standing here 
                  <lb/>
               to speak for it and to advocate it as heartily as I do. It is hardly possible to show where the 
                  <lb/>
               colony will be benefited by Confederation, without discussing the terms, which is not my present 
                  <lb/>
               intention to do; but I promise Honourable Members that if these Resolutions get into Committee, 
                  <lb/>
               I will fully satisfy them of the local advantages that must accrue to the Colony from union with 
                  <lb/>
               Canada, on the terms proposed in these Resolutions. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I believe, Sir, that many of the objections which have been raised to Confederation have 
                  <lb/>
               arisen from prejudiced feelings. I have no reason to be prejudiced against or partial to Canada. 
                  <lb/>
               I believe that Canadians as a people are no better than others, and no worse. I have no ties 
                  <lb/>
               in Canada, no particular reason for entertaining any feeling of affection for Canada; and if <lb/>I did not believe that the advance which we make will be met in a becoming spirit, ["Hear, 
                  <lb/>
               hear,"] then I should be of opinion that Confederation would be nothing more than on union 
                  <lb/>
               on paper, one not beneficial to this Colony or to Canada. There are statesmen there, Sir, 
                  <lb/>
               who know that it would be useless to try to beat us down on terms; for what would be the 
                  <lb/>
               use of Confederation if it afterwards turned out that this Colony was injured, rather than 
                  <lb/>
               benefited, by it. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Honourable Junior Member for Victoria asks what guarantee have we that the terms 
                  <lb/>
               will be carried out. I say at once, Sir, that if the terms are not carried out, if the Canadian 
                  <lb/>
               Government repudiate their part of the agreement, we shall be equally at liberty to repudiate 
                  <lb/>
               ours. [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. Helmcken</persName>—"How?"] <supplied><persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. Mr. TRUTCH</persName></supplied> We should, I maintain, be at liberty to change; but I, for 
                  <lb/>
               one, do not approach this subject with any such feeling. [" Hear, hear," from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DeCosmos</persName>.] 
                  <lb/>
               <supplied><persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. Mr. TRUTCH</persName></supplied> There are always two sides to a bargain, and if the terms which are frankly and honestly 
                  <lb/>
               proposed are not fairly and honourably dealt with, we should, in my opinion, be at perfect liberty 
                  <lb/>
               to draw back. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               There is, however, one real and practical objection which has always suggested itself to 
                  <lb/>
               my mind from the first, and that is, that the same measures that apply to the circumstances 
                  <lb/>
               of Canada, such as tariff, will not apply equally in all respects to this Colony. It will be asked, 
                  <lb/>
               then, why is there no suggestion as to some alteration or modification of the tariff in the terms. 
                  <lb/>
               The reason is somewhat similar to the reason for the omission of all mention of Responsible 
                  <lb/>
               Government. You would find it very difficult to come to any conclusions on this subject in 
                  <lb/>
               this Council. It is impracticable to define now positively what precise tariff would best suit 
                  <lb/>
               this country. Some favour a free port. I should be inclined to favour it myself if I believed 
                  <lb/>
               it, practicable. Some, on the other hand, say that we must have protection to agriculture, and 
                  <lb/>
               that without it we cannot compete with the farmers of Oregon. This point was fully discussed 
                  <lb/>
               in the Executive Council, but it was decided to omit any conditions for the regulation of Customs 
                  <lb/>
               dues from these terms; and I do not think that this measure ought to be complicated with the 
                  <lb/>
               tariff question. I believe that we may safely trust this people with whom we are about to 
                  <lb/>
               negotiate, to do as much for us in this direction as we could do for ourselves; it will be to 
                  <lb/>
               their interest to do so. It requires no argument to show that it will be to the interest of 
                  <lb/>
               Canada, after Confederation, to advance the prosperity of this country. If it be possible to 
                  <lb/>
               adopt a special tariff to this part of the Colony, and I see no reason why it should not be 
                  <lb/>
               adopted, I confidently hope to see such a special tariff arranged under Confederation. [" Hear, 
                  <lb/>
               hear," from <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Mr. DeCosmos</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. Mr. TRUTCH</persName></supplied> Rely upon it, Sir, that there are statesmen in Canada who have 
                  <lb/>
               a far wider and longer political experience than Members of this House, and who would be 
                  <lb/>
               able to point out many means of prosperity, for which we are looking with so much anxiety,<lb break="no"/>powerful minds, before which I feel humbled,―men who I cannot for a moment suppose would 
                  <lb/>
               fail to see as plainly as we do that Confederation would be of no benefit to Canada unless it 
                  <lb/>
               redound to the advantage of British Columbia. This requires no argument; it is perfectly 
                  <lb/>
               plain common sense. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               If we are not to have Confederation, what are we to have? What is the proposition of 
                  <lb/>
               those who oppose Confederation? The people of this Colony have been, for a long time past, 
                  <lb/>
               asking for a change, and it has been the policy of those who ask for change to throw the blame 
                  <lb/>
               of everything upon the Government. The policy of the Imperial Government on this matter 
                  <lb/>
               is clearly expressed in Earl Granville's despatch. He does not say you must confederate, 
                  <lb/>
               whether you will or not; it is left to the people to decide this question for themselves; but he 
                  <lb/>
               
           
            
            <pb n="24" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_024.jpg"/>
            
            
               <fw type="num">24</fw> <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> 
                 
               says, virtually, " You have for years been asking for a change, you complain that your present 
                  <lb/>
               form of Government does not suit you; we point out for your consideration Confederation, 
                  <lb/>
               which, if it suits you, we favour; the Government of Canada is ready to step in and assist <lb/>you to carry out your views for the advancement of your local interests." Now, Sir, I say to 
                  <lb/>
               this Council,—If you don't want Confederation, what do you want? To remain as you are? 
                  <lb/>
               This I know you are not satisfied to do. What then? Establish a sort of Independent Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of about 6,000 people, connected with nobody, owing allegiance to nobody? The idea is  
                  <lb/>
               absurd. There appears, then, to be no alternative to Confederation, but that suggestion which 
                  <lb/>
               has been shadowed forth during this debate, and which I, for one, decline to consider as a 
                  <lb/>
               possibility. And so we come to Confederation as our manifest destiny. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               To sum up my argument in support of the motion of the Honourable the Attorney-General- <lb/>I advocate Confederation because it will secure the continuance of this Colony under the 
                  <lb/>
               British Flag, and strengthen British interests on this Continent; and because it will benefit 
                  <lb/>
               this community, by lessening taxation and giving increased revenue for local expenditure; 
                  <lb/>
               by advancing the political status of the Colony; by securing the practical aid of the Dominion 
                  <lb/>
               Government, who are, I believe, able to—and whose special care it would be to devise and- <lb/> carry into effect measures tending to develop the natural resources, and to promote the pros<lb break="no"/>perity of this Colony; and by affording, through a railway, the only means of acquiring a 
                  <lb/>
               permanent population, which must come from the east of the Rocky Mountains. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HOLB1">The Hon. Mr. HOLBROOK</persName> said:—Sir, In rising to continue this
                  debate, after the able <lb/> speech of the Hon. Chief Commissioner of Lands and
                  Works, I feel that there is little left for me <lb/> to say, as when we go into
                  Committee I shall have an opportunity of expressing my opinion upon <lb/> the
                  terms; and it would be factions to oppose a measure which has to come before the
                  people <lb/> for their decision. The way, Sir, that I understand the question of
                  Confederation to stand at <lb/> present, is that it is not a mere abstract
                  question of Confederation with Canada, but a question <lb/> of certain terms which
                  have to be laid before the people; therefore, I say that any opposition <lb/>
                  against this being done would be factious. As regards myself, I shall abide by
                  such decision, <lb/> whatever it may be, as I consider the people themselves are
                  the best judges as to whether they <lb/> will "benefit, or otherwise, by becoming
                  part and parcel of the Dominion of Canada. This matter <lb/> has evidently been
                  well considered by the Executive Council, most of whom are largely interested
                  <lb/> in the welfare of the Colony, and several of them have been as much opposed
                  to immediate <lb/> Confederation, when the question has been before this Council
                  on other occasions, as I have <lb/> been. But having had an opportunity of seeing
                  the documents which have come from the <lb/> Imperial Government on the subject,
                  the Executive have arrived at the decision that it is best <lb/> for this question
                  to go to the country, upon the assumption that the people will ask for Confed<lb break="no"/>eration to be carried out on certain terms; therefore, I say, Sir,
                  let it go to the people and <lb/> settlers of the Colony, and by their verdict let
                  it be decided. Earl Granville has sent out a <lb/> despatch which states, in
                  pretty plain terms, that we were not able to govern ourselves; and <lb/> there
                  was, perhaps, more truth than poetry in this; for we have had the greatest liberty
                  granted <lb/> to us, and yet we have not been content. Our Gold Mining Laws have
                  been made by the Mining <lb/> Board; we have had the most liberal Land Laws; and
                  if we have had a want that the law <lb/> could satisify it has been immediately
                  granted. <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Our Officials are an honour to the country. As an Englishman, I am proud of them. 
                  <lb/>
               Justice has been properly administered in the country; there has been absolutely security to 
                  <lb/>
               life and property so much so that a man can travel in perfect safety from Cariboo to Victoria, 
                  <lb/>
               and capital can be safely invested in any part of the Colony. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We have excellent roads, and one of the richest spots on the whole earth for our Colony, 
                  <lb/>
               whether as regards mining wealth or agricultural resources; and yet a petition has emanated 
                  <lb/>
               from a small body of foreign residents in the City of Victoria, asking to be annexed to the 
                  <lb/>
               great Republic adjoining. I am well aware, Sir, that, as has been well said by the Hon. Chief 
                  <lb/>
               Commoner, the petition was paltry and unworthy of notice, and that those who signed it 
                  <lb/>
               were insignificant; and I may be allowed to say that we of the Mainland had no feelings in 
                  <lb/>
               common with them. If it were within reason to contemplate the possibility of the occurrence 
                  <lb/>
               of such an alternative. it might be worth while to point out its disadvantages, and to show 
                  <lb/>
               that under it we should not even have representation, as without a certain population, which 
                  <lb/>
               we have not, we could not elect a member, and we should fall back to what Washington Territory 
                  <lb/>
               and Oregon were in the days before this City of Victoria was brought forward by the Fleet, 
                  <lb/>
           
           
            
            <pb n="25" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_025.jpg"/>
            
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">25</fw>
            
           
               to the encouragement and development of the neighbouring States, equally, or perhaps in excess 
                  <lb/>
               of the interests of our own Colony. We may say that liberty had run wild; people have actually 
                  <lb/>
               become dissatisfied because they have had too much of it. I remember a similar discontent 
                  <lb/>
               with excess of liberty in Paris, after the Revolution of 1848; the people revelled in excess of 
                  <lb/>
               freedom, and from so much liberty they fell into another Revolution. It is only in a country 
                  <lb/>
               with such free institutions as England, that such a petition could have been signed with 
                  <lb/>
               impunity; for if it means anything at all, it did not stop short of treason. In most other 
                  <lb/>
               countries the signers would have forfeited their liberty; in some that I have lived in, the 
                  <lb/>
               penalty would have been death. Speaking for the Mainland, Sir, and coming from the Royal 
                  <lb/>
               Town of New Westminster, I have a right to speak in the name of its loyal inhabitants. I say 
                  <lb/>
               that, although Confederation with Canada meets with favour in some quarters, the feelings 
                  <lb/>
               of the inhabitants are, and ever will be, thoroughly loyal to the glorious flag of Great Britain, 
                  <lb/>
               and feel proud of belonging to that flag which represents honour, power, justice, and wealth, 
                  <lb/>
               and which is stainless and untarnished, whether unfurled in the face of an enemy and defended 
                  <lb/>
               by its sons, or floating in peace over such a Colony as this. We have had our complaints on 
                  <lb/>
               the Mainland, and we considered the removal of the Capital and centralization of business at 
                  <lb/>
               Victoria an injustice to the rest of the Colony, for the reason, principally, that Victoria, from 
                  <lb/>
               its proximity to the United States, draws its supplies thence, instead of from the Mainland, 
                  <lb/>
               to the gain of the neighbouring States, and consequent loss to the agricultural districts of the 
                  <lb/>
               Mainland of some $10,000 annually, in the article of beef alone; and for the reason that, by 
                  <lb/>
               the Fleet being placed at Esquimalt, we of the Mainland were not only left without protection, 
                  <lb/>
               but that the agricultural interests of Washington Territory and Oregon were being built up 
                  <lb/>
               with the money expended by the Fleet in the purchase of supplies, which if spent in the 
                  <lb/>
               Valley of the Fraser would, by this time, have given us there a population of some thousands. 
                  <lb/>
               The people of my part of the Colony have favoured Confederation, in the belief that the resources 
                  <lb/>
               of the Colony would receive some consideration from the Dominion Government. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We all acknowledge that population is required, and I think there is no reason to doubt 
                  <lb/>
               that it will come. I do not attribute the depression, as some Hon. Members have done, to 
                  <lb/>
               bad Government. We merely followed the course of other gold countries in over trading, and 
                  <lb/>
               placed all our dependence upon a single mining district, and when we did not find another 
                  <lb/>
               Williams Creek so rapidly as we expected, we became disheartened. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               But, Sir, I mean to state, and I do so without fear of contradiction, that our natural 
                  <lb/>
               resources are more prosperous to-day than they have ever been before, and I need only point 
                  <lb/>
               to the 8,000 acres of land taken up last year as an example of real and solid prosperity. We 
                  <lb/>
               shall acquire population from Canada by means of the railroad, and the large amount of money 
                  <lb/>
               required for its construction will tend to our prosperity. Our merchants also want something 
                  <lb/>
               fixed, that they may not be threatened with constant change, which renders commerce fluctuating 
                  <lb/>
               and uncertain. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I consider, Sir, that the time is opportune for Confederation for many reasons, amongst 
                  <lb/>
               others, that there is a favourable opportunity for us, with the aid of Canada, to make arrange<lb break="no"/>ments for the reception of some of the emigrant poor, who are now being assisted by the <lb/>Societies in England to go out to the Colonies. Work could be found for them on the railway, 
                  <lb/>
               and by this means much of our valuable agricultural land might be settled up. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I shall reserve to myself the right of opposing some of the terms when they come under 
                  <lb/>
               discussion, and of asking that others may be inserted. I should be glad to see inserted in 
                  <lb/>
               the terms a clause empowering our Local Government to make her own tariff, so as to protect 
                  <lb/>
               our farming interests, in a similar manner under the Imperial Government, the Isle of Man 
                  <lb/>
               and the Channel Islands have rights reserved; but I am of opinion that the full tariff of the 
                  <lb/>
               Dominion should in all cases be charged, and that the Local Government of British Columbia 
                  <lb/>
               should have the exclusive benefit of any extra tariff. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Indians, also, should be secured the same protection that they have under our own 
                  <lb/>
               Government. They are now content with us, and with the way in which the laws are adminis<lb break="no"/>tered, and it is quite possible that they may hereafter be a source of great trouble, if they are 
                  <lb/>
               not considered as well as white men. 
                  <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I shall hail with pleasure the salmon laws of Canada, spoken of by one Honourable Member, 
                  <lb/>
               which will prevent the placing of salmon traps at the mouth of the Fraser, stopping thereby 
                  <lb/>
               the fish from ascending the river, and by that means cutting off the food of the Indians, and 
                  <lb/>
               
           
            
            <pb n="26" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_026.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">26</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
           
               taking from them the means of support; but I should much regret to see any laws brought into 
               <lb/>
               operation which would grant monopolies, such, for instance, as in the case of cranberries, which 
               <lb/>
               are at present a source of living to many hundreds of Indians. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               As regards our defences: we should have the right to have our own forces, as every one 
               <lb/>
               would have to serve in the Militia; but so long as English troops are stationed in Canada, we 
               <lb/>
               ought, when we become an integral part of the Dominion, to have our share of them. And at 
               <lb/>
               no very distant future I trust that the great scheme of Confederation may be carried out, 
               <lb/>
               and that the Dominion may have a Royal Prince at its head, and then may the views of the 
               <lb/>
               great Anglo―Saxon race as regards commerce and trade become enlightened so that English 
               <lb/>
               goods may come into the Dominion duty free. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               As we shall, from our position on the Pacific Coast, be the keystone of Confederation, 
               <lb/>
               I hope we may become the most glorious in the whole structure, and tend to our own and 
               <lb/>
               England's future greatness. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I shall support the motion of the Honourable the Attorney-General. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">The Hon. Mr. WOOD</persName> said :—Sir, I rise to support the amendment
                  of the Honourable Junior <lb/> Member for Victoria, to postpone the consideration
                  of these Resolutions for six months. I desire, <lb/> Sir, to express my
                  unqualified opposition to what is termed the Confederation of this Colony <lb/>
                  with the Dominion of Canada on the basis of the Organic Act; and in dealing with
                  the subject <lb/> I shall address myself to three several heads of objection:
                  <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Firstly, to the principle of the Organic Act of 1867, as applied to the British North American 
               <lb/>
               Provinces; 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Secondly, to the special application of the principle to this Colony; 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Thirdly, to the mode in which the consent of its adoption is now attempted to be obtained. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Referring for a moment to my own personal position in this Council, I should wish to say 
               <lb/>
               that I feel bound as a non―representative and non―official member to present my own views. 
               <lb/>
               My mouth is not closed by official reticence, nor do I represent any constituency. I am here, 
               <lb/>
               bound by my duty as a Member of this Council, to express my own conscientious views in 
               <lb/>
               respect of the measure in explicit terms, in the interests no less of this Colony than of Great 
               <lb/>
               Britain, which in this, as in every Colonial question, I cannot but hold to be identical. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               With respect to the general principle of Confederation of the British North American 
               <lb/>
               Provinces, it will be remembered that, in 1867, I was one of those Members who did vote 
               <lb/>
               that Confederation, on fair and equitable terms, was desirable I am of that opinion still; 
               <lb/>
               but my objection is that no terms based on the Organic Act of 1867 can be fair or equitable. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It cannot be denied that the idea of a confederation and general alliance between the 
               <lb/>
               British Colonies in North America is a very captivating idea. The existence of a homogeneous 
               <lb/>
               nation tending to act as a counterpoise to the great Republic to the south of us, is a grand<lb/>
               political idea, but it is an idea most dangerous and difficult to carry out. When I voted in 
               <lb/>
               1867 for Confederation on fair and equitable terms, I had in my mind Confederation in the 
               <lb/>
               general acceptance of the word as understood by all political writers and by the world in 
               <lb/>
               general— a union of free and self-governed States, united by a federal compact for purposes 
               <lb/>
               of offence and defence, of peace and war, and for the purposes of maintaining and preserving 
               <lb/>
               uniformity in laws and institutions which affect the social and commercial relation of life; 
               <lb/>
               such laws and institutions as criminal law and practice, the general administration of justice, 
               <lb/>
               and the laws regulating commerce and navigation. Such a Confederation I then believed to be 
               <lb/>
               possible, I am foolish enough to believe it to be possible still; but Confederation as understood 
               <lb/>
               by Canadian and Imperial statesmen—Confederation as effected by the Organic Act of 1867- <lb/> is not Confederation at all. I would, indeed, throw the word Confederation to the winds, since 
               <lb/>
               by Confederation is obviously meant union, incorporation, and absorption. The Organic Act 
               <lb/>
               of 1867, provides for the entire transfer of all effective legislative power and control to Ottawa, 
               <lb/>
               as the seat of the Dominion Government, where, owing to the much greater wealth and population 
               <lb/>
               of Canada, the influence and authority of Canada bear all before it. It is a principle too obvious 
               <lb/>
               for proof or dissertation, that Confederation in its proper sense can only thrive where the States 
               <lb/>
               bound together by the federal compact are not only free, but where they are nearly equal. 
               <lb/>
               Excess of power in any one State is fatal to the interests of the rest. No, Sir, the word Con<lb break="no"/>federation has no application to the intended movement. Lord Granville. in his despatch, no 
               <lb/>
               longer calls it by such a term. Union and Incorporation are spoken of, not Confederation, and 
               <lb/>
               the movement really is one of incorporation, absorption, and annihilation. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <pb n="27" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_027.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">27</fw>
            
            <p>
               Now, Sir, the objections that I raise are objections to the provisions of the Organic Act, 
               <lb/>
               and I find it necessary, for the purposes of my argument, to turn to those provisions. I do not 
               <lb/>
               mean to detain the Council at unnecessary length, but as the question before us is one which 
               <lb/>
               concerns the future of this Colony for all time, I trust that I shall be excused if I dwell for a 
               <lb/>
               few moments upon these points. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               If we come into Confederation, we come in, as I understand it, under this Organic Act; and 
               <lb/>
               it is on account of the overwhelming influence of Canada in the joint Legislature of the Dominion, 
               <lb/>
               as given by that Act, that I object to the general principle of the Confederation of the North 
               <lb/>
               American Provinces of Great Britain. I am told I am in error, that profound statesmen in 
               <lb/>
               Great Britain and in Canada have determined otherwise, and that Confederation, on the basis 
               <lb/>
               of the Organic Act of 1867, is the policy of Great Britain 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I regret, Sir, that I cannot be silenced by the weight of such authority. No statesmanship, 
               <lb/>
               no conclusion, is of any value except for the reasoning on which it is founded; and I am ready 
               <lb/>
               to rest the whole matter on simple argument and reason. All States large enough and populous 
               <lb/>
               enough to warrant such privileges, eagerly and passionately desire the power of self-government. 
               <lb/>
               It is the common passion of our race. Formerly, even now, in other places, it is British policy 
               <lb/>
               to give these powers; and as New South Wales has thrown off Victoria and Queensland, so 
               <lb/>
               would it appear to be reasonable to extend the principle to the British Provinces in North 
               <lb/>
               America, rather than to adopt a different policy, for the simple reason that it is in accordance 
               <lb/>
               with the instincts of the Anglo-Saxon race, and the just rights of man. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We want self-government, which means the protection of our own interests, and the estab<lb break="no"/>lishment of our own welfare in our own way; the passing of our own Estimates in our own way; 
               <lb/>
               the selection of those who rule, and the subsequent meeting of our rulers, face to face, in open 
               <lb/>
               Council, that they may show us the results of their ruling. It means the imposition and collec― 
               <lb/>
               tion of our own taxes, fostering our own industries, and the power of the purse. These are the 
               <lb/>
               elements of self-government, and they are reserved to the Dominion Government, and taken from 
               <lb/>
               the Provinces; hence my objections to the Organic Act. For these reasons I say that Confedera― 
               <lb/>
               tion—or rather union—with Canada cannot be fair and equal, on account of the overwhelming 
               <lb/>
               influence of Canada in the Dominion Parliament, now and in the future; for it always must be 
               <lb/>
               so. Canada can extend, and will extend, and even of herself would be able to sway the destinies 
               <lb/>
               of the Dominion. And are we to accept this position because we are told that British statesman<lb break="no"/>ship wills it? Statesmanship, Sir, is nothing more than very sound common sense put into 
               <lb/>
               practice—sound common sense, backed by a knowledge of mankind and of the subject matter to 
               <lb/>
               which that statesmanship is applied. And, although it is not for me to depreciate the renown 
               <lb/>
               of my countrymen, it cannot be disguised that they have not unfrequently gone astray, and been 
               <lb/>
               forced to submit to the control of national interests and national will. It is not difficult to find 
               <lb/>
               instances of error in British statesmanship, as applied to Colonial affairs. The errors of British 
               <lb/>
               statesmen, with a majority of the House of Commons-and the British Nation to back them, cost 
               <lb/>
               Great Britain the thirteen United States. The errors of British Statesman, with a majority of 
               <lb/>
               the House of Commons and the British Nation to back them, have inflicted wrongs upon Ireland, 
               <lb/>
               which are only now in process of removal; and the policy of British statesmen, with the British 
               <lb/>
               Nation to back it, has created a difference which has gone far to alienate tile affections of the 
               <lb/>
               Colonists of New Zealand. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               In this question of Confederation it is impossible not to see the self―intorest of Great Britain 
               <lb/>
               underlying the whole matter. England is alarmed at the extent of her Colonial possessions, and 
               <lb/>
               her obligations to protect them by sea and land. Of all her possessions, the Dominion of Canada 
               <lb/>
               is the most assailabie; and, doubtless, Great Britain stands alarmed at the responsibility and 
               <lb/>
               cost of protecting so enormous a frontier. The question of Confederation is the question of 
               <lb/>
               every tax-paying Englishman, and whatever may be the <hi rendition="simple:italic">reasoning</hi> put forth, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">motive</hi> is 
               <lb/>
               economy and security to the tax―paying public of Great Britain. Confederation is, doubtless, 
               <lb/>
               of value to Great Britain, as establishing a counterpoise to the United States of America, and 
               <lb/>
               probably inducing the Dominion of Canada to ask for and obtain independence, and so relieve 
               <lb/>
               the Mother Country from the cost and duty of defending it. This is, I believe, the entire 
               <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">statesmanship</hi> of the measure—a statesmanship meritorious in English eyes—but, as I believe, 
               <lb/>
               fraught with extreme danger to British interests in this quarter of the globe. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Turning now to what may be called the argument in favour of Confederation, we have 
               <lb/>
               Lord Granville's despatch. Lord Granville, it must be admitted, has ably, gracefully, and 
               <lb/>
               
        
            
            <pb n="28" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_028.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">28</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
         

               plausibly put before us the supposed advantages of Confederation :―" Her Majesty's Govern<lb break="no"/>"ment believe that a Legislature selected from an extended area, and representing a diversity 
               <lb/>
               "of interests, was more likely to deal more comprehensively with large questions, and more 
               <lb/>
               "impartially with small questions, and more conclusively with both, than is possible when 
               <lb/>
               "controversies are carried on and decided upon in the comparatively narrow circle in which 
               <lb/>
               "they arise. Questions of purely local interest would be more carefully and dispassionately 
               <lb/>
               "considered when disengaged from the larger politics of the country, and at the same time 
               <lb/>
               " would be more sagaciously considered by persons who have had this larger political education. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               "Finally, they anticipate that the interests of every Province of British North America 
               <lb/>
               " would be more advanced by enabling the wealth, credit, and intelligence of the whole to be 
               <lb/>
               " brought to bear on every part, than by encouraging each in the contracted policy of taking 
               <lb/>
               "care of itself, possibly at the expense of its neighbour." 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               This I understand to be the argument of the Colonial Office in favour of Confederation; and 
               <lb/>
               although I fully admit that it is well put, I believe that no argument is more fallacious. It is 
               <lb/>
               delicate ground for me to touch when I presume to differ from what comes from so able a man. 
               <lb/>
               On this point I wish to make myself distinctly understood. I do not profess to be a statesman 
               <lb/>
               or a politician, but as a lawyer of mature age, pretending to a fair share of common sense and 
               <lb/>
               a knowledge of human nature, I will venture to say, that if there is one passion more powerful in 
               <lb/>
               the minds of Colonists of Anglo-Saxon origin than another, it is the passion for self―government; 
               <lb/>
               in all English communities there is an ardent passion for self-government. Colonists here, as 
               <lb/>
               everywhere else, are animated by an intense desire to govern themselves in the way they think 
               <lb/>
               best; and to delegate that power to others is destructive of every feeling of self-respect and of 
               <lb/>
               social and political liberty. ' 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It is not necessary for me to prove that this is the case, it is too notorious for comment; 
               <lb/>
               and as long as the spirit of liberty exists in the British Nation, we shall find that no one Province 
               <lb/>
               will submit to legislation at the hands of a Legislature in which its interests and welfare are 
               <lb/>
               overwhelmed and overborne. To secure submission to a Legislature such as that of the Dominion 
               <lb/>
               of Canada, where the majority of the Canadian Members make the law, uniformity of interest 
               <lb/>
               and feeling is necessary; and not only will the feeling of any separate Province be wounded by 
               <lb/>
               the consciousness that self-government is withheld from it, but on finding that its interests, or 
               <lb/>
               its feelings, are overwhelmed and subjected to the interests and feelings of a dominant portion, 
               <lb/>
               the sense of discontent and dissatisfaction will become universal and national, hence will ensue 
               <lb/>
               a condition of things most perilous 'to British interests generally. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            
            
            <p>
               The bond of union between Canada and the other Provinces bears no resemblance to the 
               <lb/>
               union between England and her Colonial Possessions. There is no natural love and original 
               <lb/>
               feeling of loyalty. The feeling of loyalty towards England is a feeling blind, instinctive, strong, 
               <lb/>
               born with us and impossible to be shaken off; and I believe it is impossible to transfer a feeling 
               <lb/>
               of loyalty and fealty at will. The connection between the Mother Country and a Colony—even a 
               <lb/>
               Crown Colony―is well understood in principle and in practice. The Mother Country guarantees 
               <lb/>
               the Colony from enemies abroad and the entire work of inter-colonial management is, except in 
               <lb/>
               matters of prerogative, left to the Colonists themselves. The Crown pretends to no dictation, 
               <lb/>
               nor has it any interest at variance with the interests of the Colonists, Although in a Crown 
               <lb/>
               Colony the official element is supreme, it is well understood that it is to govern—and public 
               <lb/>
               opinion forces it to govern—according to the well-understood and well-established wishes of 
               <lb/>
               the Colony at large. The Government can not and dare not interfere except to prevent crude, 
               <lb/>
               irrational, or vicious legislation. There is no direct conflict between the Mother Country and 
               <lb/>
               a Colony in these days; but it cannot be supposed that any British Province will submit patiently 
               <lb/>
               to injustice at the hands of a Canadian Ministry or a Canadian House of Commons. If any 
               <lb/>
               scheme has been devised more likely than another to raise and keep alive local irritation it is, 
               <lb/>
in my judgment, the scheme of Confederation on the basis of the Organic Act of 1867. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               What is said by Lord Granville is true in theory, but practically it is opposed to human 
               <lb/>
               nature; and in endeavouring to carry out elaborate and elevated views Great Britain stands a 
               <lb/>
               fair chance of losing the whole of British North America, 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Thus far I have treated of the general policy of the Organic Act. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            <p>
               With respect to the applicability of the scheme of Confederation to this Colony I have more 
               <lb/>
               special and particular grounds of objection, I consider such an union inexpedient on several 
               <lb/>
grounds.<lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            
            
            <pb n="29" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_029.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">29</fw>
            
            <p>
               First, the remoteness of the Colony from Canada; 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Secondly, the comparative insignificance of British Columbia; 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               And, thirdly, the diversity of its interests from those of Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               That these objections specially apply to the extension of the principle to this Colony no 
               <lb/>
               one can doubt. Lord Granville admits that the distance is an objection, but thinks that a 
               <lb/>
               Railway will annihilate time and space. He thinks that the Government can be carried on at 
               <lb/>
               a distance of 3,000 miles without difficulty. This Railway is to bridge over the vast desert that 
               <lb/>
               intervenes between this Colony and Ottawa. The notion that we can with any effect represent 
               <lb/>
               the interests of this Colony in the Parliament at Ottawa at a distance of 3,000 miles is to me 
               <lb/>
               absurd. With a population such as ours, even if we have the representation suggested by the 
               <lb/>
               terms, with eight Members of Parliament against one hundred and eighty-two, and four Senators 
               <lb/>
               against seventy―two, how can it be supposed to be possible that our voices could he heard? 
               <lb/>
               When Lord Granville spoke of "comprehensiveness" am "impartiality" in a Legislature, surely 
               <lb/>
               he must have lost sight of the constituent elements of a House of Commons. For let us consider, 
               <lb/>
               without any reflection upon the House of Commons at Ottawa, what is the nature of the House 
               <lb/>
               of Commons of England, or of any other assembly of the same nature? Every House of Commons 
               <lb/>
               is but an assemblage of the Members of Parliament pledged to support the material interests of 
               <lb/>
               their constituents, whenever those interests are affected. I never can anticipate anything but 
               <lb/>
               the representation of the views and the material interests of constituents in any House of 
               <lb/>
               Commons. I believe that members would always vote according to the interests of men whose 
               <lb/>
               votes they would have again to solicit, and of whose interests public opinion holds them to he 
               <lb/>
               the acknowledged advocates. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               How can we find eight men in a place like this, where at all events; the most valuable 
               <lb/>
               members of society are professional and business men, without selecting them from a class who 
               <lb/>
               are politicians by profession? Most men here are workers of some sort, and actively employed 
               <lb/>
               in their several professions and businesses, and we should have extreme difficulty in finding eight 
               <lb/>
               good men who wou|d spare the time and expense to go to Ottawa. What we should want would 
               <lb/>
               be such men as are now at Ottawa, the principal business men, bankers, merchants, and profes<lb break="no"/>sional men; but time and space will prevent this most valuable class of men from leaving British 
               <lb/>
               Columbia and representing our interests at Ottawa, and we shall be compelled either to retain 
               <lb/>
               the services of Canadian gentlemen, who, living in Canada, would be the British Columbian repre― 
               <lb/>
               sentatives only in name, or we should have to take eight representatives who will be content to 
               <lb/>
               make politics a profession, and we shall have to pay them for their services. To the insignifi<lb break="no"/>cance of British Columbia as a Province of the Dominion the same remarks apply. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Difference of interests is a still more material point. Upon this point direct conflict is sure 
               <lb/>
               to arise. Canada belongs to the Atlantic, and looks to the Old World for her markets. We are 
               <lb/>
               a new country, our staples are totally different. Questions cannot but arise between British 
               <lb/>
               Columbia and Canada—between the East and the West—in which Canadian interests will 
               <lb/>
               prevail over those of British Columbia; and aggravated by the feeling of wounded pride and 
               <lb/>
               forced insignificance, the Colonists of British Columbia will feel naturally aggrieved. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Colonial feeling is well known—pride and attachment to the Mother Country and 
               <lb/>
               intense sensitiveness and tenacity where injustice or wrong is done. Once let this feeling he 
               <lb/>
               roused amongst us and it will not be long before British Columbia is clamorous for repeal; 
               <lb/>
               and not obtaining it, the country will be ripe for any other change, however violent.<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Now, Sir, with respect to the third head of my objections. With respect to the mode in 
               <lb/>
               which the consent of this Colony is attempted to be obtained, I am sorry to notice what I cannot 
               <lb/>
               but call a spirit of diplomacy and a spirit of management characterizing the whole movement 
               <lb/>
               in favour of Confederation on the part of the Imperial Government, it is obvious throughout 
               <lb/>
               that the Imperial Government desires to obtain their end and aim of Confederation in a mer― 
               <lb/>
               cantile spirit of bargain and sale, which jars upon my feelings of right and wrong. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               If this Council is properly the Legislature of British Columbia; if we reflect the intelligence, 
               <lb/>
               the substance, and the interests of the Colony, we ought to have originated these Resolutions 
               <lb/>
               ourselves. The matter should have arisen spontaneously amongst us, without any attempt at 
               <lb/>
               leading or forcing. What may be His Excellency's own views upon the subject of Confederation 
               <lb/>
               we cannot tell. I look upon Lord Granville's despatch as a diplomatic order, couched in polite 
               <lb/>
               language, but nevertheless a requirement to the Governor to carry out the will of the Colonial 
               <lb/>
               Office, without reference to his own convictions. All that we are told by His Excellency upon 
               <lb/>
               
           
            
            <pb n="30" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_030.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">30</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
         
               this subject is that the Colony will derive "material benefit" from Confederation, and the Colony 
               <lb/>
               has been offered by the Executive certain material benefits in the shape of a Railway, a Dock, 
               <lb/>
               cash in hand, and freedom from debt, in return for the transfer of all legislation to the Dominion 
               <lb/>
               of Canada. These "material benefits " being paraded before the eyes of the colonists, the 
               <lb/>
               bargain is afterwards to be accepted or refused by a Council composed mainly of Representative 
               <lb/>
               Members. This mode of operation, no less than the bargain itself, is equally objectionable in 
               <lb/>
               my eyes. The material benefits—the Dock, the Railway, the money payments—are in effect 
               <lb/>
               nothing more than bribes to the present generation to forego the rights of self-government. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I have no doubt that the Colony will accept the bargain. The Colony is a small one, the 
               <lb/>
               population not exceeding 6,500 adult white men, and of these many are gentlemen of Canadian 
               <lb/>
               proclivities, Canadians by birth, who are naturally, and I may say patriotically, in favour of a 
               <lb/>
               union with their native country. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               There are many, also, who, in the present adverse condition of things in this Colony, are 
               <lb/>
               desirous of change of any kind, and eager for any opportunity of benefiting by operations which<lb/>
               promise to throw population, capital, and enterprise into the Colony. We have suffered much 
               <lb/>
               from pecuniary depression, and when we have an offer from a great country to come and spend 
               <lb/>
               money among us, can you doubt that any one will fail to feel these advantages; while many 
               <lb/>
               more hope for political power and eminence in a system which they expect will carry with it 
               <lb/>
               Representative Institutions, if not Responsible Government. Can we doubt that the vote will 
               <lb/>
               be in favour of Confederation? The people of this country will sell themselves for the con<lb break="no"/>sideration of the present, and posterity will hereafter ask indignantly what right had we to 
               <lb/>
               shackle them, and to deprive them of rights which cannot be sold. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We shall reap the benefit, and those that come after us will reap the disadvantage and 
               <lb/>
               humiliation. It is not in the power of the present generation to dispose of the birthright of 
               <lb/>
               its descendants. Liberty and self-government are inalienable rights. The original vice of the 
               <lb/>
               matter still remains, and when once the material benefits are enjoyed or forgotten, and the 
               <lb/>
               consciousness of disadvantage is apparent, reaction will set in; a party of repudiators and 
               <lb/>
               repealers will arise, who with great show of justice will clamorously demand the reversal of 
               <lb/>
               an organic change, founded on political error and wrong. Although our masters at Ottawa may 
               <lb/>
               be ever so amiable and ever so pure, the moment we feel the yoke we shall repent; it is not in 
               <lb/>
               the nature of Englishmen to submit to tyranny of any description; and dissent such as our 
               <lb/>
               posterity will express, will be on only too sound grounds. I say, Sir, that this matter ought not 
               <lb/>
               to be brought forward now, when the country is in a state of depression, ready to catch at 
               <lb/>
               anything. Recourse should not be now had to Representative Institutions for the first time, 
               <lb/>
               when the obvious effect is the acceptance by this Colony of a confederation which carries with 
               <lb/>
               it direct, immediate, pecuniary gain. Few have the self-denial to reject a bait so invitingly 
               <lb/>
               dangled before their eyes. If the Colonists are to be trusted with Representative Institutions, 
               <lb/>
               for the purpose of effecting so important and radical a constitutional change, why are they not 
               <lb/>
               to be trusted with Representative institutions altogether? It is notorious that the Colony is, 
               <lb/>
               probably with justice, considered by the Imperial Authorities unfit for full Representative Insti<lb break="no"/>tutions, and that a Council, with a predominant official element within it, is the only fit body 
               <lb/>
               to deal with important questions. Yet this Council is to be differently constituted, and the 
               <lb/>
               ultimate terms to be accepted by the people alone, for the sole purpose of forwarding the 
               <lb/>
               cause of Confederation. The whole scheme for effecting Confederation is but a scheme of 
               <lb/>
               temptation very difficult to forego, though it must be admitted recourse is not had to actual 
               <lb/>
               or practical force and obligation. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I have delivered my honest opinion on this matter, <hi rendition="simple:italic">liberavi animam mcam</hi>, I fear at great 
               <lb/>
               length. But I have spoken according to my conscientious convictions and a spirit of the truest 
               <lb/>
               loyalty. I am desirous to promote the interests of the British Nation; and I believe the present 
               <lb/>
               movement puts them in great peril. I have given you the best proof of my sincerity. I have 
               <lb/>
               spoken against my own interests. I have material interests in this Colony which will greatly 
               <lb/>
               benefit by the movement which will ensue from the building of a Railroad and a Dock. The 
               <lb/>
               interests of friends and connections who are dear to me will be much benefited; and those who 
               <lb/>
               know the world tell me that it would have been much better for me if I had bent before 
               <lb/>
               the storm which I cannot avoid; that the honours and rewards of my profession are not likely 
               <lb/>
               to be bestowed upon one who is no friend to a popular, an Imperial, and a Canadian movement; 
               <lb/>
               but I cannot act against political conviction. I am here to give honest counsel, and I have done 
               <lb/>
               it, come what may. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <pb n="31" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_031.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">31</fw>
            
            <p>
               The question has always appeared to me to be this :—Confederation with England, which 
               <lb/>
               we have; Confederation in its truest sense; Confederation with all the security of protection, 
               <lb/>
               and all the pride of self-government, now or hereafter to be, when the Colony shall have 
               <lb/>
               population and wealth sufficient: or Confederation—or, as it should be termed, " Incorporation "- <lb/> with Canada. Incorporation with a country to which we are bound by no natural tie of affection 
               <lb/>
               or duty, and remote in geographical position, and opposed to us in material interests Incor<lb break="no"/>poration with all the humiliation of dependence, and to my mind the certainty of reaction, 
               <lb/>
               agitation, and discontent. Canada can never become the <hi rendition="simple:italic">assignee</hi>, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">official assignee</hi>, the 
               <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">Downing Street official assignee</hi> of the affection and loyalty which exists between this depend<lb break="no"/>ency and the Mother Country. I am opposed to the political extinction of this Colony, and 
               <lb/>
               its subservience to the will of a majority of the House of Commons at Ottawa, and the admin<lb break="no"/>istration of its affairs by the political adherents of Canadian statesmen. And all this for 
               <lb/>
               what? For "material benefits," for a money consideration, in which the ring of the dollar 
               <lb/>
               only faintly conceals the clink of the fetter. I am grieved at the mode in which the change 
               <lb/>
               is sought to be effected, and view the bargain and sale of political independence for ourselves 
               <lb/>
               and our descendants for a few dollars in hand, and a few dollars in the future, as equally 
               <lb/>
               shameful and void. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Railway or no railway—consent or no consent—the transfer of Legislative power to 
               <lb/>
               Ottawa, to a place so remote in distance and in interest, is an injustice and a political 
               <lb/>
               extravagance which time will most surely establish. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName>, Member for Victoria District, then
                  rose and said :—Mr. President, <lb/> I congratulate you, Sir, and this House upon
                  the noble work on which we are engaged. We are <lb/> engaged, I believe, in
                  Nation-making. For my part I have been engaged in Nation-making for <lb/> the last
                  twelve years—ever since I have been engaged in politics in the Colony. [<persName ref="pers:ALST1">Hon
                  Registrar- <lb break="yes"/> General</persName>—"You have not made a Nation yet"] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> The Hon.
                  Registrar-General says that I have <lb/> not made a Nation yet. I need only, in
                  reply, quote for his enlightenment the old adage " Rome <lb/> was not built in a
                  day." [Laughter.] In the humble part that I have taken in politics, I have <lb/>
                  ever had one end in view. I have seen three Colonies united on the Pacific Coast.
                  [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Hon. Mr. <lb/> Helmcken</persName> ― "Three?"] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> Yes, three: Stekin, British Columbia, and
                  Vancouver Island; and if <lb/> I had had my way, instead of the United States
                  owning Alaska, it would have been British <lb/> today. I have advocated the union
                  of those three Colonies, and in the union of two of them <lb/> particularly I have
                  taken a prominent part. For many years I have regarded the union of <lb/> the
                  British Pacific Territories, and of their consolidation under one Government, as
                  one of the <lb/> steps preliminary to the grand consolidation of the British
                  Empire in North America. I still <lb/> look upon it in this light with the pride
                  and feeling of a native―born British American. From <lb/> the time when I first
                  mastered the institutes of physical and political geography I could see <lb/>
                  Vancouver Island on the Pacific, from my home on the Atlantic; and I could see a
                  time when <lb/> the British Possessions, from the United States boundary to the
                  Arctic Ocean, and extending <lb/> from the Atlantic to the Pacific, would be
                  consolidated into one great Nation. <lb/>
               </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Sir, my political course has been unlike that of most others in this Colony. Allow me to 
               <lb/>
               illustrate my meaning by the use of another old adage. My course has been that of " beating 
               <lb/>
               the bush whilst others caught the bird." My allegiance has been to principle, and the only 
               <lb/>
               reward I have asked or sought has been to see sound political principles in operation. There<lb break="no"/>fore, Sir, I say again that I congratulate you and this Honourable House on the noble work 
               <lb/>
               on which we are all engaged. <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We are here, Sir, laying the corner stone of a great Nation on the Pacific Coast. When 
               <lb/>
               we look at past history, we find some nations that date their origin in the age of fable; some 
               <lb/>
               have been produced by violence, and extended their empire by conquest. But we are engaged 
               <lb/>
               in building up a great Nation in the noon-day light of the nineteenth century, not by violence, 
               <lb/>
               not by wrong, but I hope, Sir, by the exercise of that common sense which the Honourable 
               <lb/>
               gentleman who preceded me called statesmanship. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It was not my intention yesterday to have taken up the attention of this House with any 
               <lb/>
               remarks until we were in Committee of the Whole, although I have taken, for historical 
               <lb/>
               purposes, ample notes of the debate. Allusions have, however, been made during the course of 
               <lb/>
               this debate, amongst others to myself. I am, therefore, compelled to crave the indulgence of 
               <lb/>
               the House for a time to set myself right before this Council and the country, and to add my 
               <lb/>
               
           
            <pb n="32" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_032.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">32</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
          
               humble opinion to those around me in favour of the consideration of this question in Com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the Whole. I shall support the general principle of Confederation [Hear, hear], as I 
               <lb/>
               have always done, if we get to the discussion of the terms proposed. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               First, Sir, let me allude to some of the statements of the Honourable the Attorney-General 
               <lb/>
               (Mr. Crease) and the Chief Commissioner of Lands and Works (Mr. Trutch), and to the 
               <lb/>
               Honourable Executive Member for Victoria City (Mr. Helmcken). Sir, I know something about  
               <lb/>
               the history of Confederation. Up to the opening of this Session Confederation has been  
               <lb/>
               a subject of agitation. It may properly be divided into several heads: Firstly, agi<lb break="no"/>tation; secondly, negotiation; thirdly, inauguration; and fourthly, I hope, successful 
               <lb/>
               operation. Now, Sir, it is apparent that every act of mine in reference to Confederation, up 
               <lb/>
               to the time it was announced in Earl Granville's despatch, up to the time His Excellency the 
               <lb/>
               Governor sent down his Message—every act of mine was in the line of agitation. It was with 
               <lb/>
               the view to bring about the consideration of terms with the Dominion Government; to hear 
               <lb/>
               what they would do; to bring the question before the people, and to canvass its defects and 
               <lb/>
               advantages, that I for one have agitated the question. In doing so I have come in for blows 
               <lb/>
               from open enemies and treason from false political friends. Sir, the era of agitation has now 
               <lb/>
               passed, and we advance to the era of negotiation. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               When I heard the Hon. Attorney―General, yesterday, invoking High Heaven; and when I 
               <lb/>
               heard him explaining the position of Official Members upon this question; when I heard him 
               <lb/>
               state that he was always in favour of Confederation, there flashed across my mind one of the<lb/>
               proverbs of Solomon, which I cannot refrain from repeating: " Such is the way of an adulterous 
               <lb/>
               woman; she eateth and wipeth her mouth and saith I have done no wickedness" [Laughter] 
               <lb/>
               Sir, I respect any Honourable Member who will, if he sees reason to change his opinion, come<lb/>
               down and frankly tell the honest truth; but when an Honourable Member tries to make political 
               <lb/>
               capital out of other men's labour, I confess I do not respect him. On the contrary, such men as 
               <lb/>
               the latter, when officers of a Government, remind me of the remark of a celebrated French 
               <lb/>
               philosopher, who said: "That in all the mysterious ways of Providence there is nothing so 
               <lb/>
               inscrutable as his purpose in committing the destiny of nations to such creatures as these." 
               <lb/>
               [Laughter]<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               There are men in this Colony entitled to some honour; some men who are entitled to praise 
               <lb/>
               for having brought Confederation to its; present stage; but they are not the Honourable gentle<lb break="no"/>man, the Minister of Justice, nor the Honourable the Chief Commissioner. [Hear, hear.] 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Is Earl Granville entitled to the credit of bringing this matter forward? Is Governor 
               <lb/>
               Musgrave, or his Cabinet, or the Officials? No, Sir, I should be doing wrong if I permitted it 
               <lb/>
               to be supposed that the credit was due to any one of them. I have assisted to make history, 
               <lb/>
               and this is a page of it. Let it go forth to the world that the people of this country have 
               <lb/>
               made Confederation the important question that it is to-day. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Hon. Chief Commissioner, whom we have heard with so much pleasure today, made an 
               <lb/>
               allusion to me. He said that when I brought this matter before the Council in 1868, that the 
               <lb/>
               Executive Council opposed Confederation then, and the present terms proved their wisdom in 
               <lb/>
               delaying the question at that time. On that occasion my object was only agitation to open 
               <lb/>
               negotiations. But, Sir, what did I hear at that time? "You pension the officials and we 
               <lb/>
               will all vote for Confederation." and I think I could mention another Executive Councillor who 
               <lb/>
               said: " Do you think we are such fools as to vote for Confederation without being provided for? " 
               <lb/>
               That was the kind of wisdom in vogue, in 1868. Sir, I again object to Hon. Members taking credit 
               <lb/>
               where no credit is due. [Hear, hear.] 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Let us turn now to the Honourable Member for Victoria City (Dr. Helmcken), once a warm 
               <lb/>
               and generous friend to Confederation; and what has been the result of his opposition? Impo<lb break="no"/>tence. He was impotent to retard the question. He was impotent to advance it. By impotent, 
               <lb/>
               I mean powerless. He was impotent to stem the course of events. He hung out the banner of 
               <lb/>
               Anti―Confederation in Victoria. and won his seat by crying: "down with Confederation." Before 
               <lb/>
               he contested the seat with me, I told him that the Canadian Government would not negotiate 
               <lb/>
               until the North―West Territory question was settled. Yet the Hon. Member for Victoria City 
               <lb/>
               charged me with backing down from Confederation. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            <p>
               The Hon. Member for New Westminster, also, denounced me in his elegant English in the 
               <lb/> <hi rendition="simple:italic">Columbian</hi> as giving up the cause of Confederation. But, Sir, why did I say that the 
               <lb/>
Canadian Government would not enter into negotiations with us? It was because I had in 
               <lb/>
               
           
            
            <pb n="33" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_033.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">33</fw>
            
        

               my pocket, at the time, a despatch from a Canadian Cabinet Minister, which said that the 
               <lb/>
               Dominion Government would not negotiate until the questions then pending with respect to the 
               <lb/>
               North-West Territory were settled. The Hon. Member for Victoria City held up, however, his 
               <lb/>
               puny arm against Confederation. But has he stopped it? No! Not a day, not an hour; for as 
               <lb/>
               soon as the North―West Territory question was settled, then came a despatch to the Governor 
               <lb/>
               to push on Confederation. I think I have said enough, Sir, to show that it was the people 
               <lb/>
               who took this matter in hand, and it is the people who will carry it through. [Hear, hear.] 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Although I have risen unprepared to make a set speech, there are still some points raised 
               <lb/>
               in debate which, in my opinion, require attention. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Hon. Attorney-General, after opening, his budget upon Confederation, has referred to 
               <lb/>
               the three courses which those terms had to take:—First, they are to be arranged by this House; 
               <lb/>
               next, to go to the Canadian Government; and, thirdly, to be ratified by the people of this 
               <lb/>
               Colony. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I hope, Sir, that this House will deal with these terms in the interests of British Columbia. 
               <lb/>
               I stand here not as a Canadian, but as a British Colombian; my allegiance is due first to British 
               <lb/>
               Columbia. I sincerely hope that these terms will be dealt with from a British Colombian 
               <lb/>
               point of view [Hear. hear, hear, hear], and first as to the money value of Confederation. 
               <lb/>
               [Hear, hear, from <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. Helmcken</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> It may grate on the ear of the once Solicitor-General (Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Wood) to mention money: but, Sir, I believe in the old adage that: "Money makes the mare 
               <lb/>
               to go." I do not intend to allude to the terms in the Resolutions at present, any further than 
               <lb/>
               to say, that I do not believe in going into Confederation without good terms. I believe that it 
               <lb/>
               would be traitorous to British Columbia to consent to Confederation without good terms; and 
               <lb/>
               that we would not do our duty if we did not insist upon getting them. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Hon. Attorney―General asks why we are not prosperous? In my opinion, Sir, the 
               <lb/>
               causes of our want of prosperity are various. They first arose under the administration of 
               <lb/>
               Sir James Douglas in 1858, and have been perpetuated down to the present day. The people 
               <lb/>
               were then almost driven away, and down to the present time the Government have done 
               <lb/>
               nothing comparatively to induce population to settle in the Colony. Another reason is, that 
               <lb/>
               the country is somewhat rugged, and not so attractive for settlement as some others. The 
               <lb/>
               Hon. Member for Victoria City says that it is our proximity to the United States. I most 
               <lb/>
               respectfully deny it. Population would have come if greater efforts had been made to get it. 
               <lb/>
               The Attorney―General is consistent in one thing. He said in 1867, and he says in his 
               <lb/>
               speech now, that British Columbia is of vital importance to Canada. I cannot see it. I 
               <lb/>
               cannot see why the Canadian Railway, if this was a foreign country and our boundary 
               <lb/>
               coterminous with that of Canada, might not have run through to connect with our railway 
               <lb/>
               system, as the French railways connect with those of Belgium. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               When sitting in the Vancouver Island House of Assembly, in the place now occupied by 
               <lb/>
               the Hon. Chief Commissioner, I defined British Colonists to be politically, nothing but subordi<lb break="no"/>nate Englishmen; and I contend, Sir, that Confederation will give us equal political rights 
               <lb/>
               with the people of Great Britain. In labouring for this cause, Sir, my idea has been and is 
               <lb/>
               to assist in creating a nationality—a sovereign and independent nationality. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Now, I come to the Hon. Member for Victoria City again. I really confess, Mr. President, 
               <lb/>
               that I expected more sterling opposition from that Hon. gentleman, I thought we had here 
               <lb/>
               the modern Charles Martel, the celebrated armed warrior who had gone out to drive the 
               <lb/>
               Saracens—the Canadians—back across the Rocky Mountains. I thought that he would have 
               <lb/>
               protested like Paul the Protestant. [Dr. Helmcken—" What became of St. Paul?"] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> Paul was 
               <lb/>
               converted, and I hope the Hon. Member may share the same fate. [Laughter.] I expected the 
               <lb/>
               Hon. Member to have deliverd a philippic, that would have done honour to Demosthenes when 
               <lb/>
               declaiming against Philip of Macedon. But, I really don't know but what he has been set up 
               <lb/>
               as a target by the Government—a man of straw—to draw the shot of all the Confederate party. 
               <lb/>
               I don't know why he was taken into the Executive Council. I thought that this Council was 
               <lb/>
               an united and impenetrable phalanx, but it seems that it is otherwise. What a happy family 
               <lb/>
               that Executive Council must be! The Member for Caribou and the Member for the City differ 
               <lb/>
               in their views, and both differ in this House from the Honourable Executive Councillors at 
               <lb/>
               the other end of the table. It is like Barnum's happy family. But the Honourable gentleman 
               <lb/>
               has told us some things which are good, and besides that he is going to raise other issues. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. Helmcken</persName> ― "I?"] 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
        
            <pb n="34" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_034.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">34</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
            <p>
               <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> Yes, the Honourable gentleman said that the issue would be raised at the next election, 
               <lb/>
               between going to Canada and going somewhere else. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. Helmcken</persName> ―"I said that I thought it very probable if mean terms were proposed by 
               <lb/>
               Canada, the people would raise other issues."] 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p><supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> O! "the people," those much abused words. I believe in the people when they are right. 
               <lb/>
               But the Honourable gentleman did threaten to raise the issue of going somewhere else. Now, 
               <lb/>
               Sir, where else except to Canada could we go? The Honourable Member talks of the agri<lb break="no"/>cultural interests. Why, Sir, by going somewhere else, these interests from Comox to Sooke, 
               <lb/>
               and from Soda Creek and Kamloops to the Lower Fraser would be destroyed. The country<lb/>
               would be flooded by produce from the United States. From Comox to Sooke, from the delta of 
               <lb/>
               the Fraser to Cariboo, the farming interests would be destroyed by going somewhere else. If 
               <lb/>
               that question came up, Sir, the farmers would quickly put it down. The Honourable Member 
               <lb/>
               for Victoria City says that the question comes here by desire of Her Majesty's Government. 
               <lb/>
               Sir, I say again, that it comes here by desire of the people, a large proportion of whom have 
               <lb/>
               asked Her Majesty's Government and the Government at Ottawa to bring it here. I am thank<lb break="no"/>ful that the question of Confederation is here. The Honourable gentleman says it is a 
               <lb/>
               Government measure, and that the terms must he passed. I say, again, that I hope terms will 
               <lb/>
               be passed of such a character as will contribute to the prosperity and happiness of this Colony. 
               <lb/>
               The Honourable Executive Councillor   that this is a Government measure, and that it 
               <lb/>
               ought to be an open question. Why does he not retire from his seat then? I would not be 
               <lb/>
               a candidate for his place. ' 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr Helmcken</persName> ―" There are no candidates. The Executive Council are appointed."] 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> Then I am sorry for the choice that has been made. Why, Sir, the programme settled by  
               <lb/>
               Government would leave it virtually an open question by referring the terms to a popular vote. <lb/>
               I may have something to say upon that hereafter. How patriotic will the Honourable gentleman<lb/>
               be when he goes outside, and says that this nominative Council, pre ded over by a paid Colonial<lb/>
               Secretary, have done this! How very easy it is for an Honourable gentleman to talk about the<lb/>
               autocracy of Government, when it suits him to do so. Look at his conduct in voting supplies.<lb/>
               When my Honourable friend on my left (the Member for Lillooet) tried to bring in a Bill to 
               <lb/>
               repeal the Crown Salaries Acts, was he not choked off by the Honourable Member for Victoria. 
               <lb/>
               City objecting first? But I am only delaying the House. [Hear, hear.] The Honourable 
               <lb/>
               Magisterial Member for Victoria City says " hear, hear." Now, Sir, as far as I am concerned, 
               <lb/>
               the Honourable Member has my full permission to withdraw. [Laughter.] I have always been 
               <lb/>
               ready to take a British subject vote on this question; but the Honourable Member for Victoria 
               <lb/>
               has always  dissented from that proposal. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Honourable Member for Victoria City has a remarkable way of putting things. But a 
               <lb/>
               few days ago he stated in this House, that if the people will only support the Government in 
               <lb/>
               getting the terms proposed, all will be right. I quote from the Colonist newspaper of 20th 
               <lb/>
               February, 1870, in which the Honourable gentleman is made to say, "I hope the people will 
               <lb/>
               support the Government in trying to get terms." He now comes down here and opposes them. 
               <lb/>
               [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. Helmcken</persName> —"I don't oppose the terms. I oppose Confederation."] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> A distinction without 
               <lb/>
               a difference. The Honourable Executive Councillor says the time is inopportune. I say, Sir. 
               <lb/>
               that now is the time. If the new gold discoveries, which have been mentioned in the course of 
               <lb/>
               this debate, really exist, now is the time to confederate, and to take means to attract and retain 
               <lb/>
               population. I have spent five years of my life in the mining districts of California, and 
               <lb/>
               have helped to build up town after town; but how are they now? Many of these towns which 
               <lb/>
               had their 5,000 inhabitants have almost none now. It will be the same with our gold-mining 
               <lb/>
               towns. I fear the Honourable gentleman will always say the time is inopportune, not only 
               <lb/>
               before the population arrives, but when it is here, and after it goes. If we can make a good 
               <lb/>
               bargain with Canada, by all means let us make it, and make it now. I like the word bargain, 
               <lb/>
               it sounds like business. What did the Honourable Member for Victoria say at the last election?- <lb/> " Don't let us have Confederation, for we shall have a surplus revenue of $100,000 in 1869, and 
               <lb/>
               we will do better without Confederation." Confederation was inopportune then. There was a 
               <lb/>
               large deficit or falling off in the revenue for 1869, and yet he says it is inopportune now. He 
               <lb/>
               said yesterday, we shall have a reduction of the public debt in 1873 of about $36,000, and by 
               <lb/>
               funding the floating debt make another saving of $15,000 per year. So that for a paltry saving 
               <lb/>
               of $50,000 three years hence, the Confederation question is now inopportune, I am surprised at 
               <lb/>
               
        
            
            <pb n="35" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_035.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">35</fw>
            
            
          
               the Honourable gentleman. First, it is inopportune, because of the present depression; second, 
               <lb/>
               inopportune at the last election, because things looked so bright; thirdly, inopportune now, 
               <lb/>
               because we can save $50,000. Your predecessor as Minister of Finance, Mr. President, promised 
               <lb/>
               great things, but the Governor's Message with the Estimates shows how they have turned out. 
               <lb/>
               I do not deal in prophesy, but in facts. Let any one look at Cariboo. Look at Victoria. If we 
               <lb/>
               wait for the time to be opportune, we may wait until it is too late. Suppose any unforeseen 
               <lb/>
               accident were to happen to our gold mines. If the golden spring is dried up, the golden stream 
               <lb/>
               that now flows from Cariboo to Victoria will be dried up also. We are asked by the Honourable 
               <lb/>
               Member for Victoria to wait for the Census of 1871. What has the census of Canada to do with 
               <lb/>
               the question? The basis of population as set forth in these terms is all fiction. It does not come 
               <lb/>
               up to my idea of nation-making. Why not deal with facts? Why set up some legal fiction of 
               <lb/>
               John Doe and Richard Roe? I want facts, not fiction. Let us base our financial calculations 
               <lb/>
               upon facts, and the rest will work itself out satisfactorily. Much has been said, during the 
               <lb/>
               debate, about the Red River Territory and its settlement. For my part I don't care if the Red 
               <lb/>
               River difficulty is never settled, so far as it bears on the question before the Council. I believe 
               <lb/>
               that the Red River country and the valley of the two Saskatchewans are not so favourable for 
               <lb/>
               settlement as some amongst us are accustomed to assert. But whether the North―West Territory 
               <lb/>
               is confederated or not, I go in for Confederation, because I believe we can make terms, and 
               <lb/>
               good terms, with Canada. The Honourable Member for Victoria City talks of the drawbacks 
               <lb/>
               to Confederation arising out of the vast extent of country, and our great distance from the seat 
               <lb/>
               of the Federal Government. That will hardly scare anybody, with the example of the United 
               <lb/>
               States before us. Next he says that the Dominion is only an experiment, and that it may break 
               <lb/>
               up. How often have I heard people predict that the United States, as a nation, must break up, 
               <lb/>
               as it was only an experiment. Why, Sir, they forget that the States had existed as separate 
               <lb/>
               Government's for one hundred and fifty years before their union. So with the Provinces of the 
               <lb/>
               Dominion of Canada; they existed as separate Governments for the last hundred to two hundred 
               <lb/>
               years, and Confederation is but the application of long-tried principles to a larger territory. 
               <lb/>
               Why did not the Honourable Member for Victoria City, when he said there were defects in the 
               <lb/>Confederation machine, tell us what the great defects in the machine were? He has merely 
               <lb/>
               raised up a scarecrow. Then he says it is absurd to ally ourselves to people who were 3,000 
               <lb/>miles away; but nothing in his argument showed me that the absurdity was proven. I remem<lb break="no"/>ber, Sir, when the communication between California and Washington was by Panama and 
               <lb/>
               Nicaragua. Was California then less to the United States than now? We now can hold com<lb break="no"/>munication with Ottawa by San Francisco and the Pacific Railroad, and will be as near to our 
               <lb/>
               Central Government as Washington Territory. The Honourable Member speaks of people 3,000 
               <lb/>
               miles away being unable to do as well for us as we could do for ourselves. I believe they could 
               <lb/>
               do just as well, so far as some general principles are concerned, if we only settled the conditions 
               <lb/>
               properly. With regard to the States of the neighbouring Republic getting on better than the 
               <lb/>
               Provinces or ourselves, I would ask, where is the progress of Washington Territory, as com<lb break="no"/>pared with our own country? [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr Helmcken</persName> ―" It contains a much larger population"] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> The 
               <lb/>
               population is only five thousand voters!<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Honourable gentleman is pursuing the same devious course as he did in past years, 
               <lb/>
               when he opposed reform, when our Government might have been beneficial to the Colony, had 
               <lb/>
               it been based on the popular will. He says that the deposition of the Free Port drove people 
               <lb/>
               out of the Colony. I take this occasion to state that, in my belief, the deposition of the Free 
               <lb/>
               Port was the commencement: of the permanent prosperity of this city, and brought in its train 
               <lb/>
               the dawning of prosperity throughout the whole district, from Comox to Sooke. which includes 
               <lb/>
               the district which I have the honour to represent, and which now numbers six hundred voters, 
               <lb/>
               all of whom are prosperous. There, Sir, lies the key-stone of Confederation! If the terms 
               <lb/>
               between British Columbia and Canada do not protect the farming interests, the largest and the 
               <lb/>
               only permanent interest in this Colony, Confederation will do no good. If it does not protect 
               <lb/>
               the farming interest, I vote against Confederation, first, last, and all the time. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It would be most unwise to join Canada without protection. We must have a control over 
               <lb/>
               certain imports in the terms, for a protective tariff is the only inducement to farmers to remain 
               <lb/>
               upon the soil. We depend upon them to build up a permanent interest in the country, that will 
               <lb/>
               last for ever. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               We most certainly do want extension of commerce but the true mode to obtain extension 
               <lb/>
               is to add to its volume internally. First, I believe in developing internal trade and industry; 
               <lb/>
               
        
            
            <pb n="36" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_036.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">36</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
            
      
               next, I believe in external trade. Allow these terms as brought down by the Government to 
               <lb/>
               pass, and in a few years you will reduce Victoria to the position of a mere smuggling village. 
               <lb/>
               Protection is a necessity. So long as there are nations and national interests, so long will it be 
               <lb/>
               necessary to have laws to protect those interests. Allow me, Sir, on this point to say that there 
               <lb/>
               is a great revolution in the value of realty, capital, and labour commencing on the Pacific Coast. 
               <lb/>
               The equalization of the value of realty, capital, and labour has commenced. The whole tendency 
               <lb/>
               of events in the countries to the south of us is to equalize the value of labour, of real estate, of 
               <lb/>
               capital, of manufactures, and of produce on this coast with their value on the Atlantic side. 
               <lb/>
               No such revolution in values has over occurred on the Pacific Coast, except that produced by 
               <lb/>
               the discovery of gold, as has been produced since the opening of the Pacific Railroad. Take off 
               <lb/>
protection, then, from our farmers, and they are reduced to the condition of agriculturists to the 
               <lb/>
               south of us, who will be reduced to the condition of those in the east. No doubt the prices of 
               <lb/>
               our farmers will be reduced by the revolution that is going on; but give them protection against 
               <lb/>
               foreign competition, and there will still be inducement for them to remain. The Honourable <lb/>
Chief Commissioner referred to this in a very proper spirit; and the Honourable Member for 
               <lb/>
               New Westminster says that it is one of the most important questions. I hope, therefore, that 
               <lb/>
               the subject will have due weight with them. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
            
            <p>
               The Government of Canada, according to the proposed terms, would give us a surplus revenue 
               <lb/>
               of $200,000. [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. Helmcken</persName> —" No."] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> The Honourable Member says no. He may be right. But 
               <lb/>
               upon the calculation that we shall have $200,000 surplus revenue, I say that this subsidy will be 
               <lb/>
               equivalent to four hundred farmers who earn in the Colony $500 each, annually. By taking 
               <lb/>
               off protection from our farmers. to get the $200,000, we would injure the country instead of 
               <lb/>
               benefiting it. But get the surplus of $200,000, and at the same time protection for our farmers, 
               <lb/>
               and we will do a prosperous business under Confederation. This is what we have to arrange, 
               <lb/>
               what we have to get into the terms, [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. Helmcken</persName> ―" All right! I will help you"] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> I would 
               <lb/>
               say that " extremes meet," for I now meet in Honourable friend (I mean political enemy) [" No, 
               <lb/>
               no,"] to secure protection. I do not see, with the Honourable Member for Victoria City, that we 
               <lb/>
               can get all we want without Confederation by a judicious arrangement of tour own tariff. I can 
               <lb/>
               show that what we want most in this Colony population, and that population employed in a 
               <lb/>
               remunerative manner. Isolation will not secure population. Confederation on proper terms will 
               <lb/>
               give us population; will give us means to employ labour remuneratively; will enlarge our com<lb break="no"/>merce, and build up our industry. If it give us public works,—if it give us a railroad from a 
               <lb/>
               point on the Fraser, below Yale, to Savona's Ferry on Lake Kamloops,—and if we connect Lake 
               <lb/>
               Okanagan with the Spel-mah-cheen River, by railway, which is only about thirteen miles—not 
               <lb/>
               only will the whole country from Osoyoos Lake, on the boundary, behind the Cascades, be 
               <lb/>
               opened up and connected with our chief commercial city, with a cheap and speedy means of 
               <lb/>
               transportation, but all this tract of country traversed by the railways and lake communication 
               <lb/>
               will be utilized in producing wheat and wool, and other articles for exportation. Victoria, then, 
               <lb/>
               will be built up, and will be the chief commercial city of British Columbia, with all other parts 
               <lb/>
               of the Colony tribute to her. This is what Confederation on proper terms will do for us. The 
               <lb/>
               Honourable Member tor Victoria said that no lasting union could be maintained, unless the 
               <lb/>
               interests of British Columbia are preserved, if I look (for argument sake) at these things from 
               <lb/>
               a Canadian point of view, I find that by serving the interests of Brilish Columbia, the interests 
               <lb/>
               of Canada will be served. Canada, as well as British Columbia, will benefit by a protective duty 
               <lb/>
               here. Canada will get the revenue under protection, and British Columbia will have its industry 
               <lb/>
               protected from foreign competition. And there is no reason that we should not have our 
               <lb/>
               interests protected, [<persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. Helmcken</persName> —"The Organic Act says no."] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> The Organic Act says no 
               <lb/>
               such thing. Confederation is diversity in unity: really and essentially a general unity, and an 
               <lb/>
               application of law to diverse interests. First, we find that New Brunswick, under the Organic 
               <lb/>
               Act, gets a temporary subsidy of $63,000 per anuum. None of the other Provinces receive any 
               <lb/>
               temporary subsidy under that Act. New Brunswick is allowed to collect export dues on lumber. 
               <lb/>
               All the other Provinces are prohibited from levying dues on lumber. Now, if New Brunswick 
               <lb/>
               gets an additional subsidy, and levies a lumber tax prohibited to the other Provinces, why cannot 
               <lb/>
               British Columbia get exemption from uniformity in her favour? Nova Scotia gets two subsidies, 
               <lb/>
               equal to $160,000, which are not in the Organic Act. The Crown lawyers say that the grant, is 
               <lb/>
               not unconstitutional. This is a noted exception, made to satisfy the Nova Scotia repeal party. 
               <lb/>
               Another exception is found in the compulsory provision that appointments to the Judiciary shall 
               <lb/>
               be made from the Bar of the Provinces for which the appointment is made, till the laws and 
               <lb/>
         
            
            <pb n="37" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_037.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">37</fw>
            
          

               practice are assimilated. If the Organic Act is wrong, I say change the Act. But I believe 
               <lb/>
               that I have successfully shown that exceptions have been and can be made under the Organic 
               <lb/>
               Act. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Now, let us see what this horrible Canadian tariff is. It is too high on cattle for us; not 
               <lb/>
               high enough on bacon, butter, cheese, and lard by a few cents; and imposes nothing on hay, 
               <lb/>
               hops, and grain of all kinds. I explained the whole to my constituents, at eleven meetings, and 
               <lb/>
               they said, get these few alterations made to suit us, and we will support Confederation. So we 
               <lb/>
               must have an alteration. Why, Sir, under the English Constitution different tariffs can be 
               <lb/>
               imposed. Look at the difference in the excise spirit duties that were levied formerly in Scotland 
               <lb/>
               and England, for instance. As a lawyer, not as a judge, I give my opinion that we can have one 
               <lb/>
               tariff in British Columbia, and another in the Atlantic Provinces, under the Organic Act; and if 
               <lb/>
               the Act does not allow it, then we must alter it. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I have already given notice of motion respecting protection for our farmers and manufac<lb break="no"/>turers. I desire to add a resolution to the proposed terms, keeping the power in the hands of 
               <lb/>
               the Local Legislature to impose a tax on certain imports, in case the tariff be too low. With 
               <lb/>
               respect to brewers, the tariff can easily be arranged so as to protect them; and the Honourable 
               <lb/>
               Member for New Westminster has answered the objection to the Dominion fishery laws. As for 
               <lb/>
               commerce, that common sense that the Hon. Mr. Woods calls statesmanship, will settle that; 
               <lb/>
               for if Confederation would injure the commercial interests of British Columbia, it would also 
               <lb/>
               injure the interests of the Dominion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Honourable Member for Victoria City has said a great deal about centralization. But 
               <lb/>
               I say, Sir, that there must be a centre somewhere. We cannot have it in British Columbia, and 
               <lb/>
               a centre would be no worse in Ottawa than in Washington. The Pacific Coast, so far as the 
               <lb/>
               United States are concerned, is represented at Washington, which is not so large a city as 
               <lb/>
               New York. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Representation is one of the most important elements in free Governments; and as it has 
               <lb/>
               been urged by the Hon. Mr. Wood and others, that British Columbia would not he heard in the 
               <lb/>
               Canadian Senate or Commons, and that our small delegation would be crushed and out-voted, 
               <lb/>
               I will briefly examine the subject. Now, Sir, the whole of the Pacific States of the United 
               <lb/>
               States have only twelve Representatives in Congress―six in the Senate and six in the House of 
               <lb/>
               Representatives. California has two Senators and three Representatives; Oregon, two Senators 
               <lb/>
               and one Representative; Washington Territory, one Delegate; and Nevada, two Senators and 
               <lb/>
               one Representative. Now, it is proposed in the Resolutions to grant to British Columbia twelve 
               <lb/>
               Members—four in the Senate and eight in the Commons―a number equal to the whole represen<lb break="no"/>tation of the Pacific States, with 1,000,000 people, in the United States Congress. Again, there 
               <lb/>
               are only five States that have more than twelve Members in Congress. They are New York, 
               <lb/>
               Pennsylvania, Illinois, Indiana, and Ohio. Take another glance at the representation of the 
               <lb/>
               States most remote from Washington. Texas has five Members; Florida, three; Maine, seven; 
               <lb/>
               and California, five. Remoteness and small numbers have never caused any of those States to 
               <lb/>
               be treated unfairly. Under the popular system of government there, the small States do not go 
               <lb/>
               to the wall. Has little Delaware gone to the wall? Has Rhode Island gone to the wall? No; 
               <lb/>
               neither would British Columbia go to the wall in the Parliament of Canada. The Government 
               <lb/>
               of Canada is based on the popular will; and that is the highest of guarantee that we shall be 
               <lb/>
               treated fairly by the Dominion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I have never heard of Scotland being injured because she had a smaller representation in 
               <lb/>
               Parliament than England. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>[<persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. Wood</persName>—"Yes, yes. Two revolutions followed immediately upon union"]<lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> Yes; but that don't affect my proposition. A little blood-letting, however, does no harm 
               <lb/>
               occasionally. I would not object to a little revolution now and again in British Columbia after 
               <lb/>
               Confederation, if we were treated unfairly; for I am one of those who believe that political 
               <lb/>
               hatreds attest the vitality of a State. [Hear, hear.] 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Honourable and learned Member for Victoria says that all power will be taken away 
               <lb/>
               by Confederation. Why, Sir, the Honourable gentleman cannot have read the Organic Act. <lb/>
               For he will find the exclusive powers of the Dominion and the Provinces clearly set forth in it. 
               <lb/>
               Then, Sir, on the question of guarantee for the fulfilment of the conditions by Canada, there 
               <lb/>
               appears to be some misapprehension in the Honourable gentleman's mind. In point of fact, we 
               <lb/>
               have a guarantee from the Imperial Government. If the Dominion refuse to keep the terms 
               <lb/>
               and repudiate their part of the bargain, we can appeal to the Imperial Government to release us. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <pb n="38" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-03-10_Page_038.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">38</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            
            <p>
               [<persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon Mr. Wood</persName> ―" Let us have it in black and white."] 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
              <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> Why, let the Act be repealed and down go the terms. The sovereign power is in the 
               <lb/>
               Parliament of England. It made the Act, and if it is violated without redress, it can repeal 
               <lb/>
               it, and the power of Canada ceases. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The Honourable and learned Member for Victoria City has referred to the possibility of 
               <lb/>
               a Fenian invasion, and said what will become of the Railway in such an event. I believe, Sir, 
               <lb/>
               on such an extraordinary occasion, such as invasion, each one in the Colony would be patriotic 
               <lb/>
               enough to do without a few miles of Railway, until the invasion may be put down. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               It has been asked what is the gain under Confederation. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               At present we have no surplus revenue. But with Confederation on equitable terms, there 
               <lb/>
               will be a clear gain of $384,000 annually from subsidies and reduction of tariff; therefore, as 
               <lb/>
               $384,000 is to nothing, so is Confederation to Isolation. There are a great many points to 
               <lb/>
               which I could allude were I disposed to trespass longer on the time of the Council; but I reserve 
               <lb/>
               them until we go into Committee. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               There are, however, some few things to which I will passingly allude. It is important to 
               <lb/>
               British Columbia to know what will be the qualification of Members to the Dominion Parliament 
               <lb/>
               [Hear, hear, from <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr Helmcken</persName>] <supplied><persName ref="pers:DECO1">The Hon. Mr. DeCOSMOS</persName></supplied> and the qualification of electors. And with reference to 
               <lb/>
               the Local Constitution, it may be necessary for us to know whether our Governors cannot be 
               <lb/>
               elected as in the United States. instead of being appointed on the English principle; and 
               <lb/>
               whether we may not acquire the right to pass local laws over the veto of the Governor, by a 
               <lb/>
               two-third vote of the Legislature. The usury laws, imprisonment for debt, and many other 
               <lb/>
               matters will require careful consideration and attention. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               With respect to the main principle, I am in favour of Confederation, provided the financial 
               <lb/>
               terms are right in amount, and if the other terms will contribute to the advancement and 
               <lb/>
               protection of our industry. If we cannot get favourable terms, which I believe we can, it will 
               <lb/>
               then be for the people of this country to say whether we shall remain in isolation or seek some<lb/>
               other more favourable union. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The debate was here adjourned until Friday, at 1 o'clock. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>



     <!-- GL, 2017-03-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->       
         
            
           <!-- <p>
               FRIDAY, 11th MARCH, 1870. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The debate was resumed by the Hon. Mr. RING, who on rising was greeted with cries of 
               <lb/>
               " Spoke, spoke." 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Hon. Mr. Ring said:—Sir, I have only spoken to the amendment, and have a right to speak 
               <lb/>
               to the original motion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Doubts were expressed as to the Hon. gentleman's right to speak a second time, but the 
               <lb/>
               Presiding Member was not called upon to decide, and Mr. Ring proceeded :<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <p>Sir. the Hon. Member for Victoria District commenced by congratulating the Council on 
               <lb/>
               having the grand question of Confederation now before them. He congratulated them on the 
               <lb/>
               great advantage of being able to grapple with a great question like this. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I cannot compliment him on the way in which he introduced his subject. I admire his 
               <lb/>
               perseverance and confess that on many subjects he enlightens Members on both sides of the 
               <lb/>
               House. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               I lament to find that having alluded to the opening speech of the Attorney-General, he 
               <lb/>
               thought fit to cast unwarrantable imputations upon that gentleman and the members of the 
               <lb/>
               Government. He suddenly turned aside and quoted a text, which he applied to the Official 
               <lb/>
               Members of this Council, He likened one of them to a woman who forgets her modesty and 
               <lb/>
               shame and goes after lovers for broad; to her who has a harlot's forehead, and refuses to 
               <lb/>
               be ashamed. Sir, I deprecate such allusions; they throw no light upon the subject. I think 
               <lb/>
               that an Honourable and grave body like this, on hearing such charges, should have at once 
               <lb/>
               risen to express their indignation rather than have condoned it by their silence. Nothing is 
               <lb/>
               more easy than to take any one act of a man, or of a body of men, and apply it to a sinister 
               <lb/>
               motive, when it is capable of an honourable one, Sir. I was very glad that the Hon. Attorney. 
               <lb/>
               General had the courage to follow the example of the English House of Commons. He, finding 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>-->
            
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>