<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgBCLC_1870-04-06" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgBCLC">British Columbia Legislative Council</name>, <date when="1870-04-06">6 April 1870</date>, Province of BC, Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>W.S. Sebright Green</editor>
          
         
               <title>Legislative Council, Debate on the Subject of Confederation with Canada</title>.
                    

          <date when="1912"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Victoria, B.C.</pubPlace>: <publisher>William H. Cullin</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="165"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_157.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_158.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_159.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_160.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_161.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
<item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_162.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_163.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_164.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_165.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-03-22">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-22">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-25">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_157">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_157.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_158">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_158.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_159">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_159.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_160">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_160.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_161">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_161.jpg"/>
      </surface>
<surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_162">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_162.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_163">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_163.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_164">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_164.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_165">
         <graphic url="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_165.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="157" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_157.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">157</fw>
           
<!-- GL, 2017-03-22, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

<!-- <p> 
     Hon. MR. WALKEM—Sir, I have made few speeches during this debate, but this is a 
     <lb/>
     question on which I must ask leave to say a few words. Session after Session the question has 
     <lb/>
     been brought down We have had always a large Victoria element, and this question has. 
     <lb/>
     unfortunately, always taken a Victoria and Mainland issue. I have studied this matter care<lb break="no"/>fully. With regard to the Acts themselves they are very strong; they commence with preambles 
     <lb/>
     as to construction, maintenance, and repair. The toll was not mentioned as to continue merely 
     <lb/>
     until the debt was extinguished, therefore I think the vote should be taken on another view. 
     <lb/>
     The benefits accrue equally to Victoria and the Upper Country; probably the farmer gets the 
     <lb/>
     lion's share; I know the Upper Country pretty well: formerly the miner used nothing outside 
     <lb/>
     of bacon and flour. This should not he made an Island and Mainland question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Dr. HELMCKEN —I do not regard the subject as a joke. We have paid $60,000 for 
     <lb/>
     roads on Vancouver Island—roads not one-twentieth the length of those on the Mainland. 
     <lb/>
     Victoria gets more kicks than halfpence. Victoria pays the greater part of the tolls. I belong 
     <lb/>
     to a company who pay a large proportion. What do they propose in place of a road toll? 
     <lb/>
     Some one must pay it. Thirty thousand dollars per annum is required to keep roads in repair. 
     <lb/>
     I say Victoria and Vancouver Island are more concerned with What is for the good of the 
     <lb/>
     Colony, generally, than any part of the Mainland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS—l rise to bear testimoin to the fairness of the Hon. Members for 
     <lb/>
     Vancouver Island in whatever concerns the Mainland. I have always seen a desire on the part 
     <lb/>
     of Vancouver Island Members to legislate for the whole, and not for a part, of the Colony. 
     <lb/>
     I am as tired of this bickering as any Member of the Mainland. I consider it our duty to be 
     <lb/>
     more united. It the Hon. Members for New Westminster and Yale would talk less about 
     <lb/>
     injustice to the Mainland it would be better. I regret the action of the Hon. Member for 
     <lb/>
     Yale; it is factions. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Hon. MR. BARNARD—Vancouver Island has always made practical jokes of any questions 
     <lb/>from the Mainland. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. DECOSMOS rose to order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. BARNARD—l referred to the Hon. gentleman for Victoria City. There are no 
     <lb/>
     road tolls on Vancouver Island. (Yes a road tax! —Hon. Dr. Helmckenl As soon as the roads 
     <lb/>
     are paid for the people or the Mainland will, to a man, refuse to pay any more road tolls. Every 
     <lb/>
     item has been used as a threat against Confederation. I do not offer any such threat. I believe 
     <lb/>
     the Upper Country would accept Confederation on the terms proposed; but if the Government 
     <lb/>
     expect that they will be able to collect this $60,000 from the population of the Upper Country 
     <lb/>
     they are mistaken.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. DECOSMOS —The Hon. Member for Yale is unjust to Vancouver Islanders. The 
     <lb/>
     Whole ot' this Colony is paying large sums of money for interest on debt on roads. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. BARNARD)—I did not say what I did with reference to Vancouver Island 
     <lb/>
     Members without consideration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. ROBSON—I hope that Government Members. in view of the absence of the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Chief Commissioner, will vote so as to allow this resolution to go forward. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL—I must express a contrary hope. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The amendment of Hon. Mr. Barnard was carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Committee rose and reported the resolutions complete. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Council resumed. and the resolutions passed in Committee were adopted, except those with 
     <lb/>
     regard to the purchase of Alaska and the State of Maine. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     WEDNESDAY, 6TH APRIL, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The Hon. Attorney-General. in the absence of the Hon. Colonial Secretary, Presiding 
     <lb/>
     Member. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On motion, the House resolved itself into Committee of the Whole, to take into consideration 
     <lb/>
     the Message of His Excellency the Governor respecting the provision to be made for the sending. 
     <lb/>
     of Delegates to Ottawa. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Ball in the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <pb n="158" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_158.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">158</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
            

<p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Hon. COLLECTOR OF CUSTOMS</persName> —Sir, I rise to move,- <lb/>
               </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"That suitable provision be made by this House for the payment of the expenses of the 
     <lb/>
     
     
    " Delegates to be sent from this Colony to Ottawa to negotiate the terms of the Confederation 
     <lb/>" of this Colony with the Dominion of Canada." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     This has been one of the preliminary steps taken by the other Colonies before going into 
     <lb/>
     Confederation. If it has been necessary in other cases, it is certainly necessary for us. The 
     <lb/>
     expense is comparatively small, probably from $2,500 to $3,000, and the Governor has preferred 
     <lb/>
     to bring the matter before the Council now, instead of putting it into a supplementary estimate 
     <lb/>
     next session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName> —Sir, I beg to inquire why these resolutions
                  cannot be transmitted by post. <lb/> I do not see why the Colony should be put to
                  the expense of conveying the message; there is <lb/> postal communication with
                  Canada. and sufficient means of conveying to the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment what we have agreed upon. There can be no necessity to send Hon. Members to
                  Ottawa. <lb/> The fact of our doing so would lead to the presumption that
                  Confederation is agreed upon. I <lb/> differ from that. I say the people want to
                  have the terms before them. Let us first see whether <lb/> the Colony assents to
                  Confederation in the abstract. Why should we send three or four Hon. <lb/> and
                  learned gentlemen—learned, no doubt. Why, I say, should we have the Colony put to
                  so <lb/> much expense when it is in a state of poverty and bankruptcy. [No, no.] I
                  say, dispatch the <lb/> terms in the ordinary way by post.   <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I hope, Sir, it will not be necessary to
                  fight our battles over again. <lb/> This House has, in the name of the Colony—[No
                  no, from <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hons. Ring</persName> and <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Drake</persName>.] <supplied><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName></supplied> Perhaps <lb/> it will suit some Hon. Members
                  better to say a majority of this House, [No no] Perhaps <lb/> certain Hon. Members
                  will have the decency to be quiet until their turn comes to speak. A <lb/>
                  majority of this House—an overwhelming majority—has decided upon terms. We shall
                  get the <lb/> consent of the Canadian Government to these, or modified, conditions
                  and then submit them to <lb/> the people, That is the only way. If we were, as
                  proposed by the Hon. Member for Nanaimo, <lb/> to ask the people whether they
                  wanted Confederation, what would they say? [<persName ref="pers:RING1">MR Ring</persName>—They <lb/> would say " No! "]
                  <supplied><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName></supplied> They would say most emphatically, " Yes, on terms." They have said so <lb/> for
                  years. The Governor has adopted the usual course. These resolutions will go to the
                  <lb/> Canadian Government and come back. perhaps, modified, and the people will
                  then be asked if <lb/> they will have Confederation on these terms. The terms are
                  now proposed to be sent to Ottawa. <lb/> I cannot agree with the Hon. Member for
                  Nanaimo that it would be cheaper to send them by <lb/> post, The first outlay
                  might be smaller, but it might cause delay, and, in my opinion, British <lb/>
                  Columbia cannot afford delay. The telegraph might do, but it would cost more. It
                  ought to <lb/> be by delegation. I think the House is entitled to know who are to
                  go. I presume the Govern<lb break="no"/>mnent will be prepared to give us the
                  names. I, for one. would be unprepared to vote a sum of <lb/> $2,500, or more
                  likely. $5,000, if I thought the Governor would send Delegates who would not <lb/>
                  be acceptable to the people. I say that the people ought to be represented, and
                  that particular <lb/> Members who will fairly represent the people on the
                  Responsible Government question ought to <lb/> go. I say that if the Delegates are
                  silent on Responsible Government the Cabinet at Ottawa <lb/> will raise it. If the
                  Delegates say that British Columbia is not prepared for it. that it has <lb/> been
                  voted down. the Cabinet will say, they have reason to believe that the people, or
                  a large <lb/> proportion of them. want it, and that they have had enough of
                  discontent. I say. that although <lb/> Responsible Government is not. strictly
                  speaking, a condition, it underlies and permeates the <lb/> whole question. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Hon. COLLECTOR OF CUSTOMS</persName> —Nothing would be easier than to
                  forward the resolutions <lb/> by post to Canada. "his has probably been done
                  already; but on every one of the resolutions, <lb/> as you all know. there are
                  numerous points requiring planations, and to make these effective <lb/> the
                  presence at Ottawa of Delegates on our part, understanding the question and
                  authorized to <lb/> act for us. would appear to be indispensable. I am inclined to
                  think that the names of the <lb/> Delegates are pretty well known, but I have no
                  authority to mention them here. The Governor <lb/> has chosen them on his own
                  responsibility, and he does not ask the Council to share that respon<lb break="no"/>sibility. For what purpose should the names be given? Does the Council wish to
                  canvass the <lb/> merits of each individual? What those gentlemen will say on the
                  subject of Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment I am not prepared to tell you;
                  but I tell you this, that on that subject and on every other <lb/> they will act
                  with fairness and ability. with no discredit to themselves and with no discredit
                  to <lb/> us. I am ready at any rate to trust them so far as that. I hope this
                  Council will trust them, <lb/>as the Governor has shown himself ready to trust
                  them. Every year there are expenses that <lb/>
                  <pb n="159" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_159.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>
                  <fw type="num">159</fw> cannot be provided for except in the Supplementary
                  Estimates. This will doubtless be one of <lb/> them. There will be no
                  objectionable special tax, that I know of, proposed on this account. If <lb/>
                  there is, it will be time enough to oppose it when it. comes. in the meantime you
                  are asked <lb/> simply to authorize the expenditure of a small sum of money for an
                  object of infinite importance. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —There is a mighty curious dust kicked up
                  by great opposites when <lb/> they meet. I think we shall see some of these
                  gentlemen hoisted on their own petards. I have <lb/> a pretty good idea who the
                  gentlemen are, and I do not think they represent the people, especially <lb/> in
                  the matter of Responsible Government. I believe the Governor will act fairly and
                  honourably, <lb/> but I think he will not select men who will he acceptable to the
                  people. My opinion is. that the <lb/> Hon. Chief Commissioner, the Hon. Member for
                  Victoria, and the Hon. Attorney-General do not <lb/> represent the people. Popular
                  members will he untrue to themselves <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Hon. MR. DEWDNEY</persName> —The Hon. Member has had his guess. I do not
                  desire to mention <lb/> names. I would merely suggest that His Excellency be
                  requested to select one of the Delegates <lb/> from the Mainland. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —My views on Responsible Government
                  have been so often <lb/> expressed that there is no occasion to refer to them
                  again, but I am astonished that after Hon. <lb/> Members have told us that the
                  people are a unit in favour of Responsible Government, they <lb/> should be afraid
                  to trust it to the people, or to the Council, which His Excellency has told you
                  <lb/> he will form after this Session. Why, then, are Hon. Members so desirous to
                  weight down the <lb/> terms? Are they afraid that the people will not be so
                  unanimous at the polls in favour of <lb/> Responsible Government? His Excellency
                  has told you that, if allowed by Her Majesty's <lb/> Government, he proposes to
                  form a Council which will be representative. I, for one, have no <lb/> doubt about
                  the permission. The question will then he left to that Council. Why are Hon. <lb/>
                  Members afraid to leave this question to the representatives of the people? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —I will answer the Hon. Chief
                  Commissioner: we are not afraid <lb/> of putting the question before the people,
                  but I am afraid that members of that delegation will <lb/> misrepresent the
                  opinions of the people to the Canadian Government; I fear the people will not
                  <lb/> be represented <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName> —Mr. Chairman. I intend to oppose the
                  resolution proposed by the Hon. <lb/> Collector of Customs. I think that if Hon.
                  Members examine this message in connection with <lb/> His Excellency's speech, it
                  is apparent that the resolutions were sent down complete. This <lb/> House was not
                  allowed to alter them. The recommendations of Hon. Members were voted down. <lb/>
                  I think it would be better to send the resolutions by post as the resolutions of
                  Government; they <lb/> are not the resolutions of this Committee. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —They are the resolutions of this
                  House. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName> —No; only of the official majority. The
                  expense is unnecessary; it is <lb/> one which will be incurred to enforce the
                  views of Government. His Excellency asks that he <lb/> should be authorized to
                  expend a sum of money for this special purpose. A special tax is asked <lb/> for.
                  If we accede to this message we are assuming the responsibility. I would like to
                  ask this <lb/> question: Is the Delegation to take powers from this House or from
                  the Government? <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —I must reply without delay to one
                  proposition. I would <lb/> like the Hon. gentleman to point out any one example or
                  suggestion which, if defeated, was <lb/> not defeated by a majority of so-called
                  popular members, with the exception of Responsible <lb/> Government, in which
                  there was a minority of, so-called, representative members. The Hon. <lb/>
                  gentleman's remarks fall to the ground. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —The mistake has been made at that end of
                  the table. I think <lb/> we are in duty bound to send Delegates and raise the
                  money. My only objection is, that the <lb/> names are withheld. I cannot
                  understand why Hon. Members should vote against this message. <lb/> I believe we
                  are all agreed that Delegates should go, but if names are not sent down, I must
                  <lb/> vote against it. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —Mr. Chairman. I scarcely expected a
                  discssion upon this point; I <lb/> should have supposd that this House would have
                  voted the money at once. The question is <lb/> whether this Delegation will be
                  representative or not. I do not intend to offer any factions <lb/> opposition. I
                  am satisfied that the people will take means to send a people's delegation. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:BARN1">Hon. MR. BARNARD</persName> —Current report names the gentlemen. The
                  object of sending by <lb/> delegates is that the terms may be modified if
                  necessary. If unsatisfactory, will not the people <lb/> have a right to say: "How
                  could we expect anything better." Here are two members recent <lb/>
                  <pb n="160" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_160.jpg"/>
                  <fw type="num">160</fw>
                  <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> converts, and one a decided
                  opponent. How can a popular member go to his constituents after <lb/> voting this
                  money? The people are in earnest in this matter. I stand on the floor of this
                  House <lb/> a Government contractor, and likely to support the Government, but so
                  long as I gave a straight <lb/> vote on Confederation my constituents cared not
                  about anything else. On the Mainland we have <lb/> been firm on Confederation all
                  through, and the Mainland is ignored. The two Hon. gentlemen <lb/> at the head of
                  this table represent the Island, and the other Hon. Member represents the Island.
                  <lb/> The Mainland is not going to be satisfied, particularly when the Hon. senior
                  Member for Victoria, <lb/> who has consistently opposed. and will oppose,
                  Confederation. is lo be one of the Delegation. <lb/> For the first time in twenty
                  years the Hon. gentleman leaves this Island. He knows nothing <lb/> about the
                  interior of the country. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DRAK1">Hon. MR. DRAKE</persName> —The Hon. Chief Commissioner stated that the
                  whole of the recom<lb break="no"/>mendations were carried, except one, by the
                  majority of the popular vote. I instance free port <lb/> and the telegraph to the
                  contrary. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —I must explain that I spoke from
                  recollection. I was not <lb/> in the House. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I claim that the official members who voted
                  against Responsible <lb/> Government must be struck out. But if we allow them to
                  be counted, there is still a majority <lb/> of six to three of the representative
                  members in favour of Responsible Government; and I say <lb/> that this resolution
                  ought to be transmitted with such explanation as is necessary. With regard <lb/>
                  to Responsible Government being in the hands of: the New Council, Members will, we
                  may <lb/> presume, be elected for four years; consequently, the question will, in
                  all probability, be post<lb break="no"/>poned for four years. And I say that those
                  who keep back Responsible Government will run <lb/> a great risk of having
                  Confederation defeated at the polls. Some Hon. Members may desire <lb/> such a
                  result. If so. I can understand the course they are taking. With regard to the
                  <lb/> individuals going on the Delegation, if we are to take the general rumour,
                  there is not one <lb/> who will properly represent: the Mainland. There are two
                  recent converts, and one open <lb/> opponent of Confederation, an implacable and
                  politically unprincipled enemy to Confederation, <lb/> leagued with some power, I
                  won't say with the cloven-footed gentleman, but with some power <lb/> to defeat
                  Confederation. The people will not be satisfied. It is extraordinary thumbs:
                  Governor <lb/> should make such a selection, ignoring the whole Confederation
                  party and the whole Mainland <lb/> as a territory. I could not justify myselll it
                  I voted for this resolution, which will virtually be <lb/> voting for three island
                  Members, two recent converts and one—[No, no, from <persName ref="pers:HELM1">Dr. Helmcken</persName>] <lb/> <supplied><persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName></supplied> well, I
                  won't say it again. (Laughter) I can understand a Government dishonest at heart
                  <lb/> pursuing this course. but I cannot understand a Government that is true to
                  the cause doing so. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> —Mr. Chairman, Hon. Members seem to
                  be in position of <lb/> fighting shadows in the dark. If they are wroug in their
                  suppositions all the words that have <lb/> been spoken today are thrown away. I
                  fully concur in what fell from the Hon. Collector of <lb/> Customs, that it is not
                  proper that these names should be given. Hon. Members who favour <lb/>
                  Confederation should be the last to object to the Governor's selecting members.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. Mr. ROBSON</persName> —I have faith in the honesty of His
                  Excellency in the matter of Con<lb break="no"/>federation. The only act that shook
                  me and other Confederationists was the appointment of <lb/> the Hon. Member for
                  Victoria City lo the Executive Council. I believe His Excellency to be a <lb/>
                  Confederate at heart. I will. in order to simplifv matters, move to report
                  progress. and ask <lb/> leave to sit again, so that the Governor may have the
                  opportunity of sending down names, or, <lb/> at all events, of satisfying the
                  Mainland that their interests, and Responsible Government, are <lb/> cared for.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     The motion to rise and report progress was lost. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:RING1">Hon. MR. RING</persName> —I think this debate, it it may be so called,
                  is quite uncalled for and <lb/> unnecessary. It is ridiculous to bring up the
                  names of men who may possibly go to Ottawa <lb/> and discuss them; it ought not to
                  be allowed; it is waste of time and lungs. I had prepared <lb/> a resolution that
                  the terms should be sent by post. but I see that it would be vain to put it to
                  <lb/> the vote. If delegates go they ought to be properly equipped. I shall not,
                  therefore, oppose <lb/> the vote. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DEWD1">Hon. MR. DEWDNEY</persName> —I agree with the Hon. Member for Nanaimo
                  that this debate is <lb/> waste of time. I think the Mainland will be represented.
                  <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. MR. DECOSMOS</persName> —I think it is not a question whether
                  Island or Mainland is repre<lb break="no"/>sented. We want the views of different
                  parties represented, leaving out the Mainland and <lb/> Island. <lb/>
               </p>

            <pb n="161" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_161.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">161</fw>


            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I express a hope that the Government will
                  not press Government <lb/> vote. <lb/>
               </p>

    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> —I can inform Hon. Members that I feel
                  perfectly satisfied <lb/> that the Governor will not: send down names. The Hon.
                  Member who names the Delegates has <lb/> better information than myself. The House
                  having given unanimous adhesion to the terms. <lb/> —[No, no, I was the
                  exception,—<persName ref="pers:DECO1">Hon. Mr. DeCosmos</persName>.] —<supplied><persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName></supplied> at all events it was passed by a <lb/> majority,
                  and so becomes the act of the Council,—we could not expect Canada to send
                  Delegates <lb/> here; they would be unable to refer to the Executive Council. It
                  must injure the terms if in <lb/> the debates of this House an expression of
                  opinion goes forth to the world that the Governor <lb/> has not Confederation
                  truly at heart. The Hon. Member for New Westminster says that I am <lb/>a convert,
                  and that I represent Victoria. I am glad that the old idea that I leaned too much
                  <lb/>to New Westminster is exploded; I should be sorry that it should run in the
                  other direction. <lb/>The Hon. Member for New Westminster has told us if we
                  cannot; get Responsible Government, <lb/>he would not consent to make it a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi>. <lb/>
               </p>

    

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:ROBS1">Hon. MR. ROBSON</persName> —I have never said that Confederation would
                  be refused without <lb/> Responsible Government. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:CREA1">Hon. ATTORNEY-GENERAL</persName> — I have no doubth am not speaking from
                  positive knowledge <lb/> —that the Delegates will be clothed with full power to
                  discuss all the suggestions made on this <lb/> matter. If Responsible Government
                  is started by the Canadian Cabinet it will receive full <lb/> consideration <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:HUMP1">Hon. MR. HUMPHREYS</persName> —The people do not mistrust His
                  Excellency, but they do think <lb/> that if certain Members of the Government are
                  sent on this Delegation they will endeavour to <lb/> keep up the present system. I
                  am satisfied that if the Hon. Members named are sent, Con<lb break="no"/>federation is killed. <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
                  <persName ref="pers:TRUT1">Hon. CHIEF COMMISSIONER</persName> said those who support Confederation
                  are injuring the <lb/> cause. I believe, Sir, that it a consistent supporter of
                  Confederation from the Island, and one <lb/> from British Columbia are sent as
                  this Delegation, with one Member of the Government, such <lb/> a Delegation would
                  carry confidence even if the terms were modified. I propose to vote for <lb/> this
                  resolution. I hope the Delegates will be such as will give satisfaction. I contend
                  that <lb/> there are orlicials who would add weight to that Delegation, and I
                  should not like to see official <lb/> members left out.   <lb/>
               </p>

            <p>
     On division the resolution was carried, only one vote being against it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On motion of the Hon. Chief Commissioner, Committee rose and reported resolution passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     House adopted resolution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Reported for the Government by</hi> 
     <lb/></p>

<p rendition="simple:right">
     W.S. SEBRIGHT GREEN 
     <lb/>
            </p>
       

<pb n="162" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_162.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">162</fw>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>

</div>
<div type="document">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">PROPOSED TERMS OF UNION.</head>

   <table>
   <row><cell rendition="simple:centre">AMENDMENTS PROPOSED BY THE LEGISLATIVE 
     <lb/>COUNCIL. <lb/></cell> 
       
       <cell rendition="simple:centre">    <p>RESOLUTIONS SUBMITTED BY THE GOVERN<lb break="no"/>MENT.<lb/></p>
          
          <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That it is expedient that the Colony 
     <lb/>of British Columbia shall be Confederated with 
     <lb/>Canada, on the following Terms and Conditions; 
     <lb/>that is to say :<lb break="no"/>1. Canada shall be liable for the Debts and 
     <lb/>Liabilities of British Columbia existing at the 
     <lb/>time of Union. 
     <lb/></p>
            
            <p>2. The population of British Columbia shall 
     <lb/>for the purpose of financial arrangements be 
     <lb/>estimated at 120,000. British Columbia not 
     <lb/>having incurred debts equal to those of other 
     <lb/>Provinces now constituting the Dominion, shall 
     <lb/>be entitled to receive, by half-yearly payments 
     <lb/>in advance from the General Government, 
     <lb/>interest at the rate of 5 per cent. per annum 
     <lb/>on the difference between the actual amount of 
     <lb/>its indebtedness at the date of Union and the 
     <lb/>proportion of the Public Debt of Canada for 
     <lb/>120,000 of the population of Canada at the time 
     <lb/>of. Union. 
     <lb/></p>
            
            <p>3. The followin sums shall be annually paid 
     <lb/>by Canada to British Columbia, for the support 
     <lb/>of the Local Government and Legislature, to 
     <lb/>wit:-<lb/></p></cell></row>
   
    <row><cell rendition="simple:centre">        <p>
     That the Governor be respectfully requested 
     <lb/>
     to strike out figures "$35,000," and insert in 
     <lb/>
     lieu thereof " $75,000," 
     <lb/></p></cell>
          
       <cell rendition="simple:centre"><p>An annual grant of $35,000, and a further 
     <lb/>sum equal to 80 cents a head per annum of the 
     <lb/>population, both payable half-yearly in advance, 
     <lb/>the population of British Columbia being esti<lb break="no"/>mated as aforesaid at 120,000. Such grant 
     <lb/>equal to 80 cents a head to be augmented in 
     <lb/>proportion to the increase of population, when </p></cell></row>
      
     <row><cell rendition="simple:centre">       <p>
     That the figures "400,000" be altered to 
     <lb/>
     " 1,000,000." 
     <lb/></p></cell>
  
        <cell rendition="simple:centre"><p> <lb/>such may be shown, until the population 
     <lb/>amounts to 400,000, at which rate such grant 
     <lb/>shall thereafter remain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>4. The Dominion shall guarantee interest at 
     <lb/>the rate of 5 per centum per annum on such 
     <lb/>sum, not exceeding £100,000, as may be required 
     <lb/>for the construction of a first-class Graving 
     <lb/>Dock at Esquimalt. 
     <lb/></p>
            <p>5. In addition to the other provisions of this 
     <lb/>Resolution, Canada shall assume and defray the 
     <lb/>charges of the following services :- <lb/> a. Salary and allowances of the Lieutenant- 
     <lb break="yes"/>Governor;<lb/> 
               <lb/></p></cell></row>
      
    <row><cell rendition="simple:centre">        <p>
     That word "pensions" be inserted after the 
     <lb/>
     word "allowances." 
     <lb/></p></cell>
       
      <cell rendition="simple:centre"> <p>
     b. Salaries and allowances of the Judges and 
     <lb/>
     Officers of the Supreme Court, and of 
     <lb/>
     the County Courts; 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     c. The charges in respect of the Department 
     <lb/>
    of Customs; 
     <lb/>
            </p>
<p>d. The postal Department;<lb/></p></cell></row>
   </table>

            <pb n="163" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_163.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">163</fw>
            

<table><row>
   <cell/>
<cell rendition="simple:centre"><p>
     e. Lighthouses, Buoys, Beacons, and Lightship, 
     <lb/>
     and such further charges as may be incident 
     <lb/>
     to and connected with the services. 
     <lb/>
     which by "The British North America 
     <lb/>
     Act, 1867," appertain to the General 
     <lb/>
     Government, and as are or may be al<lb break="no"/>lowed to the other Provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6. Suitable Pensions, such as shall he approved 
     <lb/>
     of by Her Majesty's Government, shall he pro<lb break="no"/>vided by the Government of the Dominion for 
     <lb/>
     those of Her Majesty's Servants in the Colony, 
     <lb/>
     whose position and emoluments derived there<lb break="no"/>from would be affected by political changes on 
     <lb/>
     the admission of this Colony into the Dominion 
     <lb/>
     of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     7, The Dominion Government shall supply an 
     <lb/>
     efficient and regular fortnightly Steam Com<lb break="no"/>munication between Victoria and San Francisco 
     <lb/>
     by Steamers adapted and giving facilities for 
     <lb/>
     the conveyance of passengers and cargo. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     8. Inasmuch as no real (Union can subsist- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     between this Colony and Canada without the 
     <lb/>
     speedy establishment of connminication across<lb/>
     the Rocky Mountains by Coach Road and Rail-</p></cell></row>
     
   <row><cell rendition="simple:centre"> <p>
     That the word " and," between "construct" 
     <lb/>
     an: " open," he erased, and words " and maintain" 
     <lb/>
      be inserted after " traffic." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That this Section be altered so that the sec<lb break="no"/>tion of the Main Trunk Road between Yale 
     <lb/>
     and New Westminster may be included in the 
     <lb/>
     Coach Road which the Dominion Government 
     <lb/>
     is to be asked to construct within three years 
     <lb/>
     from the date of Union. 
     <lb/>
            </p></cell>
   
<cell><p>way, the Dominion shall, within three years 
     <lb/>
     from the date of Union, construct and open for 
     <lb/>
     traffic such Coach Road, from some point on the 
     <lb/>
     line of the Main Trunk Road of this Colony to 
     <lb/>
     Fort Garry, of similar character to the said Main 
     <lb/>
     Trunk Road; and shall further engage to use 
     <lb/>
     all means in her power to complete such Rail<lb break="no"/>way communication at the earliest practicable 
     <lb/>
     date, and that Surveys to determine the proper 
     <lb/></p></cell></row>
   
    <row><cell/>
       <cell rendition="simple:centre"> <p>line for such Railway shall he at once com<lb break="no"/>menced: and that a sum of not less than one 
     <lb/>
     million dollars shall he expended in every year, 
     <lb/>
     from and after three years from the date of 
     <lb/>
     Union, in actually constructing the initial sec<lb break="no"/>tions of such Railway from the Seaboard of 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia, to connect with the Railway 
     <lb/>
     system of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     9. The Dominion shall erect and maintain, 
     <lb/>
       Victoria, a Marine hospital and a Lunatic 
     <lb/>
     Asylum, either attached to the Hospital or 
     <lb/>
     separate, as may be considered most convenient. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Dominion shall also erect and maintain 
     <lb/>
     a Penitentiary, or other principal Prison, at 
     <lb/>
     such place in the Colony as she may consider 
     <lb/>
     most suitable for that purpose. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     10. Efficient Coast Mail Steam Service, in 
     <lb/>
     connection with the Post Office, shall he estab<lb break="no"/>lished and maintained by the Government of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion, between Victoria and New West<lb break="no"/>minster, Nanaimo, and such other places as 
     <lb/>
     may require such services. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     11. Whatever encouragement, advantages, and 
     <lb/>
     protection are afforded hy the Dominion Govern- <lb/>
            </p></cell></row></table> 

            <pb n="164" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_164.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">164</fw>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw>




           <table>
<row><cell/>
   <cell rendition="simple:centre">      <p>
     ment to the Fisheries of any of its Provinces, 
     <lb/>
     shall be extended in similar proportion to British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia, according to its requirements for the 
     <lb/>
     time being. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     12. British Columbia shall participate, in fair 
     <lb/>
     proportion, in any mensures which may be 
     <lb/>
     adopted, and funds which may be appropriated, 
     <lb/>
     by the Dominion, for the encouragement of 
     <lb/>
     Immigration. 
     <lb/>
            </p></cell></row>
              
             <row><cell rendition="simple:centre"> <p>That the figures "91" be inserted after 
     <lb/>
     figures "18". 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     That the following words he added at the 
     <lb/>
     end of the clause :—" Provided, however, that 
     <lb/>
     the number of Members of the Senate shall 
     <lb/>
     never be reduced below the number of Four, 
     <lb/>
     and the number of Members of the House of 
     <lb/>
     Commons below the number of Eight." 
     <lb/>
            </p></cell>
          
     

     <cell rendition="simple:centre">       <p>
     13. British Columbia shall be entitled to be 
     <lb/>
     represented in the Senate by Four Members, 
     <lb/>
     and by Eight Members in the House of Commons 
     <lb/>
       until the year 18 , and thereafter the 
     <lb/>
     Representation in the Senate and in the House 
     <lb/>
     of Commons shall be increased, subject to the 
     <lb/>
     provisions of " The British North America Act, 
     <lb/>
     1867."   
     <lb/>
            </p></cell></row>

      <row>
         <cell/>
          <cell rendition="simple:centre">  <p>
     14. The Union shall take effect on such day 
     <lb/>
     as Her Majesty by Order in Council (on an 
     <lb/>
     Address to that effect in terms of. the 146th 
     <lb/>
     Section of "The British North America Act, 
     <lb/>
     1867,") may direct; and British Columbia may, 
     <lb/>
     in such Address, specify the Districts, Counties, or 
     <lb/>Divisions, if any for which any of the Four<lb/>Senators to whom the Colony shall be entitled<lb/>shall be named, the Electoral Districts for<lb/>which—and the time within which—the first<lb/>Election of Members to serve in the House of<lb/>Commons shall take place.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     15. The Constitution of the Executive authority 
     <lb/>and of the Legislature of British Columbia<lb/>shall, subject to the provisions of "The British<lb/>North America Act, 1867," continue as existing<lb/>at the time of Union, until altered under the<lb/>authority of the said Act.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

            <p>
     16. The provisions in "The British North 
     <lb/>
     America Act, 1867," shall (except those parts 
     <lb/>
     thereof which are in terms made, or by reason<lb break="no"/>able intendment may be held to be, specially 
     <lb/>
     applicable to and only affect one and not the 
     <lb/>
     whole of the Provinces new comprising the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion, and except so far as the same may 
     <lb/>
     be varied by this Resolution) be applicable to 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia, in the same way and to the 
     <lb/>
     like extent as they apply to the other Provinces 
     <lb/>
     of the Dominion, and as if the Colony of British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia had been one of the Provinces origin<lb break="no"/>ally united by the said Act. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With reference to Defences :- <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>a. That it shall be an understanding with the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion, that their influence will be used, 
     <lb/>
     to the fullest extent, to procure the continued 
     <lb/>
     maintenance of the Naval Station at Esquiinalt. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     b. Encouragement to be given to develop the 
     <lb/>
     efficiency and organization of the Volunteer 
     <lb/>
     Force in British Columbia. 
     <lb/>
            </p></cell></row></table>
            

            <pb n="165" facs="final/images/BC_LC_1870-04-06_Page_165.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">CONFEDERATION DEBATE.</fw> <fw type="num">165</fw>
</div>  

<div type="document">          

<head>SUPPLEMENTARY RESOLUTIONS</head>

            <p>
     IN REFERENCE TO CONFEDICRATION, PROPOSED BY THE LEGISLATIVE COUNCIL 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That in the opinion of this Council, the duties levied upon maltsters and brewers 
     <lb/>
     under and by virtue of the Excise Laws of Canada would he detrimental if made applicable to 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia, that His Excellency be therefore earnestly requested to take such steps as 
     <lb/>
     he may deem advisable to bring the same to the notice of the Canadian Government, and 
     <lb/>
     further to take care that no export duties shall be charged on spars exported from British 
     <lb/>
     Columbia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That this Council respectfully represent to His Excellency the Governor, that, in 
     <lb/>
     negotiating the Terms of Union of British Columbia with Canada, it is of the first importance 
     <lb/>
     to point out to the Government of' that Dominion, that the circumstances of this Colony are in 
     <lb/>
     many respects so different from those of the Eastern Provinces, that the application of the 
     <lb/>
     present Canadian Tariff to this Colony, while reducing the aggregate burthen of taxation, would 
     <lb/>
     injurious affect the agricultural and commercial interests of this community; and that it 
     <lb/>
     he, therefore. urgently impressed upon that Government that it is ahsolutely necessary to our 
     <lb/>
     well-being under Confederation that special rates of Customs Duties, and special Customs 
     <lb/>
     Regulations, be arranged for the Colony, in such manner as may be found practically most 
     <lb/>
     advisable, so as to secure, While our requirements in this respect remain as at present, an equal 
     <lb/>
     measure of protection to our Agricultural Products, and of facility to our Commerce, as are 
     <lb/>
     provided under the existing British Columbia Tariff. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That a respectful Address he presented to His Excellency the Governor, recom<lb break="no"/>mending that the Dominion Government shall be requested to cause a Geological Survey of 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia to be made; such Survey to be commenced within one year after its admission 
     <lb/>
     into Union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That His Excellency the Governor be respectfully requested to insert in the 
     <lb/>
     Terms of Confederation to be proposed to Canada, some such clause as the following :- <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>All public works and property of British Columbia at the time of admission to belong to 
     <lb/>
     British Columbia, except such public works and property as shall properly belong to the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion under the British North America Act, and such portion of the main trunk road 
     <lb/>
     through British Columbia, or other roads then constructed, as may be necessary to complete a 
     <lb/>
     continuous line of coach road from a point at or below Yale to a point at the foot of the 
     <lb/>
     Eastern slope of the Rocky Mountains, and that the same shall he free of toll of every kind 
     <lb/>
     whatsoever. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
          
         </div>

  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>