<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="missed_page_template" type="template">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">Legislature</name>, <date when="1856-01-01">date(-range)</date>, debate title/description]</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
          <persName ref="pers:FAN1">Gloria Fan</persName>
        </respStmt> 
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
        </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  

  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="debate">
        <p>NORTH-WEST TERRITORIES—REPER-<lb/>
          SENTATION IN SENATE.<lb/>
          Bill (No.253) to increase the representa-<lb/>
          tion of the North-west Territories in the<lb/>
          Senate, read a second time, and the House<lb/>
        went into committee thereon.</p>
        <p>On Section 1.</p>
        <p>Mr. MACLEAN. I should think that the<lb/>
          government would incorporate in this Bill<lb/>
          a clause carrying out the pledge to reform<lb/>
          the Senate given to the people by the Lib-<lb/>
          eral party some years ago. For more months<lb/>
          past the Liberal papers have been declaring<lb/>
          that the Liberals have a majority of from<lb/>
          ten to fifteen in the Senate and that they<lb/>
          now control that body. If that be the fact, <lb/>
          then the pledges of the Liberals made in<lb/>
          1803, that the Senate ought to be re-<lb/>
        formed—</p>
        <p>Mr. JOHNSTON (Cape Breton). So it has<lb/>
        been.</p>
        <p>Mr. MACLEAN. What the Liberals<lb/>
          pledged themselves to do was not to reform<lb/>
          the personnel of the Senate, but to reform<lb/>
          its constitution, and here is a chance for<lb/>
          them to carry out that pledge. But, if the<lb/>
          government does not carry out its pledge<lb/>
          to reform the Senate, let me point out that<lb/>
          they are responsible for the action of that<lb/>
          chamber, and if a measure designed in the<lb/>
          public interests such as the cattle-guard<lb/>
          clause in the Railway Act, comes to grief<lb/>
          in the Senate, then the government must be<lb/>
          held responsible. In view of the fact that<lb/>
          an election seems to be at hand, and that<lb/>
          strange things may take place within the<lb/>
          coming month in connection with public<lb/>
          legislation. I take this opportunity of point-<lb/>
          ing out, that whatever the Senate does, the<lb/>
          government must be held responsible for it.<lb/>
          I do not purpose to introduce a measure<lb/>
          to reform the Senate, but I have been wait-<lb/>
          ing for this opportunity to say, that in view<lb/>
          of the statement in the Liberal press that<lb/>
          the government controls the Senate, they<lb/>
          are responsible for the conduct of the Sen-<lb/>
          ate, not having carried out their pledge to<lb/>
        reform it.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>