<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="missed_page_template" type="template">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">Legislature</name>, <date when="1856-01-01">date(-range)</date>, debate title/description]</title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
          <persName ref="pers:FAN1">Gloria Fan</persName>
        </respStmt> 
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt><p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
        </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  

  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="debate">
        <p>SECESSION</p>
        <p>Shall the Territories Be <lb/>Divided?</p>
        <p>The Debate in the Assembly on <lb/> 
        the Constitutional Memorial— <lb/>
        Dr. Brett Proposes the Princi-<lb/>
        ple of Secession of Alberta—In-<lb/>
        singer's Reply — Magrath for <lb/>
        Secession—Fearon Champions <lb/>
        Unity.</p>
        <p>  The Memorial to the Governor-General<lb/>
        in Council endorsed by the Assembly,<lb/>
        setting forth the position of the Territo-<lb/>
        ries and our immediate requirements, was<lb/>
          published in full in THE LEADER last<lb/>
          week. This week we commence the <lb/>
          report of the debate on the question. THE<lb/>
          LEADER possesses the only accurate and<lb/>
          complete report of this debate that exists<lb/>
          or was taken. It was probably the most<lb/>
          important debate that has taken place in<lb/>
          the Assembly for years, and, as such, is<lb/>
          deserving of the space which will be de-<lb/>
        voted to it.—</p>
        <p>MR. ROSS</p>
        <p>in moving that the House go into com-<lb/>
          mittee of the whole to consider the drafted<lb/>
          memorial from the special committee,<lb/>
          setting forth the legislative and financial<lb/>
          position of the Assembly, suggested that<lb/>
          if discussion were to take place on the<lb/>
          contents of the Assembly, suggested that<lb/>
          if discussion were to take place on the<lb/>
          contents of the memorial, asking for Ter-<lb/>
          ritorial autonomy as against provincial<lb/>
          autonomy, it would be better for it to<lb/>
          take place at once rather than in commit-<lb/>
          tee where questions of principle ought not<lb/>
          to be dealt with. Having already made a<lb/>
          lengthy speech regarding the subject, he<lb/>
          need say nothing now, except to express<lb/>
          his pleasure that the memorial practically<lb/>
        was along lines he had suggested.</p>
        <p>MR. BRETT</p>
        <p>(Banff) said he agreed the time for pre<lb/>
          senting the memorial had arrived. The<lb/>
          present question was probably the most<lb/>
          important the House had before it for con-<lb/>
          sideration. While, however, it was only<lb/>
          a temporary measure the memorial asked<lb/>
          for, he was one of those who believed the<lb/>
          time had come when they should with no<lb/>
          uncertain sound tell the Dominion Gov-<lb/>
          ernment, or indicate to them in what<lb/>
          position they would like the Territories<lb/>
          placed. He was not going to state that<lb/>
          the memorial should indicate that a more<lb/>
          radical change than was asked for therein<lb/>
          should take place at once. It was a serious<lb/>
          thing to too rapidly get to an advanced<lb/>
          condition if the conditions of the country<lb/>
          would not warrant it; still at the same<lb/>
          time it was equally bad that they should<lb/>
          linger along and not do that which they<lb/>
          considered was for the best advancement<lb/>
          of the country. In considering that<lb/>
          question they were called upon to consider<lb/>
          two great principles. In the first place<lb/>
          should they ask for responsible govern-<lb/>
          ment, and if they did should they ask it<lb/>
          for the Territories as a whole? He did<lb/>
          not think that was something they could<lb/>
          arrive at very suddenly, nor did he think<lb/>
          it was probably wise to take his ideas or<lb/>
          opinions on the matter, for everyone<lb/>
          should be prepared to give his own views,<lb/>
          and have good reasons for those views.<lb/>
          There was no use disguising the fact that if<lb/>
          the people of the Territories as a whole<lb/>
          were asked "Do you want the Territories<lb/>
          erected into a province such as Ontario,<lb/>
          or any other province of the Dominion?"<lb/>
          he believed a large majority would at once<lb/>
          exclaim "No!" (Hear, hear.) That<lb/>
          answer would be very largely due to the<lb/>
          fact that many people were not sufficiently<lb/>
          educated on what it really meant to get<lb/>
          provincial powers and to be established<lb/>
          into a province. Many people were<lb/>
          laboring under mistaken ideas with refer-<lb/>
          ence to the expenses that would naturally<lb/>
          attach to the erection of a province. Some<lb/>
          had the idea that immediately on the<lb/>
          erection of a province they would be<lb/>
          forced to form municipalities. That would<lb/>
          not be necessary. It was true that in<lb/>
          Manitoba and other provinces muni-<lb/>
          cipalities has been formed. British<lb/>
          Columbia, however, was an exception.<lb/>
          The Territories has just as much power<lb/>
          to-day in forming municipalities as they<lb/>
          would have, had they full responsible<lb/>
          government. In British Columbia they<lb/>
          had a less number of municipalities than<lb/>
        there were in the Territories.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haultain: They have direct taxa-<lb/>
        tion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brett: So far as direct taxation is<lb/>
          concerned we possess all the powers to-<lb/>
          day of direct taxation of any province of<lb/>
          the Dominion. The direct taxation in<lb/>
          British Columbia was poll tax, and the<lb/>
          Territories could have the same thing.<lb/>
          But it did not follow that if the Territo-<lb/>
          ries were formed into a province, these<lb/>
          powers would be exercised any more than<lb/>
          now. He thought that would dispose of<lb/>
          that objection. There were sufficient<lb/>
          other considerations for them to think of<lb/>
          in debating their present conditions. Was<lb/>
          it going to be any advantage to them? If<lb/>
          it was going to cost more than now, if<lb/>
          they were going to have less money to<lb/>
          expend on the industries of the country,<lb/>
          and on improvements in the country,<lb/>
          under provincial formation of government,<lb/>
          that would probably be one of the strong-<lb/>
          est reasons that it was not advisable. If<lb/>
          they were going to undertake a responsi-<lb/>
          bility they did not think they could carry<lb/>
          out, that was probably another reason<lb/>
          why they should give it due consideration.<lb/>
          As the memorial sets out, they are not<lb/>
          now receiving as much money as they are<lb/>
          entitled to. It was fair to assume, then,<lb/>
          that so far as their financial position was<lb/>
          concerned they would be better off were<lb/>
          they in the form of a province, than they<lb/>
          are now. The next thing for considera-<lb/>
          tion was, were they prepared to under-<lb/>
          take the responsiblities? He claimed<lb/>
          that the Territories, with the present<lb/>
          population, were as well qualified to<lb/>
          assume responsiblity as was the province<lb/>
          of Manitoba, when she undertook full<lb/>
          provincial government,—as was the pro-<lb/>
          vince of British Columbia (hear, hear).<lb/>
          Another point was, in what position would<lb/>
          in place the Territories with reference to<lb/>
          the making of laws? He believed in a<lb/>
          better. Another question was, had the<lb/>
          time arrived when they should take this<lb/>
          step? Some would say the time had not<lb/>
          arrived because they were not strong<lb/>
          enough to assume the responsibilities.<lb/>
          They were not strong enough to go to the<lb/>
          Dominion Government and make a con-<lb/>
          tract with them. He was not unmindful<lb/>
          of the fact that there was a great deal in<lb/>
          being strong. The stronger they were the<lb/>
          better bargain probably they could make.<lb/>
          But as he understood the manner in<lb/>
          which portions of the Dominion had been<lb/>
          taken into confederation and established<lb/>
          as provinces, they entered in on a basis<lb/>
          which was stated in the British North<lb/>
          America Act and which no government<lb/>
          could go behind. If the Territories were<lb/>
          taken into confederation to-day they<lb/>
          would only receive the same amount per<lb/>
          capita as they would were they ten times<lb/>
          stronger. They would certainly receive<lb/>
          more as population grow for expenses of<lb/>
          government. That amount was regulated<lb/>
          according to population. Manitoba re-<lb/>
          ceived $35,000 for expenses of govern-<lb/>
        ment, while latterly a better arrange-</p>
        <cb/>
        
        <p>ment was made them, and now they<lb/>
          get $50,000. The same thing would at-<lb/>
          tach to the Territories. Another question<lb/>
          to consider was, —as tothe amount of<lb/>
          money that should be claimed in lieu of<lb/>
          lands over which they had no control.<lb/>
          That resolved itself into the question of<lb/>
          making a bargain. They could state an<lb/>
          amount they were willing to begin with,<lb/>
          and the bargin need not be made in a<lb/>
          manner that finally settled it, so that<lb/>
          later they could go to the Dominion Gov-<lb/>
          ernment and ask for a greater amount in<lb/>
          lieu of their lands. Another objection, to<lb/>
          undertake great responsibilities now, was<lb/>
          that business was depressed, and we had<lb/>
          hard times; wait until there was a reviv-<lb/>
          al of trade, and so on. Times had been<lb/>
          bad all over the world, and the sooner<lb/>
          they could help themselves, all the sooner<lb/>
          wuld they relieve themselves of the de-<lb/>
          pressed condition. They would not, of<lb/>
          course, interfere with the cause that had<lb/>
          made the depression so general, but they<lb/>
          could during depressed times, —if they<lb/>
          had it within their power, —go on with<lb/>
          public works, do things that in other pro-<lb/>
          vinces were doing good for the people.<lb/>
          Thus, he said, they would be hastening<lb/>
          the time when they would not be suffer-<lb/>
          ing from the effects of these hard times.<lb/>
          The question of the Territories remaining<lb/>
          as they are must come to and end some-<lb/>
          time, and it was for the House very<lb/>
          largely to determine whether it should<lb/>
          come now or be deferred. He believe<lb/>
          that so long as they curtailed their demands<lb/>
          simply to a portion of what they were<lb/>
          entitiled to, they would receive less and<lb/>
          less every year. The time had come<lb/>
          when they should tell the Dominion Gov-<lb/>
          ernment in unmistakable terms that at<lb/>
          the expiration of this Assembly, —two<lb/>
          years hence, —they would expect full pro-<lb/>
          vincial powers would be given to the Ter-<lb/>
          ritories, either as a whole or divided. He<lb/>
          had stated there were no provincial taxes<lb/>
          in Manitoba, nor would it be necessary to<lb/>
          have them here. He might be asked,—<lb/>
          In what way are you going to raise the<lb/>
          revenue to carry on the Government? In<lb/>
          the first place they would get a grant of<lb/>
          money sufficient for the expenses of<lb/>
          Government as they do in British Colum-<lb/>
          bia. Then they would have in their pow-<lb/>
          er the collection of other taxes, license<lb/>
          fees, and so forth, as in British Columbia.<lb/>
          He would now refer more particularly to<lb/>
          Alberta. If provincial government would<lb/>
          be a good thing for the whole of the Ter-<lb/>
          ritories, he claimed it would not be unfair<lb/>
          for a portion of the Territories to ask for<lb/>
          it. The time had come not only for the<lb/>
          Territories as a whole to ask for provin-<lb/>
          cial powers, but it was high time some-<lb/>
          thing should be done in the direction of<lb/>
          giving to the western portion of the Ter-<lb/>
          ritories full provincial powers. The con-<lb/>
          ditions of the eastern and western por-<lb/>
          tions of the Territories were quite differ-<lb/>
          ent in many respects. In the west there<lb/>
          were resources which would greatly assist<lb/>
          the country generally if properly develop-<lb/>
          ed. They had ranching, grain growing, <lb/>
          minerals, coal, industries in coal oil and<lb/>
          so on, which under proper conditions<lb/>
          would make that portion of the country<lb/>
          one of the richest, if not the richest part of<lb/>
          the whole of the Territories. With proper<lb/>
          railway facilities those coal fields would<lb/>
          immediately be got into active operation.<lb/>
          That would largely increase the popula-<lb/>
          tion in those parts. Those people would<lb/>
          furnish a local market for those who rais-<lb/>
          ed cattle, grain and vegetables to the<lb/>
          north of them. They had diversified in-<lb/>
          terests there could deal with each other.<lb/>
          The benefits they would obtain from<lb/>
          having a provincial form of government<lb/>
          would be that they would have power to<lb/>
          do as they thought best for the develop-<lb/>
          ment of the country. Nearly every mem-<lb/>
          ber of that Assembly must have a feeling<lb/>
          of disappointment with reference to the<lb/>
          North-West Territories. They had been<lb/>
          standing still—marking time. He did<lb/>
          not think the best efforts had been made<lb/>
          in their behalf. The powers of the pro-<lb/>
          vince would make them progress much<lb/>
          more rapidly than it had. British Col-<lb/>
          umbia to-day was attracting the attention<lb/>
          of the world. They had not got a rich<lb/>
          mines which if developed, they did not<lb/>
          know but what might be as valuable<lb/>
          as those in British Columbia. The mines<lb/>
          being developed in British Columbia<lb/>
          would not be developed were it not<lb/>
          that the B.C. government had made good<lb/>
          roads, and so made it possible for the<lb/>
          people to get into the mountainous dis-<lb/>
          tricts. Had British Columbia been de-<lb/>
          pendent year after year as the Territories<lb/>
          were, and asking for something and only<lb/>
          getting a small amount, that province<lb/>
          would not have progressed as it had done.<lb/>
          There was another thing which might be<lb/>
          an argument in support of his contention<lb/>
          for provincial powers for Alberta. There<lb/>
          was a good deal in a name. The name<lb/>
          "The Territories," had an altogether<lb/>
          different sound to intending immigrants<lb/>
          than that of a "province." They did not<lb/>
          dissociate in their minds the United States<lb/>
          territories from the North-West Territo-<lb/>
          ries. It was a cold, inhospitable name.<lb/>
          The Territories was thought to be a land<lb/>
          of cold and snow for about two-thirds of<lb/>
          the year. He had heard many people say<lb/>
          the name was bad, and retarded immigra-<lb/>
          tion. People said they would try "a<lb/>
          province." I was a more civilized name,<lb/>
          —a more congenial name. Were they a<lb/>
          province, the name of "The province"<lb/>
          would enhance their chances of getting<lb/>
          immigrants above what they were now.<lb/>
          He hoped the House would amend the<lb/>
          terms of the memorial by recommending<lb/>
          to the Dominion Government, that at the<lb/>
          expiration of that Assembly the time<lb/>
          would have arrived when Alberta and<lb/>
          Athabasca should be erected into a pro-<lb/>
          vince. He hope the House would<lb/>
          remember he was speaking for Alberta.<lb/></p>
        <p>Mr. Haultain: What part of Alberta?</p>
        <p>Mr. Brett: I am speaking for that<lb/>
          portion as I understand it, and for that<lb/>
          portion where my interest lie. Some<lb/>
          might say. Why ask for Alberta to be set<lb/>
          apart? The eastern and western parts<lb/>
          of Assiniboia had not such a large popula-<lb/>
          tion as Alberta.</p>
        <p>Mr. Insinger: No, no; the hon. gen-<lb/>
        tleman is very much out there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brett thought if the hon. member<lb/>
          would carry out the figures as they were<lb/>
          in the memorial he would find the Alber-<lb/>
        <cb/>
          ta had a larger population than the<lb/>
          Assiniboia. No, (continued Mr.Brett,<lb/>
          looking at a paper crowded with figures)<lb/>
          the two Assiniboias had a population of<lb/>
          about 10 per cent more than Alberta,<lb/>
          carrying out the figures on the same lines<lb/>
          as was done in the memorial. Some<lb/>
          might say, why have not Assiniboia and<lb/>
          Saskatchewan asked to be made into a<lb/>
          province? He had never seen a stronger<lb/>
          appeal made than Saskatchewan was mak-<lb/>
          ing some time ago for some form of pro-<lb/>
          vincial government. He would now speak<lb/>
          for Alberta as he understood it; not for<lb/>
          the whole of Alberta but a portion of it.<lb/></p>
        <p>Mr. Haultain: Hear, hear.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brett, continuing, said if they<lb/>
          would look at the increase of population<lb/>
          as figured out in the memorial they would<lb/>
          find out that in the years 1891-94 it was<lb/>
          57 per cent, much larger than in Assini-<lb/>
        boia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Page: Does the hon.member con-<lb/>
          tend that the increase has been the same<lb/>
          during the last two years, that it was<lb/>
        during the three preceding years?</p>
        <p>Dr. Brett replied that he was discussing<lb/>
          a memorial which had been placed before<lb/>
          the House, and he dared say it had been<lb/>
          prepared very carefully and with due re-<lb/>
        gard to absolute correctness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haultain: But that is Territorial<lb/>
        increase.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brett: Yes, that is certainly Terri-<lb/>
          torial increase, but if in 1891-94 Alberta<lb/>
          increased 57 per cent, there was no reason<lb/>
          to his mind, why that increase had not<lb/>
          gone on since then. The increase of 40<lb/>
          per cent, claimed for the whole of the<lb/>
          Territories in the memorial was based on<lb/>
          the figures that Alberta had increased 57<lb/>
          per cent, Eastern Assiniboia 35 per cent,<lb/>
          Western Assiniboia 24 per cent, Saskat-<lb/>
          chewan 33 per cent. Taking that as a<lb/>
          basis the increase during 1891-97 would<lb/>
          be Alberta 90 per cent, the two Assini-<lb/>
          boias 92 per cent, and Saskatchewan 110<lb/>
        per cent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Insinger: How does the hon. mem-<lb/>
          ber compute these calculations out of the<lb/>
          memorial? I know a little about the<lb/>
          figures there, and I don't see how under<lb/>
          any circumstances the deductions can be<lb/>
          drawn from the memorial. The increases<lb/>
          in the memorial are based on the whole<lb/>
          population, but to jump from that to the<lb/>
          increase that happened in different parts<lb/>
        is something a little absured.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brett answered that he would stand<lb/>
          accused of being absured, —but the figures<lb/>
          showed a general increase in 1892-95 of<lb/>
          57 per cent, and in the Territories of 40<lb/>
          per cent, and there was no reason to show<lb/>
          that Alberta had not increased as much<lb/>
          since. He obtained his figures in the<lb/>
          office, and he believed they were absolute-<lb/>
          ly correct. They were from the census<lb/>
          returns taken by the N.W.M. Police. If<lb/>
          the hon gentleman who composed the<lb/>
          committee to draft the memorial were<lb/>
          warranted in saying that the whole of the<lb/>
          Territories had increased at the rate of<lb/>
          40, that was ten per cent a year, it was<lb/>
          fair to assume, in the absence of anything<lb/>
          to the contrary, that Alberta had increas-<lb/>
          ed in the same rate since 1894 (Hear,<lb/>
          hear). That was a fair thing. He might<lb/>
          appear ridiculous, but he certainly didn't<lb/>
          realize to a very large extent that he was<lb/>
          ridiculous in making a computation of<lb/>
          that kind. He was simply giving a rea-<lb/>
          son, why, as a representative of Alberta,<lb/>
          he was justified in asking the House to<lb/>
          indicate to the Dominion Government<lb/>
          that the time had arrived when it and<lb/>
          Athabasca should be set apart as a pro-<lb/>
          vince by itself. While the population<lb/>
          was increasing, and they had been getting<lb/>
          an increased grant year by year, it was<lb/>
          found that Alberta had been contributing<lb/>
          much more to the local revenues than<lb/>
          other parts of the Territories. Of the<lb/>
          total revenue contributed by the Territo-<lb/>
          ries (30,040). Alberta contributed 56 per<lb/>
          cent, and eastern and western Assiniboia 37<lb/>
          per cent. That made only 93 per cent. The<lb/>
          other portions was made up of moneys he<lb/>
          could not compute. Alberta contributed<lb/>
          a good deal more than all the rest of the<lb/>
          Territories. He would give a few items.<lb/>
          The liquor license was 424,907. Of that,<lb/>
          Alberta contributed $15,178; the balance<lb/>
          of the Territories showed $9,729. That<lb/>
          showed Alberta contributed the most.<lb/>
          (Laughter, and an hon. member: "And<lb/>
          it is a sign of progress!") The cost of<lb/>
          collecting that 49,729 in the two Assini-<lb/>
          boias and Saskatchewan was $4,076, so<lb/>
          that the net amount contributed by<lb/>
          those portions was $5,652; while to<lb/>
          collect $15,178 in Alberta it only cost<lb/>
          $1,849, so in that respect Alberta's net<lb/>
          contribution was $13,329. Looking at it<lb/>
          in that way Alberta contributed 78 per<lb/>
          cent of the net revenues of the Territo-<lb/>
          ries. (Hear, hear, and laughter). He<lb/>
          knew those figures were rather startling.<lb/>
        (Renewed laughter.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Haultain: What is the magnificent<lb/>
        total of the revenue?</p>
        <p>Mr. Brett: The magnificent total of<lb/>
        revenue is $30,040.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haultain: What is the net reve-<lb/>
        nue?</p>
        <p>Mr. Brett: For licenses under the<lb/>
          Liquor Ordinance, the only item I can<lb/>
          give the hon. gentleman, the gross reve-<lb/>
          nue is $24,908. The expenditure attend-<lb/>
          ing the collection of that is $5,926, leav-<lb/>
          ing a net revenue of $19,982. That is<lb/>
          outside the expenses of the chief license<lb/>
          inspector and so on. In it were not in-<lb/>
          cluded the meetings of commissioners, and<lb/>
          so on. Proceeding, the hon. gentleman<lb/>
          remarked, some might say the magnificent<lb/>
          sum, as the hon.member for Macleod<lb/>
          called it, was only $30,040, but even in<lb/>
          that small amount if there was a very large<lb/>
          disparity between the amount contributed<lb/>
          by one partner in the firm with the<lb/>
          amount he got out of it, he was justified<lb/>
          in looking around for some remedy.<lb/>
          Someone might ask, what if Alberta did<lb/>
          contribute 78 per cent of the net revenue,<lb/>
          what had that to do with it? Nothing, if<lb/>
          78 per cent was spent in Alberta of the<lb/>
          firm's money. But they found that Al-<lb/>
          berta came out at the wrong end there.<lb/>
          Last year Alberta received about 30 per<lb/>
          cent of the full amount paid for schools<lb/>
          in the Territories. It might be said,<lb/>
          whose fault was that? If Alberta had<lb/>
          had a greater number of schools establish-<lb/>
          ed she would have had a larger proportion<lb/>
          of the money. He presumed that as many<lb/>
          schools as were required were established<lb/>
          there; he did not know anything to the<lb/>
          contrary. Then the expense of spending<lb/>
          that money was five times greater in<lb/>
        <cb/>
          Assiniboia and Saskatchewan than in<lb/>
          Alberta. Then on roads and bridges Al-<lb/>
          berta had had a little over one-third the<lb/>
          total money, having contributed over<lb/>
          three-fourths of the net revenues from<lb/>
        local sources.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haultain: The net revenue ex-<lb/>
        pended upon roads and bridges?</p>
        <p>Mr. Brett: No. While Alberta had<lb/>
          contributed over three-fourths of the net<lb/>
          local revenue, they had received less than<lb/>
          one-third in school and only a trifle over<lb/>
          a third of the full amount expended for<lb/>
          roads and bridges. That condition of<lb/>
          affairs justified him, as one representative<lb/>
          of Alberta, to ask that Alberta should be<lb/>
          relieved,and placed in a position of col-<lb/>
          lecting its own revenues and doing as it<lb/>
          liked. In conclusion the hon. member<lb/>
          further argued that Alberta was entitled<lb/>
          to provincial status on the ground of ex-<lb/>
          cess in increase of population, and also of<lb/>
          extent of acreage. He could understand<lb/>
          it was not going to be an easy matter to<lb/>
          get the sanction of the House. It was<lb/>
          not anything the House would voluntarlly<lb/>
          tender to Alberta. He did not think the<lb/>
          Territories were sufficiently tired of Alber<lb/>
          ta, or sufficiently discontented with the<lb/>
          part Alberta played with reference to the<lb/>
          contributions to the general fund and so<lb/>
          on. He could not readily understand, as<lb/>
          was always the case in secession, or one<lb/>
          part asking to be relieved from another<lb/>
          portion, there always would be some ob-<lb/>
          jection taken. But he thought the time<lb/>
          would soon come when there would be<lb/>
          unanimity of feeling that the course he<lb/>
          proposed was the best thing not only for<lb/>
          Alberta but also for several portions of<lb/>
          the Territories to be constructed into a<lb/>
        province. (Hear, hear.)</p>
        <p>(Continued on Page 5.)</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>