<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgAssinLAssem_1870-05-04" type="full">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgAssinLAssem">Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</name>, <date when="1870-05-04">4 May 1870</date>, Debates on Manitoba Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
         <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        
      </titleStmt>
      
      <publicationStmt><p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>


        <bibl>
          
<editor>Norma Jean Hall</editor>.
          
       
          <title>Reconstituted Debates of the Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</title>.
                    

          <date when="2010-11-15"/>.  
          
          <pubPlace>Winnipeg</pubPlace>: <publisher>Provincial Government of Manitoba</publisher>.
          
<!-- GL, 2017-03-24, The document itself does not contain any publishing info, but the editor's home page, https://hallnjean.wordpress.com/whats-done/, indicates that this project was initiated by the Manitoba Government which has their own link to the document in their resources, http://www.gov.mb.ca/imr/ir/major-initiatives/pubs/laa%20debates.pdf   -->

          <biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="91"/>.
        </bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
<!-- TEMPLATE: Provide a simple description of why this specific set of pages was 
        selected. This is especially important in cases where discontinuous 
        page-ranges are used.  -->
        <p></p>
      </samplingDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
     <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-24">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-27">Marked-up people.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="debate">
    <head>Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</head>

  	


<div type="section">

    
<p><emph>Assembly Chamber, Upper Fort Garry</emph></p>

<p>Wednesday, 4 May 1870</p>
    
<p>The President took the chair at half-past two P.M.</p>
    
<p>The minutes having been read and approved the House resolved itself again into committee of the whole on the Liquor Laws, Hon. Mr. Bunn in the chair.</p>
    
<p>The paragraph commencing with the words "on payment of the sum of Ten </p>

<p>Pounds sterling" was first taken up, and on motion of <persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName>, seconded
            by <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, was amended by adding the word "retail"
            before the word "liquor" on the sixth line, and the words "and also in all local
            papers," after the word "reside" in the nineteenth line.</p>
    
<p>Paragraph carried as amended.</p>
    
<p>The two following paragraphs carried without alteration.</p>
    
<p>In the next the word "twelve" in the second line was changed to "twenty-four" and the paragraph carried as amended.</p>
    
<p>The next paragraph carried.</p>
    
<p>The succeeding paragraph was as follows:</p>
    
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Any person may sue an offender for manufacturing or selling without a license, and shall be entitled to half the fine actually recovered."</p></quote>
    
<p>This paragraph carried as follows, on motion of <persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> seconded by
              <persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Mr. Tait</persName>:</p>
 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"> 
<p>"Any person may sue another for manufacturing illegally, spirits, wine or fermented liquors or selling the same without a license, and shall be entitled to half the fine actually recovered."</p></quote>  
    
<p>The next paragraph carried.</p>
    
<p>In the paragraph following, on motion of <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName> all the words
            after the word "any" in the fourth line, were struck out, and the words "any Indian
            reserve" inserted. The object of the hon. mover, was, he said, to prevent the sale of
            spirituous liquors, not merely on the present Indian reserve, but on any land which
            might be set apart as an Indian reserve.</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName>,
            the first paragraph under the head "Wholesale Licenses" was amended by striking out the
            words "Ten Pounds" in the seventh line, and inserting the following:— "not less than
            Twenty Pounds sterling, and not more than Thirty Pounds sterling." — Paragraph
            carried</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName>, moved to
            add a clause requiring wholesale licenses to be granted twice a year — on the first day
            of June, and first day of December — The latter motion dropped.</p>
    
<p>Next paragraph carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName> moved the adoption of the third paragraph under the head
            "Wholesale Licenses," which was as follows:</p>
    
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Such Wholesale Licenses shall be issuable by the Benches of District Magistrates in their several districts, on the first week day of December, and on no other day to persons applying to the President either before or after that day."</p></quote>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Mr. Tait</persName> moved an amendment to the effect that Licenses might be taken
            out at any time during the year.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:OLON1">Hon. Mr. Olone</persName>, moved
            in amendment, that all wholesale licenses shall be granted by the President of the Fort
            Garry District Court on the first week day in June and the first week day in December,
            and on no other day. </p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> opposed the amendment moved by <persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr.
              O'Donoghue</persName>. But it carried on a division — Yeas 10; nays 9.</p>
    
<p>The fourth paragraph, giving magistrates power to grant or refuse the license in every case, was struck out, on motion of Hon. Mr. Tait seconded by Hon. Dr. Bird.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Mr. Tait</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName>, moved the
            adoption of the next paragraph, prescribing the form of wholesale license. </p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> — I think there should be conditions attached to the
            license of a wholesale as well as a retail liquor dealer. Many of the conditions to
            which the latter are subjected, it would be well to bring the wholesale man under also
            (hear, hear).</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Mr. Tait</persName> — The only conditions I would like to impose is that they
            should sell good liquor (laughter).</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> did not see the necessity of further binding the wholesale
            dealer. All the early clauses of the law, in some of which the fines set forth were very
            heavy, included wholesale as well as retail dealers.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName> moved in amendment that the following clause be added to the
            paragraph:— </p>
  
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"> 
<p>"And that all selling be confined to the premises for which this license is granted."</p></quote> 
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> and <persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Mr. Tait</persName> opposed Hon. Mr. Hay's
            amendment on the ground that it would sanction a gross injustice. The nature of the
            wholesale business was such that many buildings and stores in different sections were
            often required for it.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName> contended that the wholesale man should in this respect be
            placed on no better footing than the retailer. If they did not add his proviso,
            wholesale men would be enabled to peddle liquors all over the country.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> seconded the amendment which was carried on a division —
            Yeas 14; nays 2.</p>
    
<p>In accordance with the suggestion of the Chairman the Committee agreed to amend sub-section 2, Article V, by inserting therein the words "Good Friday and Christmas Day."</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> moved to add the following clause in reference to
            manufacturing of spirituous liquors or beer — </p>
 
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">  
<p>"That on payment of the sum of Fifteen Pounds sterling, it shall be lawful for the District Magistrates in their several districts assembled during the session of any District Court, to guarantee a license to any person to manufacture and sell by wholesale spirits, wine, or beer."</p></quote> 
    
<p><persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:GARR1">Hon. Mr. Garrioch</persName>, moved in
            amendment that the words "Fifteen Pounds sterling" be struck out of the motion and the
            words "Ten Pounds sterling" be inserted instead thereof.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> contended that as the manufacturer clearly had the advantage
            of the importer he ought to contribute Five Pounds per annum [illegible: then?] towards
            the revenue. The manufacturer besides being exempt from import duty, was able to distil
            his liquor for, say, Six Shillings per gallon; whereas, the importer's liquor cost him
            Ten Shillings to Twelve Shillings per gallon.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName> differed with the hon. member, and if any change were to be
            made he would either place the importer and manufacturer on equal terms or else
            discriminate in favor of the latter.</p>
    
<p>Amendment carried on a division:— Yeas 9; nays 8.</p>
    
<p>Committee rose and reported the adoption of the resolutions which had been before them.</p>
    
<p>House took a recess of half an hour.</p>
    
<p>The President having resumed the chair, business having been resumed,</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr.
              Poitras</persName>, the President was requested to name a member to preside, in order
            to allow him (the President) more liberty to attend to other matters of public
            importance.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The President</persName> having thanked the House for acting on this suggestion, which
            he had previously thrown out, called the Hon. Mr. Bunn to the chair and retired.</p>
    
<p>The House then resumed the consideration of the Law Committee Report.</p>
    
<p>Article VI, under the head "Customs Duties," with the articles up to and including the thirteenth, was taken up and adopted.</p>
    
<p>Article XIV being put,</p>
    
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"That a duty of two shillings per gallon should be imposed on all wines and Spirituous Liquors imported into the country," </p></quote>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:SINC3">Hon. Mr. T. Sinclair</persName>,
            moved in amendment that the words "two shillings" in the article be struck out, and "one
            shilling" inserted, and that the article, so amended, be adopted.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TOUR2">Hon. Mr. Touron</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:DAUP1">Hon. Mr. Dauphinais</persName>, moved
            in amendment that the original article be adopted — Amendment carried on a division —
            Yeas 10; nays 8.</p>
    
<p>Article I, under the head "Constables" was amended on motion of <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr.
              Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:OLON1">Hon. Mr. Olone</persName>, as follows:— In
            the first line, the words "not exceeding fourteen," were struck out, and the words "not
            less than sixteen" inserted. In sub-section 2, the figure 2 was changed to 3 and in
            sub-section 5 the figure 2 was also changed to 3. This gave a total police force of not
            less than sixteen, distributed as follows: Manitobah 1, the Portage 2, White Horse
            Plains 3, Fort Garry 7 (2 of whom are for special duty in town), and St. Andrew's 3. </p>
    
<p>The original motion placed the total number at not more than fourteen, with two for St. Andrew's, and two for White Horse Plains. On motion of <persName ref="pers:SINC3">Hon. Mr. Sinclair</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName>, the constables for St. Andrew's were increased to three; and on motion of <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName>, the White Horse Plain constables were increased to three. </p>
    
<p>Article carried as amended, and the two following articles were carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The Chairman</persName> moved that Article I under the head "Intestate Estates" be
            amended by substituting for the word "intermeddle" the words "dispose of, or
            distribute."</p>
    
<p>Not being seconded, the amendment dropped and the article carried.</p>
    
<p>Articles II and III were also carried.</p>
    
<p>Article I under the head "Postal," carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:SINC3">Hon. Mr. Sinclair</persName> moved that after the word "Pembina," in the second
            Article, the words "twice a week" be inserted.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName>, moved in
            amendment that the Article be adopted as it stood — Carried.</p>
    
<p>Article III carried.</p>
    
<p>Article IV was also carried, with the addition of the word "Winnipeg" after the words "General Post Office."</p>
    
<p>Article V carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:OLON1">Hon. Mr. Olone</persName>, moved
            that the House adjourn till tomorrow afternoon at one o'clock.</p>
    
<p>Hon. members were moving off at once, when, </p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:DELO2">Hon. Mr. De Lorme</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName>, moved in
            amendment that the House adjourn till ten o'clock tomorrow forenoon.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The Chairman</persName> ruled that the motion had not been properly seconded, seven or
            Eight members were on their feet at the same time — and amid the confusion he did not
            hear it seconded.</p>
    
<p>The amendment was then moved as an original motion.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Mr. Tait</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:OLON1">Hon. Mr. Olone</persName>, moved in
            amendment that the House adjourn till one o'clock tomorrow afternoon.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The Chairman</persName> ruled that an amendment to a motion for adjournment was out of
            order, and adjourned the House till ten o'clock next morning.</p>
 
</div>

                                                                                                                
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>