<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgAssinLAssem_1870-06-23" type="full">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgAssinLAssem">Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</name>, <date when="1870-06-23">23 June 1870</date>, Debates on Manitoba Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
         <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        
      </titleStmt>
      
      <publicationStmt><p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>


        <bibl>
          
<editor>Norma Jean Hall</editor>.
          
       
          <title>Reconstituted Debates of the Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</title>.
                    

          <date when="2010-11-15"/>.  
          
          <pubPlace>Winnipeg</pubPlace>: <publisher>Provincial Government of Manitoba</publisher>.
          
<!-- GL, 2017-03-24, The document itself does not contain any publishing info, but the editor's home page, https://hallnjean.wordpress.com/whats-done/, indicates that this project was initiated by the Manitoba Government which has their own link to the document in their resources, http://www.gov.mb.ca/imr/ir/major-initiatives/pubs/laa%20debates.pdf   -->

          <biblScope unit="page" from="110" to="110"/>.
        </bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
<!-- TEMPLATE: Provide a simple description of why this specific set of pages was 
        selected. This is especially important in cases where discontinuous 
        page-ranges are used.  -->
        <p></p>
      </samplingDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
     <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-24">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="debate">
    <head>Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</head>

<div type="section">

<head>Third Session</head>
    
<p><emph>Assembly Chamber, Upper Fort Garry</emph></p>

<p><emph>Thursday, 23 June 1870</emph></p>
    
<p>The third session of the Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia was opened today by the President, Hon. Louis Riel. There was a fair attendance of members present — the absentees being made up of those having long distances to come, who were, no doubt, detained by the recent rains.</p>
    
<p>In opening the proceedings, <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">the President</persName> briefly addressed the House.</p>
    
<p>Hon. Mr. Tait rose to move an adjournment. It was, he said, rather late — some more members might be looked for by to-morrow — and there was, he understood, a general desire that a matter of so much consequence as Rev. Mr. Richot's report should not come up at that sitting. The co-delegates of the rev. gentleman were absent — but he (Mr. Tait) moved an adjournment till one P.M. next day in order that some more members might be present to hear and consider the report which it was understood Rev. Mr. Richot was prepared to make of the mission to Canada.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> seconded the motion. As to the report, he had every confidence in Rev. Mr. Richot. Judge Black, in all probability, would not return — Mr. Scott was not expected for some days — but there could be only one report — and in giving that report Rev. Mr. Richot's statement might very well be taken.</p>    
<p>The motion carried. The House then adjourned.</p>
 
</div>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                           
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>