<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgAssinLAssem_1870-04-30" type="full">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgAssinLAssem">Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</name>, <date when="1870-04-30">30 April 1870</date>, Debates on Manitoba Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
         <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        
      </titleStmt>
      
      <publicationStmt><p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>


        <bibl>
          
<editor>Norma Jean Hall</editor>.
          
       
          <title>Reconstituted Debates of the Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</title>.
                    

          <date when="2010-11-15"/>.  
          
          <pubPlace>Winnipeg</pubPlace>: <publisher>Provincial Government of Manitoba</publisher>.
          
<!-- GL, 2017-03-24, The document itself does not contain any publishing info, but the editor's home page, https://hallnjean.wordpress.com/whats-done/, indicates that this project was initiated by the Manitoba Government which has their own link to the document in their resources, http://www.gov.mb.ca/imr/ir/major-initiatives/pubs/laa%20debates.pdf   -->

          <biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="80"/>.
        </bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
<!-- TEMPLATE: Provide a simple description of why this specific set of pages was 
        selected. This is especially important in cases where discontinuous 
        page-ranges are used.  -->
        <p></p>
      </samplingDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
     <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-24">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-27">Marked-up people.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="debate">
    <head>Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</head>


<div type="section">

    
<p><emph>Assembly Chamber, Upper Fort Garry</emph></p>

<p>Saturday, 30 April 1870</p>
    
<p>The President took the chair at eleven o'clock A.M.  </p>
    
<p>Minutes read and carried. Consideration of law committee report resumed.</p>
    
<p>Article XXI carried on motion of <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:DELO1">Hon. Mr. De Lorme</persName>.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, seconded <persName ref="pers:BRUC1">by Hon. Mr. Bruce</persName>, moved the adoption of Article XXII, with the substitution of the words "not over" for the word "under" wherever the latter occurs in the Article — Carried as amended.</p>    
<p>Article XXIII carried on motion of <persName ref="pers:DELO1">Hon. Mr. De Lorme</persName> seconded by <persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName>.</p>
    
<p>Article XXIV carried on motion of <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName> seconded by <persName ref="pers:SINC3">Hon. T. Sinclair</persName>.</p>
    
<p>Article XXV carried on motion of <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. Mr. Lascerte</persName>
            seconded by <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName>.</p>
    
<p>Article XXVI carried on motion of <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName> seconded by <persName ref="pers:SINC2">Hon. J. Sinclair</persName>.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> moved the adoption of Article XXVII, with the addition at the end of the Article of the words "above the age of fifteen years."</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BRUC1">Hon. Mr. Bruce</persName> seconded the motion, which was carried on a division — Yeas 16; nays 4.</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:GUNN3">Hon. Mr. Gunn</persName>, moved the adoption of Article XXVIII.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName>, moved in amendment that for the word "three" in the article, the word "two" be substituted.</p>
    
<p>Amendment lost on a division:— Yeas 10; nays 13.</p>
    
<p>Original motion carried — Yeas 13; nays 10.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:SCHM1">Hon. Mr. Schmidt</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName>, moved the adoption of Article XXIX which was as follows:—</p>
  
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">  
<p>"The Judge of the Supreme Court, shall be <hi rendition="simple:italic">ex officio</hi> a Justice of the Peace."</p></quote>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, moved in amendment that the Article be struck out.— Carried on a division — Yeas 18; nays 4.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, moved the adoption of Article XXX.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName> moved in amendment that the word "those" after the word "all," in the Article be struck out, and all after the word "country" in the said article. His object was, he said, to make it clear that the jurisdiction of the Supreme Court extended to all parts of the country.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> seconded the amendment.</p>
    
<p>After debate the amendment carried on a division — Yeas 12; nays 5.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> moved the adoption of Article XXXI, with the following alterations: that the words "or other person entitled" in the second line, be struck out, and the word "qualified" inserted, and that all after the word "paying" in the sixth line be struck out and the following inserted — "a license of Ten Pounds sterling per annum in advance." The latter amount was, he urged, the least they could think of charging an outsider entering on the lucrative profession of law in this country.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName> seconded the amendment.</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName>, as an amendment to the amendment, moved the adoption of Article as it stood — Not seconded.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName>'s amendment was put and carried on a division:— Yeas 14; nays 8. </p>
    
<p>Article XXXII carried on motion of <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName> seconded by <persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName>.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:GUNN3">Hon. Mr. Gunn</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:TOUR2">Hon. Mr. Touron</persName>, moved the adoption of Article I under the head "Customs Duties."</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:SCHM1">Hon. Mr. Schmidt</persName> moved in amendment that the House take a recess of fifteen minutes.</p>
    
<p>The House took a recess for half an hour.</p>
    
<p>The President having resumed the chair,</p>
    
<p>Business having been resumed,</p>
    
<p>Article I under the head "Customs Duties," was put and carried, as moved.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName> moved the adoption of Article II, with the addition of a sub-section providing that "mill and factory machinery" should be among the articles exempt from duty.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> seconded the motion and a sub-section (13) was added in accordance therewith, and the Article carried as amended.</p>    
<p>Article III carried on motion of <persName ref="pers:GARR1">Hon. Mr. Garrioch</persName> seconded by <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. Mr. Lascerte</persName>.</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, Article IV was adopted, on taking out the word "say", in the tenth line.</p>
    
<p>Article V carried on motion of <persName ref="pers:DELO1">Hon. Mr. De Lorme</persName> seconded by <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. Mr. Lascerte</persName>.</p>
    
<p>At half-past one P.M. on motion of <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, the House adjourned till Monday following at one P.M.</p>

 
</div>

                                                                                                                                                  
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>