<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgAssinLAssem_1870-04-29" type="full">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgAssinLAssem">Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</name>, <date when="1870-04-29">29 April 1870</date>, Debates on Manitoba Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
         <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        
      </titleStmt>
      
      <publicationStmt><p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>


        <bibl>
          
<editor>Norma Jean Hall</editor>.
          
       
          <title>Reconstituted Debates of the Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</title>.
                    

          <date when="2010-11-15"/>.  
          
          <pubPlace>Winnipeg</pubPlace>: <publisher>Provincial Government of Manitoba</publisher>.
          
<!-- GL, 2017-03-24, The document itself does not contain any publishing info, but the editor's home page, https://hallnjean.wordpress.com/whats-done/, indicates that this project was initiated by the Manitoba Government which has their own link to the document in their resources, http://www.gov.mb.ca/imr/ir/major-initiatives/pubs/laa%20debates.pdf   -->

          <biblScope unit="page" from="73" to="77"/>.
        </bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
<!-- TEMPLATE: Provide a simple description of why this specific set of pages was 
        selected. This is especially important in cases where discontinuous 
        page-ranges are used.  -->
        <p></p>
      </samplingDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
     <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-24">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-27">Marked-up people.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="debate">
    <head>Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</head>

  
<div type="section">

    
<p><emph>Assembly Chamber, Upper Fort Garry</emph></p>

<p>Friday, 29 April 1870</p>
    
<p>The President took the chair at two o'clock P.M.</p>
    
<p>The minutes of the previous sitting having been read and confirmed, the House resumed the consideration of the Law Committee Report.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:NORQ1">Hon. Mr. Norquay</persName>, moved the
            adoption of Article III under the head "Administration of Justice." — Carried</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:OLON1">Hon. Mr. Olone</persName>, moved the
            adoption of Article IV, with the substitution of the words "not more than" for the word
            "under" in sub-section 1. The alteration was made so as to enable the District Courts to
            dispose of cases of debt of ten pounds and under. — Carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName>, moved that Article V be adopted. </p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:MCKA4">Hon. Mr. McKay</persName> moved in amendment that a sub-section be added to the article, providing that in any case in which the sum involved was over five pounds, an appeal to the General Court might be made.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName> believed in giving every man having a case before the District Court, the right to appeal.</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> also argued on the same side. He did not believe in limiting
            the right to appeal to cases over five pounds, under the amendment proposed, simply
            because [if] the debt is below five pounds, you give him no appeal. If you give the
            right of appeal at all, give it to all parties coming before the Court.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:MCKA4">Hon. Mr. McKay</persName>, in Indian and English advocated his amendment. It was in the
            interest of the poor man that an appeal should not be in every case. Suppose the sum
            involved to be but twenty shillings, and the rich man loses and appeals it. The latter
            may out of mere spite, take the poor man to the General Court, and perhaps in the long
            run the latter may lose the case and be saddled with great additional expense.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">The President</persName> — There is this to be borne in mind in relation to the hon.
            gentleman's argument, that the losing party may be either rich or poor.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Wm. Tait</persName> — I support the original motion as it appears to me to be the
            fairest. The appellant knows if his cause is a bad one, the consequences of appeal will
            fall on himself. As to Article XXII, which has been referred to, it offers no chance in
            favor of a man having a case: for both parties must agree before they can go before a
            magistrate; and one of them may not consent.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:FRAS5">Hon. Mr. Fraser</persName> — I would suggest the amount of the judgment be struck out,
            and that it be not necessary to deposit it. Suppose a man desires to make an appeal, he
            has not only to pay the usual deposit, but also the judgment, which latter amount might
            be too large for him to be able to deposit. In a country like this, where many poor men
            may come into Court, I do not see why they should be practically shut out from appealing
            by being compelled to deposit the amount of the judgment.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> — The hon. gentleman would have us strike out the amount of
            the judgment, the very thing for which the parties came into Court. It is all very good
            to take care of the poor man. But in Courts, poor and rich are treated alike. If you got
            a judgment against a man, surely you are not going to allow the man to walk off from
            Court simply because he says, I appeal, and pays his twenty shillings. What hold have
            you over such a man for the amount of the judgment?</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Mr. Tait</persName> — If I get judgment against a man, I cannot see where the
            fairness lies in allowing that man to keep me out of my money three or six months by
            appealing, and perhaps a few days before Court sits, coming and paying the judgment.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName> — I believe it would be very hard to settle any case
            before the District Courts if what Hon. Mr. Fraser contends for were to prevail. If two
            men came before the District Court and judgment is given against one, the man against
            whom the case is decided, if he wishes to take advantage of the other, has only to say,
            I appeal, and pay a small deposit, and keep the other person out of his money for nearly
            three months. Fifteen days before the General Court, he may then come forward and pay
            the debt. </p>
    
<p>The amendment, not being seconded, dropped and the Article carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:OLON1">Hon. Mr. Olone</persName>, moved the adoption of Article VI.</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> said — This article was very much debated in committee, the
            great point at issue being as to whether a case should be tried in the district where
            the plaintiff or defendant resided.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:PARE2">Hon. Mr. Parenteau</persName>, moved in amendment that the Article be not adopted until amended so as to provide that cases should be tried in the district where the defendant resides.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> said that he was inclined to think that in justice to all parties the case ought to be tried in the defendant's district,— otherwise a man who was untried would be in reality subjected to punishment by being compelled to go, perhaps, a long way from home, at the summons of the plaintiff.</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName> was almost positive that in England the case had to be tried in
            plaintiff's district.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:MCKA4">Hon. Mr. McKay</persName> urged that in this country it was usual to bring the case on
            in the district where defendant resided — that is, in the case of the District
            Courts.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:NORQ1">Hon. Mr. Norquay</persName> argued that the plaintiff ought to have the right to bring
            the debtor to his district.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Mr. Tait</persName> contended that as District Courts were expressly formed for
            the benefit of those residing in the District, the plaintiff ought not to be enabled to
            bring a charge against a man and have him taken to any other district for trial. If the
            District Courts were not formed for the benefit of residents, why not have one Court in
            the centre, as in the case of the General Court?</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:SCHM1">Hon. Mr. Schmidt</persName> was in favor of having the case tried in defendant's
            district, as plaintiff was the aggressive party.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> supported the amendment. He believed that in other countries, in nearly all cases, the trial came off in defendant's district. If a merchant gives goods on credit, he does so at his own risk, for his own profit, and if he seeks to recover any debts which have been contracted, he should not be allowed to force the debtor, in many cases, a poor man, to come many miles from home in order to stand his trial.</p>    
<p>After a lengthy debate the amendment was put and carried on a division: Yeas 17; nays 5.</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:SCHM1">Hon. Mr. Schmidt</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName>, Article VII carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:DELO2">Hon. Mr. De Lorme</persName>, moved the adoption of Article VIII,— Carried on a division: Yeas 19, nays 2.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:GARR1">Hon. Mr. Garrioch</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:NORQ1">Hon. Mr. Norquay</persName>, moved Article IX — Carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:SINC3">Hon. Mr. T. Sinclair</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:SINC2">Hon. Mr. J. Sinclair</persName>, moved Article X — Carried.</p>    
<p>On article XI a debate arose.	</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> moved that Article XI be struck out and the following substituted:—	</p> 

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">   
<p>XI. 1. That in criminal cases jurors shall be each entitled to a fee of five shillings per day paid out of the public funds; and in civil cases five shillings per day paid out of the public funds: and in civil cases five shillings a day for each case on which they may serve. Should any case occupy more than one day, the jurors sitting thereon shall be entitled to five shillings a day each for each day or part of a day,— payable by plaintiff or defendant as the Court may decide.</p>

<p>2. Witnesses in criminal cases shall be entitled to the same amount per day as jurors; and in civil cases a witness shall be entitled to five shillings per day for each case and for each day of attendance in Court until the case is disposed of.</p></quote>
    
<p>After debate, at seven P.M., <persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, moved that the House take a recess for an hour and a half — Carried.</p>
    
<p>On resuming business at half-past eight P.M., Article XI, on motion of <persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:TOUR2">Hon. Mr. Touron</persName>, was put and carried.</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Mr. Tait</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, Article XII carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> moved the adoption of Article XIII with the substitution of the word "one pound" for "half a pound," before the word "pemmican."</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName> seconded the motion.</p>
    
<p>After debate, the article was carried, as amended, on a division: Yeas 16; nays 3.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:GUNN3">Hon. Mr. Gunn</persName>, moved
            the adoption of Article XIV, carried.</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:SINC2">Hon. J. Sinclair</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, Article XV carried.	</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> moved that Article XVI be amended by striking out the words "five pounds sterling for such license and." His object was to make a distinction in favor of the people of this country, by providing that they should be able to go into Court without any entrance fee the first year.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName> seconded the motion which was carried as amended.</p>    
<p>The consideration of Article XVII was postponed on motion of <persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:SCHM1">Hon. Mr. Schmidt</persName>, <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">the President</persName> having suggested that it was not explicit enough. </p>
    
<p>Article XVIII carried, on motion of <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:GUNN3">Hon. Mr. Gunn</persName>.</p>
    
<p>Article XIX carried, on motion of <persName ref="pers:SINC3">Hon. T. Sinclair</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName>.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">Hon. Mr. Sinclair</persName>, moved the adoption of Article XX.</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> suggested that in this article the word "or" after the
            word "newspaper," be changed to "and," and that the words "at the doors of all the
            churches" be struck out, and the following inserted instead "in some conspicuous place
            near the several churches."</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName> adopted Mr. O'Donoghue's suggestion and the Article carried as so amended.</p>
    
<p>At ten o'clock P.M., on motion of <persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:GARR1">Hon. Mr. Garrioch</persName>, the House adjourned.</p>
 


</div>


      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>