<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgAssinLAssem_1870-05-07" type="full">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgAssinLAssem">Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</name>, <date when="1870-05-07">7 May 1870</date>, Debates on Manitoba Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
         <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        
      </titleStmt>
      
      <publicationStmt><p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>


        <bibl corresp="bibl:lgAssinLAssem">
          
<editor>Norma Jean Hall</editor>.
          
       
          <title>Reconstituted Debates of the Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</title>.
                    

          <date when="2010-11-15"/>.  
          
          <pubPlace>Winnipeg</pubPlace>: <publisher>Provincial Government of Manitoba</publisher>.
          
<!-- GL, 2017-03-24, The document itself does not contain any publishing info, but the editor's home page, https://hallnjean.wordpress.com/whats-done/, indicates that this project was initiated by the Manitoba Government which has their own link to the document in their resources, http://www.gov.mb.ca/imr/ir/major-initiatives/pubs/laa%20debates.pdf   -->

          <biblScope unit="page" from="101" to="104"/>.
        </bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
<!-- TEMPLATE: Provide a simple description of why this specific set of pages was 
        selected. This is especially important in cases where discontinuous 
        page-ranges are used.  -->
        <p/>
      </samplingDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
     <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-24">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-27">Marked-up people.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="debate">
    <head rendition="simple:centre">Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</head>

  	
<div type="section">

    
<head rendition="simple:right">Assembly Chamber, Upper Fort Garry</head>

<head rendition="simple:right">Saturday, 7 May 1870</head>
    
<p>The President took the chair at four o'clock P.M.</p>
    
<p>Minutes having been read and confirmed and routine business transacted,</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:DELO2">Hon. Mr. De Lorme</persName>,
            moved — That all laws heretofore in force be repealed, on the 20th inst., and that the
            laws passed during the present session by the President and the Legislative Assembly of
            Assiniboia shall come into force on and after the 20th day of May next.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Mr. Tait</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:SINC2">Hon. J. Sinclair</persName>, moved in
            amendment that the following be added to the motion — The first General Quarterly Court
            shall be held on the second Tuesday in June next, instead of the usual time this month.— </p>

<p>Withdrawn. </p>
    
<p>Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue's motion carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Mr. Tait</persName> then moved a resolution providing for a sitting of the General
            Quarterly Court on the second Tuesday in June next — Carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, moved — That no action for the recovery of debt be brought before the August term of the Supreme Court. Those who have not been in the Settlement since the first day of November 1869, and those who may be preparing to leave the Settlement without satisfying their creditors, as provided for in the seventeenth Article under the heading "Administration of Justice," do not come under this law.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TAIT2">Hon. Mr. Tait</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:SINC2">Hon. J. Sinclair</persName>, moved in amendment that in all cases of debt, where the debtor is able to pay, this law shall not apply.</p>    
<p>Amendment lost on a division:— Yeas 4; nays 16 — Motion carried.</p>
    
<p>The House having resolved that Mr. W. Coldwell be paid the sum of fourteen pounds for reporting on the last Convention, and requested the Treasurer to pay the same, a Recess of half an hour was taken.</p>
    
<p>Business having been resumed,</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:RIEL1">The President</persName> formally approved of the Laws, and the blanks in the heading
            were filled up so as to show that the Laws were passed on the seventh day of May,
            1870.</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr.
              Poitras</persName>, the House went into committee of the whole to consider the
            nomination of magistrates and other public officials.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:RIEL1">The President</persName> — A law has been already passed, providing that, unless in
            certain unavoidable cases, all the old public officers shall be continued in office.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> — I held office as a J.P. but cannot accept office under the
            present arrangement, for reasons I have already pointed out in relation to the
            jurisdiction of the Supreme Court.</p>
    
<p>After debate, in the course of which the hope was expressed that the hon. member would not resign his position of J.P.,</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> suggested that the magistrates for the several districts
            should be named by the members present. In case the offices in any district were vacated
            by death or otherwise, or the holder were clearly disqualified, it would be for members
            to suggest some to fill the vacancies.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> — Is it necessary that District Magistrates should reside in the district for which they are appointed?</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> — I think so. </p>
    
<p>After [this] debate,</p>

<p>Lists were prepared for the several districts except Manitoba, which district was left to the arrangement of Hon. Mr. McKay. The lists contained the names of those most eligible, and were as follows:—</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre"><emph>Fort Garry District</emph></p>

    
<p><emph>J.P.s</emph> — Roger Goulet, R. McBeath, Hon. J. McKay.</p>

<p><emph>Magistrates</emph> — Pierre De Lorme, Hon. John Bruce, Hon. A.G.B. Bannatyne, President of the District Court; B. Morin, A. Fidler, John Fraser.</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre"><emph>White Horse Plains District</emph></p>

    
<p><emph>J.P.</emph> — Magnus Birston.</p>

<p>	Magistrates — Hon. J. McKay, President of Manitoba District Court; D. Spence, [Charles Ademar] Barron, Patrice Breland, R. Morgan, Hon. W. Tait, President White Horse Plains District Court.</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre"><emph>St. Andrew's District</emph></p>

    
<p><emph>J.P.</emph> — Donald Gunn, Senr.</p>

<p><emph>Magistrates</emph> — Thomas Sinclair, Charles Begg, John Tait, Alexander McBeath.</p>

<p rendition="simple:centre"><emph>Portage La Prairie</emph></p>

    
<p><emph>J.P.</emph> — Charles Curtis.</p>

	<p><emph>Magistrates</emph> — David Spence, and Hon. John Norquay, Junr.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:TOUR2">Hon. Mr. Touron</persName> proposed that Mr. Norbert Laronce of the parish of St. Norbert, be added to the list of magistrates.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:RIEL1">The President</persName> said that if each parish were to be represented, perhaps the magistrates might be too numerous. — Dropped.</p>    
<p>The lists having been submitted to the House, were approved of, and passed.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:RIEL1">The President</persName>, addressing the House,— It occurs to me that before we close, something may yet be done. We are here twenty-eight representatives of the people, but at the same time we feel in some manner that we are alone. In some respects the people still look to those who had been their leaders up to last Fall,— those composing the old Government; and it might be well if men such as these had an opportunity of joining in the administration of affairs. With this object in view the Executive thought of suggesting that a Senate should after this form a part of the Legislative authority. Senate is, of course, but a name, and the power it would have could be used well or ill, as other things. The names of those composing it would, of course, be the best guarantee we could offer for the feasibility and utility of the proposition.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> read the minutes of an Executive Council meeting from which it appeared that on the 7th inst. that body resolved that it was expedient to form a Senate, in accordance with a resolution passed in the recent Convention of English and French representatives, which was to the effect that whenever the Legislative Assembly felt it to be expedient, another Chamber should be formed — making the Legislature consist of two Houses. It was also resolved by the Executive that the following names should be submitted to the Assembly of those eligible to the Senate:— Right Reverend Bishop Taché, Right Reverend Bishop Machray, the Representative of the Hudson Bay Company in this country, Mr. Salomon Amlin, Mr. Roger Goulet, Mr. Andrew McDermott, senr., Mr. Patrice Breland, Mr. John Sutherland, Mr. McKenzie of Portage La Prairie, and either Mr. Truthwaite or Captain Kennedy.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> stated that a further resolution of the Executive Council was to the effect that the Senate should be composed of ten members, appointed for two years each — that the two bishops and their successors should be members for life,— and that in the absence of either bishop he might depute a person to act for him in the Senate.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:RIEL1">The President</persName> said — This is merely a proposition submitted, and this session I do not see that hon. members, who are anxious to return home, can fairly be asked to do more than pronounce on the question as to whether there shall be a Senate or not. Should the division be in the affirmative, details can be fixed next session. It is too important a question perhaps to take up in detail at present.</p>
    
  <p><persName ref="pers:HARR3">Hon. Mr. Harrison</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:OLON1">Hon. Mr. Olone</persName>, moved that the report be accepted.</p>    
<p>After debate,</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:LACE2">Hon. Mr. Lascerte</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName>, the House adjourned (at quarter past ten o'clock P.M.) till Monday following.</p>




</div>


                                                                                                                     
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>