<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgAssinLAssem_1870-04-28" type="full">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgAssinLAssem">Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</name>, <date when="1870-04-28">28 April 1870</date>, Debates on Manitoba Confederation with Canada.</title>
        
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
         <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
        </respStmt>
        
      </titleStmt>
      
      <publicationStmt><p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p></publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>


        <bibl>
          
<editor>Norma Jean Hall</editor>.
          
       
          <title>Reconstituted Debates of the Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</title>.
                    

          <date when="2010-11-15"/>.  
          
          <pubPlace>Winnipeg</pubPlace>: <publisher>Provincial Government of Manitoba</publisher>.
          
<!-- GL, 2017-03-24, The document itself does not contain any publishing info, but the editor's home page, https://hallnjean.wordpress.com/whats-done/, indicates that this project was initiated by the Manitoba Government which has their own link to the document in their resources, http://www.gov.mb.ca/imr/ir/major-initiatives/pubs/laa%20debates.pdf   -->

          <biblScope unit="page" from="69" to="73"/>.
        </bibl>

        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <samplingDecl>
<!-- TEMPLATE: Provide a simple description of why this specific set of pages was 
        selected. This is especially important in cases where discontinuous 
        page-ranges are used.  -->
        <p></p>
      </samplingDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
     <change who="lyallg" when="2017-03-24">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      <change who="kim_nguyen" when="2017-03-25">Marked-up people.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="debate">
    <head>Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia</head>

  

<div type="section">

    
<p><emph>Assembly Chamber, Upper Fort Garry</emph></p>

<p>Thursday, 28 April 1870</p>
    
<p>The President took the chair at half-past eleven A. M.</p>
    
<p>The minutes having been read and approved, </p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:RIEL1">The President</persName> briefly addressed the House.</p>    
<p>Recess at noon.</p>
    
<p>The President resumed the chair at three o'clock P.M.</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:TOUR2">Hon. Mr. Touron</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr.
              Poitras</persName>, it was resolved that the report of the committee on the Local Laws
            be taken up and considered article by article.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> moved the adoption of the first article. "That the heading 'Laws of Assiniboia, passed by the Governor and Council of Assiniboia,' be altered to 'Laws of Assiniboia, passed by the President and Legislative Assembly of Assiniboia' on the _______day of ______1870."</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName> seconded the motion.</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:MCKA4">Hon. Mr. McKay</persName>, moved in
            amendment that the article be adopted as it stands, filling up the first blank with
            "26th," and the second blank with "April." The hon. gentleman argued that the date ought
            to be that at which the session began, as in law the session was supposed to be a
            continuous session, and that every law was referable to the date at which the House
            began to sit.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> strongly objected to the words "Governor and Council of
            Assiniboia," in the original motion. The laws before the House were not the old laws a
            little altered. The old laws were taken as a guide, but none of them were adopted
            without undergoing many alterations. He was of opinion that the first step ought to be
            the repealing of all the old laws.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> — As a matter of fact, none of our laws will be passed on the 26th April, and I do not think that date should be inserted. Laws should not be made retroactive. If we make them such, we render it possible for a person to be charged with a breach of law which could not be known to him, for the very good reason that no such law was in force at the time of his alleged offence.</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> maintained his position that the laws should date from the
            commencement of the session. As to Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue's idea about repealing the laws,
            if adopted its effect would be to leave us without laws altogether. It would not be wise
            to repeal the old laws, until new ones had been sanctioned by the Executive.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName>,
            moved in amendment — That all the laws of the Governor and Council of Assiniboia, as
            heretofore in force, be repealed from and after the 15th day of May, 1870.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> objected to the last amendment, on the ground that it was out
            of place. At present the motion was merely to adopt a heading.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:RIEL1">The President</persName> — I do not think it would be well to frighten people by
            depriving them of all local law: Of course, even though there were no such laws in
            existence, we would still be under the laws of England. But even though that were the
            case, it was best not to repeal the old laws until others were substituted.</p>
    
<p>Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue's amendment was put and lost on a division:— Yeas 8, nays 11.</p>
    
<p>Hon. Mr. Bunn's amendment was then put and lost on a division:— Yeas 2; nays 19.</p>
    
<p>And the original motion was carried on a division — Yeas 14, nays 5.</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:FRAS5">Hon. Mr. Fraser</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName>, Article I under the head "General Provisions," was carried.</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:DELO2">Hon. Mr. DeLorme</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BRUC1">Hon. Mr. Bruce</persName>, Article II carried.</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:TOUR2">Hon. Mr. Touron</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, Article III carried.</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:BANN1">Hon. Mr. Bannatyne</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr.
              Bird</persName>, Article IV was put.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> — I think this Article is misplaced. We have not yet defined what the general law of the country is, the fifth Article, which specifies that the law of England is to be the general law of the country, ought to precede the one at present before the House.</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> — The article in question and many others might be changed in
            position to advantage. But I had the idea that a Publication Committee was to be
            appointed to revise all the articles and arrange them in order of sequence.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:SCHM1">Hon. Mr. Schmidt</persName> — The report of the committee has been submitted to the
            Legislative Assembly; and why should we not arrange it at once, without further
            reference to committees?</p>
    
<p>The article was then carried.</p>
    
<p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:BRUC1">Hon. Mr. Bruce</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:DELO2">Hon. Mr. De Lorme</persName>, Article V carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:SCHM1">Hon. Mr. Schmidt</persName> moved that all local enactments on record up to the 25th
            day of April, 1870, "be now repealed."</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName> moved in amendment that the Article be laid on the table. His
            object was to allow the old laws to stand till new ones were enacted.</p>
    
<p>No seconder.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> moved in amendment "As Hon. Mr. Hay's amendment has no
            seconder," that the Article be struck out.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:FRAS5">Hon. Mr. Fraser</persName> seconded the amendment which was carried on a division —
            Yeas 15; nays 8.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName>, seconded by <persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName>, moved the
            adoption of Article I under the head "Administration of Justice," on striking out the
            word "That" at the head of the Article — carried.</p>
    
<p>Article II under same head being put,</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> said he approved of the first five sub-sections of the article — although it seemed to him that the Fort Garry district was larger in population than any of the others. Seconded by <persName ref="pers:OLON1">Hon. Mr. Olone</persName>, he moved the adoption of the first five sub-sections leaving the balance of the Article to be dealt with separately as it would require attention.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> moved in amendment that the word "that" in the first line of the article and the word "all" before the words "District Courts" be struck out, and that with these alterations the Article as reported be adopted.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> seconded the amendment.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:MCKA4">Hon. Mr. McKay</persName> suggested that the period specified for holding the Manitoba Court be altered.— I would say that the first Tuesday in June would be a better day for holding the Court in that district than the fourth Tuesday in June.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Mr. Bunn</persName>, with the consent of the seconder and the House, altered his amendment in accordance with this suggestion.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:ODON1">Hon. Mr. O'Donoghue</persName> withdrew his motion.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:GARR1">Hon. Mr. Garrioch</persName> — In the definition of the Portage district, what is meant by the extreme end of the settlement? There were settlers at Rat Creek and White Mud River. Were they included in that district?</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> — In committee the White Mud River section was repeatedly mentioned, and was supposed to be included.</p>    
<p><persName ref="pers:GARR1">Hon. Mr. Garrioch</persName> — White Mud River lies more in the vicinity of Manitobah
            than of the Portage. I think it ought to be included in Manitobah.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:DAUP1">Hon. Mr. Dauphinais</persName> — I think White Mud River belongs rather to the Portage
            district.</p>
    
<p>In reply to Hon. Mr. Schmidt, <persName ref="pers:MCKA4">Hon. Mr. McKay</persName> said that in spring the people
            of White Mud River had a better road to go to the Portage than to Manitobah.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> — By Manitobah the committee only meant the Lake Settlement
            proper.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:GARR1">Hon. Mr. Garrioch</persName> moved in amendment to add the following words to sub-section 2: "And from thence to the Rocky Island in Lake Manitoba."</p>    
<p>After debate the latter amendment was withdrawn on the understanding, <persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> said, that the limits of the districts have been defined by the Legislature in a general way; matters of minor detail, such as it alluded to, would be dealt with by the Executive.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> having put his amendment as a substantive motion, it
            carried.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BIRD1">Hon. Dr. Bird</persName> moved that the House adjourn.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:HAY1">Hon. Mr. Hay</persName> moved in amendment that in future the House meet at nine
            o'clock A.M. and sit till noon; and with a recess of an hour and a half for dinner, sit
            till five P.M.; and that members not in attendance punctually be fined, say, Ten
            Shillings for each offence (laughter).</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:POIT1">Hon. Mr. Poitras</persName> seconded the amendment.</p>
    
<p><persName ref="pers:BUNN1">Hon. Mr. Bunn</persName> seconded the original motion, and the amendment, having been
            ruled out of order, dropped.</p>
    
<p>At seven o'clock P.M. the House adjourned till one o'clock P.M., following day.</p>


</div>
  
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>