<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-05-29" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-05-29">29 May 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1869">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
    
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

           <date when="1975"/>.
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="511" to="515"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0511.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0512.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0513.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0514.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0515.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0511">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0511.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0512">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0512.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0513">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0513.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0514">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0514.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0515">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0515.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="511" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0511.jpg"/>
            
<div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF COMMONS 
               <lb/></head>

              <head rendition="simple:right">Saturday, May 29, 1869 
               </head>
<p>
               The Speaker took the chair at three o'clock. 
               <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               PETITIONS 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>

            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BOWM1">Mr. Bowman</persName> presented a petition from 160 
               <lb/>
               inhabitants of Berlin for the repeal of the 
               <lb/>
               duty on books. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:OLIV2">Mr. Oliver</persName> presented a report from the Se<lb break="no"/>lect Committee appointed to consider the best 
               <lb/>
               means of relieving the country from the exist<lb break="no"/>ing plethora of American silver. The Commit<lb break="no"/>tee expressed the opinion that, all private ef<lb break="no"/>forts to remove the silver from circulation 
               <lb/>
               having failed, the intervention of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment had become necessary. They recom<lb break="no"/>mended that the plan adopted by the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment last year, by which $1,000,000 were 
               <lb/>
               exported to England, or any other plan which 
               <lb/>
               would have the same result, be resorted to 
               <lb/>
               until an amount equal to $5,000,000 should be 
               <lb/>
               withdrawn from the circulation of the coun<lb break="no"/>try. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>     
      <div type="section">     
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               THE NORTH WEST 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> moved consurrence in 
               <lb/>
               the resoltuions reported from Committee of the 
               <lb/>
               Whole respecting the acquisition of the North 
               <lb/>
               West Territory. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD2">Hon. John Sandfield Macdonald</persName> said he did 
               <lb/>
               not take credit for having done anything by 
               <lb/>
               any act of his during his public life towards 
               <lb/>
               the acquisition of this Territory. He did not, 
               <lb/>
               however, object to the scheme, although he 
               <lb/>
               had doubts whether the hopes built upon it 
               <lb/>
               would be realized. But he wished hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen on the Treasury Benches to satisfy him 
               <lb/>
               what they proposed to do with regard to pro<lb break="no"/>viding access to the Territory. Had they any 
               <lb/>
               scheme by which those who assumed the re<lb break="no"/>sponsibility of governing that Territory could 
               <lb/>
               reach it at all seasons of the year? A mere 
               <lb/>
               waggon road and water communication from 
               <lb/>
               Thunder Bay to Fort Garry would not satisfy 
               <lb/>
               the public. If we had not a winter road the 
               <lb/>
               country would be of no use. The Indians 
               <lb/>
               would very probably regard the influx of set<lb break="no"/>tlers as an invasion of their country, and what 
               <lb/>
               would we do in the event of our receiving in 
               <lb/>
               the winter-time "telegraphic intelligence," say 
               <lb/>
               by way of Pembina, that there had been a for<lb break="no"/><pb n="512" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0512.jpg"/><fw type="num">512</fw>  
               <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">May 28, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>midable Indian rising? Would it be neces<lb break="no"/>sary to maintain a standing army there to 
               <lb/>
               guard against such consequences, or were the 
               <lb/>
               settlers to be left unprotected? He did not 
               <lb/>
               mean to oppose the resolutions; but he thought 
               <lb/>
               the country would like to know what provi<lb break="no"/>sion was made against the eventualities to 
               <lb/>
               which he had alluded. He did not think the 
               <lb/>
               means we had at our disposal arising from the 
               <lb/>
               ordinary revenues of the country would be at 
               <lb/>
               all adequate for undertaking a railway or 
               <lb/>
               canal. Was it proposed to borrow money in 
               <lb/>
               order to provide a practicable route? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said before these questions 
               <lb/>
               were answered he would suggest the pro<lb break="no"/>priety of confining the discussion at present 
               <lb/>
               to the resolutions actually before the chair; 
               <lb/>
               which were for the purpose merely of acquir<lb break="no"/>ing the Territory. Other resolutions would no 
               <lb/>
               doubt have to be submitted to provide for 
               <lb/>
               gaining access to the territory and governing 
               <lb/>
               it, and it might be as well to reserve till then 
               <lb/>
               the discussion of the question raised by the 
               <lb/>
               member for Cornwall. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> said the member for 
               <lb/>
               Lambton had taken the correct view of the 
               <lb/>
               matter. When these resolutions passed an 
               <lb/>
               address would be sent from here, and we 
               <lb/>
               would then have to wait until effect was 
               <lb/>
               given to it by an Order in Council, or a 
               <lb/>
               proclamation by Her Majesty; and it would 
               <lb/>
               be necessary also to have an Imperial Act 
               <lb/>
               granting the Imperial guarantee. But mean<lb break="no"/>while, as soon as the address passed, the 
               <lb/>
               Government would bring a measure before 
               <lb/>
               the House to obtain authority to form a Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Government in that part of the Terri<lb break="no"/>tory which might be deemed fit for cultiva<lb break="no"/>tion, in order that as soon as the Queen's 
               <lb/>
               Proclamation issued no time might be lost in 
               <lb/>
               laying out townships for settlement. It would 
               <lb/>
               also be necessary for the Parliament of Can<lb break="no"/>ada to make adequate provision for establish<lb break="no"/>ing, as soon as possible, a suitable communica<lb break="no"/>tion with the country. There were certain pro<lb break="no"/>visional communications which might be 
               <lb/>
               established almost immediately, and the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of permanent communication, which 
               <lb/>
               would require a larger expenditure of money, 
               <lb/>
               would also have to be considered after the 
               <lb/>
               Provisional Government was established and 
               <lb/>
               further information obtained as to the re<lb break="no"/>sources of the country, and what parts of it 
               <lb/>
               were most suitable for cultivation. The 
               <lb/>
               Government would then be better prepared 
               <lb/>
               to come down next session with a measure 
               <lb/>
               on the subject. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. Smith</persName> alluded to the statement 
               <lb/>
               of the Quebec Conference, that this territory 
               <lb/>
               
          
            
            <pb n="513" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0513.jpg"/>
            
        
               was not to be added to the Dominion until 
               <lb/>
               the financial conditions of the Federal 
               <lb/>
               Government was such as to admit of it. The 
               <lb/>
               finances of the Dominion were clearly not in 
               <lb/>
               that condition at present. The people of the 
               <lb/>
               Maritime Provinces certainly were led to ex<lb break="no"/>pect that this burden would not have to be 
               <lb/>
               shouldered till they were better able to bear 
               <lb/>
               it. There was very little doubt, too, but that 
               <lb/>
               the expenditure in opening up that country 
               <lb/>
               would be necessarily enormous, more than 
               <lb/>
               could be borne, and, in his view, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had been altogether premature in this 
               <lb/>
               measure. The £300,000 asked for at the outset 
               <lb/>
               was but a small amount compared with that 
               <lb/>
               which would be needed for the opening up 
               <lb/>
               and governing of that country. For one he 
               <lb/>
               was dissatisfied with the course adopted by 
               <lb/>
               the Government on this point. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. Tilley</persName> denied that any advocate of 
               <lb/>
               Confederation in the Maritime Provinces, and 
               <lb/>
               especially in New Brunswick, had ever stated 
               <lb/>
               that this Territory would not be assumed un<lb break="no"/>til some indefinite period in the future, when 
               <lb/>
               the Dominion would be very rich, any more 
               <lb/>
               than they pretended the Intercolonial Railway 
               <lb/>
               would be postponed until the annual revenue 
               <lb/>
               would bear the cost of it. No such statement 
               <lb/>
               was ever made by him, at all events. He al<lb break="no"/>ways spoke of that Territory as one which 
               <lb/>
               would be absorbed in the Confederation be<lb break="no"/>fore 1871. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BROW1">Mr. Brown</persName> advocated prompt action in the 
               <lb/>
               interests of the settlers in the North West, as 
               <lb/>
               well as of the people of Canada. The settlers 
               <lb/>
               in the Red River section had for years ap<lb break="no"/>pealed to the Imperial and Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ments in vain for a change of government. And 
               <lb/>
               they had the further mortification of seeing 
               <lb/>
               that while England and Canada neglected the 
               <lb/>
               British subjects there, the Americans pro<lb break="no"/>tected their people. They had established a 
               <lb/>
               consulate there, and in many ways showed a 
               <lb/>
               due care for their fellow citizens—while they 
               <lb/>
               were doing this, what was the state of affairs 
               <lb/>
               among the British settlers? A cruel and grasp<lb break="no"/>ing monopoly oppressed and kept them down, 
               <lb/>
               and even illegally fined and imprisoned them. 
               <lb/>
               Facts of this nature he could establish by an 
               <lb/>
               affidavit which showed that very great in<lb break="no"/>justice indeed had been perpetrated by the 
               <lb/>
               Hudson's Bay Company. Hence it was that 
               <lb/>
               he implored hon. gentlemen not to delay, but 
               <lb/>
               to take the most prompt and energetic action 
               <lb/>
               in order to bring about a new state of affairs 
               <lb/>
               in that country. As to the question of route, 
               <lb/>
               by way of Minnesota was a very good one, 
               <lb/>
               but it was not advisable that emigrants should 
               <lb/>
               
        
            
            <pb n="514" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0514.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">514</fw> 
               <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">May 29, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>
        
               be sent around by that route while a much 
               <lb/>
               shorter one could be made across our own 
               <lb/>
               Territory. After speaking some time on the 
               <lb/>
               subject of route, Mr. Brown said in reference 
               <lb/>
               to the people of this country leaving for the 
               <lb/>
               United States many causes had been assigned, 
               <lb/>
               but there was one which he might mention, 
               <lb/>
               though perhaps it might appear invidious to 
               <lb/>
               do so. In the county he had the honour to 
               <lb/>
               represent there was a gentleman, a member 
               <lb/>
               of the Legislature, who had for years en<lb break="no"/>couraged people to leave the county of Brant, 
               <lb/>
               and settle in Arkansas. If the American 
               <lb/>
               Government could secure emigrant agents, 
               <lb/>
               within the very walls of our Legislature, it 
               <lb/>
               was no wonder that people left this country, 
               <lb/>
               (hear, hear). 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:FERG1">Mr. Ferguson</persName> desired to say a word or two 
               <lb/>
               in reply to the member for Westmoreland. 
               <lb/>
               To begin with that gentleman's opposition 
               <lb/>
               was too late. An agreement had been signed 
               <lb/>
               for the purchase of the Territory, but un<lb break="no"/>doubtedly the £300,000 to be paid as pur<lb break="no"/>chase money, would be so much thrown away 
               <lb/>
               unless followed up by the expenditure of 
               <lb/>
               much large sums for the opening out of the 
               <lb/>
               country. He felt very well satisfied with the 
               <lb/>
               mission of the delegates to England on this 
               <lb/>
               subject, and thought they deserved every 
               <lb/>
               credit. The hon. gentleman advocated the 
               <lb/>
               making of good roads into that country, and 
               <lb/>
               strongly urged that very soon something better 
               <lb/>
               than waggon roads should be constructed 
               <lb/>
               to open up communications with the North- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               West. He hoped the Government would not 
               <lb/>
               only borrow as much money as would enable 
               <lb/>
               them to purchase that Territory, but also a 
               <lb/>
               sum sufficiently large to establish a good per<lb break="no"/>manent line of steam communication. The 
               <lb/>
               Territory which they had acquired was mag<lb break="no"/>nificent, and would be cheap at one million 
               <lb/>
               instead of £300,000. He believed that to-day 
               <lb/>
               the Americans would gladly give twenty 
               <lb/>
               millions of dollars for it. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:THOM4">Mr. Thompson</persName>. (Ont. N.) strongly advocated 
               <lb/>
               the construction of a railroad to open up 
               <lb/>
               this splendid North West. By judicious ex<lb break="no"/>penditure such as this a very large and 
               <lb/>
               yearly increasing emigration to that country 
               <lb/>
               might be promoted; but if the tide of travel 
               <lb/>
               were left to find its way there by the round<lb break="no"/>about way of Minnesota, much of it would 
               <lb/>
               be lost by the way. He viewed this question 
               <lb/>
               of easy access to the North West as one of 
               <lb/>
               the greatest importance, and trusted that it 
               <lb/>
               would be dealt with by the House in no 
               <lb/>
               niggardly spirit of economy. The question of 
               <lb/>
               protection of the emigrants also required to 
               <lb/>
        
            <pb n="515" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-29_Page_0515.jpg"/>
            
        
               be dealt with by the Government, and would, 
               <lb/>
               he hoped, receive every consideration at 
               <lb/>
               their hands. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The resolutions were then concurred 
               in,<lb/>
               and 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               On motion of <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> seconded 
               <lb/>
               by <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName>, it was resolved "that 
               <lb/>
               an address embodying the resolutions be 
               <lb/>
               presented to Her Majesty, and that a select 
               <lb/>
               Committee, composed of Sir John A. Mac<lb break="no"/>donald, Sir George Cartier, Hon. Mr. Mc<lb break="no"/>Dougall, Hon. Mr. Tilley, Hon. Mr. Chauveau 
               <lb/>
               and Dr. Grant, be appointed to draw up such 
               <lb/>
               address." The address was then introduced, 
               <lb/>
               read a first and second time, and ordered 
               <lb/>
               to be engrossed; and a message was ordered 
               <lb/>
               to be sent to the Senate acquainting that 
               <lb/>
               body that the address had been passed, and 
               <lb/>
               requesting their concurrence. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
      </div>

<div type="section">
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               PATENTS OF INVENTION 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> moved the second 
               <lb/>
               reading of the Bill respecting Patents of In<lb break="no"/>vention, from the Senate. It was, he said, the 
               <lb/>
               same in many respects as the Bill adopted 
               <lb/>
               by the House last Session, with an additional 
               <lb/>
               clause enabling a person in New Brunswick 
               <lb/>
               or elsewhere in the Dominion to obtain under 
               <lb/>
               the new measure a patent which could cover 
               <lb/>
               the whole territory in the Dominion, provided 
               <lb/>
               that he was a British subject, and that the 
               <lb/>
               subject matter of the invention had not been 
               <lb/>
               already used in any other part of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion. To some extent, also, this measure 
               <lb/>
               amended a provision of the former law ap<lb break="no"/>plicable to the late Province of Canada. By 
               <lb/>
               that law it was necessary that an applicant 
               <lb/>
               for a patent should be a British subject; but 
               <lb/>
               by the present measure, a residence in any 
               <lb/>
               of the Provinces for a year or more, irre<lb break="no"/>spective of being a British subject, entitled 
               <lb/>
               a person to apply for a patent. Under the 
               <lb/>
               former Bill, a person introducing an inven<lb break="no"/>tion from any foreign country except Eng<lb break="no"/>land or the States, could get a patent for it 
               <lb/>
               here. That provision of the law was now set 
               <lb/>
               aside, as the present moment, when negotia<lb break="no"/>tions were expected between ourselves and 
               <lb/>
               the States in regard to reciprocity, was hard<lb break="no"/>ly the time for conceding to the Americans 
               <lb/>
               any advantage. Nothing could be done in 
               <lb/>
               that way until they had established more 
               <lb/>
               reciprocal commercial relations between the 
               <lb/>
               two countries. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> desired to ask an explana<lb break="no"/>tion on one point. It was said that patents 
               <lb/>
               in New Brunswick were to be made to cover 
               <lb/>
               the whole Dominion. Before the effect of 
               <lb/>
               such a law could be judged it would be nec- 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>