<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-05-25"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-05-25">25 May 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
     
         
         <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.  
          

           <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="435" to="436"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-25_Page_0435.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-25_Page_0436.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-22">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-22">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-18">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-05-25_Page_0435">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-25_Page_0435.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-05-25_Page_0436">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-25_Page_0436.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="435" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-25_Page_0435.jpg"/>
           

<div type="section">
 <head>HOUSE OF COMMONS</head>
            
            <p>Tuesday, May 25, 1869 
               <lb/></p>
               
<p>The Speaker took the chair at three o'clock. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MORR1">Messrs. Morris</persName>, <persName ref="pers:SIMA1">Simard</persName> and others, pre<lb break="no"/>sented petitions praying that no fundamental 
               <lb/>
               change be made in the present system of 
               <lb/>
               banking and currency. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BOWM1">Mr. Bowman</persName> presented a petition from 
               <lb/>
               Berlin for the repeal of the Insolvency Act. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Hon. Mr. Langevin</persName> brought down a return 
               <lb/>
               to the address for the correspondence with 
               <lb/>
               the Imperial Government and the British 
               <lb/>
               Minister at Washington, relative to a renewal 
               <lb/>
               of the Reciprocity Treaty; also papers rela<lb break="no"/>tive to the death of Dr. Hogan, of the Nova 
               <lb/>
               Scotia Railway; also papers relative to the 
               <lb/>
               seizure of the schooner "Mazeppa," in British 
               <lb/>
               waters, by an armed force from the United 
               <lb/>
               States. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> introduced a Bill to 
               <lb/>
               continue for a limited time the charter of 
               <lb/>
               the Jacques Cartier Bank. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIMA1">Mr. Simard</persName> introduced a Bill to continue 
               <lb/>
               the charter of the Union Bank of Lower 
               <lb/>
               Canada. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MORR1">Mr. Morris</persName> introduced a Bill to amend the 
               <lb/>
               charter of the City Bank. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>         
    <div type="section">     
            
            <head>
               THE NORTH-WEST 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> moved that on Friday 
               <lb/>
               next the House resolve itself into Committee 
               <lb/>
               of the Whole to consider the North-West 
               <lb/>
               resolutions, which he said were not yet print<lb break="no"/>ed, on account of yesterday having been a 
               <lb/>
               holiday. They would be in the hands of mem<lb break="no"/>bers to-morrow. The object of the resolutions 
               <lb/>
               was merely to give effect to the preliminary 
               <lb/>
               arrangement entered into by the Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Public Works and himself in England, and 
               <lb/>
               which had been ratified by their colleagues. 
               <lb/>
               The report and all the correspondence with 
               <lb/>
               reference to this important subject, were in 
               <lb/>
               the hands of members, and he hoped there 
               <lb/>
               would be no objection to his making this 
               <lb/>
               motion, although the resolutions were not 
               <lb/>
               printed, his objection being to expedite busi<lb break="no"/>ness. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said there could be no ob<lb break="no"/>jection to the hon. gentleman's motion, but 
               <lb/>
               
          
            
            <pb n="436" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-25_Page_0436.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">436</fw>
               <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">May 25, 1869<lb/> </fw>
            
       
               he hoped the resolutions would be distributed 
               <lb/>
               as early as possible. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> begged also to state 
               <lb/>
               that two despatches had been accidentally 
               <lb/>
               omitted from the return sent down to the 
               <lb/>
               House. They would be brought down tomor<lb break="no"/>row by message and would be in the hands 
               <lb/>
               of members before the discussion came on. 
               <lb/>
               They were a despatch from the Colonial Sec<lb break="no"/>retary acknowledging the reply to the ad<lb break="no"/>dress by both Houses of Parliament, and his 
               <lb/>
               subsequent despatch stating that on account 
               <lb/>
               of a legal difficulty Her Majesty had been 
               <lb/>
               advised not to comply with the request in the 
               <lb/>
               address. This despatch was mentioned in one 
               <lb/>
               of the resolutions which it was intended to 
               <lb/>
               submit to the House. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The motion was agreed to. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
    </div>

<div type="section">    
            
            <head>
               QUEEN'S PRINTER 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> gave notice that on 
               <lb/>
               Friday he would introduce a Bill respecting 
               <lb/>
               the office of Queen's Printer. It was proposed 
               <lb/>
               that the Queen's Printer should be a salaried 
               <lb/>
               officer with £500 a year, and have the control 
               <lb/>
               of all Government printing, the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi>, the 
               <lb/>
               Statutes and the Government printing gen<lb break="no"/>erally, and that all the printing except what 
               <lb/>
               was confidential should be given out to pub<lb break="no"/>lic competition for a term of five years. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> congratulated the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment on having arrived at this decision. He 
               <lb/>
               felt assured they would receive the support 
               <lb/>
               of this side of the House in carrying out the 
               <lb/>
               policy now announced. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The following Bills were read a third time 
               <lb/>
               and passed:-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Act to place all Canadian Vessels on an 
               <lb/>
               equal footing as regards pilotage in the port 
               <lb/>
               of Quebec, and for other purposes respecting 
               <lb/>
               pilotage.— <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Act respecting Cruelty to Animals, from 
               <lb/>
               the Senate.— <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir Geo. E. Cartier</persName>. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Act respecting certain Offences relative to 
               <lb/>
               Her Majesty's Army and Navy, from the 
               <lb/>
               Senate.— <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir Geo. E. Cartier</persName>. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            <p>
               Act for the better protection of Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's Military and Naval Stores, from the 
               <lb/>
               Senate.— <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
            
            <p>
               Act respecting Joint Stock Companies in<lb break="no"/>corporated by letters patent, from the Senate. 
               <lb/>
               —— <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">     
         
            
            <head>
               SUPPLY 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> moved the reception of the 
               <lb/>
               report of the Committee of Supply. The sev-<lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>       
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>