<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_MB_1870-03-07" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-03-07">7 March 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.  

         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.    
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="253" to="254"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-03-07_Page_0253.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-03-07_Page_0254.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-03-07_Page_0253">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-03-07_Page_0253.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-03-07_Page_0254">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-03-07_Page_0254.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="253" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-03-07_Page_0253.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     7 mars 1870 DÉBATES DES COMMUNES 253 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
   <div type="section">         

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     HOUSE OF COMMONS 
     <lb/>
</head>
            <head rendition="simple:right">Monday, March 7. 1870 
     
            </head>

            <p>The Speaker took the chair at three o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     DUTY ON COAL 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Several petitions were presented, asking for 
     <lb/>
     the imposition of a duty on coal and other 
     <lb/>
     articles imported from the United States. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     ASYLUM FOR INEBRIATES 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Also, a petition from Baptists of the Lower 
     <lb/>
     Provinces, asking for the establishment of an 
     <lb/>
     Asylum for Inebriates. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     IMMIGRATION AND COLONIZATION 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DUNK1">Hon. Mr. Dunkin</persName> presented the first report 
     <lb/>
     of the Committee on Immigration and Coloni<lb break="no"/>zation, recommending the reduction of the 
     <lb/>
     number of members required to form a 
     <lb/>
     quorum. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PETITIONS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACF1">Mr. MacFarlane</persName> presented the second report 
     <lb/>
     of the Committee on Standing Orders recom<lb break="no"/>mending the extension of the time for receiv<lb break="no"/>ing petitions for one week. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     AMALGAMATION OF BANK OF 
     <lb/>
     COMMERCE WITH GORE BANK 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MORR2">Mr. Morrison</persName> introduced a Bill intituled: 
     <lb/>
     "An Act to provide for the amalgamation of the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian Bank of Commerce, and the Presi<lb break="no"/>dent, Directors and Company of the Gore 
     <lb/>
     Bank". Referred to the Standing Committee on 
     <lb/>
     Banking and Commerce. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     DETROIT RIVER TRANSIT COMPANY 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CARL1">Hon. Mr. Carling</persName> introduced a Bill intituled: 
     <lb/>
     "An Act to incorporate the Detroit River 
     <lb/>
     Transit Company". Referred to the Committee 
     <lb/>
     on Railways. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     NORTH-WEST PAPERS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said that before going on 
     <lb/>
     with the "questions" by members, he wished to 
     <lb/>
     bring a matter to the attention of the House. 
     <lb/>
     He said that on Friday last the report of the 
     <lb/>
     Committee appointed to look over the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     West papers, was brought down. He under<lb break="no"/>stood that the correspondents of some of the 
     <lb/>
     newspapers had got possession of some of the 
     <lb/>
     papers connected with that report. It would be 
     <lb/>
     well if these gentlemen should understand that 
     <lb/>
     these documents should not be published 
     <lb/>
            

            
            <pb n="254" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-03-07_Page_0254.jpg"/>
            
<fw type="num">254</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">March 7, 1870 
     <lb/></fw>
            

     before they were laid before the House, and 
     <lb/>
     that no newspaper should get them before the 
     <lb/>
     House did. If the practice of allowing the press 
     <lb/>
     to have the use of these papers was to be 
     <lb/>
     continued, it was only fair that they should be 
     <lb/>
     given to all the newspapers at the same time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said, as he 
     <lb/>
     understood the matter, these and all other 
     <lb/>
     papers were brought down for the use of the 
     <lb/>
     members of the House and no person should 
     <lb/>
     get them before them. The prime object in 
     <lb/>
     getting down papers was for the use of the 
     <lb/>
     House. That the information should be given to 
     <lb/>
     the public, through the press, was a secondary 
     <lb/>
     consideration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said the members of the 
     <lb/>
     press were not to be blamed, because, as a rule, 
     <lb/>
     they had been allowed to get possession of 
     <lb/>
     these documents as soon as they were brought 
     <lb/>
     down; but, in this case, where eliminations 
     <lb/>
     were to be made, it was not expedient that they 
     <lb/>
     should have been taken away. However, the 
     <lb/>
     general rule authorized the press correspond<lb break="no"/>ents in their attempts to get the ordinary 
     <lb/>
     papers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said this was 
     <lb/>
     an exceptional case. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WOOD2">Hon. Mr. Wood</persName> asked if he had understood 
     <lb/>
     the leader of the Government to state, that 
     <lb/>
     when papers were brought down to the House 
     <lb/>
     that they were not then public, and had not the 
     <lb/>
     members of the press a right to get them and 
     <lb/>
     print them? He had always understood that 
     <lb/>
     papers were published, and were public prop<lb break="no"/>erty as soon as they were brought down to the 
     <lb/>
     House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said that these 
     <lb/>
     papers were given to the press as a matter of 
     <lb/>
     practice, but still the principle should not be 
     <lb/>
     violated, that the House should have the com<lb break="no"/>plete control of papers laid on the table. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     THOROUGHBRED STOCK 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BENO1">Mr. Benoit</persName> asked whether it was the inten<lb break="no"/>tion of the Government to abolish, during the 
     <lb/>
     present session, the duties imposed by the 
     <lb/>
     tariff of 1868 on cattle imported specially for 
     <lb/>
     the improvement of the breed? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HINC1">Hon. Sir Francis Hincks</persName> said he must return 
     <lb/>
     an answer similar to the one he gave last week 
     <lb/>
     on a kindred subject, namely, that the policy of 
     <lb/>
     the Government on this and other matters of 
     <lb/>
     the same kind would be declared at a future 
     <lb/>
     period of the session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <!--<p>
     [Mr. Mackenzie—M. Mackenzie.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>