<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_MB_1870-02-15" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-02-15">15 February 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1870">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>. 
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="4"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0001.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0002.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0003.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0004.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-06">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0001">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0002">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0002.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0003">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0003.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0004">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0004.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0001.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     15 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
<div type="section">           
<head rendition="simple:centre">
     HOUSE OF COMMONS 
     <lb/></head>
     <head rendition="simple:right">Tuesday. Feb. 15, 1870 
     
            </head>

            <p>
     The House having met at three o'clock, was 
     <lb/>
     summoned by a message from His Excellency, 
     <lb/>
     to meet in the Senate Chamber. Having attend<lb break="no"/>ed and being returned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     NEW MEMBERS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Speaker</persName> informed the House that during 
     <lb/>
     the recess he had received communications; he 
     <lb/>
     also informed the House that during the recess 
     <lb/>
     the Clerk had received from the Clerk of the 
     <lb/>
     Crown in Chancery, Certificates of the Elec<lb break="no"/>tion and Return of the following Members, to 
     <lb/>
     fill up vacancies which had occurred during 
     <lb/>
     the recess:-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Of John Lorne McDougall Esq., for the South 
     <lb/>
     Riding of the County of Renfrew. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Of Barthelemy Pouliot, Esq., for the Elector<lb break="no"/>al District of L'Islet. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Of the Hon. Sir Adams George Archibald, for 
     <lb/>
     the Electoral District of Colchester (Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Of Julius Scriver, Esq., for the Electoral Dis<lb break="no"/>trict of Huntingdon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Of the Hon. Sir Francis Hincks, K.C.M.G., 
     <lb/>
     C.B., for the North Riding of the County of 
     <lb/>
     Renfrew. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Of the Hon. Christopher Dunkin, for the 
     <lb/>
     Electoral District of Brome; and 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Of the Hon. Alexander Morris, for the South 
     <lb/>
     Riding of the County of Lanark. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The newly elected members having previous<lb break="no"/>ly taken the oath, were severally introduced 
     <lb/>
     and took their seats. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Speaker</persName> reported, that when the House 
     <lb/>
     did attend His Excellency the Governor Gener<lb break="no"/>al this day in the Senate Chamber, His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency was pleased to make a Speech to both 
     <lb/>
     Houses of Parliament, of which Mr. Speaker 
     <lb/>
     said he had, to prevent mistakes, obtained a 
     <lb/>
     copy, which he read to the House as follows:-<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Honourable Gentlemen of the Senate, 
     <lb/>
     Gentlemen of the House of Commons,</hi> 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>I recur, with confidence, to your advice, and 
     <lb/>have much satisfaction in being enabled, on 
     <lb/>the present occasion, to summon you to the 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="2" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0002.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">2</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">
     February 15, 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
           
     discharge of your public duties at the period of 
     <lb/>
     the year most convenient to yourselves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The circumstances under which we meet are 
     <lb/>
     in many respects auspicious. The bounty of 
     <lb/>
     Providence crowned the harvest with abun<lb break="no"/>dance, and made the Fisheries unusually pro<lb break="no"/>ductive; in many districts existing industries 
     <lb/>
     have been enlarged, and new enterprises have 
     <lb/>
     started into activity, furnishing fresh avenues 
     <lb/>
     for commerce, and additional employment for 
     <lb/>
     our people; whilst every day new sections of 
     <lb/>
     the country are being opened to the labours of 
     <lb/>
     the husbandman. The trade and wealth of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion are on the increase, and the equal 
     <lb/>
     administration of the laws maintains, as 
     <lb/>
     heretofore, the enjoyment of a general sense of 
     <lb/>
     security. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I have watched, with much anxiety, the 
     <lb/>
     course of events in the North-West Territories. 
     <lb/>
     Unfortunate misapprehensions of the inten<lb break="no"/>tions with which the country was sought to be 
     <lb/>
     acquired by Canada have led to complications 
     <lb/>
     of a grave character. With a view to their 
     <lb/>
     removal, I have thought it desirable to exhaust 
     <lb/>
     every means of conciliation, before adopting 
     <lb/>
     other measures; and the latest advices lead me 
     <lb/>
     to expect that the groundless alarms enter<lb break="no"/>tained by a portion of the inhabitants, have 
     <lb/>
     given place to a desire to listen to the explana<lb break="no"/>tions which I have caused to be made to them. 
     <lb/>
     Efforts made in the spirit which has animated 
     <lb/>
     my Government throughout, can scarcely fail 
     <lb/>
     to accomplish an equitable and peaceful solu<lb break="no"/>tion of the existing difficulty, and thereby 
     <lb/>
     secure the speedy incorporation of the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     West Territories with Canada, an object so 
     <lb/>
     earnestly desired by the Empire and the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     As the Act for the temporary Government of 
     <lb/>
     the Territories when united with Canada, will 
     <lb/>
     expire at the close of the present Session, a 
     <lb/>
     measure providing for their Government will 
     <lb/>
     be submitted for your consideration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Charters of most of the Banks of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion were, last Session, extended for a 
     <lb/>
     limited period, with the view that during the 
     <lb/>
     interval the questions of Banking and Curren<lb break="no"/>cy should receive the consideration which their 
     <lb/>
     importance demands. A measure intended to 
     <lb/>
     ensure safety to the community, without inter<lb break="no"/>fering with the legitimate operations of the 
     <lb/>
     Banks will be submitted for your consider<lb break="no"/>ation, and will, I trust, be found calculated to 
     <lb/>
     place those important interests upon a sound 
     <lb/>
     and stable basis. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            
            <pb n="3" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0003.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     15 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->

            <p>
     The Laws in force on the subject of the 
     <lb/>
     Elective Franchise, and the regulation of Par<lb break="no"/>liamentary Elections in the several Provinces 
     <lb/>
     of the Dominion, vary much in their opera<lb break="no"/>tions, and it is important that uniform provi<lb break="no"/>sion should be made, settling the Franchise 
     <lb/>
     and regulating Elections to the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons. A measure upon this subject will be 
     <lb/>
     submitted for your consideration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Under the operation of an Act of the Imperi<lb break="no"/>al Parliament, passed in the year 1869, to 
     <lb/>
     amend the laws relating to the Coasting Trade, 
     <lb/>
     and Merchant Shipping in British Possessions, 
     <lb/>
     a period of two years is given to the Legisla<lb break="no"/>tures of the several Colonies of the Empire to 
     <lb/>
     make provision for the regulation of the Coast<lb break="no"/>ing Trade. In the absence of legislation on the 
     <lb/>
     subject, within the period named, the provi<lb break="no"/>sions of the Imperial Law will be in force. The 
     <lb/>
     extent and value of our internal commerce, 
     <lb/>
     render legislation on this subject desirable, 
     <lb/>
     and a measure with regard to it will be submit<lb break="no"/>ted for your consideration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The creation of a Court of Appeal under the 
     <lb/>
     powers conferred upon you by the Union Act, 
     <lb/>
     is a matter deserving your attention. A meas<lb break="no"/>ure will be submitted to you for the establish<lb break="no"/>ment of such a Court, and for conferring upon 
     <lb/>
     it certain original jurisdiction. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The year 1871 is that in which the next 
     <lb/>
     decennial Census is fixed by law to take place. 
     <lb/>
     As there are different laws on the subject in 
     <lb/>
     the several Provinces, it will, therefore, be 
     <lb/>
     necessary to pass a General Act, to establish a 
     <lb/>
     uniform and accurate system throughout the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. Steps have already been taken to 
     <lb/>
     secure the co-operation of Newfoundland and 
     <lb/>
     Prince Edward Island; and, I trust, a Census 
     <lb/>
     upon one system will be made simultaneously 
     <lb/>
     in all Her Majesty's British North American 
     <lb/>
     Possessions. I need not expatiate on the impor<lb break="no"/>tance of the information which the tables of 
     <lb/>
     the Census are calculated to afford, as, in addi<lb break="no"/>tion to their interest and value on general 
     <lb/>
     grounds, it must be recollected that upon them 
     <lb/>
     depends the readjustment of the Parliamen<lb break="no"/>tary representation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gentlemen of the House of Commons,</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I have directed that the accounts of the last 
     <lb/>
     year shall be laid before you. The Estimates for 
     <lb/>
     the present financial year will also be submit<lb break="no"/>ted. They have been framed with every regard 
     <lb/>
     to economy, compatible with the efficiency of 
     <lb/>
     the Public Service; and you will, I trust, be of 
     <lb/>
     opinion that the Finances are in a satisfactory 
     <lb/>
     state, and that the people can, without incon<lb break="no"/>venience, afford, for the service of her Majesty, 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="4" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-15_Page_0004.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">4</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 15, 1870</fw>
           
     the supplies which it will be the duty of my 
     <lb/>
     Government to ask you to vote. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Honourable Gentlemen of the Senate, 
     <lb/>
     Gentlemen of the House of Commons,</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Act respecting the Militia and Defence 
     <lb/>
     of the Dominion has not failed to engage my 
     <lb/>
     attention. The high spirit and loyalty of the 
     <lb/>
     people are placed in a clear light by the fact 
     <lb/>
     that the Active Militia have, voluntarily, come 
     <lb/>
     forward largely in excess of the quota required, 
     <lb/>
     as well as by the zealous attendance of the 
     <lb/>
     various Corps at the annual training in the 
     <lb/>
     camps, and by the promptness with which they 
     <lb/>
     assembled in force, at the call of duty, on more 
     <lb/>
     than one occasion, when Fenian marauders 
     <lb/>
     threatened the peace of the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I have observed, with great satisfaction, the 
     <lb/>
     efforts which have been made in several of the 
     <lb/>
     Provinces of the Dominion to foster and 
     <lb/>
     encourage immigration to our shores. The con<lb break="no"/>tinued progress of great public works, in many 
     <lb/>
     portions of the country, will afford the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of early employment to intending immi<lb break="no"/>grants, and I look forward with confidence to 
     <lb/>
     the addition of a large and valuable class of 
     <lb/>
     settlers to our population during the coming 
     <lb/>
     season. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     During the Summer and Autumn I had the 
     <lb/>
     opportunity of visiting different parts of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion. I proceeded first to Quebec, thence 
     <lb/>
     to the Maritime Provinces; and at Halifax, I had 
     <lb/>
     the honour of receiving His Royal Highness 
     <lb/>
     Prince Arthur. Subsequently I attended His 
     <lb/>
     Royal Highness in a tour to the Province of 
     <lb/>
     Ontario. Everywhere the great capabilities of 
     <lb/>
     the country, and the proofs of vigorous indus<lb break="no"/>try made themselves apparent, and it became 
     <lb/>
     my pleasing duty to report to Her Majesty's 
     <lb/>
     Government, as the result of my observations, 
     <lb/>
     that the inhabitants of the Dominion are well 
     <lb/>
     contented with their position and prospects, 
     <lb/>
     and that the wish nearest their hearts is to 
     <lb/>
     avail themselves of the franchises and full 
     <lb/>
     powers of legislation, which they possess, in 
     <lb/>
     order to build up, as a portion of the British 
     <lb/>
     Empire, institutions of their own choice, by 
     <lb/>
     laws of their own making. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I now leave you to the labours of the session, 
     <lb/>
     with earnest aspirations for your complete 
     <lb/>
     success. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On motion of the <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Mac<lb break="no"/>donald</persName>, His Excellency's speech was ordered to 
     <lb/>
     be taken into consideration tomorrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PRELIMINARY PROCEEDINGS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Resolved, That the Votes and Proceedings of 
     <lb/>
     this House be printed, being first perused by [...]
     <lb/>
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>