<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-06-22" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-06-22">22 June 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1869">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="932" to="933"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-22_Page_0932.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-22_Page_0933.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-06">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-22_Page_0932">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-22_Page_0932.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-22_Page_0933">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-22_Page_0933.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="932" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-22_Page_0932.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">932</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 22, 1869</fw>
            
<p>
    [...] ment; and also to authorize, if necessary, the 
     <lb/>
     amalgamation of the said bank with any 
     <lb/>
     other bank or banks, and for other purposes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Act to amend the Charter and increase the 
     <lb/>
     Capital Stock of the North Shore Transpor<lb break="no"/>tation Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Act to continue for a limited time the 
     <lb/>
     Charters of certain Banks. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Act respecting Nova Scotia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Act to amend the Act of the late Province 
     <lb/>
     of Canada, 12 Vic., cap. 114. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Act to consolidate the laws relative to the 
     <lb/>
     Powers and Duties of the Trinity House of 
     <lb/>
     Quebec, and for other purposes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Act respecting Juvenile offenders within 
     <lb/>
     the Province of Quebec. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Act to amend the Act 31 Vic., chapter 33, 
     <lb/>
     and to make another provision with respect 
     <lb/>
     to the salaries and travelling allowances of 
     <lb/>
     the Judges. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Act for granting to Her Majesty certain 
     <lb/>
     Sums of Money required to defray certain 
     <lb/>
     Expenses of the Public Service for the finan<lb break="no"/>cial years ending respectively the 30th of 
     <lb/>
     June, 1869, and the 30th of June, 1870, and 
     <lb/>
     for other purposes relating to the Public 
     <lb/>
     Services. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After which His Excellency the Governor- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     General was pleased to reserve the following 
     <lb/>
     Bills for the signification of Her Majesty's 
     <lb/>
     pleasure thereon:-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>An Act respecting the Salary of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor-General. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     An Act for the Relief of John Horace 
     <lb/>
     Stevenson. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     THE PROROGATION 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Honourable Gentlemen of the Senate:-<lb/> men of the House of Commons:-</hi><lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The time has come when I am able to re<lb break="no"/>lease you from your labours, and I have the 
     <lb/>
     greatest pleasure in doing so, inasmuch as 
     <lb/>
     the session of which the opening was delayed 
     <lb/>
     for the reasons you are cognizant of, has ne<lb break="no"/>cessarily been protracted to a period some<lb break="no"/>what later than suits the general conveni<lb break="no"/>ence. Satisfaction may, I think, be express<lb break="no"/>ed at the result of your deliberations. In 
     <lb/>
     addition to the long list of measures and 
     <lb/>
     amendments on subjects of internal policy 
     <lb/>
     which has passed under your notice, your 
     <lb/>
     records show that memorable steps have been 
     <lb/>
     taken towards the accomplishment of the 
     <lb/>
     great scheme of uniting the whole of British 
     <lb/>
     North America in a single Confederation. 
     <lb/>
     You have sanctioned the arrangement enter<lb break="no"/>ed into in London by the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/><pb n="933" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-22_Page_0933.jpg"/><!--<fw type="dateline">22 juin 1869 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->ment in reference to the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tory. That wide expanse will, I hope, ere 
     <lb/>
     long be opened to settlement, and become 
     <lb/>
     the abode of myriads of thriving and indus<lb break="no"/>trious immigrants. The terms of the dele<lb break="no"/>gates from Newfoundland, and which it may 
     <lb/>
     be expected will prove acceptable to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of that island, have met with your con<lb break="no"/>currence. The basis has been laid for nego<lb break="no"/>tiations with the Government of Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island. Moreover, what is not of less 
     <lb/>
     importance, seeing that the good will of the 
     <lb/>
     people already within the Dominion is a mat<lb break="no"/>ter perhaps of greater, at least, of equal con<lb break="no"/>cern with the acquisition of new territories, 
     <lb/>
     you have adopted the precautions of timely 
     <lb/>
     and well-considered liberality in order to sat<lb break="no"/>isfy reasonable demands, and conciliate attach<lb break="no"/>ment in Nova Scotia. The Acts rendering 
     <lb/>
     the Criminal Law uniform will insure an ex<lb break="no"/>act and equal procedure, and cannot fail to 
     <lb/>
     be conducive in the highest degree to the 
     <lb/>
     public advantage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gentlemen of the House of Commons:</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     In Her Majesty's name I thank you for the 
     <lb/>
     supplies you have granted for the public ser<lb break="no"/>vice. Though the revenue accruing from im<lb break="no"/>port duties has not reached the expected 
     <lb/>
     standard, I rejoice to think that a vigilant 
     <lb/>
     supervision of the public expenditure has ob<lb break="no"/>viated the necessity of imposing any fresh 
     <lb/>
     burdens on the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Honourable Gentlemen and Gentlemen:</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I will not detain you further than to ex<lb break="no"/>press the hope that in returning to your 
     <lb/>
     homes you will find the country blessed with 
     <lb/>
     every prospect of an abundant season, and 
     <lb/>
     that you will continue your services to the 
     <lb/>
     State by encouraging industrial pursuits, dif<lb break="no"/>fusing contentment, and upholding the au<lb break="no"/>thority of the law in your respective neigh<lb break="no"/>bourhoods. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAUC1">Hon. Mr. Cauchon</persName> then announced that 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency was pleased to prorogue Par<lb break="no"/>liament to the 3lst of July, and Parliament 
     <lb/>
     stood prorogued accordingly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>