<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_MB_1870-02-17" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-02-17">17 February 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1870">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.

          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>. 
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="13" to="14"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="18" to="18"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="32" to="32"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="53"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0013.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0014.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0018.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0032.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0050.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0051.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0052.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0053.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-08">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0013">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0013.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0014">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0014.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0018">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0018.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0032">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0032.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0050">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0050.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0051">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0051.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0052">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0052.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0053">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0053.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="13" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0013.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     17 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
            
<div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">
     HOUSE OF COMMONS 
     <lb/></head>

     <head rendition="simple:right">Thursday, Feb. 17. 1870 
     
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The Speaker took the chair at three o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SAVA1">Mr. Savary</persName> rose to move the Address in reply 
     <lb/>
     to the speech from the Throne. With reference 
     <lb/>
     to the first paragraph he believed the House 
     <lb/>
     would agree with His Excellency that this was 
     <lb/>
     a most suitable time for the meeting of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. The last session was held at a later 
     <lb/>
     period, but that was owing to circumstances 
     <lb/>
     which rendered it necessary. The circum<lb break="no"/>stances under which they met was referred to 
     <lb/>
     in the second clause of His Excellency's 
     <lb/>
     Speech. The country had cause of congratula<lb break="no"/>tion for an abundant harvest last year through<lb break="no"/>out the whole Dominion. The Fisheries also 
     <lb/>
     had been unusually productive, and not only 
     <lb/>
     that, but the prices for fish ruled high. Repre<lb break="no"/>senting as he did a county largely interested in 
     <lb/>
     this important branch of our industries, it was 
     <lb/>
     especially gratifying to him to be able to make 
     <lb/>
     this statement. He would not enlarge upon the 
     <lb/>
     question of fisheries; but it was well known 
     <lb/>
     that the American Government had adopted a 
     <lb/>
     policy of excluding our fish from their mar<lb break="no"/>kets, except upon payment of a very high duty. 
     <lb/>
     This system still continued. It was satisfactory 
     <lb/>
     to know, that though our fisheries were subject 
     <lb/>
     to these burdens, our citizens were not subject 
     <lb/>
     to other burdens which the people of the 
     <lb/>
     United States had to bear. A more loyal, indus<lb break="no"/>trious and contented class of people, he was 
     <lb/>
     glad to say, did not exist in the Dominion, than 
     <lb/>
     the population of Nova Scotia engaged in the 
     <lb/>
     fisheries. (Hear, hear.) Notwithstanding the 
     <lb/>
     burdens under which they laboured, they were 
     <lb/>
     prosperous and contented, and looked with the 
     <lb/>
     utmost confidence to this Government to give 
     <lb/>
     them that protection which the importance of 
     <lb/>
     their industry demanded. His Excellency had 
     <lb/>
     not promised any particular measure with ref<lb break="no"/>erence to the increased protection of the fisher<lb break="no"/>ies guaranteeing to them those rights which 
     <lb/>
     the law of nations had given them; but he had 
     <lb/>
     reason to believe, that now that the United 
     <lb/>
     States were apparently determined to maintain 
     <lb/>
     their restrictions upon our fisheries, our Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment were disposed to take steps to protect 
     <lb/>
     this important branch of our industries. With 
     <lb/>
     regard to the North-West Territory misappre<lb break="no"/>hensions had undoubtedly existed with refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the intentions with which that country 
     <lb/>
     was sought to be acquired by Canada. There 
     <lb/>
     had been a complete misunderstanding on the 
     <lb/>
     subject. What object could the Dominion have 
     <lb/>
     in acquiring that Territory hostile to the 
     <lb/>
     inhabitants of the Territory, (hear, hear). It 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="14" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0014.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">14</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 17, 1870</fw>
            
     was inconsistent with the very spirit of our 
     <lb/>
     institutions not to recognize the rights of the 
     <lb/>
     people of every portion of the Dominion, how<lb break="no"/>ever small in number they might be. Whether 
     <lb/>
     the country was large or small their rights 
     <lb/>
     were the same, and though the people of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West were now small in number, we 
     <lb/>
     look forward to the day when that country 
     <lb/>
     would contain millions. It was contrary to the 
     <lb/>
     very spirit of our institutions that we should 
     <lb/>
     seek to obtain possession of that country for 
     <lb/>
     any other than the mutual good of the inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants of the Territory and ourselves. He 
     <lb/>
     rejoiced, and he believed the House would also 
     <lb/>
     rejoice, at the assurance His Excellency had 
     <lb/>
     given, that it was desirable to exhaust every 
     <lb/>
     means of conciliation before resorting to other 
     <lb/>
     measures. This proved that peace and harmony 
     <lb/>
     were recognized as the basis of our Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. We did not seek to extend our country by 
     <lb/>
     conquest but by peaceable means, and by 
     <lb/>
     mutual co-operation of the whole people to 
     <lb/>
     extend British institutions on the whole north<lb break="no"/>ern portion of this Continent, which in the 
     <lb/>
     Good Providence of God still belongs to the 
     <lb/>
     Crown of Great Britain (hear, hear). The 
     <lb/>
     Opposition had given them to understand that 
     <lb/>
     there would be a discussion on this subject, 
     <lb/>
     and it was quite right that all steps taken in 
     <lb/>
     connection with the acquisition of that Territo<lb break="no"/>ry be thoroughly discussed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—Hear, hear. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SAVA1">Mr. Savary</persName>—It was very easy to be wise 
     <lb/>
     after the event, but if errors had been commit<lb break="no"/>ted, though he would not say there had been 
     <lb/>
     any, this was a question on which the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment could confidently look for the generous 
     <lb/>
     consideration and forbearance of the House. He 
     <lb/>
     was not forgetful of the fact that he was one of 
     <lb/>
     those who could not at first see the propriety 
     <lb/>
     or necessity of so early seeking the incorpora<lb break="no"/>tion of this Territory into the Dominion; but 
     <lb/>
     his objections were founded upon doubt as to 
     <lb/>
     the pecuniary ability of the Dominion to 
     <lb/>
     expend so large a sum of money as he then 
     <lb/>
     believed to be necessary for the acquisition of 
     <lb/>
     the Territory. But the negotiations with the 
     <lb/>
     Hudson's Bay Company were conducted with 
     <lb/>
     consummate tact and ability—a tact and abili<lb break="no"/>ty crowned with a gratifying success, entitling 
     <lb/>
     the two gentlemen who were charged by the 
     <lb/>
     Government with those negotiations to the 
     <lb/>
     gratitude of this House and of the country, and 
     <lb/>
     the result was the acquisition of the Territory 
     <lb/>
     at a cost infinitely less than was apprehended. 
     <lb/>
     He had no doubt that, with the spirit in which 
     <lb/>
     the negotiations had been conducted, before 
     <lb/>
     long all difficulties connected with the 
     <lb/>
     immediate acquisition of the Territory would 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0018.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">18</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>  <fw type="dateline">February 17, 1870</fw>
            <p>
     wield the sceptre of our great Empire, and long 
     <lb/>
     may we remain loyal, devoted and law-abiding 
     <lb/>
     subjects of that Crown. He had great pleasure 
     <lb/>
     in moving the Address in reply (cheers). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SCRI1">Mr. Scriver</persName> in rising to second the Address, 
     <lb/>
     said he would claim the indulgence of the 
     <lb/>
     House, which he was sure would be extended 
     <lb/>
     to him while he endeavoured to fulfil the task 
     <lb/>
     which he accepted, and he would rely upon 
     <lb/>
     their indulgence, for the topics in the Address 
     <lb/>
     had been eloquently referred to by the honour<lb break="no"/>able mover. He could rejoice with His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency that the circumstances under which they 
     <lb/>
     met were so auspicious. They were in striking 
     <lb/>
     contrast with those under which the House met 
     <lb/>
     last session, when general gloom was cast over 
     <lb/>
     the country by the deficient harvest and other 
     <lb/>
     reverses, which tend to discourage the people. 
     <lb/>
     Though there were some adverse circum<lb break="no"/>stances, there was every reason to feel thank<lb break="no"/>ful for our gratifying bountiful harvest. It was 
     <lb/>
     desirable that a better market should be 
     <lb/>
     obtained for our agriculturists, and he had 
     <lb/>
     hoped that there would be a renewal of the 
     <lb/>
     commercial relations which formerly subsisted 
     <lb/>
     with the United States, and our agriculturists 
     <lb/>
     have this market for the disposal of their 
     <lb/>
     coarse grains; but they had been disappointed. 
     <lb/>
     It now becomes us to assume an independent 
     <lb/>
     policy (hear, hear), and to build up our manu<lb break="no"/>facturing interests, and thus create a home 
     <lb/>
     market for surplus produce. He hoped that 
     <lb/>
     future legislation would be in that direction. 
     <lb/>
     They would all rejoice at the prospect of a 
     <lb/>
     termination of the difficulties in the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     West but though the Act for the government of 
     <lb/>
     that Territory would, he hoped, be a liberal 
     <lb/>
     Act, that portion of the Dominion would con<lb break="no"/>tinue to be a Territory for some time. He trust<lb break="no"/>ed, however, that it would soon exchange that 
     <lb/>
     condition for a full grown State. He endorsed 
     <lb/>
     the views of the hon. mover in regard to the 
     <lb/>
     Finances, and also with regard to the desirabil<lb break="no"/>ity of an assimilation of the Currency. He con<lb break="no"/>sidered that the franchise could advantageous<lb break="no"/>ly be extended here as in the Mother Country, 
     <lb/>
     and saw no reason why a large class of intelli<lb break="no"/>gent people should be deprived of that privi<lb break="no"/>lege merely because they did not possess a 
     <lb/>
     certain amount of property. He thought that 
     <lb/>
     the Census would show progress in every part 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="32" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0032.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">32</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">
     February 17, 1870<lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     Brunswick. He could not congratulate the 
     <lb/>
     House upon progress of Confederation. It was 
     <lb/>
     time it was carried, but from expressions he 
     <lb/>
     had heard from members of this House he was 
     <lb/>
     forced to conclude that the Province was not 
     <lb/>
     satisfied. The policy of the Government with 
     <lb/>
     reference to the Intercolonial Railway had 
     <lb/>
     already been fully discussed and he did not 
     <lb/>
     intend to say anything further than that he 
     <lb/>
     should have been glad to have seen the policy 
     <lb/>
     with reference to the construction of that road 
     <lb/>
     materially altered. He thought a policy of 
     <lb/>
     economy should have been pursued. The policy 
     <lb/>
     which had been adopted in the construction of 
     <lb/>
     the Intercolonial Railway has given us the 
     <lb/>
     management of several hundred miles of rail<lb break="no"/>way—an arrangement that could not be carried 
     <lb/>
     on as well under Government control as by 
     <lb/>
     private parties, and it involved responsibilities 
     <lb/>
     which it would have been better not to assume. 
     <lb/>
     He was convinced that the expenditure upon 
     <lb/>
     this railway would itself form a serious burden 
     <lb/>
     upon the resources of the country. He regretted 
     <lb/>
     to observe that the policy which had been pur<lb break="no"/>sued with reference to Newfoundland and 
     <lb/>
     Prince Edward Island had borne results worse 
     <lb/>
     than barren. They had received a more decided 
     <lb/>
     negative from Newfoundland as regards Con<lb break="no"/>federation. And this House stood in the awk<lb break="no"/>ward position of having legislated with regard 
     <lb/>
     to terms to be offered to Prince Edward Island, 
     <lb/>
     which terms had been rejected entirely. With 
     <lb/>
     regard to the North-West question he was 
     <lb/>
     sorry to arrive at the same conclusion. An 
     <lb/>
     avowed resistance had been given to attempts 
     <lb/>
     to incorporate that Territory into the Domin<lb break="no"/>ion. Who was responsible for that state of 
     <lb/>
     things he would not pretend to say until all the 
     <lb/>
     correspondence and other papers connected 
     <lb/>
     with the matter had been laid before the 
     <lb/>
     House. When he looked from one end to the 
     <lb/>
     other of the Dominion he must pronounce the 
     <lb/>
     administration of the hon. member for Kings<lb break="no"/>ton a failure as regards the important measure 
     <lb/>
     entrusted to him, (hear, hear). He would fur<lb break="no"/>ther say that if there had been one thing that 
     <lb/>
     had saved Confederation from public disap<lb break="no"/>proval, it was not what had been done by the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Government but the efficient man<lb break="no"/>agement which had characterized the Local 
     <lb/>
     Governments of Quebec and Ontario—emi<lb break="no"/>nently the populous and wealthy Province of 
     <lb/>
     Ontario, and these Provinces could be appealed 
     <lb/>
     to as a proof of the satisfactory manner in 
     <lb/>
     which local powers had been administered. The 
     <lb/>
     Speech of the Governor General was a serious 
     <lb/>
     disappointment to him. There was but one 
     <lb/>
     source of congratulation in that Speech—it was 
     <lb/>
     thankfulness for the bountiful harvests; there 
     <lb/>
     was no hope held out that there would be a 
     <lb/>
     reconciliation of difficulties with that Prov<lb break="no"/>ince, and there is nothing to make us hope that 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <!--<p>
     [Hon. Sir A. T. Galt—L'hon. sir A. T. Gen.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            
            <pb n="50" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0050.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">50</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">
     February 17, 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     would have refused his support to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, on the ground of the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     entering the Cabinet. The Finance Minister 
     <lb/>
     now stated that he (Sir Alexander) had accord<lb break="no"/>ed him support, when in office, but he had been 
     <lb/>
     mistaken. He had given the hon. gentleman no 
     <lb/>
     support, unless it was for a very short time just 
     <lb/>
     previous to the dissolution in 1854. He (Sir 
     <lb/>
     Alexander) was in opposition to the Hincks 
     <lb/>
     Government of which Lafontaine and Baldwin 
     <lb/>
     were chiefs, and was in the strongest possible 
     <lb/>
     opposition with the present Minister of Justice, 
     <lb/>
     and moreover opposed the most important part 
     <lb/>
     of his policy. He (Sir Alexander) gave Hincks 
     <lb/>
     no support in his financial plans. Great excite<lb break="no"/>ment was caused about the Clergy Reserve and 
     <lb/>
     Seigniorial Tenure questions, and because 
     <lb/>
     nothing was put in the speech of Lord Elgin, he 
     <lb/>
     had opposed the Government of the day, of 
     <lb/>
     which Hincks was a member. With regard to 
     <lb/>
     the financial policy of those gentlemen there 
     <lb/>
     were some policies which required a certain 
     <lb/>
     amount of time to develop, and the policy 
     <lb/>
     which had been installed and carried out by 
     <lb/>
     the present Finance Minister was one which 
     <lb/>
     time had developed and which time and the 
     <lb/>
     country had almost unanimously condemned. 
     <lb/>
     He (Sir Alexander) had had experience in the 
     <lb/>
     finances of this country, and the difficulties 
     <lb/>
     and labours which had devolved upon Finance 
     <lb/>
     Ministers, from the time the present Finance 
     <lb/>
     Minister left, have been caused by legislation 
     <lb/>
     he originated. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JONE3">Mr. Jones</persName> (Leeds and Grenville) saw little 
     <lb/>
     good in Coalitions, and said when the Reform 
     <lb/>
     element was fully represented in the Cabinet 
     <lb/>
     by Brown, Howland and McDougall, some of 
     <lb/>
     the most extravagant acts of the Government 
     <lb/>
     took place. He regretted to see nothing in the 
     <lb/>
     Speech having reference to the fraudulent 
     <lb/>
     transactions of certain Government employees, 
     <lb/>
     and respecting which the country demanded 
     <lb/>
     information. He also regretted that no refer<lb break="no"/>ence had been made to Reciprocity, and spoke 
     <lb/>
     of the protection the Americans gave to their 
     <lb/>
     produce, which was admitted free to Canada, 
     <lb/>
     while Canadian produce had to pay heavy 
     <lb/>
     duties. He had a right to complain that the 
     <lb/>
     Reform party had seats offered them in the 
     <lb/>
     ministry, and good Conservatives, like himself, 
     <lb/>
     had a very poor chance. (Laughter.) This was 
     <lb/>
     very demoralizing. He had to stand alone in 
     <lb/>
     advocating the rights of the country, the 
     <lb/>
     Reformers following the Hon. George Brown, 
     <lb/>
     and Conservatives going like sheep after their 
     <lb/>
     leader. (Laughter.) He hoped they would 
     <lb/>
     devote more time in future discussing the real 
     <lb/>
     interests of the country, and less to personal 
     <lb/>
           
   
            <!--<p>
      [Hon. Sir A. T. Galt—L'hon. air A. T. Galt 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            
            <pb n="51" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0051.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     17 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
           
     explanations. A great deal of personal discus<lb break="no"/>sion had taken place but he could not see that 
     <lb/>
     the country had derived much benefit from the 
     <lb/>
     Reform element in the Cabinet. Several arbi<lb break="no"/>trations had been allowed under their rule 
     <lb/>
     which every Government had resisted. He 
     <lb/>
     instanced the Grand Trunk postal allowance, 
     <lb/>
     which was formerly $70,000, and although they 
     <lb/>
     had demanded an arbitration repeatedly, it was 
     <lb/>
     disallowed till Brown came in, and the result 
     <lb/>
     of the arbitration then sanctioned was that the 
     <lb/>
     grant was increased to $167,000. There was the 
     <lb/>
     claim for extras on the Ottawa Buildings also 
     <lb/>
     submitted by the Coalition Government, and 
     <lb/>
     he could only congratulate the country on the 
     <lb/>
     end of the Coalition. He was glad to welcome 
     <lb/>
     some new adherents to his way of thinking, 
     <lb/>
     and excited some laughter by complaining that 
     <lb/>
     when the Government were hard pushed they 
     <lb/>
     went to the opposite side of the House and 
     <lb/>
     purchased the leading men in Opposition, 
     <lb/>
     instead of taken respectable Conservatives like 
     <lb/>
     himself. He asked why there had been no allu<lb break="no"/>sion to the state of the Public Departments, in 
     <lb/>
     which plundering had been going on for the 
     <lb/>
     last fourteen years, and for which the heads of 
     <lb/>
     the Departments should be held responsible. 
     <lb/>
     He complained that no reference had been 
     <lb/>
     made to reciprocity, for want of which the 
     <lb/>
     country was suffering, and said that there was 
     <lb/>
     intense dissatisfaction among the farmers of 
     <lb/>
     Ontario on account of the want of protection, 
     <lb/>
     which allowed the Americans to send their 
     <lb/>
     Corn and coarse grains to the lumberers and 
     <lb/>
     millers to the exclusion of the producers here, 
     <lb/>
     who were undersold. The question of Confed<lb break="no"/>eration had seemed to occupy every mind to 
     <lb/>
     the exclusion of other matters, and he hoped 
     <lb/>
     that information of an important kind regard<lb break="no"/>ing the North-West would be furnished by the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary of State for the Provinces, who had 
     <lb/>
     lately been visiting the half-breeds and who he 
     <lb/>
     trusted had effected an improvement on that 
     <lb/>
     race. (Laughter.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOWE1">Mr. Bowell</persName> said the introduction of the 
     <lb/>
     Finance Minister would prove the destruction 
     <lb/>
     of the party in power. There was scarcely a 
     <lb/>
     man in Quebec or Ontario who had not opposed 
     <lb/>
     the appointment when it was proposed. The 
     <lb/>
     course followed by the Premier in bringing in 
     <lb/>
     such men, would result in his having a smaller 
     <lb/>
     following than he had at the time of the Coali<lb break="no"/>tion. He could easily understand the position of 
     <lb/>
     the member for Sherbrooke, who had to bear 
     <lb/>
     the burden of the sins committed by the 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="52" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0052.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">52</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">
     February 17, 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
          
     present Finance Minister when he had former<lb break="no"/>ly been in office. Not a man who took the 
     <lb/>
     stump in defence of the Government, of which 
     <lb/>
     the member for Sherbrooke formed a part, who 
     <lb/>
     did not take that ground in his defence and had 
     <lb/>
     to defend him (Sir Alexander) against the sins 
     <lb/>
     and iniquities of the present Finance Minister, 
     <lb/>
     to which he had fallen heir. It was strange that 
     <lb/>
     when the Finance Minister took office, if he 
     <lb/>
     was a Reformer, that he could not get a 
     <lb/>
     Reformer to resign in his favour, but had to get 
     <lb/>
     a Conservative to do so in a Conservative 
     <lb/>
     county. Galt's action in resigning on the 
     <lb/>
     Clergy Reserve question was quite intelligible 
     <lb/>
     to those who knew that it had been kept as a 
     <lb/>
     stalking horse for 25 years, and would never 
     <lb/>
     have been settled but for the Minister of Jus<lb break="no"/>tice and his friends who grappled with the 
     <lb/>
     subject, and settled the question equitably to 
     <lb/>
     all parties. He demanded that the charges 
     <lb/>
     against Messrs. Howe and Langevin should be 
     <lb/>
     explained, for if guilty of a tithe of what they 
     <lb/>
     were accused, they should be dismissed by 
     <lb/>
     their colleagues; if they supported them, they 
     <lb/>
     should all be driven out of office. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Howe was about to speak when <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Mackenzie</persName> said the ministerial explanations 
     <lb/>
     should be separated from the real debate on the 
     <lb/>
     Address, which it was almost too late to dis<lb break="no"/>cuss at that hour. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName> said he would be judged by 
     <lb/>
     his acts, and not by the slanders of the last few 
     <lb/>
     weeks. When the papers came down he would 
     <lb/>
     be ready to meet his slanderers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The first clauses of the Address were passed. 
     <lb/>
     On the one referring to the North-West being 
     <lb/>
     put, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MASS2">Mr. Masson</persName> (Terrebonne) expressed his dis<lb break="no"/>satisfaction at the position taken by the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, in reference to the North-West, and 
     <lb/>
     stated that on the introduction of the resolu<lb break="no"/>tions for an address to Her Majesty for the 
     <lb/>
     acquisition of the North-West in 1867, the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment had been asked to delay the matter at 
     <lb/>
     least until the second part of the session, a 
     <lb/>
     period of about two months, in order to afford 
     <lb/>
     the members an opportunity of well consider<lb break="no"/>ing the question which might in the future 
     <lb/>
     involve us in great difficulties with the Indi<lb break="no"/>ans, and be a source of enormous expense to 
     <lb/>
     the country. The answer given was, that no 
     <lb/>
     time could be lost, as the Americans were pour<lb break="no"/>ing into the country, and as any delay on our 
     <lb/>
     part would result in the annexation of those 
     <lb/>
     Territories to the United States, who were only 
     <lb/>
     watching an occasion. Over two years had 
     <lb/>
          
   
        <!--    <p>
     [Mr. Bowell—M. Bowell.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
           
            <pb n="53" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-17_Page_0053.jpg"/>
           <!-- <fw type="dateline">
     17 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
         
     passed since then, and, notwithstanding the 
     <lb/>
     dissatisfaction of the immense majority of the 
     <lb/>
     inhabitants and rumors of armed interference, 
     <lb/>
     our neighbours have not shewn the slightest 
     <lb/>
     idea of taking possession of the country. He 
     <lb/>
     charged the Government with great impru<lb break="no"/>dence, inasmuch as while buying not property 
     <lb/>
     but individuals, no care had been taken to 
     <lb/>
     ascertain their wishes. Until lately there had 
     <lb/>
     been a complete Government in the Territory, 
     <lb/>
     of which the Governor only was connected 
     <lb/>
     with the Hudson Bay Company, the interests 
     <lb/>
     of some of the members of the Council being in 
     <lb/>
     fact different from theirs, and if the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment here did not consult the people, they 
     <lb/>
     should at least have consulted the existing 
     <lb/>
     Government. Among the members of the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil were the Anglican and Roman Catholic 
     <lb/>
     Bishops who had always worked most har<lb break="no"/>moniously together for the good of the Colony, 
     <lb/>
     and whose advice would have been of the 
     <lb/>
     greatest importance. He then referred to a book 
     <lb/>
     or report written by Bishop Taché, who had 
     <lb/>
     lived over a quarter of a century in that Terri<lb break="no"/>tory and travelled over it in every direction. 
     <lb/>
     That report, he was informed, had remained 
     <lb/>
     unpublished in the hands of the Government 
     <lb/>
     for over two years, while the House had been 
     <lb/>
     furnished with the opinions of men who had 
     <lb/>
     remained in the country only a short time, 
     <lb/>
     gathered the greater part of their information 
     <lb/>
     from hearsay, and generally got up their 
     <lb/>
     reports with a particular object in view. He 
     <lb/>
     reflected severely on the Government for hint<lb break="no"/>ing at the use of force, and asked how it would 
     <lb/>
     have been regarded had the people of Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia been threatened, that every attempt at 
     <lb/>
     conciliation having been tried, other means 
     <lb/>
     would be used. He asked for the same treat<lb break="no"/>ment for the half-breeds of whatever race, as 
     <lb/>
     had been given to Nova Scotia. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName> wished the remarks of the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Terrebonne had been made 
     <lb/>
     after we had seen the policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, which would be based upon broad liberal 
     <lb/>
     principles. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> moved, seconded by <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Holton</persName>, the adjournment of the debate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The House adjourned at a quarter to eleven. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>