<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-04-23" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-04-23">23 April 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1869">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
           <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="57" to="57"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="59" to="60"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-23_Page_0057.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-23_Page_0059.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-23_Page_0060.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-18">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-23_Page_0057">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-23_Page_0057.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-23_Page_0059">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-23_Page_0059.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-23_Page_0060">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-23_Page_0060.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="57" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-23_Page_0057.jpg"/>
            

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BOWE1">Mr. Bowell</persName> would be happy to proceed at 
               <lb/>
               once if he thought he could have the assistance 
               <lb/>
               of the member for Chateauguay. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> would lend his assistance 
               <lb/>
               in going on, at all events. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BOWE1">Mr. Bowell</persName> said it was the practice of mem<lb break="no"/>bers to select their own time to proceed with 
               <lb/>
               their Bills, and he would do so. Others had 
               <lb/>
               already done so that day. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The matter then dropped. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
  <div type="section">
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               QUEBEC P.O. BUILDINGS 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CASA1">Mr. Casault</persName> enquired whether it was the 
               <lb/>
               intention of the Government to cause to be 
               <lb/>
               erected at Quebec, the Post Office for which 
               <lb/>
               an appropriation was made by the Parliament 
               <lb/>
               of the former Province of Canada, and 
               <lb/>
               whether the same is still available for the 
               <lb/>
               construction of that building. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> replied that the vote 
               <lb/>
               of the late Parliament of Canada had fallen 
               <lb/>
               with the Parliament itself. As to the Post 
               <lb/>
               Office, the Government would see about it. 
               <lb/>
               (Laughter.) 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
  </div>

<div type="section">
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               NORTH-WEST TERRITORY 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCCO2">Mr. McConkey</persName> enquired whether, in view 
               <lb/>
               of the acquisition of the North-West territory 
               <lb/>
               it was the intention of the Government to ask 
               <lb/>
               for an appropriation to open a communication 
               <lb/>
               between Fort William and Fort Garry, and if 
               <lb/>
               so, when operations to that end would be 
               <lb/>
               commenced. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said Parliament 
               <lb/>
               must first consent to the acquisition of that 
               <lb/>
               territory, before they could discuss any im<lb break="no"/>provements. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
</div>

<div type="section">  
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               AN ALLEGED DISMISSAL 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
   <p> 
      <persName ref="pers:CAME1">Mr. Cameron</persName> (Inverness) moved an address 
               <lb/>
               for copies of the correspondence relative to 
               <lb/>
               the dismissal of Mr. Cameron, a Postmaster 
               <lb/>
               of River Inhabitants, in Nova Scotia. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> stated that Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Cameron was never dismissed. The Post Office 
               <lb/>
               had been removed to a more central place. 
               <lb/>
               However, all the papers would be brought 
               <lb/>
               down. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CAME1">Mr. Cameron</persName> addressed the House explain<lb break="no"/>ing there had been a real grievance in the 
               [...] <lb/>
               
    
            
            <pb n="59" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-23_Page_0059.jpg"/>
            
       [...] which were really for the public interest to 
               <lb/>
               produce. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—Certainly. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:STRE1">Mr. Street</persName> differed with the member for 
               <lb/>
               Lambton in his statement, that the trustees 
               <lb/>
               were not exercising all the vigilance they 
               <lb/>
               could in respect to the realization of this prop<lb break="no"/>erty. It was property very difficult to realize, 
               <lb/>
               but both from personal knowledge and inter<lb break="no"/>views with the administrators from time to 
               <lb/>
               time, he felt convinced that they were making 
               <lb/>
               every effort in their power to bring to a real<lb break="no"/>ization at as early a period as possible the 
               <lb/>
               property under their control. He believed it 
               <lb/>
               would be found on enquiry that they were 
               <lb/>
               exerting themselves by every means in their 
               <lb/>
               power to convert that property with a regard 
               <lb/>
               to the interest of the creditors, and to the ad<lb break="no"/>vantage of the shareholders, and every other 
               <lb/>
               party having an interest in the winding up of 
               <lb/>
               this estate. His object in rising was simply to 
               <lb/>
               inform the mover of the resolution, that he 
               <lb/>
               had fallen into an error in thinking that the 
               <lb/>
               trustees did not exercise necessary vigilance 
               <lb/>
               and discretion. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said he did not question the 
               <lb/>
               vigilance or discretion of the trustees. He 
               <lb/>
               merely questioned the delay and expressed 
               <lb/>
               the opinion that the affairs of the Trust ought 
               <lb/>
               to be proceeded with more expeditiously. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The motion was carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div> 
         
<div type="section">          
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               THE FENIAN RAIDS 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:GALT1">Mr. Galt</persName> postponed, till Monday next, his 
               <lb/>
               motion regarding the outlay incurred by Can<lb break="no"/>ada in defence of the frontier during the 
               <lb/>
               raids from the States in 1863 and 1864. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>         
         
      <div type="section">     
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               REVENUE FROM TOBACCO, &amp;c. 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:GODI1">Mr. Godin's</persName> address for a statement of rev<lb break="no"/>enue from tobacco, &amp;c., was carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
      </div>
        
<div type="section">         
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               AMERICAN SILVER 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:OLIV2">Mr. Oliver's</persName> address regarding the expor<lb break="no"/>tation of American silver was also carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>
        
<div type="section">       
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               NORTH-WEST TERRITORY 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BODW1">Mr. Bodwell's</persName> address as to outlay in 
               <lb/>
               establishing communication between Fort 
               <lb/>
               William and Red River having been moved, 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            <pb n="60" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-23_Page_0060.jpg"/>
            
           <fw type="num">60</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 23, 1869</fw>
            
<p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName> said, he supposed the 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentleman desired to get, at one view, 
               <lb/>
               the whole expenditure on that service. Papers 
               <lb/>
               containing this would be brought down 
               <lb/>
               shortly. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said, if there was any report 
               <lb/>
               from Mr. Dawson, regarding the exploration 
               <lb/>
               of the present read, perhaps it would be ad<lb break="no"/>visable to include it in the papers to be sent 
               <lb/>
               down. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName> said, Mr. Dawson was 
               <lb/>
               not strictly in the employ of the Government 
               <lb/>
               at present, but it was understood that he was 
               <lb/>
               preparing a report on the subject of his last 
               <lb/>
               exploration. Last year he had been asked to 
               <lb/>
               make a more thorough exploration of the 
               <lb/>
               country between Lake Superior and the Lake 
               <lb/>
               of the Woods, and he had done so, and had 
               <lb/>
               been very successful in finding a road much 
               <lb/>
               superior in every way to that formerly pro<lb break="no"/>posed. On this subject he would make a full 
               <lb/>
               and, it was to be hoped, a satisfactory report. 
               <lb/>
               All the papers connected therewith would be 
               <lb/>
               brought down. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               In answer to <persName ref="pers:MACF1">Mr. Macfarlane</persName>, 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName> said Mr. Dawson 
               <lb/>
               chiefly devoted his attention to the district 
               <lb/>
               between the head of Lake Superior and the 
               <lb/>
               Lake of the Woods. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The motion carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The House adjourned at 4:30 o'clock. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>