<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-06-21" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-06-21">21 June 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1869">
          

          
               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.
          

         <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="902" to="905"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0902.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0903.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0904.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0905.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-30">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-30">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-18">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0902">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0902.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0903">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0903.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0904">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0904.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0905">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0905.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="902" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0902.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">902</fw>  <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 21, 1869<lb/></fw>
            
<p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> congratulated the House 
     <lb/>
     that the Senate had conceded that great right 
     <lb/>
     refused by the Minister of Militia, trial by 
     <lb/>
     Jury. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The amendments were read a second time 
     <lb/>
     and agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     REGISTRATION OF VESSELS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> announced that the 
     <lb/>
     Act respecting the Admeasurement and Reg<lb break="no"/>istration of Vessels would be reserved, and 
     <lb/>
     the opinion of the Home authorities obtained 
     <lb/>
     thereon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     ADMINISTRATION OF JUSTICE 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     On motion of <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> the 
     <lb/>
     House went into Committee on the Act re<lb break="no"/>specting the summary Administration of Jus<lb break="no"/>tice in Certain Cases, <persName ref="pers:HARR4">Mr. Harrison</persName> in the 
     <lb/>
     chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Committee rose and reported the Bill 
     <lb/>
     With amendments, which were concurred in, 
     <lb/>
     and the Bill read a third time and passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     DISEASES OF ANIMALS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The House then went into Committee on 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Hon. Mr. Langevin's</persName> Bill respecting Con<lb break="no"/>tagious Disease affecting Animals, <persName ref="pers:HARR4">Mr. Harri<lb break="no"/>son</persName> in the chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Bill was reported, and read a third 
     <lb/>
     time and passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     LEGISLATION IN CANADA 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald's</persName> Bill to remove 
     <lb/>
     doubts as to legislation in Canada regarding 
     <lb/>
     offences not wholly committed within its lim<lb break="no"/>its, was read a second time and passed 
     <lb/>
     through the remaining stages. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SUPPLY 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     On motion of <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName>, the House 
     <lb/>
     again went into Committee of Ways and 
     <lb/>
     Means, on the ordinary resolutions on which 
     <lb/>
     the Supply was based. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The following is the text of the resolu<lb break="no"/>tions: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     1st. That towards making good the supply 
     <lb/>
     granted to Her Majesty for the financial 
     <lb/>
     year ending the 30th day of June, 1869, the 
     <lb/>
     sum of $380,904.12 be granted out of the 
     <lb/>
     Consolidated Revenue Fund of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2nd. That towards making good the sup<lb break="no"/>ply granted to Her Majesty for the financial 
     <lb/>
           
            
            <pb n="903" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0903.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     21 juin 1869 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
         
     year ending on the 30th day of June, 1870, 
     <lb/>
     the sum of $14,205,016.68 be granted out of 
     <lb/>
     the Consolidated Revenue Fund of Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     3rd. That it is expedient to provide that, 
     <lb/>
     in order to enable the Consolidated Revenue 
     <lb/>
     Fund to meet the charges placed thereon, the 
     <lb/>
     Governor in Council be authorized to raise by 
     <lb/>
     way of loan, with the guarantee of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of the United Kingdom, a sum of 
     <lb/>
     money not exceeding $1,460,000 (£300,000 ster<lb break="no"/>ling) on the credit of the Consolidated Reve<lb break="no"/>nue Fund, being the sum voted to be paid 
     <lb/>
     to the Hudson's Bay Company whenever 
     <lb/>
     Rupert's Land is admitted into the Dominion; 
     <lb/>
     and that such loan may be raised on such 
     <lb/>
     terms, for such period, at such rate of interest, 
     <lb/>
     with such sinking fund and subject to such 
     <lb/>
     conditions as the Governor in Council may 
     <lb/>
     think most advantageous, with the approval 
     <lb/>
     of the Commissioners of Her Majesty's Trea<lb break="no"/>sury, and that such loan be a charge on the 
     <lb/>
     said Consolidated Revenue. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     4th. That it is expedient to provide that, 
     <lb/>
     in order to enable the Consolidated Revenue 
     <lb/>
     Fund to meet the charges therein, the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor in Council may raise by way of 
     <lb/>
     loan on the credit of the said fund a further 
     <lb/>
     sum not exceeding $1,460,000, being the sum 
     <lb/>
     voted for the purpose of opening communi<lb break="no"/>cation with the North-West Territory and 
     <lb/>
     establishing a Government therein, and pro<lb break="no"/>viding for the settlement thereof; and that 
     <lb/>
     such further loan be raised on such terms, 
     <lb/>
     for such period, at such rate of interest, with 
     <lb/>
     such sinking fund, and subject to such con<lb break="no"/>ditions as the Governor in Council may think 
     <lb/>
     most advisable, and that the same be a charge 
     <lb/>
     on the said Consolidated Revenue Fund. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5th. Whereas, authority has been given by 
     <lb/>
     the Act 31 Vic., Cap. 13, to raise by way of 
     <lb/>
     loan the balance of £2,000,000 sterling re<lb break="no"/>quired for the Intercolonial Railway, not yet 
     <lb/>
     negotiated; and by the Act 31 Vic., Cap. 41, 
     <lb/>
     to raise by way of loan £1,100,000, which 
     <lb/>
     may be required for certain works of Forti<lb break="no"/>fication; and by the Act 31 Vic., Cap. 
     <lb/>
     48, to issue Dominion Stock to the extent of 
     <lb/>
     the deposits made by Insurance Companies 
     <lb/>
     under the said Act, and by the Act of the late 
     <lb/>
     Province of Canada, 29 and 30 Vic., Cap. 10, 
     <lb/>
     and the Act of the Dominion, 31 Vic., Cap 
     <lb/>
     46, to issue Provincial notes to the extent of 
     <lb/>
     the balance of the sum of $8,000,000 therein 
     <lb/>
     mentioned; and whereas, over and above the 
     <lb/>
     said loans, there remained on the lst day of 
     <lb/>
     July, 1868, a balance of debentures, or other 
     <lb/>
     securities, negotiable under the authority of 
     <lb/>
     various Supply Acts, and under the Act of the 
     <lb/>
     late Province of Canada, 22 Vic., Cap. 14, sec. 
     <lb/>
     6, and under the Act of the Dominion of 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="904" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0904.jpg"/>
         
     <fw type="num">904</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 21, 1869<lb/></fw>

     Canada, 31 Vic., cap. 4, sec. 2, to the extent 
     <lb/>
     of the sum of $8,380,925.55 (<hi rendition="simple:italic">vide</hi> Public Ac<lb break="no"/>count, 1867-68, statement 26, part 2nd, p. 42), 
     <lb/>
     and whereas during the current financial year 
     <lb/>
     a further amount of debentures has been re<lb break="no"/>deemed, to the extent of $1,573,600, to which 
     <lb/>
     extent there is authority under the Acts above 
     <lb/>
     cited for the issue of new debentures or other 
     <lb/>
     securities, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Resolved,—That it is advisable that the 
     <lb/>
     authority to issue new debentures or other 
     <lb/>
     securities to the extent of the two last sums 
     <lb/>
     above named, amounting in the whole to 
     <lb/>
     $9,954,525.54 be cancelled and repealed, and 
     <lb/>
     that in lieu thereof, in order to meet such 
     <lb/>
     redemption and other charges on the Consoli<lb break="no"/>dated Fund, the Governor-in-Council may 
     <lb/>
     raise by way of a loan, on the credit of the 
     <lb/>
     said fund during the year ending 30th June, 
     <lb/>
     1870, a sum not exceeding $7,000,000 over 
     <lb/>
     and above the four special loans first above 
     <lb/>
     enumerated, that is to say; the balance of 
     <lb/>
     the Intercolonial Loan, the loan for Works 
     <lb/>
     of fortifications, the Dominion stock to cover 
     <lb/>
     Insurance Companies deposits, and the bal<lb break="no"/>ance issuable of Provincial notes, together 
     <lb/>
     with the two sums of $1,460,000 each for the 
     <lb/>
     purchase and opening out of the North-West 
     <lb/>
     Territories, as provided by the 3rd and 4th 
     <lb/>
     of the resolutions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     6th. That if at any time the Governor in 
     <lb/>
     Council shall deem it advisable to change the 
     <lb/>
     form of any of the existing funded debt by 
     <lb/>
     substituting one class of securities for an<lb break="no"/>other, the restriction as to the above 
     <lb/>
     total sum of $7,000,000, which shall not be 
     <lb/>
     exceeded in the year ending 30th June, 1870, 
     <lb/>
     shall not prevent the issue of new securities 
     <lb/>
     in the place of the old ones called in and re<lb break="no"/>deemed, provided neither the capital of the 
     <lb/>
     debt nor the annual charge for interest shall 
     <lb/>
     be thereby augmented. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     7th. That the Governor in Council may 
     <lb/>
     authorize the raising of the sums mentioned 
     <lb/>
     in the foregoing resolutions by any of the 
     <lb/>
     methods following, or partly by one and 
     <lb/>
     partly by another of such methods, that 
     <lb/>
     is to say, by the issue or issues 
     <lb/>
     of Dominion stock or debentures or of ex<lb break="no"/>chequer bills or exchequer bonds, or by the 
     <lb/>
     granting of terminable annuities, any of which 
     <lb/>
     securities shall be in such form and be made 
     <lb/>
     payable for such sums and bearing such rates 
     <lb/>
     of interest not exceeding 6 per cent per an<lb break="no"/>num, for or redeemable at such period of 
     <lb/>
     time respectively as the Governor in Council 
     <lb/>
     may deem expedient, and such provision 
     <lb/>
     may be made for the creation of a sinking 
     <lb/>
     fund for the payment of such loans and the 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="905" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-21_Page_0905.jpg"/>
           <!-- <fw type="dateline">
     21 juin 1869 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
    
     management thereof as the Governor in 
     <lb/>
     Council may deem expedient; and all sums of 
     <lb/>
     money so raised shall form part of the Con<lb break="no"/>solidated Revenue Fund. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> explained that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment took power in the resolutions to borrow 
     <lb/>
     to the extent of $7,000,000, repealing all other 
     <lb/>
     powers of borrowing conferred by previous 
     <lb/>
     Acts, the object being to restrict the bor<lb break="no"/>rowing power to the Supply Bill of each 
     <lb/>
     year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> did not see why the 
     <lb/>
     Government should ask the power to borrow 
     <lb/>
     with nine millions in the exchequer? 
     <lb/>
     (Laughter). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> replied that it was required 
     <lb/>
     for a special service. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> thought the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment announcement alarming, and implying 
     <lb/>
     the possibility, if not the probability, of the 
     <lb/>
     revenue falling short of the expenditure. It 
     <lb/>
     was a strange proceeding after all the finan<lb break="no"/>cial feats of the session. Mr. Holton said 
     <lb/>
     that before going into Committee, he intend<lb break="no"/>ed to call the attention of the Government 
     <lb/>
     to the fact that a very important Govern<lb break="no"/>ment measure had disappeared from the 
     <lb/>
     Order papers on Saturday night. The House 
     <lb/>
     had been repeatedly told that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment were going to push this measure 
     <lb/>
     through. He wished to know whether they 
     <lb/>
     intended to keep faith with the House and 
     <lb/>
     country in this matter; whether they in<lb break="no"/>tended resurrecting that order (laughter), 
     <lb/>
     which they could easily do by a day's no<lb break="no"/>tice? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> said the Government 
     <lb/>
     were not under the necessity of doing this. 
     <lb/>
     There had been three other notices on the 
     <lb/>
     paper; and that afternoon the Government 
     <lb/>
     would give the hon. gentleman an opportunity 
     <lb/>
     of taking up the matter. (Laughter) . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Committee rose and reported the resolu<lb break="no"/>tions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CRIMINAL LAW 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald's</persName> Bill respecting the 
     <lb/>
     Criminal Law, to repeal certain amendments 
     <lb/>
     therein mentioned, passed through its remain<lb break="no"/>ing stages. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     BANK CHARTERS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose's</persName> Bill, to continue for a 
     <lb/>
     limited time the charters of certain Banks, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>