<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-05-31" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-05-31">31 May 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1869">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.

         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.
          

         <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="539" to="539"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-31_Page_0539.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
         
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-05-31_Page_0539">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-31_Page_0539.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="539" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-31_Page_0539.jpg"/>
            
            <p>
             [...]  the exuberant anxiety which prevailed on 
               <lb/>
               the other side of the line to regulate the af<lb break="no"/>fairs of all other nations. It was said the 
               <lb/>
               British Parliament had discussed the conduct 
               <lb/>
               of the Canadian Parliament with reference to 
               <lb/>
               the Militia Bill. That was true, and he must 
               <lb/>
               say he felt indignant at the tone of remark 
               <lb/>
               which was then indulged in. But it should be 
               <lb/>
               remembered that the British Parliament had 
               <lb/>
               an interest in that question, for if we did not 
               <lb/>
               provide for the defence of the country it de<lb break="no"/>volved on them to do so. In conclusion he 
               <lb/>
               again argued that this Parliament had no time 
               <lb/>
               to waste on a matter foreign to it. They had 
               <lb/>
               just acquired the North-West, and had to con<lb break="no"/>sider how they were to govern it. They had 
               <lb/>
               got the elephant and must find out how to 
               <lb/>
               feed him. There were never 181 gentlemen 
               <lb/>
               assembled together as a representative body 
               <lb/>
               who had more responsible duties to discharge, 
               <lb/>
               and the duties which really belonged to them 
               <lb/>
               were quite sufficient to engross all their at<lb break="no"/>tention. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName>, referring to the argument of the 
               <lb/>
               President of the Council, that this Parliament 
               <lb/>
               had so much on its hands that it could not 
               <lb/>
               expend time in discussing a question of this 
               <lb/>
               kind, said if they looked to the period of the 
               <lb/>
               Session at which they had arrived, and that 
               <lb/>
               the Government had as yet brought to the 
               <lb/>
               stage of discussion hardly any of their more 
               <lb/>
               important measures, the argument was merely 
               <lb/>
               an evasion. They were said to be within a 
               <lb/>
               fortnight of their prorogation, and the elec<lb break="no"/>tion Bill had not as yet been so much as 
               <lb/>
               printed. As regards the North West negotia<lb break="no"/>tions, they had been brought before the House 
               <lb/>
               at so late a period that Parliament had not 
               <lb/>
               yet been asked to deal with the question, 
               <lb/>
               which the hon. gentleman had alluded to, of 
               <lb/>
               how the North West was to be governed. Cer<lb break="no"/>tainly the measures of the Government were 
               <lb/>
               not so forward as to admit the excuse that 
               <lb/>
               Parliament had not time to discuss this ques<lb break="no"/>tion. Then it was asked by the Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Justice would England so interfere with us; 
               <lb/>
               and the answer had already been given that 
               <lb/>
               England did interfere with us, and that not by 
               <lb/>
               an address from its Parliament, but by a des<lb break="no"/>patch from a Secretary or Under-Secretary of 
               <lb/>
               State, which was held sufficient to reverse the 
               <lb/>
               vote of this full Parliament, and to convert a 
               <lb/>
               majority of 136 in one session into a minority 
               <lb/>
               of 60 the next session. The President of Coun<lb break="no"/>cil said the conduct of the British Parliament, 
               <lb/>
               in discussing the proceedings of the Canadian 
               <lb/>
               Parliament with reference to the Militia Bill, 
               <lb/>
               was excusable, because they had an interest [...]
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>