<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-04-16"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-04-16">16 April 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="7"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="12"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="22"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0005.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0006.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0007.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0011.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0012.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0016.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0017.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0018.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0019.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0020.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0021.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0022.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-14">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-18">Marked-up people</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0005">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0005.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0007">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0006.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0006">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0007.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0011">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0011.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0012">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0012.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0016">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0016.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0017">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0017.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0018">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0018.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0019">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0019.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0020">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0020.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0021">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0021.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0022">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0022.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="5" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0005.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">HOUSE OF COMMONS</fw>
            
            
            
         
            <fw type="dateline">
               Friday, April 18, 1869 
               <lb/>
            </fw>
            <p> The Speaker took the chair at 3 o’clock. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

<div type="section">
            <head>
               PETITIONS 
</head>
            <p>
               Several petitions were presented. 
               <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            
            <head>
               SIR G. E. CARTIER 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>

            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir Geo. E. Cartier</persName> took his seat amid ap<lb break="no"/>plause. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">       
         
            
            <head>
               NEW MEMBER FROM WELLINGTON 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSS3">Mr. Ross</persName>, of Centre Wellington, was in<lb break="no"/>troduced by <persName ref="pers:STIR1">Mr. Stirton</persName> and <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>, 
               <lb/>
               and took his seat. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">        
         
            
            <head>
               THE ADDRESS 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The consideration of the address in answer 
               <lb/>
               to the Speech from the Throne was then 
               <lb/>
               taken up. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SIMP2">Mr. Simpson</persName> (Algoma) moved the adoption 
               <lb/>
               of the Address. On looking round him he saw 
               <lb/>
               so many in every way better qualiﬁed for the 
               <lb/>
               task he had undertaken that he felt keenly 
               <lb/>
               his own inability; but he trusted that the 
               <lb/>
               same kindness which had been extended to 
               <lb/>
               him on a former occasion, would also be ex<lb break="no"/>tended to him on this. With the opening 
               <lb/>
               paragraphs of the Speech few hon. gentlemen 
               <lb/>
               would, he believed, differ. He would desire 
               <lb/>
               more particularly to allude to the acquisition 
               <lb/>
               of the Hudson’s Bay Territory. They could 
               <lb/>
               not go into a single railway station without 
               <lb/>
               ﬁnding crowds of emigrants, some of them 
               <lb/>
               the young men of the country, who were 
               <lb/>
               going to ﬁnd their home in the Western 
               <lb/>
               States which the Dominion had not to offer. 
               <lb/>
               Hence, it was a subject of profound congrat<lb break="no"/>ulation that these negotiations had been car<lb break="no"/>ried on and completed, and that there could 
               <lb/>
               be now opened up to emigration a Territory 
               <lb/>
               offering far greater advantages than any por<lb break="no"/>tion of the United States. It was high time 
               <lb/>
               this Hudson’s Bay difficulty should be sur<lb break="no"/>mounted; for if Canada did not take hold of 
               <lb/>
               that country at once, in the course of a few 
               <lb/>
               years she would be squatted out. Minnesota 
               <lb/>
               and Dacotah were rapidly ﬁlling up, bringing 
               <lb/>
               the tide of immigration to the very borders 
               <lb/>
               of that North West Territory. He had lived 
               <lb/>
               some time in that section, and believed that 
               <lb/>
               its opening up and access to it by way of 
               <lb/>
               Canada would be an immense boom to the 
               <lb/>
               farming population of this Continent—as well 
               <lb/>
               as Europe. He knew the hardships endured 
               <lb/>
               
  
            
            <pb n="6" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0006.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">
               6</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> 
               <fw type="dateline">April 16, 1869<lb/></fw>
               

       
               by settlers in the bush, where a man’s life<lb break="no"/>time almost was spent before he could earn 
               <lb/>
               a competency; while, in this new territory, a 
               <lb/>
               poor man could go in and get a splendid start 
               <lb/>
               in a couple of years. As a grazing country, too, 
               <lb/>
               it had no superior. But the ﬁrst thing to be 
               <lb/>
               secured, on the acquisition of that territory, 
               <lb/>
               would be good and easy communication be<lb break="no"/>tween Canada and the North-West, through 
               <lb/>
               the British territory. For the last two years 
               <lb/>
               the Government had been engaged in open<lb break="no"/>ing a road between Thunder Bay, Lake Supe<lb break="no"/>rior, and Fort Garry. His opinion was that 
               <lb/>
               there was only one mode of communication 
               <lb/>
               by which they could hope to accomplish 
               <lb/>
               much in that section, and that was by rail<lb break="no"/>road. If the Dominion had not cash enough, 
               <lb/>
               then let them give lands to build such a rail<lb break="no"/>road. One of the earliest steps to be taken 
               <lb/>
               regarding the North-West was, the formation 
               <lb/>
               of a proper Government there. A land oiﬁce 
               <lb/>
               of some description ought also be speedily 
               <lb/>
               established. The aborigines, he would also 
               <lb/>
               remind them, had to be dealt with. A very 
               <lb/>
               material step to take would be the establish<lb break="no"/>ment of a department which would act hon<lb break="no"/>ourably and justly towards the Indians; and 
               <lb/>
               though the Hudson’s Bay Company was ex<lb break="no"/>cessively unpopular in Canada, he believed 
               <lb/>
               the Government could not do better than take 
               <lb/>
               a leaf out of the Company’s books, in the 
               <lb/>
               management of the Indians. The Company 
               <lb/>
               certainly never had any trouble with them; 
               <lb/>
               but had since they came into their country 
               <lb/>
               always maintained the most friendly rela<lb break="no"/>tions with the aborigines. In the North-West, 
               <lb/>
               he conceived, free grants of land would have 
               <lb/>
               to be made. The reservation of the treaty to 
               <lb/>
               be given to the Company had been objected 
               <lb/>
               to; but he thought it indispensable even if 
               <lb/>
               regard were had merely to that class of the 
               <lb/>
               Company’s ofﬁcers which conducted their 
               <lb/>
               trade in the country. Many of them had left 
               <lb/>
               their homes when young. It was certain the 
               <lb/>
               stockholders in London would never give 
               <lb/>
               them a sixpence on transferring the terri<lb break="no"/>tory, and these traders were men unﬁtted for 
               <lb/>
               the ordinary occupations of life. It would be 
               <lb/>
               hard to cast them abroad on the world with<lb break="no"/>out giving them a chance. In connection with 
               <lb/>
               the opening up of this territory, something 
               <lb/>
               had to be done to improve navigation on 
               <lb/>
               Lakes Huron and Superior. Additional steam<lb break="no"/>boat communication and harbours of refuge 
               <lb/>
               would have to be provided. Coming to the 
               <lb/>
               paragraphs regarding the admission of New<lb break="no"/>foundland into the Union, the House would, 
               <lb/>
               he was sure, fully agree with him that was a 
               <lb/>
               subject of congratulation. With the Union full 
               <lb/>
               and complete, there would be strength and </p>
            
         
            

            
         <pb n="7" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0007.jpg"/>
            
            
            <p>
               peace. Having alluded to the other para<lb break="no"/>graphs of the address, the hon. gentleman 
               <lb/>
               sat down amid cheers. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BOLT1">Mr. Bolton</persName>, in seconding the Address, said 
               <lb/>
               he would not trouble the House at any great 
               <lb/>
               length. It was gratifying to have His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency’s assurances of the prevalence of peace<lb break="no"/>ful counsels among the nations of the earth, 
               <lb/>
               giving the Dominion the assurance that it 
               <lb/>
               might continue to enjoy the peace it had 
               <lb/>
               hitherto been blessed with. In future, he 
               <lb/>
               trusted their resources would be devoted to 
               <lb/>
               the extension of the peaceful and industrial 
               <lb/>
               interests of the Dominion. In view of pros<lb break="no"/>pective large additions to the Dominion, it 
               <lb/>
               was to be hoped that those peaceful senti<lb break="no"/>ments would continue to prevail, and that 
               <lb/>
               the resources of the Dominion would be large<lb break="no"/>ly increased. Having expressed his grati<lb break="no"/>fication that Newfoundland had asked for 
               <lb/>
               admission into the Union, he expressed the 
               <lb/>
               pleasure he felt at the prospect that the dis<lb break="no"/>content of Nova Scotia would be allayed. He 
               <lb/>
               was sure that for wrong done to Nova Scotia, 
               <lb/>
               if any, reparation would be made. That was 
               <lb/>
               something against which not a voice would 
               <lb/>
               be raised. There were other topics of great 
               <lb/>
               importance alluded to in the speech; but they 
               <lb/>
               did not at that stage require a more extended 
               <lb/>
               notice. He had great pleasure in seconding 
               <lb/>
               the motion for the adoption of the address. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The Speaker</persName> having put to the House the 
               <lb/>
               adoption of the ﬁrst paragraph of the address, 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> said that before proceed<lb break="no"/>ing to the debate on the address, he desired 
               <lb/>
               to call the attention of gentlemen on the 
               <lb/>
               Treasury Benches to the necessity for offer<lb break="no"/>ing to the House explanations touching the 
               <lb/>
               changes made since last session in the con<lb break="no"/>stitution of the Government. They all heard 
               <lb/>
               the rumour that a distinguished member of 
               <lb/>
               the House who had been in strenuous oppo<lb break="no"/>sition to the Government during the whole 
               <lb/>
               of last Session, and not only in strenuous op<lb break="no"/>position to the Government, but to the funda<lb break="no"/>mental laws of the country, had become a 
               <lb/>
               member of the Government. It was to be 
               <lb/>
               taken for granted that the Government 
               <lb/>
               
      
            
       
            <pb n="11" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0011.jpg"/>
            
            
    
               now returned after a most successful mission 
               <lb/>
               and the negotiations could be renewed. In the 
               <lb/>
               meantime he could inform the House that the 
               <lb/>
               Department of Inland Revenue had been 
               <lb/>
               most successfully managed by the Post-<lb break="yes"/>
               master-General, who attended to these ad<lb break="no"/>ditional arduous duties during the whole of 
               <lb/>
               the winter, though at great personal loss and 
               <lb/>
               labour. The interests of the public service in 
               <lb/>
               this respect had not, therefore, suffered in 
               <lb/>
               any way. The thing, of course, could not be 
               <lb/>
               carried on, and it was the intention of the 
               <lb/>
               Government to ﬁll up the vacancy, and place 
               <lb/>
               a responsible man at the head of the Depart<lb break="no"/>ment. As to the proportional representation 
               <lb/>
               of the Provinces in the Cabinet, his honour<lb break="no"/>able friend would remember that it was 
               <lb/>
               stated by the Government during the ﬁrst 
               <lb/>
               session that these matters, the formation of 
               <lb/>
               the Government, division of the ofﬁces, &amp;c., 
               <lb/>
               were of necessity experimental, and this was 
               <lb/>
               the case yet. In the event of the absorption 
               <lb/>
               of the great North-West and Newfoundland 
               <lb/>
               into the Dominion, new duties and responsi<lb break="no"/>bilities would be involved, and very probably 
               <lb/>
               a re-adjustment of the different heads of the 
               <lb/>
               Departments. But he had no doubt that with<lb break="no"/>in the limits of a legitimate opposition, the 
               <lb/>
               Government would be supported in any ef<lb break="no"/>forts they might make to administer the new 
               <lb/>
               state of affairs. As to Mr. Howe, he (Sir 
               <lb/>
               John) hoped the people of Hants would soon 
               <lb/>
               enable that hon. gentleman to explain his 
               <lb/>
               own position on the ﬂoor of the House. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> thanked the Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Justice for his full and explicit information. 
               <lb/>
               It would be unusual and inconvenient to 
               <lb/>
               debate at that moment the policy involved in 
               <lb/>
               the explanations; but there was just one 
               <lb/>
               point more that ought to be explained. The 
               <lb/>
               Minister of Justice said in the course of his 
               <lb/>
               explanations, that negotiations had been en<lb break="no"/>tered into with the view of ﬁlling the vacant 
               <lb/>
               offices before the two members of the Cabinet 
               <lb/>
               went to England. As a matter of courtesy, 
               <lb/>
               the House was entitled to know what direc<lb break="no"/>tion these negotiations took, and why they 
               <lb/>
               did not go on. Having been informed that 
               <lb/>
               negotiations had been entered into, the House 
               <lb/>
               was entitled to know all about them. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said that at the 
               <lb/>
               proper time a full and frank explanation 
               <lb/>
               would be given. The negotiations ought never 
               <lb/>
               to be stated until they came to a result. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
      
            <pb n="12" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0012.jpg"/>
          
              <fw type="num"> 12</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS 
               DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 16, 1869<lb/></fw> 
     

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName>—You mentioned them 
               <lb/>
               yourself. (Laughter.) 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said that it was 
               <lb/>
               merely mentioned. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said there was one other 
               <lb/>
               point. The House had just been informed that 
               <lb/>
               the ﬁlling up of certain ofﬁces had been a 
               <lb/>
               matter of experiment. It would be desirable 
               <lb/>
               that the House should be informed concern<lb break="no"/>ing the two ofﬁces of Secretaries of State. Of 
               <lb/>
               course, this House was aware that the duties 
               <lb/>
               of both ofﬁces had been discharged by one 
               <lb/>
               person, the member for Dorchester. The 
               <lb/>
               House was entitled to know if that honour<lb break="no"/>able gentleman was hereafter to discharge 
               <lb/>
               the duties of both offices. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> was glad his atten<lb break="no"/>tion had been called to that subject. The 
               <lb/>
               ofﬁce of Secretary of State had been created 
               <lb/>
               because the necessity was felt for having a 
               <lb/>
               channel of communication between the Do<lb break="no"/>minion and Provincial Governments. It was 
               <lb/>
               deemed desirable that the numerous ques<lb break="no"/>tions which it was supposed would arise in 
               <lb/>
               this way should be disposed of by some one 
               <lb/>
               Minister. On the commencement of the new 
               <lb/>
               order of things, however, it was found that 
               <lb/>
               until the relative positions of the Provincial 
               <lb/>
               and Dominion Governments were ascertain<lb break="no"/>ed, until they came to be clearly deﬁned like 
               <lb/>
               those of old established Governments, a good 
               <lb/>
               portion of the subjects which would be or<lb break="no"/>dinarily assigned to the charge of the Sec<lb break="no"/>retary of State, had to be disposed of by the 
               <lb/>
               Minister of Justice. So many questions arose 
               <lb/>
               in constitutional law and kindred topics, that 
               <lb/>
               he, as Minister of Justice, had been obliged 
               <lb/>
               to direct his attention to them. Therefore a 
               <lb/>
               great deal of the work which would even<lb break="no"/>tually fall on some such ofﬁcer as the Secre<lb break="no"/>tary of State, devolved at present on the 
               <lb/>
               Minister of Justice. All correspondence be<lb break="no"/>tween the Provinces and the Dominion of 
               <lb/>
               course was conducted by the Secretary of 
               <lb/>
               State. For the present it was proposed that 
               <lb/>
               things should remain as they were, because 
               <lb/>
               it was clear that if there was any necessity 
               <lb/>
               for the offices, before the extension of the 
               <lb/>
               Dominion boundary, that necessity would be 
               <lb/>
               greatly increased the moment Newfoundland 
               <lb/>
               and the North West became part of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion. As he had stated before, the distribu<lb break="no"/>tion of ofﬁces and power was of necessity to 
               <lb/>
               a great extent experimental in the Dominion. 
               <lb/>
               From the mover of the Address they had 
               <lb/>
               heard what the Government would be ex<lb break="no"/>pected to do if they assumed the control of 
               <lb/>
               the North-West. The subjects then alluded 
               <lb/>
               to as having to be dealt with were numerous 
               <lb/>
               
    

            <pb n="16" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0016.jpg"/>

               <fw type="num">16</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> 
               <fw type="dateline">April 16, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            
   
               held in Norfolk in order to consider whether 
               <lb/>
               it was possible for that hon. gentleman to 
               <lb/>
               secure his re-election. The meeting, he pre<lb break="no"/>sumed, turned out to be rather unsatisfactory 
               <lb/>
               in its results, and a careful investigation of 
               <lb/>
               the wording of the Act enabled the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to come to the conclusion that it was 
               <lb/>
               possible, in violation of the spirit of the law, 
               <lb/>
               to allow the hon. gentleman to continue to sit 
               <lb/>
               here without obtaining from his constituents 
               <lb/>
               their sanction to his acceptance of ofﬁce. How 
               <lb/>
               were they to know to what extent this might 
               <lb/>
               not be pushed; if this were permitted what 
               <lb/>
               safeguard was there against the ﬁlling of this 
               <lb/>
               House with office-holders? During the last 
               <lb/>
               session of Parliament there had been con<lb break="no"/>siderable discussion on matters of economy; 
               <lb/>
               and the hon. gentleman with whom he 
               <lb/>
               claimed connection, had endeavoured to en<lb break="no"/>force economical principles on the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Various large amounts were asked 
               <lb/>
               for by the Administration. They wanted 
               <lb/>
               $5,000,000 for fortiﬁcations; but in common 
               <lb/>
               with others he had contended most earnestly 
               <lb/>
               against granting any such sum for the forti<lb break="no"/>fication of an impossible frontier. It had 
               <lb/>
               been claimed by the Minister of Justice that 
               <lb/>
               Mr. Howe had not taken a position against 
               <lb/>
               the Government, having come here pledged 
               <lb/>
               to adherence to no party in the House. Now 
               <lb/>
               he (Mr. Mackenzie) had happened to have 
               <lb/>
               taken down the words of that distinguished 
               <lb/>
               gentleman. He desired to speak with all pos<lb break="no"/>sible respect of him and say as little as 
               <lb/>
               possible against him until he was present, 
               <lb/>
               if he was to be present, and able to defend 
               <lb/>
               himself. But speaking of the acquisition of 
               <lb/>
               the North-West Territory, Mr. Howe said—<lb/>
               “in speaking on this question, I shall try 
               <lb/>
               to consider myself a Canadian, and speak 
               <lb/>
               from that point of view.” Mr. Howe then 
               <lb/>
               spoke as a Canadian, supposing the Union to 
               <lb/>
               be consummated. He was not speaking merely 
               <lb/>
               as a Nova Scotian, but he gave his views as a 
               <lb/>
               distinguished member of the House, and 
               <lb/>
               these views were not only hostile, but <hi rendition="simple:italic">bitterly</hi> 
               <lb/>
               hostile to the hon. gentlemen opposite. 
               <lb/>
               (Hear, hear.) Who did not recollect the 
               <lb/>
               powerful language in which he denounced 
               <lb/>
               the entire fortiﬁcation scheme of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and ridiculed the absurdity of the Do<lb break="no"/>minion Government, assuming control of the 
               <lb/>
               management of the far North-West. The 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentleman then seemed to prefer rather 
               <lb/>
               that the territory should fall into the hands 
               <lb/>
               of the United States, than that it should be<lb break="no"/>come part and parcel of the Dominion. On 
               <lb/>
               that policy he was at entire variance with 
               <lb/>
               the Government, and it would be instructive 
               <lb/>
               to know whether he has reversed his opinion 
               <lb/>
               on this question, or whether the Government 
               <lb/>
               
 
            
            <pb n="17" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0017.jpg"/>
            
            
  
               have altogether ignored his opinion on this 
               <lb/>
               and other material points of their policy when 
               <lb/>
               they asked him to assume oﬁice with them. 
               <lb/>
               These observations had been made by Mr. 
               <lb/>
               Mackenzie simply in consequence of the state<lb break="no"/>ments of the Minister of Justice that he had 
               <lb/>
               occupied a neutral position in the House. Had 
               <lb/>
               the remarks not been made, he should not 
               <lb/>
               have taken the liberty of dealing with the 
               <lb/>
               President of the Council in his absence. Re<lb break="no"/>verting to the question of fortiﬁcations, he 
               <lb/>
               (Mr. Mackenzie) expressed his surprise that 
               <lb/>
               nothing had been said as to the progress of 
               <lb/>
               these extensive works. Last year they were 
               <lb/>
               considered necessary, because the Ministry 
               <lb/>
               were apprehensive of war. The House was 
               <lb/>
               now assured that there was no danger of such 
               <lb/>
               a calamity. It would be well they should be 
               <lb/>
               informed as to what had been done in the 
               <lb/>
               way of fortiﬁcations, and if anything had 
               <lb/>
               been performed during the recess. He had 
               <lb/>
               visited certain portions of the country. He 
               <lb/>
               had been up the Ottawa through the interior, 
               <lb/>
               and had observed a number of points on the 
               <lb/>
               Ottawa and Lake Superior admirably adopted 
               <lb/>
               for fortiﬁcations if hon. gentlemen could only 
               <lb/>
               induce the Yankees to come to these particular 
               <lb/>
               places to make their attacks. (Laughter.) He 
               <lb/>
               felt at present as he felt last Session, that they 
               <lb/>
               had a most extravagant mode of conducting 
               <lb/>
               the public affairs of the country. In their 
               <lb/>
               attempts to re-organize their Departments; 
               <lb/>
               and even in their Militia Law, what was it 
               <lb/>
               but the same story—expense, expense con<lb break="no"/>tinually! Take the Militia Law as a sample. 
               <lb/>
               Under the former law, the enrollment was 
               <lb/>
               effected without expense. The same service 
               <lb/>
               had cost $63,000; and what was the grand 
               <lb/>
               result of their attempt at improving the 
               <lb/>
               Militia system? Simply that a more ridicu<lb break="no"/>lous farce than their present organization was 
               <lb/>
               never perpetrated on any civilized country. 
               <lb/>
               In the western Province they had old super<lb break="no"/>annuated men, who, for social and other 
               <lb/>
               reasons were appointed as captains and 
               <lb/>
               colonels. Men in every local city, as far as 
               <lb/>
               he knew, had been appointed to ofﬁcer the 
               <lb/>
               battalions without any reference to their 
               <lb/>
               military qualiﬁcations. Then they had Mili<lb break="no"/>tary Schools established by gentlemen now at 
               <lb/>
               the head of the Ontario Government; Schools, 
               <lb/>
               which it was supposed would be of advantage 
               <lb/>
               in this respect, that when they had been in 
               <lb/>
               operation some years, they would have turned 
               <lb/>
               out a body of trained officers, capable of dis<lb break="no"/>charging the duties appertaining to com<lb break="no"/>manders and subalterns of the militia force. 
               <lb/>
               He did not know how it was in other counties; 
               <lb/>
               but he believed that in his own county, though 
               <lb/>
               many respectable men had been appointed, 
               <lb/>
               men of both political parties, still there was 
               <lb/>
               

            
         <pb n="18" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0018.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">
               18</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> 
               <fw type="dateline">April 16, 1869<lb/>
               
            </fw>
            

               not among them a man who could make any 
               <lb/>
               pretentions to military knowledge, and he 
               <lb/>
               believed matters to be worse still in the 
               <lb/>
               county adjoining. These appointments had 
               <lb/>
               been avowedly made from one little party; 
               <lb/>
               and they had the hon. gentleman who was in- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               trusted with this selection avowing in his own 
               <lb/>
               paper that, until all his Tory friends had been 
               <lb/>
               satisﬁed, not one should get a commission who 
               <lb/>
               had opposed the Government or himself at 
               <lb/>
               the last election. (Hear, hear.) This was the 
               <lb/>
               new mode of administering the Militia affairs 
               <lb/>
               of the Dominion. (Hear, hear.) In the Militia 
               <lb/>
               administration there had not only been ex<lb break="no"/>travagance, but there had been a direct viola<lb break="no"/>tion of the votes passed by this House, and 
               <lb/>
               the utmost practical inefﬁciency. He was told 
               <lb/>
               the other day, on good authority, that in one 
               <lb/>
               parish, where it was known there were alto<lb break="no"/>gether only 65 male adults, a return had been 
               <lb/>
               made of something over 300, in order to in<lb break="no"/>crease the amount allowed per head for 
               <lb/>
               enrollment. He made these complaints with 
               <lb/>
               profound regret. He was desirous to see the 
               <lb/>
               Militia force organized on an efﬁcient footing, 
               <lb/>
               and he was sorry to say that, so far as he had 
               <lb/>
               been able to observe, this had not been done. 
               <lb/>
               The Minister of Militia was not directly to 
               <lb/>
               blame, having been absent from the country 
               <lb/>
               for six months, but some one ought to be held 
               <lb/>
               responsible. Until the papers were brought 
               <lb/>
               down, it would be manifestly inexpedient to 
               <lb/>
               discuss the question as to the admission of 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland into the Confederation; but 
               <lb/>
               as a sincere friend of the Union of the Prov<lb break="no"/>inces and British connection, he congratu<lb break="no"/>lated the Government, the House and the 
               <lb/>
               country on the application of another of our 
               <lb/>
               North American Colonies to be admitted 
               <lb/>
               into the Union, and he begged to say that 
               <lb/>
               anything he could do to aid the Government 
               <lb/>
               in carrying this matter to a successful com<lb break="no"/>pletion should be done most heartily and 
               <lb/>
               most cheerfully. (Hear, hear.) In regard to 
               <lb/>
               the opening up of the North-West Territory, 
               <lb/>
               he hoped the propositions of the Government 
               <lb/>
               would be so well considered that it would 
               <lb/>
               not be necessary for the hon. gentlemen acting 
               <lb/>
               with him to propose any serious amendment, 
               <lb/>
               as it was for the interest of the country that 
               <lb/>
               all questions connected with the opening up 
               <lb/>
               of that vast Territory should be settled as 
               <lb/>
               soon as possible, and upon as equitable a 
               <lb/>
               basis as possible. It was a serious matter to 
               <lb/>
               undertake the government of that great Prov<lb break="no"/>ince, as it soon would be, and the whole 
               <lb/>
               matter was one which would require the 
               <lb/>
               utmost attention of the Government and all 
               <lb/>
               other members of this House. He particularly 
               <lb/>
               recognized in that his own responsibility, as 
               <lb/>
               a member of the House, and should aid in 
               <lb/>


            <pb n="19" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0019.jpg"/>
            

               perfecting arrangements which would have 
               <lb/>
               an inﬂuence on the condition of all the Prov<lb break="no"/>inces for many generations. Mr. Mackenzie 
               <lb/>
               then reverted to the pernicious system in<lb break="no"/>augurated by this Government, in allowing 
               <lb/>
               officeholders to retain their seats in the House 
               <lb/>
               without even requiring them to go before 
               <lb/>
               their constituents for re-election. He said they 
               <lb/>
               might just as well admit Judges and other 
               <lb/>
               such functionaries as the Arbitrator between 
               <lb/>
               the Provinces and the Intercolonial Railroad 
               <lb/>
               Commissioners. He had heard that another 
               <lb/>
               member of the House was to be appointed a 
               <lb/>
               Commissioner for codifying the laws; but he 
               <lb/>
               sincerely trusted that if such a step had been 
               <lb/>
               intended it would be reconsidered. Such a 
               <lb/>
               policy was in the highest degree destructive 
               <lb/>
               of public morality, and would gradually de<lb break="no"/>stroy in the public mind that respect which 
               <lb/>
               ought to exist for the Legislature of the 
               <lb/>
               country. There was another point to which 
               <lb/>
               he would allude before sitting down. The 
               <lb/>
               Minister of Justice professed to have con<lb break="no"/>structed this Government on the Coalition 
               <lb/>
               principle. They had been told by the Minister 
               <lb/>
               of Public Works and the late Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Inland Revenue that it was solely because it 
               <lb/>
               was a Coalition Government that they had 
               <lb/>
               entered it—that it was solely because such a 
               <lb/>
               Government was necessary in order to the 
               <lb/>
               right conducting of our affairs, and in order 
               <lb/>
               to sustain some hon. gentlemen in the Lower 
               <lb/>
               Province who had taken ofﬁce, that they had 
               <lb/>
               consented to enter it. Those hon. gentlemen 
               <lb/>
               also claim that the three Reformers from On<lb break="no"/>tario, and the others from the Lower Prov<lb break="no"/>inces, would be able to counterpoise the 
               <lb/>
               Conservative element, or at least to equal it. 
               <lb/>
               Well, if it was necessary that the Province 
               <lb/>
               of Ontario should have three representatives 
               <lb/>
               from the Reform ranks in the Cabinet, how 
               <lb/>
               must it have suffered when there was only 
               <lb/>
               one such representative, and that one absent 
               <lb/>
               from the country for the last six months, 
               <lb/>
               allowing the Conservative element to run 
               <lb/>
               riot in the organization of the militia, the 
               <lb/>
               management of the Intercolonial and every<lb break="no"/>thing else. (Hear, hear.) The Minister of 
               <lb/>
               Customs belonged originally to the Reform 
               <lb/>
               party, and perhaps it might be said that the 
               <lb/>
               hon. gentleman had been sufficient for the 
               <lb/>
               interests of that party in the Cabinet, in the 
               <lb/>
               absence of his colleague; but if the hon. 
               <lb/>
               gentleman yielded as easily on every matter 
               <lb/>
               that concerned the party he professed to rep<lb break="no"/>resent as he seemed to have yielded with 
               <lb/>
               reference to the Intercolonial route, the pro<lb break="no"/>tection given by him amounted to very little. 
               <lb/>
               The result had shown that he (Mr. Mac<lb break="no"/>kenzie) was right in the prophecy he 
               <lb/>
               ventured to make when the Coalition was 
               <lb/>
                

            
         <pb n="20" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0020.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">20</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 16, 1869</fw> 
            
         formed, that it would end in the absorption 
               <lb/>
               of the minority element. (Hear, hear). 
               <lb/>
               Some of the Conservative organs, indeed, 
               <lb/>
               had claimed that, as at the last election, the 
               <lb/>
Conservative element came a majority 
               <lb/>
               amongst the representatives of Ontario; 
               <lb/>
               therefore, the Ontario Conservatives were 
               <lb/>
entitled to three seats in the Cabinet, and the 
               <lb/>
               Reformers to but two. With reference to this 
               <lb/>
               he (Mr. Mackenzie) contended that this result 
               <lb/>
               had been obtained by its being sedulously 
               <lb/>
               urged upon the people that it did not matter 
               <lb/>
               whether a Conservative or a Reformer was 
               <lb/>
               elected, and that the only question with refer<lb break="no"/>ence to a candidate should be whether he 
               <lb/>
               would support the Government. In this way, 
               <lb/>
               by the joint action of the Minister of Justice 
               <lb/>
               and the Premier of Ontario, the Reformers 
               <lb/>
               had been cheated out of a fair representation 
               <lb/>
               in this House. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

  
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD2">Hon. J. S. Macdonald</persName>—We beat you, at all 
               <lb/>
               events. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said they had tried to 
               <lb/>
               beat him, but had completely failed. The 
               <lb/>
               honourable gentleman ventured to make a 
               <lb/>
               pilgrimage into his (Mr. Mackenzie’s) county, 
               <lb/>
               but was compelled to beat an ignominious 
               <lb/>
               retreat, and his majority was twice the num<lb break="no"/>ber of the electors, if not of the souls, in the 
               <lb/>
               whole constituency. (Hear, hear). He had 
               <lb/>
               thought it expedient to call the attention of 
               <lb/>
               the Liberals in the House to the manner in 
               <lb/>
               which they had been treated by honourable 
               <lb/>
               gentlemen opposite. He had never expected 
               <lb/>
               that the Minister of Public Works would be 
               <lb/>
               either the representative or the protector of 
               <lb/>
               the Reform party in the Cabinet; but he had 
               <lb/>
               expected that some decent measure of atten<lb break="no"/>tion would have been paid to the position 
               <lb/>
               that was taken in the organization of the 
               <lb/>
               Government. Mr. Mackenzie then said he 
               <lb/>
               would refrain from entering on any more full 
               <lb/>
               discussion of the matters embraced in the 
               <lb/>
               address, until the papers were brought down, 
               <lb/>
               and again congratulated the House on the 
               <lb/>
               prospect we had that we should soon be not 
               <lb/>
               merely in theory, but in fact, a Confederation 
               <lb/>
               of the British North American Provinces-<lb/> knit together in such a way as to promote 
               <lb/>
               mutual interests and to maintain the glory of 
               <lb/>
               our fatherland and our connection with it. 
               <lb/>
               (Cheers). 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
            <p>
               Paragraphs two to ﬁve were agreed to. 
               <lb/>
Paragraph six, relating to the North-West 
               <lb/>
               negotiations having been put-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> said there was an evi<lb break="no"/>dent desire on the part of the House not 
               <lb/>
               
  
            
            <pb n="21" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0021.jpg"/>
            
     
               to prolong the debate, and agreeing in that 
               <lb/>
               desire, he would not make a speech. He felt 
               <lb/>
               bound to say, however, that so far as he 
               <lb/>
               could judge from the papers which had been 
               <lb/>
               published, he conceived we had nothing 
               <lb/>
               whatever to congratulate ourselves upon 
               <lb/>
               in the result of the mission to England. 
               <lb/>
               He had been from the initiation of 
               <lb/>
               the movement an agreeing party to 
               <lb/>
               the policy of acquiring the North-West and 
               <lb/>
               he still thought it most desirable we 
               <lb/>
               should acquire it; but he must say, so far as 
               <lb/>
               he could judge from these papers, that our 
               <lb/>
               case had been most deplorably mismanaged. 
               <lb/>
               We had now, perhaps, an opportunity of 
               <lb/>
               getting that Territory; but it was on terms 
               <lb/>
               which ought never to have been assented to. 
               <lb/>
               He should be prepared at the proper time to 
               <lb/>
               show, unless there were something in the 
               <lb/>
               papers which had not yet been given to the 
               <lb/>
               public, that our representatives had been 
               <lb/>
               completely out-generaled by the very able 
               <lb/>
               men who represented the H. B. Co. in Eng<lb break="no"/>land, and also by the Colonial Minister him<lb break="no"/>self. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The sixth and the remaining paragraphs 
               <lb/>
               of the Address were agreed to. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> then moved that the 
               <lb/>
               resolutions be referred to a Committee, con<lb break="no"/>sisting of Messrs. Cartier, Tilley, Langevin, 
               <lb/>
               Simpson, Bolton and the mover to prepare 
               <lb/>
               and report an Address. —Carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The Committee immediately reported the 
               <lb/>
               Address, which was ordered to be engrossed 
               <lb/>
               and presented to His Excellency by such 
               <lb/>
               members of the House as are members of 
               <lb/>
               the Privy Council. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> reminded the Premier 
               <lb/>
               that the names of the Intercolonial Railway 
               <lb/>
               Commissioners had not yet been ﬁnally an<lb break="no"/>nounced to the House. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said a message, 
               <lb/>
               making the announcement, was in his office 
               <lb/>
               ready to be brought down. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> asked when the papers 
               <lb/>
               relating to the Nova Scotia arrangement, the 
               <lb/>
               admission of Newfoundland and the acqui<lb break="no"/>sition of the Hudson’s Bay Territory would 
               <lb/>
               be brought down? 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said the Nova Sco<lb break="no"/>tia papers were complete, and would be 
               <lb/>
               brought down immediately. The Newfound<lb break="no"/>land papers were incomplete, but he would 
               <lb/>
               consider whether he could bring down the 
               <lb/>
               papers showing what had been done so far. 
               <lb/>
               The Hudson’s Bay papers were also incom<lb break="no"/><pb n="22" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-04-16_Page_0022.jpg"/><fw type="num">22</fw><fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw><fw type="dateline">April 16, 1869<lb/></fw>plete. The Governor-General was warranted 
               <lb/>
               in making the statement he did as to the 
               <lb/>
               acceptance of the proposal by the Company, 
               <lb/>
               having received a cable despatched to that 
               <lb/>
               eﬁect from Earl Granville; but of course 
               <lb/>
               a despatch from Earl Granville must be re<lb break="no"/>ceived before the House could be invited to 
               <lb/>
               take action. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> then moved that on Tues<lb break="no"/>day next His Excellency’s speech be taken 
               <lb/>
               into consideration as the ﬁrst formal step 
               <lb/>
               towards constituting a Committee of Supply. 
               <lb/>
               Carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The House at 20 minutes past 5 adjourned 
               <lb/>
               till Monday. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>  
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
