<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_MB_1870-03-10" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-03-10">10 March 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1870">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.  

         
           <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.     
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="337" to="338"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-03-10_Page_0337.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-03-10_Page_0338.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-03-10_Page_0337">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-03-10_Page_0337.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-03-10_Page_0338">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-03-10_Page_0338.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="337" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-03-10_Page_0337.jpg"/>
            <!--fw type="dateline">
     10 mars 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
            <p>
    [...] weight, and he thought that the building might 
     <lb/>
     be finished in a cheap and substantial manner. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Hon. Mr. Langevin</persName> said the Government 
     <lb/>
     were fully aware of the difficulty of complet<lb break="no"/>ing the library according to the original inten<lb break="no"/>tion, but when the estimates came down he 
     <lb/>
     would be prepared to explain the intentions of 
     <lb/>
     the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   <div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     MONTREAL AND CHAMPLAIN RAILWAY 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SCRI1">Mr. Scriver</persName> introduced a Bill intituled: "An 
     <lb/>
     Act to incorporate the Montreal and Cham<lb break="no"/>plain Junction Railway Company". 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   </div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PUBLIC ACCOUNTS COMMITTEE 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The Public Accounts Committee submitted 
     <lb/>
     their second report. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     ST. FRANCIS AND MEGANTIC 
     <lb/>
     INTERNATIONAL RAILWAY COMPANY 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POPE1">Mr. Pope</persName> introduced a Bill intituled: "An Act 
     <lb/>
     to incorporate the St. Francis and Megantic 
     <lb/>
     International Railway Company". 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PUBLICATION OF RED RIVER PAPER 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> called the attention of the 
     <lb/>
     House to the fact that some newspapers had 
     <lb/>
     published correspondence with respect to the 
     <lb/>
     Red River affair, including also the names of 
     <lb/>
     parties interested, notwithstanding the injunc<lb break="no"/>tion recommended some days ago. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said his atten<lb break="no"/>tion was drawn to this matter last night by the 
     <lb/>
     hon. member for Châteauguay, and he had told 
     <lb/>
     the gentleman that he regretted very much 
     <lb/>
     that the papers had been published. However, 
     <lb/>
     he was determined to enquire into the 
     <lb/>
     circumstances. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said the publication was 
     <lb/>
     exceedingly unfortunate. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—Yes, it was. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said that while, personally, 
     <lb/>
     he would wish to extend to the Press all facili<lb break="no"/>ties for obtaining information, still, in a matter 
     <lb/>
     of this nature he thought that the public papers 
     <lb/>
     should show some regard for the public inter<lb break="no"/>ests, and should have refrained from publish<lb break="no"/>ing those documents. If this matter were to be 
     <lb/>
     considered at all, he would suggest to the 
     <lb/>
     leader of the Government that there was a 
     <lb/>
     Standing Committee to which it could be 
     <lb/>
          
            
            <pb n="338" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-03-10_Page_0338.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">338</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">
     March 10, 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
          
     referred as a question concerning the privi<lb break="no"/>leges of Parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said the whole 
     <lb/>
     thing depended on ascertaining the sources 
     <lb/>
     whence the information was derived; the writ<lb break="no"/>ers of this correspondence might have to be 
     <lb/>
     removed from the Press, in order to procure 
     <lb/>
     information on that point. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> said the peculiarity of the 
     <lb/>
     published correspondence was that it purport<lb break="no"/>ed to be drawn from the report laid before the 
     <lb/>
     House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—I see that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName>—If the Committee finds 
     <lb/>
     that the information comes from extraneous 
     <lb/>
     sources, what course is there to be followed? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GALT1">Hon. Sir. A. T. Galt</persName> said the chief indiscre<lb break="no"/>tion was in allowing the suppressed parts to 
     <lb/>
     appear. If it should turn out that the corre<lb break="no"/>spondence laid before the Committee had been 
     <lb/>
     given to the press from the Committee, then 
     <lb/>
     there would be shown a gross breach of 
     <lb/>
     privilege. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName> said he never saw a copy of 
     <lb/>
     those papers till he saw them that forenoon. 
     <lb/>
     The publication of the papers could only be 
     <lb/>
     accounted for on the grounds that a person 
     <lb/>
     who had figured in them had shown them to 
     <lb/>
     the press. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> suggested whether it would not be 
     <lb/>
     better to refer the investigation to another 
     <lb/>
     Committee than the one which had had the 
     <lb/>
     papers before them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SCAT1">Mr. Scatcherd</persName> observed that it was a ques<lb break="no"/>tion whether the House should proceed to 
     <lb/>
     investigate an isolated case. If a rule were to be 
     <lb/>
     made to apply, then it should be to all cases. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said that the press ought to 
     <lb/>
     get all the returns that were brought down, 
     <lb/>
     where nothing injurious to the public interests 
     <lb/>
     was concerned; but the peculiarity in that case 
     <lb/>
     was that the press were informed it would be 
     <lb/>
     imprudent to publish those papers until laid 
     <lb/>
     before the Committee. It was this circumstance 
     <lb/>
     which constituted it an offence to publish the 
     <lb/>
     papers. When the leader of the House solemnly 
     <lb/>
     declared those papers should not be printed 
     <lb/>
     because it would be dangerous to the public 
     <lb/>
     interests, then they should not have been 
     <lb/>
     published. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> moved that the 
     <lb/>
     Committee, to which was referred the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     West correspondence, should be revived with 
     <lb/>
     power to enquire into the improper publication 
     <lb/>
     of the correspondence.—Carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <!--<p>
     [Mr. Mackenzie—M. Mackenzie] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>