<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_MB_1870-02-24"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-02-24">24 February 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.  
    
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1979"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="171" to="175"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0171.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0172.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0173.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0174.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0175.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-08">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0171">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0171.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0172">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0172.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0173">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0173.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0174">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0174.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0175">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0175.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="171" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0171.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     24 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     HOUSE OF COMMONS 
     <lb/></head>

    <p rendition="simple:right"><emph>Thursday, February 24, 1870</emph> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Speaker took the chair at three o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CHAMPLAIN CANAL 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:RYAN2">Mr. Ryan</persName> (Montreal West) presented a peti<lb break="no"/>tion from the Hon. John Young for an Act of 
     <lb/>
     Incorporation of a Company to construct a 
     <lb/>
     canal from Lake Champlain to the St. 
     <lb/>
     Lawrence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     INAUDIBLE EXPLANATIONS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DUFR1">Mr. Dufresne</persName> complained that he had been 
     <lb/>
     misreported in a speech he delivered on Tues<lb break="no"/>day evening. The explanations which he gave 
     <lb/>
     were inaudible in the gallery. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     NORTH WEST TERRITORY 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> moved the 
     <lb/>
     appointment of a special committee to examine 
     <lb/>
     papers connected with the North West Territo<lb break="no"/>ry, and to report what portions it would be 
     <lb/>
     expedient to lay before the House, composed of 
     <lb/>
     Sir John, Howe, Langevin, Tilley, Morris, 
     <lb/>
     Dunkin, J. S. Macdonald, McDougall, Holton, 
     <lb/>
     Mackenzie and Blake. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir George-É. Cartier</persName> referred to a 
     <lb/>
     remark of the hon. member for North Lanark, 
     <lb/>
     that he regretted that he (Sir George) had not 
     <lb/>
     in his speech said anything in condemnation of 
     <lb/>
     the proceedings of the insurgents at Red River. 
     <lb/>
     He begged to remind the House that he had on 
     <lb/>
     two or three occasions, in his speech, con<lb break="no"/>demned the disturbances, but in some of the 
     <lb/>
     papers it had been merely stated that he con<lb break="no"/>firmed the statement of the Hon. Mr. Langevin. 
     <lb/>
     He mentioned this so that he might not be 
     <lb/>
     misunderstood. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName> called attention to the 
     <lb/>
     great difficulty under which the reporters 
     <lb/>
     laboured, in ascertaining what was said in the 
     <lb/>
     House. These gentlemen had a very onerous 
     <lb/>
     duty to perform, and every facility should be 
     <lb/>
     given them. The difficulty in hearing might be 
     <lb/>
     obviated by erecting a temporary gallery for 
     <lb/>
     short-hand reporters only, over each of the 
     <lb/>
     entrances into the Chamber, lower down than 
     <lb/>
     the present gallery. Such an arrangement 
     <lb/>
     would not probably interfere with the artistic 
     <lb/>
     beauty of the House, and would certainly bring 
     <lb/>
     the reporters within hearing distance. Where 
     <lb/>
     they were, he had been told, it was utterly 
     <lb/>
     impossible to hear many of the gentlemen who 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="172" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0172.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">172</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 24, 1870</fw>
         
     were in the habit of addressing the House, 
     <lb/>
     especially the leader of the Government, whose 
     <lb/>
     remarks, above all others, ought to be correctly 
     <lb/>
     reported. Such an arrangement as he had sug<lb break="no"/>gested could be carried out in two or three 
     <lb/>
     days, and at a very trifling expense. With ref<lb break="no"/>erence to the remarks of the Minister of Militia 
     <lb/>
     he was exceedingly pleased to find that hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman so anxious that no misunderstand<lb break="no"/>ing with regard to his position and the position 
     <lb/>
     of the Government on the North-West question 
     <lb/>
     should go to the country. He had always 
     <lb/>
     believed that the Minister of Militia would 
     <lb/>
     take a broad Canadian view of this question, 
     <lb/>
     and not be influenced by local, sectional or 
     <lb/>
     national feeling, in dealing with it. He then 
     <lb/>
     referred to certain statements in the papers, 
     <lb/>
     and particularly to the reported remarks of the 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Mr. Letellier de St Just, in the Senate, 
     <lb/>
     that he had been guilty of doubtful acts in 
     <lb/>
     connection with the treaty with the Indians in 
     <lb/>
     the Manitoulin Island. He would briefly state 
     <lb/>
     the facts in connection with this matter. In the 
     <lb/>
     first place he had observed, in certain papers, 
     <lb/>
     especially in certain organs of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, a desire to create a prejudice against him 
     <lb/>
     personally, because of some supposed miscon<lb break="no"/>duct in connection with the Manitoulin treaty. 
     <lb/>
     Fortunately, that supposed misconduct, what<lb break="no"/>ever it was, had never been heard of among the 
     <lb/>
     half-breeds of Red River. He had made particu<lb break="no"/>lar enquiries on this point, and found they had 
     <lb/>
     heard nothing about these stories. Attempts 
     <lb/>
     had been made by Sir Francis Bond Head to 
     <lb/>
     have the Island of Manitoulin conveyed to the 
     <lb/>
     Government, in order that homes might be 
     <lb/>
     provided for such Indians from the mainland 
     <lb/>
     as desired to go there. The policy of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of that day was not carried out: few of 
     <lb/>
     the Indians went to the Island, but in course of 
     <lb/>
     time a number of Indians from the Western 
     <lb/>
     States went there. The late Chancellor of 
     <lb/>
     Upper Canada, by the authority of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, undertook to negotiate a treaty with the 
     <lb/>
     Indians for the ceding of the Island to the 
     <lb/>
     Government, and propositions were made to 
     <lb/>
     them which they did not accept. In course of 
     <lb/>
     time a number of Indians from the Western 
     <lb/>
     States of America, amongst others the Pot<lb break="no"/>tawotamies, came to the Island. They were 
     <lb/>
     under the control of two or three Jesuit missio<lb break="no"/>naries, and a village grew up which appeared 
     <lb/>
     to be prosperous. The Government of which Sir 
     <lb/>
     John A. Macdonald and Sir George-E. Cartier 
     <lb/>
     were members, came to the conclusion that it 
     <lb/>
     was desirable that the Island should be ceded 
     <lb/>
     to the Government, and opened for settlement. 
     <lb/>
     The late Chancellor of Upper Canada, then 
     <lb/>
     Commissioner of Crown Lands, undertook to 
     <lb/>
     negotiate for the Island, and sent Commission<lb break="no"/>ers there who were not acceptable. When the 
     <lb/>
     Government of John A. Macdonald came into 
     <lb/>
           
   
            <!--<p>
     [Hon Mr. McDougall—L'hon. M. McDougallJ 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            
            <pb n="173" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0173.jpg"/>
           <!-- <p>
     24 février 1870 DÉBATES DES COMMUNES 173 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
           
     office, he (Mr. McDougall) came to the Crown 
     <lb/>
     Lands Department, and this question was 
     <lb/>
     brought under his notice. He found an Island 
     <lb/>
     some 90 miles long, and 20 or 30 miles wide; a 
     <lb/>
     portion of it was very good land, and he was 
     <lb/>
     authorized by the Government to negotiate for 
     <lb/>
     its cession. He went personally to the Island, 
     <lb/>
     along with the able Assistant Superintendant 
     <lb/>
     of Indian affairs. A conference was held with 
     <lb/>
     the Indians, and a treaty was formed. It was a 
     <lb/>
     fair treaty, and one of the most favourable ever 
     <lb/>
     made with the Indians in this country. It 
     <lb/>
     secured them the possession of the lands they 
     <lb/>
     held, and all money which should come from 
     <lb/>
     the sale of the remainder. But the treaty did 
     <lb/>
     not meet the views of the Jesuit missionaries, 
     <lb/>
     who did not think that the portion of the 
     <lb/>
     Island under their control should be ceded to 
     <lb/>
     the Government; so to please them a line was 
     <lb/>
     drawn, leaving the eastern portion of the 
     <lb/>
     Island under the control of these gentlemen. As 
     <lb/>
     far as he (Mr. McDougall) was concerned, he 
     <lb/>
     was acting as agent for the Government. There 
     <lb/>
     had been no complaint, except by some parties 
     <lb/>
     who brought the matter before the other 
     <lb/>
     House, and a Committee reported that the 
     <lb/>
     documents should not be printed, on account of 
     <lb/>
     their baseless character. From that time to this, 
     <lb/>
     those who had objected to his services with 
     <lb/>
     regard to the treaty, had been saying that he 
     <lb/>
     was guilty of something or other to the preju<lb break="no"/>dice of the interests of the Indians and the 
     <lb/>
     missionaries. What he had done was in the 
     <lb/>
     interests of the country, and those who 
     <lb/>
     referred to Manitoulin Island should look into 
     <lb/>
     the matter and understand the facts well 
     <lb/>
     before they undertook to censure him. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said that he 
     <lb/>
     was in Opposition at the time of the Manitou<lb break="no"/>lin transaction referred to, and was not 
     <lb/>
     inclined to look very favourably on the actions 
     <lb/>
     of the Government, but he could now in justice 
     <lb/>
     to the hon. gentleman state, that his impression 
     <lb/>
     was, that it was a good arrangement, and car<lb break="no"/>ried out with every fairness to those con<lb break="no"/>cerned. In reference to the statements concern<lb break="no"/>ing this matter, which had been made in some 
     <lb/>
     of the newspapers, he said that they, whether 
     <lb/>
     supporting the general policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment or not, had no sanction from himself or 
     <lb/>
     his colleagues. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SIMP2">Mr. Simpson</persName> (Algoma) said that he had 
     <lb/>
     some knowledge of the state of matters in 
     <lb/>
     Manitoulin Island, and could state that every<lb break="no"/>body in that section of country considered the 
     <lb/>
     treaty made by the member for Lanark to be 
     <lb/>
     one of great justice to the Indians. The territo<lb break="no"/>ry was very large and sparsely populated by 
     <lb/>
     Indians. The land, however, is very good, and is 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="174" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0174.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">174</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 24, 1870 <lb/></fw>
          
     fast settling up. There had been no complaint 
     <lb/>
     made as to the course taken by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said it was very strange that 
     <lb/>
     these statements should appear in what were 
     <lb/>
     known as Government organs. It had appeared 
     <lb/>
     to many others, as well as to the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man, that an attempt was being made to turn 
     <lb/>
     him into a scapegoat for the Government, upon 
     <lb/>
     whom the whole blame of the transactions 
     <lb/>
    could be fixed. Any blame affixed, or attacks , 
     <lb/>made upon him, for his conduct after leaving 
     <lb/>Canada, must be borne by the Government; 
     <lb/>and he (Mr. Mackenzie) thought that any 
     <lb/>attacks made by the Government organs 
     <lb/>should be repudiated in the same manner as 
     <lb/>had been done in this case by the leader of the 
     <lb/>Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said that he 
     <lb/>
     had always been personally opposed to what 
     <lb/>
     was called organism, as he considered it was an 
     <lb/>
     unwholesome system, and one not known to 
     <lb/>
     British practice. Various sections of public 
     <lb/>
     opinion had their organs or papers holding 
     <lb/>
     their opinions, but he denied being responsible 
     <lb/>
     for any opinions expressed by any newspapers. 
     <lb/>
     He had always avoided anything of this kind in 
     <lb/>
     any part of the country. The hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Lambton was entirely in error in his state<lb break="no"/>ments as to the course of the Government in 
     <lb/>
     respect to this matter. It was not only papers 
     <lb/>
     supporting the Government that had attacked 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for Lanark. The first paper 
     <lb/>
     calling for his return was the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName> considered it due to himself 
     <lb/>
     to make an observation. He hardly knew any<lb break="no"/>body that could influence a newspaper. He had 
     <lb/>
     never written a line for a paper in Canada, nor 
     <lb/>
     influenced an article in any way. The hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Lanark complains of rumors and 
     <lb/>
     statements made by newspapers during his 
     <lb/>
     absence, and he thought it would have been 
     <lb/>
     better if that gentleman had in reference to 
     <lb/>
     rumours in the North-West, come home to his 
     <lb/>
     colleagues, and stated to them what he had 
     <lb/>
     heard, giving them an opportunity of making 
     <lb/>
     then, the same flat denial as had that day been 
     <lb/>
     made on the floor of the House. He did not 
     <lb/>
     think that gentlemen on either side of the 
     <lb/>
     House would like to hold themselves respon<lb break="no"/>sible for everything said in the papers usually 
     <lb/>
     supporting them. Much as the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     admired the Globe, he would not, he thought, 
     <lb/>
     like to pledge his reputation on the veracity of 
     <lb/>
     everything it said. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—How do you know I admire 
     <lb/>
     it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
           <!-- <p>
     [Mr. Simpson (Algoma)—M. Simpson (Algoma).] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            
            <pb n="175" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-24_Page_0175.jpg"/>
         <!--   <p>
     24 février 1870 DÉBATES DES COMMUNES 175 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The Speaker</persName> then presented a message from 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency with the papers relative to the 
     <lb/>
     recent occurrences in the North-West Territo<lb break="no"/>ry, which, on motion of Sir John A. Macdonald 
     <lb/>
     were referred to the special committee above 
     <lb/>
     named. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> moved, that 
     <lb/>
     when the House adjourns, it stand adjourned 
     <lb/>
     till Monday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> said the House might fairly 
     <lb/>
     enough use an hour or two tomorrow afternoon 
     <lb/>
     in advancing current public business, and do a 
     <lb/>
     good deal towards launching new public 
     <lb/>
     business. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Motion agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">
     ELECTION LAW 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> introduced a 
     <lb/>
     bill intituled: "An Act respecting elections of 
     <lb/>
     members of the House of Commons", and said 
     <lb/>
     that as it would affect all parties, he desired 
     <lb/>
     the bill to have the fullest consideration. It 
     <lb/>
     could be discussed clause by clause, and he 
     <lb/>
     proposed on Government days, when the 
     <lb/>
     House was not otherwise employed, to take up 
     <lb/>
     this bill by clauses, and give it the most careful 
     <lb/>
     consideration, in order to have no hurry about 
     <lb/>
     it and have a good election law. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Bill read a first time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     COURT OF APPEAL 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said he had 
     <lb/>
     intended to introduce a bill respecting the 
     <lb/>
     Court of Appeal, but he had received printed 
     <lb/>
     observations from the judges, and the bar of 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick had also expressed their opin<lb break="no"/>ions, which were worthy of full consideration, 
     <lb/>
     and he wished carefully to read them before he 
     <lb/>
     brought down the bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> asked if the Hon. Minister of Jus<lb break="no"/>tice would bring down the statements of the 
     <lb/>
     Judiciary and Bar. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—Certainly. He 
     <lb/>
     would be very glad to do so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     OFFICIAL ARBITRATORS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Hon. Mr. Langevin</persName> introduced a bill 
     <lb/>
     intituled: "An Act to extend the powers of 
     <lb/>
     official Arbitrators, to certain cases therein 
     <lb/>
     mentioned". 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:YOUN2">Hon. Mr. Young</persName> inquired the amount of 
     <lb/>
    salary and allowances to the Dominion Arbi<lb break="no"/>trators. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>