<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_MB_1870-02-23"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-02-23">23 February 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.  
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

           <date when="1979"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="157" to="159"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-23_Page_0157.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-23_Page_0158.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-23_Page_0159.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-08">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-23_Page_0157">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-23_Page_0157.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-23_Page_0158">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-23_Page_0158.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-23_Page_0159">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-23_Page_0159.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="157" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-23_Page_0157.jpg"/>
           <!-- <fw type="dateline">
     23 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said full infor<lb break="no"/>mation on all points had been sent by the 
     <lb/>
     Government to the Hon. John Rose in connec<lb break="no"/>tion with the Intercolonial Railway, for the 
     <lb/>
     purpose of enabling the Imperial Government 
     <lb/>
     to make any statement they might desire under 
     <lb/>
     the Imperial Act. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head>
     OTTAWA RIVER NAVIGATION 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WORK1">Mr. Workman</persName> asked whether it was the 
     <lb/>
     intention of the Government to adopt the 
     <lb/>
     necessary steps to improve the navigation of 
     <lb/>
     the Ottawa river, and more particularly to 
     <lb/>
     enlarge and deepen the most important part of 
     <lb/>
     our land navigation—the Grenville and Carle<lb break="no"/>ton Canal. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Hon. Mr. Langevin</persName> said the matter was 
     <lb/>
     engaging the serious attention of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     ST. LAWRENCE AND WELLAND CANALS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MAGI1">Mr. Magill</persName> asked whether it was the inten<lb break="no"/>tion of the Government to introduce a measure 
     <lb/>
     during the present session of Parliament, 
     <lb/>
     having for its object the enlargement of the St. 
     <lb/>
     Lawrence and Welland Canals, so as to afford 
     <lb/>
     greater facilities for the trade and commerce of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion, now so rapidly on the increase. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Hon. Mr. Langevin</persName> said that some progress 
     <lb/> 
     had been made in the direction alluded to, and 
     <lb/>
     that the Government intended to place such a 
     <lb/>
     sum in the Estimates this year, with the view 
     <lb/>
     to the accomplishment of this work, and that 
     <lb/>
     they expected to see it completed this year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     NORTH-WEST TERRITORY PAPERS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said that he had given notice 
     <lb/>
     of an address for the production of the Com<lb break="no"/>mission of the Hon. W. McDougall as Lieuten<lb break="no"/>ant-Governor of Rupert's Land, etc., but he 
     <lb/>
     understood that the papers would be immedi<lb break="no"/>ately brought down. If so, his motion would 
     <lb/>
     drop. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said they 
     <lb/>
     would be on the table to-morrow, and all the 
     <lb/>
     correspondence affecting the public services, of 
     <lb/>
     interest, would be included. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
<head>
     NOVA SCOTIA ARRANGEMENTS 
     <lb/>
          </head>  
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> moved an address for des<lb break="no"/>patches or correspondence with the Imperial 
     <lb/>
     Government or any of the Provincial Govern<lb break="no"/>ments on the subject of the new financial 
     <lb/>
     arrangements made with Nova Scotia, etc. He 
     <lb/>
     said that what remarks he might think it 
     <lb/>
          
   
      
            <pb n="158" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-23_Page_0158.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">158</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 23, 1870 <lb/></fw>
           
     necessary to make he would make after the 
     <lb/>
     papers were brought down. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said he had no 
     <lb/>
     objection to producing the papers he had, but 
     <lb/>
     with regard to the resolutions adopted by the 
     <lb/>
     Local Legislature, he had no means of obtain<lb break="no"/>ing them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said he took it for granted 
     <lb/>
     that copies of the Address of the Ontario House 
     <lb/>
     presented to His Excellency through the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Government, were in their posses<lb break="no"/>sion and could be produced. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said he could 
     <lb/>
     not speak for that; but all papers that the 
     <lb/>
     Government had would be produced. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     COMMUNICATION WITH THE 
     <lb/>
     NORTH-WEST 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> moved an address for reports 
     <lb/>
     of the Superintendents of roads, etc., from 
     <lb/>
     Hudson's Bay to Fort Garry and other docu<lb break="no"/>ments. He said that various rumours had 
     <lb/>
     reached him with regard to the money expend<lb break="no"/>ed on those roads, and the mode in which it 
     <lb/>
     had been expended. The public had been led to 
     <lb/>
     believe from reports in the public papers that 
     <lb/>
     the expenditure had been anything but credit<lb break="no"/>able, and that the work had not made that 
     <lb/>
     progress during the past Session which might 
     <lb/>
     reasonably have been expected. He did not 
     <lb/>
     attach such importance to these rumours as to 
     <lb/>
     believe them to be absolutely correct, but he 
     <lb/>
     thought that he had sufficient knowledge of 
     <lb/>
     the matter to entitle him to call for those 
     <lb/>
     papers, so that they might have an opportunity 
     <lb/>
     of knowing whether those rumours were cor<lb break="no"/>rect or not. He was informed that some por<lb break="no"/>tions of the road, though very expensively 
     <lb/>
     built, would be, through the incapacity or gross 
     <lb/>
     carelessness of the engineer, practically useless 
     <lb/>
     when the construction of it was fully com<lb break="no"/>pleted. The matter was very serious, and he 
     <lb/>
     brought it thus early before the House, because 
     <lb/>
     the work in question was one in which he 
     <lb/>
     wished to co-operate with the Government in 
     <lb/>
     endeavouring to push forward in the best pos<lb break="no"/>sible manner, and at the earliest possible day, 
     <lb/>
     the completion of this work. It was not credit<lb break="no"/>able to them that—when the spring opened, 
     <lb/>
     and the possible troubles in the North-West 
     <lb/>
     might necessitate some action on the part of 
     <lb/>
     the Government—they should have to rely for 
     <lb/>
     their means of communication or transit on a 
     <lb/>
     foreign country; and, believing as he did, that 
     <lb/>
     they had in this route the nucleus of the best 
     <lb/>
     and the cheapest route to the North-West Ter<lb break="no"/>ritory, he thought that the attention of the 
     <lb/>
         
   
           <!-- <p>
     [Mr. Mackenzie—M. Mackenzie.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
           
            <pb n="159" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-23_Page_0159.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     23 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
       
     Government ought to be called to the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture on it. He also wished to ask for informa<lb break="no"/>tion as to whether the Government had taken 
     <lb/>
     means to utilise and clear the navigation from 
     <lb/>
     Fort Frances to the west end of Lake Superior, 
     <lb/>
     146 miles of clear navigation, and hoped before 
     <lb/>
     long to bring before the House the wisdom and 
     <lb/>
     necessity of having some better means of com<lb break="no"/>munication, and more suitable for the heavy 
     <lb/>
     traffic they might expect from that country. He 
     <lb/>
     also thought that it was desirable that they 
     <lb/>
     should have railroad communication, thus 
     <lb/>
     commencing the great work which would only 
     <lb/>
     end by connection with the Pacific. He would 
     <lb/>
     enter into further explanations when the 
     <lb/>
     papers were before the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LANG1">Hon. Mr. Langevin</persName> thought that when the 
     <lb/>
     papers were before the House they would be 
     <lb/>
     found satisfactory. They would be placed on 
     <lb/>
     the table as early as possible. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     PARLIAMENT BUILDINGS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> moved an address for the 
     <lb/>
     accounts rendered to the Government, and 
     <lb/>
     placed before the Dominion Arbitrators for 
     <lb/>
     work and materials on the Parliament build<lb break="no"/>ings, etc. He would also like to know whether 
     <lb/>
     that entirely closed the accounts for the build<lb break="no"/>ing with the original contractors, as he had 
     <lb/>
     understood that there was something still fur<lb break="no"/>ther claimed by the contractors. If such was 
     <lb/>
     the case he hoped the Government would sus<lb break="no"/>tain its officers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said if the 
     <lb/>
     accounts asked for referred only to those 
     <lb/>
     which had reference to what had taken place 
     <lb/>
     since the Dominion there could be no objec<lb break="no"/>tion. The return would be very expensive, and 
     <lb/>
     he should throw the whole responsibility on 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> did not wish in the slightest 
     <lb/>
     way to incommode the Government or public 
     <lb/>
     service, but if the hon. gentleman wished, he 
     <lb/>
     would be very glad to look at the correspond<lb break="no"/>ence. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member might feel perfectly sure that Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would support its own officers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName> said that the evidence 
     <lb/>
     and documents were very voluminous. He 
     <lb/>
     thought that the hon. member for Lambton 
     <lb/>
     desired to know whether there was any such 
     <lb/>
     application as he had referred to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said if the 
     <lb/>
     matter was made into a motion he would 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>