<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-06-19" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-06-19">19 June 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1869">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
   
          
         
           <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>. 
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="886" to="891"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="899" to="899"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0886.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0887.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0888.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0889.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0890.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0891.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0899.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
         
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-30">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-30">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-18">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0886">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0886.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0887">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0887.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0888">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0888.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0889">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0889.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0890">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0890.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0891">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0891.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0899">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0899.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="886" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0886.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">886</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES<lb/></fw> <fw type="dateline">June 19, 1869</fw>
            <p>
     [...] On the item for opening up communication 
     <lb/>
     with the North West, &amp;c. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> objected to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment asking for so large a sum as $1,460,000 
     <lb/>
     for this purpose, as it was clear from their 
     <lb/>
     own statement that they did not expect to 
     <lb/>
     spend this summer more at the outside than 
     <lb/>
     some $200,000 or $300,000. This was the state<lb break="no"/>ment of the Minister of Public Works last 
     <lb/>
     evening. It was the intention of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment apparently to offer in the London mar<lb break="no"/>ket the bonds of the Dominion guaranteed by 
     <lb/>
     the Imperial Government to the extent of 
     <lb/>
     £300,000. This sum was to pay off the Hud<lb break="no"/>son's Bay Company, and in connection with 
     <lb/>
     these bonds it was probably the intention 
     <lb/>
     of the Government to offer an equal amount 
     <lb/>
     of Dominion bonds unguaranteed. The object 
     <lb/>
     for which this latter loan was sought would 
     <lb/>
     be declared in the prospectus in which the 
     <lb/>
     loan was offered. But the appropriation on 
     <lb/>
     which this half of the loan was based would 
     <lb/>
     be cancelled by the time $200,000 or so had 
     <lb/>
     been expended and the remainder would then 
     <lb/>
     probably go, contrary to the terms on which 
     <lb/>
     the loan was negotiated, to replenish the 
     <lb/>
     exchequer of the Hon. the Finance Minister, 
     <lb/>
     and assist him perhaps in recouping the 
     <lb/>
     former loan under the Imperial guarantee, 
     <lb/>
     which he had undertaken to recoup. Regard 
     <lb/>
     it in what light he would, he (Mr. Holton) 
     <lb/>
     looked on so large an appropriation for an 
     <lb/>
     indefinite purpose, as being unsound in the 
     <lb/>
     last degree. If the hon. gentlemen were pre<lb break="no"/>pared with a bold policy for opening up and 
     <lb/>
     setting that country he would be prepared to 
     <lb/>
     consider it. But, instead of securing the adop<lb break="no"/>tion of such a policy the course the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment were now pursuing would result in the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion being bled to death by these annual 
     <lb/>
     expenditures of a few hundred thousand 
     <lb/>
     dollars to the accomplishment of no purpose 
     <lb/>
     beyond that of depleting the Treasury and 
     <lb/>
     crippling our resources. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> said that the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     was aware that without taking this step the 
     <lb/>
     Government could not get power to borrow 
     <lb/>
     the amount needed. He quite agreed with 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member as to the desirability of a 
     <lb/>
     bold and comprehensive policy with reference 
     <lb/>
     to the opening up and settlement of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West, and for that purpose asked a 
     <lb/>
     sum which would probably be more than 
     <lb/>
     enough so as far as this year's expenditure 
     <lb/>
     was concerned. When the Government had 
     <lb/>
     to go on the market for the £300,000, for the 
     <lb/>
     purchase of the territory, it would be ex<lb break="no"/>tremely unwise in them not to take advan<lb break="no"/>tage of this, and raise some more on their 
     <lb/>
            
    
    
           
            <pb n="887" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0887.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     19 juin 1869 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
        

     own unguaranteed debentures on account. 
     <lb/>
     The hon. gentleman made some further ex<lb break="no"/>planations, which were inaudible in the 
     <lb/>
     gallery, except that he said, that in entering 
     <lb/>
     on this new territory the Government had 
     <lb/>
     really no idea of what amount they would 
     <lb/>
     require to spend. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The item was concurred in, and the four 
     <lb/>
     following items. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On the item, $8,000 for Emigration, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> asked further explanations. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> explained that the 
     <lb/>
     Government, in furtherance of Emigration, 
     <lb/>
     had appointed as Emigration Agent Mr. Moy<lb break="no"/>lan, an Irish Catholic gentleman, who had 
     <lb/>
     been a long time in the country and had 
     <lb/>
     ample experience in Ireland as well as Can<lb break="no"/>ada. It was proposed to give him £300 a year 
     <lb/>
     and an office. A sub-agent was also to be 
     <lb/>
     appointed in the North of Ireland. It was 
     <lb/>
     proposed to appoint a Protestant agent. A 
     <lb/>
     Scotch agent would also be appointed; Scotch 
     <lb/>
     emigration being, as a rule, of the very best 
     <lb/>
     class. Mr. Allan, of the Montreal Steamship 
     <lb/>
     line, had been spoken to to find a suitable 
     <lb/>
     man. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The item was concurred in. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On the item, $20,000 for Collection of 
     <lb/>
     Customs, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> said that he thought the 
     <lb/>
     expense of collecting the revenue of Halifax, 
     <lb/>
     10 per cent, was too much. The Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Customs had promised to take steps to reduce 
     <lb/>
     the expenditure at an early day. It was also 
     <lb/>
     charged by an hon. member of that House 
     <lb/>
     that for out-port services a number of useless 
     <lb/>
     appointments had been made for purely 
     <lb/>
     political reasons. It was charged that a num<lb break="no"/>ber of men were appointed to such positions 
     <lb/>
     where no revenue was collected. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. Tilley</persName> replied that there were no 
     <lb/>
     out-port officers at all in the port of Halifax. 
     <lb/>
     There was no port nearer than Tangier 
     <lb/>
     where any such officers were employed. He 
     <lb/>
     believed that in Halifax and other ports per<lb break="no"/>sons had been placed in the offices at a later 
     <lb/>
     period of life than ought to have been the 
     <lb/>
     case. He hoped to get rid of these, as they 
     <lb/>
     were inefficient, but did not see his way to 
     <lb/>
     doing so at present. As to the cost of revenue 
     <lb/>
     collection at Halifax, it was 5 and 10 per 
     <lb/>
     cent, as stated. He was satisfied that a reduc<lb break="no"/>tion in the out-port service might take place, 
     <lb/>
     for, do what he could in that direction, hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen would see that for the first year 
     <lb/>
            
            <!--<p>887<lb/>
            </p>-->
            <pb n="888" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0888.jpg"/>
     <fw type="num">888</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 19, 1869</fw>

     of Confederation the cost of the service under 
     <lb/>
     discussion was $24,000. This year it was pro<lb break="no"/>posed to reduce it to $20,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCDO2">Mr. McDonald</persName> (Lunenburg) explained that 
     <lb/>
     a much larger number of vessels come into 
     <lb/>
     Halifax in proportion to the amount of $8,000, 
     <lb/>
     than into other ports like Montreal, where 
     <lb/>
     the importations were carried on in larger 
     <lb/>
     vessels than was the case at Halifax. The 
     <lb/>
     number of vessels at Halifax being much 
     <lb/>
     larger the expense of collection was of course 
     <lb/>
     greater. As to the charge that a number of 
     <lb/>
     elderly persons had been taken into the Cus<lb break="no"/>toms Department in that Province, the Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Customs was mistaken. There were 
     <lb/>
     old men of 76 and 80 in the service, but they 
     <lb/>
     had entered it 40 years ago, were miserably 
     <lb/>
     paid, and were in fact unable to leave. Some 
     <lb/>
     provision should be made for such men. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JONE3">Mr. Jones</persName> dissented from the idea that per<lb break="no"/>sons who had grown grey in the service of 
     <lb/>
     this country should be provided for by the 
     <lb/>
     country. Clergymen, farmers, mechanics grew 
     <lb/>
     grey in the service of their country, but no 
     <lb/>
     one proposed to pension them out of the 
     <lb/>
     public funds. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CHIP1">Mr. Chipman</persName> said the common feelings of 
     <lb/>
     humanity prompted men to provide for ser<lb break="no"/>vants who had grown old in their services, 
     <lb/>
     and even for their support. The Government 
     <lb/>
     should act on the same principle. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HARR4">Mr. Harrison</persName> said that in different trades 
     <lb/>
     there were arrangements, by making small 
     <lb/>
     contributions, to make provision for their old 
     <lb/>
     or infirm members. A similar arrangement 
     <lb/>
     should be made with reference to the em<lb break="no"/>ployees. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WOOD3">Hon. Mr. Wood</persName> pointed out that the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of life insurance was open to the civil 
     <lb/>
     service. He was opposed to the present sys<lb break="no"/>tem. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The item was agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On the item, Purchase of Red River Ter<lb break="no"/>ritory $1,460,000, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> suggested that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment should take means to issue, for the 
     <lb/>
     benefit of intending settlers, information as 
     <lb/>
     to the topography of the country, and the 
     <lb/>
     means to be adopted to secure a location. He 
     <lb/>
     suggested also the propriety of procuring for 
     <lb/>
     distribution a certain number of copies of 
     <lb/>
     Russell's very valuable work, which, he re<lb break="no"/>marked, contained more information than 
     <lb/>
     any other as to the Territory. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
           <!-- <p>
     [Hon. Mr. Tilley—L'hon. M. Tilley.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

            <pb n="889" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0889.jpg"/>
           <!-- <fw type="dateline">
     19 juin 1869 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GRAY1">Hon. Mr. Gray</persName> expressed his high approval 
     <lb/>
     of Mr. Russell's work, and his concurrence 
     <lb/>
     in the suggestion that a number of copies be 
     <lb/>
     procured for distribution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DUNK1">Hon. Mr. Dunkin</persName> approved the suggestion, 
     <lb/>
     and desired also that it should be distributed 
     <lb/>
     in the French language. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:JONE3">Mr. Jones</persName> (Leeds) made some remarks as 
     <lb/>
     to the policy which should be adopted in 
     <lb/>
     opening up a route to the Red River. He rec<lb break="no"/>ommended the Government to be very cau<lb break="no"/>tious about spending much money on the 
     <lb/>
     mixed land and water route from Lake Su<lb break="no"/>perior to Fort Garry. Such a route could not 
     <lb/>
     be open for more than four months in the 
     <lb/>
     year. He pronounced the country known as 
     <lb/>
     the fertile belt to be utterly unfit for agricul<lb break="no"/>tural purposes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName>—Did Sir Isaac Newton 
     <lb/>
     say anything about it? (Laughter.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JONE3">Mr. Jones</persName>—Not directly but indirectly, in 
     <lb/>
     shewing the influence of the planetary ar<lb break="no"/>rangement on high latitudes. (Laughter.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SIMP2">Mr. Simpson</persName> from his personal knowledge 
     <lb/>
     coincided with the views of Mr. Dawson on 
     <lb/>
     the question of route. He thought there was 
     <lb/>
     no chance of getting emigrants in by way of 
     <lb/>
     the United States. They would be beset on 
     <lb/>
     their way by agents with all sorts of induce<lb break="no"/>ments to get them to settle short of their des<lb break="no"/>tination. He hoped the Government would 
     <lb/>
     press forward the works recommended by 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Dawson. It was premature at present to 
     <lb/>
     consider the question of a railroad. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CHAM1">Mr. Chamberlin</persName> pointed out that even if 
     <lb/>
     the route from Lake Superior, as part of 
     <lb/>
     main line of communication, should ultimate<lb break="no"/>ly be abandoned, it would be valuable as a 
     <lb/>
     colonization road to the valuable lands in the 
     <lb/>
     vicinity of Rainy Lake. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName>, with reference to the 
     <lb/>
     suggestion of the member for Lambton, did 
     <lb/>
     not see how he could meet his views as to cir<lb break="no"/>culating the publication to which reference 
     <lb/>
     had been made. He shared in the high appre<lb break="no"/>ciation of that work which had been ex<lb break="no"/>pressed, but that work was now in course of 
     <lb/>
     sale, and all who desired to make themselves 
     <lb/>
     familiar with the character and resources of 
     <lb/>
     the country would procure the work. A large 
     <lb/>
     edition would be published of the report of 
     <lb/>
     the Committee on Emigration; and Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Dawson's evidence, embodied in that report, 
     <lb/>
     would give, he understood, very clearly the 
     <lb/>
     information desired. But as a general rule he 
     <lb/>
      
            <pb n="890" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0890.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">890</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 19, 1869</fw>
       
     thought the giving of such information should 
     <lb/>
     be left to private enterprise. The Government, 
     <lb/>
     at least, should be careful in putting its <hi rendition="simple:underline">im<lb break="no"/>primatur</hi> on the statement which would guide 
     <lb/>
     immigrants in deciding as to the place of set<lb break="no"/>tlement. The Government during the summer 
     <lb/>
     would take some further steps to ascertain 
     <lb/>
     by examination the character of the country. 
     <lb/>
     It had got into the newspapers that as Min<lb break="no"/>ister of Public Works he proposed shortly to 
     <lb/>
     visit the territory. He hoped, with the assent 
     <lb/>
     of his colleagues, he might be able to do so, 
     <lb/>
     and he trusted he might be accompanied by 
     <lb/>
     the Minister of Public Works of Ontario, 
     <lb/>
     which would receive a large addition to its 
     <lb/>
     domain. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName>—How? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName>—By the settlement of 
     <lb/>
     the boundary of Upper Canada. He believed 
     <lb/>
     the boundary of Upper Canada extended 
     <lb/>
     further into the territory than its jurisdiction 
     <lb/>
     had ever gone, and he presumed that Upper 
     <lb/>
     Canada would find it easier to deal with the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Government in such a matter than 
     <lb/>
     with the Hudson's Bay Company. As re<lb break="no"/>garded the practicability of the route from 
     <lb/>
     Fort William, that was a settled matter. He 
     <lb/>
     thought there could be no question that it 
     <lb/>
     was the duty of the Government to open up 
     <lb/>
     the route that would afford the speediest 
     <lb/>
     access to the territory, and postpone action 
     <lb/>
     as to the permanent and more expensive com<lb break="no"/>munications until they had better ascertained 
     <lb/>
     the character of the country, and the best 
     <lb/>
     modes of reaching it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> asked if he was to un<lb break="no"/>derstand from the Minister of Public Works 
     <lb/>
     that he considered Ontario inherited the claim 
     <lb/>
     of Canada to a part of the territory, a claim 
     <lb/>
     which covered nearly the whole of the desir<lb break="no"/>able part of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName> said the pretension 
     <lb/>
     was that the River Mississippi formed the 
     <lb/>
     western boundary of Upper Canada, as fixed 
     <lb/>
     by the Act of 1774. The Mississippi rose in 
     <lb/>
     American territory; and the question as to the 
     <lb/>
     extension of the line it formed would have to 
     <lb/>
     be determined by local considerations. But it 
     <lb/>
     was also claimed that the fertile portion of 
     <lb/>
     the North-West formed part of Canada under 
     <lb/>
     the old French <hi rendition="simple:underline">regime</hi>, and was therefore not 
     <lb/>
     included in the charter of the Hudson's Bay 
     <lb/>
     Company. But it was never contended that 
     <lb/>
     that formed part of Upper Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     June 19, 1869 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->

            <pb n="891" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0891.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     19 juin 1869 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName>, threw out especially for 
     <lb/>
     the consideration of the Member for Cornwall 
     <lb/>
     the suggestion whether the Province of On<lb break="no"/>tario, under its present able and economical 
     <lb/>
     Government, might not with advantage to 
     <lb/>
     itself and to the whole Dominion, undertake 
     <lb/>
     this work of opening up communication with 
     <lb/>
     the North-West, colonizing it, and annexing 
     <lb/>
     it for the time being to Ontario, with the 
     <lb/>
     proviso that at some future time it might come 
     <lb/>
     into the Dominion as a separate Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD2">Hon. John Sandfield Macdonald</persName>, as Premier 
     <lb/>
     of Ontario, would have no objections to un<lb break="no"/>dertake the outlay of the money that was 
     <lb/>
     now being voted by this House (Laughter.) 
     <lb/>
     He did not suppose his hon. friend meant that 
     <lb/>
     Ontario was to provide this money. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName>—You can raise money by 
     <lb/>
     selling the lands. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD2">Hon. John Sandfield Macdonald</persName> said the 
     <lb/>
     Province of Ontario had already lands enough 
     <lb/>
     on hand and was satisfied With its present 
     <lb/>
     condition without extending its domain in the 
     <lb/>
     meantime. The chief benefit that Ontario got 
     <lb/>
     from Confederation was that it had now the 
     <lb/>
     management of its own affairs, and he was 
     <lb/>
     afraid it would only result in loss and dis<lb break="no"/>aster if it were to enter on the large specula<lb break="no"/>tion suggested by the member for Chateau<lb break="no"/>guay, of annexing and opening up the 
     <lb/>
     North-West. As regarded the boundary he 
     <lb/>
     hoped they would not have so much trouble 
     <lb/>
     in that matter with the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment as they had had with regard to getting 
     <lb/>
     the arbitration between Ontario and and 
     <lb/>
     Quebec proceeded with. He believed that mat<lb break="no"/>ter would have been sooner settled if they 
     <lb/>
     had referred it to the Emperor of Russia or 
     <lb/>
     King of the Belgians. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The item was concurred in and the two 
     <lb/>
     following items. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the 3rd, Advances by the Government 
     <lb/>
     during the Fenian Raid to St. Catharines, 
     <lb/>
     $800. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> asked an explanation re<lb break="no"/>specting a claim so extraordinary on the face 
     <lb/>
     of it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> said it was the amount ex<lb break="no"/>pended by Capt. Schofield on behalf of St. 
     <lb/>
     Catharines in feeding the troops during the 
     <lb/>
     raid, which amount he was made personally 
     <lb/>
     responsible for in an action, and in order to 
     <lb/>
     relieve him the Government placed this 
     <lb/>
     amount in the estimates. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="899" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-19_Page_0899.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     19 juin 1869 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
            
<p>
     have brought it before the House at the time 
     <lb/>
     as a matter of privilege, instead of waiting 
     <lb/>
     to go to the library and fortify himself with 
     <lb/>
     authorities. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The Speaker</persName> said the language used by 
     <lb/>
     the member for Cornwall was capable of two 
     <lb/>
     constructions. The construction that occurred 
     <lb/>
     to him at the moment was one which con<lb break="no"/>veyed a severe reflection on himself. He had 
     <lb/>
     no doubt now, however, that the hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman's language was used in a different 
     <lb/>
     sense, and he begged to express his regret at 
     <lb/>
     having misunderstood him. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     INSOLVENT ACT 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     On motion of <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">hon. Mr. Rose</persName>, the Amend<lb break="no"/>ments made in the Senate respecting the In<lb break="no"/>solvency Act were read and amended. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     THIRD READINGS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The House went into Committee on the 
     <lb/>
     following Bills which were read a third time 
     <lb/>
     and passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Act respecting the Inspection of Steam<lb break="no"/>boats, for the greater safety of passengers by 
     <lb/>
     them. <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Act respecting inquiries and investigations 
     <lb/>
     into Shipwrecks and other matters.— <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John 
     <lb/>
     A. Macdonald</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Act to provide for the Temporary Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Rupert's Land and the North-West 
     <lb/>
     Territory when united with Canada.— <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John 
     <lb/>
     A. Macdonald</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Act respecting the Admeasurement and 
     <lb/>
     Registration of Vessels, from the Senate.-<lb/> <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The following Bills were Considered in 
     <lb/>
     Committee and reported:-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Respecting Prompt and Summary Admin<lb break="no"/>istration of Criminal Justice in certain cases. 
     <lb/>
     — <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Respecting the Punishment of Juvenile Of<lb break="no"/>fenders— <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     With the consent of the House <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. 
     <lb/>
     Macdonald</persName> moved that Monday be a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment day, and that the House meet from 11 
     <lb/>
     till 1, 3 till 6, and 7:30 till the adjournment; 
     <lb/>
     With the consent of the House His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency, the Governor-General, would prorogue 
     <lb/>
     the House on Tuesday or Wednesday—Car<lb break="no"/>ried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The House adjourned at 12 o'clock. 
     <lb/>
    <!-- 96068—57 1/2 
     <lb/>-->
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>