<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-06-04" type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-06-04">4 June 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1869">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
  
         
         <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

         <date when="1975"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="612" to="613"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-04_Page_0612.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-04_Page_0613.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-12">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-12">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-04_Page_0612">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-04_Page_0612.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-04_Page_0613">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-04_Page_0613.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="612" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-04_Page_0612.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">612</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS 
               DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 4, 1869<lb/></fw>
            
            <p>[...] happy hours there, and there is no hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber in this House who knows better the great 
               <lb/>
               importance of this work than that hon. Minis<lb break="no"/>ter. Therefore he hoped the Government would 
               <lb/>
               take this matter into their serious considera<lb break="no"/>tion and see that some action was taken, par<lb break="no"/>ticularly as there is a sufficient amount now 
               <lb/>
               on hand to complete this work. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>

            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> said the subject 
               <lb/>
               would be considered. He hoped the hon. 
               <lb/>
               member had no design of erecting Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward into a separate province. (Laughter.) The 
               <lb/>
               construction of this canal had been recom<lb break="no"/>mended for defensive purposes at a time when 
               <lb/>
               naval warfare was very different from at 
               <lb/>
               present. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:GIBB1">Mr. Gibbs</persName> presented a petition from the On<lb break="no"/>tario Bank, praying for an extension of its 
               <lb/>
               charter, and for power to remove its head 
               <lb/>
               office to such place in the Provinces of On<lb break="no"/>tario and Quebec, as a majority of the share<lb break="no"/>holders may select. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HARR4">Mr. Harrison</persName> introduced a Bill to amend the 
               <lb/>
               Act incorporating the Royal Canadian Bank, 
               <lb/>
               the rule of the House having been previously 
               <lb/>
               suspended. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MORR1">Mr. Morris</persName> introduced a Bill to incorporate 
               <lb/>
               the Canada Marine Insurance Company, the 
               <lb/>
               rule having been suspended. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
  <div type="section">       
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               THE NORTH WEST 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> introduced a Bill for 
               <lb/>
               the organization and government of Rupert's 
               <lb/>
               Land and the North West. The hon. gentleman 
               <lb/>
               said he was aware he could only introduce this 
               <lb/>
               Bill by the consent of the House; but he hoped 
               <lb/>
               that would be given. Under the address Her 
               <lb/>
               Majesty might at any time by an Order in 
               <lb/>
               Council, or a proclamation, declare the North 
               <lb/>
               West Territory to be part of the Confederation; 
               <lb/>
               and it is probable that before the Dominion 
               <lb/>
               Parliament meets again that proclamation will 
               <lb/>
               take effect. In consequence of this it was nec<lb break="no"/>essary that we should have authority to go 
               <lb/>
               there, accept the transfer, and administer the 
               <lb/>
               country provisionally until Parliament met. 
               <lb/>
               The Government did not intend at present to 
               <lb/>
               submit anything like a permanent measure on 
               <lb/>
               this subject; but had prepared the short Bill 
               <lb/>
               he held in his hand, which would sufficiently 
               <lb/>
               provide for the organization and government 
               <lb/>
               of the country during the few months which 
               <lb/>
               
          
            
            <pb n="613" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-04_Page_0613.jpg"/>
            
        
               might elapse between the issuing of the proc<lb break="no"/>lamation and the convening of Parliament. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> asked if this was the only Bill 
               <lb/>
               which was to be introduced on the subject. 
               <lb/>
               Did the Government think there would be 
               <lb/>
               sufficient time to consider a measure of such 
               <lb/>
               magnitude? The President of the Council, who 
               <lb/>
               was so much opposed to this measure at one 
               <lb/>
               period, was now among those who were press<lb break="no"/>ing it on, when members were almost leav<lb break="no"/>ing for home. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName> said that the business could 
               <lb/>
               be got through well enough if hon. gentlemen 
               <lb/>
               on the other side would not waste so much 
               <lb/>
               time in wrangling. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> thought the President of the 
               <lb/>
               Council ought to be the last man to complain 
               <lb/>
               of taking up the time of the Dominion; for if 
               <lb/>
               any person took up the time of the House, not 
               <lb/>
               perhaps talking nonsense, but something 
               <lb/>
               which had no bearing on the subject, it was 
               <lb/>
               that hon. gentleman. (Hear and cheers.) The 
               <lb/>
               President of the Council was not to be the 
               <lb/>
               judge of what was important and what was 
               <lb/>
               unimportant. (Hear). The House was told the 
               <lb/>
               other night that the measure just introduced 
               <lb/>
               was a great one on which to expend our 
               <lb/>
               thoughts. For his part, he thought the discus<lb break="no"/>sion of such a measure only a waste of time 
               <lb/>
               and would not enter on it. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               The second reading of the Bill was ordered 
               <lb/>
               for Tuesday. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
  </div>        
         
        <div type="section">  
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               NEWFOUNDLAND AND PRINCE EDWARD 
               <lb/>
               ISLAND 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               A message was brought down from His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency enclosing copies of minutes of the 
               <lb/>
               Privy Council of Canada and delegates from 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland, on the subject of the union of 
               <lb/>
               that colony with the Dominion, and copies of 
               <lb/>
               the resolutions adopted as the basis of such 
               <lb/>
               union. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            <p>
               Another message was sent from His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency transmitting copies of minutes of a meet<lb break="no"/>ing of the Privy Council of Canada on the 
               <lb/>
               subject of the admission of Prince Edward Is<lb break="no"/>land into the Dominion of Canada, which His 
               <lb/>
               Excellency recommended to the consideration 
               <lb/>
               of the House. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> moved for a committee on 
               <lb/>
               Tuesday next, to consider the resolutions on 
               <lb/>
               Newfoundland. He explained the resolutions 
               <lb/>
               <hi rendition="simple:italic">seriatim</hi>. It was proposed that Newfoundland 
               <lb/>
               should receive five per cent interest on the 
               <lb/>
               difference between its actual debt and the [...]
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
   </div>      </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>