<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-06-18" type="full" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-06-18">18 June 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1869">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
   
     
          
         
           <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="869" to="873"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="875" to="876"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0869.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0870.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0871.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0872.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0873.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0875.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0876.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-24">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-24">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-18">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0869">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0869.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0870">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0870.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0871">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0871.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0872">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0872.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0873">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0873.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0875">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0875.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0876">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0876.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="869" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0869.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">869</fw>
            <p>
              [...] and Misdemeanors in the Province of On<lb break="no"/>tario. The honourable gentleman said that he 
               <lb/>
               understood the members from the Province of 
               <lb/>
               Quebec desired to have the provisions of this 
               <lb/>
               Bill extended to them, and for his part he 
               <lb/>
               had, of course, no objection, but would like 
               <lb/>
               to see the provisions of the measure extended 
               <lb/>
               to all the Provinces. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ABBO1">Hon. Mr. Abbott</persName> moved that the amend<lb break="no"/>ments to the Bill be not now concurred in, 
               <lb/>
               but that it be referred back to the Committee 
               <lb/>
               of the Whole to provide that the measure be 
               <lb/>
               extended to the Province of Quebec. Carried. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The House then went into Committee on 
               <lb/>
               the Bill—<persName ref="pers:HARR4">Mr. Harrison</persName> in the chair. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               The Committee rose and reported the Bill, 
               <lb/>
               which was  subsequently read a third time 
               <lb/>
               and passed as amended. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
  <div type="section">      
            
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               KINGSTON PENITENTIARY 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> then said he was here to 
               <lb/>
               move the House into Committee again on the 
               <lb/>
               vote respecting the salaries of the Warden 
               <lb/>
               and other officers of the Penitentiary at 
               <lb/>
               Kingston. The Government felt that they 
               <lb/>
               owed a respectful acquiescence to the feelings 
               <lb/>
               expressed by the House last night that the 
               <lb/>
               salaries of these officers should be reduced, 
               <lb/>
               and he therefore proposed to go into Com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the Whole with a View of reducing 
               <lb/>
               the amount for the service by $1,325, which 
               <lb/>
               was the aggregate amount of the increase. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
  </div>        
         
        <div type="section">     
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
               SUPPLEMENTARY ESTIMATES 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> asked if the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man proposed to consider the Supplementary 
               <lb/>
               Estimates to-night. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> —Yes. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> said he was glad to hear 
               <lb/>
               the announcement made by the Finance Min<lb break="no"/>ister a little while ago that he would ask the 
               <lb/>
               House to acquiesce in the reduction. He had 
               <lb/>
               been about to ask not what action the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment intended to take in consequence of 
               <lb/>
               this defeat (hear and laughter,) but what 
               <lb/>
               action they proposed taking in respect to this 
               <lb/>
               item of salaries. (Hear.) With regard to the 
               <lb/>
               Supplementary Estimates which had just been 
               <lb/>
               placed in the hands of members they were, 
               <lb/>
               he observed, in two sets, the first having 
               <lb/>
               reference to the services for the current year 
               <lb/>
               which would expire in about twelve days. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <pb n="870" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0870.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">870</fw> 
               <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 18, 1869<lb/></fw>
               
                  <p>
               He would call attention to the fact that for 
               <lb/>
               the services of the current year votes aggre<lb break="no"/>gating $250,000 additional were to be asked 
               <lb/>
               for, while the Supplementary Estimates for 
               <lb/>
               next year amounted to $5,465,675. It was fair, 
               <lb/>
               however, to reduce this by the amount which 
               <lb/>
               the House had already to pay for acquiring 
               <lb/>
               the possessionary rights of the Hudson's Bay 
               <lb/>
               Company, $1,460,000. This would reduce the 
               <lb/>
               amount we had to vote for next year to about 
               <lb/>
               $4,000,000, a large amount of money even 
               <lb/>
               to us, who were accustomed to dealing with 
               <lb/>
               large figures under our new economy. There 
               <lb/>
               was one rather startling amount, that of 
               <lb/>
               $1,460,000 for opening up communication with 
               <lb/>
               the North-West Territory, establishing its 
               <lb/>
               Government, and providing for its settlement. 
               <lb/>
               Before considering this appropriation the 
               <lb/>
               House ought to be placed in a position to 
               <lb/>
               consider the whole question of opening up 
               <lb/>
               communication with and governing the Terri<lb break="no"/>tory. He did not say that the amount asked 
               <lb/>
               was excessive; but he maintained that the 
               <lb/>
               House ought not to be called on to vote so 
               <lb/>
               large a sum until the Government declared 
               <lb/>
               what policy was to be pursued in regard to 
               <lb/>
               these Territories; whether it was to be a bold 
               <lb/>
               and comprehensive policy, looking to the early 
               <lb/>
               settlement of the country, or whether we were 
               <lb/>
               in this respect to die as it were of depletion; 
               <lb/>
               whether we were to spend hundreds of thou<lb break="no"/>sands of dollars in this question annually with 
               <lb/>
               no policy, and as usually happened in such 
               <lb/>
               cases, without accomplishing any definite re<lb break="no"/>sult, or whether we were to pursue such a 
               <lb/>
               settled wise policy as must advance our 
               <lb/>
               interest in that quarter. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> said he would offer a few 
               <lb/>
               explanations in regard to the first set of sup<lb break="no"/>plementary estimates, those which were 
               <lb/>
               additional for the current year, amounting in 
               <lb/>
               the aggregate to $380,000. It was but right 
               <lb/>
               the House should understand that this was 
               <lb/>
               not an additional sum over and above that 
               <lb/>
               which had been stated before as the expen<lb break="no"/>diture for the year. They were brought in 
               <lb/>
               as supplementary estimates made in accord<lb break="no"/>ance with the rule laid down by the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of submitting every shilling of 
               <lb/>
               expenditure to the approbation of the House. 
               <lb/>
               A large portion of those estimates had already 
               <lb/>
               been laid before the House in the shape of 
               <lb/>
               unprovided items, with the particulars of 
               <lb/>
               which the House was already in possession; 
               <lb/>
               and we now bring them down in this shape 
               <lb/>
               in order to comply technically with the rule 
               <lb/>
               
     
            
            <pb n="871" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0871.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">871</fw>
   
               requiring a formal vote of the House for every 
               <lb/>
               expenditure. The first item in the Estimates 
               <lb/>
               for the current year, which was new, was 
               <lb/>
               $3,000 for the Administration of Justice. It 
               <lb/>
               was asked lest the Department might find 
               <lb/>
               itself short before the 30th of June next. The 
               <lb/>
               next item, $20,000 additional for the mainte<lb break="no"/>nance of the Penitentiary at Kingston, was a 
               <lb/>
               new vote, occasioned by a variety of circum<lb break="no"/>stances already explained. The next two 
               <lb/>
               items, for the Rockwood Asylum and the New 
               <lb/>
               Brunswick Penitentiary, were included in the 
               <lb/>
               expenditure already laid before the House. 
               <lb/>
               Some of the items connected with the main<lb break="no"/>tenance of the St. John Penitentiary were 
               <lb/>
               chargeable against New Brunswick, and the 
               <lb/>
               amount expended for the maintenance of the 
               <lb/>
               local prisoners was properly chargeable 
               <lb/>
               against the Administration of Justice; but 
               <lb/>
               the Dominion required to advance money to 
               <lb/>
               meet these amounts, and the Government 
               <lb/>
               considered that even though these sums were 
               <lb/>
               to be charged to New Brunswick, that still 
               <lb/>
               a specific vote should be asked for their 
               <lb/>
               expenditure from the Dominion. The next 
               <lb/>
               item was $3,590. In the detailed estimates 
               <lb/>
               that amount had been omitted altogether, 
               <lb/>
               partly in consequence of the representations 
               <lb/>
               of the member for Lunenburg. Last year we 
               <lb/>
               reduced the expenditure, but we had not 
               <lb/>
               been able to dispense altogether with some 
               <lb/>
               of the officers. The next item, for Emigra<lb break="no"/>tion and Quarantine, was occasioned by ad<lb break="no"/>ditional efiorts made in Europe to induce 
               <lb/>
               emigration, a gentleman having been spe<lb break="no"/>cially sent there, and other steps having been 
               <lb/>
               taken. The four items under the next head, 
               <lb/>
               Public Works, have been included in the re<lb break="no"/>turns already before the House in the nine 
               <lb/>
               months' expenditure. The $98,000 for the 
               <lb/>
               Intercolonial Railway was already in hand. 
               <lb/>
               The items for the repair of the steamer <hi rendition="simple:italic">Druid</hi> 
               <lb/>
               was as now, and also that following for 
               <lb/>
               Lighthouse and Coast service. Under the 
               <lb/>
               head Civil Government, there was $3,700 to 
               <lb/>
               provide for the salaries of certain Deputy- 
               <lb break="yes"/>
               heads and the Secretary of the Treasury 
               <lb/>
               Board, part of whose salaries had hitherto 
               <lb/>
               been charged to separate services, and in 
               <lb/>
               lieu of such separate payments the House 
               <lb/>
               was aware that the salaries of Messrs. Tru<lb break="no"/>deau, Griffin, Bouchette and Langton had been 
               <lb/>
               made up in separate ways, partly out of 
               <lb/>
               Customs, Excise and Stamps; partly out of 
               <lb/>
               inspection of railways and partly out of the 
               <lb/>
               Civil Service Board, in addition to their nor<lb break="no"/>mal salaries. The sum now mentioned was in 
               <lb/>
               full of all their services. The next item, Col<lb break="no"/>lection of Revenue from Public Works, was at 
               <lb/>
               the disposal of the Commissioner in 1868, but 
               <lb/>
               was paid in the course of the current year. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            <pb n="872" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0872.jpg"/>
           
     <fw type="num">872</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> 
     <fw type="dateline">June 18, 1869<lb/></fw>
               
            <p>The next item, $15,000 for the Post Office, 
     <lb/>was occasioned by the contract entered into 
     <lb/>for the Halifax service, not included in the 
     <lb/>vote of last year, and was also owing to the 
     <lb/>plan adopted with reference to the Great 
     <lb/>Western Railroad since arranging for the 
     <lb/>payment of their debt. The next four items 
     <lb/>were the balance of the appropriation of 1867- 
     <lb break="yes"/>68. Last year, the House would remember, 
     <lb/>there was considerable doubt as to whether 
     <lb/>the whole of the sum voted would be needed 
     <lb/>for the year. The rigid rule required that 
     <lb/>all money voted for a certain year should 
     <lb/>lapse on the expiry of that year, and that it 
     <lb/>should not be available for service next 
     <lb/>year. It was found impossible to give the 
     <lb/>charge for the payment of services rendered 
     <lb/>previous to June 30th last, and therefore these 
     <lb/>services had to be provided for in the mean<lb break="no"/>time. It was done by Order in Council. In the 
     <lb/>same sense this was an infringement of the 
     <lb/>rule; but it was an unavoidable infringement 
     <lb/>of the Audit Act. This vote was merely to get 
     <lb/>the approbation of the House to the appropria<lb break="no"/>tion of a year ago being carried forward a 
     <lb/>few days beyond the year for which it was 
     <lb/>voted to summarise. He might mention that 
     <lb/>the new votes amounted to $250,000, but there 
     <lb/>had been already paid $167,000, leaving the 
     <lb/>new vote in reality $83,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName>—Do I understand that the 
     <lb/>
     aggregate amount of the expenditure for the 
     <lb/>
     year, as asserted in the Budget speech, is 
     <lb/>
     only exceeded by $83,000? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> found it was not even so 
     <lb/>
     much, only $68,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName>—Which amount is just 
     <lb/>
     about the surplus. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName>—No; we have $250,000. And 
     <lb/>
     here he would with pleasure take the oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity of informing the House that the in<lb break="no"/>crease from the customs for May was $300,<lb break="no"/>000 in excess of the previous year, and 10 per 
     <lb/>
     cent in excess of what he had estimated. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WOOD1">Hon. Mr. Wood</persName>—In what portion of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion did the excess chiefly arise? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> said he could not give the 
     <lb/>
     exact proportion. His impression was that 
     <lb/>
     whereas the falling off last year was greater 
     <lb/>
     in Nova Scotia, the proportionate increase this 
     <lb/>
     year was also greater. The great bulk of 
     <lb/>
     the increase was, no doubt, at Montreal, To<lb break="no"/>ronto and Halifax. Coming to the supplemen<lb break="no"/>tary estimates for June, 1870, amounting to 
     <lb/>
     over $5,000,000, the honourable gentleman 
     <lb/>
     would notice that half of the amount was for 
     <lb/>
           

    
            <pb n="873" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0873.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">873</fw>
        
     the Intercolonial expenditure. Of the balance, 
     <lb/>
     $2,800,000 was for the Northwest Territory. 
     <lb/>
     He quite agreed with the honourable member 
     <lb/>
     for Chateauguay, that the Government ought, 
     <lb/>
     at as early a day as possible, to endeavour to 
     <lb/>
     define their policy as to that Territory and 
     <lb/>
     the communication therewith. His impression 
     <lb/>
     was that it ought to be done in a large and 
     <lb/>
     comprehensive way; but there must first be 
     <lb/>
     exploration. We must know all about the coun<lb break="no"/>try beyond the Laurentian range, north of 
     <lb/>
     Nipissing, in order to ascertain whether our 
     <lb/>
     communication would be in the direction or 
     <lb/>
     from the head of Lake Superior. Every hon. 
     <lb/>
     member admitted the propriety of borrowing 
     <lb/>
     money to pay off the Hudson's Bay Company, 
     <lb/>
     to organize that Government there, and to 
     <lb/>
     obtain communication with it. But the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment had no power to borrow the money 
     <lb/>
     until the matter had been agreed to in Com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the Whole, and hence they asked for 
     <lb/>
     it in that way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. Smith</persName> asked explanations about 
     <lb/>
     the vote of $5,200, two years' salary as a gra<lb break="no"/>tuity to the retiring Warden of Kingston Peni<lb break="no"/>tentiary. If this gentleman had been an officer 
     <lb/>
     of the Province of Canada, why should not 
     <lb/>
     his retiring allowance be charged to that 
     <lb/>
     Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> said the retiring Warden 
     <lb/>
     had rendered 25 or 30 years' faithful service, 
     <lb/>
     and had now retired in consequence of old 
     <lb/>
     age and infirmity. No one would say that 
     <lb/>
     he did not merit some allowance, and it was 
     <lb/>
     given in this form because there was no pro<lb break="no"/>vision for pensions for retiring public officers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>, in reply to Hon. Mr. Smith's 
     <lb/>
     remark, said that already the complication of 
     <lb/>
     accounts between the several Provinces was 
     <lb/>
     bad enough, but it would be worse if pay<lb break="no"/>ments like this were charged to the Prov<lb break="no"/>ince in which the officer had rendered service. 
     <lb/>
     He thought it better it should be charged to 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion, representing the Province on 
     <lb/>
     which the chief burden of such payments 
     <lb/>
     would probably fall. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
        </div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SUPPLY 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The House then went into Committee of 
     <lb/>
     Supply, <persName ref="pers:STRE1">Mr. Street</persName> in the chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="875" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0875.jpg"/>
          <fw type="num">875</fw>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD2">Hon. John Sandfield Macdonald</persName> said this 
     <lb/>
     was not the place for discussing his action in 
     <lb/>
     the Ontario Legislature. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The item was agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On the item, Maintenance of the Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia Railway—additional $30,000—in reply 
     <lb/>
     to Mr. Mackenzie, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName> said it was not the 
     <lb/>
     case that the road had been worked more 
     <lb/>
     successfully before Confederation than since. 
     <lb/>
     In 1866 the actual deficit was $33,835. In 
     <lb/>
     the year ending 30th June 1868 the expen<lb break="no"/>ses were $255,530, and the revenue $253,994, 
     <lb/>
     making a deficit of $1,506. The estimate for 
     <lb/>
     the current year, based on the result of 10 
     <lb/>
     months, gave an expenditure of $270,000, and 
     <lb/>
     a revenue of about the same amount. As re<lb break="no"/>garded the European and North American 
     <lb/>
     Railway of New Brunswick, in 1866 the gross 
     <lb/>
     receipts were $148,330, and the repairs and 
     <lb/>
     working expenses, $96,570. In 1868 the reve<lb break="no"/>nue was $166,758, and working expenses $131,<lb break="no"/>684. For the first 9 months of the present 
     <lb/>
     year the revenue was $136,664, and the ex<lb break="no"/>penses $90,212. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The item was agreed to, as were also the 
     <lb/>
     remaining items in the supplementary esti<lb break="no"/>mates for 1868-9. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the item in the Supplementary Esti<lb break="no"/>mates for the year ending 30th June, 1870, 
     <lb/>
     for opening communication with the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     West Territory, etc., $1,460,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> asked what measures were 
     <lb/>
     to be taken to open up means of access to Red 
     <lb/>
     River. He thought it necessary to have im<lb break="no"/>mediately a road that would be passable in 
     <lb/>
     some way or another. His impression was 
     <lb/>
     that it should be proceeded with this season, 
     <lb/>
     so as to enable people to reach Red River 
     <lb/>
     early next season—through our own territory. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName> said, already there 
     <lb/>
     were working parties on part of the route- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     that from Lake Superior to the navigable 
     <lb/>
     waters—and 5 or 6 miles had been construc<lb break="no"/>ted. Immediately after the action of the House 
     <lb/>
     as to the actual transfer of the North-West 
     <lb/>
     Territory, Mr. Snow's party had been sent out 
     <lb/>
     to complete the road from Lake of the Woods 
     <lb/>
     to Fort Garry. The Audit Act standing in the 
     <lb/>
     way, he had himself advanced a little of his 
     <lb/>
     credit with the Bank of Montreal, in antici<lb break="no"/>pation of the vote of this House. As to the 
     <lb/>
     water communication, that was a matter the 
     <lb/>
            
            <pb n="876" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-06-18_Page_0876.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">876</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">June 18, 1869</fw>
        

     Government had not yet undertaken to deal 
     <lb/>
     with. He had seen notices in the newspapers 
     <lb/>
     that parties were prepared, with reasonable 
     <lb/>
     encouragement, to put on the navigable 
     <lb/>
     reaches of navigation, boats of proper con<lb break="no"/>struction. The first thing was to get the road, 
     <lb/>
     and then the water communication could be 
     <lb/>
     taken advantage of. The works immediately 
     <lb/>
     contemplated involved an expenditure of 
     <lb/>
     $270,000, the whole of which would, probably, 
     <lb/>
     not be expended within the year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> claimed that the House 
     <lb/>
     was entitled to full information as to how it 
     <lb/>
     was proposed to employ the $1,460,000 now 
     <lb/>
     asked. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> said it was impossible, be<lb break="no"/>fore the country was actually acquired, to 
     <lb/>
     give all the details of this expenditure. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName>-Then why ask this $1,<lb break="no"/>460,000? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> replied that a large expen<lb break="no"/>diture would be necessary. We had to pro<lb break="no"/>vide means of access to the Territory, must 
     <lb/>
     make surveys, and must take energetic means 
     <lb/>
     to get people into the Territory. In order to 
     <lb/>
     do this a loan was necessary, and the round 
     <lb/>
     sum of £300,000 sterling had been fixed upon. 
     <lb/>
     All the Government now asked was a vote 
     <lb/>
     of credit for that amount, and the details of 
     <lb/>
     their scheme would be submitted to Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment next session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> admitted that the money 
     <lb/>
     required for opening the North-West should 
     <lb/>
     be borrowed rather than raised by taxation; 
     <lb/>
     but was it necessary to borrow it now? Had 
     <lb/>
     not the Finance Minister stated yesterday 
     <lb/>
     that he had $9,000,000 which he had the 
     <lb/>
     greatest possible difficulty in investing? Why 
     <lb/>
     then should he borrow in addition to this 
     <lb/>
     large amount, when he would have to ex<lb break="no"/>pend during the next year some $200,000. 
     <lb/>
     He contended that before the House was 
     <lb/>
     asked to vote this million and a half, the 
     <lb/>
     Government should submit some settled pol<lb break="no"/>icy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ROSE1">Hon. Mr. Rose</persName> pointed out that if he were 
     <lb/>
     to take the money referred to by the mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Chateauguay and apply it to paying 
     <lb/>
     the Hudson's Bay Company or opening up 
     <lb/>
     the North West, it would be, according to 
     <lb/>
     that hon. gentleman's doctrine, a breach of 
     <lb/>
     trust. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>