<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_MB_1870-04-06"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-04-06">6 April 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgHC_1870">
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.  
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

         <date when="1979"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="890" to="899"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0890.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0891.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0892.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0893.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0894.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0895.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0896.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0897.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0898.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0899.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-05-09">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-05-09">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0890">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0890.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0891">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0891.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0892">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0892.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0893">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0893.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0894">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0894.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0895">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0895.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0896">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0896.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0897">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0897.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0898">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0898.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0899">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0899.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="890" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0890.jpg"/>
           
<fw type="num">890</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">April 6th, 1870</fw>

 <head rendition="simple:centre">CANADA CENTRAL RAILWAY</head>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ABBO1">Hon. Mr. Abbott</persName> moved the second reading 
     <lb/>
     of the Bill intituled: "An Act respecting the 
     <lb/>
     Canada Central Railway Company". 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD2">Hon. Mr. Macdonald</persName> (Cornwall) said he 
     <lb/>
     would propose certain amendments when the 
     <lb/>
     Bill went into Committee, and would then take 
     <lb/>
     occasion to express his views on that kind of 
     <lb/>
     legislation, which did not insist upon any secu<lb break="no"/>rity that the work would be done. He would 
     <lb/>
     always raise his voice against any scheme 
     <lb/>
     which had for its object self-aggrandizement 
     <lb/>
     and jobbery. These schemes prevented honest 
     <lb/>
     companies from building Railways. He did not 
     <lb/>
     expect to succeed in his opposition, as no doubt 
     <lb/>
     the Government would support this scheme as 
     <lb/>
     all Governments did Railway schemes. Before 
     <lb/>
     he retired from the arena of politics he wished 
     <lb/>
     to see the system adopted in England with 
     <lb/>
     regard to Committees adopted in Canada, viz.: 
     <lb/>
     That members of the Committee should sit 
     <lb/>
     judicially and not as partisans. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ABBO1">Hon. Mr. Abbott</persName> said he would be prepared 
     <lb/>
     to answer the hon. gentleman when the Bill 
     <lb/>
     went into Committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Bill was read the second time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     RED RIVER 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAME1">Hon. Mr. Cameron</persName>—I am exceedingly 
     <lb/>
     anxious to know from the Government wheth<lb break="no"/>er they have had any additional intelligence 
     <lb/>
     from Fort Garry, and whether they are in a 
     <lb/>
     position to give to the House any further infor<lb break="no"/>mation in respect to the barbarous murder 
     <lb/>
     which has so short a time since taken place 
     <lb/>
     there. I am also desirous of knowing whether 
     <lb/>
     the first Minister is in a position to inform the 
     <lb/>
     House what the Government intend to do in 
     <lb/>
     reference to that matter, as there has been no 
     <lb/>
     subject since Confederation, or for many years 
     <lb/>
     before, which has so agitated the whole of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion, and more particularly that portion 
     <lb/>
     of it from which I come, than the whole ques<lb break="no"/>tion of the North-West, particularly connected 
     <lb/>
     with the great tragedy so recently enacted. I 
     <lb/>
     am quite aware that the Government of the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion must necessarily have certain dif<lb break="no"/>ficulties in reference to the question, and there 
     <lb/>
     must be probably a certain amount of reticence 
     <lb/>
     connected with it. That we can all understand 
     <lb/>
     and appreciate, but there are certain things 
     <lb/>
     which the Government must be enabled to tell 
     <lb/>
     this House, and which I shall expect and the 
     <lb/>
     country will expect they will tell this House. It 
     <lb/>
     is clear that the country still belongs to Great 
     <lb/>
     Britain in an Imperial sense, and has not been 
     <lb/>
     ceded over to us in the manner, which, at one 
     <lb/>
     time, it was supposed it would be ceded. It is 
     <lb/>
     therefore clear that the British Government 
     <lb/>
       


           <!-- <milestone type="unknown"/>
            
            <p>
     CHEMIN DE FER DU CANADA CENTRAL 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable M. Abbott propose la deuxième 
     <lb/>
     lecture du Bill intitulé: «Acte relatif à la Com<lb break="no"/>pagnie de chemin de fer du Canada Central». 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable M. Macdonald (Cornwall) 
     <lb/>
     déclare qu'il proposera certains amendements 
     <lb/>
     lorsque le Bill sera présenté en Comité et qu'il 
     <lb/>
     en profitera pour exprimer son opinion sur ce 
     <lb/>
     type de Bill, lequel n'exige aucune garantie 
     <lb/>
     quant à l'exécution des travaux. Il s'opposera 
     <lb/>
     toujours aux projets issus de l'arrivisme et des 
     <lb/>
     intrigues. A son avis, ce genre de projets empê- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     che les sociétés honnêtes de construire des che— 
     <lb/>
     mins de fer. Il ne pense pas qu'on tienne 
     <lb/>
     compte de ses arguments; le Gouvernement 
     <lb/>
     appuiera sans doute ce projet comme le font 
     <lb/>
     tous les gouvernements pour les projets de 
     <lb/>
     construction de chemins de fer. Avant de quit<lb break="no"/>ter la politique, il souhaite voir adopter au 
     <lb/>
     Canada le système relatif aux comités institué 
     <lb/>
     en Angleterre et voulant que les membres des 
     <lb/>
     comités soient juges et non pas parties. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable M. Abbott dit qu'il répondra à 
     <lb/>
     son honorable collègue lorsque le Bill sera pré- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     senté en Comité. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Le Bill est lu pour la deuxième fois. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     RIVIÈRE ROUGE 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable M. Cameron—J'ai vraiment 
     <lb/>
     hâte que le Gouvernement nous informe s'il a 
     <lb/>
     reçu d'autres nouvelles de Fort Garry et s'il 
     <lb/>
     peut renseigner la Chambre sur le meurtre 
     <lb/>
     ignoble qui a eu lieu à cet endroit, il n'y a pas 
     <lb/>
     longtemps. Je voudrais aussi savoir si 1e pre<lb break="no"/>mier ministre peut dire à la Chambre quelle 
     <lb/>
     sera la position du Gouvernement dans cette 
     <lb/>
     affaire, car depuis la Confédération et bien des 
     <lb/>
     années avant elle, aucun problème n'a autant 
     <lb/>
     ébranlé la Puissance et en particulier, l'endroit 
     <lb/>
     d'où je viens, que tout le problème du Nord- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     Ouest et particulièrement, le drame en ques<lb break="no"/>tion. Je sais parfaitement que le Gouverne- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment de la Puissance doit avoir des difficultés 
     <lb/>
     quant à cette affaire et que c'est avec réticence 
     <lb/>
     qu'il abordera le sujet. Nous comprenons cela, 
     <lb/>
     mais il y a un certain nombre de détails que le 
     <lb/>
     Gouvernement doit pouvoir fournir à cette 
     <lb/>
     Chambre. Le pays s'attend, tout comme moi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     même, à ce que le Gouvernement les fournisse. 
     <lb/>
     De toute évidence, le pays appartient encore, 
     <lb/>
     dans le sens impérial du terme, à la Grande- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     Bretagne et ne nous a pas été cédé de la 
     <lb/>
     manière dont nous avons supposé à un 
     <lb/>
     moment, qu'elle nous le serait. Il est donc clair 
     <lb/>
     que c'est 1e Gouvernement britannique qui a le 
     <lb/>
     plus d'intérêt à mater tout mouvement révolu- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tionnaire pouvant s'y faire jour. Nous compre- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nons sans difficulté pourquoi le Gouvernement 
     <lb/>
     de la Puissance désirerait que le Gouverne- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>-->


            <pb n="891" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0891.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">891</fw>
          

     are in the first instance the parties who are 
     <lb/>
     interested in bringing to a close any revolu<lb break="no"/>tionary movement, which may have taken 
     <lb/>
     place there, and therefore we can naturally 
     <lb/>
     understand why it would be that this Govern<lb break="no"/>ment should desire that the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would in the first place explain very 
     <lb/>
     clearly and distinctly what it intends to do 
     <lb/>
     before the Dominion Government should state 
     <lb/>
     in the most explicit manner what its views 
     <lb/>
     would be in reference to the question; but 
     <lb/>
     although that is the case, and although we 
     <lb/>
     know that the territory belongs to the Imperial 
     <lb/>
     Government, there are certain responsibilities 
     <lb/>
     which attach to our Government, and which 
     <lb/>
     Government cannot by any possibility ignore, 
     <lb/>
     and which we, the representatives of the 
     <lb/>
     people of the Dominion, demand that they shall 
     <lb/>
     not ignore in which we are all interested as 
     <lb/>
     Canadians, and which require that we should 
     <lb/>
     adopt a certain and determined course, (hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear). There can be no doubt whatever, there 
     <lb/>
     can be but one feeling, not merely amon st all 
     <lb/>
     members of this House, but amongst l the 
     <lb/>
     inhabitants of this country, that a barbarous 
     <lb/>
     murder has taken place in that territory, (hear, 
     <lb/>
     hear). That a man who has gone forth from 
     <lb/>
     here under the belief, no doubt, that he would 
     <lb/>
     be as well protected there as in any other part 
     <lb/>
     of Her Majesty's Dominions, has suffered with 
     <lb/>
     his life, because he has been loyal and true to 
     <lb/>
     the flag of his country, and we cannot help 
     <lb/>
     feeling that whatever the connection may be 
     <lb/>
     between the British Government and the 
     <lb/>
     Dominion Government in relation to the 
     <lb/>
     manner in which what has taken place here 
     <lb/>
     shall be accounted for, that we ourselves and 
     <lb/>
     the Government have resting upon us, the re<lb break="no"/>sponsibility which the people of this country 
     <lb/>
     must require at their hands, totally irrespec<lb break="no"/>tive of any action by the Imperial Government. 
     <lb/>
     Not that I would for a single moment interfere 
     <lb/>
     with the Imperial authority, but we must all 
     <lb/>
     recollect the position which our Government 
     <lb/>
     has taken. We must remember that we sent an 
     <lb/>
     agent out to that Western Territory, with all 
     <lb/>
     the preparations, and with a Commission to 
     <lb/>
     take the place, of the Government of that Ter<lb break="no"/>ritory. We must remember that large numbers 
     <lb/>
     of persons knowing perfectly well that that 
     <lb/>
     Territory was soon to come under our jurisdic<lb break="no"/>tion, went there with the full belief that they 
     <lb/>
     would be as safe out in that Western Territory, 
     <lb/>
     as they would be in the City of Ottawa, Mon<lb break="no"/>treal or Toronto, and that, therefore, our Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and we ourselves did assure to those 
     <lb/>
     people certain responsibilities, which by no 
     <lb/>
     possibility can we get rid of, (hear, hear). Now, 
     <lb/>
     Sir, what one desires to know is this—what are 
     <lb/>
     the views of our Government in respect to this 
     <lb/>
     matter? If the British Government are still 
     <lb/>
     possessors of the territory because we have not 
     <lb/>
         


            <!--<fw type="running">DÉBATS DES</fw>
            <fw type="num">COMNIUNES</fw>
            <fw type="num">891</fw>
            <p>
     ment impérial s'explique très clairement sur ce 
     <lb/>
     qu'il a l'intention de faire avant de donner le 
     <lb/>
     plus explicitement possible son propre point de 
     <lb/>
     vue à ce sujet. Bien que nous admettions cela 
     <lb/>
     et que nous sachions fort bien que ce territoire 
     <lb/>
     appartient au Gouvernement impérial, certai- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nes responsabilités incombent a notre Gouver- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nement et i1 ne peut aucunement s'y soustraire. 
     <lb/>
     En tant que représentants de la population de 
     <lb/>
     la Puissance, nous exigeons que le Gouverne— 
     <lb/>
     ment ne se dérobe pas a ses responsabilités, 
     <lb/>
     lesquelles sont aussi les nôtres comme Cana- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     diens et nous obligent à adopter une certaine 
     <lb/>
     ligne de conduite. (Bravo! Bravo!) Il n'y a pas 
     <lb/>
     l'ombre d'un doute que les membres de cette 
     <lb/>
     Chambre, comme tous les habitants de ce pays 
     <lb/>
     partagent le même avis: nous estimons tous 
     <lb/>
     qu'un meurtre ignoble a eu lieu sur notre terri- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     toire. (Bravo! Bravo!) Un homme est parti d'ici, 
     <lb/>
     croyant sans doute qu'il serait aussi bien pro<lb break="no"/>tégé là-bas qu'en tout autre endroit des domi<lb break="no"/>nions de Sa Majesté et il lui en a coûté la vie 
     <lb/>
     d'avoir été loyal envers son pays. Nous ne pou- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     vons nous empécher de penser, quelle que soit 
     <lb/>
     la collaboration entre le Gouvernement britan- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nique et le Gouvernement de la Puissance, à ce 
     <lb/>
     qu'il convient de faire dans ce cas, que le Gou- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     vernement et nous-mêmes devons assumer la 
     <lb/>
     responsabilité que les habitants de ce pays ont 
     <lb/>
     placée entre nos mains, nonobstant toute 
     <lb/>
     mesure prise par le Gouvernement impérial. Je 
     <lb/>
     n'ai pas la moindre intention de m'ingérer dans 
     <lb/>
     des questions du ressort du Gouvernement 
     <lb/>
     impérial; nous devons cependant garder à l'es- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     prit la position que notre Gouvernement a 
     <lb/>
     prise. Nous devons nous souvenir que nous 
     <lb/>
     avons envoyé un agent dans ce Territoire de 
     <lb/>
     l'Ouest, à la tête d'une Commission chargée de 
     <lb/>
     remplacer 1e gouvernement dudit Territoire. 
     <lb/>
     Nous ne devons pas oublier qu'un grand 
     <lb/>
     nombre de personnes, sachant très bien que ce 
     <lb/>
     territoire serait bientôt soumis à notre juridic- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tion, sont allées s'y installer en croyant qu'elles 
     <lb/>
     y seraient aussi en sécurité qu'à Ottawa, Mont- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     réal on Toronto. Notre Gouvernement et nous- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     mémes avons assumé certaines responsabilités 
     <lb/>
     envers ces personnes et il est impossible de 
     <lb/>
     nous y soustraire. (Bravo! Bravo!) Or, ce que 
     <lb/>
     nous voulons savoir se résume à ceci: quelles 
     <lb/>
     sont les vues de notre Gouvernement concer- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nant cette affaire? Si le Gouvernement britan- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nique possède toujours le territoire parce que 
     <lb/>
     nous n'avons pas encore acquitté les trois cent 
     <lb/>
     mille livres que nous nous étions engagés à lui 
     <lb/>
     verser, s'il est toujours chargé d'appliquer la 
     <lb/>
     loi équitablement et de protéger la vie dans ce 
     <lb/>
     pays, s'il lui incombe de mater les mouvements 
     <lb/>
     insurrectionnels, il ne serait que juste que nous 
     <lb/>
     en soyons informés et le comprenions. Si, 
     <lb/>
     moyennant ces trois cent mille livres, nous 
     <lb/>
     pouvons remplir nous-mêmes ces fonctions, je 
     <lb/>
     suis prêt, en ce qui me concerne, à prendre ma 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->


            <pb n="892" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0892.jpg"/>
         
  <fw type="num">892</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">April 6th, 1870</fw>


     paid over the three hundred thousand pounds 
     <lb/>
     that we contracted to pay, if they are still 
     <lb/>
     responsible for the due administration of law 
     <lb/>
     and the protection of life in that country, if 
     <lb/>
     they are the persons to put down insurrection<lb break="no"/>ary movements, then, of course, it is quite right 
     <lb/>
     that we should have an opportunity of under<lb break="no"/>standing and knowing that. If they require 
     <lb/>
     that we should pay the three hundred thousand 
     <lb/>
     pounds and that we should take upon ourselves 
     <lb/>
     the responsibility, I say for one that I am 
     <lb/>
     prepared to take my portion of the responsibili<lb break="no"/>ty in saying, that in the dawning birth of this 
     <lb/>
     new Dominion that the life of one of our people 
     <lb/>
     was worth three hundred thousand pounds 
     <lb/>
     (cheers), and that we should not for one 
     <lb/>
     moment allow, if it becomes necessary to assert 
     <lb/>
     our authority, and if any question arose with 
     <lb/>
     reference to our position with regard to that 
     <lb/>
     and to whether the expenses were to be borne 
     <lb/>
     by the Imperial Government or ourselves, that 
     <lb/>
     we should be prepared to show that we are 
     <lb/>
     enabled as a people—as we know in the opin<lb break="no"/>ion of some people, almost an independent peo<lb break="no"/>ple—that we are ready to take our part in 
     <lb/>
     defending not merely the property, but what is 
     <lb/>
     of more importance, the lives of our people, 
     <lb/>
     against any attempt which may be made by 
     <lb/>
     any insurrectionary party which may spring 
     <lb/>
     up in any part of the country, (hear, hear). And 
     <lb/>
     what I think we ought to have, and what I 
     <lb/>
     think we may fairly ask for, I and the gentle<lb break="no"/>men on this side of the House who are in the 
     <lb/>
     habit of supporting the Government, believing 
     <lb/>
     that they have the interests of the Dominion at 
     <lb/>
     heart, what we really require from them is to 
     <lb/>
     know whether when these people have gone to 
     <lb/>
     that territory under the idea that they were to 
     <lb/>
     be protected, whether when these insurrection<lb break="no"/>ists have taken up arms in the manner that 
     <lb/>
     they have done, whether when the difficulties 
     <lb/>
     have arisen that have culminated in the bar<lb break="no"/>barous murder of this man, when all these 
     <lb/>
     things have taken place we would desire to 
     <lb/>
     know whether the Government are deter<lb break="no"/>mined, whatever may occur, to endeavour, so 
     <lb/>
     far as in their power, to meet the exigencies of 
     <lb/>
     the case and to exercise whatever influence 
     <lb/>
     and power the Dominion may have, in order 
     <lb/>
     that they may be so met, and we would desire 
     <lb/>
     to know very clearly and distinctly, whether 
     <lb/>
     any difficulty whatever is to be thrown in the 
     <lb/>
     way, in reference to that; whether these people 
     <lb/>
     who have gone out there are to consider them<lb break="no"/>selves as protected; whether Government, if 
     <lb/>
     they are in a position to state so, are so ready 
     <lb/>
     to assume the responsibility which may be cast 
     <lb/>
     upon them; whether they are prepared to 
     <lb/>
     follow up what must necessarily take place in 
     <lb/>
     reference to this matter, and whether if these 
     <lb/>
     self-styled deputies should come down here to 
     <lb/>
     treat as if they were the ambassadors of a 
     <lb/>
         


   
            <!--<p>
     [Bon. Mr. Cameron—L'hon. M. Camel-on.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
          
            <p>
     part de responsabilité. A l'aube de ce nouveau 
     <lb/>
     Dominion, la vie d'un des nôtres vaut bien ces 
     <lb/>
     trois cent mille livres (Bravo!) et s'il fallait 
     <lb/>
     affirmer notre autorité et si un problème sur— 
     <lb/>
     gissait quant à notre position à cet égard et 
     <lb/>
     quant à la question de savoir qui, du Gouver- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nement impérial ou de notre Gouvernement, 
     <lb/>
     doit assumer la dépense, nous ne devrions pas 
     <lb/>
     douter un seul instant de notre aptitude à 
     <lb/>
     prouver que nous sommes prêts en tant que 
     <lb/>
     peuple—et certains disent un peuple presque 
     <lb/>
     indépendant—à faire notre part pour défendre 
     <lb/>
     non seulement les biens, mais qui plus est, la 
     <lb/>
     vie de notre population contre toute atteinte 
     <lb/>
     insurrectionnelle, où que ce soit dans notre 
     <lb/>
     pays. (Bravo! Bravo!) Ce qu'à mon avis nous 
     <lb/>
     devrions savoir et pouvons raisonnablement 
     <lb/>
     demander à savoir, les députés de ce côté de la 
     <lb/>
     Chambre et moi-même qui avons l'habitude 
     <lb/>
     d'appuyer 1e Gouvernement en présumant qu'il 
     <lb/>
     a l'intérêt de la Puissance à cœur, c'est ceci: 
     <lb/>
     sachant que des personnes ont choisi de s'ins- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     taller sur ce territoire avec la conviction qu'el- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     les y seraient protégées, sachant que des rebel- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     les ont pris les armes comme ils l'ont fait, et 
     <lb/>
     connaissant les difficultés qui ont mené au 
     <lb/>
     meurtre barbare de cet homme, malgré tous ces 
     <lb/>
     événements, le Gouvernement est-i1 toujours 
     <lb/>
     décidé, envers et contre tout, à faire face, dans 
     <lb/>
     les limites de son pouvoir, aux exigences de ce 
     <lb/>
     problème et à exercer l'influence et les droits 
     <lb/>
     dont il dispose à cette fin? Nous voudrions 
     <lb/>
     connaitre en détail les difficultés pouvant 
     <lb/>
     surgir à ce sujet. Les personnes qui sont allées 
     <lb/>
     vivre là-bas peuvent-elles se considérer comme 
     <lb/>
     protégées? Si oui, le Gouvernement est-il prêt à 
     <lb/>
     assumer la responsabilité qui pourrait lui reve- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nir? Est-il prêt à prendre les mesures qui s'im- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     posent? Ces soi—disant députés devraient-ils 
     <lb/>
     venir ici en tant qu'ambassadeurs d'un pays 
     <lb/>
     civilisé'? Ne devrait-on pas plutôt les traiter 
     <lb/>
     comme d'arrogants rebelles qui non seulement 
     <lb/>
     ont exigé ce qu'ils appellent une «Déclaration 
     <lb/>
     des droits de l'homme», ce que nous, leurs com- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     patriotes, serions disposés à leur accorder si 
     <lb/>
     leurs revendications étaient fondées, mais qui 
     <lb/>
     ont aussi trempé leurs mains dans le sang d'un 
     <lb/>
     innocent compatriote? Si ces hommes, là-bas, 
     <lb/>
     s'imaginent qu'ils ont des droits sur le sol, sur 
     <lb/>
     toutes ces propriétés, qu'ils peuvent en dispo<lb break="no"/>ser à leur guise, et nous empêcher de nous y 
     <lb/>
     rendre; s'ils s'imaginent que nous n'avons abso- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     lument aucun droit sur cette partie du pays et 
     <lb/>
     qu'ils peuvent envoyer des délégués pour trai- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ter avec nous comme s'ils en avaient le droit et 
     <lb/>
     comme si leurs revendications étaient raison- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nables et correctement faites, si ces délégués 
     <lb/>
     représentent les gens qui ont osé, au sein d'une 
     <lb/>
     parodie de «cour martiale», condamner un 
     <lb/>
     homme à mort pour l'assassiner ensuite, eh 
     <lb/>
     bien! je souhaite, moi; que notre Gouverne- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment, tout en se tenant prêt à accorder toute 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->


            <pb n="893" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0893.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">893</fw>
          

     civilized country, whether they are to be treat<lb break="no"/>ed after the manner of truculent rebels who 
     <lb/>
     have not merely demanded what they call a 
     <lb/>
     Bill of Rights, which we as their fellow coun<lb break="no"/>trymen would be perfectly willing to give them 
     <lb/>
     if they have any grievance under which they 
     <lb/>
     suffer, but who have dared to steep their hands 
     <lb/>
     in the blood of an unoffending man who came 
     <lb/>
     from this country. If these men up there fancy 
     <lb/>
     that they have rights in the soil, that they are 
     <lb/>
     entitled to have all that property, that they 
     <lb/>
     have a right to do with it as they please, and 
     <lb/>
     that we are not to go there and that we have no 
     <lb/>
     right in it whatever, and they are sending 
     <lb/>
     down people to treat with us, as if they had the 
     <lb/>
     right to treat with us, in a manner in which 
     <lb/>
     they might say they would have, if they were 
     <lb/>
     fairly coming before us with claims which we 
     <lb/>
     might meet, but if these men are delegates 
     <lb/>
     from those who with a self-styled and so-called 
     <lb/>
     court-martial have dared to doom a man to 
     <lb/>
     death, and thereby murdered him, I say I hope 
     <lb/>
     that our Government will be in a position to 
     <lb/>
     say, that although prepared to concede, as we 
     <lb/>
     all hope that they will concede, everything 
     <lb/>
     honourable and just to the people of that terri<lb break="no"/>tory, that they will take care not to treat with 
     <lb/>
     men who come here with their hands red with 
     <lb/>
     blood, red with the blood of an unoffending 
     <lb/>
     fellow citizen; a man who went there with the 
     <lb/>
     guarantee of the Government, under the belief 
     <lb/>
     that everything would be rightly and properly 
     <lb/>
     conducted, and who had laid down his life 
     <lb/>
     because he believed that the same power which 
     <lb/>
     protected the poor captive in Abyssinia, would 
     <lb/>
     protect the free man in Red River. Now, I hope 
     <lb/>
     that the hon. Minister will give us an answer 
     <lb/>
     that will set the feelings of the people at rest, 
     <lb/>
     knowing as he does that the feelings of the 
     <lb/>
     people of the country is excited to a red hot 
     <lb/>
     heat, (cheers). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—My hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend commenced his remarks by asking the 
     <lb/>
     Government and myself, whether we had any 
     <lb/>
     later news to give relating to this deplorable 
     <lb/>
     event, the murder of this man, than we had 
     <lb/>
     when I addressed the House last on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject. I have simply to state that we have no 
     <lb/>
     further intelligence, but the intelligence is 
     <lb/>
     complete as to the fact of the man having been 
     <lb/>
     shot by a party of men calling themselves a 
     <lb/>
     Court Martial. That the man was murdered 
     <lb/>
     there can be no doubt. I stated that I would 
     <lb/>
     have full information from the Commissioner, 
     <lb/>
     who was sent on behalf of the Government on 
     <lb/>
     a mission of conciliation, and for the purpose 
     <lb/>
     of assisting Governor McTavish to restore 
     <lb/>
     order. That gentleman is now in this city, and 
     <lb/>
     is preparing a report, and so much of it as can 
     <lb/>
     be properly laid before this House will be laid 
     <lb/>
     on the table. I suppose that will be done in a 
     <lb/>
           


           <!-- <p>
     demande honnête et juste aux habitants de ce 
     <lb/>
     territoire, saura éviter de traiter avec des 
     <lb/>
     hommes dont les mains sont rouges du sang 
     <lb/>
     d'un concitoyen innocent. Le malheureux 
     <lb/>
     s'était rendu à cet endroit avec l'assurance du 
     <lb/>
     Gouvernement que tout se déroulerait dans un 
     <lb/>
     climat d'honnêteté et selon les règles; il a payé 
     <lb/>
     de sa vie, croyant que le pouvoir qui protege un 
     <lb/>
     pauvre captif en Abyssinie, protégerait aussi 
     <lb/>
     un homme libre à la Rivière Rouge. J'espère 
     <lb/>
     maintenant que l'honorable ministre, sachant à 
     <lb/>
     quel point tous les esprits sont embrasés, 
     <lb/>
     répondra de manière à les calmer. (Bravo!) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable sir John A. Macdonald—Mon 
     <lb/>
     honorable collègue a commencé par demander 
     <lb/>
     au Gouvernement et à moi-même si nous en 
     <lb/>
     savions plus sur ce déplorable incident, le 
     <lb/>
     meurtre de cet homme, que lors de mon dernier 
     <lb/>
     rapport à la Chambre à ce sujet. Nous n'avons 
     <lb/>
     aucun autre renseignement, mais nous savons, 
     <lb/>
     sans équivoque, que cet homme a été tué par 
     <lb/>
     un groupe d'individus qui s'est baptisé «Cour 
     <lb/>
     martiale». Son exécution ne fait aucun doute. 
     <lb/>
     J'ai dit que j'obtiendrais tous les renseigne- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ments voulus du commissaire que le Gouverne- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment a mandé en mission de conciliation et 
     <lb/>
     pour aider le Gouverneur McTavish à rétablir 
     <lb/>
     l'ordre. Ce commissaire est de retour et rédige 
     <lb/>
     actuellement un rapport. Tout ce qui pourra 
     <lb/>
     étre divulgué à la Chambre devrait l'étre sous 
     <lb/>
     peu, je pense. Voila pour les nouvelles. L'hono- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     rable député me demande de plus amples ren- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     seignements quant à la ligne de conduite que le 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->


            <pb n="894" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0894.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">894</fw>

            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
            <fw type="dateline">April 6th, 1870</fw>


     very short period. So much for the information. 
     <lb/>
     The hon. gentleman asks me to give further 
     <lb/>
     information as to the course the Government is 
     <lb/>
     about to pursue. I can only say to my hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend and to the House, and both he and the 
     <lb/>
     House will fully appreciate the reticence which 
     <lb/>
     I feel it my duty to observe in the matter, I can 
     <lb/>
     only say that the Government are fully aware 
     <lb/>
     of, and appreciate the gravity of the position, 
     <lb/>
     and have been so through the whole of this 
     <lb/>
     winter, and since the events which occurred 
     <lb/>
     about the end of October, they understand and 
     <lb/>
     fully appreciate the responsibility that rests 
     <lb/>
     upon them. They have been in constant com<lb break="no"/>munication with Her Majesty's Government on 
     <lb/>
     the subject, and I may say that the two Gov<lb break="no"/>ernments are acting in accord and unison— 
     <lb/>
     (hear, hear)—and with the one object in view, 
     <lb/>
     that of retaining that country as a portion of 
     <lb/>
     Her Majesty's Dominions, and of restoring law 
     <lb/>
     and order therein. We are acting in complete 
     <lb/>
     unison with Her Majesty's Government, and 
     <lb/>
     the line of conduct has been settled upon. What 
     <lb/>
     that line of conduct may be, must be for the 
     <lb/>
     present withheld from the House. It would 
     <lb/>
     simply be giving information at an improper 
     <lb/>
     time, and it would soon arrive at improper 
     <lb/>
     quarters. But I am glad to say that Her Majes<lb break="no"/>ty's Government are acting in accord with us, 
     <lb/>
     and have adopted our suggestions and have 
     <lb/>
     approved of the course we have devised, and 
     <lb/>
     that course I am sure will be carried out to a 
     <lb/>
     successful completion at no distant day. Fur<lb break="no"/>ther I cannot say. It would be improper for me 
     <lb/>
     to say any more, and I am quite sure the House 
     <lb/>
     will not ask nor expect me to say more. With 
     <lb/>
     respect to the delegation the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     has spoken of, I can only say that if they arrive 
     <lb/>
     here they will be received and heard, and there 
     <lb/>
     will be attentive consideration given to what<lb break="no"/>ever they may say in the matter. One hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman has spoken—and I see the press has 
     <lb/>
     spoken in the same sense—as if this delegation 
     <lb/>
     were coming from the persons who are the 
     <lb/>
     instigators and accessories of the murder of 
     <lb/>
     this man, and therefore should not be received. 
     <lb/>
     I do not understand that there are any such 
     <lb/>
     persons coming here, (hear, hear). There was a 
     <lb/>
     meeting held, as the House and country knows, 
     <lb/>
     months ago, composed of representatives elect<lb break="no"/>ed of the resident inhabitants, both English 
     <lb/>
     and French. That meeting was held for the 
     <lb/>
     purpose of conferring—you may call it a con<lb break="no"/>ference in fact—as to the state of the country, 
     <lb/>
     and what their claims should be before assent<lb break="no"/>ing to come into the Union. That body I believe 
     <lb/>
     was elected by the people, and was composed 
     <lb/>
     of a respectable body of men as a whole. The 
     <lb/>
     delegates I understand were selected by this 
     <lb/>
     meeting, and you will at once see there can be 
     <lb/>
     no assassin among them when I tell you that 
     <lb/>
     Judge Black is at their head, a gentleman who 
     <lb/>
       

           <!-- <p>
     [ Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald—L'hon. sir John A. Macdonald.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
           
            <p>
     Gouvernement est sur le point d'adopter. Je 
     <lb/>
     puis seulement dire à mon honorable collègue 
     <lb/>
     et à la Chambre, avec la certitude qu'ils com- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     prendront la discrétion que je dois observer en 
     <lb/>
     la matière, que le Gouvernement est parfaite- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment conscient de la gravité de la situation et 
     <lb/>
     l'a été durant tout l'hiver; cependant, depuis 
     <lb/>
     l'incident qui a eu lieu vers la fin du mois 
     <lb/>
     d'octobre, il a pleinement conscience de la res- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ponsabilité qui lui incombe. Il est en communi<lb break="no"/>cation constante avec le Gouvernement de Sa 
     <lb/>
     Majesté à ce sujet; je peux dire que les deux 
     <lb/>
     gouvernements agissent d'un commun accord; 
     <lb/>
     (Bravo! Bravo!) leur but unique est de mainte— 
     <lb/>
     nir ce pays parmi les dominions de Sa Majesté 
     <lb/>
     et d'y rétablir l'ordre. Nous agissons de concert 
     <lb/>
     avec le Gouvernement de Sa Majesté et avons 
     <lb/>
     fixé la marche à suivre, mais ne pouvons la 
     <lb/>
     divulguer à la Chambre pour le moment, car si 
     <lb/>
     ces renseignements sont diffusés à un moment 
     <lb/>
     inopportun, ils auront tôt fait de venir aux 
     <lb/>
     oreilles de ceux qui doivent les ignorer. Cepen- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     dant, je suis heureux d'affirmer que le Gouver- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nement de Sa Majesté nous appuie, qu'il a 
     <lb/>
     adopté nos recommandations et approuvé la 
     <lb/>
     ligne de conduite que nous nous sommes tracée 
     <lb/>
     et que nous suivrons avec succès, je l'espère, 
     <lb/>
     sous peu. Je ne peux pas en dire davantage, 
     <lb/>
     sous peine d'être indiscret. Je suis certain que 
     <lb/>
     la Chambre ne me posera pas d'autres ques<lb break="no"/>tions à ce sujet. En ce qui concerne les mem— 
     <lb/>
     bres de la délégation dont l'honorable député a 
     <lb/>
     fait mention, je ne puis que déclarer que s'ils 
     <lb/>
     viennent, ils présenteront leurs doléances et 
     <lb/>
     nous les écouterons avec la plus grande atten<lb break="no"/>tion. Un des honorables députés semblait 
     <lb/>
     croire, tout comme la presse, je le constate, que 
     <lb/>
     cette délégation représentait les instigateurs et 
     <lb/>
     les complices du meurtre de cet homme et que 
     <lb/>
     nous ne devrions donc pas la recevoir. A ma 
     <lb/>
     connaissance, tel n'est pas du tout le cas. 
     <lb/>
     (Bravo! Bravo!) Il y a des mois, comme le 
     <lb/>
     savent la Chambre et 1e pays tout entier, les 
     <lb/>
     représentants élus par les populations anglaise 
     <lb/>
     et française se sont réunis en Comité. Ce 
     <lb/>
     Comité, qu'on pourrait en fait appeler Confé- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     rence, avait pour but de conférer sur l'état du 
     <lb/>
     pays et de préciser les demandes à formuler 
     <lb/>
     avant de consentir à faire partie de l'Union. 
     <lb/>
     Les membres de ce Comité ont, je crois, été 
     <lb/>
     élus par le peuple; ce sont des personnes res- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     pectables. Les délégués ont, semble-t—il, été 
     <lb/>
     choisis au cours de cette réunion; vous vous 
     <lb/>
     rendrez facilement compte qu'il ne peut pas y 
     <lb/>
     avoir d'assassin parmi eux, quand je vous aurai 
     <lb/>
     dit qu'ils sont dirigés par le juge Black qui a 
     <lb/>
     présidé à la cour de la plus grande juridiction 
     <lb/>
     criminelle et civile de l'endroit et qui jouit de 
     <lb/>
     la confiance et du respect de tous, y compris de 
     <lb/>
     ceux qui se sont insurgés. Il est, bien sûr, hors 
     <lb/>
     de question d'accuser 1e juge Black d'avoir 
     <lb/>
     prêté son concours à une telle infamie, ou 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->


            <pb n="895" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0895.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">895</fw>
        

     has presided at the court there of the largest 
     <lb/>
     criminal and civil jurisdiction, and who enjoys 
     <lb/>
     the confidence and respect of all parties—even 
     <lb/>
     of the persons who are now insurgents. He is at 
     <lb/>
     the head of the deputation, and any imputation 
     <lb/>
     or insinuation that he could in any way 
     <lb/>
     countenance any such outrage as that spoken 
     <lb/>
     of, is, of course, out of the question. I may say 
     <lb/>
     further, in order to show the character of the 
     <lb/>
     delegation, and how it is esteemed by the 
     <lb/>
     people there, that when Judge Black thought at 
     <lb/>
     first that he could not come here in conse<lb break="no"/>quence of private and personal matters, it was 
     <lb/>
     settled that the Anglican Bishop of Rupert's 
     <lb/>
     Land, Bishop Macrae, should go in his place. Of 
     <lb/>
     course from his position it would be under<lb break="no"/>stood that he is a gentleman of the highest 
     <lb/>
     character, and I believe he is regarded as an 
     <lb/>
     honour to his Church and his profession. How<lb break="no"/>ever, Judge Black found it possible to come, 
     <lb/>
     and, I believe, he will be here with the rest. 
     <lb/>
     They will be heard; and so much importance, I 
     <lb/>
     may say, is attached to the fact that this body 
     <lb/>
     is coming here—this body of <hi rendition="simple:italic">quasi</hi> ambassa<lb break="no"/>dors—that Sir Stafford Northcote, who is Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor of the Hudson Bay Company, is coming 
     <lb/>
     out here for the very purpose of meeting them. 
     <lb/>
     They will be heard, and their representations 
     <lb/>
     will receive every consideration, and possibly 
     <lb/>
     the result of the conference may be the subject 
     <lb/>
     of discussion in this House before the end of 
     <lb/>
     the present session. I do not know that it is 
     <lb/>
     necessary, or that it would be proper or expedi<lb break="no"/>ent for me to say anything more in answer to 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend. If there is anything I have 
     <lb/>
     omitted I will be very glad to supplement my 
     <lb/>
     present statement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—There are one or two points 
     <lb/>
     upon which I would like further information. 
     <lb/>
     When I asked the Government two days ago 
     <lb/>
     the questions that have just been more fully 
     <lb/>
     asked by the hon. member for Peel, I said I was 
     <lb/>
     led to believe from the letters received, and 
     <lb/>
     from information in the newspapers, that there 
     <lb/>
     were still more prisoners confined there, and 
     <lb/>
     that I had some apprehension for the safety of 
     <lb/>
     these prisoners in the hands of such desperate 
     <lb/>
     men as seem to have control of affairs there at 
     <lb/>
     present. I have seen stated that this unfortu<lb break="no"/>nate gentleman who was murdered, asked 
     <lb/>
     leave before his murder to take a farewell of 
     <lb/>
     his fellow prisoners, and that at that time there 
     <lb/>
     were forty-seven persons in prison. Now, the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman has not stated whether he has 
     <lb/>
     any further information as to the fate of the 
     <lb/>
     forty-seven, who were undoubtedly in prison 
     <lb/>
     when this man was murdered. I asked that 
     <lb/>
     question two days ago. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—It was my 
     <lb/>
     impression that I had answered it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>



            <!--<fw type="running">DÉBATS DES</fw>
            <fw type="num">COMMUNES</fw>
            <fw type="num">895</fw>
            <p>
     même de l'insinuer. Je pourrais ajouter pour 
     <lb/>
     montrer l'intégrité de la délégation et l'estime 
     <lb/>
     dans laquelle ses membres sont tenus par les 
     <lb/>
     habitants de cet endroit, qu'au début, lorsque 
     <lb/>
     le juge Black avait jugé qu'il ne pouvait venir 
     <lb/>
     ici pour des raisons personnelles, on avait 
     <lb/>
     décidé que l'évêque anglican de Rupert, Mon<lb break="no"/>seigneur Macrae, prendrait sa place. Etant 
     <lb/>
     donné son poste, cet évéque doit avoir une 
     <lb/>
     réputation irréprochable et, d'après ce qu'on 
     <lb/>
     m'a dit, il fait honneur à son Eglise et à sa 
     <lb/>
     profession. Toutefois, le juge Black a pu se 
     <lb/>
     libérer et je crois qu'il viendra avec le reste de 
     <lb/>
     la délégation. Nous les entendrons et pour vous 
     <lb/>
     prouver l'importance de la visite de cette délé— 
     <lb/>
     gation quasi officielle, je vous dirai que sir 
     <lb/>
     Stafford Northcote, gouverneur de la Compa<lb break="no"/>gnie de la Baie d'Hudson viendra ici méme, 
     <lb/>
     pour rencontrer les membres. Nous les rece- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     vrons et examinerons soigneusement leurs 
     <lb/>
     doléances. Il se peut que le résultat de ces 
     <lb/>
     entretiens soit à l'ordre du jour de la Chambre 
     <lb/>
     avant la fin de cette session. Je ne crois pas 
     <lb/>
     qu'il soit nécessaire, opportun ou utile d'en dire 
     <lb/>
     plus long, en réponse à mon honorable ami. 
     <lb/>
     Mais si j'ai omis quelque chose, je serais heu- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     reux qu'on me le signale. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     M. Mackenzie—Il y a un ou deux points sur 
     <lb/>
     lesquels j'aimerais plus de renseignements. Il y 
     <lb/>
     a deux jours, lorsque j'ai posé au Gouverne- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment les questions que l'honorable député de 
     <lb/>
     Peel a repris, plus en détail, j'ai dit que les 
     <lb/>
     lettres et les journaux m'incitaient à penser 
     <lb/>
     qu'il y avait toujours beaucoup de prisonniers 
     <lb/>
     à cet endroit et que je craignais quelque peu 
     <lb/>
     pour leur sécurité devant la détermination de 
     <lb/>
     ceux qui semblent diriger cette région actuelle- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment. J'ai lu que la malheureuse victime a 
     <lb/>
     demandé, avant d'être exécutée, à faire ses 
     <lb/>
     adieux à ses compagnons au nombre de qua- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     rante-sept à ce moment-là. Or, l'honorable 
     <lb/>
     député n'a pas précisé si l'on a été informé du 
     <lb/>
     sort de ces quarante—sept personnes, sans nul 
     <lb/>
     doute emprisonnées lorsque cet homme a été 
     <lb/>
     assassiné. Je rappelle que j'ai posé cette ques<lb break="no"/>tion, il y a deux jours. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable sir John A. Macdonald—J e 
     <lb/>
     pensais y avoir répondu. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->


            <pb n="896" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0896.jpg"/>
        
     <fw type="num">896</fw> 
   <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw>
<fw type="dateline">April 6th, 1870</fw>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—The answer given was, that 
     <lb/>
     there would not be any definite information 
     <lb/>
     until they had the report from Mr. Donald A. 
     <lb/>
     Smith. I am very glad to hear that this Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and the Imperial Government are in 
     <lb/>
     accord in the determination to assert the 
     <lb/>
     supremacy of the British Crown in that territo<lb break="no"/>ry. But I have noticed a statement in the tele<lb break="no"/>graphic reports this morning that Mr. Monsell, 
     <lb/>
     the Under-Secretary of State for the Colonies, 
     <lb/>
     stated in his place in the English House of 
     <lb/>
     Commons on Monday night, that the demands 
     <lb/>
     made upon the Imperial Government for 
     <lb/>
     Imperial troops to go to Red River, were then 
     <lb/>
     under consideration of the Government, 
     <lb/>
     (hear). So that it is quite evident that on 
     <lb/>
     Monday night, at last, there is some discrepan<lb break="no"/>cy between Mr. Monsell's statement and the 
     <lb/>
     one the hon. gentleman opposite just made. Of 
     <lb/>
     course I accept the statement just made, but I 
     <lb/>
     mention this to show that there is some 
     <lb/>
     misunderstanding. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—No, no, 
     <lb/>
     (hear). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—Very well, I am very glad 
     <lb/>
     to hear it, (hear). With reference to the dele<lb break="no"/>gates I am bound to take the statement of the 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman, that Judge Black in coming, as 
     <lb/>
     I have no information from the papers or 
     <lb/>
     otherwise, but I fully endorse the sentiments 
     <lb/>
     of the member for Peel regarding the two other 
     <lb/>
     persons who are coming here, and who were so 
     <lb/>
     intimately connected with the persons in rebel<lb break="no"/>lion, and I think they ought not to be received. 
     <lb/>
     We have first to vindicate the British law and 
     <lb/>
     supremacy in that country before we can hold 
     <lb/>
     communication with the people in rebellion. I 
     <lb/>
     have seen it stated that Riel has been issuing 
     <lb/>
     decrees and assuming supreme power—not 
     <lb/>
     assuming the functions of a Provisional Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment but the functions of a permanent Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, and acting as if no election of dele<lb break="no"/>gates had taken place. I have seen it stated that 
     <lb/>
     two of the delegates were appointed actually 
     <lb/>
     by force, that the inhabitants present were 
     <lb/>
     overawed by those who had power at the 
     <lb/>
     moment, and that the whole proceeding was 
     <lb/>
     merely to gain time until they could obtain 
     <lb/>
     assistance from the filibusters and others in 
     <lb/>
     the United States, with whom we know they 
     <lb/>
     have been in active communication since the 
     <lb/>
     beginning of the insurrection. I wish to know 
     <lb/>
     further from the hon. gentleman whether any 
     <lb/>
     delay is to take place in forwarding the prepa<lb break="no"/>rations that must be made—for there must be 
     <lb/>
     no squeamishness in this matter—until these 
     <lb/>
     delegates should come here, until Sir Stafford 
     <lb/>
     Northcote should come here, until there should 
     <lb/>
     be ample time to discuss these matters with 
     <lb/>
     these people, such delay as would prevent the 
     <lb/>
         

           <!-- <p>
     (Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald—L'hon. sir John A. Macdonald.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     April 6th. 1870 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     M. Mackenzie—La réponse a indiqué qu'il 
     <lb/>
     n'y aurait aucun renseignement définitif avant 
     <lb/>
     le rapport de M. Donald A. Smith. Je suis très 
     <lb/>
     heureux d'apprendre que ce Gouvernement et 
     <lb/>
     le Gouvernement impérial se font un devoir 
     <lb/>
     commun d'affirmer la suprématie de la Cou- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ronne sur ce territoire. Pourtant, ce matin, j'ai 
     <lb/>
     noté dans les rapports télégraphiques que M. 
     <lb/>
     Monsell, sous-secrétaire d'État aux Colonies a 
     <lb/>
     déclaré lundi soir à la Chambre des Communes 
     <lb/>
     de Londres, que le Gouvernement étudiait les 
     <lb/>
     pressions exercées sur le Gouvernement impé- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     rial concernant l'envoi de troupes à la Rivière 
     <lb/>
     Rouge. (Bravo! Bravo!) Il est donc évident que, 
     <lb/>
     lundi soir au moins, il y avait encore diver<lb break="no"/>gence entre la déclaration de M. Monsell et 
     <lb/>
     celle que l'honorable député vient de faire. 
     <lb/>
     J'accepte bien entendu cette dernière; mais je 
     <lb/>
     voulais simplement montrer qu'il y a quelques 
     <lb/>
     divergences. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable sir John A. Macdonald—Mais 
     <lb/>
     non, il n'y en a pas. (Bravo!) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     M. Mackenzie—Très bien. je suis ravi de 
     <lb/>
     l'entendre. (Bravo!) En ce qui concerne les 
     <lb/>
     délégués, je dois accepter la déclaration de l'ho- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     norable député, selon laquelle le juge Black 
     <lb/>
     viendra, puisqu'il n'y a pas d'autres renseigne- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ments à ce sujet dans la presse ou ailleurs. 
     <lb/>
     Cependant, j'appuie entièrement le député de 
     <lb/>
     Peel quant aux deux autres personnes qui 
     <lb/>
     viendront ici et qui étaient très proches des 
     <lb/>
     insurgés; je crois que nous ne devrions pas les 
     <lb/>
     recevoir. Nous devons défendre la justice et la 
     <lb/>
     suprématie britanniques dans ce pays avant de 
     <lb/>
     communiquer avec des rebelles. J'ai lu quelque 
     <lb/>
     part que Riel a émis des décrets et s'est appro- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     prié le pouvoir suprême, assumant les fonc- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tions d'un gouvernement non pas provisoire 
     <lb/>
     mais permanent et qu'il agit comme si l'on 
     <lb/>
     n'avait pas élu de délégués. J'ai vu, par ailleurs, 
     <lb/>
     que deux de ces délégués ont en fait été 
     <lb/>
     nommés par la force et que les personnes pré- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sentes ont été intimidées par les détenteurs du 
     <lb/>
     pouvoir qui avaient imaginé toute cette mise 
     <lb/>
     en scène pour gagner du temps, jusqu'à ce 
     <lb/>
     qu'ils puissent obtenir l'aide d'aventuriers et 
     <lb/>
     autres agitateurs américains avec lesquels nous 
     <lb/>
     savons qu'ils sont en communication active 
     <lb/>
     depuis le début de l'insurrection. Je voudrais 
     <lb/>
     bien que l'honorable député me dise s'il y aura 
     <lb/>
     du retard dans les préparatifs—la délicatesse 
     <lb/>
     n'étant pas de mise dans cette affaire—en vue 
     <lb/>
     de l'arrivée de la délégation et de sir Stafford 
     <lb/>
     Northcote avec qui nous discuterons in extenso 
     <lb/>
     du problème, un tel retard pourrait empêcher 
     <lb/>
     le départ des forces nécessaires au rétablisse- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment de l'ordre dans cette région. Nous savons 
     <lb/>
     maintenant que la navigation commencera 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

            <pb n="897" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0897.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">897</fw>
           

     departure of the forces necessary, in order to 
     <lb/>
     enforce order there. It is known now sir, that 
     <lb/>
     navigation will soon open on the upper Lakes, 
     <lb/>
     and within three or four weeks it will be possi<lb break="no"/>ble for vessels to traverse Lake Superior to 
     <lb/>
     Thunder Bay; and I trust nothing will prevent 
     <lb/>
     the execution by the Government of every<lb break="no"/>thing necessary to forward forces there at the 
     <lb/>
     earliest possible moment, (hear). This is a 
     <lb/>
     matter, of course, in which I am aware the 
     <lb/>
     Government have difficulties to contend with; 
     <lb/>
     and I am quite disposed to make every allow<lb break="no"/>ance for those difficulties; and I hope nothing 
     <lb/>
     will prevent the Government adopting an ener<lb break="no"/>getic course, (hear). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—With regard 
     <lb/>
     to the statement in the telegraphic news 
     <lb/>
     respecting the statement of Mr. Monsell, I can 
     <lb/>
     merely say that the telegraph is not usually 
     <lb/>
     very accurate. I do not know what explana<lb break="no"/>tions he may have made in the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons, and can only repeat what I have said, 
     <lb/>
     that the two Governments are quite in accord 
     <lb/>
     as to the policy pursued, and that policy is one 
     <lb/>
     of action, (hear). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—I am very glad to hear that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—With regard 
     <lb/>
     to the prisoners, I can only repeat the state<lb break="no"/>ment I made before. Mr. Smith understood that 
     <lb/>
     half of them had been discharged or were to be 
     <lb/>
     discharged as soon as he left, and the remain<lb break="no"/>der in a day or two. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—Have you any positive 
     <lb/>
     information that they were discharged? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—I am sure 
     <lb/>
     they are all discharged by this time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—Then does the Government 
     <lb/>
     intend to delay active proceedings in the 
     <lb/>
     meantime? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—I have told 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend that the two Governments are 
     <lb/>
     quite in accord, and that our policy is one of 
     <lb/>
     action—(cheers)—and I think my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     ought to be satisfied with that. Judge Black 
     <lb/>
     was coming down at once, and asked Mr. Smith 
     <lb/>
     to make arrangements for him, and Mr. Smith 
     <lb/>
     did make arrangements for him, sending con<lb break="no"/>veyances en route. Mr. Smith left on the 19th of 
     <lb/>
     March, and Judge Black was shortly to follow 
     <lb/>
     him, but he did not make any arrangements for 
     <lb/>
     the others, as they did not ask him. He had 
     <lb/>
     made arrangements for conveyance to St. Paul, 
     <lb/>
     and from St. Paul still further this way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


           <!-- <fw type="running">DÈBATS DES</fw>
            <fw type="num">COMMUNES</fw>
            <fw type="num">897</fw>
            <p>
     bientôt sur les Grands lacs et que, dans trois ou 
     <lb/>
     quatre semaines, des navires pourront traver<lb break="no"/>ser le lac Supérieur pour se rendre à Thunder 
     <lb/>
     Bay. J'espère que rien n'empêchera le Gouver- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nement de prendre toutes les mesures nécessai— 
     <lb/>
     res pour envoyer des hommes a cet endroit le 
     <lb/>
     plus tôt possible. (Bravo!) Je sais que le Gou- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     vernement aura des difficultés et je suis tout 
     <lb/>
     prêt à en tenir compte; j'espère néanmoins que 
     <lb/>
     rien ne l'empêchera d'avoir une attitude éner- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     gique. (Bravo!) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable sir John A. Macdonald—En ce 
     <lb/>
     qui concerne la déclaration de M. Monsell men- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tionnée dans les bulletins télégraphiques, je me 
     <lb/>
     bornerai à souligner l'inexactitude habituelle 
     <lb/>
     de ces bulletins. J'ignore quelles explications 
     <lb/>
     ce monsieur a pu donner à la Chambre des 
     <lb/>
     Communes et je ne puis que répéter ce que j'ai 
     <lb/>
     déjà dit, c'est-à-dire que les deux gouverne- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ments sont parfaitement d'accord sur l'attitude 
     <lb/>
     à adopter; tous deux estiment qu'on doit agir. 
     <lb/>
     (Bravo!) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     M. Mackenzie—Je suis très heureux de vous 
     <lb/>
     l'entendre dire. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable sir John A. Macdonald—Au 
     <lb/>
     sujet des prisonniers, je ne peux que répéter ce 
     <lb/>
     que j'ai déjà dit. M. Smith a compris que la 
     <lb/>
     moitié d'entre eux avait été libérée ou devait 
     <lb/>
     l'être aussitôt après son départ et que les autres 
     <lb/>
     le seraient dans un jour ou deux. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     M. Mackenzie—Savez-vous de façon positive 
     <lb/>
     s'ils ont été libérés? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable sir John A. Macdonald—Oui, 
     <lb/>
     je suis sûr qu'ils ont tous été libérés depuis. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     M. Mackenzie—Dans ce cas, le Gouverne- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment a-t-il l'intention de retarder les prépara- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tifs en attendant? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable sir John A. Macdonald—J'ai 
     <lb/>
     dit à mon honorable collègue que les deux 
     <lb/>
     gouvernements étaient d'accord sur une politi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     que d'action (Bravo!) et cette réponse devrait 
     <lb/>
     satisfaire mon honorable ami. Le juge Black 
     <lb/>
     doit venir incessament et il a demandé à M. 
     <lb/>
     Smith de prendre les dispositions voulues, ce 
     <lb/>
     que M. Smith a fait en envoyant des voitures à 
     <lb/>
     sa rencontre. M. Smith est parti le 19 mars et le 
     <lb/>
     juge Black devait le suivre peu après. Cepen- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     dant, M. Smith n'a pas pris de dispositions pour 
     <lb/>
     les autres voyageurs, ces derniers ne lui ayant 
     <lb/>
     pas demandé de le faire. Il avait prévu le trans<lb break="no"/>port jusqu'à Saint-Paul et de Saint-Paul jus- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     qu'à proximité d'ici. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->


            <pb n="898" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0898.jpg"/>
       

     <fw type="num">898</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">April 6th, 1870</fw> 
     

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GALT1">Hon. Sir A. T. Galt</persName>—Has any information 
     <lb/>
     been received of Judge Black's arrival at St. 
     <lb/>
     Paul? Mr. Smith left St. Paul a number of days 
     <lb/>
     ago, and it is possible that these gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     hearing of this deplorable event, will not now 
     <lb/>
     come at all. I think while this House is in 
     <lb/>
     session, it is absolutely necessary that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment should before the House closes, put 
     <lb/>
     the House in full possession of the course it 
     <lb/>
     proposes to take. I can quite understand that a 
     <lb/>
     certain amount of reticence is absolutely 
     <lb/>
     necessary and is desirable, but at the same 
     <lb/>
     time when the representatives of the people 
     <lb/>
     are here assembled, I think the Government 
     <lb/>
     cannot with any propriety ask that this ques<lb break="no"/>tion should remain over until Parliament rises, 
     <lb/>
     for we are told that Parliament may rise short<lb break="no"/>ly, and that the Government intend to bring it 
     <lb/>
     to a close as speedily as possible. I think we 
     <lb/>
     should have the assurance that whatever 
     <lb/>
     course is pursued, this House should be 
     <lb/>
     informed of it. I think there can no doubt 
     <lb/>
     whatever that the Rubicon has been passed, by 
     <lb/>
     the execution, the homicide of Scott, and as 
     <lb/>
     these individuals have appealed to force, my 
     <lb/>
     conviction is that force must be resorted to. For 
     <lb/>
     my own part there is no one more willing to 
     <lb/>
     meet any reasonable complaint or remove any 
     <lb/>
     reasonable misapprehension that these people 
     <lb/>
     may be labouring under, but I do think that 
     <lb/>
     when, without any provocation, as far as we 
     <lb/>
     can judge from the information before us, they 
     <lb/>
     have slain men, the responsibility now rests 
     <lb/>
     with our Government, with the Imperial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and with us (hear), and that we 
     <lb/>
     cannot divest ourselves of that responsibility 
     <lb/>
     by simple acquiescence with what the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment may consider right, (hear). I think the 
     <lb/>
     Government should give the House an opportu<lb break="no"/>nity of affirming or disapproving the policy 
     <lb/>
     they may see fit to adopt, (hear). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—Of course the 
     <lb/>
     Government is in the hands of the House, and 
     <lb/>
     any hon. member can bring this subject up 
     <lb/>
     whenever he pleases. We must make such 
     <lb/>
     efforts as we think it our duty to do, we must 
     <lb/>
     take such a course and abide the consequences 
     <lb/>
     of approbation or disapprobation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GALT1">Hon. Sir A. T. Galt</persName>—I hope the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man does not misunderstand me. I only wish to 
     <lb/>
     know if the Government would announce their 
     <lb/>
     policy before the House rises. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Hon. Sir John A. Macdonald</persName>—I really hope 
     <lb/>
     and believe that before this Parliament rises, 
     <lb/>
     matters will be in such a state that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment can, without injury to public interests, 
     <lb/>
     but rather in promotion of public interests, 
     <lb/>
     take, as it were, the House into our confidence, 
     <lb/>
       

   
           <!-- <p>
     [Bon. Sir John A. Macdonald—L'hon. sir John A. Macdonald] 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     L'honorable sir A. T. Galt—A-t-on eu con<lb break="no"/>firmation de l'arrivée du juge Black a Saint- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Paul? M. Smith a quitté cet endroit, il y a 
     <lb/>
     quelques jours et il se peut que ces messieurs 
     <lb/>
     aient décidé de ne pas venir quand on les a 
     <lb/>
     informés du drame. Pendant que la Chambre 
     <lb/>
     est en session et avant qu'elle ne s'ajourne, il 
     <lb/>
     est indispensable, à mon sens. que le Gouver- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nement lui expose son plan en détail. Je com- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     prends qu'une certaine discrétion soit absolu- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment nécessaire et même souhaitable, mais par 
     <lb/>
     ailleurs, lorsque les représentants du peuple 
     <lb/>
     sont assemblés ici, je crois que le Gouverne- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ment ne peut exiger que cette question reste en 
     <lb/>
     suspens jusqu'à la clôture du Parlement qui 
     <lb/>
     pourrait avoir lieu bientôt. Le Gouvernement 
     <lb/>
     aurait même l'intention de l'ajourner le plus 
     <lb/>
     tôt possible. D'après moi, on doit nous donner 
     <lb/>
     l'assurance que cette Chambre sera avisée de la 
     <lb/>
     ligne de conduite suivie, quelle qu'elle soit. 
     <lb/>
     Sans l'ombre d'un doute, ces individus ont 
     <lb/>
     franchi le Rubicon en exécutant l'homme en 
     <lb/>
     question, en assassinant Scott et comme ils ont 
     <lb/>
     eu recours à la force, je suis convaincu que 
     <lb/>
     nous devons également y recourir. Nul ne sau- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     rait etre plus disposé que moi à tenir compte de 
     <lb/>
     tout doléance raisonnable et à dissiper tout 
     <lb/>
     malentendu dont ils pourraient être victimes, 
     <lb/>
     mais je crois sincèrement que lorsqu'on assas- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     sine des hommes sans provocation, à en juger 
     <lb/>
     par les renseignements dont nous disposons, il 
     <lb/>
     appartient à notre Gouvernement, au Gouver- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nement impérial et à nous—mêmes, d'agir, 
     <lb/>
     (Bravo!) et nous ne pouvons échapper à cette 
     <lb/>
     responsabilité en approuvant tout simplement, 
     <lb/>
     une décision que le Gouvernement peut esti- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     mer appropriée. (Bravo!) A mon sens, ce der- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     nier devrait donner a la Chambre l'occasion de 
     <lb/>
     se prononcer sur la politique qu'il juge oppor<lb break="no"/>tune en l'occurrence. (Bravo!) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable sir John A. Macdonald—Il est 
     <lb/>
     bien évident que le Gouvernement est dans les 
     <lb/>
     mains de la Chambre et que tout honorable 
     <lb/>
     député peut soulever" cette question quand bon 
     <lb/>
     lui semble. Nous devons faire les efforts que 
     <lb/>
     nous estimons commandés par notre devoir. 
     <lb/>
     Nous devons adopter une ligne de conduite et 
     <lb/>
     en subir les conséquences. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable sir A. T. Galt—J'espère que 
     <lb/>
     l'honorable député ne se méprend pas sur le 
     <lb/>
     sens de mes paroles. Je désire simplement 
     <lb/>
     savoir si le Gouvernement nous fera part de sa 
     <lb/>
     position avant l'ajournement de la Chambre. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable sir John A. Macdonald—J'es- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     père et je crois sincèrement qu'avant la clôture 
     <lb/>
     de cette session, la situation permettra au Gou- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     vernement non pas au détriment de l'intérêt 
     <lb/>
     public, mais en sa faveur, d'accorder, si j'ose 
     <lb/>
     dire, sa confiance à la Chambre et de lui indi- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>-->


            <pb n="899" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-04-06_Page_0899.jpg"/>
           <fw type="num">899</fw>
        

     if I may use such an expression, and show 
     <lb/>
     what the policy of the Government is, (hear). 
     <lb/>
     Of course events changing every day may 
     <lb/>
     change the course this Government now think 
     <lb/>
     fit to pursue. I think if the Government do not 
     <lb/>
     make a full statement to the House before the 
     <lb/>
     prorogation, they are bound to make such a 
     <lb/>
     statement as will meet the approbation of the 
     <lb/>
     House, (hear). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The matter was then dropped. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2018-05-09, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day --> 

   
           <!-- <p>
     FERRIES 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Morris moved the House into Com<lb break="no"/>mittee to consider the resolution on the subject 
     <lb/>
     of Ferries. He explained that there was no 
     <lb/>
     Statute regulating the granting of licences to 
     <lb/>
     ferries between any two Provinces, and be<lb break="no"/>tween any of the Provinces and the adjoining 
     <lb/>
     country. What he desired, was a law providing 
     <lb/>
     certain regulations to be observed by all par<lb break="no"/>ties applying for such licenses, and the result 
     <lb/>
     would be to do away with existing evils and 
     <lb/>
     promote the public interest. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> advocated as little interfer<lb break="no"/>ence as possible with the ferries. He called 
     <lb/>
     attention to the policy with regard to the 
     <lb/>
     American ferry steamers which was attended 
     <lb/>
     with great practical inconvenience both to 
     <lb/>
     their own citizens and ours, as from the restric<lb break="no"/>tions placed on our steamers in their ports, 
     <lb/>
     their ferry boats, knowing that they could 
     <lb/>
     obtain all the traffic, took towing and other 
     <lb/>
     work. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. Holton thought the mover should 
     <lb/>
     have been a little more explicit. He desired to 
     <lb/>
     know what was proposed to be done with the 
     <lb/>
     ferry opposite Ottawa, and with such ferries as 
     <lb/>
     those at Detroit, Sarnia and Ogdensburg. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     After some further discussion the resolutions 
     <lb/>
     were agreed to, and the Committee rose and 
     <lb/>
     reported, and Mr. Morris introduced a Bill 
     <lb/>
     founded on the resolutions, intituled: "An Act 
     <lb/>
     respecting Ferries", which was read a first 
     <lb/>
     time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     NOVA SCOTIA BANK ISSUES 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Sir Francis Hincks moved the House 
     <lb/>
     into Committee on the resolutions, to empower 
     <lb/>
     Banks in Nova Scotia to issue notes, between 
     <lb/>
     $20 and $4, they being at present prevented 
     <lb/>
     from issuing any under $20.—Resolutions 
     <lb/>
     reported. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <fw type="running">DEBATS DES</fw>
            <fw type="num">COMMUNES</fw>
            <fw type="num">899</fw>
            <p>
     quer sa ligne de conduite. (Bravo!) Il est cer<lb break="no"/>tain que l'évolution quotidienne des événe- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ments peut modifier la ligne de conduite jugée 
     <lb/>
     actuellement appropriée par le Gouvernement. 
     <lb/>
     Je crois que si ce dernier ne fait pas un exposé 
     <lb/>
     complet de la situation à la Chambre avant la 
     <lb/>
     clôture du Parlement, il fera une déclaration 
     <lb/>
     qui recevra l'appui de la Chambre. (Bravo!) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On passe à autre chose. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     BACS 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable M. Morris propose que la 
     <lb/>
     Chambre siège en Comité pour examiner la 
     <lb/>
     résolution concernant les bacs. Il explique qu'il 
     <lb/>
     n'existe pas d'Acte régissant la concession de 
     <lb/>
     licences autorisant les bacs à exercer leur acti- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     vité entre deux provinces quelconques, ainsi 
     <lb/>
     qu'entre une province et le pays voisin. Ce qu'il 
     <lb/>
     désire, c'est un Acte comportant certaines 
     <lb/>
     règles obligatoires pour toutes les parties 
     <lb/>
     demandant ces licences, ce qui aurait pour 
     <lb/>
     effet d'éliminer les difficultés actuelles, dans 
     <lb/>
     l'intérêt de tous. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     M. Mackenzie voudrait qu'on intervienne le 
     <lb/>
     moins possible dans l'affaire des bacs. Il attire 
     <lb/>
     1'attention sur la politique relative aux bacs à 
     <lb/>
     vapeur américains, laquelle comporte des 
     <lb/>
     inconvénients d'ordre pratique pour les Améri- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     cains autant que pour nous, Canadiens. Il men- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tionne les restrictions touchant nos bacs à 
     <lb/>
     vapeur dans les ports des États-Unis et signale 
     <lb/>
     que les bacs américains, sûrs d'obtenir tout le 
     <lb/>
     trafic, s'occupent aussi de remorquage et d'au- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     tres travaux. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable M. Holton croit que le motion- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     naire aurait dû être un peu plus explicite. Il 
     <lb/>
     désire connaître les projets concernant le bacs 
     <lb/>
     en face d'Ottawa, ainsi que les traversiers de 
     <lb/>
     Détroit, de Sarnia et d'Ogdensburg. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Après plus ample discussion, le Comité enté- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     rine les résolutions et fait rapport. M. Morris 
     <lb/>
     présente un Bill fondé sur les résolutions et 
     <lb/>
     intitulé: «Acte concernant les passages d'eau», 
     <lb/>
     dont il est donné lecture une première fois. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     EMISSION DE BILLETS PAR LES 
     <lb/>
     BANQUES DE NOUVELLE-ECOSSE 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     L'honorable sir Francis Hincks propose que 
     <lb/>
     la Chambre siège en Comité pour discuter des 
     <lb/>
     résolutions autorisant les banques de Nouvelle- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     Écosse à émettre des billets de $4 à $20, ces 
     <lb/>
     banques n'ayant pas le droit, actuellement, 
     <lb/>
     d'émettre des billets de moins de $20. Le 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Comité fait rapport des résolutions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>