<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_MB_1869-05-21"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1869-05-21">21 May 1869</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
          
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Second Session</title>.
                    

          <date when="1975"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Information Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="424" to="424"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-21_Page_0424.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
        
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-15">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-15">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-18">Marked-up people.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1869-05-21_Page_0424">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-21_Page_0424.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="424" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1869-05-21_Page_0424.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">424</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">May 21, 1869</fw>
            
            <p>
               The Bill was then ordered for a second 
               <lb/>
               reading on Tuesday. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
        <div type="section">
            
            <head>
               THE NORTH-WEST 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:CART2">Sir George E. Cartier</persName> gave notice that on 
               <lb/>
               Tuesday next he would move, seconded by 
               <lb/>
               <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName>, that the House go into 
               <lb/>
               Committee of the Whole to consider a series 
               <lb/>
               of resolutions respecting the acquisition of 
               <lb/>
               the territorial and other rights of the Hud<lb break="no"/>son's Bay Company in Rupert's Land, and 
               <lb/>
               any other part of British North America not 
               <lb/>
               comprised in Canada, Rupert's Land, or Brit<lb break="no"/>ish Columbia, and respecting the admission 
               <lb/>
               of the North West Territory. He said the 
               <lb/>
               resolutions would be distributed as soon as 
               <lb/>
               possible, but perhaps would not be ready in 
               <lb/>
               French and English for the House to go into 
               <lb/>
               Committee on Tuesday. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
        </div>

<div type="section">      
            
            <head>
               DUTY ON AMERICAN GRAIN 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:JONE3">Mr. Jones</persName> (Leeds and Grenville North) gave 
               <lb/>
               notice that he would move, on the first con<lb break="no"/>venient day, that it is expedient to impose a 
               <lb/>
               duty on all American Wheat, corn, rye, barley, 
               <lb/>
               and other grains imported into Canada, in<lb break="no"/>tended to be used in the manufacture of 
               <lb/>
               spirits, Wine, beer and other spirituous liquors, 
               <lb/>
               and that such duty be 20 per cent on the 
               <lb/>
               estimated value of such grain at the Canadian 
               <lb/>
               port of entry. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">       
         
            
            <head>
               OFFENCES AGAINST THE PERSON 
               <lb/>
               
            </head>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MACD1">Sir John A. Macdonald</persName> moved the second 
               <lb/>
               reading of the Bill respecting offences against 
               <lb/>
               the person. 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
         
            
            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:DORI1">Hon. Mr. Dorion</persName> said, since he had given 
               <lb/>
               notice of his amendment with reference to 
               <lb/>
               flogging, he found the Minister of Justice had 
               <lb/>
               got his other Bills so amended as to reduce 
               <lb/>
               the cases in which flogging was to be ad<lb break="no"/>ministered to a very few. His (Mr. Dorion's) 
               <lb/>
               feeling, however, was so strong that we ought 
               <lb/>
               not to recede from the position we had taken 
               <lb/>
               long ago on this subject, that he must persist 
               <lb/>
               in his amendment. If we looked to the history 
               <lb/>
               of flogging, we would find that in the Middle 
               <lb/>
               Ages it was very frequently administered, 
               <lb/>
               with a view of driving from crime; but with<lb break="no"/>in the last half century a great change has 
               <lb/>
               taken place in the opinion of publicists, and 
               <lb/>
               in the criminal law of almost every other 
               <lb/>
               country, with reference to this matter. It had 
               <lb/>
               been abolished in Prussia, Russia, Austria, 
               <lb/>
               Switzerland, in large portions of Italy, and 
               <lb/>
               in fact it now existed, partially indeed, and 
               <lb/>
               in a very few cases in England; and the 
               <lb/>
               
            </p>
            
            
            
</div>       
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
