<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgHC_MB_1870-02-21"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgHC">House of Commons</name>, <date when="1870-02-21">21 February 1870</date>, Canadian Confederation with Manitoba</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

               <editor>P.B. Waite</editor>.
    
         
          <title>House of Commons Debates, First Parliament, Third Session</title>.
                    

           <date when="1979"/>.   
          

          <pubPlace>Ottawa</pubPlace>: <publisher>Minister of Supply and Services Canada</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="95"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="117" to="120"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0079.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0080.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0081.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0082.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0083.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0084.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0085.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0086.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0087.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0088.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0089.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0090.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0091.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0092.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0093.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0094.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0095.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0117.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0118.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0119.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0120.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-12-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-12-08">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-22">Marked-up people </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0079">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0079.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0080">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0080.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0081">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0081.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0082">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0082.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0083">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0083.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0084">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0084.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0085">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0085.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0086">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0086.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0087">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0087.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0088">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0088.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0089">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0089.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0090">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0090.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0091">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0091.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0092">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0092.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0093">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0093.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0094">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0094.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0095">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0095.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0117">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0117.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0118">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0118.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0119">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0119.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0120">
         <graphic url="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0120.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="79" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0079.jpg"/>
           <!-- <fw type="dateline">
     21 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->

<div type="section">
            <head>
     HOUSE OF COMMONS 
     <lb/></head>

     <p>Monday, February 21, 1870 
     <lb/></p>
           
   
            <p>
     The Speaker took the chair at three o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     A petition was presented from certain citi<lb break="no"/>zens of Hamilton, asking for the abolition of 
     <lb/>
     duty on refined salt. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head>
     THE ADDRESS 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName> resumed the debate on the 
     <lb/>
     Address. After referring to the ceremony at the 
     <lb/>
     opening of the Session—a scene of which, he 
     <lb/>
     said, the country might be proud—he observed 
     <lb/>
     that his two hon. friends who moved and 
     <lb/>
     seconded the Address to the Speech from the 
     <lb/>
     Throne, were like two heralds proclaiming the 
     <lb/>
     lists opened. Then the hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Châteauguay threw down his glove and struck 
     <lb/>
     the shield of his (Mr. Howe's) hon. friend on 
     <lb/>
     the left (Sir F. Hincks), who at once picked up 
     <lb/>
     the glove and accepted the challenge. The 
     <lb/>
     opening debate took place in the presence of 
     <lb/>
     Queen Victoria's son; but, although the Prince 
     <lb/>
     had been present at the debate in Congress, 
     <lb/>
     and had traversed a great portion of this coun<lb break="no"/>try, he had witnessed no such scene, embody<lb break="no"/>ing as it did the representation and security of 
     <lb/>
     the people, and a system of well-preserved lib<lb break="no"/>erty. A few years ago, he (Mr. Howe) had spent 
     <lb/>
     some ten weeks in Washington, and during all 
     <lb/>
     that time there was a deadlock between the 
     <lb/>
     Government and the Legislature; but no such 
     <lb/>
     thing could occur here and this was a subject 
     <lb/>
     of earnest congratulation. During the debate 
     <lb/>
     the Ministry had been challenged for explana<lb break="no"/>tions, and he had been challenged two or three 
     <lb/>
     times; and this was the first chance he had of 
     <lb/>
     rising to say a word in his own defence or give 
     <lb/>
     the explanations which the House had a right 
     <lb/>
     to demand. He would beg gentlemen on the 
     <lb/>
     other side to acquit him of remissness in not 
     <lb/>
     speaking, but he had wanted to narrow the 
     <lb/>
     debate and have a discussion on the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     West. At the same time he had nothing to 
     <lb/>
     conceal. The Opposition had a right to know 
     <lb/>
     and his friends on his own side of the House 
     <lb/>
     had a right to know, if he, last summer, had 
     <lb/>
     done anything to weaken the hold he had on 
     <lb/>
     the gentlemen on his own side of the House. It 
     <lb/>
     would be in the memory of the House that 
     <lb/>
     during the short session of 1867 he delivered on 
     <lb/>
     the other side of the House his opinion on the 
     <lb/>
     subject of the North-West. (Hear, hear.) It was 
     <lb/>
     known too, how, in the presence of an immense 
     <lb/>
     force on the other side, he had avowed and 
     <lb/>
     maintained the belief that the Imperial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment should assume the charge of that 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="80" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0080.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">80</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">
     February 21, 1870<lb/>
            </fw>
       
     Country. He believed that it should be formed 
     <lb/>
     into a Crown Colony, or a series of Crown 
     <lb/>
     Colonies, and that the Queen would have the 
     <lb/>
     benefit of all the trade without the people of 
     <lb/>
     the Dominion incurring the risk of extending 
     <lb/>
     their territories or burthening themselves with 
     <lb/>
     the expense. The session of Parliament to 
     <lb/>
     which he had referred, lasted forty days, and 
     <lb/>
     after it closed and went home. When Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment opened again he found that it had decid<lb break="no"/>ed to purchase the Territory. After this, dele<lb break="no"/>gates were sent to England, and the 
     <lb/>
     arrangements they had made were, he admit<lb break="no"/>ted, of an advantageous character. The policy 
     <lb/>
     as to the  North-West was settled when he went 
     <lb/>
     into the Government last spring, and there was 
     <lb/>
     nothing to be done except to carry out the 
     <lb/>
     policy which Parliament had laid down. He 
     <lb/>
     now addressed the House in the presence of his 
     <lb/>
     friends in the Government, and would ask 
     <lb/>
     them whether, from the day he entered the 
     <lb/>
     Cabinet, they had not his sincere and hearty 
     <lb/>
     co-operation in the course they had determined 
     <lb/>
     to pursue. He would now say something as to 
     <lb/>
     his connection with this question, but every<lb break="no"/>thing that related to the policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment after the insurrection, it would be more 
     <lb/>
     convenient to discuss when the papers came 
     <lb/>
     down. He proposed now to confine himself 
     <lb/>
     chiefly to those points on which the gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     opposite had made observations in the matter 
     <lb/>
     of his conduct. About mid-summer he had gone 
     <lb/>
     up the Upper Ottawa, and on his return was 
     <lb/>
     about to pay a visit to his own Province, when 
     <lb/>
     he was surprised to receive a note from one of 
     <lb/>
     the Government as to exchanging the office he 
     <lb/>
     then held to that of Secretary of State for the 
     <lb/>
     Provinces. On reference to this particular cir<lb break="no"/>cumstance, he would observe it had been stated 
     <lb/>
     abroad, and not contradicted, that there was 
     <lb/>
     some French conspiracy, some conspiracy, 
     <lb/>
     hatched he did not know exactly where, or by 
     <lb/>
     whom, but hatched in some decree in the inter<lb break="no"/>ests of Lower Canada, and by some gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     who represented that section of the country. 
     <lb/>
     He would now state that the proposal was 
     <lb/>
     made to him by the Minister of Justice, sitting 
     <lb/>
     in the Hon. Mr. McDougall's house, and no one 
     <lb/>
     was present but three persons; and those three 
     <lb/>
     were themselves. There was not in the city a 
     <lb/>
     French member of the Cabinet, save the Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Chapais. Sir George-E. Cartier and the 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Mr. Langevin were in the Lower Prov<lb break="no"/>inces. He did not know whether they were 
     <lb/>
     conversant with the proposition or not. Next 
     <lb/>
     day, going down the river to Montreal, he put 
     <lb/>
     the question to the Minister of Justice. "Do you 
     <lb/>
     really wish me to change office? I have no 
     <lb/>
     desire to change for I am happy enough where 
     <lb/>
     I am." (Laughter.) He further stated to Sir 
     <lb/>
     John A. Macdonald that he desired no change, 
     <lb/>
     but at the same time, was perfectly willing to 
     <lb/>
          
   
           <!-- <p>
     [Hon. Mr. Howe—L'hon. M. Howe.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            
            <pb n="81" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0081.jpg"/>
           <!-- <fw type="dateline">
     21 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
           
     assist the Government in any department they 
     <lb/>
     desired. He also said to Sir John, "I know Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia, New Brunswick, Newfoundland and the 
     <lb/>
     two Provinces of Ontario and Quebec, but what 
     <lb/>
     do I know of the North-West? But if it is wise 
     <lb/>
     for me to act, the best thing I can do is to go to 
     <lb/>
     the country, examine its approaches on every 
     <lb/>
     side, and bring back to the Government that 
     <lb/>
     amount of local and general knowledge which 
     <lb/>
     the Government may require." As a further 
     <lb/>
     evidence of this French conspiracy, Sir John A. 
     <lb/>
     Macdonald had said to him, with a good deal of 
     <lb/>
     earnestness, "I wish you would go." He (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Howe) then asked him if he were at liberty to 
     <lb/>
     discuss this matter with their colleagues? and 
     <lb/>
     Sir John A. Macdonald replied in the affirma<lb break="no"/>tive. He (Mr. Howe) soon ascertained that the 
     <lb/>
     proposal had been made with the knowledge of 
     <lb/>
     the two French members. In the conversation 
     <lb/>
     he (Mr. Howe) had with these two French 
     <lb/>
     gentlemen, they neither attempted to influence 
     <lb/>
     his judgment nor control his free action. He 
     <lb/>
     believed that the statement which had been 
     <lb/>
     made with respect to these two gentlemen was 
     <lb/>
     without the shadow of a foundation. On his 
     <lb/>
     return to Ottawa he put himself in communica<lb break="no"/>tion with Mr. McDougall, finding that the 
     <lb/>
     latter had made up his mind to accept the 
     <lb/>
     office of Lieutenant Governor. He consulted 
     <lb/>
     with Mr. McDougall as to the best way in 
     <lb/>
     which to employ his (Mr. Howe's) summer. 
     <lb/>
     Here he might take occasion to say, with 
     <lb/>
     respect to a certain matter that had been 
     <lb/>
     hinted at, that in one conversation which he 
     <lb/>
     had previous to the acceptance of office by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McDougall, he said to that gentleman, "If I 
     <lb/>
     were younger nothing would gratify my ambi<lb break="no"/>tion more than to go to the North-West, and 
     <lb/>
     there lay the foundation of a great Colony; but 
     <lb/>
     I am twenty years too old, and would not 
     <lb/>
     accept the office." Mr. McDougall knew this 
     <lb/>
     was his (Mr. Howe's) opinion before he accept<lb break="no"/>ed office. Mr. Howe having described the mode 
     <lb/>
     of his journey to the North-West, said that it 
     <lb/>
     had been objected to him that he had not sent 
     <lb/>
     back instructions before Mr. McDougall set 
     <lb/>
     out. The explanation on this head was very 
     <lb/>
     simple. When he got to Abercrombie, which 
     <lb/>
     was 315 miles from Fort Garry, he heard 
     <lb/>
     rumours and reports that the Governor would 
     <lb/>
     not be allowed to enter the Territory. These 
     <lb/>
     rumours were everywhere, even in the streets. 
     <lb/>
     Some young Canadian friends asked him how 
     <lb/>
     he knew that he would be allowed to enter the 
     <lb/>
     country. He said that he would make the 
     <lb/>
     attempt; that the party did not anticipate an 
     <lb/>
     army, but were quite prepared for any small 
     <lb/>
     force. These rumours had spread 315 miles this 
     <lb/>
     side of Fort Garry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="82" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0082.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">82</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">
     February 21, 1870<lb/>
            </fw>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOLT1">Hon. Mr. Bolton</persName>—What date? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName>—About the 1st of October. 
     <lb/>
     On the way to Fort Garry there was no 
     <lb/>
     obstruction; there was nothing but courtesy 
     <lb/>
     and rough hospitality. At the end of twenty 
     <lb/>
     days they got to Fort Garry. There he received 
     <lb/>
     three invitations to take up his quarters, one 
     <lb/>
     from Governor McTavish, one from Dr. Schultz 
     <lb/>
     and another from the Bishop of Rupert's Land. 
     <lb/>
     But he preferred to go to the hotel, and be at 
     <lb/>
     liberty to see every one and learn what he 
     <lb/>
     could. Here he had been accused of uttering all 
     <lb/>
     sorts of treason in some mysterious way. That 
     <lb/>
     was simply impossible. There was but one 
     <lb/>
     parlor in the hotel, shared by Mr. Turner and 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Sandford, with himself. People were 
     <lb/>
     coming and going, and he could have had but 
     <lb/>
     little private conversation, nine out of ten 
     <lb/>
     times these two gentlemen being present when 
     <lb/>
     he was in company with any one, and heard 
     <lb/>
     every word he spoke. What he said might have 
     <lb/>
     been said on the street. He believed it to be his 
     <lb/>
     first duty to call on Governor McTavish, but he 
     <lb/>
     found he had been attacked with haemorrhage 
     <lb/>
     of the lungs. He then addressed himself to get 
     <lb/>
     such information as he could; went to the 
     <lb/>
     Seminary of St. Boniface, visited their schools 
     <lb/>
     and generally put himself in communication 
     <lb/>
     with the leading men as far as he could ascer<lb break="no"/>tain them. He had been requested to make 
     <lb/>
     speeches to the people but he felt that it would 
     <lb/>
     be neither proper to do so in consideration of 
     <lb/>
     the position of Governor McTavish on the one 
     <lb/>
     hand, or of the incoming Governor McDougall. 
     <lb/>
     He had stated that the new Governor would be 
     <lb/>
     into the country in a week or two and that 
     <lb/>
     when Governor McTavish had laid down his 
     <lb/>
     authority, the new Governor would declare 
     <lb/>
     what the policy was to be. Mr. Alcock, who was 
     <lb/>
     there, invited him to drive with him, and he 
     <lb/>
     had done so. He visited the Bishop of Rupert's 
     <lb/>
     Land, Dr. McCrae, Arch-deacon McLean, Rev. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Black, Presbyterian Minister, and Judge 
     <lb/>
     Black, all leading and highly respectable men, 
     <lb/>
     and there was not much opportunity of speak<lb break="no"/>ing treason to them. He denied that there had 
     <lb/>
     been on his part either treasonable utterances 
     <lb/>
     or absurd chaff. That would have been simply 
     <lb/>
     foolish. When he visited Captain Kennedy, he 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Howe) and Turner, and Sandford 
     <lb/>
     occupied the same room for nearly all the time 
     <lb/>
     during the visit. Kennedy and Turner went out 
     <lb/>
     for some business transactions, and he (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Howe) was in conversation with the lady of 
     <lb/>
     the house, a woman of intelligence, and kind 
     <lb/>
     and hospitable manner. She generally passed 
     <lb/>
     in and out, getting dinner ready for them, and 
     <lb/>
           
   
          <!--  <p>
     [Hon. Mr. Howe—L'hon. M. Howe] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
           
            <pb n="83" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0083.jpg"/>
           <!-- <fw type="dateline">
     21 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
          
     he occasionally exchanged some observations 
     <lb/>
     with her. When Kennedy and Turner returned, 
     <lb/>
     they all sat down to dinner and after that they 
     <lb/>
     exchanged a few general observations. That 
     <lb/>
     was all the talk they had. Alcock and he parted 
     <lb/>
     good friends, and that was all he (Mr. Howe) 
     <lb/>
     knew of the matter. The hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Lambton had taken him to task for abusing the 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi> newspaper. He did not desire to abuse 
     <lb/>
     the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi> or any other newspaper, because he 
     <lb/>
     was too old a newspaper man himself to take 
     <lb/>
     up that course. But he would say this, that 
     <lb/>
     when he was in the house of Captain Kennedy, 
     <lb/>
     and when the subject of how the territory was 
     <lb/>
     to be governed, and how Canada was about to 
     <lb/>
     act, and what were the instructions of Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McDougall, and what he would do when he 
     <lb/>
     came into the territory, he (Mr. Howe) did 
     <lb/>
     there, as he did everywhere—he defended what 
     <lb/>
     was to be the policy of Canada in the most 
     <lb/>
     open and undisguised manner. And when he 
     <lb/>
     defended, as he was bound to do, the incoming 
     <lb/>
     Governor, against the charges and insinua<lb break="no"/>tions, and doubts, and apprehensions thrown 
     <lb/>
     out against him, when he did that what was 
     <lb/>
     the answer? He was referred to Mr. Brown's 
     <lb/>
     editorial as an evidence of the fact that he had 
     <lb/>
     said that Canada would send men in there to 
     <lb/>
     ride roughshod over the country; that the man 
     <lb/>
     who was sent was unfit on account of his 
     <lb/>
     political conduct, and was to bring with him 
     <lb/>
     instructions and men who would set at naught 
     <lb/>
     the rights and disregard the feelings of the 
     <lb/>
     people. When he found the state of public opin<lb break="no"/>ion in the district he ascertained that a number 
     <lb/>
     of Canadians had been sent out there in the 
     <lb/>
     public service, and had been there for some 
     <lb/>
     time, and certainly had not made any report 
     <lb/>
     regarding the state of feeling. When he left 
     <lb/>
     Ottawa, there was no report that would have 
     <lb/>
     led the government for a single moment to 
     <lb/>
     suppose that there was any dissatisfaction out 
     <lb/>
     there at the course government was taking. 
     <lb/>
     But when he (Mr. Howe) got into the country 
     <lb/>
     he saw there was a good deal the government 
     <lb/>
     had to learn. In the first place the English 
     <lb/>
     parts of the population were uneasy and dissat<lb break="no"/>isfied, and were discussing the matter among 
     <lb/>
     themselves. He believed the difficulties origi<lb break="no"/>nated, in the first instance, from the discus<lb break="no"/>sions by the English parts of the population, 
     <lb/>
     (hear, hear). And the ground they took was 
     <lb/>
     that they had never been consulted on the 
     <lb/>
     arrangements. They entertained fears and 
     <lb/>
     apprehensions with regard to the instructions 
     <lb/>
     given for the management of the country, that 
     <lb/>
     their rights would be to a great extent ignored. 
     <lb/>
     With regard to the French part of the popula<lb break="no"/>tion, the public grounds taken by the English 
     <lb/>
     people were widened by personal complaints, 
     <lb/>
     which, up to that time, he had never heard. But 
     <lb/>
     there was another element in the difficulty, 
     <lb/>

            <pb n="84" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0084.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">84</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 21, 1870<lb/></fw>
                 
     and it was one which, even if the Government 
     <lb/>
     had known of it, they could not have prevented 
     <lb/>
     it. Out in that country the Hudson's Bay Com<lb break="no"/>pany has something like one hundred posts 
     <lb/>
     scattered all over, and almost every one of 
     <lb/>
     these stations is worked by a hard headed 
     <lb/>
     Scotchman, (laughter). There are chief factors, 
     <lb/>
     chief traders, there is a management in London 
     <lb/>
     and a management at Red River, and every 
     <lb/>
     summer at Norway House, at Lake Winnipeg, 
     <lb/>
     representatives of the hundred posts, assemble 
     <lb/>
     and hold a regular Parliament of their own, 
     <lb/>
     and discuss matters and make arrangements 
     <lb/>
     for the following year. These men have large 
     <lb/>
     interests in the territory and in the property of 
     <lb/>
     the Company, and there was a feeling of dis<lb break="no"/>satisfaction among them. He had every reason 
     <lb/>
     to believe that there was a feeling of great 
     <lb/>
     uneasiness among the resident employees of 
     <lb/>
     the Hudson's Bay Company, or among a very 
     <lb/>
     large portion of them, and he believed that 
     <lb/>
     they thought the directors and managers in 
     <lb/>
     London, to whom the £300,000 was to be given, 
     <lb/>
     would divide it among themselves exclusively, 
     <lb/>
     which they feared would work great wrong to 
     <lb/>
     them, for some of the men. He was not pre<lb break="no"/>pared to say how many believed that they had 
     <lb/>
     fair and just claims to a portion of the pur<lb break="no"/>chase money. It was clear, first, that the Eng<lb break="no"/>lish-speaking people were uneasy respecting 
     <lb/>
     the basis of their representation; it was equally 
     <lb/>
     clear the French people were apprehensive 
     <lb/>
     upon the grounds which touched the personal 
     <lb/>
     history of the gentleman who was coming to 
     <lb/>
     govern them, and it was equally clear that an 
     <lb/>
     uneasy feeling prevailed among the Hudson's 
     <lb/>
     Bay Company's people themselves. After all, 
     <lb/>
     the House would naturally inquire if all this 
     <lb/>
     were so, why didn't he take some pains to 
     <lb/>
     remove these impressions? (Hear, hear). He 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Howe) took all the pains in his power to 
     <lb/>
     do so. He was all the time with leaders of 
     <lb/>
     society, as far as possible, and by personal 
     <lb/>
     explanations he endeavoured to remove these 
     <lb/>
     impressions; and it was only fair to say that 
     <lb/>
     when he left Winnipeg, there was not the 
     <lb/>
     slightest murmur which would lead him to 
     <lb/>
     believe that any armed opposition would be 
     <lb/>
     presented. On the contrary—and he called the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the leader of the Government, and 
     <lb/>
     the leader of the opposition, and other gentle<lb break="no"/>men on that side of the House, to the statement 
     <lb/>
     that when he left Winnipeg Governor McTav<lb break="no"/>ish was about to summon a Council, in order to 
     <lb/>
     prepare an address of welcome to present to 
     <lb/>
     Mr. McDougall, and when he left Winnipeg he 
     <lb/>
     was under the impression that that, in all prob<lb break="no"/>ability, would be done. How could he (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Howe) be expected to convey to Mr. McDougall 
     <lb/>
     any other impression than the general rumors 
     <lb/>
     and reports, and complaints which had reached 
     <lb/>
     him, and which he believed would be very soon 
     <lb/>
          
   
           <!-- <p>
     [Hon. Mr. Howe—L'hon. M. Howe.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            <pb n="85" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0085.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     21 février 1870 DÉBATES DES COMMUNES 85 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
          
     dissipated by Mr. McDougall's own conduct 
     <lb/>
     and explanations when he once got into the 
     <lb/>
     Territory. Hon. gentlemen opposite would 
     <lb/>
     allow him to say that one of his objects in 
     <lb/>
     going to Fort Garry was to get information for 
     <lb/>
     the use of the Government, and for his own use 
     <lb/>
     when he returned. He had no written instruc<lb break="no"/>tions, and was not to do any particular thing, 
     <lb/>
     but was left to his own guidance to collect such 
     <lb/>
     information as would be likely to be valuable 
     <lb/>
     to government. He must say that Governor 
     <lb/>
     McTavish had met him in the most friendly 
     <lb/>
     way, and had placed in his hand the records of 
     <lb/>
     the old Council of that country, and these he 
     <lb/>
     had studied for two days. He procured and 
     <lb/>
     brought home for the use of the Minister of 
     <lb/>
     Justice a copy of the laws as they existed in 
     <lb/>
     that Territory, that Government might know 
     <lb/>
     the laws to which the people were accustomed. 
     <lb/>
     He also obtained a list of names of old council<lb break="no"/>lors, so that Government might know in 
     <lb/>
     making appointments how to select men of 
     <lb/>
     experience in whom confidence had been 
     <lb/>
     reposed already. He discharged his trust faith<lb break="no"/>fully and honourably, and did all any man 
     <lb/>
     could to quiet the difficulties. He met McDou<lb break="no"/>gall in the open prairie, when a cold north-east 
     <lb/>
     wind was blowing. Fortunately he (Mr. Howe) 
     <lb/>
     was travelling with the wind on his back, but 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member for North Lanark had the 
     <lb/>
     wind in his face—as with his family of chil<lb break="no"/>dren he travelled—he had to face the storm. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">A Member</persName>—It has been in his face ever 
     <lb/>
     since. (A laugh.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName>—If hon. gentlemen had been 
     <lb/>
     on the open prairie that bitter morning, he 
     <lb/>
     thought they would not have been exceedingly 
     <lb/>
     anxious to hold communication with any one; 
     <lb/>
     and when there were women and children con<lb break="no"/>cerned, it would have been barbarous to have 
     <lb/>
     stopped the cavalcade. Therefore, they merely 
     <lb/>
     exchanged a few greetings and passed on. Now, 
     <lb/>
     looking back at all that he had done, he was 
     <lb/>
     not conscious that they could have made it 
     <lb/>
     much better if they had stopped for an hour or 
     <lb/>
     two and held consultation. He could merely 
     <lb/>
     have made a few general observations about 
     <lb/>
     the rumors he had heard, and the last he knew 
     <lb/>
     was that a council was to be summoned to 
     <lb/>
     prepare an address of welcome to Mr. McDou<lb break="no"/>gall on his arrival. Therefore he passed on, 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="86" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0086.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">86</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 21, 1870<lb/></fw>
                    
     after giving him (Mr. McDougall) a hint or two 
     <lb/>
     upon one or two topics, which he thought it 
     <lb/>
     would be better for him to avoid. With these 
     <lb/>
     explanations he would leave the matter with 
     <lb/>
     the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName> desired to make a few 
     <lb/>
     remarks in reply to the honourable Secretary 
     <lb/>
     of State, who had, he thought, very properly 
     <lb/>
     abstained from any observations on the gener<lb break="no"/>al subject, but had confined himself to what 
     <lb/>
     appeared to be in his mind, an answer to some 
     <lb/>
     charges that have been made against his con<lb break="no"/>duct in the North-West Territory. He (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McDougall) saw no necessity on his part to 
     <lb/>
     offer any observations to the House on any<lb break="no"/>thing that had fallen from the honourable gen<lb break="no"/>tleman except that he felt it his duty to him, 
     <lb/>
     the Government and the country to state that 
     <lb/>
     having ascertained or heard of certain state<lb break="no"/>ments and conversations which the honourable 
     <lb/>
     gentleman had indulged in, in that country, 
     <lb/>
     and having met with a good deal of difficulty, 
     <lb/>
     as he then believed, and still believed, on 
     <lb/>
     account of the injudicious statements—to call 
     <lb/>
     them no harsher name—of the honourable gen<lb break="no"/>tleman there, he had spoken freely on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject to members of the press who had com<lb break="no"/>mented on them, and he therefore felt 
     <lb/>
     constrained to make a few observations to the 
     <lb/>
     House and would endeavour to convey simply 
     <lb/>
     what he had learned from the friends as well as 
     <lb/>
     the enemies of Canada in that territory. The 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentleman opposite by his own confession 
     <lb/>
     did very little to smooth the way for the intro<lb break="no"/>duction of Canadian authority and his own 
     <lb/>
     representative. He (Mr. Howe) had stated that 
     <lb/>
     he found a very uneasy state of feeling among 
     <lb/>
     the English and Scotch portion of the popula<lb break="no"/>tion; that they had grave doubts as to the 
     <lb/>
     nature of the Government to be imposed upon 
     <lb/>
     them; and he had stated that he endeavoured to 
     <lb/>
     remove those feelings. He stated also that he 
     <lb/>
     had found great dissatisfaction among the 
     <lb/>
     employees of the Hudson Bay Company, 
     <lb/>
     against which they had complaints to make, 
     <lb/>
     and that they thought the officers to be intro<lb break="no"/>duced by the Canadian Government would 
     <lb/>
     interfere with their privileges and profits. He 
     <lb/>
     had gone on to say that among the French 
     <lb/>
     half-breeds there was some uneasiness, and 
     <lb/>
     from what he (Mr. McDougall) gathered, he 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Howe) wished to convey that they were 
     <lb/>
     opposed to the person who had been appointed 
     <lb/>
     to govern them. He thought the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Howe) had treated him rather cruelly in 
     <lb/>
     not telling him of this state of affairs when 
     <lb/>
     they had met on the prairie, even if he was 
     <lb/>
          
   
           <!-- <p>
     [Hon. Mr. Howe—L'hon, M. Howe.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            <pb n="87" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0087.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     21 février 1870 DÉBATES DES COMMUNES 87 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
           
     facing a storm. He was sure he should have 
     <lb/>
     been most happy to have turned back to hear 
     <lb/>
     his news, (hear, hear). The hon. gentleman, if 
     <lb/>
     he had so desired, had ample opportunity to 
     <lb/>
     state these facts, but instead of so doing he had 
     <lb/>
     spoken of the soil and the climate. The former 
     <lb/>
     he said was excellent, but the latter was execr<lb break="no"/>able. He had not felt warm for three weeks 
     <lb/>
     (laughter). This was the burden of the conver<lb break="no"/>sation he indulged in, and he (Mr. McDougall) 
     <lb/>
     was so amused at finding he had nothing to 
     <lb/>
     combat but the climate that he indulged in a 
     <lb/>
     little badinage against the hon. gentleman, who 
     <lb/>
     complained that he had had to float across a 
     <lb/>
     river through the ice, and averred that a coun<lb break="no"/>try where this had to be done in the middle of 
     <lb/>
     October was not fit for a white man to live in. 
     <lb/>
     He (Mr. McDougall) had recalled to the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman's recollection that this sometimes 
     <lb/>
     happened on the St. Lawrence at Quebec at the 
     <lb/>
     same time of the year, and chatted and ban<lb break="no"/>tered with him for some time defending the 
     <lb/>
     country till the people in the carts poked out 
     <lb/>
     their heads to listen to the conversation. At 
     <lb/>
     last he said to him "then you do not envy me 
     <lb/>
     my position" and he replied, "no, upon my soul 
     <lb/>
     I don't" (great laughter). The hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     had also failed to write him (Mr. McDougall) 
     <lb/>
     from Fort Abercrombie as he had promised. 
     <lb/>
     The letter received from him was dated St. 
     <lb/>
     Paul's and did not reach him till weeks after<lb break="no"/>wards. After the admission made by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman as to what he found in the country 
     <lb/>
     it was surely his duty to tell him of the dif<lb break="no"/>ficulties he was to meet instead of warning 
     <lb/>
     him of the terrors of the climate (hear, hear). 
     <lb/>
     In order to prevent any misunderstanding that 
     <lb/>
     might arise from hasty words in this dispute he 
     <lb/>
     thought it well to read an extract from a letter 
     <lb/>
     which he wrote from Pembina to a member of 
     <lb/>
     the Government. He had written this letter 
     <lb/>
     quite deliberately, and upon what he deemed 
     <lb/>
     sufficient information. After some preliminary 
     <lb/>
     sentences which it was not necessary to read, 
     <lb/>
     he wrote as follows: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "Laross Farm, Pembina, Nov. 13 1869. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I enclose extracts from two letters received 
     <lb/>
     the night before last, from Fort Garry. I send 
     <lb/>
     them confidentially because they were written 
     <lb/>
     under that protection and because they may 
     <lb/>
     not be agreable to our friend from Nova Scotia. 
     <lb/>
     You will I know give me credit for sufficient 
     <lb/>
     coolness and distrust of other people's impres<lb break="no"/>sions to scrutinize before I believe, and to be 
     <lb/>
     tolerably sure before I act, but it is unfortunate 
     <lb/>
     to say the least, that Mr. Howe's remarks when 
     <lb/>
     here, have been interpreted in the same sense 
     <lb/>
     by the enemies as by the friends of Canada. I 
     <lb/>
     differ from him entirely as to his estimate of 
     <lb/>
     the soil and climate and capabilities of this 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="88" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0088.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">88</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 21, 1870<lb/></fw>
                     
     country—from all I see, as well as from all I 
     <lb/>
     hear. The Red River, a sluggish stream, is not 
     <lb/>
     frozen over except at a few points, and at these 
     <lb/>
     it would be dangerous for a grown man to 
     <lb/>
     cross. It is raining as I write (Nov. 13) and the 
     <lb/>
     cattle still feed on the Prairie. Our horses 
     <lb/>
     which were jaded and thin when we arrived 
     <lb/>
     here, and have had nothing to eat but Prairie 
     <lb/>
     hay—cured at the proper season—are now in 
     <lb/>
     fair condition to start upon another journey. 
     <lb/>
     These facts are better than speculations and 
     <lb/>
     will carry more weight with those who know 
     <lb/>
     how to weigh them, than rhetorical flourishes." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     He (Mr. McDougall) had written thus, 
     <lb/>
     because he knew from the views expressed by 
     <lb/>
     the Honourable Secretary of State that he 
     <lb/>
     would return to Canada and endeavour to 
     <lb/>
     depreciate the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     "What Mr. Howe may have said to the mal<lb break="no"/>contents, I of course do not know, but from his 
     <lb/>
     remarks to me on the Prairie when we met I 
     <lb/>
     infer that he disapproved of the ardour of the 
     <lb/>
     friends of Canada in the settlement and 
     <lb/>
     excused the hostility of those who are now its 
     <lb/>
     armed enemies. He did this, I have no doubt 
     <lb/>
     conscientiously, and without perhaps reflect<lb break="no"/>ing upon the use that would soon be made of 
     <lb/>
     his expressions. The Canadian Government 
     <lb/>
     and Canadians have done nothing to injure 
     <lb/>
     these people, but everything to benefit them. 
     <lb/>
     They helped to save them from starvation-<lb/> gave them good wages for their labor—and by 
     <lb/>
     competition in trade and farming enabled them 
     <lb/>
     to obtain both food and clothing in greater 
     <lb/>
     quantities and at lower prices than before. 
     <lb/>
     They cannot specify a single grievance against 
     <lb/>
     Canada in the past, and I have not heard of one 
     <lb/>
     that they apprehend in the future except, that 
     <lb/>
     they—three or four thousand serfs of yester<lb break="no"/>day—will not be entrusted with the govern<lb break="no"/>ment and destiny of a third of the American 
     <lb/>
     continent! What ground exists for sympathy 
     <lb/>
     with them in such a case I am unable to per<lb break="no"/>ceive, or why those who have advocated the 
     <lb/>
     claims and defended the flag of Canada, and 
     <lb/>
     who are now ready to risk their lives for us, 
     <lb/>
     should be repulsed, and those who are leagued 
     <lb/>
     with Yankee sympathisers and foreign Jesuits 
     <lb/>
     to resist the authority of the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and, if need be, murder its representa<lb break="no"/>tives, excused and encouraged, I cannot discov<lb break="no"/>er. I write thus strongly because I feel that the 
     <lb/>
     thoughtlessness and spleen, and thin blood, 
     <lb/>
     and inability to forget recent personal antece<lb break="no"/>dents and declarations of your missionary, 
     <lb/>
     have put obstacles in my way—the magnitude 
     <lb/>
   
            <!--<p>
     [Hon. Mr. McDougall—L'hon. M. McDougall.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            <pb n="89" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0089.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     21 février 1870 DÉBATES DES COMMUNES 89 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
           
     and gravity of which you will appreciate as 
     <lb/>
     events develop themselves—and who, as far as 
     <lb/>
     I can learn, did nothing and said nothing, but 
     <lb/>
     flatly refused to do anything or say anything 
     <lb/>
     on behalf of Canada, its policy, or its 
     <lb/>
     representatives. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     This is the report that reaches me, and I have 
     <lb/>
     no evidence to the contrary. Indeed, Mr. Howe 
     <lb/>
     told me himself that he had said nothing and 
     <lb/>
     promised nothing on my behalf, except that I 
     <lb/>
     would deal justly with all interests. In one 
     <lb/>
     sense this was prudent; in another—and in the 
     <lb/>
     presence of a conspiracy known to be on foot<lb break="no"/>reticence by a high functionary from Canada 
     <lb/>
     was as mistaken and as fatal to the cause of 
     <lb/>
     order, as the silence of the local authorities, 
     <lb/>
     who are believed by the rebels to be on their 
     <lb/>
     side . . . 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     You may show this to Sir George and Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Tilley, but I wish it to be considered confiden<lb break="no"/>tial. Understand my remarks about Mr. Howe 
     <lb/>
     are not inspired by any ill-feeling or sinister 
     <lb/>
     motive of any kind. I have always had a strong 
     <lb/>
     regard for him politically and personally, but 
     <lb/>
     he has blundered awfully (more than once). 
     <lb/>
     This time, I am the victim and do not experi<lb break="no"/>ence pleasurable sensations at the prospect." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     He remarked that in a portion of the conver<lb break="no"/>sation he had with Mr. Howe on the prairie 
     <lb/>
     there were some very strong hints against the 
     <lb/>
     conduct of friends of Canada in the territory. 
     <lb/>
     But recalling his experience of events there, 
     <lb/>
     and after hearing the statements made in vari<lb break="no"/>ous quarters as to the course pursued by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Howe, he had nothing to alter, nothing to abate 
     <lb/>
     from the views expressed in that letter. It 
     <lb/>
     seemed to him the' honourable gentleman 
     <lb/>
     might very easily, under the circumstances, 
     <lb/>
     have paved the way for the entry of the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian Representative. Instead of that he 
     <lb/>
     was in communication with, and visited the 
     <lb/>
     Bannatynes, the McKennies, the Kennedy's, 
     <lb/>
     the very men who are now in rebellion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName>—I never was at the houses 
     <lb/>
     of either Bannatyne or McKenny. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName> Understood the honourable 
     <lb/>
     gentleman to say that he had been at Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Kennedy's? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCDO7">Hon. Mr. McDougall</persName> said that he understood 
     <lb/>
     that the British flag had been raised over the 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="90" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0090.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">90</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 21, 1870<lb/></fw>
        
        
     residence of a Canadian at Fort Garry in 
     <lb/>
     honour of the arrival of a member of the 
     <lb/>
     Canadian Government, and that the honour<lb break="no"/>able gentleman had denounced those who had 
     <lb/>
     raised that flag and wished that it should be 
     <lb/>
     pulled down. It did not appear to him that this 
     <lb/>
     was the spirit which ought to have been dis<lb break="no"/>played by the honourable gentleman if he was 
     <lb/>
     loyal, and anxious to promote the policy of the 
     <lb/>
     government of Canada. He might have taken 
     <lb/>
     some opportunity as a public man, a man who 
     <lb/>
     was master of our language, to inform those 
     <lb/>
     people of the boon that was about to be con<lb break="no"/>ferred upon them. If the honourable gentleman 
     <lb/>
     deemed it necessary, for his own justification, 
     <lb/>
     he (Mr. McDougall) trusted that the House 
     <lb/>
     would grant a committee and that the matter 
     <lb/>
     would be enquired into, that it might be ascer<lb break="no"/>tained whether a member of the government 
     <lb/>
     had gone out to that country and added fuel to 
     <lb/>
     the flame. The people there know the history of 
     <lb/>
     this and they knew what impelled him to 
     <lb/>
     change his seat from one side of the house to 
     <lb/>
     the other, and they pointed to him and said 
     <lb/>
     "are we to be treated in any other way than 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia? Nova Scotia was on the point of 
     <lb/>
     rebellion, shall we not carry out the same 
     <lb/>
     plan?" And the honourable gentleman said "go 
     <lb/>
     ahead—you are quire right," and they did go 
     <lb/>
     ahead and barricaded the road and sent word 
     <lb/>
     that he (Mr. McDougall) was not to enter the 
     <lb/>
     territory. The leaders of the rebellion there are, 
     <lb/>
     he had every reason to believe, from uncon<lb break="no"/>tradicted reports from all parts, confidently 
     <lb/>
     relying upon the support of that honourable 
     <lb/>
     gentleman in his seat, and some of those who 
     <lb/>
     sit beside him. It was that which caused them 
     <lb/>
     to go to such extremes to imprison Canadians, 
     <lb/>
     to imprison poor Mrs. Schultz, and to refuse to 
     <lb/>
     allow her husband, or Dr. Macdonald, who was 
     <lb/>
     also a prisoner and a man of skill, to see her. It 
     <lb/>
     was that that emboldened them, in their inhu<lb break="no"/>man treatment of loyal men who were driven 
     <lb/>
     out of the territory in the depth of winter to 
     <lb/>
     perish on the plains, (hear, hear). He, (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McDougall), while the hon. gentleman was 
     <lb/>
     speaking, had received a letter from Mr. Pro<lb break="no"/>vencher, who is still at Pembina, and this was 
     <lb/>
     what he said: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "Pembina, February 3, 1870. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Sir,—According to the last information 
     <lb/>
     received here, the position is very critical at 
     <lb/>
     Fort Garry, Riel is more powerful than ever, 
     <lb/>
     and his orders are the only laws enforced. 
     <lb/>
     Nobody is allowed to go out of the Fort without 
     <lb/>
     his permission, and when he is absent or 
     <lb/>
     engaged, they must wait. The council are now 
     <lb/>
     discussing with Mr. Smith the new "Bill of 
     <lb/>
           
   
         <!--   <p>
     [Hon Mr. McDougall—L'hon. M. McDougall.] 
     <lb/></p>-->
          
            <pb n="91" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0091.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     21 février 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
         
     Rights," composed of twenty articles, and in 
     <lb/>
     the interest of the freedom of speech, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smith is kept prisoner. So is Salaberry; but for 
     <lb/>
     what reason, I dont't know, perhaps as a hos<lb break="no"/>tage. I believe that the discussion will last 
     <lb/>
     perhaps two or three weeks more. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The soldiers are more numerous than ever, 
     <lb/>
     mostly living on pemican, tea, sugar and rum 
     <lb/>
     taken from the stores of Schultz and the Com<lb break="no"/>pany. No more talk about the pledge. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     It can be interesting for you to know that the 
     <lb/>
     gate at Fort Garry is guarded by an American 
     <lb/>
     citizen, and that two other American citizens 
     <lb/>
     were sent after Schultz to re-arrest him (with<lb break="no"/>out success). So much for the neutrality laws." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     He continued to say that the action of the 
     <lb/>
     rebels, or malcontents, or whatever they might 
     <lb/>
     be called, had, from the beginning to the end, 
     <lb/>
     been caused by the fact that they had been 
     <lb/>
     sustained in it; that they had been encouraged 
     <lb/>
     to enforce their demands by driving him, and 
     <lb/>
     every man who was supposed to be desirous of 
     <lb/>
     assisting in supporting the Dominion of 
     <lb/>
     Canada, out of the territory, by the belief that 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman opposite would sustain 
     <lb/>
     them in their line of action. It was for the 
     <lb/>
     country to say whether he (Mr. McDougall) 
     <lb/>
     who, he thought, it would be acknowledged, 
     <lb/>
     had made considerable sacrifices in his efforts 
     <lb/>
     to secure the union of all the Provinces, had 
     <lb/>
     been sustained by the hon. gentleman in bring<lb break="no"/>ing this territory peaceably and amicably into 
     <lb/>
     the Confederation. He had very serious doubts 
     <lb/>
     on the subject. He had nothing to complain of 
     <lb/>
     in the conduct of the other members of the 
     <lb/>
     Government. He looked back with the greatest 
     <lb/>
     satisfaction to his connection with the hon. 
     <lb/>
     gentleman at the head of the Government, and 
     <lb/>
     the Hon. Minister of Militia, who sat beside 
     <lb/>
     him, especially the latter gentleman, with 
     <lb/>
     whom he had been to England on a mission of 
     <lb/>
     serious importance. Circumstances coccurred 
     <lb/>
     there, and kindness was shown which he 
     <lb/>
     would never forget. He would always look 
     <lb/>
     upon him as a personal friend whom it would 
     <lb/>
     please him to serve. But on the whole he took it 
     <lb/>
     that it was not such a Government, such a 
     <lb/>
     combination as is best fitted to deal with the 
     <lb/>
     great question now before the House. He trust<lb break="no"/>ed the House would have a better opportunity, 
     <lb/>
     under more favorable circumstances, of dis<lb break="no"/>cussing this matter when the papers were 
     <lb/>
     brought down. He did not know whether the 
     <lb/>
     Government intended to bring down all the 
     <lb/>
     papers. He took the liberty of making the 
     <lb/>
     observation now that in the interests of the 
     <lb/>
     public it would be well that the hon. gentlemen 
     <lb/>
     should look carefully at the nature of the docu<lb break="no"/>ments before sending them to the House as 
     <lb/>
           
            <pb n="92" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0092.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">92</fw>
            <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">
     February 21 , 1870 
     <lb/>
            </fw>
     
     there was this difficulty, that in getting infor<lb break="no"/>mation as well as he could for the government, 
     <lb/>
     it was necessary to mention names and per<lb break="no"/>sons. If the fact of these persons having 
     <lb/>
     informed and assisted the government, should 
     <lb/>
     reach the territory, their lives and property 
     <lb/>
     would be endangered. He had offered to one of 
     <lb/>
     the members of the government, to look over 
     <lb/>
     the papers in the most friendly spirit, with a 
     <lb/>
     view to prevent any injury to any individual in 
     <lb/>
     the territory, on account of the exposure of 
     <lb/>
     their conduct in the premises. He trusted this 
     <lb/>
     would be done. All the papers could be placed 
     <lb/>
     upon the table without mentioning names or 
     <lb/>
     involving any one. When the papers were on 
     <lb/>
     the table, the whole matter could be discussed. 
     <lb/>
     His conduct had been discussed and assailed 
     <lb/>
     by the public press, but he was not so thin- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     skinned and could wait better than his friend 
     <lb/>
     opposite, who, it was known, had made great 
     <lb/>
     blunders before, and he thought it would 
     <lb/>
     appear had done so in this case. (Hear, hear.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName> said he had heard for the 
     <lb/>
     first time the letter which the member for 
     <lb/>
     Lanark had read with reference to himself. It 
     <lb/>
     appeared it was to be shown to his two col<lb break="no"/>leagues, but not to him. When the papers were 
     <lb/>
     laid before the House it would appear why the 
     <lb/>
     people of Red River, stung with madness, 
     <lb/>
     imprisoned every Canadian they could find. 
     <lb/>
     They would find the reason in that honourable 
     <lb/>
     gentleman's own handwriting. If Canadian 
     <lb/>
     people up there were not murdered it was to be 
     <lb/>
     wondered at, in view of the documents that the 
     <lb/>
     honourable gentleman had the hardihood and 
     <lb/>
     audacity to publish in that country. That hon<lb break="no"/>ourable gentleman very kindly offered to sit 
     <lb/>
     down with members of the Government, and 
     <lb/>
     select from among the papers those which 
     <lb/>
     should be brought down. No doubt that gentle<lb break="no"/>man would be glad to do that, but the House 
     <lb/>
     should be in possession of full information. 
     <lb/>
     The honourable gentleman said he (Mr. Howe) 
     <lb/>
     objected to a flag with Canada on it hoisted. 
     <lb/>
     Yes he did object to it. Long before he reached 
     <lb/>
     Red River he heard of an individual who was 
     <lb/>
     putting himself forward as a friend and repre<lb break="no"/>sentative of Canada. He learnt from Canadians 
     <lb/>
     on the way up the character of that individual; 
     <lb/>
     and when he got up there that individual hoist<lb break="no"/>ed a flag on his chimney. But he (Mr. Howe) 
     <lb/>
     felt not the slightest desire to fraternize with 
     <lb/>
     him. The member for Lanark knew well that 
     <lb/>
     one of the people he sent into the country, not 
     <lb/>
     content with attending to the duty with which 
     <lb/>
     he was charged, had written home to Canada 
     <lb/>
     language grossly insulting to the women of a 
     <lb/>
     large majority of the population of the North- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     West, that had created so deep a feeling of 
     <lb/>
     indignation, that one of the half-breed ladies-<lb/>
          
            
<!--<p>[Hon. Mr. McDougall—L'hon. M. McDougall.] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
            
            <pb n="93" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0093.jpg"/>
            <!--<fw type="dateline">
     21 février 1870 DÉBATES DES COMMUNES 93 
     <lb/>
            </fw>-->
            
     as much a lady as one could expect in that 
     <lb/>
     place—had turned that individual out of her 
     <lb/>
     house, and slapped his face. The hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for Lanark wrote a public despatch calling the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the Government to those charges 
     <lb/>
     against his colleagues and friends. When the 
     <lb/>
     papers were brought down, he (Mr. Howe) 
     <lb/>
     would be prepared to justify not only all he 
     <lb/>
     had stated, but all public documents to which 
     <lb/>
     he had put his hand. The member for Lanark 
     <lb/>
     had said that he (Mr. Howe) told the people of 
     <lb/>
     Red River to go ahead. He denied this, and said 
     <lb/>
     that he had not used a single expression, while 
     <lb/>
     in the territory, that could properly be con<lb break="no"/>sidered an instigation to insurrection. When 
     <lb/>
     they came to discuss the whole question, it 
     <lb/>
     might be his duty to show to the House that 
     <lb/>
     the cause of the difficulties with which they 
     <lb/>
     had to contend was more or less attributed to 
     <lb/>
     the gentleman selected as Lieutenant Gover<lb break="no"/>nor. He did not know of this till he got to the 
     <lb/>
     territory, but the honourable gentleman would 
     <lb/>
     find that there were certainly as many person<lb break="no"/>al objections to him as he could rake up with 
     <lb/>
     reference to him (Honourable Mr. Howe). The 
     <lb/>
     people of Red River should be governed the 
     <lb/>
     same as the people of Ontario and Quebec, by 
     <lb/>
     their minds (cheers from both sides). If we 
     <lb/>
     could not do that then he would say abandon 
     <lb/>
     the country, and let grass grow over the prai<lb break="no"/>ries, and the wild animals roam in the woods. 
     <lb/>
     Let us not go hence to shed human blood for 
     <lb/>
     the purpose of showing that a great Reformer 
     <lb/>
     from Canada—a great stalking horse of a Grit 
     <lb/>
     (laughter), in the absurd spirit of a tyrant, 
     <lb/>
     desired to grasp the power of a dictator. Read 
     <lb/>
     the documents when they come down and 
     <lb/>
     judge for yourselves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName> desired to say a few words, not 
     <lb/>
     upon the policy of the Government in regard to 
     <lb/>
     Red River, but as to the sufficiency or insuffi<lb break="no"/>ciency of the personal explanations that had 
     <lb/>
     been made. He was willing to believe that 
     <lb/>
     when the Hon. Secretary for the Provinces 
     <lb/>
     consented to accept that office with the condi<lb break="no"/>tion of a visit to Red River, that he was not 
     <lb/>
     aware of dissatisfaction existing in the Territo<lb break="no"/>ry. Otherwise he would have been a most 
     <lb/>
     improper person to go upon a public mission to 
     <lb/>
     conciliate those people, seeing that he himself 
     <lb/>
     furnished a living example of the good results 
     <lb/>
     of persistent and almost violent opposition. 
     <lb/>
     Well, the hon. gentleman went up to Red River, 
     <lb/>
     and found as he had described a state of dis<lb break="no"/><pb n="94" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0094.jpg"/><fw type="num">94</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 21, 1870<lb/></fw>satisfaction among all classes. But he did not 
     <lb/>
     raise his voice in the endeavour to dissipate 
     <lb/>
     that dissatisfaction, by telling them of the real 
     <lb/>
     intentions of the Canadian Government, 
     <lb/>
     because, forsooth, that would disturb the har<lb break="no"/>mony of society there—disturb the unanimity 
     <lb/>
     which prevailed against Canada. That was an 
     <lb/>
     excuse of the lamest kind, and one which the 
     <lb/>
     country could not accept. The hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     had denied that he did anything to invite 
     <lb/>
     insurrection, but he had not yet denied that he 
     <lb/>
     counselled them not to resist, but to obtain 
     <lb/>
     their rights by constitutional means. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName>—Not only did I not attempt 
     <lb/>
     to instigate armed insurrections or to bar out 
     <lb/>
     the Governor, but the grounds I took every<lb break="no"/>where in presence of all leading people was 
     <lb/>
     this: that there was no ground for apprehen<lb break="no"/>sion at all; that when Mr. McDougall came into 
     <lb/>
     the territory, if he was a sensible man, (cheers 
     <lb/>
     and laughter from the opposition benches), he 
     <lb/>
     would learn the views of the people, and 
     <lb/>
     govern his actions accordingly, and that as 
     <lb/>
     soon as possible a responsible government 
     <lb/>
     would be granted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName>—To tell disaffected people who 
     <lb/>
     suspected their Governor, that if he was a 
     <lb/>
     sensible man he would do so and so, was rather 
     <lb/>
     a curious way to allay their apprehensions. If 
     <lb/>
     that was so, it were better for the Governor 
     <lb/>
     that he (Mr. Howe) had never said a word in 
     <lb/>
     his defence. Well the honourable gentleman 
     <lb/>
     left the country, without having given any 
     <lb/>
     public assurance to the masses, which might 
     <lb/>
     have tended to allay the agitation. There was 
     <lb/>
     an old parable about a man going down to 
     <lb/>
     Jericho and falling among thieves, who 
     <lb/>
     stripped him, wounded him and left him half 
     <lb/>
     dead. By and by there came a priest that way 
     <lb/>
     but he passed on the other side, (laughter). It 
     <lb/>
     was true his hon. friend from North Lanark 
     <lb/>
     had not at that period fallen among thieves, 
     <lb/>
     but he was on his way to them, and his hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend for Hants met him, and though there 
     <lb/>
     was time for chaffing and joking, not a word 
     <lb/>
     was uttered as to the difficulties before the 
     <lb/>
     Lieutenant Governor. He was utterly unable to 
     <lb/>
     understand how, with loyal feelings towards 
     <lb/>
     the settled designs of this country and towards 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentleman appointed as Governor, and 
     <lb/>
     who was about to enter that territory, his hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend from Hants could have acted as he did 
     <lb/>
     upon that occasion. He hoped that gentleman 
     <lb/>
     could yet recollect some other and more 
     <lb/>
     reasonable excuse for his extraordinary con<lb break="no"/><!--  <p>[Mr. Blake-M. Blake.] 
     <lb/></p>--><pb n="95" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0095.jpg"/><!-- <p>
     21 février 1870 DÉBEATES DES COMMUNES 95 
     <lb/></p>-->duct, as facts now stood he was charged with 
     <lb/>
     the most gross neglect of a solemn duty. Was 
     <lb/>
     he to excuse himself with the fact that the 
     <lb/>
     wind was strong, and that trivial remarks 
     <lb/>
     about the climate, and chaff about the wind 
     <lb/>
     took place? He hoped that the hon. gentleman 
     <lb/>
     might be able to interrupt him again with fur<lb break="no"/>ther explanations in justification of this most 
     <lb/>
     gross, cruel, and direct violation of this most 
     <lb/>
     solemn duty, which one colleague owed to 
     <lb/>
     another. Then they had the circumstance that 
     <lb/>
     the hon. gentlemen had objected to the flag of 
     <lb/>
     England floating in the wind. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName>—It was not that flag. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName>—What flag was it? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOWE2">Hon. Mr. Howe</persName>—It was not that. It had 
     <lb/>
     Canada upon it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BLAK1">Mr. Blake</persName>—Then the hon. gentleman makes 
     <lb/>
     a distinction between the two. (Cheers.) He 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Blake) concluded, amid cheers, by 
     <lb/>
     expressing his strong dissatisfaction at the 
     <lb/>
     course pursued by the hon. gentleman. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The third paragraph was then carried. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HOLT1">Hon. Mr. Holton</persName> said the leader of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment had given as a reason the other 
     <lb/>
     evening why there should be an adjournment, 
     <lb/>
     that it was only due to the able and elaborate 
     <lb/>
     speech of the member for Lambton that it 
     <lb/>
     should be answered by one of the gentlemen on 
     <lb/>
     the Treasury Benches. They had been waiting 
     <lb/>
     patiently, two or three clauses of the address 
     <lb/>
     had been passed, and the ministry had not yet 
     <lb/>
     been heard from. The Opposition could afford 
     <lb/>
     to allow the Address to go without further 
     <lb/>
     debate, if the Ministry could. But there were 
     <lb/>
     some points in the speech of the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for Lambton which clearly should not be left 
     <lb/>
     unanswered. Explanations especially were 
     <lb/>
     required of the statements made by the 
     <lb/>
     Finance Minister in a letter with his own sig<lb break="no"/>nature, lately published, in which he said that 
     <lb/>
     the peace of the country was threatened by 
     <lb/>
     armed invasion from without, and from trea<lb break="no"/>son within. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The fourth clause of the Address were then 
     <lb/>
     passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MASS3">Mr. Masson</persName> (Soulanges)—It is not my 
     <lb/>
     intention to detain the House very long; but I 
     <lb/>
     wish only to observe that up to this time of the 
     <lb/>
     proceedings, the French-speaking portion of 
     <lb/>
     the House had not the opportunity of having 
     <lb/>
     any ministerial explanations in their own lan<lb break="no"/>guage, therefore those who do not understand 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="117" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0117.jpg"/>
            <!--<p>
     21 février 1870 DÉBATES DES COMMUNES 117 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MACK1">Mr. Mackenzie</persName>—I did not bring it up as a 
     <lb/>
     grievance, but as a deception practiced upon 
     <lb/>
     Reformers at the elections in 1867. I wish the 
     <lb/>
     whole of you were Conservatives, and then we 
     <lb/>
     would have no difficulty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir George-È. Cartier</persName> said the matter 
     <lb/>
     did not affect or interest the representatives of 
     <lb/>
     the other Provinces. The hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Lambton said that he wished to see them all 
     <lb/>
     Conservatives; but let him try to get up a 
     <lb/>
     Liberal party. With regard to the charge of the 
     <lb/>
     want of success in Confederation, and support<lb break="no"/>ing it by the cases of Newfoundland and Prince 
     <lb/>
     Edward Island, and the North West, he would 
     <lb/>
     refer to those countries. With regard to New<lb break="no"/>foundland, it had rejected the proposal; but the 
     <lb/>
     terms were not those of the Government but of 
     <lb/>
     the House. The House agreed to their proposed 
     <lb/>
     terms, and then they ceased to be their pro<lb break="no"/>posals; and he was surprised to see that such 
     <lb/>
     intelligent men as the members for Lambton 
     <lb/>
     and Sherbrooke should found their charges 
     <lb/>
     upon such a foundation. He would tell the 
     <lb/>
     House that if they would be quiet, in a short 
     <lb/>
     time the terms would be accepted. With regard 
     <lb/>
     to Prince Edward Island, the Government had 
     <lb/>
     made certain proposals, but they did not like to 
     <lb/>
     do anything without the approval of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. They had telegraphed the terms they 
     <lb/>
     should submit, and they had not yet received a 
     <lb/>
     reply. They could not force such powerful 
     <lb/>
     Provinces as Newfoundland and Prince 
     <lb/>
     Edward Island to accept their terms, but they 
     <lb/>
     must wait. With regard to the North-West Ter<lb break="no"/>ritory, the proceedings adopted had not been 
     <lb/>
     the action simply of the Government, but had 
     <lb/>
     been adopted by the House. After the plans had 
     <lb/>
     been adopted by Parliament the House was 
     <lb/>
     responsible for them. He hoped his hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     did not object to that. The responsibility rested 
     <lb/>
     not upon the Government, but upon the Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment which had passed it; they had done all in 
     <lb/>
     their power to bring about the admission of the 
     <lb/>
     North-West into Confederation. He would 
     <lb/>
     admit that at the time the Confederation Act 
     <lb/>
     was discussed in Quebec, and at the discus<lb break="no"/>sions on it, they were not in possession of all 
     <lb/>
     the information that was desirable. The idea 
     <lb/>
     was that the Hudson Bay Company were not 
     <lb/>
     treating the inhabitants kindly, and that they 
     <lb/>
     would enter the Union gladly, but recent cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances showed that the Government of 
     <lb/>
     the country was not as unpopular as it was 
     <lb/>
     represented. His own impression was that the 
     <lb/>
     population had become indifferent to it, and 
     <lb/>
     the late lamentable circumstances proved that 
     <lb/>
     it was partly unpopular. He regretted that his 
     <lb/>
     own colleague was now to be addressed as an 
     <lb/>
     opponent. Before he accepted the office, he 
     <lb/>
     came to him (Sir George) and asked him 
     <lb/>
          
            <pb n="118" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0118.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">118</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">FEBRUARY 21, 1870<lb/></fw>
                 
     whether he would support him. He promised 
     <lb/>
     him to do so for he thought that he would have 
     <lb/>
     been a good Governor. He thought now that he 
     <lb/>
     would have been a good Governor if he could 
     <lb/>
     have got into the country and could have 
     <lb/>
     explained to the settlers that the Government 
     <lb/>
     intended to do them no wrong. There could be 
     <lb/>
     no doubt that the Scotch and English half- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     breeds did not find fault with what the French 
     <lb/>
     Canadian half-breeds were doing. It had been 
     <lb/>
     published in some papers that there was a 
     <lb/>
     conspiracy against his hon. friend, because a 
     <lb/>
     French Gouvernor ought to be sent there, and 
     <lb/>
     that the Territory ought to be a second Quebec. 
     <lb/>
     He thought that these statements were the 
     <lb/>
     most wicked untruths that had ever been pub<lb break="no"/>lished. He had promised his friend his support, 
     <lb/>
     and he should not have been guilty of doing 
     <lb/>
     anything to give the least appearance of truth 
     <lb/>
     to such a wicked and mischievous untruth. The 
     <lb/>
     French Canadians were an impulsive race, and 
     <lb/>
     he thought it very wrong for a writer or a 
     <lb/>
     speaker to attempt to raise a disturbance in the 
     <lb/>
     East as well as in the West. They were French 
     <lb/>
     Canadians, but they were also British subjects 
     <lb/>
     (cheers), and were as much British, even if not 
     <lb/>
     more so, than the British, (cheers). He was a 
     <lb/>
     pure Frenchman, and he defied them to pro<lb break="no"/>duce a more loyal man. Suppose that he was 
     <lb/>
     appointed to the Governorship, would his 
     <lb/>
     being a French Canadian make him unfit for 
     <lb/>
     that position? (No! no.) Sir G.-E. Cartier then 
     <lb/>
     contrasted the liberality of the Provinces of 
     <lb/>
     Ontario and Quebec, and gave a stirring 
     <lb/>
     description of the loyalty of the old French 
     <lb/>
     inhabitants of the Province of Quebec. As to 
     <lb/>
     the inhabitants of the Red River, the French 
     <lb/>
     had gone there with their fathers, but some 
     <lb/>
     stupid fanatical papers had said there should 
     <lb/>
     be no Frenchmen there. At any rate there was 
     <lb/>
     no intention to send a French Government 
     <lb/>
     there; but still their paper had no right to 
     <lb/>
     speak of the French population as they had 
     <lb/>
     done. The Red River must be a Province like 
     <lb/>
     Quebec, Ontario, Nova Scotia, or New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, but a Province for every race to settle in. 
     <lb/>
     He thanked God there were in Lower Canada 
     <lb/>
     250,000 honest English-speaking residents; and 
     <lb/>
     he and his co-nationalists only regretted that 
     <lb/>
     there were not double the number. At the last 
     <lb/>
     census there were 80,000 French Canadians in 
     <lb/>
     Upper Canada. He hoped at the next census 
     <lb/>
     there would be 100,000 more (laughter), and he 
     <lb/>
     was convinced that the Upper Province would 
     <lb/>
     not be the worse for this increase. The address 
     <lb/>
     stated that the policy of conciliation would be 
     <lb/>
     adopted. There was the case of Ireland, con<lb break="no"/>quered hundreds of years ago, and the misgov<lb break="no"/>ernment there was only now about to be 
     <lb/>
     relieved by Protestant votes. We wanted no 
     <lb/>
     such state of things here—no country baptized 
     <lb/>
     in blood. The House and country ought to be 
     <lb/>
          
   
            <!--<p>
     [Hon. Sir George-È. Cartier—L'hon. sir George-È. Cartier,] 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

            <pb n="119" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0119.jpg"/>
           <!-- <p>
     21 février 1870 DÉBATES DES COMMUNES 119 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
         
     thankful that the North-West Territory would 
     <lb/>
     be annexed without a drop of blood being shed, 
     <lb/>
     (hear, hear). The moderation of the half-breeds 
     <lb/>
     had been remarkable; and now they under<lb break="no"/>stood the policy of the Government was to be 
     <lb/>
     pacific. He was afraid that Mr. Macdougall had 
     <lb/>
     been misled by some designing people in Red 
     <lb/>
     River. But papers would come before the 
     <lb/>
     House, and they would show the necessity of 
     <lb/>
     having this unfortunate difficulty settled as 
     <lb/>
     soon as possible. Some papers asserted that 
     <lb/>
     Bishop Taché had encouraged the movement. 
     <lb/>
     He had the authority of Bishop Taché to deny 
     <lb/>
     it <hi rendition="simple:italic">in toto</hi>. Some days before Bishop Taché left 
     <lb/>
     for Rome in December last, Bishop Taché was 
     <lb/>
     informed that Mr. Macdougall was to come. 
     <lb/>
     The Bishop wrote to the College of St. Boni<lb break="no"/>face, to the nuns in the convent there, telling 
     <lb/>
     them to welcome Mr. Macdougall. The nuns 
     <lb/>
     having the little children under their control, 
     <lb/>
     were prepared to receive him by singing the 
     <lb/>
     National Anthem. As to the remarks which Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Mackenzie had made as to the militia he (Sir 
     <lb/>
     George) could inform him that there were 
     <lb/>
     enrolled in Lower Canada 43,000 men, or 3,500 
     <lb/>
     beyond the quota. There was also an excess 
     <lb/>
     over the quota in Ontario, New Brunswick, and 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia. There had been strictures as to 
     <lb/>
     the success of Confederation, but could it be 
     <lb/>
     denied that the Nova Scotian's difficulty <hi rendition="simple:italic">de 
     <lb/>
     facto</hi> had been settled? It was well after all that 
     <lb/>
     the Constitutional Act of Confederation had 
     <lb/>
     been tested in Nova Scotia. There the Local 
     <lb/>
     Parliament was against the Dominion Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, but still it could not impede the whole of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation. By the action of the last Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment giving justice to Nova Scotia, the cause of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation had been vastly strengthened. 
     <lb/>
     Sir A. T. Galt had accused the Government of 
     <lb/>
     slowness in carrying out Confederation; but 
     <lb/>
     New Jersey and Rhode Island had been for 
     <lb/>
     years out of the American Union. Let Sir A. T. 
     <lb/>
     Galt, who is so great an admirer of American 
     <lb/>
     institutions, give the Dominion the same time 
     <lb/>
     for the work of Confederation. The work of 
     <lb/>
     incorporating Red River, Newfoundland and 
     <lb/>
     Prince Edward Island would be completed 
     <lb/>
     before our American neighbors had settled 
     <lb/>
     their difficulties. The Hon. Mr. Huntington had 
     <lb/>
     taken part in a meeting in the Eastern Town<lb break="no"/>ships, called for the discussion of Indepen<lb break="no"/>dence, but luckily the member for Missisquoi 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Chamberlin) was there and opposed him. 
     <lb/>
     The result was that Mr. Huntington did not try 
     <lb/>
     to hold a meeting of the same kind anywhere 
     <lb/>
     else in Lower Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="120" facs="final/images/Man_H_of_C_1870-02-21_Page_0120.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">120</fw> <fw type="running">COMMONS DEBATES</fw> <fw type="dateline">February 21, 1870<lb/></fw>
           
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HUNT2">Hon. Mr. Huntington</persName> said, the question of 
     <lb/>
     Confederation was an old one, started by Sir A. 
     <lb/>
     T. Galt in 1858, seized on, and adopted by Sir 
     <lb/>
     G.-É. Cartier, and soon after introduced into a 
     <lb/>
     speech from the Throne. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir George-É. Cartier</persName> said the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had real work to do to incorporate the 
     <lb/>
     different Provinces; but the Hon. Mr. Hunting<lb break="no"/>ton had found it easier work to get up an 
     <lb/>
     agitation. He did not blame any one who cher<lb break="no"/>ished ideas about "Independence" but in Eng<lb break="no"/>land, amongst some of the public men and 
     <lb/>
     writers, there was an erroneous idea as to 
     <lb/>
     "Independence." There had sprung up there an 
     <lb/>
     abominable school of politicians, who would 
     <lb/>
     measure the greatness of England by estimat<lb break="no"/>ing the savings of a few thousands a year. But 
     <lb/>
     if there were diseased parts in the body politic 
     <lb/>
     of England, let them show that they at heart, 
     <lb/>
     as members of the Empire, were healthy, and 
     <lb/>
     let them show by pronouncing that we have no 
     <lb/>
     desire for "Independence". (Cheers.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HUNT2">Hon. Mr. Huntington</persName> said that the Minister 
     <lb/>
     of Militia confounded the theory of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion with its practical working. The Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion question had been of slow growth. It was 
     <lb/>
     first proposed years ago by the member for 
     <lb/>
     Sherbrooke, who stood alone in the matter, and 
     <lb/>
     it was only when it was likely to be successful 
     <lb/>
     that the scheme was taken up by the Minister 
     <lb/>
     of Militia and a coalition formed to carry it. 
     <lb/>
     Judging from analogy he had little doubt that 
     <lb/>
     before long Cartier would make the indepen<lb break="no"/>dence question his own and earn great credit 
     <lb/>
     by carrying out other men's ideas, as he had 
     <lb/>
     done before. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART2">Hon. Sir George-É. Cartier</persName> said the agita<lb break="no"/>tion now at all events was very slow. England 
     <lb/>
     was the centre of the British system. If there 
     <lb/>
     was any disease of the heart, let Canada prove 
     <lb/>
     herself sound and show herself determined to 
     <lb/>
     maintain the connection in spite of anything 
     <lb/>
     which might be uttered by any British Radical, 
     <lb/>
     (cheers). 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The fifth to the ninth paragraphs were 
     <lb/>
     adopted. On the reading of the tenth, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CART3">Mr. Cartwright</persName> moved the adjournment of 
     <lb/>
     the House, and after remarks from some of the 
     <lb/>
     members the House adjourned at 11:35. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>