<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1867-05-22"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1867-05-22">22 May 1867</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="61" to="66"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_061.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_062.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_063.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_064.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_065.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_066.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-04-18">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-04-18">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_061">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_061.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_062">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_062.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_063">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_063.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_064">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_064.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_065">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_065.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_066">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_066.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="61" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_061.jpg"/>
    <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw>  <fw type="num">61</fw>
    

   <!-- GL, 2018-04-18, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
           <!-- <p>
     House adjourned till to-morrow morn<lb break="no"/>ing at 10 o'clock.   <lb/>J.M.<lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <head rendition="simple:right">
     WEDNESDAY, May 22nd. 
     <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>The House having met, the Journals<lb/>were read, and several Bills received a<lb/>second reading.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     A Bill relating to the Election of Mem<lb break="no"/>bers to serve in the General Assembly,<lb/>so far as relates to the County of Glou<lb break="no"/>cester.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The following Bills were read a third 
     <lb/>time and passed the House:<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     A Bill relating to the Export Duty on 
     <lb/>Lumber.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill relating to the officer of Receiver<lb/>General.<lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">BURYING GROUND AT ST. ANDREWS.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:CHAN1">Mr. CHANDLER</persName> the<lb/>House went into Committee (Mr. Lewis<lb/>in the Chair) to take into considereation<lb/>a Bill to repeal Section 4, Chapter 27,<lb/>Act 14 Victoria, entitled "An Act relat<lb break="no"/>ing the Public Burying Gounds in the<lb/>Town of St. Andrews."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CHAN1">Mr. CHANDLER</persName> said that an Act of<lb/>Assembly had been passed by which it<lb/>was declared that certain Public Bury<lb break="no"/>ing Grounds in St. Andrews should not<lb/>be used for the interment of the bodies<lb/>of diseased persons. The fourth section<lb/>of said Act contained a clause that the<lb/>Act should not come into operation until<lb/>certain things had been done. Those<lb/>things have been done, and they were<lb/>now in a position to have that section re<lb break="no"/>pealed. He then read a Petition praying<lb/>for the repeal of the section which he ob<lb break="no"/>served brought the matter clearly and<lb/>distinctly before the House. He said the<lb/>Petition was signed by all the clergymen<lb/>and almost all the inhabitants of St. An<lb break="no"/>drews. He would not make any more<lb/>observations further than to say that<lb/>burial grounds in the neighborhood of a<lb/>Town affected the health of its inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants. These burial grounds were at<lb/>the head of the town, which was situa<lb break="no"/>ted on a slightly inclined plain, and they<lb/>water running through those grounds<lb/>got into wells, and this had a highly<lb/>injurious effect upon the health of the<lb/>people of the place. He hoped there<lb/>would be no opposition to the Bill, but<lb/>that it would be allowed to pass.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was then agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> presented a Petition from<lb/>the Rev. C. S. Ogg, Francis Elliot,<lb/>George McNell and others, the ministers,<lb/>Elders and Trustees of St. Andrews<lb/>Church, praying that a Bill may be pass<lb break="no"/>ed authorizing the sale of the old church,<lb/>and to add the proceeds towards defray<lb break="no"/>ing the expense incurred in the erection<lb/>of the new Church belonging to the said<lb/>Petitioners and congregation.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> brought in a Bill to autho<lb break="no"/>rise the Trustees of the St. Andrews<lb/>Church, Chatham, to sell or otherwise<lb/>

            <cb/>
          
dispose of the old St. Andrews Church in<lb/>the Town of Chatham.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> said a Bill had 
     <lb/>passed a Committee of the House yes<lb break="no"/>terday relating to the Great Roads, but<lb/>they had since, on a closer examination,<lb/>discovered a word or two which re<lb break="no"/>quired alteration. He wished to know<lb/>whether it could be altered, or whether<lb/>it was necessary to recommit the Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said that if it involved   
     <lb/>any principle it could not be altered<lb/>without being recommitted, but if it<lb/>was a mere verbal alteration to rectify<lb/>an error it was not necessary to recom<lb break="no"/>mit it.<lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Mr. McCLELAN</persName> said itw as but to<lb/>change a name, which would extend<lb/>the road about one mile and a half fur<lb break="no"/>ther.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>His hon. <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">the SPEAKER</persName> put the ques<lb break="no"/>tion the HOuse, to whether the alteration<lb/>should be made without recommitting<lb/>the Bill. Question carried in the affir<lb break="no"/>mative.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> presented a Petition from<lb/>a number of the inhabitants of the<lb/>County of Westmorland, prayinig that<lb/>an Act may pass to provie for the con<lb break="no"/>struction of a Canal to connect the wa<lb break="no"/>ters of the Bay of Fundy with the Gulf<lb/>of St. Lawrence.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> the<lb/>House went into a committee of the<lb/>Whole (Mr. Botsford in the Chair) on<lb/>"A Bill to authorize the City Council<lb/>of Fredericton to raise money, by way<lb/>of a loan, for the erection of a Country<lb/>Market and City Hall in the said City."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The BIll was agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> presented a Peti<lb break="no"/>tion praying that an Act may pass to<lb/>Incorporate the St. John Trades' Co<lb break="no"/>operative Association.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">QUESTION CONCERNING UNION.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> asked whether the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment had received any information<lb/>either direct from england, from or<lb/>through Canada, or from or though<lb/>Nova Scotia, or from any other source<lb/>in reference to the proclamation of<lb/>Union.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> replied that he had<lb/>not received any information in refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the proclamation from any<lb/>source.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> hoped the Secretary had<lb/>not given instruction to keep the infor<lb break="no"/>mation back.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> replied that he<lb/>had not.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CHAN1">Mr. CHANDLER</persName> presented a Peti<lb break="no"/>tion praying that Section 2, Chap. 47 of<lb/>Section 26 Victoria, relating to certain<lb/>exemptions from duty at the Port of<lb/>St. stephen, be repealed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of Hon. Mr. CONNELL<lb/>the House went into Committee (Mr.<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
          

     Botsford in the Chair) on "A Bill to 
     <lb/>amend Chap. 45 of the Revised statutes<lb/>of Municipalities."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> gave notice that he would<lb/>move a resolution for an Address to<lb/>His Excellency the Administrator of the<lb/>Government for a return showing any<lb/>increase that may have taken place,<lb/>since the first day of June last, in the<lb/>salaries and emoluments of the officers<lb/>and employees connected with the Euro<lb break="no"/>pean and North American Railway.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill relating to Great Roads was<lb/>read a third time and passed the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> submitted papers<lb/>relating to the claims of the PRince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island Steamship Company.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> moved that the in<lb break="no"/>vestigation of these matters be referred<lb/>to a Select Committee.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Committee — Messrs. Stevens, Ryan<lb/>and Beveridge.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">REPRESENTATION OF COUNTIES<lb/>
            </head>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> moved the House into<lb/>a Committee of the Whole on "A Bill<lb/>to repeal certain sections of a law re<lb break="no"/>lating to the election of Representatives<lb/>to serve in the General Assembly, and<lb/>to make other provisions in lieu there<lb break="no"/>of.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. — A few days ago,<lb/>when I was advocating an incrrease of<lb/>representation for the County of Carle<lb break="no"/>ton, several members thought it would<lb/>be better to introduce a Bill to reduce<lb/>the representation on the floors of the<lb/>House instead of increasing it. That<lb/>coincided with my views, for I thought<lb/>in view of our altered circumstances<lb/>we should reduce our expenses as much<lb/>as possible. The basis upon which the<lb/>representation of the Counties now<lb/>stand is very unfair. In the County of<lb/>Carleton, which I have the honor to re<lb break="no"/>present, the have one representative<lb/>to 9400 inhabitants; County of Albert<lb/>one to 4722; Charlotte one to 5907;<lb/>Gloucester one to 7519; Kent one to<lb/>7927; King's one to 7761; Northumber<lb break="no"/>land one to 4700; Queen's one to 6600;<lb/>Restigouehe one to 2437; St. John one<lb/>to 3085; Westmorland one to 6311;<lb/>York one to 5810. This representation<lb/>is very unfair, and when I had a Bill<lb/>before the House to increase the repre<lb break="no"/>sentation of Carleton it was generally<lb/>conceded that if a Bill was prepared<lb/>which would do justice to all sections<lb/>of the country it would receive the sup<lb break="no"/>port of the hon. members of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature. Accordingly I introduced a Bill<lb/>which is now befoer the Committee,<lb/>which provides that there shall be one<lb/>member for every 7500 inhabitants. My<lb/>first idea was to make it for every 8000,<lb/>
          

            <pb n="62" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_062.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="num">62</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> 


     but upon considering the question I 
     <lb/>
     found some of the Counties had about 
     <lb/>
     15000 inhabitants, and the Bill would 
     <lb/>
     deprive them of having two represen<lb break="no"/>tatives. The principle of the Bill is to 
     <lb/>
     have one representative for every 7500 
     <lb/>
     inhabitants, but in no case to allow any 
     <lb/>County to have more than three re<lb break="no"/>presentatives. St John City should 
     <lb/>have two members, and the County 
     <lb/>should be represented the same as other 
     <lb/>Counties. According to this arange<lb break="no"/>ment there will be thirty members in 
     <lb/>the House, unless we give the City of 
     <lb/>Fredericton one, which would make the 
     <lb/>whole ntttnber thirty-one. I would con<lb break="no"/>fine the City of St. John to two mem<lb break="no"/>bers, for I do not believe cities should 
     <lb/>be represented according to population. 
     <lb/>It is not so in Great Britain, if it were 
     <lb/>so the City of London would have one- 
     <lb break="yes"/>sixth of the representation of all Eng<lb break="no"/>land. Having made these few remarks 
     <lb/>I shall be glad to hear tlte views of 
     <lb/>other hon. members on the floors of the 
     <lb/>House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:RYAN1">Mr. RYAN</persName>.—If I am rightly informed,      
     <lb/>according to this Bill some counties will<lb/>only have one representative. I think<lb/>any Country, however small it may be,<lb/>should have not less than two members.<lb/>Suppose a Country should have but one<lb/>member, and he should absent, or<lb/>sick; who would attend to the affairs of<lb/>that County? We cannot give the repre<lb break="no"/>sentation exactly on the basis of popula<lb break="no"/>tion, but even if we did, it would remain<lb/>so only until the next census, because one<lb/>County frequently increases faster than<lb/>other Counties. I would suggest that<lb/>every County that has four members<lb/>should be reduced to three ; that would<lb/>take five members from the floors of the<lb/>House, and leave a representation of<lb/>thirty-six. I have frequently tried to get<lb/>an increase of representation for King's,<lb/>but unfortunately for some cause or other<lb/>—either from want of being pressed pro<lb break="no"/>perly, or from a determination of the<lb/>House not to do justice to King's—I have<lb/>never been able to effect it. The propo<lb break="no"/>sition I have just made is a good one,<lb/>and will do justice to all. We should<lb/>decrease our expense under any circum<lb break="no"/>stances, but particularly now when we<lb/>are going into Union, for the duties and<lb/>requirements of the Legislature will not<lb/>be so great as they have been hereto<lb break="no"/>fore.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr. HIBBARD</persName>.—I fully agreee with<lb/>the Bill brought in by my hon. friend, if<lb/>he can carry it, but if he cannot carry it<lb/>I agree with the suggestion of my hon.<lb/>friend from King's. There seems to be<lb/>a dread around the floors of the House of<lb/>placing the representation upon the basis<lb/>of population. Suppose it does give but<lb/>one representative to some of the Coun<lb break="no"/>ties, is not the same provision made for<lb/>
       

  <cb/>
        

     
     the representation to the General Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment, and I do not believe but we will<lb/>get our rights at Ottawa. I have always<lb/>advocated the principle of representation<lb/>by population, and I still support it. This<lb/>Bill must be prospective, for the mover<lb/>has not power to dissolve the House. If<lb/>he carries it he should make it prospec<lb break="no"/>tive, because it cannot be carried out<lb/>until the House dies out by law, or the<lb/>Government tells us to go home. If the<lb/>Government would dissolve the House to<lb/>carry out the provisions of this Bill they<lb/>would meet with the approbation of the<lb/>country. This Bill brings us down to<lb/>thirty-one members. I believe ten mem<lb break="no"/>bers would do all the work we have done<lb/>here up to this time. I do not doubt<lb/>but five men would have done its Thirty-<lb break="yes"/>one men are amply sufficient to legislate<lb/>upon all the local wants we will require.<lb/>I firmly believe that if we husbanded our<lb/>resources. reduced our expenses, and<lb/>acted economically, there would not be a<lb/>Province in the British Empire that<lb/>would have as much for its local pur<lb break="no"/>poses as we would have. But if we re<lb break="no"/>tain forty-one members in the House,<lb/>create new offices, assist Western Exten<lb break="no"/>sion, while we have no revenue but what<lb/>we derive from our Public Domain and<lb/>what we receive from the General Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, there will be nothing before us<lb/>but direct taxation. Representation by<lb/>population is the fair, honest principle,<lb/>and however hard it may bear on some<lb/>Counties, we must take something as a<lb/>basis, and if that basis should reduce the<lb/>representation of the County of Charlotte<lb/>to two, I would agree to it. My col<lb break="no"/>leagues may have something to say about<lb/>it, but for myself I would go for it, be<lb break="no"/>cause I believe ten men could do all the<lb/>work we have to do. I hope the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Government will give due<lb/>consideration to this question, regardless<lb/>of interested motives, and do all they can<lb/>for the reduction of the expenses of the<lb/>Legislature.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. BABBIT</persName>.—I think justice should     
     <lb/>be done to all parties, but this Bill is go<lb break="no"/>ing too far for a good many of the hon.<lb/>members. I acknowledge I do not like<lb/>representation by population. (A mem<lb break="no"/>ber—You supported the Quebec Scheme.)<lb/>I never advocated the principle of repre<lb break="no"/>sentation by population, for I believe it<lb/>will eventually lead to universal suffrage,<lb/>(Mr. Tilley,—That is not the principle in<lb/>this Bill, for it limits the representation<lb/>of Counties to three members.) I do not<lb/>think we have so many conflicting inter<lb break="no"/>ests in this Province to require a strict<lb/>adherence to this principle, and I do not<lb/>think it is right to deprive a county of<lb/>having two members because it has a few<lb/>inhabitants less than the required num<lb break="no"/>ber. I think those Counties which have<lb/>four representatives should be reduced to<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
      

     three, and this would lessen the expense        
     <lb/>to the country. It is not right to reduce<lb/>any County to one member, therefore I<lb/>cannot support the Bill, but I would sup<lb break="no"/>port a Bill to reduce the number in the<lb/>Counties that have four members.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LEWI1">Mr. LEWIS</persName>.—I think those hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen who are favorable to reducing the<lb/>number of members must have their faces<lb/>turned towards Ottawa. We cannot do<lb/>with one member in each County, be<lb break="no"/>cause he might be sick, and the County<lb/>would not be represented at all. This<lb/>Bill will not answer unless we are going<lb/>to give up New Brunswick and go to<lb/>Ottawa. I would go for striking one<lb/>member from some of those large Coun<lb break="no"/>ties, for we must curtail the expense and<lb/>live within our resources. If our expen<lb break="no"/>diture is beyond our means bankruptcy<lb/>must ultimately ensue. I do not think<lb/>the hon. member was in earnest when he<lb/>brought in this Bill ; he only brought it<lb/>in to have a discussion, and had no idea<lb/>of passing it. I will go for letting the<lb/>representation stand as it is, although I<lb/>have no objection to have one member<lb/>taken from each of the large Counties.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>—I will say for the<lb/>information of the hon. member who has<lb/>just sat down that I am in earnest. I want<lb/>to reduce the expense of the country,<lb/>and I want the country to know who are<lb/>willing to reduce them. I suppose there<lb/>will be some difficulty in carrying it, as<lb/>the members of those small Counties<lb/>which are likely to be reduced will go<lb/>against it. My hon. friend is very gen<lb break="no"/>erous ; he wants to take off of the large<lb/>Counties ; that is "take my neighbour<lb/>but let me alone." I believe the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of this House should do their duty<lb/>and have the interest of their country at<lb/>heart. My hon. friend said we should<lb/>not reduce a County to one member be<lb break="no"/>cause he might get sick ; if a man finds<lb/>he cannot attend to the duties of his con<lb break="no"/>stituents he should give place to another<lb/>man who can. My opinion is that we<lb/>must decrease the representation, or to<lb/>do justice to some counties we must in<lb break="no"/>crease it. My hon. friend from Queen's<lb/>(Mr. Babbit) said he did not like the<lb/>principle of representation in the Bill.<lb/>I would like him to introduce a Bill upon<lb/>juster terms. He said it would lead to<lb/>universal suffrage. I showed him how<lb/>unfair it would be to have population as<lb/>the basis of representation in large cities.<lb/>Hon. members will find fault with the<lb/>Bill, but I say if it is not right let them<lb/>prepare a better one.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BEVE1">Mr. BEVERIDGE</persName>—I can agree with<lb/>some things my hon. friend said, but not<lb/>with all he said. The County he repre<lb break="no"/>sents is only sixty miles in length ; my<lb/>County is one hundred and twenty miles<lb/>long, therefore it would be unfair to take<lb/>one representative from Victoria. In that<lb/>
          

            <pb n="63" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_063.jpg"/>
          
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> <fw type="num">63</fw>

         
district territory should be taken into ac<lb break="no"/>count as well as population. If we had<lb/>but one representative, and he should<lb/>live at one end of the County, he would<lb/>never see half of his constituents. I<lb/>would be prepared to go for reduction in<lb/>the large Counties if it was necessary to<lb/>reduce the representation, but would<lb/>rather not have it reduced.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FERR2">Mr. FERRIS</persName>.—There are always two<lb/>parties in every County, and if a small<lb/>County sent but one representative it<lb/>would give one man all the power. I do<lb/>not think a County with one representa<lb break="no"/>tive would get fair play in the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture, but those large Counties might be<lb/>represented by three members as well as<lb/>four. It is just throwing away so much<lb/>money to send four representatives, for I<lb/>think the Counties would be just as well<lb/>represented by two, and there could be a<lb/>reduction made of four or six in the Le<lb break="no"/>gislative Council.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName>.—If a reduction<lb/>takes place it should be done by some<lb/>general rule which would do justice to<lb/>every County. I am in the happy posi<lb break="no"/>tion, that if either the small or large<lb/>Counties are reduced, we in York will<lb/>have the same representation.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>.—The Bill does not 
     <lb/>
     provide that it was only suggested that 
     <lb/>
     the City of Fredericton should have 
     <lb/>one.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName>.—I have no doubt<lb/>but that would be the result, for the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee would be showing some little fair<lb/>play. Although some of our best men<lb/>will be abstracted from us in consequence<lb/>of this Ottawa Legislature, yet I still be<lb break="no"/>lieve that forty-one good men will remain<lb/>in New Brunswick capable of doing the<lb/>business of the Province. We had forty-<lb break="yes"/>one members when our population was<lb/>but 170,000, and we have the same num<lb break="no"/>ber now when our population was 252,<lb break="no"/>000 five years ago. Some very import<lb break="no"/>ant features in the business of the coun<lb break="no"/>try, such as Education and the settlement<lb/>of the country, have still to be attended<lb/>to. Then again, one member cannot at<lb break="no"/>tend properly to the duties of his County.<lb/>It would be better to throw two Counties<lb/>into one than to have only one represen<lb break="no"/>tative for a County, but it would be re<lb break="no"/>trorgading to do even that. Carleton<lb/>County should have three members, and<lb/>King's four ; with those two exceptions<lb/>I cannot see any alteration we can make<lb/>which would be advantageous. We<lb/>should not go into this question now, as<lb/>ten or twelve of the members here will<lb/>legislate upon this who will not legislate<lb/>here again, for they will be in Ottawa.<lb/>Let us get through with all these changes<lb/>which must take place in consequence of<lb/>the General Legislature being at Ottawa,<lb/>and then those who are here years after<lb/>this, can take the question up cooly and<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
         
deliberately, with ample time to consider<lb/>the question and do justice to the differ-<lb break="yes"/>end Counties. With these opinions I<lb/>must go against passing the Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Hon. Mr. McMILLAN</persName>.—I am opposed<lb/>to the Bill, not because I happen to re<lb break="no"/>present one of the smallest Counties, for<lb/>I believe that that County, in consequence<lb/>of certain changes at hand, will contain as<lb/>large a population as some of the largest 
     <lb/>
     Counties in the Province, but because I 
     <lb/>
     believe there will be no saving of money 
     <lb/>
     effected by the reduction. If you are 
     <lb/>
     going to carry out the principles of Re<lb break="no"/>sponsible Government you will find they 
     <lb/>
     cannot be carried out in a small Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture. If you leave nine man in the Exe<lb break="no"/>cutive and reduce the House to thirty-five, 
     <lb/>
     you could not turn the Government out 
     <lb/>
     at all. There will be talent enough in 
     <lb/>
     the House to carry out the principles of 
     <lb/>
     Responsible Government after the lead<lb break="no"/>ing men in this House go to Ottawa. 
     <lb/>
     You will have the cleverest young men in 
     <lb/>
     the country come here to receive a politi<lb break="no"/>cal education, with a view to a higher 
     <lb/>position in the General Government. 
     <lb/>There will be sufficient talent left in this 
     <lb/>House to deal with all matters left for 
     <lb/>them. Probably fifteen in this House 
     <lb/>will offer for Ottawa ; is it fair for them 
     <lb/>now to pass a law which will not affect 
     <lb/>them at all, but will affect the party re<lb break="no"/>sponsible for it hereafter. We are on<lb/>the eve of great changes, therefore, those<lb/>who are left should decide with regard to<lb/>this reduction, and not those who are go<lb break="no"/>ing into another sphere, and who, in or<lb break="no"/>der to gain popularity, try to make it ap<lb break="no"/>pear that there will be a great saving of<lb/>money. I believe it is premature to dael<lb/>with this matter ; we had better leave it<lb/>to the parties who are to be af<lb break="no"/>fected by it ; they can determine whether<lb/>they can do with a less representation<lb/>than they now have, and they will be<lb/>responsible to the people for their de<lb break="no"/>cision.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I was rather astonished 
     <lb/>by some of the remarks made by my hon.<lb/>friend, the Postmaster General ; he says<lb/>because some gentlemen will go to Otta<lb break="no"/>wa they cannot have any interest here.<lb/>He expects to get a seat at Ottawa, but I<lb/>should not suppose that would prevent<lb/>him from having a sympathy for the peo<lb break="no"/>ple he represents. I do not suppose that<lb/>because a man is going to Ottawa he<lb/>should have no voice on this question, for<lb/>those who go to Ottawa still expect to<lb/>
    remain citizens of New Brunswick. In 
     <lb/>speaking upon the appointment of Dele<lb break="no"/>gates last year I moved that the Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive Councillors should reside in the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, but no hon. member here except 
     <lb/>the French Brigade sympathized with the 
     <lb/>proposition. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>.—I sympathized with<lb/>the proposition and a great many sug<lb break="no"/>
       

            <cb/>
         

     gestions of my hon. friend I gave him 
     <lb/>credit for, but he brought in a resolution<lb/>to get certain conditions, and if we could<lb/>not get them we could have no Union.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I wished to restrict the<lb/>power of the Delegates, for I did not<lb/>approve of the Quebec Scheme, and I<lb/>took many objections to it. Some of<lb/>those objections were adopted, but other<lb/>objections, equally forcible to my mind,<lb/>where not adopted. I took an objection<lb/>to the principle of representation by<lb/>population, but I find this principle is<lb/>laid down in this Act of Union as inflex<lb break="no"/>ible and immutable. The conflicting<lb/>opinions on this small Bill corroborate<lb/>the opinion I then took. It is wrong in<lb/>principle, and not recognized or adopted<lb/>in any part of the British Empire, but for<lb/>purposes peculiarly ultra Canadian that<lb/>principle was laid down and established<lb/>and becomes the governing principle of<lb/>the country. In the Act of Union it is<lb/>established, and I will venture to pro<lb break="no"/>phesy that in a few years Upper Canada<lb/>will have a numerical majority of repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives, not only over Lower Canada,<lb/>but over the Lower Provinces, too and<lb/>we will be at her mercy. They should<lb/>have agreed upon a certain number of<lb/>representatives and not increased them.<lb/>We cannot help it now, but what I have<lb/>seen here to-day in reference to this Bill<lb/>has satisfied me of the wisdom of the<lb/>course we took upon that question.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     My hon. friend, the Postmaster Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, is wrong to say we have no right to 
     <lb/>
     legislate upon this matter ; the people of 
     <lb/>
     this country expect us to legislate upon 
     <lb/>
     it. Was it not preached in every part of 
     <lb/>
     the Province that the expenses of the 
     <lb/>
     Legislature would be vastly reduced ? 
     <lb/>
     Where is the reduction to be made ? Two 
     <lb/>
     offices created already, and I do not 
     <lb/>
     know how many more the Government 
     <lb/>
     contemplate to carry before the close of 
     <lb/>
     the Session. We resisted their measure 
     <lb/>
    yesterday, in regard to the appointment 
     <lb/>of Receiver General, and got the salary 
     <lb/>reduced from £590 to £400, and we had 
     <lb/>a section struck out which provided for 
     <lb/>the appointment of a clerk in the Re<lb break="no"/>ceiver General's office ; by this means<lb/>we saved the country £300 a year for all<lb/>time to come.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     I do not think it would be wise to have 
     <lb/>any County confined to only one repre<lb break="no"/>sentative, because he might have impera<lb break="no"/>tive business that would call him home,<lb/>and he could not attend to his legislative<lb/>duties. I am willing to support any hon.<lb/>member who will bring forward a Bill to<lb/>reduce those Counties that have four<lb/>members to three, leaving other Counties<lb/>as they are.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DOW1">Dr. DOW</persName>.—My hon. friend (Mr.<lb/>Smith) has said, in speaking about the<lb/>Bill for appointing a Receiver General,<lb/>that they saved this country three hun<lb break="no"/>
    

            <pb n="64" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_064.jpg"/>
        
<fw type="num">64</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> 
 
dred pounds a year for all time to come.<lb/>That will appear very well in the Debates,<lb/>but we know the hon. mover of the Bill<lb/>stated that it would only continue for<lb/>some months, and then the Legislature<lb/>would have the right to legislate upon<lb/>that Bill again, and when the vote was<lb/>taken it was with that understanding,<lb/>and it may be that then the Legislature<lb/>will make the salary £500 and appoint<lb/>a clerk besides. While I believe we<lb/>should keep our expenses as low as pos<lb break="no"/>sible, I do not believe that you can get a<lb/>first class man to take the office of Re<lb break="no"/>ceiver General and act without a clerk<lb/>for $1,600 a year. I have heard it stated<lb/>here that the President of the United<lb/>States received but $25,000 a year. The<lb/>President, although his salary is $25,000,<lb/>gets from the Treasury Department over<lb/>$100,000 a year to pay his expenses,<lb/>The Chamberlain of New York gets<lb/>$70,000, and ladies in New York offices<lb/>get $100 a month. For the office of Re<lb break="no"/>ceiver General you must have a man who<lb/>understands the routine of office, and one<lb/>who will take the responsibility. To ask<lb/>a man to give bonds for £10,000 a year<lb/>and give him a salary of only $1,600 is<lb/>perfectly absurd.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     I cannot support my hon. friend's Bill, 
     <lb/>
     for I believe one man cannot represent a 
     <lb/>
     County. When Confederation was in<lb break="no"/>troduced, I took the position that by the 
     <lb/>
     consolidation of the British North Ame<lb break="no"/>rican Colonies on this continent they 
     <lb/>
     would be advanced as an important part 
     <lb/>
     of the British empire, and we would have 
     <lb/>
     an increased population in consequence 
     <lb/>
     of the construction of the Intercolonial 
     <lb/>
     Railway. Why, then, should we go for 
     <lb/>
     reducing the representation in our Legis<lb break="no"/>lature when we expect such an increase 
     <lb/>
     of population ? I firmly believe that the 
     <lb/>
     construction of this road and branches 
     <lb/>
     will greatly increase our population. 
     <lb/>
     This is the position I took at the time of 
     <lb/>
     the election, and it is the position l would 
     <lb/>
     take again. You may call it Ottawa on 
     <lb/>
     the brain ; this is a new disease, but I can 
     <lb/>
     cure it. I can give you a recipe that will 
     <lb/>
     kill it dead, and I get it myself I will 
     <lb/>
     take the same remedy. I did not intend 
     <lb/>
     to say anything about this Bill, but I 
     <lb/>
     cannot vote for it. I believe we are to 
     <lb/>
     grow in importance and prosperity, and 
     <lb/>
     we will require just as many and as 
     <lb/>
     zealous men in the Legislature after these 
     <lb/>
     men go to Ottawa as we have now. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FLEW2">Mr. W. P. FLEWELLING</persName>.—I do not 
     <lb/>
     think this Bill is exactly what is required 
     <lb/>
     by the members ol the House. I do not 
     <lb/>
     agree with it, from the fact, which has 
     <lb/>
     been stated by some of the members here, 
     <lb/>
     that it will leave some counties with only 
     <lb/>
     one representative. I think the only 
     <lb/>
     way of doing equal justice to all the 
     <lb/>
     Counties is to reduce the number of 
     <lb/>
     members in the large Counties to three, 
     <lb/>
         

            <cb/>
         

     
     and there should be an amendment made         
     <lb/>
     to the Bill to carry out that arrangement,        
     <lb/>I cannot agree with the hon. friend from<lb/>Charlotte (Mr. Hibbard) that the whole<lb/>business of the House could be done with<lb/>fifteen members, for it would require<lb/>more than that to carry out the principles<lb/>of Responsible Government. We are<lb/>now going to change the constitution—it<lb/>is a good time to make a reduction in the<lb/>number of members. I have always<lb/>advocated the necessity of economy, and<lb/>I think we can do very well with 36<lb/>members on the floors of the House to<lb/>carry out the necessary requirements of<lb/>the country. I should like to hear every<lb/>member present express his opinion in<lb/>regard to the best means of bringing<lb/>about this desirable result.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.—I think every member on<lb/>the floors of this House must be aware<lb/>that this country expects that there will<lb/>be a reduction in the number of mem<lb break="no"/>bers in the House, and a vast amount of<lb/>retrenchment practised here. The mul<lb break="no"/>tifarious matters connected with the<lb/>legislation of the Province are taken from<lb/>our hand, and there is no necessity for the<lb/>same number of members, the same ex<lb break="no"/>penditure, or the same length of Session.<lb/>Nova Scotia, with a population of one<lb/>hundred thousand more than we have,<lb/>and more numerous resources, has reduced<lb/>her Legislature some eleven or twelve,<lb/>leaving three members for Pictou, three<lb/>for the City of Halifax, and two for each<lb/>of the other Counties. The proposition<lb/>made to take one member from each of<lb/>our Counties having four members ap<lb break="no"/>pears reasonable, and ought to be taken<lb/>into consideration. My hon. friend from<lb/>Carleton (Mr. Lindsay) made out a very<lb/>strong case in regard to Carleton being<lb/>very badly used. I heard recently of<lb/>great injustice being done to the River<lb/>Counties in the appointment of Senators,<lb/>and we find they always vote together on<lb/>any question affecting their interest. Now<lb/>take the population of the five River Coun<lb break="no"/>ties, that is the five above King's, and di<lb break="no"/>vide them by the number of members, and<lb/>it will give you one member for every fifty<lb/>five hundred inhabitants. Then take the<lb/>four North Shore Counties, and divide<lb/>the inhabitants by the number of mem<lb break="no"/>bers, and it will give on representative<lb/>for every five thousand four hundred<lb/>inhabitants. This shows that each mem<lb break="no"/>ber from the North represents one hun<lb break="no"/>dred inhabitants more than each member<lb/>from the River Counties. Therefore, I<lb/>cannot see that so much injustice has<lb/>been done to Carleton as has been re<lb break="no"/>presented. I believe that the members<lb/>from Victoria feel so much interest in<lb/>promoting the welfare of Carleton as they<lb/>do in promoting the welfare of their own<lb/>County, and so <hi rendition="simple:italic">vice versa</hi> all through the<lb/>River Counties.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     It appears to me to be very desirable 
     <lb/>that Counties that have two or three<lb/>members should be divided off into Rid<lb break="no"/>ings, as they are in Canada ; then can<lb break="no"/>didates would not have to run their<lb/>election through the whole County, and<lb/>this would save trouble, both to the<lb/>candidates themselves and those whom<lb/>they represent. Something should be<lb/>done, and the question if whether it is<lb/>advisable to do it in this short Session.<lb/>The Bill will not take effect until the next<lb/>general election, and until something of<lb/>that kind is looked forward to, it is<lb/>hardly desirable to legislate upon the<lb/>subject. We should approach the ques<lb break="no"/>tion with a determination to do justice to<lb/>every section of the Province. I believe<lb/>thirty members on the floors of this House<lb/>will answer all purposes for many years<lb/>to come, for our interests are not so varied<lb/>that they would not be able to manage<lb/>our affairs. We should either reduce the<lb/>numbers or reduce the pay. It is not so<lb/>much the number of members that should<lb/>be considered as the expense incurred<lb/>while we are here. We should be al<lb break="no"/>lowed pay for thirty days, and if we<lb/>stayed any longer it should be at our<lb/>own expense. People say, Why do you<lb/>remain so long at Fredericton, when you<lb/>might do your business in half the time?<lb/>Why do you not retrench your expendi<lb break="no"/>ture, in order that it may be applied to<lb/>the building of Roads and Bridges, in<lb break="no"/>stead of squandering it away in the<lb/>House of Assembly ? I have always<lb/>advocated the principle of retrench<lb break="no"/>ment, for I felt the necessity for it in<lb/>our public affairs. I am satisfied it is<lb/>the wish of the country that the rep<lb break="no"/>resentation should be reduced, more<lb/>particularly as politicians have been<lb/>stating in every County in the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince that one of the great advantages<lb/>we would have by going into Con<lb break="no"/>federation wold be that we would<lb/>have more money, from the saving in<lb/>the expenses of our Legislature than<lb/>we had hitherto.<lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I think the representation should be 
     <lb/>reduced very materially. If this Bill<lb/>before the House is not thought to be<lb/>a correct one, let some one bring in a<lb/>better Bill and I shall go for it, but if<lb/>another is not brought in, I shall go for<lb/>this.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCQU1">Mr. McQUEEN</persName>.—When a Bill was 
     <lb/>presented the other day to increase the<lb/>representation of King's, we were told<lb/>that it was an annual offering. I did<lb/>not go for it, because I thought it de<lb break="no"/>sirable to reduce the number of mem<lb break="no"/>bers. I thought King's, Carleton and<lb/>Kent were each entitled to an additional<lb/>member, but as equal justice could be<lb/>done at all by reducing the representa<lb break="no"/>tion, I considered it would be better to<lb/>reduce the number on the floors of the<lb/>
          

            <pb n="65" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_065.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw>  <fw type="num">65</fw> 
 

     House. Some say they will go for 
     <lb/>
     reducing them one half. I would not 
     <lb/>
     go for that at the present time, for the 
     <lb/>
     simple  reason that I believe in a repre<lb break="no"/>sentative Government we ought to have 
     <lb/>
     a deliberative body sufficient to think, 
     <lb/>
     consider and weigh all matters that 
     <lb/>
     come before us.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr.  STEVENS</persName>.— A constitutional 
     <lb/>
     change like this requires us to exercise 
     <lb/>
     mature  deliberation. There is  not a 
     <lb/>
     member around the House but would 
     <lb/>
     be inclined to give the question a calm 
     <lb/>
     consideration, in order that the best re<lb break="no"/>sults might be obtained. A great deal 
     <lb/>has been said in regard to the expres<lb break="no"/>sions of the people of the country. It 
     <lb/>is said they expect us to retrench at this  
     <lb/>time. If  retrenchment is necessary  
     <lb/> now it is necessary at all times. 
     <lb/>Whatever the people wish me to do in 
     <lb/>this question I would do, for it is their 
     <lb/>own business ; but I do not know the 
     <lb/>minds of the people of Charlotte, 
     <lb/>whether they want the representation 
     <lb/>reduced or not, for it is a question that 
     <lb/>has not been much considered. Should 
     <lb/>I, on returning home, find the people 
     <lb/>wished this reduction to be made, I 
     <lb/>would be well prepared to vote upon 
     <lb/>the amendment. I make these remarks 
     <lb/>because I do not see the reason for any 
     <lb/>hurry in passing a measure of this kind ; 
     <lb/>even if the measure was complete there 
     <lb/>would be nothing lost by the delay. 
     <lb/>What is gained by delaying it ? In 
     <lb/>another year you will ascertain the 
     <lb/>views of the people upon it.  I am not 
     <lb/>now in a position to know their views, and  
     <lb/>as the people sent me here to carry out  
     <lb/>their wishes I cannot say to them when I 
     <lb/>return home I consented to take away 
     <lb/>one of your representatives without 
     <lb/>knowing that you desired it. It would 
     <lb/>be much more gratifying to all to have 
     <lb/>the matter stand over until another ses<lb break="no"/>sion. It might be very well for those 
     <lb/>who no longer expect  to sit in the Local 
     <lb/>Legislature to vote upon this question, 
     <lb/>for they will not be affected by it, as 
     <lb/>they expect to go to Ottawa ; but it 
     <lb/>would be more graceful for  them to al<lb break="no"/>low those who come in after them to 
     <lb/>deal with the question, for they would 
     <lb/>then have the minds of the people upon 
     <lb/>it. The people may say we never asked  
     <lb/>you to reduce our representation. We 
     <lb/> would then feel that we had not been 
     <lb/>acting in accordance with their wishes. 
     <lb/>Then again, when you go to alter the 
     <lb/> representation you should  begin at the 
     <lb/>bottom and regulate the whole thing. 
     <lb/>You must make some arrangement in 
     <lb/>regard to the Executive, for if you al<lb break="no"/>low nine members to hold seats there 
     <lb/>it would give the Government such a 
     <lb/>predominance that you could not move 
     <lb/> them ; therefore, this matter requires 
     <lb/>mature deliberation, and this, I think,<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
         

     is apparent to every one. I desire all<lb/>economy to be used. The duties of the 
     <lb/>
     House will  be curtailed, and there will 
     <lb/>
     be no need for the House to sit so many 
     <lb/>
     days. Instead of sitting  two months 
     <lb/>
     the House will be able to discharge its 
     <lb/>
     duties in one month, and this will be a 
     <lb/>
     curtailment of expenses at once, arising 
     <lb/>
     out of the business we have to do, and 
     <lb/>
     there  will be no encroachment there 
     <lb/>
     upon the rights of the people. The du<lb break="no"/>ties that  remain for us to do still require 
     <lb/>
     as much deliberation as they ever did, 
     <lb/>
     for you cannot tell me wherein they re<lb break="no"/>quire less ; but it will only require half 
     <lb/>
     the time to attend to them, in conse<lb break="no"/>quence of their number being less than 
     <lb/>
     formerly.  
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCAD1">Hon. Mr. McADAM</persName>.—If the people 
     <lb/> are in favor of this Bill we should go 
     <lb/>for it. ln order to do justice to the 
     <lb/>County of King's we should pass a Bill 
     <lb/>to reduce  the representation, for I do 
     <lb/>not think it would be right to increase 
     <lb/>the representation under the present 
     <lb/>circumstances. I think we should go 
     <lb/>for the amendment suggested by the 
     <lb/>hon. member from King's. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:QUIN1">Mr. QUINTON</persName>.—I do not think it 
     <lb/>right to be  legislating so far  ahead, as 
     <lb/>there is no  necessity for passing this 
     <lb/>Bill at  present. It would be better to 
     <lb/>let it stand over until the House met 
     <lb/>next winter, and  not be taking up the 
     <lb/>time of the  House at this short session. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr.  HIBBARD</persName>.—I do not like the 
     <lb/>idea of lopping a member off of a Coun<lb break="no"/>ty because it has four representatives, 
     <lb/>we should adopt a fair basis of repre<lb break="no"/>sentation.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BABB1">Mr. BABBITT</persName>.—My hon. friend from<lb/>Westmorland (Mr. Smith) in the course<lb/>of his remarks said, that in speaking 
     <lb/>
     upon the appointment of Delegates last  
     <lb/>
     year he had moved that the Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Councillors should reside in the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, but no member here, except the 
     <lb/>
     French  Brigade, sympathized with the 
     <lb/>
     proposition. In the  few remarks I 
     <lb/>
     made at that time I said. " I agree with 
     <lb/>
     the proposition made by the ex-Attorney  
     <lb/>
     General, that if the Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cillors appointed to seats at Ottawa are 
     <lb/>
     simply to  have a property qualification 
     <lb/>
     here, it will not amount to a great deal, 
     <lb/>
     because some of them would remove to 
     <lb/>Canada, and instead of looking after our<lb/>
    interests they would be looking after 
     <lb/>the interests of the Canadians, for it is 
     <lb/>natural to suppose that a man would be 
     <lb/>most interested in the place in which he 
     <lb/>resides. We should instruct our Dele<lb break="no"/>gates in unmistakable terms that it 
     <lb/>should be provided in the Scheme that 
     <lb/>our  Legislative Councillors should both 
     <lb/>reside and have  their property qualifi<lb break="no"/>cation in this Province.  If this idea is 
     <lb/>not carried out I shall think it was the 
     <lb/>fault of our Delegates and not of the<lb/>
           

            <cb/>
         

     Canadians, because  it is immaterial to 
     <lb/>
     them whether they reside here or there." 
     <lb/>
     My opinion then was plain and distinct 
     <lb/>
     on the question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.—My hon. and 
     <lb/>
     learned friend (Mr. Smith) was wrong 
     <lb/>
     in  reference to the general opinion ex<lb break="no"/>pressed by  the House at that time. The 
     <lb/>
     general feeling  of the House was that 
     <lb/>
     the Legislative Councillors should re<lb break="no"/>side in the Province. When the para<lb break="no"/>graph was read in  reference to the ap<lb break="no"/>pointment of Legislative Councillors in 
     <lb/>
     Lower Canada there was a general 
     <lb/>
     concurrence in the opinion that the 
     <lb/>Legislative Councillors should be re<lb break="no"/>quired to live in the Province.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName>.—My hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Kerr) refers to Nova Scotia as hav<lb break="no"/>ing reduced her representation to two 
     <lb/>members for each County. This would<lb/>
    act very unfairly here, as it would give 
     <lb/>the small Counties all the advantages. 
     <lb/>Neither would it be right to take repre<lb break="no"/>sentation by population, upon the terms  
     <lb/>of the Bill, as that would be doing great<lb/>injustice to the small Counties, for any 
     <lb/>County having  less than 1500 inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants would only have one representa<lb break="no"/>tive. It is the length of the Session<lb/>more than the number of members which<lb/>causes the increased expenses  of the 
     <lb/>Legislature. In 1851 when the repre<lb break="no"/>sentation was the same as it is now the 
     <lb/>expenses of the Legislature were $32,<lb break="no"/>000, whilst in 1866 the expenses were 
     <lb/> $41,000 ; no doubt but the latter session 
     <lb/>was much longer than the former, on 
     <lb/>account of the increased business they 
     <lb/>had to do. Our business will be much 
     <lb/>decreased, and we will have only local 
     <lb/>matters to attend to, therefore our ses<lb break="no"/>sion need not exceed forty days. There 
     <lb/>will be less  expenditure about the House 
     <lb/>for Coaches, &amp;c. ; there will be a less 
     <lb/>amount of printing done, and this will 
     <lb/>reduce our  expenditure very materially. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>.—  Every hon. member 
     <lb/>says retrenchment is necessary, but no 
     <lb/>one is ready to begin. All have admitted 
     <lb/>that something should be done, but they 
     <lb/>do not tell us what that something is. 
     <lb/>Some people try to get all they can, and 
     <lb/>they have no conscience unless the law 
     <lb/>gives it to them. They have their $2,400  
     <lb/>a year, and then are off on their pleasure 
     <lb/>excursions at  $10 a day more. It is a 
     <lb/>regular grab   game all round. A man 
     <lb/>tries to hold on all he can get, and then 
     <lb/>get as much more as he can—that prin<lb break="no"/>ciple is carried out in dual representation. 
     <lb/>One man wants to have one office here, 
     <lb/>and another in Canada, just as if there 
     <lb/>was not a man here fit for the  office except 
     <lb/>the present Attorney General. I never 
     <lb/>sought an office, and if I did I would not 
     <lb/>get it. So far as the Government is con<lb break="no"/>cerned, if they manage the affairs of the 
     <lb/> country properly, they shall have my  
     <lb/>
          

            <pb n="66" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-22_Page_066.jpg"/>
        

    <fw type="num">66</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw>  
 

     support, but if they fail to do that they    
     <lb/>shall have my opposition. I believe jus<lb break="no"/>tice should be done to every section of<lb/>the country, and this Bill provides that<lb/>the representation shall be upon a fair<lb/>basis, and I cannot see any force in the<lb/>objections taken to it, but I shall have no<lb/>objection to reporting progress, in order<lb/>to allow members time to consider the<lb/>question<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FLEW2">Mr. W. P. FLEWELLING</persName> moved an<lb/>amendment to the Bill, which provided<lb/>that the representation for each County<lb/>now having four representatives should<lb/>be reduced to three, thus reducing the<lb/>whole number of members to thirty-<lb break="yes"/>six.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Progress was then reported upon the<lb/>Bill, and leave asked to sit again.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>, by command of 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency the Administrator of the 
     <lb/>
     Government. laid before the House the 
     <lb/>
     Report of the Delegation to England to 
     <lb/>
     arrange for a Union of the British North 
     <lb/>
     American Provinces. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     (<hi rendition="simple:italic">Report will appear in Appendix.</hi>)    
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Hon. Mr. CONNELL</persName> presented a Pe<lb break="no"/>tition from the Warden and Councillors<lb/>of the Municipality of Carleton County,<lb/>praying that an Act may pass to abolish<lb/>the office of Secretary Treasurer, and au<lb break="no"/>thorize them to appoint a Secretary and<lb/>Treasurer in lieu thereof.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> brought in a " Bill<lb/>to amend an Act entitled an Act to in<lb break="no"/>corporate the People's Bank of New<lb/>Brunswick."<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> brought in a "Bill    
     <lb/>to incorporate the Governors of the Wig<lb break="no"/>gins Male Orphan Institution."<lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> moved that the "Bill 
     <lb/>to repeal certain sections of a Law rela<lb break="no"/>ting to the election of Representatives to<lb/>serve in the General Assembly and to<lb/>make other provisions in lieu thereof,"<lb/>be referred to a select Committee.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Resolution adopted, and Bill referred<lb/>to Messrs. Lindsay, Chandler, Wetmore,<lb/>Young, Betsford, Sutton, Thompson.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion the House adjourned until<lb/>10 o'clock to-morrow.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">T.P.D.<lb/>
            </p>
   
<!-- GL, 2018-04-18, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->



            <!--<p>
      THURSDAY, May 23.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The following Bills were read a second  
     <lb/>time :<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      A Bill to authorise the Trustees of   
     <lb/>Saint Andrews Church, Chatham, to sell<lb/>or otherwise dispose of the old Church<lb/>of Saint Andrews, in Chatham.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     
     A Bill to amend the Act to Incorporate     
     <lb/>the People's Bank of New Brunswick,<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to Incorporate the Governors of<lb/>the Wiggins' Male Orphan Institution.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The following Bills were read a third       
     <lb/>time :<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     A Bill relating to Public Burial Grounds 
     <lb/>In the Town of Saint Andrews.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to amend the law relating to<lb/>Municipalities.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to authorize the City Council of<lb/>the City of Fredericton to raise monies,<lb/>bu way of loan, for the erection of a<lb/>Market House in the said City.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>PROCLAMATION OF UNION.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.—Mr. Speaker, I<lb/>have just received a note and telegram<lb/>containing the information that the pro<lb break="no"/>clamation of Union has been issued,<lb/>which, by permission of the House, I<lb/>will read.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>THURSDAY MORNING<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>My Dear Sir :<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The enclosed arrived last night, but I<lb/>have only this moment received it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>You will see that the General received<lb/>it in St. John.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I am, yours faithfully,<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>G.N. CAMPBELL.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Honorable S.L. TILLEY.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>BY CABLE.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MAJOR GENERAL DOYLE,<lb/>Fredericton, New Brunswick,<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A proclamation uniting, on the first of<lb/>July next, the three Provinces, has this<lb/>day been approved by the Queen In<lb/>Council.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>DUKE OF BUCKINGHAM AND CHANDOS.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Colonial Office, London, May 22nd.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—We received that intelli,<lb/>gence last night in the papers by the<lb/>way of Canada. I will now follow up<lb/>this information by enquiring of the<lb/>Secretary the names of the persons com<lb break="no"/>posing the Senate.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.—When we get the<lb/>Proclamation the names will be made<lb/>known.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—This is a clear evasion<lb/>of the question. To any mind it is a<lb/>most extraordinary thing that the Pro<lb break="no"/>clamation of Union should be issued,<lb/>twelve men appointed to represent this<lb/>Province in the Senate, and yet the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment refuse to let the House and the<lb/>country know who they are. If the in<lb break="no"/>formation is not given I shall move a re<lb break="no"/>solution with regard to it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.— The question of<lb/>the hon. member is entirely premature.<lb/>No reliable information has yet been re<lb break="no"/>ceived by the Government, but as soon as<lb/>it arrives not an hour will be delayed<lb/>in laying it before the House,<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I know the Secretary<lb/>cannot say whether the list they have<lb/>sent home has actually been inserted in<lb/>the proclamation, but he can say who the<lb/>Government have recommended. Various<lb/>rumours are afloat as to the names of<lb/>Senators, and yet although the procla<lb break="no"/>mation is now made known containing<lb/>the list of Senators, the Secretary refuses<lb/>to let the House and country know who<lb/>have been recommended to Her Majesty<lb/>as fit men to represent this Province in<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
    

    

    

    

    

    

            <p>
     the Upper House of the General Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment. There is another question which<lb/>the crown officers should answer, and<lb/>that is whether those who are appointed<lb/>from the Legislative Council and this<lb/>House can retain their seats now the<lb/>proclamation is issued. This is a point<lb/>of great importance. and should be well<lb/>defined, so that we may know whether<lb/>they are still in a position to legislate for<lb/>this country. I am aware that I have no<lb/>physical power to make the Government<lb/>answer the questions I put, but the<lb/>country will now know why it is the in<lb break="no"/>formation is not given, and with whom<lb/>the responsibility rests.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. MR. TILLEY</persName>.— I am no lawyer,   
     <lb/>and do not therefore pretend to give a<lb/>legal opinion, but I can express my con<lb break="no"/>viction that nothing in the Imperial Act<lb/>precludes those who are appointed to the<lb/>Senate, from holding their seats till the<lb/>first of July. It is a subject for the<lb/>Crown lawyers, and when the proclama<lb break="no"/>tion is received it can be looked into and<lb/>decided.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>PETITIONS, BILLS, ETC.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> presented a Petition<lb/>from the Executors of the late Stephen<lb/>Wiggins, and the Governors appointed<lb/>under his Will, praying to be Incorpora<lb break="no"/>ted for the purpose of establishing a Male<lb/>Orphan Institution.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Petition received the laid on the<lb/>table.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. CHANDLER said that he had<lb/>been requested to ask that leave of ab<lb break="no"/>sence, till Monday next, be granted to<lb/>Messrs. Hibbard and Lindsay the for<lb break="no"/>mer being called away on urgent busi<lb break="no"/>ness, and the latter having to return<lb/>home on account of sickness.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Leave was accordingly granted.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> moved for leave to<lb/>bring in a Bill to re-establish the Court<lb/>of Chancery in this Province.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Leave granted and the Bill being<lb/>brought in was read a first time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> moved for leave to<lb/>bring in a Bill to increase the capital<lb/>stock of the Saint Stephen Bank.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Leave granted and the Bill belong<lb/>brought in was read a first time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>TRADES' ASSOCIATION.<lb/>Hon. Mr. TILLEY moved the House<lb/>into Committee on a Bill to Incorporate<lb/>the Saint John Trades' Co-operative As<lb break="no"/>sociation<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. BOTSFORD</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.—Hon. members 
     <lb/>will observe that this Act proposes to<lb/>Incorporate certain persons who desire<lb/>to be associated together for their mutual<lb/>benefit. These co-operative societies<lb/>have been established in various parts of<lb/>England, ad though in some cases they<lb/>have not worked well, yet in many others<lb/>they have succeeded in a marvellous<lb/>manner, hundreds of thousands of punds<lb/>being accumulated by mechanics and<lb/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>