<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-07-03"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-07-03">3 July 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="66" to="73"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_066.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_067.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_068.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_069.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_070.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_071.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_072.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_073.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_066">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_066.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_067">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_067.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_068">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_068.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_069">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_069.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_070">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_070.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_071">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_071.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_072">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_072.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_073">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_073.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="66" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_066.jpg"/>
       

     <fw type="num">66</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 
    

<!-- GL, 2018-03-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

    <!-- made on the REsolution, he meant that 
     <lb/>the Government would Confederate New<lb/>Brunswick and Canada if Nova Scotia did<lb/>not come in.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL was 
     <lb/>not aware that he had said any thing of<lb/>the kind, but the hon. member for St.<lb/>John (Mr. skinner) had asked the ques<lb break="no"/>tion, and he told him that he could not<lb/>say what the delegates would do. He<lb/>supposed they would do what they con<lb break="no"/>sidered best under the circumstances.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> thought the country should 
     <lb/>have some information on the subject.<lb/>The Attorney General had said that if<lb/>Nova Scotia did not come in, then Saint<lb/>John would be made the terminus of the<lb/>Inter-colonial Railway, and thus she<lb/>would be force to Confederate. He<lb/>would not ask if the Government would<lb/>pursue such a course?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. Mr. WILMOT did not see any<lb/>necessity for such a question, as Nova<lb/>Scotia had agreed to appoint delegates.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said that was only the 
     <lb/>action of the House, and not of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple. They would send home a delega<lb break="no"/>tion, and Mr. Howe would be heard at<lb/>the bar of the House of Commons and in<lb/>the Halls of St. Stephen. They ahd sent<lb/>home petitions signed by thousands ask<lb break="no"/>ing that no Union should take plaace till<lb/>after the dissolution of the House.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL said 
     <lb/>the mater would be for the deliberation<lb/>of the delegates. It was something in<lb/>the future and a contingency that might<lb/>never arise.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. CHANDLER supposed the mean<lb break="no"/>ing of what the Attorney General said<lb/>was that it was a circumstance whose<lb/>probability was so remote that there was<lb/>time enough to think and talk about it.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> thought the hon. member 
     <lb/>for Charlotte must be the 10th member of<lb/>the Government.<lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>JUSTICE IN EQUITY.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILL1">HON. Mr. WILLISTON</persName> moved the<lb/>House into Committee of the Whole on a<lb/>Bill relating to Justice in Equity. Mr.<lb/>BAbbitt in the chair. Some hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers thought this Bill should be laid over<lb/>till the next meeting of the legislature,<lb/>others were opposed to certain of its pro<lb break="no"/>visions, while others again thought the<lb/>Bill should pass. It had been in Commit<lb break="no"/>tee before, and after discussion on the<lb/>second section by the legal members of<lb/>the House it was agreed to with certain<lb/>amendments.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House adjourned till to-morrow<lb/>morning at 9 o'clock.<lb/>J.M.<lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <head rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, July 3.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName> brought in a Bill<lb/>entitled "A Bill relating to the City of<lb/>Fredericton."<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
    

            <p>The House in Committee passed the<lb/>following Bills, vis:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"A Bill to incorporate the CAulkers<lb/>Association in the City of St. John."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"A Bill to authorize the extension of<lb/>St. John STreet from Duke Street to<lb/>Reed's Point Wharf."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CAIE1">Mr. CAIE</persName> brought in a Bill entitled<lb/>"A Bill to provide for the more effec<lb break="no"/>tual repairing of Roads and Bridges in<lb/>the Parish of Carleton, County of Kent."<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    <div type="section">

    
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CONNECTION OF RAILWAY LINES 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The Select Committee appionted to 
     <lb/>take into consideration "A Bill to<lb/>authorize the connectino of Railway<lb/>lines, and to provide for the manage<lb break="no"/>ment of connecting lines of Railway in<lb/>this Province," having reccommended<lb/>the passing of the same ; the House re<lb break="no"/>solved itself into a Committee of the<lb/>Whole ( <persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName> in the chair)<lb/>to take the Bill into consideration.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> said he had derived<lb/>his information in preparing this Bil<lb/>from similar Acts which had passed<lb/>in Canada and in the State of Main. He<lb/>had submitted the Bill to the Attorney<lb/>of the St. Andrew's and Woodstock<lb/>Railway Company, and he had seen<lb/>nothing in the Bill but would recom<lb break="no"/>mend itself to the judgment of the hon.<lb/>members of the House. There were<lb/>connecting lines of Railway being built<lb/>in the Province, and it was necessary<lb/>in order to the effectual working of<lb/>those lines that provision should be<lb/>made, in case any difficulty should<lb/>occur, that they should be compelled to<lb/>allow the connection to be made. It<lb/>also makes a provision to compel them<lb/>to take freight from one line to the<lb/>other without transhipment, and regu<lb break="no"/>lates the rate of charges for carrying<lb/>such freight. These are the provisions<lb/>of the Bill. He did not anticipate much<lb/>trouble, but it might arise, therefore it<lb/>it was better to have a law of this kind.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said he was on the<lb/>Select Committee, and had raed this<lb/>Bill over carefully, and had made some<lb/>suggestions which were adopted. He<lb/>had no dobut but that the Bill was all<lb/>right, but still he would like to restrict<lb/>the Bill to two years. During that time<lb/>the St. Stephen's line would be the<lb/>only line that would be affected by it.<lb/>If the time was extended other Railway<lb/>Companies would say, we built our lines<lb/>under certain rights then existing, and<lb/>you have no right to modify them. You<lb/>held out certain rights and we thought<lb/>we would always enjoy them in per<lb break="no"/>petuity. They had better restrict it to<lb/>two years, and then if it works well<lb/>you could continue it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> would agree with<lb/>that, for if the Bill was good it could be<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
          
re-enacted. He then moved this addi<lb break="no"/>tional section: "That this Act shall<lb/>continue in operation for three years<lb/>from the passing of the same."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill with the additional section<lb/>was agree to.<lb/>
            </p>

    </div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE IN SUPPLY - NAVIGATION IM<lb break="no"/>PROVEMENTS.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> in speaking upon the<lb/>Resolution for appropriating $750 for<lb/>the improvement of the navigation on<lb/>the River St. John, and $250 for the<lb/>improvement of the Miramichi River,<lb/>said that he doubted the propriety of<lb/>appropriating the publicmoney for the<lb/>purpose of enabling the lumbermen to<lb/>drive their logs down the Miramichi<lb/>River; they should clear it out at their<lb/>own expense. If there was anything<lb/>required to improve the navigation of<lb/>the River St. John, he would have no<lb/>objection to it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SUTT1">Mr. SUTTON</persName> said if anything was<lb/>proposed that was going to benefit the<lb/>County of Northumberland hi hon.<lb/>friend (Mr. Smith) was sure to oppose<lb/>it. He was willing to support the grant<lb/>for the St. John River, but was going<lb/>to oppose the grant to Miramichi. This<lb/>he did not consider fair play, for the<lb/>grant was needed there to enable tow<lb/>boats to proceed up the river, and not<lb/>for the purpose of enabling parties to<lb/>drive logs.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> said he thought<lb/>£10,000 on the River St. John was a<lb/>small expenditure. If that sum would<lb/>secure them a daily steamer between<lb/>Fredericton and Woodstock as long as<lb/>the river was open, it would be money<lb/>wisely expended. Every description of<lb/>produce would then come down the<lb/>River, and this would be a great benefit<lb/>to St. John. He believed if they grant<lb break="no"/>ed a small sum of money from time to<lb/>time they would attain that end.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILL1">Hon. Mr. WILLSTON</persName> said there<lb/>were parties who were willing to form<lb/>themselves into a company for the pur<lb break="no"/>pose of putting a steamboat on the<lb/>Miramichi River, and they would be<lb/>derelict in their duty if they did not<lb/>grant this small sum to improve it<lb/>navigation.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Hon. Mr. CONNELL</persName> supported the<lb/>Resolution.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BEVE1">Mr. BEVERIDGE</persName> was very sorry the 
     <lb/>sum proposed was not larger. The St.<lb/>
         

            <pb n="67" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_067.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>    <fw type="num">67</fw> 
  

     John River was a much entitled to 
     <lb/>have money expended upon it as were<lb/>the great roads, for it was a means of<lb/>communication, and bit it the farmers<lb/>took their produce to market and the<lb/>merchants brought their goods up. He<lb/>thought they should have had a small<lb/>grant to improve the Tobique, as a<lb/>small grant would have enabled the<lb/>lumbermen to run their rafts down.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:RYAN1">Mr. RYAN</persName> felt inclined to go for the 
     <lb/>appropriations; the finances of the<lb/>Province belonged to the people, and<lb/>all parts of the Province had a right to<lb/>share in them. He found the House<lb/>generally had a desire to provide the<lb/>funds for improvements where they<lb/>were needed. If the people on the<lb/>river allowed their share of the publice<lb/>money to be spent in improving the<lb/>river, there should be not objection<lb/>made.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - They get their share<lb/>besides.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:RYAN1">Mr. RYAN</persName>. - My hon. friend must<lb/>bear in mind that we have our Railway<lb/>which all the Province helped to build.<lb/>In making public improvements it did<lb/>not matter if one portion of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince did not receive more than other parts.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILM1">Hon. Mr. WILMOT</persName> supported the<lb/>Resolution.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName> said that both the<lb/>River St. John and the River Mirami<lb break="no"/>chi were public highways in the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. Some parts of the River St.<lb/>John went through a sandy soil, and<lb/>the raid current occasioned bars.<lb/>They had not sufficient funds to narrow<lb/>the river, therefore they had to dredge<lb/>it through those bars, and the spring<lb/>tides frequently filled them up in a<lb/>single year. Before they becoem solid<lb/>it is much less expense to clear them<lb/>out again; that is why it is necessary<lb/>to have a grant every year. The sum<lb/>of $750 was a mere bagatelle to what<lb/>they should have been here and the<lb/>Canadian lines. They should have<lb/>$7000 instead $700. Again on the<lb/>Miramichi River this grant was not<lb/>solely for the purpose of enabling them<lb/>to run rafts down the River, but to en<lb break="no"/>able them to run towboats of about five<lb/>ton burden. $250 was a very small<lb/>grant for that river, but it would im<lb break="no"/>prove it a little.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> knew the grant<lb/>was not as much as it would be, but<lb/>they had to limit according tot he means<lb/>at their disposal. A grant of money<lb/>had been given from time to time to<lb/>improve the Upper St. John in the re<lb break="no"/>moval of some obstructions between<lb/>Fredericton and Woodstock, and some<lb/>rocks between there and the Grand<lb/>Falls, and he considered this money<lb/>would be well expended.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName> said there had been a<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
          

     grant of $5,000 made to improve 
     <lb/>Bathurst Harbor in 1861. He would<lb/>ask the Provincial Secretary whether<lb/>that grant was available now. There<lb/>had never been a cent of money spent<lb/>in dredging Bathurst Harbor.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said the appropria<lb break="no"/>tion was made as far back as 1854, and<lb/>the Government still have power to autho<lb break="no"/>rize its expenditure. It was found that<lb/>the limited sum appropriated would not<lb/>produce the desired result, and for this<lb/>reason it was not appropriated. When<lb/>Confederation is carried out the General<lb/>Government will make those harbor im<lb break="no"/>provements. Resolutions adopted.<lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">IMPROVEMENTS OF APPROACHES TO FERRY<lb/>LANDING IN ST. JOHN.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> moved that $400 be<lb/>appropriated for the improvement of ap<lb break="no"/>proaches to Ferry Landing St. John.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said the Corporation of<lb/>St. John derived a large revenue from<lb/>that ferry; the Lessee also made some £2<lb break="no"/>000 a-year from it. They had never been<lb/>asked for this before. They might just as<lb/>well give the Corporation aso much money<lb/>as to make this grant.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>. This is not the<lb/>first time a sum has been appropriated by<lb/>the Legislature of New Brunswick for<lb/>this purpose. We had the dredging ma<lb break="no"/>chine to work there which cost us more<lb/>money than we now propose to give. At<lb/>low water the boat has to do down to<lb/>Sand Point, which causes great <choice><sic>inconve<lb break="no"/>ience</sic><corr>inconvenience</corr></choice>. The people of St. John receive a<lb/>very small portion of the public money<lb/>for roads and education to what other<lb/>parts of the Province do, and this is a<lb/>very small sum asked for, considereing the<lb/>large expenditure the Corporation has<lb/>made and the convenience it will be to<lb/>the public.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. This is a private pro<lb break="no"/>perty belonging to the Corporation of St.<lb/>John, and they make a great deal of mo<lb break="no"/>ney out of it, for they have a great mono<lb break="no"/>poly. It is not like the Ferry on this<lb/>River where any person can get an Act<lb/>passed by the Legislature and establish a<lb/>Ferry; because there they have not other<lb/>place to establish a ferry. He thought it<lb/>was an entirely new grant, for he did not<lb/>think there had been any money appro<lb break="no"/>priated for that purpose before, even if<lb/>there had, a wrong done then would not<lb/>justify their doing wrong now. He had<lb/>always been disposed to do St. John the<lb/>fullest justice and to give his support to<lb/>anything that was for the benefit of St.<lb/>John if it was fair and legitimate; but he<lb/>could not see how they could justify this<lb/>expenditure. The Corporation of St.<lb/>John should advance a portion of the<lb/>profits derived from that source to make<lb/>the necessary improvements. ( <persName ref="pers:ANON1">A mem<lb break="no"/>
        

            <cb/>
 
ber</persName>. The House gave £5,000 to buld 
     <lb/>the Petiteodiac Bridge.) He had never<lb/>asked for it, and was perfectly amazed<lb/>when he saw the appropriation agreed to<lb/>by the Committee. He had always given<lb/>the credit of getting that appropriation<lb/>to the Chief Commissioner. He thought<lb/>it had been promised to him for giving<lb/>the Inter-colonial Railway his hearty sup<lb break="no"/>port.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">HON. Mr. TILLEY</persName>. It was asked for 
     <lb/>by the representatives of Albert and<lb/>Westmorland.<lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said he had not asked for 
     <lb/>it, but he believed it was got through the<lb/>agency of he Inter-colonial Railway.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:RYAN1">Mr. RYAN</persName> said the matter was 
     <lb/>brought up from time to time and rejec<lb break="no"/>ted, but at length passed, and no doubt<lb/>the Inter-colonial Railway aided this in<lb/>some way, but not in the way the hon.<lb/>member for Westorland says. When<lb/>it is proposed to build a Railway it will<lb/>always lead to some other expenditure.<lb/>He had thought it a large appropriation<lb/>and had had a conversation with Mr.<lb/>Steadman about it, and come to the con<lb break="no"/>clusion to go for it. With regard to the<lb/>appropriation for St. John, the whole mo<lb break="no"/>ney is laid out for the benefit of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple, and it is the people who pay it and<lb/>they have a right to appropriate it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> said he understood the<lb/>people had subscribed largely for the<lb/>Petitcodiac Bridge, and he could assure<lb/>them that it was not to further the pas<lb break="no"/>sage of the Inter-colonial Railway Bill<lb/>that the appropriation was made. It ap<lb break="no"/>peared to him that the Corporation had<lb/>as much right to ask them to cut downs<lb/>some of the rocks in the streets as to<lb/>ask them to make this appropriation. It<lb/>was property from which they derived an<lb/>annual rent, and the person who had it<lb/>was making money out of it. The City<lb/>of St. John was already received back in<lb/>grants to the health of teh City and a<lb/>great variety of other things, a large<lb/>share of the amount they contributed.<lb/>By her position she has derived more be<lb break="no"/>nefits from the European and North Ame<lb break="no"/>rican Railway than any other part of the<lb/>Province, and therefore he thought she<lb/>had received her full share of teh public<lb/>revenue according to the population.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> said at one time the<lb/>Corporation run the Ferry Boats on their<lb/>own account, and they found that the<lb/>wear and tear took up all the profits.<lb/>They then come to the conclusion to<lb/>rent the property, and they find the boats and<lb/>keep them in repair. In the next place<lb/>the City of St. John was taxed to the<lb/>extent of $6000 to make this improve<lb break="no"/>ment, and while the taxes are increasing<lb/>the rents are not. The people of St.<lb/>John consume a large proportion of du<lb break="no"/>tiable goods and they were entitled to a fair<lb/>share of the public revenue, particular<lb break="no"/>
     

            <pb n="68" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_068.jpg"/>
         
<fw type="num">68</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 

ly when the y tax themselves for what is<lb/>a convenience to the travelling public at<lb/>large.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Resolution agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">PARIS EXHIBITION 1867.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">HON. Mr. TILLEY</persName> moved that $4000<lb/>be granted to enable them to prepare for<lb/>the Paris Exhibition.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said that small sum of 
     <lb/>money would do no good, but would<lb/>place them in a mean position and would<lb/>not enable them to make a respectable<lb/>show at all. Canada and Nova Scotia<lb/>had expended large sums in preparing<lb/>for this Exhibition, and that would only<lb/>make us appear more ridiculous.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">HON. Mr. TILLEY</persName>. If the sum pro<lb break="no"/>posed did not cover all expenses, they<lb/>might make a further grant at the enxt<lb/>meeting of the House. There was a pos<lb break="no"/>sibility that this Exhibition might not be<lb/>carried on, for a European war may arise<lb/>and prevent the arrangements being car<lb break="no"/>ried out, but if it should be carried on it<lb/>was thought that $8000 would be required,<lb/>and it was thought necessary that the<lb/>Government should have the power to<lb/>expend $4000 the present season in mak<lb break="no"/>ing such arrangements as were deemed<lb/>requisite. In 1862 they spent a large<lb/>sum of money in the production of arti<lb break="no"/>cles that ie was impossible for them to<lb/>get up in a sgood a style as they did in<lb/>Europe. Their great object was to show<lb/>the natural productions of the country - <lb/>such as the minerals, fruit, fisheries and<lb/>cereals; for every thing of that kind was<lb/>anxiously sought for. We would not<lb/>like to see a blank at the Paris Exhibi<lb break="no"/>bition where New Brunswick ought to be,<lb/>therefore, this sum was asked for to ena<lb break="no"/>ble them to show the natural productions<lb/>of the country.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> said if they went into Con<lb break="no"/>federation it was not necessary that the<lb/>seperate Provinces should be represented,<lb/>but only the Confederacy, and the duty<lb/>of making provision for its representa<lb break="no"/>tion would devolve upon the General<lb/>Government. The United States send<lb/>their products to the Exhibition as the<lb/>products of the United States, and not as<lb/>the products of each seperate State, and<lb/>it should be the same way in the Confed<lb break="no"/>eracy; the only question was whether<lb/>they would go into Confederation in the<lb/>mean time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">HON. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said he looked<lb/>upon Confederation as a fixed fact; but<lb/>the time when this Union was to take<lb/>place was not settled, therefore, in the<lb/>mean time, some steps must be taken<lb/>this season in order that notice should<lb/>be given of what was to be done and<lb/>what the nature of the collection should<lb/>be.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said the Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary had now intimated that this Exhi<lb break="no"/>
         

            <cb/>
          
bition would cost a great deal of money;<lb/>he trusted they would not exceed the<lb/>amount proposed before the next meet<lb break="no"/>ing of the Legislature. He believed it<lb/>would be productive of no good. He<lb/>thought the interests of New Brunswick<lb/>had not suffered by not being represen<lb break="no"/>ted at the Dublin Exhibition. Nova<lb/>Scotia could send coal and gold there<lb/>which we could not. (A member. We<lb/>have the Albert coal.) What good will<lb/>the country derive from sending it there?<lb/>It is beautiful to look at but the supply<lb/>is limited. The money would be more<lb/>beneficially expended in the Province. In<lb/>view of the extraordinary expenses incur<lb break="no"/>red in the defence of the country they<lb/>had better appropriate it for their local<lb/>wants.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILM1">HON. Mr. WILMOT</persName> said that our be<lb break="no"/>ing represented at the Paris Exhibition<lb/>would have the effect of developing our<lb/>trade with France, for a trade had spring<lb/>up with that country within a very few<lb/>years. We know that the Emperor of<lb/>France is anxious to extend the trade be<lb break="no"/>tween that country and the Colonies, and<lb/>he has placed Canada in a better position<lb/>in that respect than he has other countries.<lb/>He has reduced the duty on ships from<lb/>twenty-two francs to two. If we never<lb/>try to show what we have we never will<lb/>be any thing. In Canada they are de<lb break="no"/>termined to make an excellent show, and<lb/>they are going to do the same in Nova<lb/>Scotia. He was told in Liverpool that if<lb/>we opened a communication with France<lb/>we would find a fetter market for certain<lb/>descriptions of our wood than we had<lb/>at present. Our trade had been extend<lb break="no"/>ed with South America and Cuba, and<lb/>we should endeavor to extend it wher<lb break="no"/>ever they could find a market for our pro<lb break="no"/>ducts.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Chairman then left the chair and<lb/>reported that the Resolutions for Supply<lb/>had been agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">HON. Mr. TILLEY</persName> brought in "A Bill<lb/>to provide for the repair and improve<lb break="no"/>ment of other public works and services."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Also a Bill to provide for defraying<lb/>certain expenses of the Civil Government<lb/>of the Province.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. Skinner</persName> "A Bill to<lb/>incorporate the International Telegraph<lb/>Company' was referred to a Select Com<lb break="no"/>mittee.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">SURVEY OF RAILWAY.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:LEWI1">Mr. Lewis</persName> the House<lb/>went into Committee on the following Re<lb break="no"/>solution: - <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>- "That an humble Address<lb/>be presented to His Excellency the Lieu<lb break="no"/>tenant Governor praying His Excellency<lb/>to make provision for the expenses of a<lb/>Survey made for a Branch Railway con<lb break="no"/>necting Hillsborough i the County of<lb/>Albert with the European and North Ame<lb break="no"/>rican Railway, provided such Survey and<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
locality be approved by the Governor in<lb/>
Council."</p></quote>

            <p><persName ref="pers:CHAN1">Mr. CHANDLER</persName> in the chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LEWI1">Mr. LEWIS</persName> said that under the "Fa<lb break="no"/>cilities Act' passed in 1864, provision was<lb/>made for the construction of a Railway<lb/>in the County of Alber to connect with<lb/>the Europe and North American line.<lb/>During the last winter they had employed<lb/>Engineers in making a survey of the<lb/>line, and as it was usual in other cases<lb/>they now ask to be remunerated for the<lb/>expenses of the survey of this Branch<lb/>Railway. He thought the Resolution<lb/>would commend itself to the House.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">HON. Mr. TILLEY</persName> - said the ex<lb break="no"/>pense of the Survey would be deducted<lb/>from the subsidy when the road was built,<lb/>as that was the provision made in all the<lb/>lines of Railway built under the "Faci<lb break="no"/>lity Bill." This REsolution was only<lb/>putting that line in the same position as<lb/>other Branches were in, with the excep<lb break="no"/>tion of the Miramichi Branch. The oth<lb break="no"/>ers having been surveyed with the un<lb break="no"/>derstanding that the value of the Survey<lb/>would be deducted from the subsidy. He<lb/>could see no reason why this Branch<lb/>should not have the same privilege as the<lb/>others.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. BOTSFORD</persName> asked if the survey 
     <lb/>was to be confined to one locality.<lb/>There was a better route and it was not<lb/>right to confine the survey to the pre<lb break="no"/>sent line when there was a more eligi<lb break="no"/>ble one. In the route proposed there<lb/>were a great many more ingineering<lb/>difficulties than there were in the other<lb/>route. He spoke from experience, and<lb/>he had also been told that this was the<lb/>case by the engineer who had been on<lb/>the route.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> wasid the Government had 
     <lb/>power to make certain surveys with<lb/>certain objects in view ini regard to the<lb/>other branch lines, but in the County of<lb/>Albert they had made a survey without<lb/>any authority from the Government,<lb/>and they now ask the Government to<lb/>adopt that survey. In addition to this<lb/>we are told by my hon. friend (Mr.<lb/>Botsford) from the County of West<lb break="no"/>morland that a route can be obtained<lb/>which would be more advantageous<lb/>than the one surveyed. Is this House<lb/>to pay for experimental surveys? Are<lb/>we to pass this resolution without<lb/>knowing whether the money has been<lb/>judiciously expended or not? Suppose<lb/>that survey turns out to be worthless noth<lb break="no"/>ing, and the line is not built upon it,<lb/>this money would be thrown away.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCMI1">HON. Mr. McMILLAN</persName> was informed<lb/>that there was a Company formed to<lb/>build this line. Why then did they<lb/>come to the House and ask them to pay<lb/>for this survey, for it would have to be<lb/>deducted from the subsidy? The Go<lb break="no"/>vernment were to give a subsidy of<lb/>
        

            <pb n="69" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_069.jpg"/>
           

<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">69</fw>
       


     $10,000 a mile, and this was as much     
     <lb/>as the finances of the country would<lb/>
     justify them to do. He thought the 
     <lb/>
     whole principle was wrong, and he 
     <lb/>hoped the House would not sustain such<lb/>a proposition.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Mr. MCCLELAN</persName> said that although a 
     <lb/>
     Company had been organized, the sur<lb break="no"/>vey had not been made at their instiga<lb break="no"/>tion. The survey had been made with<lb/>a view of showing the facilities that<lb/>could be afforded for constructing the<lb/>line. The resolution does not contem<lb break="no"/>plate that the Government shall bear<lb/>the expense if they do not approve of<lb/>the survey. If the survey was paid for<lb/>the other lines of Railway, he could see<lb/>no force in the arguments that this<lb/>should not be paid for because already<lb/>surveyed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SUTT1">Mr. SUTTON</persName> asked if his hon. friend<lb/>would be willing to carry out a resolu<lb break="no"/>tion providing to pay the expenses of<lb/>the survey of the line from Chatham to<lb/>Shediac, which would cost thousands of<lb/>pounds.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said if this reso<lb break="no"/>lution be carried it would place every<lb/>section of the Province in the same<lb/>position in regard to building those<lb/>
     lines of railway. His hon. friend (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Sutton) had a survey made in his sec<lb break="no"/>tion by Major Robinson, and a Company<lb/>could start to morrow and go on<lb/>with the work with the information they<lb/>have now before them. The resolution<lb/>authorizing the Government to make<lb/>surveys was passed in order to enable<lb/>them to send engineers to make sur<lb break="no"/>veys, so that capitalists could make cal<lb break="no"/>culations as to the cost before entering<lb/>upon the work. In regard to this reso<lb break="no"/>lution, the inhabitants of the district<lb/>went to work upon their own responsi<lb break="no"/>bility, having no authority from the<lb/>Legislature, and made a preliminary<lb/>survey, and they now ask to be put in<lb/>the same position as the others. They<lb/>have shown more energy in the matter<lb/>than was done by the others in going<lb/>to work upon their own responsibility<lb/>and it was equitable and fair that we<lb/>should adopt this resolution, giving<lb/>them the same privilege that was ac<lb break="no"/>corded to the other branches<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said the Subsidy Act re<lb break="no"/>quired that the contract should be made<lb/>with the Queen. The Government were<lb/>authorized to have a survey made of<lb/>the different branches, and get a plan<lb/>drawn, which they could exhibit to any<lb/>Company that proposed to build the<lb/>road. In this Branch instead of the<lb/>Government taking the initiative, the<lb/>people have caused a survey to be made<lb/>and paid for it, and they have plans to<lb/>exhibit to any Company that choose to<lb/>build the road. If we refuse to pass<lb/>this resolution, we refuse that which the<lb/>
     

            <cb/>
           

     people are entitled to, and which has 
     <lb/>been given to other sections of the<lb/>country. In one case it was prelimin<lb break="no"/>ary, in another it wasex post facto. If<lb/>the survey was not approved, it would<lb/>not be paid for by the Government, as<lb/>the resolutions requires that the survey<lb/>must be approved by the Governor in<lb/>Council.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSEY</persName> thought that a Com<lb break="no"/>pany being formed to build the road,<lb/>instead of being an objection, would be<lb/>an inducement for them to pay for the<lb/>survey. He would rather see a provi<lb break="no"/>sion made in the Resolution, that the<lb/>survey would be paid when the Com<lb break="no"/>pany commenced operations. The ob<lb break="no"/>ject of the Government should be to<lb/>encourage localities to do something to<lb/>assist themselves, in order that they<lb/>might get railroads and open up com<lb break="no"/>munication with the different parts of<lb/>the Province. Every section should<lb/>have equal justice meted out to it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Hon. Mr. MCMILLAN</persName> said, suppose<lb/>the Governor in Council approved of<lb/>the survey, and no Company was form<lb break="no"/>ed to carry it out, it would be so much<lb/>money thrown away.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The resolution was adopted.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">INSTRUCTION OF DELEGATES REGARDING<lb/>THE PROVISIONS TO BE MADE IN A<lb/>MEASURE OF UNION.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> moved the following re<lb break="no"/>solution :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Whereas the House on the 30th day of<lb/>June now instant, passed the following<lb/>Resolution, viz.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That a humble Address be<lb/>presented to His Excellency the Lieut<lb break="no"/>enant Governor, plraying that His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency will be pleased to appoint<lb/>delegates to unite with delegates from<lb/>the other Provinces in arranging with<lb/>the Imperial Government for the Union<lb/>of British North America, upon such<lb/>terms as will secure the just rights and<lb/>interests of New Brunswick, accom<lb break="no"/>panied with provision for the immediate<lb/>construction of the Inter-Colonial Rail<lb break="no"/>way, each Province to have an equal<lb/>voice in such delegation, Upper and<lb/>Lower Canada to be considered as sep<lb break="no"/>arate Provinces :"<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     And whereas the authority given to 
     <lb/>
     the delegates by said Resolution, au<lb break="no"/>thorizes them to accept the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     Scheme, (so called,) or even one more 
     <lb/>prejudical to the interests of the people<lb/>of this Province ; And whereas in view<lb/>of the transcendent importance of the<lb/>subject, it is desirable that the opinion<lb/>of this House, in reference to such<lb/>Scheme, should be expressed for the<lb/>information and guidance of such dele<lb break="no"/>gates, in the preparation of any mea<lb break="no"/>sure for the Union of British North<lb/>America ; therefore<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, As the deliberate opinion of 
     <lb/>this House, that no measure for such<lb/>Union should be adopted which does<lb/>not contain the following provisions,<lb/>viz :—<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>1st.—An equal number of Legislative<lb/>Councillors for each Province.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>2d.—Such Legislative Councillors to<lb/>be required to reside in the Province<lb/>which they represent, and for which<lb/>they are appointed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>3d.—The number of Representatives<lb/>in the Federal Parliament to be limited.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>4th.—The establishment of a Court<lb/>for the determination of questions and<lb/>disputes that may arise between the<lb/>Federal and Local Governments as to<lb/>the meaning of the Act of Union.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>5th.—Exemption of this Province<lb/>from taxation for the construction and<lb/>enlargement of Canals in Upper Cana<lb break="no"/>da, and for the payment of any money<lb/>for the Mines and Minerals and Lands<lb/>of Newfoundland.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>6th.—Eighty cents per head to be on<lb/>the population as it increases, and not<lb/>to be confined to the Census of 1861.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>7th.—Securing to each of the Mari<lb break="no"/>time Provinces the right to have at<lb/>least one Executive Councillor in the<lb/>Federal Government.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>8th,—The commencing of the Inter-<lb break="yes"/>Colonial Railway before the right shall<lb/>exist to increase taxation upon the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of this Province.<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I had intended to have<lb/>made what might be considered a<lb/>labored speech on this occasion, but<lb/>being anxious to shorten the session, I<lb/>have concluded not to make any speech<lb/>at all. The various points in this reso<lb break="no"/>lution were discussed in the former de<lb break="no"/>bate on the resolution moved by the<lb/>Attorney General. I reserve my right<lb/>to make a general reply at the close of<lb/>the discussion.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>.—I move this<lb/>amendment. Strike out the whole of<lb/>the preamble, and everything after the<lb/>word resolved, and substitute :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" That the people of the Province<lb/>having after due deliberation deter<lb break="no"/>mined that a Union of British North<lb/>America was desirable, and the House<lb/>having agreed to request His Excellen<lb break="no"/>cy the Lieutenant Governor to appoint<lb/>delegates for the purpose of settling the<lb/>plan of Union upon such terms as will<lb/>secure the just rights of New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, and having confidence that the<lb/>action of His Excellency, under the ad<lb break="no"/>vice of his constitutional advisers, will<lb/>be directed to the attainment of that<lb/>end, sound policy and a due regard to<lb/>the interests of this Province require<lb/>that the responsibility of such action<lb/>should be left unfettered by any expres<lb break="no"/>sion of opinion other than what has<lb/>already been given by the people and<lb/>their representatives."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName>—Previous to taking 
     <lb/>a division of the House upon this reso<lb break="no"/>lution, or upon the amendment, I wish<lb/>to make a few remarks in explanation<lb/>not only in regard to these resolutions,<lb/>but in regard to the remarks I made on<lb/>Friday last. From the statements I<lb/>have seen in the public prints, I infer<lb/>that I have been quite misunderstood<lb/>in the position I took in the speech I<lb/>made on that occasion before the House.<lb/>This resolution now moved asks that<lb/>certain instructions should be given to<lb/>
           

            <pb n="70" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_070.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="num">70</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>   
  

     the delegates : some of these instruc<lb break="no"/>tions suit my mind and they ought to 
     <lb/>
     be given them, but not given in the 
     <lb/>
     way provided for by this resolution. I 
     <lb/>
     stated on Friday last that I would give 
     <lb/>
     the delegates certain instructions to be a 
     <lb/>
     guide to them so far as they could be 
     <lb/>
     guided, but I would not go for making 
     <lb/>
     them positive, but would leave them a 
     <lb/>
     margin to act upon. Having heard the 
     <lb/>
     opinion of the House, and knowing that 
     <lb/>
     if the delegates went to England fetter<lb break="no"/>ed by instructions which they could not 
     <lb/>
     deviate from either in the letter or in 
     <lb/>
     the spirit, I did not wish to give them 
     <lb/>
     specific instructions. unless I knew that 
     <lb/>
     what they had been instructed to pro<lb break="no"/>cure could be obtained. It has been 
     <lb/>
     said I was for giving them positive in<lb break="no"/>structions; in this I have been misun<lb break="no"/>derstood. I was for having those in<lb break="no"/>structions presented in the form of sug<lb break="no"/>gestions in order that they might be in<lb break="no"/>formed of what the House wished. and 
     <lb/>
     they would have a discretionary power 
     <lb/>
     to set. In regard to my position upon 
     <lb/>
     this Quebec Scheme, and the position I 
     <lb/>
     have taken before this Legislature, I 
     <lb/>
     have heard it remarked here and have 
     <lb/>
     seen it stated in the public prints, that 
     <lb/>
     if I held the views that I enunciated 
     <lb/>
     here I ought to have announced them 
     <lb/>
     before the last election or not announced 
     <lb/>
     them now. I dissent from that view for 
     <lb/>
     this reason. I stated here on Friday 
     <lb/>
     that I was so much in favor of Con<lb break="no"/>federation that I would agree to give 
     <lb/>
     this power to the delegates, and would 
     <lb/>
     agree to be bound by what they should 
     <lb/>
     decide upon, but I claimed the right to 
     <lb/>
     discuss the matter and give the dele<lb break="no"/>gates certain instructions. We are not 
     <lb/>
     sent here bound to accept the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     Scheme, but we were sent here to de<lb break="no"/>liberate upon the best Scheme that 
     <lb/>
     could be devised in order to secure 
     <lb/>
     Confederation, having been so returned 
     <lb/>
     to deliberate and discuss the measure, 
     <lb/>
     I claim the right, and I think it is the 
     <lb/>
     duty of the representatives here to go 
     <lb/>
     generally into the matter. and to be heard 
     <lb/>
     pro and con in order that the best 
     <lb/>
     views might be elicited upon the ques<lb break="no"/>tion. When the delegates met in 1864 
     <lb/>
     they had the advantage of discussing 
     <lb/>
     the question with closed doors, and they 
     <lb/>
     could express their views some one way 
     <lb/>
     and some another, and only the result 
     <lb/>
     of their deliberations was made known 
     <lb/>
     to the country, but here the telegraphs 
     <lb/>
     carry the news over the country almost 
     <lb/>
     from our lips, therefore we stand in a 
     <lb/>
     worse position than the delegates did. 
     <lb/>
     When I urged my proposition upon the 
     <lb/>
     Legislature, and made my objections, I 
     <lb/>
     was telegraphed over the country as if I 
     <lb/>
     was opposed to all Confederation. I was 
     <lb/>
     set down as being an Anti-Confederate, 
     <lb/>notwithstanding that I stated that it did<lb/>
        
<cb/>

not require Fenianism to carry Con<lb break="no"/>federation, but was carried by its own 
     <lb/>merits. Stronger language could not 
     <lb/>have been used, but notwithstanding 
     <lb/>that strong language had been used, I 
     <lb/>have been misunderstood, as bringing 
     <lb/>those remarks as a sidewing to kill 
     <lb/>Confederation. It is a serious thing to 
     <lb/>have my motives so impugned after 
     <lb/>running an election so recently upon 
     <lb/>this question, and it is calculated to do 
     <lb/>me the greatest injury. My motives 
     <lb/>have not been understood in my pro<lb break="no"/>position for discussing this question. 
     <lb/>The question of Confederation had been 
     <lb/>affirmed at the polls. and the people had 
     <lb/>declared they were in favor of the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple. They sent representatives here 
     <lb/>in order to deliberate fully upon the 
     <lb/>matter. I made those objections at that 
     <lb/>time in order that the delegates might 
     <lb/>consider them. I wish to be under<lb break="no"/>stood. I state here the second time that 
     <lb/>no man in the country is more in favor 
     <lb/>of Confederation than I am. In season 
     <lb/>and out of season since the first election 
     <lb/>l have contended for it, in every posi<lb break="no"/>tion, and shall it be said now that I wish 
     <lb/>to procrastinate the question in order to 
     <lb/>defeat it. I said I was so strongly in 
     <lb/>favor of Confederation that I was will<lb break="no"/>ing to sink all other things. The ques<lb break="no"/>tion of Confederation being entirely out, 
     <lb/>of danger. I claim yet we have the right 
     <lb/>to discuss it, and make suggestions, 
     <lb/>and talk the matter over, in order that 
     <lb/>the delegates may know wherein the 
     <lb/>Scheme is considered deficient by the 
     <lb/>members of the Legislature. In regard 
     <lb/>to the resolutions before the House; the 
     <lb/>first says that each Province shall have 
     <lb/>an equal number of Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cillors. I would be content with having 
     <lb/>two added to Nova Scotia and two to 
     <lb/>New Brunswick, thus making the two 
     <lb/>Provinces together equal with either of 
     <lb/>the Canadas. This is a suggestion for 
     <lb/>an improvement in the Quebec Scheme, 
     <lb/>and because I make this suggestion 
     <lb/>should I be branded as having run an 
     <lb/>election upon false pretences. I con<lb break="no"/>tend here for the right of discussion. I 
     <lb/>know there are other hon. members who 
     <lb/>think it would be better not to discuss 
     <lb/>it. I do not say they are not correct, 
     <lb/>but I take the other view, and say we 
     <lb/>have a right to discuss it, and for so 
     <lb/>doing I should not be said to oppose 
     <lb/>it. I spoke of the representation in the 
     <lb/>Senate of the United States, and said 
     <lb/>that each State sent an equal number of 
     <lb/>representatives, and then I threw in a 
     <lb/>suggestion saying that inasmuch as those 
     <lb/>States are represented equally in the Se<lb break="no"/>nate, would it not be worth considering 
     <lb/>when the delegates come to deliberate 
     <lb/>upon the Scheme, whether or not we 
     <lb/>should have a more extended representa<lb break="no"/>tion in the Upper House. The fourth 
     <lb/>
    

            <cb/>
          

     resolution I am entirely in favor of, that 
     <lb/>
     is the  establishment of a Court for the 
     <lb/>
     determination of questions and disputes 
     <lb/>
     that may arise between the Federal and 
     <lb/>
     Local Governments as to the meaning of the 
     <lb/>
     the Act of Union. If I were a delegate 
     <lb/>
     I would ask that this fourth resolution be 
     <lb/>
     adopted. and I would struggle for it, but 
     <lb/>
     if I could not get it and the Scheme 
     <lb/>
     would be endangered by struggling, I 
     <lb/>
     would prefer a Scheme without it. Then 
     <lb/>
     the sixth resolution providing that 80 
     <lb/>
     cents per head be on the population as it 
     <lb/>
     increases and not to be confined to the 
     <lb/>
     census of 1861, meets with my entire con<lb break="no"/>currence, and I would press it upon all 
     <lb/>
     concerned, but would not make it a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine 
     <lb/>
     quo non</hi>. Some of my hon. friend's re<lb break="no"/>solutions I would like to see carried out 
     <lb/>
     in the Conference, but I would not put 
     <lb/>
     them as positive instructions not be de<lb break="no"/>viated from. After my speech on Friday 
     <lb/>
     last, some of the hon. members in the 
     <lb/>
     House said, and it has been circulated 
     <lb/>
     over the country, that just previous to 
     <lb/>
     making my speech I had an interview 
     <lb/>
     with the hon. member for Westmorland 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Smith) in the Speaker's room, and 
     <lb/>
     on account of that interview I made 
     <lb/>
     the speech I did. I do not know what 
     <lb/>
     put that in their minds. We are on the 
     <lb/>
     best of terms, but as long as I have been 
     <lb/>
     in public life I have never agreed with 
     <lb/>
     his public policy at all, but this had ne<lb break="no"/>ver affected our personal intercourse. He 
     <lb/>
     had no more idea of what I was going 
     <lb/>
     to say than a man on the other side of 
     <lb/>
     the universe. I do not know to what 
     <lb/>
     extent those insinuations have gone, but 
     <lb/>
     I know how damaging they are against 
     <lb/>
     any man holding a public situation. I 
     <lb/>
     am glad to have had an opportunity of 
     <lb/>
     setting these matters right, and main<lb break="no"/>taining my position before the country. 
     <lb/>
     I saw it stated in one of the newspapers 
     <lb/>
     that I sustained the resolution of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment because I was elected to sus<lb break="no"/>tain it, but I sustained it against my own 
     <lb/>
     convictions. That is a misrepresenta<lb break="no"/>tion. I sustained Confederation from 
     <lb/>
     convictions of my own, and my mind 
     <lb/>
     was made up afterr mature deliberation. 
     <lb/>
     I came here to see that nothing should 
     <lb/>
     be done to retard Confederation. I came 
     <lb/>
     to consider upon what terms we should 
     <lb/>
     enter into Union, and I will sustain the 
     <lb/>
     principle that we should discuss this ques<lb break="no"/>tion in order that we might agree upon 
     <lb/>
     the best Scheme to be adopted; having 
     <lb/>
     discharged that duty independent and 
     <lb/>
     tearless, if I am still to be misrepresen<lb break="no"/>ted, I cannot help it, but such is the po<lb break="no"/>sition I occupy.  
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOHN1">Mr. JOHNSON</persName>—I thought when the 
     <lb/>question for appointing delegates was be<lb break="no"/>fore the House that it had been so fully 
     <lb/>discussed that it was unnecessary for me 
     <lb/>to take up the time of the Session in 
     <lb/>speaking upon it. In regard to this re<lb break="no"/>
          

            <pb n="71" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_071.jpg"/>
           
<fw type="running">DEBATES IN THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">71</fw> 
  

     solution moved by my hon. friend from 
     <lb/>Westmorland, I di not think the House<lb/>will be willing to adopt it. If they do<lb/>adopt it, we might as well move a resolu<lb break="no"/>tion to rescind the resolution for appoint<lb break="no"/>ing the delegates. From the way it was<lb/>drawn up we would have to vote upno<lb/>all the resolutions at once. The first re<lb break="no"/>solution provides that there shall be an<lb/>equal number of Legislative Councillors<lb/>for each Province. According to that<lb/>Prince Edward Island would have the<lb/>same number of representatives as Up<lb break="no"/>per Canada. Surely that is not intended.<lb/>The next resolution provides that the<lb/>Legislative Councillors should reside in<lb/>the Province they represent. We<lb/>might just as well say our Legislative<lb/>Councillors should continue to reside in<lb/>the County they are appointed from, and<lb/>the moment they left the County they<lb/>should cease to be members of the Le<lb break="no"/>gislative Council. I do not think it would<lb/>tend to the improvement of the Scheme<lb/>that the number of representatives to the<lb/>Federal Parliament should be limited.<lb/>Under a Legislative Union we require no<lb/>written Constitution, for we would have<lb/>the institutions of the country to govern<lb/>us, but under a Federal Union, a writ<lb break="no"/>ten Constitution is necessary to define<lb/>the powers of the Local Legislatures in<lb/>contradistinction to the powers of the<lb/>General Government. It is our object<lb/>not to bind ourselves down to an iron<lb/>rule, but to leave ourselves as free<lb/>as possible. The General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would determine the number of re<lb break="no"/>presentatives for the various Provinces.<lb/>We take Lower Canada as the basis, the<lb/>intention of that is to prevent the too<lb/>rapid increase of representatives. If we<lb/>went on increasing, our representatives<lb/>would increase according as our pop<lb break="no"/>ulation increased, our House would grow<lb/>too large and be too cumbrous, therefore,<lb/>we made the provision that Lower Ca<lb break="no"/>nada should be taken as the basis, and<lb/>the number of her representatives should<lb/>not increase. If the population of Up<lb break="no"/>per Canada and the population of Lower<lb/>Canada both increase 100 per cent., the<lb/>number of representatives will still con<lb break="no"/>tinue the same as it is now. In regard<lb/>to the establishment of a Court of the<lb/>determination of questions and disputes<lb/>that may arise between the Federal and<lb/>Local Governments as to the meaning of<lb/>the Act of Union, I am opposed to hav<lb break="no"/>ing a judiciary or fourth branch to over<lb break="no"/>ride the other three. The power of the<lb/>Judges in the United States is different<lb/>from the power of the Judges in our<lb/>country. There they ahve the power to<lb/>say to nine-tenths of the Legislature, you<lb/>have no right to pass that law, and there<lb break="no"/>fore prevent the Legislature of the coun<lb break="no"/>try from legislating for the advantage of<lb/>the country. It is not necessary in our<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
         

     case, because we stand in a very differ<lb break="no"/>ent position from that they do in the<lb/>United States. When the United States<lb/>Legislature and the Local Legislatures<lb/>pass laws which conflict with each other,<lb/>it may be necessary to have a Court of<lb/>Appeal; but we have the Imperial Par<lb/>liament behind us, and this makes the<lb/>distinction between us. Suppose the Ge<lb break="no"/>neral Government passed a law that in<lb/>fringed upon the rights of the Local Le<lb break="no"/>gislatures: that must receive the Royal<lb/>sanction before it can become law, and<lb/>we can bring the matter before the Impe<lb break="no"/>rial Parliament and get redress. The<lb/>next resolution provides that this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince shall be exempt from taxation for<lb/>the construction and enlargement of ca<lb break="no"/>nals in Upper Canada, and for the pay<lb break="no"/>ment of any money for the mines and<lb/>minerals and lands of Newfoundland.<lb/>If you say the General Government shall<lb/>not expend money for the whole Union,<lb/>you strike at the root of the Confederacy<lb/>at once, and if it passed it would amount<lb/>to a vote of the House declarling they will<lb/>not go into Confederation at all. I am<lb/>not afraid that Upper Canada will tax the<lb/>whole Confederacy for enlarging the ca<lb break="no"/>nals unless it is for the general interest,<lb/>and if it be for the general interest I am<lb/>prepared to assent to it. The difficulty<lb/>we always find is, the people do not de<lb break="no"/>sire to be taxed even for the advantage<lb/>of the country. Upper Canada having to<lb/>pay so large a proportion will make a<lb/>strong opposition, they will not tax the<lb/>people more than the interest of the<lb/>country requires. While Upper and<lb/>Lower Canada remain united they willl<lb/>have sympathy for each other; but the<lb/>moment we have Confederation they be<lb break="no"/>come seperate and distinct Provinces, and<lb/>they are no longer influenced by sym<lb break="no"/>pathy of that kind. Lower Canada will<lb/>be governed by commercial and pecuni<lb break="no"/>ary interest, and when it suits their com<lb break="no"/>mercial and pecuniary interest to vote<lb/>with us they will do so, and if it suits their<lb/>interest to vote against us they will not<lb/>hesitate to cast their votes that way.<lb/>There would be as much exertion made<lb/>by Lower Canada to resist a tax for the<lb/>exclusive benefit of Upper Canada, as<lb/>there would be by the Maritime Provin<lb break="no"/>ces. Scotland went into a Legislative<lb/>Union with only 45 members against 585,<lb/>and she has improved in material wealth<lb/>very rapidly. We do not find any diffi<lb break="no"/>culty arising because she has not an equal<lb/>number of representatives with England.<lb/>The next resolution provides that the 80<lb/>cents per head be on the population as<lb/>it increases and not to be confined to the<lb/>census of 1861. This would be directly<lb/>opposed to the interests of the Lower<lb/>Provinces. If Upper Canada has 1 500,<lb break="no"/>000 population and doubles itself in the<lb/>course of ten years they get 80 cents<lb/>
     

            <cb/>
        

     a-head on 3,000,000; and if New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick doubles her population she will get<lb/>80 cents per head on 500,000. Thus we<lb/>will receive no more in proportion to our<lb/>population than Canada. It has been<lb/>argued that we give up all our revenue to<lb/>Canada and only receive 80 cents a-head<lb/>back. Suppose five personal go into part<lb break="no"/>nership and they agree each to put in an<lb/>equal amount, and they are each allowed<lb/>to draw out a certain amount for perso<lb break="no"/>nal expenses every year, and every in<lb break="no"/>crease should be added to the common<lb/>fund for the general good. If each man<lb/>draws out £600 a-year, and one man<lb/>spends the whole of his, and another man<lb/>one-half of his, it is nobodies concern;<lb/>but if the company make £500,000 that<lb/>goes into the general fund for the good<lb/>of the whole. So in this case, we place<lb/>the whole revenues of the country into<lb/>the general fund for the general purposes,<lb/>and then each Province draws out the<lb/>amount necessary for the support of its<lb/>Local Government. The faster the ge<lb break="no"/>neral fund increases the better for the<lb/>whole if it is increased without increa<lb break="no"/>sing taxation upon the people. So far<lb/>from the tariff being increased in Cana<lb break="no"/>da, I am informed that Mr. Galt has a<lb/>proposition before the Legislature to re<lb break="no"/>duce the tariff down to 15 per cent. Ac<lb break="no"/>cording to the population Canada's tariff is<lb/>much less than ours. This proposition<lb/>to reduce the tariff of Canada is not<lb/>made for the purpose of carrying Con<lb break="no"/>federation, because it has been made after<lb/>the Provinces have concluded to go into<lb/>Confederation. He finds that by the in<lb break="no"/>creased trade of the country that he<lb/>is in a position to reduce the tariff<lb/>equal to that of New Brunswick. This<lb/>is clear proof that we need not be alarm<lb break="no"/>ed about the Canadian people taxing<lb/>themselves for the sake of taxing us.<lb/>The next resolution is to secure to each<lb/>of the Maritime Provinces the right to<lb/>have at least one Executive Councillor in<lb/>the Federal Government. That would<lb/>be placing the Provinces in the worst<lb/>possible position. We would not feel<lb/>ourselves all the same people. We<lb/>would be in the country but not of it.<lb/>We would be ruled by the General Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, but we would still carry with<lb/>us the feeling that we did not belong to<lb/>it. Every effort should be made to make<lb/>us forget our Provincial identity, so we<lb/>would be one people; from Sarnia to New<lb break="no"/>foundland. I believe there is a desire<lb/>that when we go into Confederation these<lb/>Lower Provinces should go into a Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Union and become one Province.<lb/>If we do not like this Confederation we<lb/>had better keep out of it, but if we go<lb/>into it we must not talk of Canada as a<lb/>foreign country, but be one people under<lb/>one General Government. The next re<lb break="no"/>solution provide that the Inter-Colonial<lb/>
      

            <pb n="72" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_072.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">72</fw>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>
            

     Railway shall be commenced before the    
     <lb/>right shall exist to increase taxation upon<lb/>the people of this Province. Suppose we<lb/>passed this, and as my hon. friend says,<lb/>the Canadians are so cunning it would be<lb/>quite possible for them to build then miles<lb/>and then go no further, they can do that<lb/>if this provision is put in. We have pro<lb break="no"/>vided that the Inter-Colonial Railroad<lb/>shall be commenced and prosecuted to<lb/>thee completion, without asking whether<lb/>the revenues are sufficient or not, but in<lb/>regard to the canals, it is only when the<lb/>Provinces shall determine when the funds<lb/>are sufficient that the work will be pro<lb break="no"/>ceeded with. But in regard to this road<lb/>we have the assurance of the Imperial<lb/>Government, that no time shall be lost in<lb/>completing the work. It is a singular<lb/>using that the United States at the time<lb/>of the revolution, before they acquired<lb/>their independence, were making provi<lb break="no"/>sions to admit Canada into that Union,<lb/>the eleventh article of their Constitutiony<lb/>said ;<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Article XI.—Canada according to<lb/>this Confederation, and joining in the<lb/>measures of the United States, shall be<lb/>admitted into, and entitled to all the<lb/>advantages of this Union ; but no other<lb/>Colony shall be admitted into the same,<lb/>unless such admission be agreed to by<lb/>nine States."<lb/>
            </p>
   </quote>
    

    

            <p>
     They were just separating from the 
     <lb/>
     mother country. and were very anxious 
     <lb/>
     to get possession of Canada. If they 
     <lb/>
     had possession of Quebec, which com<lb break="no"/>manded the mouth of the St. Lawrence. 
     <lb/>the United States could not be attacked 
     <lb/>except from the seaboard. We have not 
     <lb/>copied the institutions of the United 
     <lb/>States, not because we found fault with 
     <lb/>the Constitution, for the wonder is not 
     <lb/>that the Cons itution has <choice><sic>faild</sic><corr>failed</corr></choice>, but that 
     <lb/>it has not failed more frequently and 
     <lb/>more fully than it has. When you con<lb break="no"/>sider that their people have come from 
     <lb/>all the nations of the earth, from repub<lb break="no"/>lics and from absolute and limited mon<lb break="no"/>archies, you must say it is a remarkable 
     <lb/>Constitution to so firmly bind the peo<lb break="no"/>ple together. It was originally formed 
     <lb/>to protect themselves from outward<lb/>danger, this was the main object of the<lb/>compact that bound the thirteen Colo<lb break="no"/>nies together. It was prepared with<lb/>the object of defending themselves<lb/>against a foreign foe, and no provision<lb/>was made for internal troubles until<lb/>afterwards. One great reason of their<lb/>difficulties, and one of the great reasons<lb/>of their war was, that there was not<lb/>sufficient power in the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Each state claimed an indepen<lb break="no"/>dent sovereignty. If you read the<lb/>Constitution of the United States as a<lb/>lawyer, and I think a large proportion<lb/>of the lawyers would come to the con<lb break="no"/>clusion that they had right—that it<lb/>
  
            <cb/>
          

     was a simple co-partnership into 
     <lb/>
     by these seperate States. and they had a 
     <lb/>
     right. upon the face of the Constitution 
     <lb/>
     to declare themselves out ol that Con<lb break="no"/>stitution. It was fortunate for the 
     <lb/>
     United States that while that would be 
     <lb/>
    the construction put upon it by a lawyer,  
     <lb/>it was not the construction put upon it by<lb/>the United States themselves, and they<lb/>had sufficient power to maintain what<lb/>they considered their right. Had the<lb/>Southern States succeeded, they had still<lb/>a country large enough for a nation, but<lb/>they knew that if they had succeeded the<lb/>States that were left would have falledn to<lb/>pieces. They would have been like a<lb/>glass toy, the moment they broke a cor<lb break="no"/>ner off it falls to pieces. The Western<lb/>States would have gone off, and they<lb/>would have split up in four or five pieces.<lb/>They would have fought the battle out as<lb/>long as they had a ma to fight or a shil<lb break="no"/>ling to pay him with. I have a copy of<lb/>the Constitution farmed subsequently to<lb/>this, and it is remarkable that this Con<lb break="no"/>stitution was framed by a Convention,<lb/>and never was submitted to a vote of the<lb/>people. If there be one way more sure<lb/>than another to drive us or lead us into<lb/>the neighboring republic, it will be by<lb/>forgetting the good old time honored in<lb break="no"/>stitutions of our country, and becoming<lb/>familiar with and practicing the Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion of the United States. The moment<lb/>we found our Confederation upon the<lb/>American principle, we will gradually<lb/>settle into the United States. If we be<lb break="no"/>come American in practice we will very<lb/>soon become American in fact. I do not<lb/>wish to have American institutions under<lb/>the British Flag. We want nothing bet<lb break="no"/>ter than British institutions, for under<lb/>them we have as much liberty, and a little<lb/>more, than they have in the United<lb/>States. Our institutions are more re<lb break="no"/>publican than the institutions of the<lb/>United States. Our people have more<lb/>power over the Government than the<lb/>people of the Unite States have over<lb/>theirs. If the veto power be exercised by<lb/>the sovereign, the ministry must go out<lb/>and another party come in. The minis<lb break="no"/>try cannot retain their power and refuse<lb/>a bill that has passed through the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature. In the United States if the veto<lb/>power is exercised it requires a two-<lb break="yes"/>thirds vote before a pill passed, can be<lb break="no"/>come law. It there be no man less than<lb/>two-thirds the minority must rule the<lb/>majority, and prevent them from having<lb/>a measure for the public interest. I will<lb/>now read (from, "Shafner's Seccssion<lb/>War In America") a letter of Washington,<lb/>President of the Convention appointed to<lb/>draw up a constitution :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:centre">"IN CONVENTION, Sept. 17, 1787.</p>

<p>"SIR: We have now the honor to<lb/>submit to the consideration of the United<lb/>States in Congress assembled that the Con<lb break="no"/>
           

            <cb/>
        
stitution which has appeared to us the 
     <lb/>most advisable.    
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The friends of our country have long<lb/>seen and desired that the power of mak<lb break="no"/>ing war, peace and treaties, that of levy<lb break="no"/>ing money and regulating commerce, and<lb/>the correspondent, executive and judicial<lb/>authorities, should be fully and effectual<lb break="no"/>ly vested in the General Government of<lb/>the Union ; but the impropriety of dele<lb break="no"/>gating such extensive trust to one body<lb/>of men is evident ; hence results the ne<lb break="no"/>cessity of a different organization. It is<lb/>obviously impracticable in the Federal<lb/>Government of these States to secure all<lb/>rights of independent sovereignty to<lb/>each, and yet provide for the interest and<lb/>safety of all. Individuals tnering into<lb/>society must give up a share of liberty to<lb/>preserve the rest. The magnitude of the<lb/>sacrifice must depend as well on situation<lb/>and circumstances as on the object to be<lb/>attained. It is at all times difficult to<lb/>draw with precision the line between<lb/>those rights which must be surrendered<lb/>and those which may be reserved ; and<lb/>on the present o casion this difficulty<lb/>was increased by a difference among the<lb/>several Sates as to their situation, ex<lb break="no"/>tent, habitants and particular interests."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Does not this meet our case, each 
     <lb/>
     State must surrender some of its rights 
     <lb/>
     for the general interest. In the forma<lb break="no"/>tion of society we have to give up some 
     <lb/>
     of our natural rights, and if they were 
     <lb/>
     not given up society could not ue form<lb break="no"/>ed. The Provinces going into Confed<lb break="no"/>eration must give up some of their local 
     <lb/>
     interests. It is not we who are giving 
     <lb/>
     more than the others, but we yield one 
     <lb/>
     point and they yield another. If we pass 
     <lb/>
     a resolution like the one under consider<lb break="no"/>ation, and Nova Scotia passes another 
     <lb/>
     giving different instructions, and the -  
     <lb/>
     delegates go into conferences, how can 
     <lb/>
     they agree at all unless each party yields 
     <lb/>
     some points and there is a compromise 
     <lb/>
     made.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The letter goes on to say : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " In all our deliberations on this sub<lb break="no"/>ject we kept steadily in our view that<lb/>which appears to us the greatest interest<lb/>of every true American—this consolida<lb break="no"/>tion of our Union—in which is involved<lb/>our prosperity, felicity, safety, perhaps<lb/>our national existence. This important<lb/>consideration, seriously and deeply im<lb break="no"/>pressed on our minds, led each State in<lb/>the Convention to be less rigid on points<lb/>of inferior magnitude than might have<lb/>been otherwise expected ; and thus the<lb/>Constitution which we now pr sent is the<lb/>result of a spirit of amity, and of that<lb/>mutual deference and concession which<lb/>the peculiarity of our political situation<lb/>rendered indispensible. That it will<lb/>meet !he full and entire approbation of<lb/>every State is not perhaps to be expect<lb break="no"/>ed, but each will doubtless consider that<lb/>had her interest been alone consulted,<lb/>the consequences might have been par<lb break="no"/>ticularly disagreeable to others ; that it<lb/>is liable to as few exceptions as could<lb/>reasonably have been expected , we hope<lb/>and believe ; that it may promote the<lb/>lasting welfare of that country so dear to<lb/>us all, and secure her freedom and happi<lb break="no"/>ness, is our most ardent wish.</p>

<p>"With great respect we have the honor
           

            <pb n="73" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-03_Page_073.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>   <fw type="num">73</fw>  


     to be, sir, your Excellency's most obe<lb break="no"/>dient humble servants.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     "By unanimous order of the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion,</p>   

<p rendition="simple:right">GEORGE WASHINGTON, <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">President</hi>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"His Excellency the President of Con<lb break="no"/>gress."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     If Washington had been writing con<lb break="no"/>cerning the position of the Provinces at<lb/>the present day, he could not have stated<lb/>the views of the parties who have to form<lb/>this Confederation more forcibly. It<lb/>states our position from the beginning to<lb/>end. We find that only eleven of the<lb/>
     States at that time adopted this Consti<lb break="no"/>tution. New York came in too late to<lb/>vote for the first President. I will now<lb/>read the organization of the United<lb/>States Government:<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On the first Wednesday in January, 
     <lb/>ten States appointed the electors to vote for<lb/>President of the new Government. On<lb/>the first Wednesday in February there<lb break="no"/>after, the electors in each State ment at<lb/>their respective Capitals and voted for<lb/>the first President, and Washington was<lb/>elected. In the meantime the State of<lb/>New York repealed its conditional ratifi<lb break="no"/>cation of the Constitution and agreed to<lb/>join the new Government, hoping to se<lb break="no"/>cure certain changes in the Constitution<lb/>in the future; but the proceedings of New<lb/>York took place after the time fixed for<lb/>the appointment of presidential electors,<lb/>and hence that State did not vote for the<lb/>President. Congress was ordered to con<lb break="no"/>vene on the 4th of March 1789, in the<lb/>City of New York, but there was not a<lb/>quorum present, and it was adjourned to<lb/>meet again on the first of April, on which<lb/>day the first Congress under the Consti<lb break="no"/>tution assembled. On the 30th April,<lb/>1789, George Washington was inaugu<lb break="no"/>rated as the first President. Thus com<lb break="no"/>menced the Constitutional Government<lb/>composed of eleven States, all of which<lb/>seceded from the Confederation of 1781,<lb/>leaving but two members in that perpet<lb break="no"/>ual Union. These were Rhode Island<lb/>and North Carolina. As the Union had<lb/>been dissolved by the secession of eleven<lb/>States, the whole structure fell; and on<lb/>the first of April, 1789, on the organization<lb/>of the Constitutional Government there<lb/>were three independent Republics, result<lb break="no"/>ing from the political revolutino of that<lb/>era; one composed of the eleven States;<lb/>another of Rhode Island, and the third<lb/>of North Carolina. Every possible effort<lb/>was made to induce the two independent<lb/>sovereign States to join the new Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and for a time they seemed to be<lb/>determined never to ratify the Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion. North Carolina yielded, and joined<lb/>the new Confederacy on the 21st No<lb break="no"/>vember, 1789; but Rhode Island con<lb break="no"/>tinued inexorable. There was a power<lb break="no"/>ful opposition among the people to the<lb/>ratification of the Constitution, and that<lb/>State maintained its independence until<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
          

     the 29th of May, 1790, being nearly two 
     <lb/>years after the Constitutional Govermment<lb/>had been adopted by the ten seceding<lb/>States. The Union finally with the in<lb break="no"/>dependent Republic of Rhode Island<lb/>completed the organization of the thir<lb break="no"/>teen United States, and established the<lb/>great American nation - the wonder of the<lb/>most wonder-teeming age. We have thus<lb/>briefly traced the formation of the new<lb/>Government of the United States under<lb/>the Constitution formed in 1787. It is<lb/>only left for us to remark, that this great<lb/>organic code of the Union was never<lb/>adopted by a vote of the people. The<lb/>Conventions of the States ratified it; but<lb/>we are unable to find that a single State<lb/>entered the Union by a vote of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple. The Legislature when they meet<lb/>are the people, and they have not only<lb/>the power to deal with subjects that were<lb/>before the people when they were elected,<lb/>but they have power to deal with all<lb/>questions that may occur during their<lb/>existence. They are the people for all<lb/>legislative purposes, and they have the<lb/>power to change the Constitution when<lb/>they think the country requires it. The<lb/>Imperial Parliament has dethroned and<lb/>elected Sovereigns without appealing to<lb/>the people. My hon. friend (Mr. Smith)<lb/>has aid that those who went for Confed<lb break="no"/>eration were looking for personal advan<lb break="no"/>tage. I say to represent the people in the<lb/>General Parliament is an object worthy<lb/>of our ambition, and my hon. friend<lb/>would be one of the first to aspire to that<lb/>position. He believes he is pursuing the<lb/>course the interest of the country re<lb break="no"/>quires, and we believe we are pursuing<lb/>the course best calculated to promote the<lb/>welfare of the country. We do not think<lb/>it is a matter of prophecy; it is simply a<lb/>matter of looking back to history, and we<lb/>know that like occurrences produce like<lb/>effects. It would be a dangerous thing<lb/>if all politicians agreed; it is much bet<lb break="no"/>ter to have the subject ventilated - to<lb/>have an opposition, and that opposition<lb/>to come before the pople and explain<lb/>this opposition. After this question had<lb/>been placed before the people in its most<lb/>glowing colours, they have seen it is for<lb/>the interest of the country to enter this<lb/>Union. These resolutions bind the de<lb break="no"/>legates hand and foot, and the moment<lb/>you pass them you reject the resolutions<lb/>to appoint the delegates. It would be<lb/>simply sending a delegation who would<lb/>come back with their fingers in their<lb/>mouths, having done nothing. There<lb/>must be mutal concessions; you could<lb/>not get five men to enter into partner<lb break="no"/>ship upon the terms one of them would<lb/>draw up. This Quebec Scheme when it<lb/>was made was not binding upon the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. It is provided in our institutions<lb/>that those who take office have both Ex<lb break="no"/>ecutive and Legislative duties to perform.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
    

            <p>The Legislature of the country must be<lb/>under their direction, and they must have<lb/>such a majority in both brances as to<lb/>be able to carry forward those measures<lb/>they think will be for the interest of the<lb/>country, and to resist those measures<lb/>which they think will be prejudicial to it.<lb/>They take the responsibility and they<lb/>must control the Legislature of the coun<lb break="no"/>try, and when it was adoped by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, it was not binding upon the coun<lb break="no"/>try, and if placed in a position in which<lb/>they cannot control it they must resign<lb/>their seats. If the Government bring for<lb break="no"/>ward a Scheme of Union and the House<lb/>refuse to pass it they must resign. It is<lb/>not necessary that they should resign if<lb/>defeated upon a question of minor im<lb break="no"/>portance, because it frequently hapens<lb/>that a Government is defeated and still<lb/>has a majority. If they then resign the<lb/>minority has to rule. I felt that when<lb/>this Scheme was first brought before the<lb/>people that the Government would be de<lb break="no"/>feated upon it. The Government were<lb/>not popular enough to carry Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, and if the House had died a natural<lb/>death they would have been defeated, and<lb/>Confederation too. My opinion was that<lb/>by dissolving the House as we did we<lb/>would lose our position a year sooner,<lb/>but Confederation would be carried a<lb/>year earlier. It being then defeated, peo<lb break="no"/>ple then began to think about it, and in<lb/>the sort space of sixteen months there<lb/>was a revolution in the feeling of the<lb/>country upon the question. My hon.<lb/>friend (Mr. Smith) came to the House<lb/>opposed to Confederation, but if he had<lb/>come to the conclusion that the people had<lb/>changed and were in favour of it, he might<lb/>have come in with a resolution in favor<lb/>of Confederation, or he might have pre<lb break="no"/>pared a Scheme differing from this where<lb/>it was defective and had a large marjority<lb/>in this House. Suppose some of the<lb/>members of his then Government had re<lb break="no"/>signed, he could then have formed a Coa<lb break="no"/>lition Government and carried his Scheme.<lb/>I suppose his was opposed to Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, and did not think it would be doing<lb/>right to take that course. I believe he<lb/>considered that the course he took would<lb/>best advance the interests of the country,<lb/>and we are also taking the course by<lb/>which we think the interests of the coun<lb break="no"/>try will be advance and its prosperity<lb/>increased.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
            <p>
     The debate was adjourned until to<lb break="no"/>morrow at 10.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> - brought in "A 
     <lb/>Bill relating to the imposition of duties<lb/>for raising a Revenue."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House adjourned until 9 A.M. to<lb break="no"/>morrow.</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">   T.P.D. <lb/>
            </p>
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>