<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-07-09"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title> 
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-07-09">9 July 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="86"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-09_Page_086.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
     
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-27">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-27">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-09_Page_086">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-09_Page_086.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="86" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-09_Page_086.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="num">86</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 


<!-- GL, 2018-03-27, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day --> 
     
     
           <!-- </p>
            <p>tained therein, the Report was agreed to,<lb/>and adopted by the House.<lb/>The House then adjourned until Mon<lb break="no"/>day morning at 10 A. M.<lb/>T. P. D.<lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <head rendition="simple:right">
     MONDAY, JULY 9. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Certain Bills were read a third time. </p>

<p>On the reading for the third time of the<lb/>Bill authorizing the appointment of De<lb break="no"/>puty Registrars, objections were taken<lb/>to certain provisions by Measrs. Johnson,<lb/>Williaton, Connell and Chandler, and on<lb/>putting the question whether it should be<lb/>sent to the Legislative Council for their<lb/>concurrence, it was carried in the nega<lb break="no"/>tive.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CHAN1">Mr. CHANDLER</persName> moved the following<lb/>Resolution :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" That the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Royal Gazette</hi> be no longer<lb/>sent to the Magistrates throughout the<lb/>country, but be sent to the Clerks of the<lb/>Peace for the respective Counties."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


<p><persName ref="pers:CHAN1">Mr. CHANDLER</persName> said the reason why<lb/>
he brought forward this motion was that  <lb/>
the sending of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi> to the Magis<lb break="no"/>trates of the country cost some £500, and <lb/>
in many cases they were not received by<lb/>
the parties for whom they were intended,<lb/>
and frequently when received were not<lb/>
read. This great expense should be saved<lb/>
if possible.</p>


            <p><persName ref="pers:MCAD1">Mr. McADAM</persName> said that he did not<lb/>know how that would work, for the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment advertising now must be inser<lb break="no"/>ted in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi> alone, and the public<lb/>would be deprived of the requisite know<lb break="no"/>ledge of the sales of lands and other mat<lb break="no"/>ters.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr. HIBBARD</persName> thought his hon. col<lb break="no"/>league was acting against his own future<lb/>interests, as the list of Magistrates is now<lb/>so large that they form the largest por<lb break="no"/>tion of the community. The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi> was<lb/>of great value to the Magistrates, as they<lb/>give the laws before they are issued in<lb/>pamphlet form.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILL1">Hon. Mr. WILLISTON</persName> would support 
     <lb/>the motion on the ground of economy.<lb/>He should like to have the opinion of the<lb/>Secretary on the question.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> was pleased to hear<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
        

     any motion that would tend to reduce the   
     <lb/>expenditure, the question was whether it<lb/>was economy in the right direction. He<lb/>always thought that the withdrawing of<lb/>the advertising of Crown Lands from the<lb/>local newspapers was an impolitic pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings, and now as the only method of<lb/>making public the sale of Crown Lands<lb/>is through the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi>, he was of opinion<lb/>that the curtailing of its circulation would<lb/>be prejudicial.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOHN1">Mr. JOHNSON</persName> took the same view of<lb/>the matter, and hoped the hon. mover<lb/>would not press it at this late period of<lb/>the Session.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CHAN1">Mr. CHANDLER</persName> by leave would with<lb break="no"/>draw the Resolution, as it was evident it<lb/>did not meet with favour.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The motion was withdrawn.<lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">AFTERNOON SESSION.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:DOW1">Dr. DOW</persName> moved the following Reso<lb break="no"/>lution :<lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>,—That a Committee be ap<lb break="no"/>pointed to make arrangements during the<lb/>recess for the Reporting and Publishing<lb/>the Debates of this House at the next<lb/>Session of the Legislature.<lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>The following members were appointed<lb/>the Committee -Dr. Dow, Hon. Mr. Con<lb break="no"/>nell, and Mr. Wetmore.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A messenger from His Excellency the<lb/>Lieutenant Governor, announced that His<lb/>Excellency commanded their attendance<lb/>in the Legislative Council Chamber. The<lb/>House having attended, His Excellency<lb/>was pleased to Prorogue the Assembly<lb/>with the following<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">SPEECH :<lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. President and Hon. Gentlemen of the  
     <lb/>Legislative Council :</hi><lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
    <hi rendition="simple:italic"> Mr. Speaker and Gentlemen of the House 
     <lb/>of Assembly:</hi><lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I have learned with much satisfaction 
     <lb/>that she opinion so strongly expressed by<lb/>Her Majesty's Government, as to the ex<lb break="no"/>pediency of a closer Union between the<lb/>British North American Provinces, has<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
         

     now received the concurrence of both 
     <lb/>Branches of the Provincial Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     It is my intention, in accordance with 
     <lb/>the wishes of the House of Atsembly<lb/>shortly to appoint Delegates who, in con<lb break="no"/>junction with Delegates from the other<lb/>Provinces of British America, will ar<lb break="no"/>range with Her Majesty's Government the<lb/>details of an Act which, as requested by<lb/>the Address of the Legislative Council to<lb/>Her Majesty the Queen, adopted in Ap<lb break="no"/>ril last, will be introduced into the Impe<lb break="no"/>rial Parliament for the purpose, of effect<lb break="no"/>ing the desired Union.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     In the Bill to which I have just assen<lb break="no"/>ted, suspending in certain cases the ope<lb break="no"/>ration of the Habeas Corpus Act, I recog<lb break="no"/>nize a proof of your watchful case for<lb/>the tranquility of the Province. The<lb/>mischievous designs of the Fenian : con<lb break="no"/>spirator have, it is true, been frustrated :<lb/>but it will, I fear, be necessary for some<lb/>time to come to exercise a careful vigi<lb break="no"/>lance entirely to prevent the revival of<lb/>their projects.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker and Gentlemen of the House    
     <lb/>of Assembly :</hi><lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I thank you for the readiness and una<lb break="no"/>nimity with which you have provided for<lb/>the exigencies of the Public Service.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. President and Hon. Gentlemen of the 
     <lb/>Legislative Council:</hi><lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker and Gentlemen of the House<lb/>of Assembly :</hi><lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Queen has been graciously pleased<lb/>to confide to me the discharge of impor<lb break="no"/>tant duties in another part of Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's Dominions ; and in now taking<lb/>leave of you on your return to your<lb/>respective Counties, I do so for the<lb/>last time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot quit without regret, a Province<lb/>to which I have become sincerely attached,<lb/>and, whilst I mark with deep interest the<lb/>progress of the new nation of which New<lb/>Brunswick will form no unimportant part,<lb/>I shall ever watch with special concern<lb/>the future fortunes of this portion of Brit<lb break="no"/>ish America.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>That it may continue to be happy and<lb/>prosperous is my earnest prayer.<lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>