<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-03-26"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-03-26">26 March 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="56" to="61"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_056.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_057.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_058.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_059.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_060.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_061.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-06">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-06">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_056">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_056.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_057">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_057.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_058">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_058.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_059">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_059.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_060">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_060.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_061">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_061.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="56" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_056.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="num">56</fw>   <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 
 


<!-- GL, 2018-03-06, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
     <!--ber of gentlemen in New York and 
     <lb/>
     Boston who were buying up large quan<lb break="no"/>tities of all the articles that came into the 
     <lb/>
    Province duty free. He had understood that 
     <lb/>the Government did not intend to collect 
     <lb/>duties on those articles that before the Reci<lb break="no"/>procity Treaty were subjected to a duty of 
     <lb/>3 per cent. St. John would soon be flooded 
     <lb/>with articles and not pay a cent of duty. 
     <lb/>But let it be supposed that the Govsmment 
     <lb/>did impose duty on these articles, the South<lb break="no"/>ern part of the Province would get them 
     <lb/>duty free. St. John being an open port, 
     <lb/>while the people of the North would have to 
     <lb/>pay duty. Such a policy would not be to<lb break="no"/>lerated were the Northern Counties properly 
     <lb/>represented at the Council Board. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FRAS1">MR. FRASER</persName>. -\- Did not flour come into 
     <lb/>the Province, duty free, before Reciprocity. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. WILLISTON. -\- He would vote 
     <lb/>against putting a duty on flour, beef. &amp;c. 
     <lb/>He would like to know what the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment intended 'to do. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>ATTORNEY GENERAL—The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment did not intend to put a duty on flour. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. WILLISTON was glad to hear that, 
     <lb/>yet it would be necessary to put a protective 
     <lb/>duty on certain articles in order to check<lb break="no"/>mate the American Government, should 
     <lb/>they put a heavy duty on exports. He was 
     <lb/>not going further into the charges against 
     <lb/>the Government. He had already stated the 
     <lb/>grounds on which he stood against them. The 
     <lb/>moment he read their Minute of Council he 
     <lb/>made up his mind to oppose them. He was 
     <lb/>opposed to them also for the reason that the 
     <lb/>Government, as at present constituted, did 
     <lb/>not sufficiently represent the interests of the 
     <lb/>North. He regretted very much that he 
     <lb/>should have to vote against the Government. 
     <lb/>For individual members of it he felt great 
     <lb/>respect. He had always been on the most 
     <lb/>friendly terms and had received the greatest 
     <lb/>kindness rrom the Attorney General, the 
     <lb/>Surveyor General, and the Provincial Se<lb break="no"/>cretary. He felt very great reluctance to 
     <lb/>vote against them ; but conscientiously 
     <lb/>believing that Confederation would advance 
     <lb/>the interests of the country. and believing 
     <lb/>that the Government were not prepared to 
     <lb/>bring in a scheme, he should therefore, vote. 
     <lb/>for the amendment. . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
    

    

    

    

            <p>
     The House then adjourned over until 
     <lb/>
     Monday, at 10 o'clock. . 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->

    
   
            <head rendition="simple:right">
     MONDAY, MARCH 26. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The Bill to amend the Act to incorpo<lb break="no"/>rate the Albert. County Railway Com<lb break="no"/>pany . 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     A Bill to authorize the Trustees of the 
     <lb/>
     St. Andrew's Church, St. John to sell 
     <lb/>
     property in Salisbury ; 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And the Bill to change the name of the 
     <lb/>
     Parish of Palmerston, in Kent, to Saint 
     <lb/>
     Luke's, were agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     A BILL TO ADD TO AN ACT RELATING TO 
     <lb/>
     THE MILITIA. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OTTY1">MR. OTTY</persName>, in explaining the objects 
     <lb/>
     of thc Bill, said that the militia law ex<lb break="no"/>empted volunteers from the payment of 
     <lb/>
     taxes to the extent of six dollars. This 
     <lb/>
     provision did not act fairly, because many 
     <lb/>
     of the volunteers who spent their time at<lb break="no"/>tending drill, paid but a small amount of 
     <lb/>
     taxes, the whole exemption amounting to 
     <lb/>
     but sixty-one cents per head for the vol<lb break="no"/>unteers in King's County. They thought: 
     <lb/>
     being exempted from six dollars taxes, 
     <lb/>
     would exempt them from statute labour, 
     <lb/>
     and a case was brought to trial, when the 
     <lb/>
     Chief Justice have his decision that it did 
     <lb/>
    not exempt them from statute labour. 
     <lb/>Therefore it was unfair that the volun<lb break="no"/>teers in the rural districts, who had to 
     <lb/>
     

            <cb/>
          

     travel some distance to attend drill,<lb/>should be exempted from so small an<lb/>amount; while the volunteers in the ci<lb break="no"/>ties who had but a short distance to o to<lb/>attend drill, are exempted from a larger<lb/>amount in consequence of their taxes be<lb break="no"/>ing higher.<lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">MR. NEEDHAM</persName> said he would have<lb/>had another section prepared for the Bill,<lb/>if he had known it was going to be in<lb break="no"/>troduced. The volunteers were exempted<lb/>to the extent of six dollars, and if his 
     <lb/>taxes were rated under that amount, he 
     <lb/>was disfranchised, because by the terms 
     <lb/>of their charter, no man could vote unless 
     <lb/>he had a receipt for his taxes from the 
     <lb/>City Treasurer. He had serious doubts 
     <lb/>whether this exemption should be a local 
     <lb/>charge. If five or six hundred volunteers 
     <lb/>in Fredericton were ordered to the North 
     <lb/>Shore, they should share the burden. 
     <lb/>They should have six dollars paid them 
     <lb/>out of the militia treasury, and let it come<lb/>in as a portion of the expenditure for the <lb/>militia. He hoped the hon. mover would<lb/>allow progress to be reported, so that an<lb/>additional section might be added to the<lb/>Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName> thought they should<lb/>do all they could to encourage the volun<lb break="no"/>teer movement. There is a great com0<lb/>plaint made in St. John about these ex<lb break="no"/>emptions. they want to raise a certain<lb/>amount of money for a local purpose, and<lb/>when the assessment is made they do not<lb/>know the number of volunteers who are<lb/>relieved from a portion of their taxes,<lb/>which causes irregularity. If the volun<lb break="no"/>teers were for the defence of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, their expenses should be provided<lb/>out of the general revenue.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:OTTY1">MR. OTTY</persName> explained that the second<lb/>section of the bill would provide a reme<lb break="no"/>dy for the irregularity complained of.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>COL. BOYD fully concurred with the<lb/>remarks made by his hon. friend from<lb/>York, in thinking that the expense should<lb/>be provided for by the Province at large.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> thought that the volun<lb break="no"/>teers of St. John did not want any ex<lb break="no"/>emptions from taxes, but they expected<lb/>when they gave their time and services<lb/>for the benefit of the Province, they<lb/>should not have to put their hands in<lb/>their pockets and be compelled to pay<lb/>the expenses necessary to be incurred for<lb/>the purpose. The least the public could<lb/>do, would be to provide them with all<lb/>things necessary for the purpose of en<lb break="no"/>abling them to learn their drill. They<lb/>should have a proper drill room, supplied<lb/>with arms, and if they were required to<lb/>wear uniform it should be provided.<lb/>Everything should be provided from the<lb/>Provincial revenues, or by the united ac<lb break="no"/>tion of the Province with the localities.<lb/>In the City of St. John half the expense<lb/>should be provided by the Province, and <lb/>half by the City and County. It was not<lb/>dealing fair with them, that it should be<lb/>necessary that concrts should be go up<lb/>for their benefit, or that they should beg<lb/>from door to door to put a coat on their<lb/>backs. He would protest against that,<lb/>and he hoped their claims upon the coun<lb break="no"/>try would be acknowledged.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">MR. LINDSAY</persName> said the present law<lb/>did not work fairly, for it was not right<lb/>that the poor man should be relieved of<lb/>but one dollar while the rich mand was<lb/>relieved of six, for they both lost the same<lb/>time. If they were going to keep up the<lb/>volunteer system, the money should come<lb/>from the Provincial revenues of the<lb/>country. They did not get the right<lb/>class of men to attend the Camp of In<lb break="no"/>
      <cb/>

struction. They were men who were<lb/>here to-day and away tomorrow, and<lb/>merely went there to have a jolly time. 
     <lb/>If they could have got the young men of 
     <lb/>the country, it would have been some 
     <lb/>benefit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">MR. MCMILLAN</persName> remarked that they 
     <lb/>
    should all be put on on equal footing, and 
     <lb/>not allow one man to receive $1 and an<lb break="no"/>other $6 for the same service. In regard 
     <lb/>to their having a free passage on the rail<lb break="no"/>way, when attending militia duties, he 
     <lb/>thought the railway was Provincial pro<lb break="no"/>perty, and they should be allowed 
     <lb/>travel on it for that purpose. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">MR. McCLELLAN</persName> thought something 
     <lb/>
     should be done to aid and encourage 
     <lb/>them, but he objected to this Bill on ac<lb break="no"/>acount of the rich man being exempted<lb/>from more taxes than the poor man.<lb/>Then in regard to localities, a martial<lb/>feeling may exist in one portion of the<lb/>country, in consequence of encourage<lb break="no"/>ments held out, and that portion of the<lb/>country would have to bear the burden of<lb/>these taxes, while the whole Province<lb/>would receive the benefit. It would also<lb/>disfranchise these volunteers, from whom<lb/>we want an expression of opinion, as<lb/>they were likely to be men of thought,<lb/>who took an interest in the affairs of the<lb/>country. their names would not go on<lb/>the Revisor's list, unless they made ap<lb break="no"/>plication to the Revisors; many of them<lb/>would not make this application, and, in<lb/>consequence, would be unable to vote.<lb/>The last section says, they shall pass<lb/>over the railway free of expense. It is<lb/>not fair that certain parties in the County<lb/>of Kings should have a privilege which is<lb/>denied to the rest of the Province. This<lb/>whole system of free passage on the rail<lb break="no"/>road was bad. It was a subject he in<lb break="no"/>tended to enquire into this session, to<lb/>ascertain how many people are allowed to<lb/>pass over the road free of expense. he was<lb/>inclined to think there was a great many<lb/>individuals went over that railroad free.<lb/>The members of the Govenrment pass<lb/>over free, and he was not sure but their<lb/>supporters passed over free too.<lb/>HON. MR. SMITH supposed he in<lb break="no"/>tended his observations to apply to the<lb/>late Government, as the present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had not been long in power, and<lb/>has had the control of it only for a few<lb/>months. It was very well for him to<lb/>say he had suspicions of this, and that<lb/>some enquiry ought to be made to see<lb/>whether those suspicions were well<lb/>grounded or not. He thought Mr.<lb/>Lawrence deserved the greatest credit,<lb/>as he saved from fifteen to twenty<lb/>thousand dollars in the expenses con<lb break="no"/>nected with that railroad. (Mr. Lind<lb break="no"/>say - I should like to see an account of<lb/>it.) He was speaking of facts. Mr.<lb/>Lawrence had paid a larger sum into<lb/>the reventues than ever had been paid<lb/>before, and that was good proof that<lb/>there was not many free passages. He<lb/>had reduced the running of the trains,<lb/>and had reduced the staff. He only<lb/>runs one through train per day, which<lb/>afforded as much accommodation to the<lb/>country as they wanted. When this<lb/>House came to examine the matter they<lb/>would sse what Mr. Lawrence had done,<lb/>and they would be disposed to give him<lb/>every praise for the manner in which he<lb/>had conducted the Railway. With re<lb break="no"/>gard to the Bill before the House, he<lb/>would like to give every encourage<lb break="no"/>ment to the Volunteers; but there should<lb/>be some provision to make the exemp<lb break="no"/>tion more equal, and to prevent their<lb/>
     
     

            <pb n="57" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_057.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES FOR THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  <fw type="num">57</fw> 
 

     names being removed from the revisors 
     <lb/>
     list. In regard to the last section of the 
     <lb/>
     bill authorising the Volunteers to pass 
     <lb/>
     over the Railroad free of expense while 
     <lb/>
    on duty, he had no objection to that, but 
     <lb/>instead of making it a matter of law, he 
     <lb/>would leave it with the Government, 
     <lb/>and they could make an order at any 
     <lb/>time to allow them a free passage. He 
     <lb/>agreed with the principle, that if the 
     <lb/>Volunteers are organized as a perman<lb break="no"/>ent institution the expense should fall 
     <lb/>upon the country. He had been rather 
     <lb/>against those Militia expenses, and 
     <lb/>would still continue so unless they were 
     <lb/>necessary for the defence of the country, 
     <lb/>but if necessary, no man should shrink 
     <lb/>from contributing according to his 
     <lb/>means for the support of that institu<lb break="no"/>tion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">MR. CONNELL</persName> objected to the Bill, 
     <lb/>
     and contended that, if the Bill was neces<lb break="no"/>sary, it should have been brought in as 
     <lb/>
     Government measure. In regard to the rail 
     <lb/>
     road, he had always paid his passage, and 
     <lb/>
     he did not thiuk the Government had any 
     <lb/>
     right to make an order for these volun<lb break="no"/>teers to go over free. The road should 
     <lb/>
     be so managed that it could be shown 
     <lb/>
     who travelled free; and if there were free 
     <lb/>
     passages given it should be stopped. at 
     <lb/>
    once. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">MR. NEEDHAM</persName> differed from his hon. 
     <lb/>friend in thinking this ought to be a Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment measure. The Militia Law was 
     <lb/>on the Statute Book, and they could do 
     <lb/>as they liked with it, for all the wisdom 
     <lb/>of the country is not centred in the Gov 
     <lb/>ernment. They came there to legislate 
     <lb/>for the whole Province, and they should 
     <lb/>deal even-handed justice to all. Particu<lb break="no"/>lar localities should not be taxed for the 
     <lb/>support of volunteers which were for the 
     <lb/>benefit of all. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL1">MR. BAILEY</persName> said that if the provisions 
     <lb/>
    of this Bill were confined to King's 
     <lb/>County, he would not oppose it, but he 
     <lb/>would be very sorry to see it extend to 
     <lb/>Queen's County. for they are not able to 
     <lb/>pay so much for defence as this Bill 
     <lb/>specifies. This Bill exempts the volun<lb break="no"/>teer from three days' labor and six dol<lb break="no"/>lars taxes, thus making the community 
     <lb/>contribute $7.50 for each volunteer. He 
     <lb/>believed the volunteer force should be 
     <lb/>paid out of the general funds of the 
     <lb/>country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     Some discussion then took place re<lb break="no"/>garding free passages on the railway, and 
     <lb/>
     on franking letters, after which progress 
     <lb/>
     was reported. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName> called the attention of 
     <lb/>
     the House to a report in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Evening 
     <lb/>
     Globe</hi> of a debate which took place in the 
     <lb/>
     House on Friday, in which he was made 
     <lb/>
     to say that "he had frequently stated his 
     <lb/>
     opinions in favor of Confederation in the 
     <lb/>
     abstract, to Judge Allen and others. but 
     <lb/>
     never so expressed himself publicly in 
     <lb/>
     the Council, although that was the im<lb break="no"/>pression he wished to convey." This 
     <lb/>
     report, he said, was utterly devoid of 
     <lb/>
     truth. What he had endeavored to im<lb break="no"/>press upon this House was, that he had 
     <lb/>
     stated in the Council that he was in favor 
     <lb/>
     of union, and that Judge Allen had au<lb break="no"/>thorized him to say that he had heard him 
     <lb/>
     express himself in favor of union in the 
     <lb/>
     abstract. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAIE1">MR. CAIE</persName>.—As all are expected to 
     <lb/>
     speak on this question, I will endeavor to 
     <lb/>
     makes a few remarks, but I think too 
     <lb/>
     much time has already been taken up, 
     <lb/>
     and too much money expended on this 
     <lb/>
     debate, which had better be expended in 
     <lb/>
     opening up roads for the poor back 
     <lb/>
   

            <cb/>
           

     settler, which the mover of this amend<lb break="no"/>ment was seemingly so anxious to save. 
     <lb/>
     I shall not take up much time in the few 
     <lb/>
     remarks I intend to make. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I am as anxious as any one on the floor 
     <lb/>
     of this House that the defences of our 
     <lb/>
     country should be put in a most efficient 
     <lb/>
     condition, and every means within the 
     <lb/>
     power of the Government should be taken 
     <lb/>
     to protect the lives and property of the 
     <lb/>
     people of this Province, particularly those 
     <lb/>
     who live on the frontier or the seaboard. 
     <lb/>
     The Government who would not enter 
     <lb/>
     into these arrangements, would be un<lb break="no"/>worthy of the people's confidence, and 
     <lb/>
     would not receive the support of this 
     <lb/>
     House for one day. I have listened with 
     <lb/>
     much attention, and with an impartial 
     <lb/>
     ear, for I am neither a disappointed 
     <lb/>
     office seeker, nor an expectant of any 
     <lb/>
     offices at the disposal of any new Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. I have listened with a disinterest<lb break="no"/>ed ear to the charges brought against 
     <lb/>
     this Government, and the defence of the 
     <lb/>
     Government. Although it is certain they 
     <lb/>
     have committed sins of omission, and it 
     <lb/>
     may be commission, yet I cannot think 
     <lb/>
     we have sufficient grounds to pass a vote 
     <lb/>
     of want of confidence in them. It is well 
     <lb/>
     known to every member of the House, 
     <lb/>
     that the Government only came into 
     <lb/>
     power a few hours before the last meet<lb break="no"/>ing of the Legislature. and during the 
     <lb/>
     whole of that session they worked almost 
     <lb/>
     night and day to prepare Bills, which had 
     <lb/>
     to be laid before this Assembly, and very 
     <lb/>
     shortly after the session was adjourned , 
     <lb/>
     the late Attorney General and the Presi<lb break="no"/>dent of the Council were deputised to go 
     <lb/>
     to England. Shortly after they returned, 
     <lb/>
     the then Attorney General was then 
     <lb/>
    elevated to the Bench of New Brunswick. 
     <lb/>Taking these things into consideration, 
     <lb/>we would not be justified in condemning 
     <lb/>them for their sin of omission. The one 
     <lb/>great object with the Opposition now is 
     <lb/>the overthrow of the present Government<lb/>- reports are raised, communications to<lb/>newspapers and telegraphs are sent, not<lb/>only through New Brunswick but through<lb/>Canada and the United States, all tending<lb/>to the one object - the overthrow of this <lb/>Government. I should like this House to<lb/>find any thruthfulness in many of these<lb/>reports. the first report represented the<lb/>government as afraid to do anything. Then<lb/>a report was got up about railroads, and<lb/>it was said by the enemies of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment that there never would be a sod turned<lb/>on either side of these railroads by those<lb/>companies, and that the report that<lb/>companies were going to build them was<lb/>only got up to help Mr. Smith in his elec<lb break="no"/>tion. Those contracts were made, and<lb/>will be laid before the House in due time.<lb/>then they say this is a do-nothing Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, for they have not made the <lb/>first move towards protecting the Prov<lb break="no"/>ince from teh Fenians. One of the mem<lb break="no"/>bers from Carleton stated that there was<lb/>not a gun or pound of powder in the <lb/>County he represented. The Attorney<lb/>General says there were five hundred<lb/>guns and then thousand rounds of cart<lb break="no"/>ridge sent to that very County, nd put<lb/>in the hands of men who knew how to<lb/>use them, and would use thm in time<lb/>of need, which we should believe,<lb/>(Mr. Lindsay - In the absence of my<lb/>colleague, I will state what I have<lb/>from good authority, that if the yeoman<lb break="no"/>ry were to be called out, they had but three<lb/>rounds of ammnnition to defend their<lb/>lives with.) I will leave that County and<lb/>the Province to decide which we are to<lb/>believe. The next report I shall allude to<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
        

     is what is called the " land jobbing." 
     <lb/>
     Communication after communication, and 
     <lb/>
     editorial after editorial were written, 
     <lb/>
     month after month. accusing the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of being the"vilest rascals" that 
     <lb/>
     ever lived upon the face of the earth;— 
     <lb/>
     that they had against all law and honesty 
     <lb/>
     given to Mr. Gibson 15,000 acres of the 
     <lb/>
     public lands. For what? The papers 
     <lb/>
     said as a reward for the part he took in 
     <lb/>
     the last election. I was asked if I would 
     <lb/>
     support a Government that had been 
     <lb/>
     guilty of such things. I said I would not 
     <lb/>
    if they had been guilty of that, but 
     <lb/>I will not condemn them unheard. 
     <lb/>What is the truth of those reports? Mr. 
     <lb/>Gibson told me that he spoke to the head 
     <lb/>of the late Government to get a quantity 
     <lb/>of land on the Nashwaak. He was asked 
     <lb/>how much he wanted. He replied, 25,<lb break="no"/>000 acres. They said this was too much, 
     <lb/>and he had better be content with less; 
     <lb/>and it was agreed that he should apply 
     <lb/>for 10,000 acres, which they agreed to 
     <lb/>grant, and the rest would come after. 
     <lb/>The Hon. John McMillan was surveyor 
     <lb/>General then, and the order for the sur<lb break="no"/>vey was made. The deputy surveyed it, 
     <lb/>and Mr. Gibson paid six or seven hun<lb break="no"/>dred dollars for the survey. The late 
     <lb/>Government was still in power, when 
     <lb/>he went and asked them what time 
     <lb/>this land was to be advertised. They 
     <lb/>told him whenever he pleased. He 
     <lb/>had not the money at the time, and he 
     <lb/>wanted to know when it would be adver<lb break="no"/>tised, so that he would have the means 
     <lb/>ready to purchase it, and this was the 
     <lb/>position in which things stood when the 
     <lb/>late Government went out. The news<lb break="no"/>papers said the present Government had 
     <lb/>given to Mr. Gibson a three years' li<lb break="no"/>cense, so that he would not be opposed 
     <lb/>at the sale of this land. This license was 
     <lb/>given twelve months previous to the pre<lb break="no"/>sent Government's coming into power. 
     <lb/>Therefore, all that has been said in the 
     <lb/>newspapers  by the editors and their cor<lb break="no"/>respondents, has fallen harmless upon the 
     <lb/>present Government, but applies to the 
     <lb/>late Government. I want this particu<lb break="no"/>larly understood, because one-half the 
     <lb/>people of Kent are up in arms about it. 
     <lb/>There is another report which I want to 
     <lb/>allude to, and which made my blood boil 
     <lb/>when I heard it. It was said that all the 
     <lb/>" Antis" were little better than Fenians 
     <lb/>or rebels. I was elected an Anti, or, 
     <lb/>more properly speaking. an opponent of 
     <lb/>the Quebec Scheme; and. although many 
     <lb/>of my best friends are Confederates, and 
     <lb/>there are others whose opinions I value 
     <lb/>very highly, who have gone through the 
     <lb/>Province lecturing on Confederation, and 
     <lb/>telling the people that it would make the 
     <lb/>country prosper by opening up a market 
     <lb/>through the length and breadth of the 
     <lb/>Canadas. Notwithstanding this, I am 
     <lb/>still opposed to the Quebec Scheme, al<lb break="no"/>though my opinion may be but as a drop 
     <lb/>in the bucket, in comparison with those 
     <lb/>eloquent gentlemen, I differ from them 
     <lb/>in respect to the opening up of the Cana<lb break="no"/>das as a market for our productions and 
     <lb/>manufactures. In place of its opening up 
     <lb/>Canada as a market for New Brunswick 
     <lb/>productions, it will open up New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick for Canadian manufactures. This 
     <lb/>can only be decided by endeavoring to 
     <lb/>find out whether New Brunswick can 
     <lb/>under-sell Canada. I might found an 
     <lb/>argument upon an experience of twenty 
     <lb/>years, during which I have imported 
     <lb/>largely of the productions and manufac<lb break="no"/>tures of Canada. A few years ago the 
     <lb/>people of the North Shore were in the 
     <lb/>
 

    
            <pb n="58" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_058.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="num">58</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 
   

     habit of importing all their castings,    
     <lb/>
     boots and shoes, soap and candles, and 
     <lb/>
    various other articles from Canada, pay<lb break="no"/>ing from seven and a half to twelve per 
     <lb/>cent., besides all other charges. And 
     <lb/>some still continue to import them and put 
     <lb/>them in our stores cheaper than they can 
     <lb/>be produced in New Brunswick; and. 
     <lb/>until a year or two ago, I have seen stoves, 
     <lb/>boots, shoes, and various other articles 
     <lb/>of that kind imported from Canada, pay<lb break="no"/>ing seven and a half per cent.. and still 
     <lb/>come cheaper than the manufactures of 
     <lb/>New Brunswick. I have bought stoves 
     <lb/>from the foundries of New Brunswick 
     <lb/>which were imported from Canada, and 
     <lb/>sold to me cheaper than they could pro<lb break="no"/>duce them themselves. A large trader 
     <lb/>in Mirimachi showed me, within nine 
     <lb/>months, a quantity of boots and shoes, 
     <lb/>which he had imported, and asked me 
     <lb/>what I thought they cost him. I said, 
     <lb/>about fifteen shillings. He said, I have 
     <lb/>paid all the expenses up to this time, and 
     <lb/>they cost me about $2.50 a pair. This 
     <lb/>was a gentleman who had advocated Con<lb break="no"/>federation. I asked him what they would 
     <lb/>cost in New Brunswick. He said $3.00. 
     <lb/>I asked him how our manufactures in 
     <lb/>New Brunswick would stand after that 
     <lb/>seven and a half per cent. duty is taken 
     <lb/>off. He said that was none of his busi<lb break="no"/>ness. I might argue this matter at some 
     <lb/>length, but I will not take up the time. 
     <lb/>I shall merely say that I object to the 
     <lb/>Quebec Scheme in various ways. It will 
     <lb/>entail an extra expense upon the union 
     <lb/>of $2,000,000 a year. That is a larger 
     <lb/>amount than we can afford to pay. Ano<lb break="no"/>ther objection is representation by popu<lb break="no"/>lation. If we are joined by Nova Scotia, 
     <lb/>Prince Edward's Island and Newfound<lb break="no"/>land, our representatives will only be 
     <lb/>forty out of one hundred and ninety-four, 
     <lb/>but it is doubtful whether we will be 
     <lb/>joined by them. Another objection to 
     <lb/>the scheme is eighty cents per head, 
     <lb/>which I consider entirely too small and 
     <lb/>too much power is given to the Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment at Ottawa. They have the power 
     <lb/>of vetoing almost everything that is 
     <lb/>done by the local Governments. That is a 
     <lb/>power l do not wish to see taken from 
     <lb/>us.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I am a New Brunswicker by adoption, 
     <lb/>
     for I have lived here since the happy days 
     <lb/>
     of childhood, and all I hold dearest on 
     <lb/>
     earth live in New Brunswick. Whatever 
     <lb/>
     I possess of wordly goods I have made in 
     <lb/>
     this Province. Therefore, it has my best 
     <lb/>
     wishes for its prosperty, and my best ser<lb break="no"/>vices are due and shall be devoted to her 
     <lb/>
     services, but notwithstanding all this I 
     <lb/>
     am a Briton by birth, and I am proud— 
     <lb/>
     as, I trust, every member on the floors of 
     <lb/>
     this House is—to call myself a British 
     <lb/>
     subject. It is fron Britain we look for 
     <lb/>
     protection and aid in our time of need. 
     <lb/>
     From Britain we have received whatever 
     <lb/>
     aid was necessary for us, and it is pretty 
     <lb/>
     certain that before long we will have to 
     <lb/>
     look to Britain again to protect our fish<lb break="no"/>eries. It, therefore, becomes our interest 
     <lb/>
     as well as our duty to meet the wishes of 
     <lb/>
     the British Government, as far as is con<lb break="no"/>sistent with our own interests. She has 
     <lb/>
     expressed a wish for a union of these 
     <lb/>
     Provinces. There may be a great diffi<lb break="no"/>culty in concocting a scheme of union, 
     <lb/>
     but l should like to see ourselves put in 
     <lb/>
     a proper light in the eyes of Britain I 
     <lb/>
     should like to be able to say to the 
     <lb/>
     British Government: The Government of 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick have said they do not 
     <lb/>
     want to go into confederation. The peo<lb break="no"/>ple have said so at the last election, an 
     <lb/>
          

            <cb/>
        

     election called for the purpose of giving<lb/>expression of opinion on that subject. 
     <lb/>
     We do not want the Quebec Scheme, we, 
     <lb/>
     the loyal people of New Brunswick, anx<lb break="no"/>ious to meet the wishes of the mother 
     <lb/>
     country in order to show their attach<lb break="no"/>ment, a scheme has been prepared which 
     <lb/>
     we now beg to submit, and which will 
     <lb/>
     show to the people of Britain that we are 
     <lb/>
     a loyal people. That is the position in 
     <lb/>
     which I should like to see us; and al<lb break="no"/>though I am still strongly opposed to 
     <lb/>
     Confederation and the Quebec Scheme, 
     <lb/>
     still if such a scheme could be concocted 
     <lb/>
     I would like to see it gone into. The 
     <lb/>
     first step would be to deputise an equal 
     <lb/>
     number of Confederates and anti-Confed<lb break="no"/>erates from each Province to consider a 
     <lb/>
     a scheme, which is to be submitted to the 
     <lb/>
     Legislature of the different Provinces, 
     <lb/>
     but before a decision is given it should go 
     <lb/>
     back to the people. and I have no doubt 
     <lb/>
     but it would meet the wishes of a large 
     <lb/>
     majority of the people of the County of 
     <lb/>
     Kent, who are now stronly opposed to 
     <lb/>
     the Quebec Scheme. Let me not be 
     <lb/>
     misunderstood. I do not want to see a 
     <lb/>
     scheme like the Quebec Scheme put upon 
     <lb/>
     the people of New Brunswick. I do not 
     <lb/>
     want to see a scheme that will harm us for 
     <lb/>
     all time to come to Canada, and place us 
     <lb/>
     in a condition of dependence upon her. 
     <lb/>
     But a scheme that will protect the best 
     <lb/>
     interests of the people of New Brunswick, 
     <lb/>
     a country in which I have lived for the 
     <lb/>
     past forty-six years, and the country in 
     <lb/>
     which I hope to die.  
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILB1">MR. GILBERT</persName>. - My hon. friend, who 
     <lb/>has just taken his seat, and myself were elec<lb break="no"/>ted to oppose a union of the British North 
     <lb/>American Colonies. We may attempt to 
     <lb/>shelter ourselves in vain, by telling the 
     <lb/>House we were pledged to oppose the 
     <lb/>Quebec Scheme, and that we can go for 
     <lb/>union in the abstract, or agree to be 
     <lb/>united politically with our sister Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces upon any terms. I tell my hon. 
     <lb/>friend that I do not think fifty of his con<lb break="no"/>stituents know much about the Quebec 
     <lb/>Scheme when they voted for him. They 
     <lb/>did so because he was opposed to union. 
     <lb/>They were not prepared to give up the 
     <lb/>Constitution of this Province, or go into 
     <lb/>any political union with Canada, without 
     <lb/>having more time than two or three 
     <lb/>weeks to consider upon it. I think he 
     <lb/>would be derelict in his duty to his con<lb break="no"/>stituents, as I would be to mine, to vote 
     <lb/>for any kind of union, unless we had fur<lb break="no"/>ther authority from the people ; therefore, 
     <lb/>I hope my hon. friend, before we get 
     <lb/>through with this debate, will look upon 
     <lb/>this question in the same light in which I 
     <lb/>look upon it, and that he will come to the 
     <lb/>conclusion that he will not be violating 
     <lb/>his pledges to his constituents of he 
     <lb/>should vote for this amendment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     As I have the honor of representing 
     <lb/>
     one - of the most important constituencies 
     <lb/>
     in the Province, who contribute largely to 
     <lb/>
     the revenues of the country, and are 
     <lb/>
     deeply interested in the proper adminis<lb break="no"/>tration of the Government of the country, 
     <lb/>
     I should neglect my duty if I should give 
     <lb/>
     a silent vote upon this most important 
     <lb/>
     question, although it would be more con<lb break="no"/>sistent with my feelings to do so, as two 
     <lb/>
     of my colleagues are in the Government. 
     <lb/>
     Sir, I regret that the affairs of this coun<lb break="no"/>try have been so conducted that it has 
     <lb/>
     become necessary to move a vote of want 
     <lb/>
     of confidence against their administra<lb break="no"/>tion, after their having such an overflow<lb break="no"/>ing majority only nine months ago. 
     <lb/>
     The hon member from the Coun<lb break="no"/>ty of Kings (Mr. Scovil) though pro<lb break="no"/>
        
            <cb/>
          
per to refer to me, in the course of his 
     <lb/>
     speech. I did not think proper to inter<lb break="no"/>rupt him while speaking, because I knew 
     <lb/>
     from experience—we. having been school<lb break="no"/>boys together—that he woull forget 
     <lb/>
     his lessons if he was interrupted. 
     <lb/>
    I had taken no part in the debate, I 
     <lb/>do not know why he referred to me, and 
     <lb/>said I had arrived at a conclusion, not 
     <lb/>through my own judgment, but through 
     <lb/>the judgment of others. He misunder<lb break="no"/>stands the person he deals with, for my 
     <lb/>hon. friend should know that this is not 
     <lb/>my character. He says it is the nature 
     <lb/>of the soil of King's County to produce 
     <lb/>fruit after its own kind, the same which 
     <lb/>was planted ; that potatoes in that Coun<lb break="no"/>ty do not produce pumpkins. Sir. that 
     <lb/>was the case when Mr. Freeze and the 
     <lb/>two McLeods were the independent and 
     <lb/>intelligent representatives from that Coun<lb break="no"/>ty. In those days, there was nothing ser<lb break="no"/>vile in the members from Kings, for they 
     <lb/>would not khow the knee nor listen to 
     <lb/>the winning voice of any man; but those 
     <lb/>men having gone to their long homes, the 
     <lb/>feelings of that County have changed in 
     <lb/>these latter days, and it is now a fact 
     <lb/>that potatoes in that County will grow 
     <lb/>pumpkins. and it may be that the true 
     <lb/>production of the soil of King's County 
     <lb/>is not present in this House, which the 
     <lb/>people of King's have sent for exhibition. 
     <lb/>and we may come to the conclusion from 
     <lb/>what we see here, that pumpkins are to 
     <lb/>be grown from potatoes in that County, 
     <lb/>the hon. member's opinion to the contrary 
     <lb/>notwithstanding. The Chief Commission<lb break="no"/>er of the board of Works said he had 
     <lb/>never referred to the hon. mover of the 
     <lb/>amendment, except when he was present, 
     <lb/>and on no occasion had he treated him as 
     <lb/>he had been by him treated; but in that 
     <lb/>same speech he refrrred to Mr. Boyd, a 
     <lb/>merchant of St. John, a gentleman of 
     <lb/>high standing, who was not in the House 
     <lb/>to defend himself. This gentleman he 
     <lb/>called "an inflated bladder" Was he 
     <lb/>not sheltering himself behind the privi<lb break="no"/>leges of this House to commit a cowardly 
     <lb/>act, to bring in the name of a private in<lb break="no"/>dividual, voluntarily, in this manner? 
     <lb/>Another hon. gentleman has taken occa<lb break="no"/>sion to refer to a gentleman who has been 
     <lb/>the leader of the late Government, and 
     <lb/>has enjoyed the confidence of the consti<lb break="no"/>tuency of St. John for many years, and 
     <lb/>who has as much interest in the welfare 
     <lb/>of the Province as those who boast so 
     <lb/>much of their dinterestedness in taking 
     <lb/>office. Has the time arrived in this coun<lb break="no"/>try when a man is to be attacked because 
     <lb/>he thinks proper to come within the walls 
     <lb/>of this House to listen to this debate? It 
     <lb/>is acting unfairly to do so, when that 
     <lb/>gentleman has not a place on the floors of 
     <lb/>this House, and in a position to defend 
     <lb/>himself, and such a course is resorted to 
     <lb/>to distract the attention of hon. members 
     <lb/>from the true issue before the House. It 
     <lb/>was for the same reason that my hon. 
     <lb/>colleague occupied fifteen minutes in try<lb break="no"/>ing to show that my hon. friend (Mr. 
     <lb/>Fisher) was wrong in giving notice of one 
     <lb/>form of amendment and submitting ano<lb break="no"/>ther. This had nothing to do with the 
     <lb/>question. The question before the House 
     <lb/>was, whether the general conduct of the 
     <lb/>Government was such that they should 
     <lb/>enjoy the confidence of the House ? I was 
     <lb/>one of those who advised him to to make 
     <lb/>the alteration, because I thought the lan<lb break="no"/>guage used in the amendment. which he 
     <lb/>first proposed to move. and which he gave 
     <lb/>notice of, might be construed to be an 
     <lb/>undue reflection upon the neighboring 
     <lb/>
   

            <pb n="59" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_059.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE 0F ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>   <fw type="num">59</fw> 


     Republic. Neither has it anything to do 
     <lb/>
     with the question, as to the manner in 
     <lb/>
     which the hon. mover of the amendment 
     <lb/>
     was ushered into the world, nor whether 
     <lb/>
     the Provincial Secretary came into the 
     <lb/>
     world proprrly fashioned, and with full 
     <lb/>
     faculties, or half baked. The Provincial 
     <lb/>
     Secretary tried hard to prove to the 
     <lb/>
     House that he was not a fool, and that he 
     <lb/>
     was competent to multiply, and manage 
     <lb/>
     the financial affairs of the country. 
     <lb/>
     Whether it he so or not, that is not the 
     <lb/>
     question at issue. We can examine the 
     <lb/>
     public accounts, and judge of them per<lb break="no"/>sonally. I have a high respect for my 
     <lb/>
     hon. friend. We have always enjoyed 
     <lb/>
     each other's friendship. These questions 
     <lb/>
     are ouly dwelt upon to divert attention 
     <lb/>
     from the real question before the House, 
     <lb/>
     Another irrelevant matter brought in was 
     <lb/>
     the election for the County of York. 
     <lb/>
     Whether my hon. friend gained his elec<lb break="no"/>tion through a change of public feeling in 
     <lb/>
     reference to Confederation or not, we know 
     <lb/>
     my hon. friend was a delegate to the Con<lb break="no"/>ference at Quebec, and in favor of the 
     <lb/>
     scheme, and it was natural to conclude 
     <lb/>
     that his return gave evidence of a change 
     <lb/>
     of feeling on that question. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We find that the Government of this 
     <lb/>
     country in bringing this House together 
     <lb/>
     have propounded the nature of their pol<lb break="no"/>icy in reference to Confederation. They 
     <lb/>
     promise to lay before this House the cor<lb break="no"/>respondence between the Mother Coun<lb break="no"/>try and the Governor General, relating to <lb/>
    a Union of these Colonies, and state that 
     <lb/>it is the opinion of Her Majesty's Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment that it is an object much to be 
     <lb/>desired that all the British North Ameri<lb break="no"/>can Colonies should agree to unite under 
     <lb/>one Government. In reply to that a mo<lb break="no"/>tion is made by the hon. member for 
     <lb/>Charlotte (Col. Boyd), at the instance 
     <lb/>and at the request of the Government. 
     <lb/>which in my mind, will bind this House, 
     <lb/>if adopted, to the principle of a union of 
     <lb/>these Colonies. It says:  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "But in any scheme for a Union of 
     <lb/>
     the British North American Colonies 
     <lb/>
     which may be proposed, it is, in the opi<lb break="no"/>nion of this House, absolutely essential 
     <lb/>
     that full protection should be afforded to 
     <lb/>
     the rights and interests of the people of 
     <lb/>
     this Province; and no measure which 
     <lb/>
     fails to obtain these objects, should be 
     <lb/>
    adopted. " 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Which means that this House is will<lb break="no"/>ing to adopt a scheme for the Union of 
     <lb/>
     the Provinces provided protection shall 
     <lb/>
     be afforded to the rights and interests of 
     <lb/>
     the people. Now the only way the de<lb break="no"/>tails of the scheme can ever be adjusted is 
     <lb/>
     through the Imperial Parliament, and if 
     <lb/>
     we adopt this answer to the Speech, I 
     <lb/>
     think it is all the British Government re<lb break="no"/>quires us to say. What is the cause of 
     <lb/>
     the delay that has taken place in the 
     <lb/>
     other branch of the Legislature, in His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency's not replying to their answer 
     <lb/>
     to the speech. May it not be that the re<lb break="no"/>ply given to that answer might indicate   
     <lb/>to the hon. members of the House before<lb/>
    question is concluded, the construc<lb break="no"/>tion which His Excellency and His Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment put upon the answer in the 
     <lb/>Speech now under discussion. I think' 
     <lb/>we commit ourselves and the Province to 
     <lb/>a union by this answer. Is the House 
     <lb/>willing to adopt it? I, for one, am not 
     <lb/>authorized to do so by the County of<lb/>Westmorland. Could not His Excellency 
     <lb/>reply that he fully appreciated our appre<lb break="no"/>hensions and fears, and while thanking 
     <lb/>
     

            <cb/>
    

     the loyal commons of New Brunswick in 
     <lb/>
     meeting the wishes of the Imperial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment as far as expressing a wish to 
     <lb/>
    have these Colonies united. he could as 
     <lb/>sure us that the Imperial Government 
     <lb/>would carry out no scheme, unless the 
     <lb/>rights of this people are protected. And 
     <lb/>how would that be looked after? By 
     <lb/>sending a delegation to the Mother Coun<lb break="no"/>try to see that when the Imperial Act un<lb break="no"/>iting these Colonies is drawn up, our 
     <lb/>rights are'protected, as we cannot do this 
     <lb/>by an Act here. Having conceded the 
     <lb/>point that we are willing to unite, the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Parliament would have to carry it 
     <lb/>into effect, because if left to the different 
     <lb/>Legislatures, you would hardly get ten 
     <lb/>members to agree upon the details of the 
     <lb/>scheme. I am pledged against Union— 
     <lb/>against having a Confederate Parliament 
     <lb/>in Ottawa; therefore, as I was elected on 
     <lb/>the anti-Confederate ticket, it is my duty 
     <lb/>to my constituents to vote for this Amend<lb break="no"/>ment, and to vote against the Government 
     <lb/>on that section, and I trust that some hon. 
     <lb/>member will more an amendment to that 
     <lb/>section in case this amendment shall be 
     <lb/>negatived. The union of the British 
     <lb/>North American Colonies was put to this 
     <lb/>country in a very hasty manner, in conse 
     <lb/>quence of which the people had not time 
     <lb/>to consider the merits of the Quebec 
     <lb/>Scheme, and union in the abstract was 
     <lb/>the question upon which they decided. 
     <lb/>Although it is the Imperial policy to unite 
     <lb/>these Colonies, yet they will not unite us 
     <lb/>unless by our own consent, because the 
     <lb/>onlv way in which the constitution of a 
     <lb/>free, intelligent and independent people 
     <lb/>can be changed at all, is by revolution 
     <lb/>or the consent of the people. Although 
     <lb/>the Imperial Government have the right 
     <lb/>and power to do so, they do wisely inform 
     <lb/>ua that they will not pass an Imperial 
     <lb/>Act to unite these Provinces unless it 
     <lb/>is agreeable with the wishes of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of this country. If we adopt this 
     <lb/>paragraph in the Address, we at once 
     <lb/>forego all further legislation in the mat<lb break="no"/>ter. The details would be settled upon 
     <lb/>by an " Imperial Act., and all they want 
     <lb/>is our consent to be united. Upper and 
     <lb/>Lower Canada were united by merely 
     <lb/>giving their consent to a union in the ab<lb break="no"/>stract. The Imperial Parliament, by an 
     <lb/>Imperial Act, settled all the details and 
     <lb/>united those two Provinces together 
     <lb/>without submitting any particular scheme 
     <lb/>for their approval. Therefore, if we pass 
     <lb/>the answer to the Speech, we will be 
     <lb/>passive in the hands of the British Go<lb break="no"/>vernment. We convey to the British 
     <lb/>Government by this Address, through 
     <lb/>His Excellency. the idea that we agree 
     <lb/>in th" opinion that it would be desira<lb break="no"/>ble to unite with the other Colonies, 
     <lb/>provided our interests are looked after 
     <lb/>in the details, and that is all that is re<lb break="no"/>quired by the British Government, but it 
     <lb/>is not what my constituents sent me here  
     <lb/>to vote for. The Quebec Scheme should 
     <lb/>have been debated in this House before it 
     <lb/>went to the people. The were called 
     <lb/>upon at six weeks notice to adopt a 
     <lb/>scheme to change the whole constitu<lb break="no"/>tion of the country. It was unreasona<lb break="no"/>ble to expect the people of this country 
     <lb/>to adopt a new constitution at so short a 
     <lb/>notice. I had doubts about it, although it 
     <lb/>is well known to the hon. members of 
     <lb/>this House, and particularly to my hon. 
     <lb/>friend, Mr. Anglin, that I some years ago 
     <lb/>advocated the principle of Union, and<lb/>contributed an article to the columns of 
     <lb/>the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Freeman</hi>, in 1863, expressing that opi<lb break="no"/>nion, from which I will read an extract: 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
            <cb/>
          
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"> <p>
     "As an individual is justified by all 
     <lb/>
    honorable and laudable means to promote 
     <lb/>and raise his position in the social scale,<lb/>so are a people as a country justified by<lb/>like means in endeavoring to occupy a 
     <lb/>proud position in the scale of nations. 
     <lb/>these Colonies, seperated as the now 
     <lb/>are, one from the other, are isolated and 
     <lb/>weak; but unite them by this great high<lb break="no"/>way, join them together in bonds of social 
     <lb/>fellowship, connect them commercially 
     <lb/>with one tariff, one postal arrangement, 
     <lb/>one currency. and what will be the sure 
     <lb/>and certain result? Why it is inevitable, 
     <lb/>it will be <hi rendition="simple:italic">a political connection</hi>. Then 
     <lb/>the ambition and aspirations of our peo<lb break="no"/>ple to have a country which they may call 
     <lb/>their own, and to speak of their country, 
     <lb/>would be realized." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     In 1863 I also expressed an opinion in 
     <lb/>
     favor ofthe Inter—Colonial Railway, and 
     <lb/>
     in favor of uniting these Colonies, on the 
     <lb/>
     floors of this House. To show this, I 
     <lb/>
     will read an extract from a report of a 
     <lb/>
     speech which l delivered in this House 
     <lb/>
     that year. published in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Head Quar<lb break="no"/>ters:</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " He looked upon this railway from a 
     <lb/>
     broad point of view. lt would tend to 
     <lb/>
     bind the Provinces together, and bring 
     <lb/>
     them into close political and commercial 
     <lb/>
     relations, and lead to the three Provinces 
     <lb/>
     adopting one political arrangement, one 
     <lb/>
     tariff, one currency, and eventually raise 
     <lb/>
     these three disjointed Provinces into a 
     <lb/>
     great country, inhabited by a great peo<lb break="no"/>ple, possessing a literature and a scien<lb break="no"/>tific reputation of its own, and having a 
     <lb/>
     Legislature thal would command the 
     <lb/>
     respect of the world."  
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

   
            <p>
     Feeling, as I have always felt, an anx<lb break="no"/>ious desire to promote the best interests 
     <lb/>
     of my native Province and feeling that it 
     <lb/>
     would be best promoted by being united 
     <lb/>
     with our sister Colonies, which union 
     <lb/>
     must bring about connection by railway, 
     <lb/>
     and lead to other benefits, and that unless 
     <lb/>
     that connection took place, we must in<lb break="no"/>eviably become united to the neighbor<lb break="no"/>ing Republic; and being descended from 
     <lb/>
     the Loyalists, who had taken up arms in 
     <lb/>
     defence of British institutions, I am not 
     <lb/>
     prepared to place myself or my posterity 
     <lb/>
     in a position that, should we become an<lb break="no"/>nexed to the United States a time might 
     <lb/>
     come when myself or posterity would be 
     <lb/>
     called upon to take up arms to fight 
     <lb/>
     against the mother country. Wishing, 
     <lb/>
     therefore, to perpetuate British institu<lb break="no"/>tions in this countt, I have always enter<lb break="no"/>tained a desire to see these British North 
     <lb/>
     American Provinces united as one Colony 
     <lb/>
     with a combined interest under the pro<lb break="no"/>tection of Great Britain. I have always 
     <lb/>
     entertained those opinions, but I was not 
     <lb/>
     prepared at so short a notice to agree to 
     <lb/>
     a union based upon the Quebec Scheme, 
     <lb/>
     for I considered that it required further 
     <lb/>
     deliberation before we should accept it. 
     <lb/>
     Neither were the people in the County of 
     <lb/>
     Westmorland in favor of it at the late 
     <lb/>
     election in March, and I should resign my 
     <lb/>
     seat before voting in favor of a union of 
     <lb/>
     theseColonies, either the abstract, by 
     <lb/>
     implication, or any other way. I express<lb break="no"/>ed feelings in favor of union at the last 
     <lb/>
     general election, but I gave reasons why 
     <lb/>
     l came out in opposition to so hasty a de<lb break="no"/>sire to bring about a union under the 
     <lb/>
     Quebec Scheme; and pledged myself 
     <lb/>
     most positively to oppose it. When 
     <lb/>
     solemn pledges are made to the people, 
     <lb/>
     upon which a man is elected to this House, 
     <lb/>
         

            <pb n="60" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_060.jpg"/>
   

     <fw type="num">60</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE 0F ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 
 

     they should be holden sacred. I am not 
     <lb/>
     the man to violate them. It might be 
     <lb/>
     proper and correct in questions affecting 
     <lb/>
     the domestic policy of the Province, 
     <lb/>
     affecting our public works or any other 
     <lb/>
     great leading interest connected with our 
     <lb/>
     own local affairs, that even an honorable 
     <lb/>
     member of this House has conscien<lb break="no"/>ciously changed his opinion from those 
     <lb/>
     he was pledged to observe at the hustings, 
     <lb/>
     to vote in this House according to his 
     <lb/>
     changed opinions. and in opposition to 
     <lb/>
     his pledges, because a member of this 
     <lb/>
     House represents not only a local consti<lb break="no"/>tuency but slso the whole people, and 
     <lb/>
     because at the next election his succes<lb break="no"/>sor, should he be not returned, could 
     <lb/>
     repeal in effect at his vote, and a suc<lb break="no"/>ceeding House could undo what a pre<lb break="no"/>vious House had done. Such cases have 
     <lb/>
     often happened in England and in the 
     <lb/>
     Colonies. We all know the course Sir 
     <lb/>
     Robert Peel took in reference to free 
     <lb/>
     trade, although pledged to his constitu<lb break="no"/>ents to support a high protective policy. 
     <lb/>
     But in cases of that kind a man might be 
     <lb/>
     justified to act different from his pledges 
     <lb/>
     and take the consequences, but this is not 
     <lb/>
     a parallel case. This Confederation 
     <lb/>
     strikes at the whole Constitution of the 
     <lb/>
     country, strikes at the Constitution of 
     <lb/>
     this House, and, if carried. no subse<lb break="no"/>quent House could alter or repeal what 
     <lb/>
     we might do. No subsequent House 
     <lb/>
     could retrace the steps which we had ta<lb break="no"/>ken. Like the fall of a tree, a subsequent 
     <lb/>House would be lifeless. The act had 
     <lb/>been committed; therefore, Sir, no mem<lb break="no"/>ber could justify himself before his coun<lb break="no"/>try, however much his opinions might 
     <lb/>have changed in reference to the desira<lb break="no"/>bility of a union, to vote for it in this 
     <lb/>Housc when he is pledged to his consti<lb break="no"/>tuents to vote against it. I shall not do 
     <lb/>so, although I am convinced of the desira<lb break="no"/>bility of being confederated and of unit<lb break="no"/>ing with our sister Colonies  But unless 
     <lb/>I get further authority from my constitu<lb break="no"/>ents, I cannot go for it. I am prepared, 
     <lb/>should my constituents want my services, 
     <lb/>to go back to them at the next election 
     <lb/>in favor of Confederation, favor of car<lb break="no"/>rying out the supreme wishes of the 
     <lb/>mother country on this question. Leav<lb break="no"/>ing this subject for the present, I have 
     <lb/>other good reasons for voting against the 
     <lb/>Government . 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Government have been guilty of mal<lb break="no"/>administration in the affairs of the Crown 
     <lb/>Land Department. They try to throw 
     <lb/>blame on the late Government. We are 
     <lb/>not here to-day to try the wrongs of the 
     <lb/>late Government or any previous Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. If the late Government should 
     <lb/>have issued an order of survey for every 
     <lb/>acre of the public land in this Province, to 
     <lb/>sell all the lands of the country to one 
     <lb/>man, would you justify this Government 
     <lb/>if they had carried it out, and sold all the 
     <lb/>lands of the country to one individual. 
     <lb/>If the late Government thought proper 
     <lb/>to issue an order for survey to lock up in 
     <lb/>the hands of one individual land to the 
     <lb/>extent of 15,000 acres, which is nearly as 
     <lb/>large as the whole Parish of Dorchester, 
     <lb/>the present Government were not bound 
     <lb/>to carry it out. I came not here to say 
     <lb/>whether the late Government did right or 
     <lb/>wrong. I am not here to advocate the 
     <lb/>late Government, for I frequently gave 
     <lb/>them opposition on questions in which I 
     <lb/>thought they were wrong. The late 
     <lb/>Government thought proper to issue an 
     <lb/>order for survey, and if the incoming 
     <lb/>Government thought a great wrong was 
     <lb/>going to he done to the people of this 
     <lb/>
      
            <cb/>
         

     country, by granting to one than 15,000 
     <lb/>
     acres in fee simple for all time to come, 
     <lb/>
    they should have refunded the money 
     <lb/>paid for the survey to the man for whom 
     <lb/>the survey was made, for the policy of the 
     <lb/>Government should be to defend the in<lb break="no"/>terests of the people in preference to sub<lb break="no"/>serving the private interests of a private in<lb break="no"/>dividual. In England we see cases where 
     <lb/>companies am subsidized to run a line of 
     <lb/>steamships. The company has to run the 
     <lb/>risk of the policy of the incoming Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in respect to the continuation of 
     <lb/>the subsidy and it is no breach of faith 
     <lb/>to withhold it. So in this case, there 
     <lb/>would have been no breach of faith what<lb break="no"/>ever, for the duty the Government owed 
     <lb/>to the people of this country was of far 
     <lb/>more importance than to comply with the 
     <lb/>wishes of a private individual, however 
     <lb/>enterprising he may be. Talk about the 
     <lb/>wrongs of Ireland, and I know she has 
     <lb/>wrongs. for if ever there was a down<lb break="no"/>trodden country it is Ireland. This wrong 
     <lb/>has been brought about by the same sys<lb break="no"/>tem this Government is now pursuing, 
     <lb/>that is, locking up large blocks of land 
     <lb/>which should belong to the yeomenry of 
     <lb/>this country. The occupier of the land 
     <lb/>should own the land, and this principle of 
     <lb/>serfdom should not be introduced into this 
     <lb/>country. Notwithstanding the expres<lb break="no"/>sion of opinion by my hon friend from 
     <lb/>the County of Kent (Mr. Caie), the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of that County will say, the land of 
     <lb/>this country belongs to the people of this 
     <lb/>country, who have to roll the black logs 
     <lb/>and pile the black stumps, and cannot 
     <lb/>afford to pay rent to any man. We must 
     <lb/>avoid the errors of the mother country 
     <lb/>and take lessons from the wrongs and 
     <lb/>errors done to Ireland, in order to pur<lb break="no"/>sue a different course. It may be very 
     <lb/>well to gratify the wishes of any private 
     <lb/>individual to sell him a large block of 
     <lb/>land, but we must reflect that in so doing 
     <lb/>we legislate for all time to come, and in<lb break="no"/>troduce into this country, in future time, 
     <lb/>n a system ruinous to the future welfare of 
     <lb/>the country, and for which our posterity 
     <lb/>will blame us, for it is natural to suppose 
     <lb/>that if we lock up whole Townships, by 
     <lb/>adopting the same course that has been 
     <lb/>adopted in Ireland, the same effects will 
     <lb/>be produced. I condemn the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment most particularly on that point, for 
     <lb/>I do not think the late Government com<lb break="no"/>mitted the incoming Government to any 
     <lb/>line of policy, and they would have been 
     <lb/>guilty of no breach of faith if they had 
     <lb/>withheld the grant, and reimbursed the 
     <lb/>individual for the costs of survey. Dur<lb break="no"/>ing the last sitting of the Legislature I 
     <lb/>expressed disappointment in the conduct 
     <lb/>of the Government, because they had no 
     <lb/>policy. I could not suppose that men 
     <lb/>would come together under our system 
     <lb/>having a constitutional and departmental 
     <lb/>Government, without having some line of 
     <lb/>policy. In England they often form a 
     <lb/>Government over night, and a full policy 
     <lb/>is arranged, otherwise the Government 
     <lb/>could not be formed. If it be an<lb break="no"/>nounced to the representatives of Her 
     <lb/>Majesty in this Province, that they 
     <lb/>have succeeded in forming a Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, the idea is conveyed that 
     <lb/>that Government has adopted some policy 
     <lb/>under which they intend to administer 
     <lb/>the affairs of the country. Confederation 
     <lb/>was settled at the polls, and the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the mother country have informed 
     <lb/>us that they will not legislate away our 
     <lb/>rights until we consent. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment should have been formed upon 
     <lb/>local policy, in a colony where a depart<lb break="no"/>
          

            <cb/>
     
mental and responsible Government is<lb/>established. Why then did the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment prescribe men, because they sym<lb break="no"/>pathised with the imperial policy, over<lb/>which policy this local Government could<lb/>have no control, any further than by ex<lb break="no"/>pressing in a despatch to the mother <lb/>country that our own people had decided<lb/>against it? The wished of the people<lb/>having been expressed at the ballot box<lb/>against the scheme, the local Government<lb/>could only be formed on a local policy,<lb/>and not antagonistic to the imperial policy, 
     <lb/>
     whatever that may be. Suppose there 
     <lb/>
     was- going to be a war between England 
     <lb/>
     and any power in any part of Europe or 
     <lb/>
     the neighboring Republic, and we should 
     <lb/>
     get up an anti-war party, or party in favor 
     <lb/>
     of war, would it be right to form a Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment in this province on either of those 
     <lb/>
     principles if it interfered with the policy 
     <lb/>
     of the Imperial Government? Not at all. 
     <lb/>
     The Government must be formed on local 
     <lb/>
     grounds to carry out the local wants and 
     <lb/>
     requirements of the country; from what 
     <lb/>
     has transpired during the debate, from 
     <lb/>
     the statements made by my hon. friend 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Wilmot, it would appear that His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency sent for him and my colleague 
     <lb/>
     to form the administration, and it would 
     <lb/>
     seem that notwithstanding Mr. Wilmot 
     <lb/>
     had had great political experience. had 
     <lb/>
     been the leading mind in a previous Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, had great knowledge of the 
     <lb/>
     commercial and agricultural wants of the 
     <lb/>
     country; that my colleague took upon 
     <lb/>
     himself the exclusive right of the forma<lb break="no"/>tion of the Government, and brought men 
     <lb/>
     together in that Government without any 
     <lb/>
     policy. and upon no known principle. I 
     <lb/>
     find no fault at the personal of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, and particularly none to my col<lb break="no"/>league. (Mr. Botsford being taken in as 
     <lb/>
     Surveyor General. I expressed myself 
     <lb/>
     at the time, satisfied at his appointment. 
     <lb/>
     I find fault that they started upon a do- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     nothing system. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>The House of Assembly was called to<lb break="no"/>gether on the 27th day of April last, and, 
     <lb/>the Speech from the Throne was delivered, 
     <lb/>but there was no policy in it: the great 
     <lb/>interests which should occupy the atten<lb break="no"/>tion of the administration of the country 
     <lb/>was completely ignore . The most im<lb break="no"/>portant interest is the settlement of te 
     <lb/>country, by which we get an increase of 
     <lb/>labor, which increases the wealth of the 
     <lb/>country. This important interest was 
     <lb/>not mentioned in the Speech. We were 
     <lb/>left in doubt as to the Legislative enact<lb break="no"/>ments that stood in the way of the com<lb break="no"/>pletion of our Railroads, and the educa<lb break="no"/>tional institutions of the country were, 
     <lb/>not alluded to. I then thought proper to 
     <lb/>rise in my place and ask for information 
     <lb/>but l was denounced by my hon. collea<lb break="no"/>gue the leader of the Government, who 
     <lb/>said he did not wish my support. At 
     <lb/>that time the Government had in their 
     <lb/>possession an important despatch from 
     <lb/>the Mother Country in reference to a 
     <lb/>Union of the Colonies. which if known 
     <lb/>to the House at that time, would have 
     <lb/>obviated the necessity of sending a dele<lb break="no"/>gation home to England. If I had known 
     <lb/>of it, I would have moved an address to 
     <lb/>have it laid before the House. I believed 
     <lb/>at that time that the Mother Country did 
     <lb/>not fully endorse a Union of the Colonies. 
     <lb/>I believed at that time that the Canadians 
     <lb/>concocted the Scheme to redress their 
     <lb/>own private wrongs, but I do not believe 
     <lb/>it now. I believed too at that time that 
     <lb/>they did not intend to build the Intercolo<lb break="no"/>nial Railway, but wished to go into a 
     <lb/>Union for the purpose of getting over 
     <lb/>
     

            <pb n="61" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-26_Page_061.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  <fw type="num">61</fw> 
   

     some local difficulties respecting repre<lb break="no"/>sentation by population. I did not know 
     <lb/>at the last session this Union was so ful<lb break="no"/>ly and completely approved of and endor<lb break="no"/>sed by the Imperial Government, and 
     <lb/>therefore I voted to send a delegation to 
     <lb/>England to represent our opinions on the 
     <lb/>question. I should not have voted for 
     <lb/>that delegation had I read that despatch, 
     <lb/>which was in the possession of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment at the time and withheld from 
     <lb/>the House, for I would then have under<lb break="no"/>stood the true policy of the British Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. They do not have one policy 
     <lb/>to-day and another tomorrow; they 
     <lb/>do not come to a conclusion very hastily<lb/>upon any matter. After making enquiry 
     <lb/>into all that related to the Colonies, and 
     <lb/>the prospect of the Reiciprocity Treaty 
     <lb/>being abrogated, they had made up their 
     <lb/>minds maturely. They have, no doubt, 
     <lb/>like other men, erred in managing the 
     <lb/>affairs of this great Empire, but they do 
     <lb/>not arrive at an hasty conclusion, one 
     <lb/>that can be repealed by our sending a de<lb break="no"/>legation to have an interview of a few 
     <lb/>hours, even although it consisted of two 
     <lb/>of our ablest men. I should have thought, 
     <lb/>however, that one delegate was sufficient. 
     <lb/>The late Attorney General should have 
     <lb/>been left to look after the business of the 
     <lb/>country, while the President of the 
     <lb/>Council would have been competent to<lb/>have made lal the repreentations to the<lb/>British Government that was necessary.<lb/>By this arrangement there would have<lb/>been a saving of five hundred pounds 
     <lb/>to the tax-payer": of this Province. The 
     <lb/>last two delegations sent home by the late 
     <lb/>Government to make arrangements con<lb break="no"/>cerning the building of Railroads cost 
     <lb/>only $900 each, while this delegation cost 
     <lb/>$3,558, which is a larger sum than was 
     <lb/>given last year for all our bye roads in the 
     <lb/>County of Westmorland. I think they 
     <lb/>compete with the Government of the 
     <lb/>Mother Country, collectively and indivi<lb break="no"/>dually, in reference  to their great British 
     <lb/>Colonial policy without having a conferee 
     <lb/>to assist him, but this delegation should 
     <lb/>not have been sent at all, and I do not 
     <lb/>believe it twould have been sent if the 
     <lb/>Government, during the sitting of the 
     <lb/>House at the last session, had communi<lb break="no"/>cated to the House information which they 
     <lb/>had of the views of the Mother Country 
     <lb/>upon the question. We should economize 
     <lb/>the public money. I have always opposed 
     <lb/>delegations. The basis of all Govern<lb break="no"/>ments is money, without which we cannot 
     <lb/>pay our liabilities, or keep up with the re<lb break="no"/>quirements or the improvements of the 
     <lb/>country; therefore, we should look close<lb break="no"/>ly into the way in which the public mo<lb break="no"/>ney is expended, and although two or 
     <lb/>three thousand dollars is a small amount 
     <lb/>yet there in a principle involved in it that 
     <lb/>when money is squandered it is our duty 
     <lb/>to express our dissatisfaction; and so it<lb/>is our duty to express our dissatisfaction<lb/>when the Govenrment violate the known<lb/>laws of the country. What puts the cri<lb break="no"/>minal in the box? It is for violating the 
     <lb/>laws of his country. Should we then 
     <lb/>permit the Government , who violate the 
     <lb/>known laws of the country, as I can show 
     <lb/>their Governmental power and influence. 
     <lb/>Some years ago, in a conflict like this, 
     <lb/>my late brother, who was then a member 
     <lb/>of this House, and in whose political 
     <lb/>school I was trained, said that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of that day had violated the laws 
     <lb/>

            <cb/>
         

     of the country in not appointing comis<lb break="no"/>sioners to build the Railroad, as required 
     <lb/>
     by law , they having taken it upon them<lb break="no"/>selves to build it by private individuals. 
     <lb/>
     There was a principle involved in this, 
     <lb/>
     and my hon. colleague Mr. Smith, and 
     <lb/>
     my late brother, were side by side on 
     <lb/>
     that question. They said, if we allow the 
     <lb/>
     Government to volate the laws of the 
     <lb/>
     country in one instance, where would 
     <lb/>
     they stop them? TheGovernment of 
     <lb/>
     the day was defeated on this principle. 
     <lb/>
     I can show a like principle involved in 
     <lb/>
     this debate. (Mr. Gilbert then read the 
     <lb/>
     law regarding the appointment of Auditor 
     <lb/>
     General, and continued.) Here is the law 
     <lb/>
     which is just as much the law of the land 
     <lb/>
     as the law which creates this Parliament 
     <lb/>
     given the electors the right to vote, or 
     <lb/>
     gives the candidates the right to offer for 
     <lb/>
     this House. If you look at the public 
     <lb/>
     accounts, you will find some $25,000 re<lb break="no"/>maining in the handa of the deputies at 
     <lb/>
     the end of the present year, scattered 
     <lb/>
     throughout the Province. The Auditor 
     <lb/>
     Genertal stands between the Government 
     <lb/>
     and the people, to audit, examine and 
     <lb/>
     vouch all accounts, he having a judicial 
     <lb/>
     power to summon witnesses from any 
     <lb/>
     part of the Province, and examine them 
     <lb/>
     on oath, in explanation of proof and 
     <lb/>
     vouchers. Have not the Government 
     <lb/>
     violated the laws of the country in not 
     <lb/>appointing this officer? What can a <lb/>Government do to cause the representa<lb break="no"/>tives of the people to withhold their con<lb break="no"/>fidence from them, if that is not suffi<lb break="no"/>cient?</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">
       T.P.D.
            </p>
   


<!-- GL, 2018-03-06, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p>
     TUESDAY, MARCH 27. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The House went into Committee of the 
     <lb/>
     Whole (MR. A. C. DESBRISAY in the 
     <lb/>
     chair) on a Bill relating to the partition of 
     <lb/>lands.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     MR. WILLISTON explained that the 
     <lb/>
     object of the Bill was to provide that the 
     <lb/>
     costs of the partition of land should be 
     <lb/>
     borne by parties having shares in it, ac<lb break="no"/>cording to the respective value of their 
     <lb/>
     shares; the costs should be apportioned 
     <lb/>
    according to the respective value of 
     <lb/>their respective shares. As the law 
     <lb/>stood, each party hnd to bear an 
     <lb/>equal proportion of the costs. Before 
     <lb/>introducing it, he had submitted the 
     <lb/>Bill to the Master of the Rolls, and it 
     <lb/>had been referred to a committee of legal 
     <lb/>gentlemen. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     A long discussion, and technical dis<lb break="no"/>cussion followed. All the hon. members 
     <lb/>
     who spoke agreed that the principle of 
     <lb/>
     the Bill was just and equitable, and as 
     <lb/>
     far as it went, was a great improvement 
     <lb/>
     over the law as it stood. But it was 
     <lb/>
     argued; that though the Bill ought to pass 
     <lb/>
     as being a step in the right direction, it 
     <lb/>
     did not go far enough. The whole mode 
     <lb/>
    of partition of lands ought to be simplified. 
     <lb/>At present parties were obliged to go 
     <lb/>into an expensive suit in the Court of 
     <lb/>Chancery, thaat might eat up the whole 
     <lb/>estate, and it might happen that one 
     <lb/>party, out of several having shares in 
     <lb/>land, could force the others into court, 
     <lb/>and compel a division against their will, 
     <lb/>and subject them to equal costs, irrespec<lb break="no"/>tive of the value of their respective shares. 
     <lb/>It was suggested that a simpler mode 
     <lb/>might be adopted. Hon Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, Hon. Suneyor General, Mesrs. 
     <lb/>Wilmot, Anglin, Kerr, Otty, Lindsay, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     McClellan, Connel, and Dr. Thompson 
     <lb/>
     spoke. Bill agreed to. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>The adjourned debate on the amend<lb break="no"/>ment to the address stood for twelve 
     <lb/>o'clock, but was not taken up until the 
     <lb/>afternoon, when Mr. Gilbert resumed. 
     <lb/>MR. GILBERT  [referring to a ques<lb break="no"/>tion put by him to hon. member from 
     <lb/>St. John (Mr. Anglin) calling on him 
     <lb/>to make known the reasons of his resig<lb break="no"/>nation ,] said he thought his hon. col<lb break="no"/>league (Attorney General) had forgot<lb break="no"/>ten that he stated to the House that he 
     <lb/>did not give his reasons for resigning 
     <lb/>his seat as an Executive Councillor. 
     <lb/>He (Mr. Gilbert) had a distinct recol<lb break="no"/>lection that he did, and they were put 
     <lb/>in the Journals of the House as a Mat= 
     <lb/>ter of record. He had called upon the 
     <lb/>hon. member of St. John (Mr. Anglin) 
     <lb/>to give his reasons for leaving the Gov - 
     <lb break="maybe"/>ernment, and he had been told that it 
     <lb/>was an extraordinary thing to ask that 
     <lb/>information; but he would tell his hon. 
     <lb/>friend that he had not done his duty to 
     <lb/>the country, in not making them known. 
     <lb/>For his own part he wished to under<lb break="no"/>stand the full reasons of his resignation, 
     <lb/>as it was important that everything 
     <lb/>should be known that had a bearning 
     <lb/>upon the question under discussion. He 
     <lb/>would now resume . 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>With regard to the great question of 
     <lb/>the union of the Colonies, and he spoke 
     <lb/>with all due deference to the able men 
     <lb/>of the Confederate party, who had 
     <lb/>framed the measure, he thought that 
     <lb/>they did submit the scheme in far too 
     <lb/>hasty a manner. It would not, he 
     <lb/>conceived, have added to the character 
     <lb/>of the people of the Province for pru<lb break="no"/>dence and sagacity, to have accepted it 
     <lb/>without deliberation and without 
     <lb/>demanding more time for serious 
     <lb/>reflection. But since the first sub<lb break="no"/>mittal of the scheme, they had had 
     <lb/>many important considerations brought 
     <lb/>before their their notice that clearly demon<lb break="no"/>strated the propriety of effecting the 
     <lb/>union of the Provinces. They had been 
     <lb/>authoritatively informed by dispatches 
     <lb/>from the Colonial Secretary, that it was 
     <lb/>the expressed and avowed policy of Her 
     <lb/>Majesty's Government, that union 
     <lb/>should take place. They had been 
     <lb/>made to understand that it was the de<lb break="no"/>sire of that Government not to have 
     <lb/> Canada pulling one way, Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>pulling in another, and New Brunswick 
     <lb/>in another, but to have them all united 
     <lb/>under one General Government, with 
     <lb/>one policy and one interest. Though<lb/> 
               <lb/>the sectional difficulties of the Canadas 
     <lb/>had he confessed, in the first instance 
     <lb/>stared the question, there were other 
     <lb/>reasons that had urged it on. The 
     <lb/>mother county had looked to the state 
     <lb/>of feeling towards herself in the neigh<lb break="no"/>boring Republic, and to its aggressive 
     <lb/>spirit; she had seen that the abrogation 
     <lb/>of the Reciprocity Treaty was certain 
     <lb/>to happen , and viewing the question of 
     <lb/>union of these Colonies as one not alone 
     <lb/>affecting themselves, but in the inter<lb break="no"/>ests of the empire at large. She de<lb break="no"/>sired their consolidation in order to 
     <lb/>continue British institutions in America.  
     <lb/>These were the reasons why she had 
     <lb/>taken so positive a stand and had ex<lb break="no"/>pressed a determination that the union 
     <lb/>of the Colonies should take place. And 
     <lb/>she looked to the vast county that 
     <lb/>stretched north of the Lakes, from 
     <lb/>Labrador to the Polar Sea, from British  
     <lb/>Columbia to Baffin Bay. She looked 
     <lb/>to the Canadas with their fertile lands,  
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>