<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1865-04-29"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-04-29">29 April 1865</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1865</title>.
                    

          <date when="1865"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
                    


          <biblScope unit="page" from="6" to="11"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_006.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_007.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_008.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_009.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_010.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_011.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
      
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-04-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-04-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_006">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_006.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_007">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_007.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_008">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_008.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_009">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_009.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_010">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_010.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_011">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_011.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="6" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_006.jpg"/>

<fw type="num">6</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>


<!-- GL, 2017-04-20, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
            <!--<p>might be so arranged now. The use of<lb/>
one coach was enough<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Mr. A. C. DESBRISAY moved an amend<lb break="no"/>ment to the Resolution, that the Contin<lb break="no"/>gent Committee be authorised to employ<lb/>
one coach for the use of the House.—<lb/>
Adopted.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Mr. NEEDHAM moved that every mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the House fold and address his own<lb/>
Debates and Journals, and post them<lb/>
without the employment of a messenger.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Hon. Mr. ALLEN hoped his honorable<lb/>
colleague would withdraw his motion.<lb/>
He thought he would do it if he gave the <lb/>
matter a few moments' consideration.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr.
HUTCHINSON was surprised at<lb/>
such a resolution being laid before the <lb/>
House. It looked like a burlesque.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. LINDSAY said that for years mem<lb break="no"/>bers had folded and addressed their own<lb/>
Journals, and he thought they could do it  <lb/>
again.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. SUTTON said the resolution was<lb/>

foolish and uncalled for, inasmuch as, if<lb/>
adopted,
it would be compulsory on mem<lb break="no"/>bers to fold and address their own Jour<lb break="no"/>nals. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Hon. Mr. ALLEN again hoped the hon.<lb/>
member would withdraw his motion. He<lb/>
thought that he would not like to see it<lb/>
inserted in the Journals of the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. NEEDHAM
would not withdraw his<lb/>
motion, unless the House consented to the<lb/>
adoption of another. It was this, that<lb/>
the offices of Sergeant at Arms, Messen<lb break="no"/>ger, and Door-keeper be abolished. If<lb/>
the House would carry that, he would<lb/>
withdraw his first resolution.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Hon. Mr. ALLEN.—Conditions could<lb/>
not be imposed on the House to influence <lb/>
the hon. member to withdraw his motion </p>
            <p>On motion of Mr. BOYD, the House here<lb/>
adjourned till to-morrow morning, at 10<lb/>
o'clock. J. M.<lb/>
            </p>-->

            <head rendition="simple:right"> SATURDAY, April 29th.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p>Mr. COSTIGAN brought in a Bill to en<lb break="no"/>courage the exploration of vacant Crown<lb/>
Lands, and the discovery of elegible tim<lb break="no"/>ber berths thereon. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. WETMORE, by leave, brought in the<lb/>
following Petitions and Bills, viz : <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to
amend an Act to provide for<lb/>
the erection of an Alms House and Work <lb/>
House, and to establish a Public Infirmary<lb/>
in and for the City of Saint John.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Petition from the Justices of the<lb/>
Peace to establish a Work House, Alms <lb/>
House and Public Infirmary.   <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> A Bill relation to the Grand Juries of<lb/>
St. John, and a Petition for the same.</p>
            <p>A Bill and Petition to provide for the<lb/>
better assessing of rates and taxes in the
<lb/>
City and County of St. John. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. WILLISTON brought in a Bill to<lb/>
authorize the Trustees of Schools in the <lb/>
Parish of Chatham, in the County of North<lb break="no"/>umberland, to sell a certain piece of land<lb/>
in the said Parish, and dispose of the pro<lb break="no"/>ceeds thereof. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. TROOP
brought in a Bill to provide <lb/>
for the relief of the sufferers by the late <lb/>
fire at Indiantown. <lb/>
Mr. OTTY moved the order of the
day, <lb/>
viz :—The consideration of the Address in <lb/>
answer to His Excellency's Speech at the <lb/>
opening of the Session.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> His Honor the SPEAKER then read the <lb/>
adddress by paragraph
; upon the reading <lb/>
of the 5th paragraph, <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. GILBERT said : This being a new <lb/>
Government it may not be amiss
for <lb/>
honorable members to express their<lb/>
opinion. The Speech being from the <lb/>
Executive, some members of whom are <lb/>
politicians of long standing, having a large<lb/>
amount of political knowledge, acquainted <lb/>
with the wants of the various parts of the<lb/>
                     <cb/> 
            
 country, therefore, we must conclude this<lb/>
in their complete policy. Although the<lb/>
present administration has only lately<lb/>
come into power, yet when I consider the<lb/>
ability of the hon. gentlemen who compose<lb/>
that Government ; when I reflect upon the<lb/>
prominent position which some of them<lb/>
have occupied in the Legislature for a<lb/>
number of years, and the long experience<lb/>
they have had in the Government of the<lb/>
country, I must suppose that they have<lb/>
had a sufficient time to have matured the<lb/>
full and entire nature of their policy.<lb/>
This Speech does not mention the great<lb/>
wants and requirements of the country. I<lb/>
see nothing in it foreshadowing their poli<lb break="no"/>cy in regard to colonization. It is coloni<lb break="no"/>zation that has made the United States<lb/>
what it is. Take from them their system<lb/>
of colonization and emigration, and let<lb/>
them depend upon their own resources,<lb/>
and instead of having a population of 30<lb/>
million, they would only have about seven<lb/>
or eight million. i consider that a pro<lb break="no"/>per system of colonization so as to secure<lb/>
an increased population, is the most im<lb break="no"/>portant subject that can occupy the atten<lb break="no"/>tion of any Government. Without an in<lb break="no"/>crease of population, we cannot have an<lb/>
increase of labour, or an increase of<lb/>
wealth, for its is labor which makes wealth.<lb/>
There are no inducements presented to<lb/>
induce emigrants to come to this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince and settle. The Crown Lands are,<lb/>
as it were, blocked up ; the small capital<lb/>
which the poor man has, is wrung from<lb/>
him in the purchase of lands on which no<lb/>
roads are made. The late Government<lb/>
made no attempts to improve the settle<lb break="no"/>ment of the country, but I did hope the<lb/>
present Government would have made it<lb/>
one of the principle features of their ad<lb break="no"/>ministration. This is no sudden idea of<lb/>
mine, for I have announced it to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of Westmorland, and it has met their<lb/>
approbation. Then there is a total ab<lb break="no"/>sence of a spirit of economy ; true, there<lb/>
is the suggestion to dispense with the Post<lb/>
Office Department, but I do not consider<lb/>
that by so doing we put a knife to that<lb/>
establishment. Why sustain the institu<lb break="no"/>tion ? There is now about £6000
defi<lb break="no"/>ciency in that Department, and there ap<lb break="no"/>pears no intention on the part of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to abolish it, but merely that they<lb/>
would not require the Postmaster General<lb/>
to be an officer of the Crown. That is<lb/>
very well so far as it goes, and I think it<lb/>
meets with the approbation of the people<lb/>
of Westmorland, but why not abolish the<lb/>
office altogether ? Mr. Howe could do<lb/>
the duties of the office at his present sal<lb break="no"/>ary. If the Government intend to abolish<lb/>
the office, why keep nine members in the<lb/>
Executive ? Why not lessen the numeri<lb break="no"/>cal strength of the Government? I think<lb/>
it would be advisable and prudent to do<lb/>
so. The second paragraph of the Speech<lb/>
will, no doubt, meet with the approbation<lb/>
of the House, and be responded to through<lb break="no"/>out the country. In the third paragraph<lb/>
it is mentioned that a diabolical murder<lb/>
has been committed, and which we all<lb/>
look upon with feelings of disapprobation.<lb/>
The late President of the United States<lb/>
was not only an honest man, but a wise<lb/>
one, and I think his death will be deplor<lb break="no"/>ed throughout the civilized world ; so far<lb/>
the Government has expressed the honest<lb/>
feelings of the country. In the United<lb/>
States they were about coming to the con<lb break="no"/>clusion of a war, and it illustrated a pro<lb break="no"/>blem, which is, that a war can be sustain<lb break="no"/>ed and carried out, on a gigantic scale,<lb/>
without a previous standing army. I<lb/>
think the great powers of Europe will<lb/>
profit by their example, and learn that it<lb/>
is not necessary in times of peace to keep<lb/>
            

            <cb/> 

    a great standing army for the purpose of<lb/>
carrying on war on a large scale. It has<lb/>
also been proved that war can be carried<lb/>
on without making a levy upon private in<lb break="no"/>dividuals, without ransacking and rob<lb break="no"/>bing churches, as was done in old times<lb/>
in Europe. It is carried on by the pro<lb break="no"/>mises of the nation ; this lesson should be<lb/>
valuable to other powers throughout the<lb/>
world. This Province requires that its<lb/>
resources should be developed by public<lb/>
works. This Province is interested in the<lb/>
welfare of St. John, it being its chief com<lb break="no"/>mercial emporium. When the trade of<lb/>
St. John is either prosperous or depressed,<lb/>
there is a corresponding degree of pros<lb break="no"/>perity of depression felt throughout the<lb/>
whole Province. We find a railroad from<lb/>
St. Andrews tapping the upper waters of<lb/>
the St. John, and gradually taking away<lb/>
the trade of that country from St. John,<lb/>
and carrying it into the United States.—
<lb/>
Nova Scotia also having a road from
Hali<lb break="no"/>fax to Pictou, the trade of that part of <lb/>
Nova Scotia and the Bay of Fundy is ta<lb break="no"/>ken to Halifax. Thus the trade of St. <lb/>
John must become depressed, unless we <lb/>
do something to connect it with Nova <lb/>
Scotia und the United States. I cannot <lb/>
see why the Government cannot
take im<lb break="no"/>mediate action in regard to the
connection <lb/>
with the United States and Nova
Scotia. <lb/>
I expected this connection 
between <lb/>
Moncton and the Nova Scotia line would <lb/>
be prosecuted immediately, and
also im<lb break="no"/>mediate steps taken to connect St. John <lb/>
with the West. I want, and hope to re<lb break="no"/>ceive information from the hon. mover of <lb/>
this Address, what law there is to prevent <lb/>
the immediate undertaking of this work. <lb/>
There was an Act passed by the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, the fourth section of which is
the
<lb/>
only section I can find in which the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment is pledged in any form.
lt says: <lb/>
" lf any company or body corporate, now <lb/>
possessing sufficient capital, shall offer to <lb/>
construct the first mentioned line of rail<lb break="no"/>way, and shall give such
assurance
of <lb/>
their ability, &amp;c." Now, I want to know <lb/>if any company having sufficient capital,<lb/>
have offered to construct Western Exten<lb break="no"/>sion ? I know of no such offer, and I<lb/>
know of no company that have offered to<lb/>
construct the line between Moncton and<lb/>
the Nova Scotia line. There is no reason<lb/>
why that gap in the line should not be<lb/>
filled up, as Nova Scotia intends to<lb/>
drive on towards the boundary line.<lb/>
I rue there may be companies formed in<lb/>
St. John ; it may be that they have raised<lb/>
sufficient capital to construct the road<lb/>
under this act ; then it might be desirable<lb/>
to wait until we see what they do, but if<lb/>
not, are the people of this Province to wait<lb/>
five years ? It is important that this time<lb/>
should not be thrown away ; we have lost<lb/>
time enough running after delegations<lb/>
which were not practicable, something in<lb/>
the distance, some great scheme that was<lb/>
to be developed in the future. In a young<lb/>
country like this, it is very important that<lb/>
we should not wait five years before we<lb/>
build Western Extension, and fill up the<lb/>
gap to the Nova Scotia boundary. Rail<lb break="no"/>ways, Telegraphs, and Steamboats, are <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>wanted to develope the resources of the<lb/>
country. These public works should be<lb/>
prosecuted at once, for the people of the</p>
            <p>country require them. I feel we have in<lb/>
the Government men who will go earnest<lb break="no"/>ly to work, with the sound of the hammer<lb/>
and pick. We want the labour of the<lb/>
country employed and something to re<lb break="no"/>present it. If the country should use its<lb/>
resources in this way, and have something<lb/>
they could show for it, it would not be<lb/>
indebtedness. We should adopt a sys<lb break="no"/>tem of strict economy, commencing with<lb/>
         
            <pb n="7" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_007.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">7</fw>

          the chief executive office of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and going over, all and every de<lb break="no"/>partment ; by this means a large amount<lb/>
could he saved annually. This is
not a <lb/>
new idea of mine. I adopted it the first
<lb/>
time I was in the House, and
attempted <lb/>
to show that £15,000 could be saved an<lb break="no"/>nually by a system of retrenchment. I <lb/>
would give the Board of Works employ<lb break="no"/>ment. I could not ind any thing that of<lb break="no"/>ficer has to do for $2.000 a
year, except to <lb/>
set up an annual report. I proposed then, <lb/>
as I propose now, that the Railway should <lb/>
be connected with the Board of Works.
<lb/>
The office of Post Master
General might <lb/>
also be connected with it, for
there is no<lb break="no"/>thing incompatible in the building of <lb/>
roads and bridges with conveying the <lb/>
mails. The work
would not be too much <lb/>
in a few hours each day ; he could perform<lb/>
the business of these three departments.<lb/>
I do not see any sound economy in the<lb/>
Speech ; merely abolishing the office of<lb/>
Post Master General as being an officer<lb/>
of the Crown does not denote it. I hope<lb/>
I may be disappointed, and that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment will adopt a strict system of eco<lb break="no"/>nomy, that they will take action and fill<lb/>
up the gap between Moncton and Nova <lb/>
Scotia, and build Western Extension ;
<lb/>
this will ultimately bring about
the union <lb/>
of the Maritme Provinces ; if they
take <lb/>
immediate action in the matter they will <lb/>
have my warm support. Another branch <lb/>
if the public service with which
we
might <lb/>
dispense, is the School inspection.
An <lb/>
inspector travelling through the country <lb/>
is no improvement to education ; it is only <lb/>
a waste of the public money. I trust that <lb/>
will occupy the attention of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and they will alter the School sys<lb break="no"/>tem so far as inspection is concerned. <lb/>
There is an increased expenditure to<lb break="no"/>wards the militia contemplated. I hope <lb/>
the Government will pause before they <lb/>
increase the expenditure in that direc<lb break="no"/>tion. They had better wait and
see
what <lb/>
will be the result of the termination of <lb/>
the war in the United States ; whether <lb/>
they intend to keep up a standing army<lb/>
or not. I believe that as soon as this war<lb/>
is over they will disband a large portion <lb/>
their army ; they can throw off war <lb/>
there as easy as they can throw of the <lb/>
habiliments of war. If that will be the <lb/>
policy of our neighbours why should we <lb/>
keep ourselves in constant dread for fear <lb/>
of an invasion from that country ? If they <lb/>
have no standing army in that country, <lb/>
and any difficulty took place,
we would <lb/>
have timely notice, and could then pre<lb break="no"/>pare and drill the militia to defend our <lb/>
country, instead of wasting the time and <lb/>
labor of the country ascertaining who are <lb/>
the best marksmen ; we had better spend <lb/>
our money on the roads of the
country, <lb/>
and the increase of our population. by this <lb/>
means increasing our means of
defence. <lb/>
We must not allow the time of this coun<lb break="no"/>try to be wasted which is important to its <lb/>
growth, as it has been heretofore. I hoped <lb/>
the hon. mover of the address would have <lb/>
given some explanation in regard to Pub<lb break="no"/>lic Works, Retrenchment and Coloniza<lb break="no"/>tion, but not hearing any thing from him<lb/>
or from the Government in reference to<lb/>
this matter I have attempted to express<lb/>
my views of what should be the policy of<lb/>
the Government. In reference to that<lb/>
part of the Speech concerning the con<lb break="no"/>ference at Quebec, I regret it
will
not <lb/>
be in the power of the Government to lay
<lb/>
before the House full minutes of
that se<lb break="no"/>cret conference, for it is of vast interest <lb/>
to the people of this Province that
they <lb/>
should have full minutes, memoranda, <lb/>
and the different divisions of that Con<lb break="no"/>ference regulating the
destinies of these
          
            <cb/> 


British Colonies. If we could get full in<lb break="no"/>formation, I think it would meet our fur<lb break="no"/>ther condemnation. So far as putting my<lb/>
vote upon the Confederation of the Bri<lb break="no"/>tish North American Provinces as pro<lb break="no"/>pounded in that scheme, I will give it my <lb/>
determined opposition. The
constituency <lb/>
of this country have condemned
that <lb/>
scheme, and I do not suppose this House <lb/>
will take any steps in regard to it ; if it <lb/>
does it will meet with
condemnation ; out <lb/>
side of that I hoped they would
have pro<lb break="no"/>pounded the policy I have suggested. I<lb/>
have suggested it in a friendly manner I <lb/>
do not stand here as the representative
of <lb/>
any man, or set of men, but as the repre<lb break="no"/>sentative of the people ; I will support <lb/>
measures and not men ; I wish to support <lb/>
no captious opposition, but to give the <lb/>
Government a fair trial. and if they do <lb/>
well they shall receive my
support. <lb/>
            </p>


            <p>Mr. OTTY.—I am surprised at the<lb/>
course the hon. gentleman (Mr. Gilbert)<lb/>
has taken. When the order of the House<lb/>
was to take up this address, it was to be<lb/>
taken up paragraph by paragraph. Four<lb/>
paragraphs have been passed, and then<lb/>
Mr. Gilbert gets up and opposes the whole<lb/>
speech in toto. I think the proper course<lb/>
would have been to have moved an<lb/>
amendment to any paragraph with which<lb/>
he could coincide. I may be wrong<lb/>
in my views, for I am a novice in these<lb/>
matters, and expect to learn a great deal.<lb/>
Mr. Gilber has been very discoursive,<lb/>
and has touched upon a great many sub<lb break="no"/>jects. I do not think every thing a Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment intend to do is foreshadowed in<lb/>
the speech ; if it was so, the speech would<lb/>
be long enough to-day, and to-morrow<lb/>
also. I cannot understand the position<lb/>
Mr. Gilbert intends to hold. If he comes<lb/>
here as the leader of the Opposition it<lb/>
will surprise me, for I understood he was<lb/>
elected as an anti-Confederate, and was<lb/>
in favor of the Government. All these<lb/>
things are calculated to impress me with<lb/>
astonishment. He has gone into West<lb break="no"/>ern Extension, and finds nothing to pre<lb break="no"/>vent the Government from legislating on<lb/>
the subject. Has he read the facility<lb/>
bills, giving power to companies to build<lb/>
Western Extension? Under one of those<lb/>
Acts money has been expended, the line<lb/>
has been surveyed, and stock taken up.<lb/>
Attempts are now being made to secure<lb/>
the balance of the money in England. If<lb/>
any Government allows a body of men to<lb/>
undertake a great work of that kind, and<lb/>
then pass new Acts upon the subjects,<lb/>
there would be an end of all confidence<lb/>
in the Government of the country. I<lb/>
consider this a very proper expression in<lb/>
the speech, " But any immediate steps<lb/>
in this direction appear to be precluded<lb/>
by existing legislation." The members<lb/>
of the Government are present, and can<lb/>
defend the wording of the speech better<lb/>
than I can ; but being the mover of the<lb/>
speech I felt called upon to reply.</p>

            <p>Hon. A. J. SMITH.—I though this<lb/>
Speech would have passed without oppo<lb break="no"/>sition. The Government do not intend<lb/>
to take up very many subjects, which<lb/>
will involve much time in their consid<lb break="no"/>eration. It is the desire of the members<lb/>
of the House to get home as soon as pos<lb break="no"/>sible at this season of the year. We<lb/>
wish to take up only those subjects which<lb/>
the necessities of the country require,<lb/>
and we expect to introduce such measures<lb/>
as will commend themselves to your<lb/>
judgment. In regard to them, every man<lb/>
has a right to act as his sense of duty<lb/>
prescribes, and the Government do not<lb/>
ask for any favor more than their acts<lb/>
deserve. I did regret to listen to the<lb/>
speech of my hon. colleague, we having<lb/>
          

            <cb/>

in the late Government fought side by <lb/>
side, and I did not think his first act
and<lb/>
vote would be in opposition to this Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. He asks why we did not sub<lb break="no"/>mit some great scheme of colonization <lb/>
and retrenchment. Has he read that part <lb/>
of the Speech wherein it is stated that<lb/>
the " Estimates of the current year will <lb/>
also be submitted to you." They
have<lb/>
been framed with as close a regard to<lb/>
economy as is consistent with a due pro<lb break="no"/>vision for the requirements of
the public <lb/>
services. (Mr. Gilbert—" I
had reference <lb/>
to the reduction of salaries.")
The Speech <lb/>
is no place to refer to the
reduction of <lb/>
salaries ; and I am satisfied the people of <lb/>
the country will give the
Government a <lb/>
fair trial, which is more than
Mr. Gilbert <lb/>
seems willing to do, for he has unequivo<lb break="no"/>cally shown himself to be in distinct op<lb break="no"/>position. He has shown a disposition<lb/>
not to give fair play. He has brought<lb/>
forward schemes which his own good<lb/>
sense will tell him it is impossible to carry<lb/>
out, and he opposes the Government be<lb break="no"/>cause those schemes are not in the<lb/>
Speech. If we must politically differ—<lb/>
though I regret it, and am prepared for<lb/>
all objections— we may continue on terms<lb/>
of friendship if he desires it ; but I say<lb/>
to him, that I think his constituents will<lb/>
not be satisfied with the course which he<lb/>
has taken in opposing the Government <lb/>
that has been in power for so short a <lb/>
time. Is my hon. colleague prepared
to <lb/>
state—knowing the facts as he does— <lb/>
that there are no existing laws which will <lb/>
preclude immediate action for the com<lb break="no"/>pletion and extension of the European and <lb/>
North American Railway. Has he ex<lb break="no"/>amined the laws? I think he is aware of
<lb/>The 
fact that Mr. Livesey his made a<lb/>proposition for the construction of the<lb/>
connection between Nova Scotia and<lb/>
Moncton. That proposition was accept<lb break="no"/>ed by the late Government, and is now,<lb/>
on the Executive books of the country.<lb/>
(Mr. Gilbert—I was not aware of it) The<lb/>
facility bill of last year promises and<lb/>
pledges the public faith of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, that any company which will form<lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">bona fide</hi> for the purpose of building those<lb/>
lines of Railroad, shall be entitled to an<lb/>
Act of Incorporation, and it will be our<lb/>
duty to carry out any work our prede<lb break="no"/>cessors have done, therefore we find it<lb/>
utterly impossible to take any immediate<lb/>
action for the accomplishment of this<lb/>
work. I regard to other matters, our<lb/>
time has been limited. We were sworn<lb/>
in on the first day of April and had three<lb/>
elections to run,—that of the Provincial<lb/>
Secretary was held as late as the 20th<lb/>
April ; since then we have done all we<lb/>
could to press on the business, but we<lb/>
find it utterly impossible for us to con<lb break="no"/>sider everything requiring to be done in<lb/>
so short a space of time. In regard to<lb/>
some Branch Railroads, I look upon the<lb/>
legislation of the last year as utterly worth<lb break="no"/>less, brought in at that time simply for<lb/>
the purpose of aiding the Government<lb/>
through the Session. We find efforts<lb/>
have been made for the construction of <lb/>
Western Extension, but up to this time<lb/>
have not been successful. However, a<lb/>
company has been organized, and an Act<lb/>
of Incorporation prepared, and that com<lb break="no"/>pany have rights under the law, therefore<lb/>
               <lb/>

we cannot undertake the
construction of <lb/>
that work as a Government measure.
<lb/>The pledged faith of the
country has <lb/>
been given to Mr. Livesey and Mr.
<lb/>
Parks. The Corporation of St. John have<lb/>agreed to take stock to the
extent of <lb/>
$400 000. We are no justified in ignor<lb break="no"/>ing the existence of the company—violat<lb break="no"/>ing the public faith and honor
of the 

            <pb n="8" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_008.jpg"/>
       <fw type="num">8</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>
 country.
 It is
the
policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, if there are no difficulties in the<lb/>
way in the finances of the country per<lb break="no"/>mit, to prosecute this work. Some charge<lb/>
us with being cautious and
non-progres<lb break="no"/>sive. It is a characteristic of
my nature<lb/>
to be cautious, and I think the same rules<lb/>
which we apply to our private affairs will<lb/>
apply as well to Government transactions.<lb/>
I have been fearful of rushing headlong<lb/>
in debt. The interest of every debt con<lb break="no"/>tracted in this country must be met by<lb/>
the people. I believe the people think<lb/>
Western Extension and the connection<lb/>
with Nova Scotia to be necessary ; there<lb break="no"/>fore I say the Government is prepared to<lb/>
proceed with those lines as soon as pos<lb break="no"/>sible ; but I say, and I think the House<lb/>
will agree with me, that existing laws<lb/>
preclude immediate action for the accom<lb break="no"/>plishment of this work. <lb/>
            </p>
  
            <p> Mr.
CORAM.—The City of St. John <lb/>
have not pledged themselves to take <lb/>
stock to the amount of $400,000.
<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Hon. Mr. SMITH.— lt is under the con<lb break="no"/>sideration of the Corporation,
therefore it <lb/>
is the same thing as if it had
been done ;<lb/>
they have a right to do it. <lb/>
            </p>
 
            <p> Mr. WETMORE—I should like to be <lb/>
set right. My impression was,
that this <lb/>
resolution had actually passed, and I <lb/>
think I nm correct. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Hon. Mr. ANGLIN.—the matter was re<lb break="no"/>ferred to a Committee to prepare
a Bill <lb/>
authorizing them to take that amount of <lb/>
stock. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Mr. CORAM.—The Committee never <lb/>
reported.  <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Hon. Mr.
SMITH.—If the Council Board <lb/>
affirmed the proposition, and appointed a <lb/>
committee to prepare a Bill, it
is not ma<lb break="no"/>terial whether the Bill is under consider<lb break="no"/>ation, or has actually passed. We would <lb/>
prefer that companies should build our <lb/>
roads, and if they go on, the Government <lb/>
is disposed to give them every facility.
<lb/>
With regard to Schools, I agree
with my <lb/>
hon. colleague, in thinking that
the pre<lb break="no"/>sents system of inspection of Schools is <lb/>
entirely useless, giving a great
amount of <lb/>
dissatisfaction throughout the
country ; <lb/>
but we feel we have no time to bring be<lb break="no"/>fore the House this Session, one of the<lb/>
most difficult subjects with which any<lb/>
Government has to do. My hon. colleague<lb/>
says he does not like the paragraph rela<lb break="no"/>ting to the Militia. On this
subject, we <lb/>
have agreed heretofore. I have not alto<lb break="no"/>gether made up my mind upon that ques<lb break="no"/>tion, but I think from the views which I <lb/>
have expressed before the country, that <lb/>
my constituents will be satisfied that no <lb/>
larger amount will be given for that pur<lb break="no"/>pose than will be necessary under all
the <lb/>
circumstances. In Nova Scotia
they have <lb/>
given $8l,000. It is expected by the <lb/>
British Government that we should
do <lb/>
something for Militia defence. If a few <lb/>
thousand pounds will satisfy the
British <lb/>
Government that we feel our responsibili<lb break="no"/>ty and try to do what we can to prepare
<lb/>
our country to defend the honor of the <lb/>
Empire, we should cheerfully give it. But <lb/>
I, as a member of the Government,
will <lb/>
not give my sanction to devote a larger <lb/>
sum of money for that purpose than is<lb/>
absolutely required. I fee satisfied, that<lb/>
when the correspondence with the Impe<lb break="no"/>rial Government upon this question is laid<lb/>
before you, the amount we may recom<lb break="no"/>mend will give satisfaction to the House,<lb/>
as I am confident it will throughout the<lb/>
country.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p> Mr. GILBERT.—The opposition I made<lb/>
should not have taken my hon. colleague<lb/>
by surprise. After hearing the result of<lb/>
the different elections throughout the<lb/>
Province, it was felt to be inevitable that<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
          

we must have a new Government. I<lb/>
then stated distinctly what my views<lb/>
would be in regard to the policy of the in<lb break="no"/>coming Government. I stated some of<lb/>
the principles which I have laid down to<lb break="no"/>day. I announced to the constituency of<lb/>
Westmorland, in his hearing, what were<lb/>
my views. If, as appears from the
speech <lb/>
of my hon. colleague, they have
not had <lb/>
time to foreshadow their policy, I am pre<lb break="no"/>pared to give them I fair, honest support <lb/>
upon their measures and acts,
aided by <lb/>
my best
judgment.</p>

<p>
Mr. MCMILLAN stated that
according <lb/>
to the way he understood the
fifth section <lb/>
of the Address, the only difficulty
in the <lb/>
way for the immediate construction of the <lb/>
work, for the completion of the
European <lb/>
and North American Railway, was
the ex<lb break="no"/>isting laws ; he denied that there was any <lb/>
such laws in existence ; he
stated
that Mr. <lb/>
Livesey had not fulfilled the requirements <lb/>
of that act, consequently was not entitled
<lb/>
to its privileges ; therefore, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment were free to build that
portion of <lb/>
the work, and had pledged themselves to <lb/>
do so immediately, but he believed that <lb/>
the finances of the country did not justify <lb/>
them in giving such a pledge ; he would <lb/>
declare his opposition to the completion <lb/>
of this railroad as a Government work. <lb/>
His hon. friend, Mr. Smith, had opposed<lb/>
the Government because they pledged the<lb/>
Province
for £20,000 I year, to construct <lb/>
the Intercolonial railroad, and now he, as <lb/>
a leader of the Government, according to <lb/>
his own announcement, would pledge the <lb/>
Province to the extent of £97,000 annu<lb break="no"/>ally, on the lines of road authorised to be <lb/>
constructed by the legislation of
last year. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Hon. Mr. HATHEWAY.—The
position <lb/>
which I occupy towards my hon friend is
<lb/>
different from what it was in the late <lb/>
House. We have been returned,
opposed <lb/>
to each other, on this great Confederation
<lb/>
Scheme. If he had been a colleague of <lb/>
mine, and the constituents of my County <lb/>
had approved of the course which he had
<lb/>
taken, my seat would have been vacated <lb/>
in twenty-four hours. He states that <lb/>
there is no law in existence to prevent
us <lb/>
from going
on and connecting Moncton <lb/>
with the Nova Scotia boundary. Why, <lb/>
Mr. Livesey is even now in Halifax en<lb break="no"/>tering into engagements for the
building <lb/>
of this road, upon the faith of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of New Brunswick. I would
<lb/>
like my hon. friend, to read the speech of <lb/>
the late Provincial Secretary, as reported <lb/>
and delivered in Carleton. wherein he is <lb/>
reported to have said: " That he was <lb/>
willing to guarantee the interest upon the <lb/>
whole money required in the construction <lb/>
of the work." That is, he was prepared <lb/>
to make Western Extension a Government <lb/>
work, besides giving the £20,000 subsidy<lb/>
for the
construction of the Intercolonial <lb/>
railway. If my hon. friend, the ex-Sur<lb break="no"/>veyor General, is opposed to Western <lb/>
Extension, why did he not tender his re<lb break="no"/>signation when a Bill for that purpose was <lb/>
brought in from St. John, and a pressure <lb/>
was brought to bear against the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to compel  them to adopt it. I would<lb/>
like to call his attention to the course<lb/>
pursued by the late Government, in refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the route
of the Intercolonial rail<lb break="no"/>road. One day they would be
telling the <lb/>
people of the North Shore the road would <lb/>
go by that route, and the next they would <lb/>
be telling the people of Sussex
by
the <lb/>
centre route, and again telling the people<lb/>
along the river St. John, that the road<lb/>
would come by this route, and this very<lb/>
city would blossom as the rose from the<lb/>
benefits accruing from this railroad. My<lb/>
hon. friend, Mr. Gilbert, would connect<lb/>
the duties of the Postmaster General with<lb/>
  

            <cb/>

 my office.
Why not impose upon me the<lb/>
duties of Attorney  General likewise ? I <lb/>
would like to know whether the office of <lb/>
Solicitor General would suit him ? The
<lb/>
Government only want a fair trail ; they<lb/>
do not wish to make use of any side is<lb break="no"/>sues ; they do not wish to tell the people<lb/>
of St. John they will build Western Ex<lb break="no"/>tension, and the people ot the North that <lb/>they will not build it. Those opposed to <lb/>
Western Extension will vote against the<lb/>
paragraph, for it is a side question. Sup<lb break="no"/>pose the paragraph is rejected, the effect <lb/>
of it will amount to nothing. I feel <lb/>
bound to defend the late Government <lb/>
from any charge brought against
them <lb/>
for their extravagance. The only act of <lb/>
that Government, for which I do not hold <lb/>
myself responsible, is their <hi rendition="simple:italic">action</hi> in Can<lb break="no"/>ada, for I recommended
the appointment <lb/>of Delegates to go there. There are other <lb/>
men in the country,
who, if they had <lb/>
adopted as independent a course a I have<lb/>
done, they might have been in the same <lb/>
proud position that I am, that is, members<lb/>
of the present Government. The people<lb/>
of the country expect us to get through<lb/>
with the business, and pass the necessary<lb/>
Bill as quickly as possible.</p>

            <p>Mr. MCMILLAN.— I deny that there<lb/>
were any pledges made that the Inter-<lb break="yes"/>
colonial railroad would go by the North<lb/>
Shore. No candidate ever stated such a<lb/>
thinkg at all. He says, if other members <lb/>
had adopted the same independent course <lb/>as he had, they might have been
in the <lb/>same proud position. Now, I differed<lb/>
from them on one point, and one only, <lb/>
that is, representation by
population, but <lb/>I considered the matter well, and believing <lb/>
that other interests would be understood , <lb/>
and to depart from that basis the difficulty<lb/>
was where to stop, outside of that, my <lb/>
voice was for it from the very
first. <lb/>
            </p>


            <p rendition="simple:centre"> AFTERNOON SESSION—2 P.M.
            </p>

            <p> Mr. MCCLELLAN.—some explanation <lb/>
should be given by the Government
in <lb/>
reference to this project concerning rail<lb break="no"/>roads. A certain section of the speech<lb/>
says : " You will do well to enquire<lb/>
whether it is possible to afford further<lb/>
facilities for the development and im<lb break="no"/>provement of the railway system, &amp;c." It <lb/>is desirable those roads should
be under<lb break="no"/>taken by companies. If there has been a <lb/>
proposition made, and accepted by the <lb/>
Government, the result of this announce<lb break="no"/>ment in the speech, will be to embarrass <lb/>
those companies.  <lb/>
            </p>



            <p> Col. BOYD.—We would like
to hear <lb/>
what the delegation appointed
for the <lb/>
purpose of considering the practicability <lb/>
of effecting a Legislative Union of the <lb/>
Maritime Provinces, have done? We have
<lb/>
got no report of their doings. The peo<lb break="no"/>ple do not care about having
their money <lb/>
squandered away, without having some<lb break="no"/>thing to show for it. Why is not this re- <lb/>
port brought before us at once ? That<lb/>
delegation was sent the 9th April last, to<lb/>
perform certain duties, which duties they <lb/>
did not
discharge. They then went to <lb/>
Canada, and allowed the Canadians to <lb/>
haul the wool over their eyes, by giving <lb/>
balls and parties, until, I believe, they got <lb/>
nearly crazy, and allowed
themselves to <lb/>be bought and sold for thirty cents a head. <lb/>
But when the question was left to the
<lb/>
people, the said, No! we don't want <lb/>
your Confederation Scheme, you only <lb/>
want to aggrandize yourselves at the ex<lb break="no"/>pense of the people of this Province. <lb/>
having told you I am opposed to this <lb/>
Scheme, I now tell you that I intend to <lb/>
vote for this address, paragraph by para<lb break="no"/>graph.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Mr. LINDSAY.—I have heard a great 

            <pb n="9" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_009.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">9</fw>

           deal about economy
; but very few, who <lb/>
have any anticipation of getting
an office, <lb/>
will go for reducing the
salaries. In re<lb break="no"/>gard to Railways, I think that if the fa<lb break="no"/>cility bill will not induce capitalists to <lb/>
embark in their construction, we should <lb/>
increase the facility and give an addition<lb break="no"/>al amount of money for that
purpose. <lb/>
The Government will tell you
that there <lb/>
is something which stands in the
way ; but <lb/>
I do not think they have taken the trouble <lb/>
to enquire whether these
companies in<lb break="no"/>tend to proceed with the work, or give up <lb/>
their rights. Their object
appears to be <lb/>
not to do anything. It is the
only true <lb/>
principle to help those who try to help <lb/>
themselves. I have heard it
stated that <lb/>
the Legislature was called for the purpose
<lb/>
of doing only such business as must be <lb/>
done, and the rest was to be postponed
<lb/>
until next winter. I say it to best to do <lb/>
the business now, for the country requires <lb/>
it. It is no saving to the country to <lb/>
postpone the business until next
winter, <lb/>
for then we would have to stay twice as <lb/>
long. If we could only stop the salaries <lb/>
of those who have got into fat offices un<lb break="no"/>til the House meets, i would have no ob<lb break="no"/>jection to it. I was elected to support <lb/>
Confederation, but that scheme is not <lb/>
likely to be adopted. Then they say <lb/>
nothing about retrenchment. Are hon. <lb/>
members to shut their months, or cry <lb/>
yea, yea, and be sent home to do the <lb/>
balance of the work next winter ? I would <lb/>
vote to do away with the office of Com<lb break="no"/>missioner of Railways. I intend to
vote <lb/>
against everything which I believe to be <lb/>
wrong. Although the present Chief
Com<lb break="no"/>missioner of the Board of Works is as <lb/>
efficient an officer as we can get, yet his <lb/>
office and the office of Solicitor General <lb/>
should he abolished and a reduction made <lb/>
in the salary of the Attorney General. <lb/>
Mr. Fisher was the only Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eral that ever visited our section of the <lb/>
country. Then there it the paragraph <lb/>
about loyalty. I hope the hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men will satisfy the Home Government <lb/>
about their loyalty. I hope we
will never <lb/>
see the day when we will be part and <lb/>
parcel of the United States, for I do not <lb/>
admire their Government. But I am con<lb break="no"/>fident we will be part of that country, <lb/>
unless the British North American
Colo<lb break="no"/>nies are united. I have no
objection to <lb/>
the hon. member for Westmorland being <lb/>
in the Government, although he may not <lb/>
be altogether consistent in the Railway <lb/>
delegation ; he left the Government be<lb break="no"/>cause they agreed to give a certain amount <lb/>
to the Intercolonial Railway, and he is <lb/>
now committed to a worse scheme, for<lb/>
which double the amount of money will<lb/>
be required. Perhaps he has thought<lb/>
better of it, and has changed his mind.<lb/>
He is economical, and agrees with me in <lb/>
many things ; but as he has got a Rail<lb break="no"/>road in his section of the country,
he <lb/>
should endeavor to open up other parts of <lb/>
the Province. All our young men are <lb/>
leaving the country for want of
employ<lb break="no"/>ment. The day will come when we will <lb/>
repent of having rejected the
Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion scheme, wherein we could
have had <lb/>
the Intercolonial Railway by paying about <lb/>
one-thirteenth of its cost. I am not <lb/>
ashamed to acknowledge that I am in <lb/>
favor of Confederation, and I
have seen <lb/>
nothing to change my views on the
ques<lb break="no"/>tion. <lb/>
            </p>
 
            <p> Mr. KERR.—I
cannot agree with that <lb/>
paragraph. Our past experience in
build<lb break="no"/>ing Railroads should be sufficient to with<lb break="no"/>hold us from building any more. The <lb/>
Railroad which we have now pays but a<lb/>
very small amount about working ex<lb break="no"/>penses. When we first entered upon the<lb/>
   
            <cb/>
          
 public work,
we used to sell our deben<lb break="no"/>tures at 7 or8 per cent above par. Now
<lb/>
they are down to 90 or 92, and it is with
<lb/>
the utmost difficulty that we can sustain <lb/>
the public institutions of the
country, and <lb/>
we have no strong reason to look
forward <lb/>
to an increased sale of our
staple article <lb/>
of ships. For the last two or three years <lb/>
our staple exports have not afforded a <lb/>
reasonable remuneration. We must all <lb/>
admit that Railroads are a great advan<lb break="no"/>tage, where they can he undertaken
and <lb/>
carried out within the means of the coun<lb break="no"/>try ; and we must also admit that our <lb/>
expenditure upon Railroads so far, has <lb/>
not caused a corresponding
benefit. It <lb/>
was stated that our lands along
the line <lb/>
would be enhanced in value to a great <lb/>
extent ; even towns were laid out and pur<lb break="no"/>chases of land made, with the idea that it <lb/>
would be largely increased in value; but <lb/>
it has all turned out adversely to what <lb/>
we anticipated, and the lands along the <lb/>
line are not worth more than
ordinary <lb/>
lands that are away from the reach of <lb/>
Railways. Several years ago we
entered <lb/>
into an arrangement with Canada and <lb/>
Nova Scotia to build the Intercolonial <lb/>
Railroad. We passed a law pledging
our <lb/>
credit for that work. That law has just <lb/>
expired. An attempt was made last year <lb/>
to repeal it. I resisted it ; because
we <lb/>
had pledged ourselves to Canada, and it <lb/>
would be wrong to do so. Last Session <lb/>
a Bill was passed to give a
bonus of <lb/>
$10,000 a mile to a number of
branch<lb break="no"/>es. Since then companies have been <lb/>
formed to build some of those branches, <lb/>
and I see no necessity for the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to interfere and undertake the <lb/>
work. I believe that if our present Rail<lb break="no"/>road had been left to the original con<lb break="no"/>tractors, it would not have entailed one- <lb break="yes"/>
third of the expense upon us that it has <lb/>
done. I believe that the line
between <lb/>
Moncton and Nova Scotia, is the only <lb/>
line that will pay the interest
on the <lb/>
money invested, and if any
company will <lb/>
undertake to build that line by receiving <lb/>
a bonus of one-fourth of its cost, they <lb/>
should have every facility to do so. I <lb/>
cannot agree to have the
Governments <lb/>
build our Railroads, and I therefore move <lb/>
the following amendment to
the fifth <lb/>
paragraph. Strike out after the first sen<lb break="no"/>tence the fourth paragraph, and insert <lb/>
the following: <lb/>
            </p>


            <p> " We trust that the liberal provision <lb/>
made by the Legislature towards
defray<lb break="no"/>ing the expense of extending and
com<lb break="no"/>pleting the European and North American<lb/>
Railway from the frontier of Nova Scotia
<lb/>
to the boundary of the United States, will <lb/>
speedily induce capitalists to undertake <lb/>
the completion of this work. The exist<lb break="no"/>ing state of the public funds,
and a due <lb/>
regard to existing liabilities, render it <lb/>
necessary to exercise great prudence in <lb/>
adding to the public burdens,
and we be<lb break="no"/>lieve that the extension of our Railway <lb/>
system can only be carried out by private <lb/>
enterprise, aided by the public revenue."
<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. CAIE.—It is not my intention to <lb/>
detain the House with any very lengthy <lb/>
remarks ; it has always been my
opinion <lb/>
that long Speeches upon every trifling <lb/>
matter which comes before the House, is <lb/>
a waste of precious time, and
consequent<lb break="no"/>ly a waste of public money ; this I shall <lb/>
endeavour to avoid, as far as possible.  I <lb/>
came here with the full intention of vot<lb break="no"/>ing with the Government. In the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment there are gentlemen from whom I<lb/>
have received many marks of
friendship ; <lb/>
gentlemen of great ability in whom I have <lb/>
great confidence, and it is
annoying to<lb/>
me to have to rise to oppose them in any<lb/>
matter, but I have been lately elected by<lb/>
    

            <cb/>
      
a County, nine-tenths of whom are op<lb break="no"/>posed to Western Extension.
It there<lb break="no"/>fore becomes my duty, painful as it is, to <lb/>
raise
my voice against any measure of this <lb/>
kind. It is my opinion that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, will but find themselves
in a posi<lb break="no"/>tion to go on with Western Extension ;
<lb/>
other roads have prior claims. It will be <lb/>
remembered that when a bill was prepar<lb break="no"/>ed providing for a road from Monc<lb break="no"/>ton to St John a bill was also prepared
<lb/>
to provide for a road up the St.
John <lb/>
river, and the sum of $50,000 or $60,<lb break="no"/>000 for opening a road along the
North <lb/>
Shore. It was found that the state of the <lb/>
finances would not permit any further <lb/>
expenditures, and that sum of money
being <lb/>
insufficient,. this road had to be aban<lb break="no"/>doned. Now if the finances of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince are in a condition to justify
the <lb/>
Government in building railroads, these <lb/>
roads have a prior claim to be commenced.
<lb/>
It will be urged by the friends of Western
<lb/>
Extension that that road will be a paying
<lb/>
road, whereas the other will not. I would <lb/>
say to those gentlemen, if they imagine
<lb/>
such to be the case, they had better
carry <lb/>
it out by companies and not as a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment measure.</p>
            <p>Dr. THOMPSON.—The way they have<lb/>
worded the Address expresses my
views <lb/>
exactly. If we build this railroad, we will <lb/>
be doing a grievous injury to those that <lb/>
come after us. We all know that our re<lb break="no"/>venue is depressed, and it will become
de<lb break="no"/>pressed more and more, if we build rail<lb break="no"/>roads as Government measures. Those <lb/>
works at home are built by companies in<lb/>
the most cautious manner ; but the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment here build them by the most ex<lb break="no"/>travagant expenditure of the public <lb/>
money. We want the money on our bye- <lb break="yes"/>
roads and on our grent roads. Some peo<lb break="no"/>ple will tell you that young men are going <lb/>
out of the country, because we did not go <lb/>
into this Confederation Scheme. I would
<lb/>
go into Confederation in five minutes if <lb/>
they would only show a reason for it.<lb/>
We have got the most noble Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion now ; we are confederated with
the <lb/>
United Kingdom of Great Britain. It is <lb/>a better confederation than they have at <lb/>
Washington. I think the Hon. member
<lb/>
had better withdraw the amendment ; I <lb/>
have the utmost confidence in the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and believe they will go the <lb/>
right way ; therefore I think the amend<lb break="no"/>ment useless.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. SMITH.—We hope the faci<lb break="no"/>lities given last year will cause
these roads <lb/>
to be built. There is an important princi<lb break="no"/>ple involved
in this amendment whether <lb/>
the hands
of the Government shall be tied<lb/>
or not. If it cannot be done through the<lb/>
instrumentality of a company, I think it <lb/>
is better it should be done as a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment work. If you cannot get a com<lb break="no"/>pany to build the road without giving <lb/>
them all it is worth ; it is better for the <lb/>
Government to build it. We will do
all <lb/>
we can ; still my conviction—my own in<lb break="no"/>dividual opinion—is, that we cannot get <lb/>
railroads built without the Government<lb/>
furnish money to build them. I think <lb/>
the House will understand this,
and not <lb/>
restrain the Government, that they
should <lb/>
not build them. <lb/>
            </p>


            <p> Mr. L. P. W. DESBRISAY.— I
regret <lb/>
that I shall vote different on
this question <lb/>
from the Hon. gentleman who has been <lb/>
returned from the same County as myself,
<lb/>
and I regret that I shall vote
almost alone <lb/>as regards the representatives from the <lb/>
North Shore. I am prepared to vote, and <lb/>
to stand by the consequences of
that vote. <lb/>
The extension of the Railway to the
Uni<lb break="no"/>ted
States ie the best thing  that can be <lb/>
done for the country, and if it cannot
be 

            <pb n="10" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_010.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">10</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>

done by private enterprise, it should be <lb/>
done by the Government. Our
staple ex<lb break="no"/>ports of ships and deals are depressed and<lb/>
likely to continue so. I am informed that <lb/>
there are ship building
companies formed <lb/>
in England, Scotland and the
Isle of <lb/>
Man, that will supply the whole world. In <lb/>
the North of Europe they only
have one- <lb break="yes"/>
third of the distance to carry their lum<lb break="no"/>ber, and they can afford to
undersell <lb/>
us in the British market. I believe <lb/>
something must he done, and I believe that <lb/>
something is, connection with the
United <lb/>
States. If I differ from men more ad<lb break="no"/>vanced in years, and with more
experi<lb break="no"/>ence I cannot help it. I believe that if <lb/>
there is any section going to be
benefit<lb break="no"/>ed by this railroad, it is the North Shore. <lb/>
I recollect moving a resolution in 1858 <lb/>
finding fault with the Government for
not <lb/>
answering a communication from Nova <lb/>
Scotia respecting the extension
of their <lb/>
lines to meet ours, they having
to build <lb/>
65 miles and we 62. I was then in favor <lb/>
of continuing our Railroad from Hali<lb break="no"/>fax to St. John ; but now I think this <lb/>
country is altered in circumstances. I<lb/>
now think it best to extend the line to <lb/>
the United States. All
our exports, with <lb/>
the exception of ship building
and the <lb/>
deal trade, lies with the United States. <lb/>
And it is the enterprise of
Americans that <lb/>
develope the resources of the country. If <lb/>
this road is built there will be
a large <lb/>
amount of trade between the two
coun<lb break="no"/>tries. Suppose there is a
steamer running <lb/>
every other day from Restigouche to
the <lb/>
Railway extending to the United States. <lb/>
Every salmon o poor man catches
there <lb/>
would be worth $2. We have got
to turn <lb/>
our attention to something else
besides <lb/>
building ships and manufacturing deals. <lb/>
I think we could have connection with <lb/>
the United States by paying very little <lb/>
more interest than we now pay ;
we are <lb/>
now paying 6 per cent, when we
should <lb/>
get it for three or four per cent.
Even if <lb/>
we have to pay six per cent, I
believe in <lb/>
four or five years it would be a
paying <lb/>
property. There is a great deal of talk <lb/>
about Confederation. It is said
we must <lb/>
go into confederation. or
annexation. It <lb/>
is a cowardly proposition to put forward <lb/>
against those who are opposed to
the <lb/>
Scheme. I am not afraid of annexation <lb/>
to the United States ; not that
I think this <lb/>
country is able to cope with the United <lb/>
States in warfare ; but I can
say we are <lb/>
able, very materially, to assist Great Bri<lb break="no"/>tain. If we should be at war, it
will be <lb/>
Great Britain's quarrel and not ours, and <lb/>
it will be time enough for us to meet it <lb/>
then.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p> Mr. LEWIS.—I
was elected to support <lb/>
Confederation, and I am free to
support <lb/>
any Government that will bring forward
<lb/>
good measures. I think the
country re<lb break="no"/>quires retrenchment, and I shall support <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> any measure
brought forward for the <lb/>
reduction of salaries, and do all
in <lb/>
my power to promote the prosperity of <lb/>
the country, and get through with
the bu<lb break="no"/>siness as quickly as possible. I believe <lb/>
Confederation would have been an ad<lb break="no"/>vantage in the country, if we only had a <lb/>
fair shake in the matter, and I do not be<lb break="no"/>lieve representation by population was
a <lb/>
fair shake. I cannot support the
build<lb break="no"/>ing of railways by Government ; for <lb/>
Railways, built as Government
measures, <lb/>
have been a curse to the
country. The <lb/>
fact is, there are so many
employees on <lb/>
that line, that it teaches us by past expe<lb break="no"/>rience not to put an thing
further of that <lb/>
kind in the hands of the Government. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr.
WILLISTON.—I feel bound to
vote <lb/>
for the amendment and to give my rea<lb break="no"/>sons for it, in as short a manner as pos<lb break="no"/>
      
            <cb/>
          
sible. In 1853 arrangements were made<lb/>
with
Peto, Betts, Brassy &amp; Co., for the<lb/>
construction of the European and North<lb/>
American Railway, for which they were<lb/>
to receive the sum of £6,500 a
mile ; <lb/>
part to be paid by the bonds of this coun<lb break="no"/>try, and part by public lands
along the <lb/>
line. This arrangement was
entered into <lb/>
in good faith with a responsible company, <lb/>
who had built a large amount of rail<lb break="no"/>ways in Europe and on this
continent. <lb/>
They came and performed a certain <lb/>
amount of work on that railway. The <lb/>
Government in 1856 entered into
an ar<lb break="no"/>rangement to purchase the work plant<lb/>
and every thing connected with it, for <lb/>
£90,000. They also passed
certain laws <lb/>
for the construction of railroads from the <lb/>
State of Maine to Shediac, from thence to <lb/>
Miramichi, and from thence to Wood<lb break="no"/>stock. According to that law it the main <lb/>
line was completed there was a
certain <lb/>
sum to be expended upon those two bran<lb break="no"/>ches. This was all done in good faith, <lb/>
and the people of the North supported the <lb/>
proposition, for the arrangement
was bene<lb break="no"/>ficial for them, and beneficial to the in<lb break="no"/>terests of the whole Province. Subse<lb break="no"/>quently the House passed a resolution <lb/>
to strike off those two branches, thereby <lb/>
the law to affect only the main line from <lb/>
Shediac to the State of Maine.
By that <lb/>
law the Government had power to build <lb/>
the road as a Government work, and by <lb/>
so doing it has cost the Province
£11,000 <lb/>
per mile, instead of £6,500 sterling, only <lb/>
a portion of which was to have come out <lb/>
of the revenue of the country. This should <lb/>
open our eyes in regard to the con<lb break="no"/>struction of railways by Government.
By <lb/>
the Speech the Government say they
<lb/>
would undertake the work if the exist<lb break="no"/>ing laws presented no obstacle, and the <lb/>
state of the finances permitted ; and  I <lb/>
have no doubt but what they would com<lb break="no"/>mence the work and carry it on, without <lb/>
squandering the money
unnecessarily, for <lb/>
I have great confidence in the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. Although I was elected to support <lb/>
Confederation,
yet I have announced my<lb/>
principles as a Conservative,
and I am <lb/>
prepared to support the present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, for I believe they are principally all <lb/>
conservatives (cries of O, no, and laugh<lb break="no"/>ter.) Two years ago we entered into an <lb/>
arrangement with Canada and Nova <lb/>
Scotia for the construction of the Inter<lb break="no"/>colonial Railway. Nova Scotia and New <lb/>
Brunswick passed the Bill for that pur<lb break="no"/>pose, but Canada rejected it.
Last
winter <lb/>
a pressure was brought against the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to induce them to repeal that <lb/>
act, so that a measure could be brought <lb/>
forward for the purpose of carrying on <lb/>
the line to the United States ; finally a <lb/>
n Bill was brought in, which was termed <lb/>
by Mr. Gilbert the Lobster Bill,
which <lb/>
provided for railway extension
all
over the <lb/>
Province. That Bill is now the law of <lb/>
the land ; that Bill gives a facility of $10,<lb break="no"/>000 a mile to any company that
would <lb/>
construct those roads. Subsequently to <lb/>
that Mr. Reynolds applied for an Act of <lb/>
Incorporation to extend the line from St. <lb/>
John westward ; that act is now
inopera<lb break="no"/>tive. So that if Mr. Parks should relin<lb break="no"/>quish his claim, there would be nothing <lb/>
to prevent the Government from
carry<lb break="no"/>ing on the work of Western Extension. <lb/>
Now I am not prepared to give them that <lb/>
power. It would be a curse to the coun<lb break="no"/>try to have it built as a government mea<lb break="no"/>sure. I would give companies every faci<lb break="no"/>lity, and grant them any amount of money ? <lb/>
the finances of the country would warrant <lb/>
me in giving, but I shall withhold my <lb/>
consent from placing the whole construc<lb break="no"/>tion of the railway in the hands of the <lb/>
           

            <cb/> 

 Government. I have seen the bad effects <lb/>
of that in the European and North Ameri<lb break="no"/>can Railway. My desire is to have the In<lb break="no"/>tercolonial Railway built,
submitting the <lb/>
route to the Imperial Government. If the
<lb/>
Government of England think fit to carry <lb/>
it through by Apohaqui, or by the valley <lb/>
of the St. John, I would submit to their <lb/>
decision, although I would hope to see it <lb/>
go by the North Shore. After that  I <lb/>
would give every facility to Western Ex<lb break="no"/>tension. It would be for the interest of <lb/>
this country to be connected
with the <lb/>
United States—connected with 30
million <lb/>
people by railroad ; but I could not, as a <lb/>
member from the North, consent
to have <lb/>
the whole of the finances of the country <lb/>
swallowed up by the Government under<lb break="no"/>taking that work as a Government mea<lb break="no"/>sure. It is my imperative duty to op<lb break="no"/>pose it. I would not trust nine angels <lb/>
around the council board to build rail<lb break="no"/>roads as Government measures. I would <lb/>
give every facility to companies,
if $10,<lb break="no"/>000 a mile is not sufficient to induce <lb/>
companies to construct the roads
of the <lb/>
Province, I would give $20,000. These<lb/>
being my views and feelings, I shall sup<lb break="no"/>port the amendment. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. HUTCHISON.—I came from<lb/>
the North Shore, and I am sure my col<lb break="no"/>leagues and I will not disagree about this
<lb/>
question, or if so it will be
only a dis<lb break="no"/>agreement in words, and not
in substance. <lb/>
I think the amendment and paragraph
are <lb/>
pretty much alike. I did not suppose there <lb/>
would be such a cavil about words. Look
<lb/>
at that paragraph ; is there any thing in it <lb/>
of which any hon. member can be
afraid. <lb/>
I am as much against the Government <lb/>
constructing public works as
any man in <lb/>
the House. Our finances are not in a <lb/>
condition to go on with these works, even <lb/>
if there were no companies in existence.
<lb/>
How can we give facilities when we have <lb/>
no money. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. CORAM.—I
was much surprised to <lb/>
see that amendment moved. There is no <lb/>
danger of the people of this country being <lb/>
driven out of the Province if the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion was carried. They should have <lb/>
brought in a resolution to go on
with the <lb/>
work immediately. They say there are <lb/>
laws in existence which prevent
them. If <lb/>
the company formed to build Western <lb/>
Extension had twelve months allowed <lb/>
them to get subscribers to take up stock,<lb/>
the Government did right to mention it <lb/>
in the speech. The twelve months now <lb/>
are almost up, and there are no signs of a <lb/>
Railroad being constructed between St. <lb/>
John and the United States. It is stated <lb/>
that there is no money paid into
the <lb/>
revenue from the Railroad ; that there <lb/>
has been an extravagant expenditure on <lb/>
the first line established in the Province. <lb/>
It need not be so now ; we have the bene<lb break="no"/>fit of past experience, and know where <lb/>
improvements can be made. If a
man <lb/>
enters a branch of business and loses his <lb/>
capital, it will caution him to be more on <lb/>
his guard. It is so with the expenditure <lb/>
on Railroads. When this line is built we <lb/>
will have the benefit of the past experi<lb break="no"/>ence of the Engineers who have worked <lb/>
on the previous road. If the road
from <lb/>
St. John cost $40,000 a mile, it
is no rea<lb break="no"/>son why the branch running to
the United <lb/>
States should cost as much, or the
branch <lb/>
running to Nova Scotia. If the company <lb/>
having a reasonable time allowed them, <lb/>
and the President of the company says, <lb/>
we are not prepared to carry out the ar<lb break="no"/>rangements, why should not the
Govern<lb break="no"/>ment take up the work and go on with <lb/>
it ? The time has come now to go ahead <lb/>
and not be pulling back. If the
Railroad <lb/>
pay but one per cent, and the branches 


            <pb n="11" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-04-29_Page_011.jpg"/>
      <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">11</fw>

     make it pay four, we should go on at 
     <lb/>once. If it does not pay but two per<lb/>cent, the wealth coming into the country<lb/>will make it up by indirect means. It<lb/>will come through the community at large,<lb/>as well as if it came directly. I must<lb/>support the resolution, because I consider<lb/>that it will forward Western Extension,<lb/>which will be a benefit to the whole com-<lb break="yes"/>unity.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Adjourned to 9 a.m. Monday 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     
     T.P.D.    
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<!-- GL, 2017-04-20, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->



           <!-- <p>
     Monday, May 1. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. BOYD moved for leave to bring in 
     <lb/>a Bill for the preservation of Deer on the <lb/>Island of Grand Manan, and also present<lb break="no"/>ed a petition from certain parties, that an<lb/>Act may pass providing for the same. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. ALLEN moved for leave to 
     <lb/>bring in a Bill to authorize the erection of<lb/>a Sorting Room near the lower bridge on<lb/>the Nashwaak.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     Mr. GILBERT moved for leave to bring          
     <lb/>in a Bill to provide for Simultaneous Elec<lb break="no"/>tions throughout the Province<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. SUTTON asked the Speaker if any                  
     <lb/>provision had been made for the services<lb/>of a Law Clerk.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     The SPEAKER had no information on the                     
     <lb/>subject.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. KERR said, he understood that a       
     <lb/>gentleman was now engaged drafting<lb/>Bills for the members of the House, and<lb/>he would like to know whether he was<lb/>engaged by the House, or by private<lb/>members.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. BOYD was in favor of the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of a Law Clerk. Although he had<lb/>personally been very successful in draw<lb break="no"/>ing up Bills, yet he believed that the ser<lb break="no"/>vices of a competent Clerk would greatly<lb/>facilitate the business of the Session. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. GILBERT never thought a Law               
     <lb/>Clerk necessary, and did not think there<lb/>had been one till the last House had cre<lb break="no"/>ated the office. The honorable members<lb/>composing the present House were pre<lb break="no"/>sumed to be wise and discreet, and he<lb/>thought quite competent to draft their<lb/>own Bills, and as he believed every unne<lb break="no"/>cessary expense should be reduced, he<lb/>would draw up a resolution that ser<lb break="no"/>vices of a Law Clerk be dispensed with.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. SUTTON thought it hardly neces<lb break="no"/>sary to bring in a motion to dispense with<lb/>the office, for, so far as this House was<lb/>concerned, no such office was in exist<lb break="no"/>ence. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. GILBERT said, it was very easy               
     <lb/>to ascertain the opinion of the House on the<lb/>question, and he would, therefore, move<lb/>that it is not desirable that the office of<lb/>Law Clerk, created by the last House, be<lb/>continued. <lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. SMITH said, it would be ab<lb break="no"/>surd to pass such a resolution, as it was<lb/>well understood that the offices created<lb/>by the last House had nothing whatever<lb/>to do with the present.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. GILBERT said if the House so un<lb break="no"/>derstood it, he would withdraw his mo<lb break="no"/>tion.<lb/>
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. BOYD then moved that a Law Clerk 
     <lb/>be employed to prepare Bills for this<lb/>House.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. CONNELL said, that in doing away   
     <lb/>with that office, the House would not be<lb/>acting right towards many of the mem<lb break="no"/>bers. Those engaged in agricultural pur<lb break="no"/>suits, and others, were not so able at legal<lb/>forms as the honorable member for West<lb break="no"/>morland. The argumentative talents, and<lb/>legal knowledge of that gentleman were<lb/>not shared by some others, and there<lb/>were members who were young in the<lb/>House who would find it difficult to draft<lb/>a Bill without the aid of a Law Clerk.<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     
     
     
     
     
     He should, therefore, vote for the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On division, the motion was negatived.   
     <lb/>The House, on motion of Mr. OTTY,<lb/>took up the order of the day, and the dis<lb break="no"/>cussion on the Address in Reply. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     FIFTH PARAGRAPH, AND MR. KERR'S       
     <lb/>AMENDMENT RESUMED.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. WETMORE.— I mentioned to the 
     <lb/>House on Saturday, that I thought there<lb/>was nothing in the existing law on the <lb/>Statute Book to prevent the Government<lb/>taking action with regard to Railway Ex<lb break="no"/>tension. On looking over the law, I can<lb break="no"/>not find anything that would directly pre<lb break="no"/>vent them. But then there is no law to<lb/>prevent murder, but simply to punish<lb/>those who commit that crime. Al<lb break="no"/>though there is nothing in the law to pre<lb break="no"/>vent the Government from carrying on<lb/>Railway extension, yet there is such a<lb/>thing as public faith, and if the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment entered into any arrangement<lb/>with parties to engage in the work, the <lb/>credit so pledged ought to be maintained.<lb/>On looking over the Facility Bill - some<lb break="no"/>times called the Lobster Bill - I find in<lb/>the fourth section, a certain bonus is given<lb/>to any company who, by conforming to<lb/>certain requirements, fulfil the terms of<lb/>the act. Under this Bill, passed by the <lb/>last House, a company was formed in St.<lb/>John, who obtained an act of Incorpora<lb break="no"/>tion, under the title of the European and<lb/>North American Railway Western Ex<lb break="no"/>tension Company. The Legislature held<lb/>out certain inducements which should ac<lb break="no"/>crue to parties complying with certain acts. <lb/>The company in St. John was formed, and<lb/>a large amount of stock secured, and be<lb break="no"/>fore Declaration day in St. John, it was<lb/>said that a gentleman - Mr. Parks - had<lb/>gone to England to get such stock taken<lb/>up there as would enable the company to <lb/>carry on the work. There is no doubt,<lb/>but that Mr. Parks has gone for that pur<lb break="no"/>pose, and the talents and energy possessed<lb/>by that gentleman leaves no room to sup<lb break="no"/>pose but that everything will be done to<lb/>accomplish the object of his mission. If<lb/>an individual makes a certain offer to ano<lb break="no"/>ther, and arranges to do certain things, if<lb/>certain acts are complied with, - if that<lb/>individual fails to fulfil the engagements<lb/>entered into, there is a Court of Chancery<lb/>through which the injured party can ob<lb break="no"/>tain redress for his grievances, but when<lb/>engagements are entered into with a<lb/>Government, and they fail to perform,<lb/>there is no redress; there is nothing but <lb/>the good faith of that Government to rely<lb/>on as a guarantee of the fulfillment of the<lb/>promises made. I feel assured that the<lb/>present Government are embarrassed in<lb/>their action by the engagements entered<lb/>into by the late Government, and that<lb/>there are certain rights existing under the<lb/>acts on the Statute Book which prevents<lb/>further legislation. I am glad that the<lb/>Government have, in as strong terms as<lb/>they could, held out to the people of the<lb/>country the promise of Western Exten<lb break="no"/>sion, as soon as circumstances will per<lb break="no"/>mit. If it was not for existing laws, and<lb/>engagements entered into under them, the<lb/>want of means to carry on the work would<lb/>not have been as great a barrier as some<lb/>seem to imagine. My only regret is, that<lb/>the Government could not proceed, but I<lb/>am satisfied they will do so as soon as<lb/>possible, and, therefore, under these cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances, shall vote that the paragraph<lb/>pass.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. CONNELL.— The subject of Rail<lb break="no"/>ways has been before this country for a<lb/>long time. In 1837 the first move was<lb/>made, and from the time the first grant<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     from the casual revenue was made down   
     <lb/>to the present, not a year has passed but<lb/>the subject has been discussed in this<lb/>House. It is much to be regretted that<lb/>the statement has been put forth here<lb/>that the legislation of the last Session is not<lb/>intended to be amended by the present<lb/>Government. I think the country looks<lb/>for this. I have always been in favor of <lb/>measure which like these tend to open<lb/>up and improve the country. True, at<lb/>the first there were great difficulties about<lb/>the St. John and Shediac Railway; but<lb/>gradually these were overcome, and now<lb/>we have that road. Still, in consequence<lb/>of having no connection at either end, it<lb/>is of little value to the country, as it in<lb break="no"/>volves a large expenditure of money<lb/>without any adequate return. It is satis<lb break="no"/>factory, however, to know that it is one<lb/>of the best constructed roads in British<lb/>North America. But it is not my pur<lb break="no"/>pose to go into the subject of that Rail<lb break="no"/>road. I believe it is necessary for the <lb/>prosperity of this country that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment take some immediate action with<lb/>regard to the extension Westward. I do<lb/>not think the statement made by them in<lb/>the paragraph under discussion is a very<lb/>correct one. I should like to ask the<lb/>Government if they have made any effort<lb/>to ascertain the nature of the difficulties<lb/>spoken of, and if they cannot be removed.<lb/>I very much doubt if any difficulties <lb/>really exist to prevent further legislation<lb/>in this matter. Will the hon. member<lb/>for St. John tell the House whether it is<lb/>the intention of the people of the County<lb/>of St. John, who have taken up stock, to<lb/>raise obstacles to the carrying out of this<lb/>work? Is not the course laid down meant<lb/>rather to assist the Government to get<lb/>rid of the responsibility resting upon<lb/>them, which, I admit, is great? I believe<lb/>the Treasury is nearly empty - then why<lb/>do they speak of the improved state of<lb/>the finances of the country? I am sur<lb break="no"/>prised that the Government should have <lb/>laid the Speech of His Excellency on the<lb/>table without propounding to the House<lb/>the policy they intend to pursue. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve it is customary for the mover of the<lb/>Address to define the policy of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and the course they intend to<lb/>pursue. I should have been pleased<lb/>to have heard the President of the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil state the policy and course of the<lb/>Government. He has not seen fit to do<lb/>so; but they come and lay the Speech<lb/>before us, and the only statement they<lb/>make in explanation of their intentions is<lb/>the introduction of a Bill for the aboli<lb break="no"/>tion of the office of the Postmaster General. <lb/>I do not now intend to speak on that sub<lb break="no"/>ject; but when it comes up I shall state<lb/>to the House the opinions I entertain as<lb/>to the importance of that office to the <lb/>commercial and financial interests of the<lb/>country. I would, however, ask if we<lb/>are to go back to the irresponsible mode<lb/>of carrying on the public business which<lb/>once existed here. If this Address pass,<lb/>the office of the Postmaster General goes<lb/>back into the hands of the parties who are<lb/>totally irresponsible to the country; and <lb/>I am prepared with facts and figures to<lb/>show that such a course would be most<lb/>destructive to the postal interests of the<lb/>Province. It is an office second to no<lb/>other. When I had the honor to hold <lb/>that office I performed the duties it in<lb break="no"/>volved, and carried into effect decisions<lb/>of the Council. I did not, however, on <lb/>every little matter consult with them, nor<lb/>should I if I held such an office again, for<lb/>I believe that it detracts from the further<lb break="no"/>ance of the interests of public business.<lb/>This is the only reform - but I call it de<lb break="no"/>
            </p>-->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>