<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-06-25"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-06-25">25 June 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="14" to="15"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-25_Page_014.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-25_Page_015.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-25_Page_014">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-25_Page_014.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-25_Page_015">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-25_Page_015.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="14" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-25_Page_014.jpg"/>
          

<fw type="num">14</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>
         
<p>
[...] action until such time as it was abso<lb break="no"/>lutely necessary to be put in force, and<lb/>that it should then come into operation<lb/>by a proclamation from the Governor in<lb/>Council. He saw no reason why this<lb/>Act should now be put in force. More<lb break="no"/>over, it provides that the Governor in<lb/>Council may suspend the operation of the<lb/>Act as often as may be deemed neces<lb break="no"/>sary whilst the Act continues. This was<lb/>quite superfluous, for of course the Act<lb/>could not be suspended after it had expi<lb break="no"/>red. When a similar Act was passed in<lb/>Canada, they were in an actual state of<lb/>invasion. Here we are laboring under<lb/>no such difficulty, and he did not think it<lb/>right that the liberty of the subject should<lb/>be endangered by the passage of such an<lb/>Act at this time. He should not move<lb/>any amendment, but should confine him<lb break="no"/>self to entering his protest against the<lb/>principle of the Bill, without there were<lb/>some tangible reason assigned for its pas<lb break="no"/>sage. The late Government had made<lb/>every provision to meet the danger by<lb/>which we had been threatened during the<lb/>last Session, and now we were in no im<lb break="no"/>mediate danger to call for the suspension<lb/>of an Act justly held dear by every Brit<lb break="no"/>ish subject.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> said the section<lb/>of the Bill objected to is a transcript of<lb/>the Canada Act, with the exception of the<lb/>time during which the Act should be in<lb/>operation. The whole matter had been<lb/>fully discussed on Saturday, and the ob<lb break="no"/>jections raised had been fully met to the<lb/>entire satisfaction of hon. members.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill then passed on a division—<lb/>Yeas 27 ; Nays 8.<lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">DISTRIBUTION OF DEBATES.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. BOTSFORD</persName> asked if the princi<lb break="no"/>ple established by the last House in the<lb/>distribution of Debates according to po<lb break="no"/>pulation would be carried out this Ses<lb break="no"/>sion ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>His Honor <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> said no<lb/>action had been taken on the subject<lb/>as yet.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Hon. Mr. McMILLAN</persName> said he<lb/>thought it would be best to go back to<lb/>the old arrangement, and give an equal<lb/>number to each member.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said his hon. friend could<lb/>not certainly object to distribution by<lb/>population, as he was so much in favor<lb/>of representation by the same rule.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Hon. Mr. CONNELL</persName> hoped the ar<lb break="no"/>rangement would be as last year, accord<lb break="no"/>ing to population. The only Counties<lb/>that suffer by numbers are Restigouche<lb/>and Sunbury.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LEWI1">Mr. LEWIS</persName> said for Albert it made<lb/>little difference which plan was adopted,<lb/>but last year the members for St. John,<lb/>feeling the force of the statements made<lb/>that the people there had the benefit of<lb/>the morning papers, very kindly divided<lb/>
           

            <cb/>
        

         

     up their surplus copies with other mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:RYAN1">Mr. RYAN</persName> said he had often brought<lb/>this matter before the house in times<lb/>past, and he was always in favor of divid<lb break="no"/>ing them according to population.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BABB1">Mr. BABBITT</persName> moved that the Debates<lb/>and Journals should be distributed ac<lb break="no"/>cording to population.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SUTT1">Mr. SUTTON</persName> moved in amendment<lb/>that the Debates and Journals be divided<lb/>equally among the members.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> was in favor of a divi<lb break="no"/>sion by population. For although he was<lb/>not a supporter of the doctrine of univer<lb break="no"/>sal suffrage, yet he thought the people all<lb/>over the Province had an equal right to<lb/>be informed with regard to the action of<lb/>this House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On division the amendment was lost,<lb/>and the original resolution was sustained<lb/>by a large majority.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">BILL RELATING TO OFFENCES.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CHAN1">Mr. CHANDLER</persName> moved the House<lb/>into Committee of the whole on a Bill re<lb break="no"/>specting offences relating to the army and<lb/>navy. Mr. Babbitt in the Chair .<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CHAN1">Mr. CHANDLER</persName> explained that this<lb/>was an addition to the law already exist<lb break="no"/>ing with regard to offences against those<lb/>enticeing soldiers or sailors to desert. In<lb/>cases of solicitation to desertion there are<lb/>two courses open to the prosecutor ; first he<lb/>can bring the matter before a jury as a mis<lb break="no"/>demeanor, or to submit the matter to two<lb/>Justices of the Peace who can punish the<lb/>offender by a fine, and if he has not the<lb/>money to meet the penalty, he is then com<lb break="no"/>mitted to the County gaol for a period of<lb/>three months. This Act is to increase<lb/>the penalty to a fine of fifty pounds, or to<lb/>imprisonment in the Provincial Peniten<lb break="no"/>tiary for six months. The sole object of<lb/>the Bill is to repress those who are al<lb break="no"/>ways willing to assist soldiers to desert.<lb/>Such a measure has been found absolute<lb break="no"/>ly necessary on the Charlotte County<lb/>border during the late trouble, and it may<lb/>also have been felt at St. John. If the<lb/>parties found guilty are put in the County<lb/>goal they lie there without any benefit to<lb/>the country.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOHN1">Mr. JOHNSON</persName> would ask his hon.<lb/>friend if he had looked into the Mutiny<lb/>Act in the preparation of his Bill. The<lb/>Act imposes a penalty, but first he must<lb/>have been indicted for a misdemeanor.<lb/>There was another point that might be<lb/>considered, namely, that when a large<lb/>penalty was inflicted, the party lay in<lb/>gaol, and the country was burdened,<lb/>whereas if the penalty was reduced from<lb/>£50 to £20, the money could be forth<lb break="no"/>coming.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> was of the same opinion<lb/>as his hon. friend from Northumberland.<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
         

     He thought if the fine was reduced the 
     <lb/>object desired would be attained, much<lb/>better than by placing it at a large sum.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Hon. Mr. CONNELL</persName> thought it might<lb/>be so worded as to be not more than<lb/>£50 nor less than £30.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On the passing of the sections, the<lb/>penalty was reduced to £20 and the time<lb/>of imprisonment to three months.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>The Bill was agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CONTINGENT REPORT. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DOW1">Mr. DOW</persName>, as chairman of the Contin<lb break="no"/>gent Committee, submitted the following<lb/>report :<lb/>
            </p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>The Committee appointed to take into<lb/>consideration the contingencies of the<lb/>House, beg to submit the following Re<lb break="no"/>port :<lb/>
            </p>


            <p>The Committee on due consideration<lb/>recommend that the sum of eight dollars<lb/>be allowed to each member of the<lb/>House to enable him to procure his ne<lb break="no"/>cessary stationery ; that no allowance<lb/>beyond that sum should be entertained.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>That the clerk shall obtain all the<lb/>stationery required for himself and as<lb break="no"/>sistants from the Board of Works. Sta<lb break="no"/>tionery obtained through any other<lb/>channel should not be entertained or<lb/>paid for, and will not be recommended<lb/>by this Committee.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Committee ask leave to make a<lb/>further report.<lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p><persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName> moved for leave to bring<lb/>in a Bill to encourage the formation of<lb/>oyster beds.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>His Honor Mr. Justice Allen attended<lb/>the House and administered the oath to<lb/>C. N. Skinner, Esq., a member for the<lb/>County of St. John.<lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">MIRAMICHI AND SHEDIAC RAILWAY<lb/>COMPANY.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILL1">Hon. Mr. WILLISTON</persName> moved the<lb/>House into Committee of the Whole on a<lb/>Bill to Incorporate the Miramichi, Richi<lb break="np"/>bucto and Shediac Railway Company.<lb/> <persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. BOTSFORD</persName> in the chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILL1">Hon. Mr. WILLISTON</persName> said this Bill<lb/>was brought in under the provisions of<lb/>an Act passed in the year 1864, which<lb/>guarantees a sum of $10,000 per mile to<lb/>any company who shall conduct a line<lb/>from Miramichi to Shediac, and other<lb/>branch lines. Most of the lines men<lb break="no"/>tioned in that Act have been located,<lb/>and the necessary Bills have been passed<lb/>by which the sum named can be secured.<lb/>This Bill is to enable the company to go<lb/>on with the work, and secure the sum<lb/>which the Facility Bill provided. And<lb/>as we are shortly to be confederated, the<lb/>Quebec Scheme having been sustained<lb/>by a large majority of the constituents<lb/>of the Province, it is necessary to se<lb break="no"/>cure this and without any delay. That<lb/>scheme provides for the amounts to be<lb/>expended on these Railways. The Bill<lb/>was a transcript of the Bill incorporat<lb break="no"/>ing the Fredericton Railway Company,<lb/>which was passed at the last session of<lb/>the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> congratulated his friend,<lb/>the Solicitor General, and the hon.<lb/>



            <pb n="15" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-25_Page_015.jpg"/>
          
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">15</fw>

        


     members on the floors of the House, on 
     <lb/>
     the policy which the Government intend 
     <lb/>
     to pursue as expounded by him. He 
     <lb/>
    was glad to know the exact position 
     <lb/>the Government now take, so frankly 
     <lb/>stated by the Hon. Solicitor General. 
     <lb/>It is now evident that whatever may be 
     <lb/>the opinions of hon.  members of the 
     <lb/>House, the scheme of Union is to be no 
     <lb/>other than the Quebec Scheme.  It was 
     <lb/>put forth to the country that there were<lb/>to be new negociations for Union, but 
     <lb/>now the policy of the Government was 
     <lb/>made known to be the Quebec Scheme 
     <lb/>without the modifications asked for. 
     <lb/>Another point for congratulation was, 
     <lb/>that the hon. member of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had left hon. members to infer 
     <lb/>that this line asked for would form part 
     <lb/>of the Inter-Colonial Road. So that 
     <lb/>after all that had been told the people 
     <lb/>on the River St. John and in other parts 
     <lb/>of the Province, that the line was to be 
     <lb/>located in their neighborhood, it was to 
     <lb/>go by the North Shore after all. He 
     <lb/>had no objection to the route now stated 
     <lb/>to be chosen. He again congratulated 
     <lb/>the hon. members in the House on the 
     <lb/>announcement which had been made so 
     <lb/>fully and frankly by the hon. member 
     <lb/>of the Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILL1">Mr. WILLISTON</persName> repudiated the idea 
     <lb/>
     of announcing the policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in what he had said, but merely 
     <lb/>
     stated that under the Quebec Scheme 
     <lb/>
     these lines were to be provided for. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOHN1">MR. JOHNSON</persName> said the question<lb/>was not one of the Union of these 
     <lb/>
     Provinces ; that would come up when 
     <lb/>
     the Resolutions were submitted. The 
     <lb/>
     object of the hon. member from West<lb break="no"/>morland was evident enough. First he<lb/>
    strove to prejudice the minds of the 
     <lb/>members on the River Saint John, and 
     <lb/>then to influence those on the North 
     <lb/>Shore. This was just what the hon. 
     <lb/>member had been striving to do for two<lb/> years past, to do on the floors of this 
     <lb/>House what he had failed to do in the 
     <lb/>Country namely, to divide the public sen<lb break="no"/>timent on the subject of Confederation 
     <lb/> The hon. member would surely remem<lb break="no"/>ber that he went home, to England and 
     <lb/>made arrangements for the construction 
     <lb/>of the line that would pass through the 
     <lb/>County of Westmorland, knowing that 
     <lb/>the Intercolonial Railroad must pass 
     <lb/>by that route wherever it would go in 
     <lb/>other sections. For himself and the 
     <lb/>constituents he represented he would 
     <lb/>say that whatever route was decided on 
     <lb/>as the cheapest and most advantageous, 
     <lb/> would not be disapproved of by the 
     <lb/>people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">MR. KERR</persName> said the Bill before the 
     <lb/>
     House was one of those provided for 
     <lb/>
     under the Facility Bill of 1864. The 
     <lb/>
     other branches had taken advantage of 
     <lb/>
     

            <cb/>
           

     the subsidy there provided, and to make 
     <lb/>
     the introduction of this Bill the point 
     <lb/>
     of attack on the subject of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, was out of place. The Act was a 
     <lb/>
     copy of  a Bill which had passed the 
     <lb/>
     last Session, incorporating the Frederic<lb break="no"/>ton Branch Railway Company, and it 
     <lb/>
     contained only such provisions as were 
     <lb/>
     calculated to secure the requisite amount 
     <lb/>
     of means to carry on the work.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said he must now go into 
     <lb/>some explanation with regard to certain<lb/>
    statements put forth for a purpose during 
     <lb/>the late elections. The Railway from 
     <lb/>Moncton to Truro was not, as the line now<lb/>contemplated on the North Shore, a merely 
     <lb/>local affair a matter of interest to 
     <lb/>the whole Province.  It was the line over 
     <lb/>which the Mails to and from England 
     <lb/>were to be carried, and affected the people 
     <lb/>of the whole country—the Governor, and 
     <lb/>the merchant alike. It was to the advan<lb break="no"/>tage of the people generally that that line 
     <lb/>should be constructed to meet the road at 
     <lb/>the Nova Scotia border. The delegation 
     <lb/>when in England met the Company who 
     <lb/>had contracted to build the road, and they 
     <lb/>required that inasmuch as the Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>Government had agreed to provide for 
     <lb/>land damages to a] much larger extent 
     <lb/>than we thought proper to go, that the 
     <lb/>Government of this country should allow 
     <lb/>for all damages over fifty pounds a mile. 
     <lb/>Mr. Allan and he consulted about the 
     <lb/>matter, and they decided that they would 
     <lb/>not be justified before the people if they 
     <lb/> returned without accomplishing their ob<lb break="no"/>ject. He hoped that the Government 
     <lb/>would not be called on for damages. It 
     <lb/>had been said that the Company who had 
     <lb/>the contract was a bogus concern ; but so 
     <lb/> far they had fulfilled all their engagements. 
     <lb/> They promised to locate the road in No<lb break="no"/>vember last, and the surveyors were there 
     <lb/>at work at the time appointed. They pro<lb break="no"/>mised to begin the work on the road in the 
     <lb/>month of June, and now they are at work 
     <lb/>and progressing favorably. Now about 
     <lb/>the  route. It had been said that he 
     <lb/>carried the route past Dorchester Corner, 
     <lb/>and by his own door, to meet his own ends 
     <lb/>and enhance the value of his property. 
     <lb/>But he had much more property over on 
     <lb/>the other line which would have struck at 
     <lb/>Shediac, and if he had been actuated by 
     <lb/>any selfish motives he would have carried 
     <lb/>it by the head of Sackville and so on to 
     <lb/>Shediac. But the route now chosen was 
     <lb/>the shortest. It ran within a few miles of 
     <lb/>the County of Albert, giving an advantage 
     <lb/>to the people of that County, they could not 
     <lb/>otherwise have obtained. It also was in 
     <lb/>the locality of the stone quarries, and the 
     <lb/>new shale works about to be erected. The 
     <lb/>interests involved were not local but of a 
     <lb/>most general nature, and in these respects 
     <lb/>differ from the lines running from St 
     <lb/>Stephen, Woodstock and other places. </p>


<p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> thought the action of 


            <cb/>
  

     the hon. member for Westmorland with 
     <lb/>
     regard to the Dorchester line was not 
     <lb/>
     quite generous to the other sections of the 
     <lb/>
     country to allow for land damages on that 
     <lb/>
     line. He thought that if they had wanted 
     <lb/>
     to meet such demands the people most in<lb break="no"/>terested should have put their hands in 
     <lb/>
     their pockets. Carleton County not only 
     <lb/>
     gave her share toward the construction of 
     <lb/>
     the European and North American Rail<lb break="no"/>way, but also taxed themselves to build 
     <lb/>their own line, and if land damages were  
     <lb/>to be anywhere, it should have been there.  
     <lb/>With regard to the subject of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion  he need say nothing, as it would come 
     <lb/>up to-morrow.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:STEV1">MR. STEVENS</persName> said the Bill before 
     <lb/>
     them was to incorporate a Railway Com<lb break="no"/>pany, and not on a Union of the Colo<lb break="no"/>nies, and he thought they were wander<lb break="no"/>ing far from the subject when they en<lb break="no"/>tered into a discussion on that subject. 
     <lb/>
     He had no objection to hear the objec<lb break="no"/>tions of the hon. ex- Attorney General, but 
     <lb/>
     they should now confine themselves to 
     <lb/>
     the subject before the Chair. The Bill 
     <lb/>
     asks only for that which they have a 
     <lb/>
     right to demand, which is to be incorpo<lb break="no"/>rated into a Company to construct a line 
     <lb/>
     under the provisions of a Bill passed by 
     <lb/>
     the House in 1861, and no opposition 
     <lb/>
     should be raised to it.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Bill was agreed to with certain 
     <lb/>
     alterations.  
     <lb/>
     
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">ASSESSMENT FOR AGRICULTURAL PUR<lb break="no"/>POSES. 
     <lb/>
            </head>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DOW1">MR. DOW</persName> moved the House into Com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the Whole on a Bill to assess 
     <lb/>
     the County of York for Agricultural 
     <lb/>
     purposes, Mr. W. P. Flewwelling in the 
     <lb/>
     chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:DOW1">MR. DOW</persName> explained that this Bill 
     <lb/>
     passed through the House at the last 
     <lb/>
     Session, but not in time to go before 
     <lb/>
      the Upper Branch. The Bill is local, 
     <lb/>
     merely asking for permission to assess 
     <lb/>
     the County of York, for the purpose of 
     <lb/>
     assisting the York County Agricultural  
     <lb/>
     Society in paying off the debt due on 
     <lb/>
    the Exhibition Palace.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     The Bill was agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BECK1">MR. BECKWITH</persName> moved the House 
     <lb/>
     into a Committee of the Whole on a 
     <lb/>
     Bill to assess the City of Fredericton 
     <lb/>
     for Agricultural Purposes, Mr. J. Flew<lb break="no"/>elling in the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BECK1">MR. BECKWITH</persName> explained that this 
     <lb/>
     Bill was similar in its nature to that just 
     <lb/>
     agreed to.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">MR. SKINNER</persName> was opposed to the 
     <lb/>
     Bill, being merely of a permissive nature. 
     <lb/>
     The debts due for that building were still 
     <lb/>
     unpaid, and there should be some mea<lb break="no"/>sure introduced by which either the City 
     <lb/>
     of Fredericton or the County of York, 
     <lb/>
     or whoever is responsible, should be 
     <lb/>
     made to clear up the debts due on the 
     <lb/>
     building.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
    </div>     </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>