<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-04-05"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-04-05">5 April 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="93" to="96"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_093.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_094.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_095.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_096.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-14">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_093">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_093.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_094">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_094.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_095">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_095.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_096">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_096.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="93" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_093.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>    <fw type="num">93</fw> 


<!-- GL, 2018-03-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
   
            <!--<p>
     credit of this country is pledged, may be    
     <lb/>L500 a mile. Is that the way the busi<lb break="no"/>ness of this country is to be conducted?<lb/>By what authority does he take charge<lb/>of the revenues of this country? Sup<lb break="no"/>pose you sent home an agent and he <lb/>pledged your credit without your<lb/>authority, would you have confidence in<lb/>him? How then can you have confi<lb break="no"/>dence in a Government which has acted<lb/>in the same way. There is another mat<lb break="no"/>ter in reference to the Governor's salary.<lb/>An outcry was raised in 1864 and a reso<lb break="no"/>lution was moved by the present Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General, fixing the Governor's sal<lb break="no"/>ary at a certain amount.  On this ques<lb break="no"/>tion he exerted all his energies to defeat<lb/>the Government. He must have cared<lb/>for his office then, for he could have had no<lb/>object in reducing the Governor's salary.<lb/>as he allows the same amount to be<lb/>drawn as heretofore.  (Mr. Smith - it is<lb/>paid back.) he should have taken a <lb/>manly position, and told the Governor<lb/>that this money should not be drawn. If<lb/>it was he would resign his situation. In<lb break="no"/>stead of this it has been a continual giv<lb break="no"/>ing in. First they swallow one thing and<lb/>then another, and the next thing they<lb/>will swallow will be confederation.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     HON. MR. SMITH made some explana<lb break="no"/>tion regarding the Governor's salary, after<lb/>which the debate was adjourned.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName> to resume at 11 o'clock  
     <lb/>tomorrow.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House was adjourned until the<lb/>usual hour.<lb/>T.P.D.<lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <head rendition="simple:right">
     THURSDAY, April 5. 
            </head>

<p> On Motion of <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>, the<lb/>House went into Committee on "A Bill<lb/>to authorize the Woodstock Branch Rail<lb break="no"/>way Company to issue Debentures."</p>

<p>This Bill produced a lengthy disucssion<lb/>when progress was reported, and the Bill<lb/>referred to a special committee.<lb/>Progress was reported on "A Bill to<lb/>amend the law relating to the Shipment<lb/>of Seamen at St. John."</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName> called the attention<lb/>of the house to a report of his speech in<lb/>the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Morning Journal</hi>, in which it was stated <lb/>that he called Mr. Cardwell "an<lb/>unprincipled scoundrel and an un<lb break="no"/>qualified liar."  He would give it an un<lb break="no"/>qualifed denial.  He had never used <lb/>such an expression, either directly or in<lb break="no"/>directly, or that could in any way be so<lb/>construed.</p>

<div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">ADJOURNED DEBATE ON THE MR. FISHER'S<lb/>AMENDMENT.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> resumed:  I regret<lb/>that I had not occupied a little more time<lb/>last evening, so that there would have<lb/>been no necessity for my making any fur<lb break="no"/>ther remarks. The debate has been pro<lb break="no"/>tracted to an alarming extent, and has<lb/>taken more time than we expected. I do<lb/>not wish to occupy more time than is ne<lb break="no"/>cessary to explain my views on this<lb/>question. When the House adjourned, I<lb/>was commenting on an important feature<lb/>in this case. It is one on which I think the<lb/>hon. gentleman who form the Government<lb/>have sacrificed the views which they en<lb break="no"/>tertained on a previous occasion. It may <lb/>be that the Lieutenant Governor has a right<lb/>to receive that amount of salary. I express<lb/>no opinion upon that point.  What was <lb/>the motive that induced the present. At<lb break="no"/>torney General to make a motion in 1864<lb/>


            <cb/>
         

     to fix the amount of the Governor's   
     <lb/>salary? Was it to create a turmoil in<lb/>the House, to turn the Government out,<lb/>and get some of his friends in? I do not<lb/>charge him with any improper motives,<lb/>for I presume he acted in a fair and legiti<lb break="no"/>mate manner, and did his duty as a mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the House of Assembly. He says<lb/>nothing but the political exigencies of the<lb/>country could induce him to take office;<lb/>therefore it must have been to set this<lb/>matter right. If His Excellency has a <lb/>right to single penny, by the same prin<lb break="no"/>ciple he may draw every fraction from<lb/>the treasury, for there is no limit. Though<lb/>the excess of salary drawn is regularly<lb/>paid back; yet it does not alter the princi<lb break="no"/>ple that it is wrong to draw it without<lb/>legal authority.  The present Attorney<lb/>General on that occasion said that the<lb/>Lieutenant Governor should receive so<lb/>much and no more, and if he drew one<lb/>single penny, from the treasury outside<lb/>and beyond the amount he was entitled<lb/>to receive, the Government of the day ought<lb/>to take the responsibility of it. I agree with<lb/>that sentiment, and I think that upon the<lb/>formation of the present Government, it<lb/>should have been made a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi><lb/>that His Excellency should not have <lb/>drawn this excess salary.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>My hon. friend (Mr.S.)  In 1864 sought<lb/>to fix the responsibility of it upon the<lb/>then existing Government.  He then<lb/>portrayed the evil of allowing money to<lb/>be drawn, without legal authority, from<lb/>the Treasury, in all its horrors. And<lb/>now, when they have the power to stop<lb/>it, they still allow the evil to exist. Is<lb/>that the way a man should act who as<lb break="no"/>sumes the leadership of the country? I<lb/>am prepared to say I have no confidence<lb/>in men who act in that way. It shows a<lb/>lack of determination, if not a lack of<lb/>principle.  My hon. friend (Mr. Smith)<lb/>says there was a solemn agreement<lb/>made between His Excellency and the<lb/>former Government that this excess of<lb/>salary should be drawn and paid back.<lb/>The Government had no power to make<lb/>agreements regarding the funds of the<lb/>country to bind us for all time to come.<lb/>Such agreements can only be made by<lb/>legislative enactment. If His Excellen<lb break="no"/>cy has a a right to draw this money, he<lb/>has a right to keep it. If arrangements <lb/>of this kind have been made by the Til<lb break="no"/>lay Government, it is no reason that the<lb/>Smith Government should follow it up.<lb/>for two wrongs do not make one right. I<lb/>think the people of the country want to<lb/>treat His Excellency with dignity and<lb/>respect, and pay him such salary as his is<lb/>entitled to without any paying back. His<lb/>Excellency may be under the impres<lb break="no"/>sion that he is giving us a bonus, and<lb/>another Governor coming here may not<lb/>have the same liberal spirit, and retain<lb/>the full amount, which has been drawn<lb/>and sanctioned by two Governments, and<lb/>we would have no remedy. My hon.<lb/>friend (Mr. Smith) talks about his pa<lb break="no"/>triotism, as though he was the only man<lb/>that had given up any thing to serve his<lb/>country. I gave up an office, because I was<lb/>induced to come here to endeavor to pre<lb break="no"/>vent the passage of the Quebec Scheme.<lb/>My hon. friend who did not want an<lb/>office, jumped into the late Attorney<lb/>General's shoes before they were hardly<lb/>vacant; he resembles one of the "No.<lb/>I thank you men." who when asked to<lb/>have a piece of cake or a glass of wine,<lb/>always said. "No, I thank you." but <lb/>they generally managed notwithstand<lb break="no"/>ing to eat and drink more than anyone<lb/>else in the company. ( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. Smith</persName> - You<lb/>wanted an office soon after you got into<lb/>the Assembly.) If I did I sought an<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
          

     office fairly, and there was the most   
     <lb/>solemn pledges and promises given me.<lb/>I hold the man that pledges his word to<lb/>another pledges his sacred honor. and if<lb/>he violates that word he is entitled to no<lb/>respect. Why were those pledges not<lb/>carried out? I am just as much entitled<lb/>to an office as my hon. friend. My<lb/>grandfather held on of the first offices<lb/>in this country, and discharged its duties<lb/>in an efficient manner. I never made a<lb/>pledge to deceive any person and I trust<lb/>my name will never be sullied by break<lb break="no"/>ing a pledge to any man.  In reference<lb/>to expiring laws, the speech of last ses<lb break="no"/>sion says:  "Your attention will be <lb/>called, with a view to their renewal, to<lb/>several enactments which owing to my<lb/>inability to call you together at an earlier<lb/>periord, have either expired or are on<lb/>the point of expiring." And the answer<lb/>says. "We will give our attention to<lb/>such enactments as have recently ex<lb break="no"/>pired or are about to expire." If the<lb/>Government thought proper to overlook<lb/>the re-enactment of such laws, they act<lb break="no"/>ed improperly and are to blame. They<lb/>tried to throw the blame upon Judge<lb/>Allan and upon the leader of the former<lb/>Governemnt. The export duty law was <lb/>known to have expired in September, and<lb/>it was the duty of the Government then<lb/>to have called the Legislature together<lb/>to re-enact that law. Another law has<lb/>expired providing for the prompt pay<lb break="no"/>ment of all demands upon the treasury,<lb/>and all money received without that is<lb/>received without the authority of law.<lb/>Unless there was a law for it, the learned<lb/>aAttorney General had no right to nego<lb break="no"/>tiate a loan of £15,000.  I think they ad<lb break="no"/>mit the error, for they have brought in<lb/>a Bill. ( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. Smith</persName> - The Bill brought<lb/>in now is included in the Treasury Note<lb/>Bill of last year.) If the Governenment<lb/>can make such arrangement as they<lb/>please, pledging the revenues of the<lb/>country without showing law for it, the<lb/>country has got into a bad position. The<lb/>Government, trying to justify the matter,<lb/>only makes it worse; upon whose <lb/>credit did they obtain money in England, <lb/>and upon whose authority? - (Mr. Smith<lb/>There was no money obtained at all, it<lb/>was simply a cash credit. In the event<lb/>of our wanting money we made an<lb/>agreement to authorize us to draw it.)<lb/>I suppose my hon. friend will tell me<lb/>whether there has been any drawn of <lb/>not. ( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. Smith</persName> - There has been £5000<lb/>drawn recently in consequence of the<lb/>Fenian excitement causing a run upon<lb/>the Savings Bank.) I am rejoiced that<lb/>at last we have got some information<lb/>He has admitted the fact that L5000 have<lb/>been drawn. By virtue of what au<lb break="no"/>thority was that money drawn? What<lb/>right had he to pledge the credit of the<lb/>Provice of L20,000. There is no law<lb/>to justify his doing it. ( <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Mr. Anglin</persName>-<lb/>There is a law authorizing the investing<lb/>in England the surplus amount in the<lb/>Savings Bank, which is held there to<lb/>meet any run upon the Bank )  Where<lb/>is the surplus money?  It is all gone.<lb/>( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. Smith</persName> - It is all right.)  It may be<lb/>all right, but it has been invested in<lb/>England. My impression is, that there<lb/>has been a wrong committed in obtain<lb break="no"/>ing this money without the sanction of<lb/>law.  If that be the case I have no dis<lb break="no"/>position to give the Government an op<lb break="no"/>portunity of interfering with the finan<lb break="no"/>ces of the country. The Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eral talks about personal attacks. I <lb/>have attacked the Government becuase<lb/>I thought they deserved it. It is well for<lb/>my hon. friend to consider, who set<lb/>the example. He as assailed the hon.<lb/>
      

            <pb n="94" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_094.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="num">94</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 
 

     mover of the Amendment, and he has 
     <lb/>
     assailed  a gentleman who is noi here to 
     <lb/>
     protect himself. I was present at a pub<lb break="no"/>lic meeting and heard this gentleman 
     <lb/>
     challenge my hon. friend to meet him 
     <lb/>
     on the public platform and discuss the 
     <lb/>
     question of Confederation ; he made a 
     <lb/>
     positive offer, distinct and emphatic, 
     <lb/>
     each, by turn, taking half an hour, on 
     <lb/>
     the following Thursday  My hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend (Mr. S.) said he  was engaged on 
     <lb/>
     Thursday. If he wanted to discuss the 
     <lb/>
     question he might have named some 
     <lb/>
     other day, instead of making that an 
     <lb/>
     excuse not to discuss the question at all. 
     <lb/>
     ( <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName> then read  the law re<lb break="no"/>garding the appointment of the Audi<lb break="no"/>tor General  and said.) Why was not 
     <lb/>
     and Auditor  General appointed? It was 
     <lb/>
    one of the most important offices in the  
     <lb/>country. It may be that the accounts 
     <lb/>are kept in a   better manner than they 
     <lb/>were, if so why do not they appoint the 
     <lb/>gentleman who    has charge of the ac<lb break="no"/>counts to the office, or are they holding 
     <lb/>it out as a bribe to somebody else? Why 
     <lb/>was it not given to Mr. Wilmot when he 
     <lb/>had the promise of it?  When promises 
     <lb/>are made in this way and not carried out, 
     <lb/>I think the gentlemen making those pro<lb break="no"/>mises are not entitled to our confidence. 
     <lb/>If a man promises to pay you a certain 
     <lb/>sum of money and he deceives you, you 
     <lb/>say he is not entitled to your confidence. 
     <lb/>The same rule  should apply to the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. I will now read a document 
     <lb/>which was presented   to the Government 
     <lb/> about the 8th of September, before the 
     <lb/>appointment of Chief Justice was made 
     <lb/>and signed long after Judge Wilmot had 
     <lb/>spoken from the Bench on the subject of 
     <lb/>confederation, 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " We,  the undersigned members of the 
     <lb/>
    General Assembly for the Province of 
     <lb/>New Brunswick, having been informed 
     <lb/>that the honorable Sir James Carter, 
     <lb/>Knight, contemplates resigning the of<lb break="no"/>fice of Chief Justice at an early period, 
     <lb/>and feeling it important the  appointment 
     <lb/>of his successor should be made in ac<lb break="no"/>cordance with the course adopted in 
     <lb/>England, beg leave to suggest, as our 
     <lb/>opinion, that the Attorney General is, 
     <lb/>by virtue of his office, entitled to claim 
     <lb/>the appointment if he thinks proper to 
     <lb/>exercise the right. But if the Attorney 
     <lb/>General thinks fit to yield in this re<lb break="no"/>spect what we consider his privilege, our 
     <lb/>opinion is the office should then be offer<lb break="no"/>ed to the respective Judges, commencing 
     <lb/>with the senior Judge by appointment, 
     <lb/>and on his refusal to accept  the  office, 
     <lb/>then to be tendered to the next senior 
     <lb/>Judge by appointment, and so on until 
     <lb/>the office is accepted We entirely  
     <lb/>disapprove of the tendering the office 
     <lb/>to any junior Judge  until the senior 
     <lb/>Judges, by appointment shall have had 
     <lb/>an opportunity of accepting  the office. 
     <lb/>10th June, A. D. 1865. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     (Signed)  
     <lb/>
            </p>

        <table>
 <row><cell>Joseph Corain,</cell><cell>G. F. Hill,</cell></row>
<row><cell>A. R. Wetmore,</cell><cell>John Lewis,</cell></row>
<row><cell>J. V. Troop,</cell><cell>Robert Young,</cell></row>
<row><cell>Geo Otty,</cell><cell>Ed. Williston,</cell></row>
<row><cell>W. B. Scovil,</cell><cell>A. R. McClelan,</cell></row>
<row><cell>John J. Fraser,</cell><cell>B. Beveridge,</cell></row>
<row><cell>W. H. Needham,</cell><cell>G. D. Baily.</cell></row>
<row><cell>E. A. Vail.</cell><cell></cell></row>
        </table>

</quote>
   
            <p>
     The Attorney General, in making his 
     <lb/>
     speech, read a letter written by Judge 
     <lb/>
     Parker, in which it was stated that his 
     <lb/>
     Honor Judge Parker would not have ac<lb break="no"/>cepted the office of Chief Justice, if he had 
     <lb/>
     not been afraid that his Honor Judge Rit<lb break="no"/>chie would not get it. I do not believe 
     <lb/>
    one word of it. If they had the power 
     <lb/>
    

            <cb/>
          

     to appoint Judge Parker, did they not 
     <lb/>
     have equal power to appoint Judge Rit<lb break="no"/>chie at that time. They had made 
     <lb/>
     pledges to give it to Judge Ritchie, and 
     <lb/>
     I can prove it. It never was the inten<lb break="no"/>tion to give it to Judge Parker, who was 
     <lb/>
     a man of high legal attainments, and 
     <lb/>
     one of the ablest lawyers in America,  
     <lb/>
     and for whom the people entertain the 
     <lb/>
     greatest respect. He was appointed in 
     <lb/>
     consequence of that document which I 
     <lb/>have read being presented to the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. ( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. Smith</persName>.—I stated 
     <lb/>that Judge Parker would  not have taken 
     <lb/>the office if he thought Judge Ritchie 
     <lb/>could have got it. We pressed the office 
     <lb/>upon Judge Parker irrespective of any 
     <lb/>such conditions, and all the members of 
     <lb/>the Government  were desirous of seeing 
     <lb/>him accept it.) If the offer had been 
     <lb/>made to Judge Parker, and he declined 
     <lb/>it, would not Judge Ritchie have got it ? 
     <lb/>This paper, signed by all the strong sup<lb break="no"/>porters of the Government would have 
     <lb/>had  no effect. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HILL1">Mr. HILL</persName>.— I was told by Mr. Wet<lb break="no"/>more in the City of St. John, that he 
     <lb/>
    wanted me, and the other members for 
     <lb/> Charlotte, to sign this paper. I told him 
     <lb/>I was unwilling to sign it, for I was op<lb break="no"/>posed to having the Attorney General ap 
     <lb/>pointed  Chief Justice. I said that it had 
     <lb/>been stated that Judge Wiimot—for whose 
     <lb/>benefit this had been signed—was not the 
     <lb/>soundest lawyer, and that he had taken a 
     <lb/>course on confedernticn which would pre<lb break="no"/>vent the present Government from giving 
     <lb/>him the appointment. He (Mr. Wet<lb break="no"/>more) said this was true, but he added, 
     <lb/>if Judge Wilmot is not appointed we will 
     <lb/>lose  the vote of every Methodist in St. 
     <lb/>John, under these circumstances, and as 
     <lb/>a favor to Mr. Wetmore, I signed this 
     <lb/>paper. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName>.—I said it would be 
     <lb/>
     an indignity to every dissenter through<lb break="no"/>out the Province, and when they get an 
     <lb/>
     opportunity they will express the same 
     <lb/>
     opinion. I do not think he signed it to 
     <lb/>
    oblige me. He signed  it after he knew 
     <lb/>that Judge  Wilmot had spoken from the 
     <lb/>Bench concerning confederation, making 
     <lb/>the following reservation : 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " We endorse the latter portion of the 
     <lb/>
     foregoing with respect to claim of senior 
     <lb/>
     Judge, but dissent from the principle that 
     <lb/>
     the Attorney General has first claim to 
     <lb/>
     any vacant Judgeship by virtue of his 
     <lb/>
     office irrespective of other qualifications." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     My hon. friend (Mr. Hill) is now pre<lb break="no"/>pared to support this Government which 
     <lb/>
     treated the opinions of its supporters 
     <lb/>
     with the most perfect contempt. ( <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Anglin</persName> —This paper was signed before 
     <lb/>
     the York election.) I think the Judge 
     <lb/>
     had a right to vote. My impression is, 
     <lb/>
     that Judge Parker has voted time after 
     <lb/>
     time at elections in St John, and has ad<lb break="no"/>dressed Grand Juries on different sub<lb break="no"/>jects, requiring laws to be enacted for a 
     <lb/>particular purpose. Dame rumor says 
     <lb/>that Judge Ritchie used to express an 
     <lb/>opinion averse to confederation, and if 
     <lb/>the matter was fully investigated, it 
     <lb/>would be found that Judge Ritchie had 
     <lb/>taken as active a part on that question as 
     <lb/>Judge Wilmot, except the remarks made 
     <lb/>before the Grand Jury. I will ask my 
     <lb/>hon. friend (Col. Boyd) if he was not 
     <lb/>asked to come up here to assist in form<lb break="no"/>ing the Government after the last elec<lb break="no"/>tion. (Col.  Boyd.—I received a let<lb break="no"/>ter from Mr. Gilmor asking me to come 
     <lb/>up to assist in forming a Government, and 
     <lb/>I told him I would.) Why was this 
     <lb/>aged gentleman asked to come up here to 
     <lb/>
 
            <cb/>
       

     assist in forming a Government when 
     <lb/>they had not the slightest idea of accept—<lb/>ing his assistance? Was not my hon.<lb/>friend (Col. Boyd) promised the office of<lb/>Sheriff? ( <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Col. Boyd</persName>.—Yes.) Was that<lb/>
    promise carried out? (Col. Boyd,—No.) 
     <lb/>The  Government have never yet made a 
     <lb/>promise which has been carried out in all 
     <lb/>its integrity. Are these the men that 
     <lb/>should have the confidence of the coun<lb break="no"/>try ? I will ask my hon. friend from the 
     <lb/>County of Kings (Mr. Otty) if he has not 
     <lb/>been promised the office of Solicitor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral ? ( <persName ref="pers:OTTY1">Mr. Otty</persName>.—No.) How was it, 
     <lb/>then, he was canvassing on the supposi<lb break="no"/>tion that he was going to get that office ? 
     <lb/>( <persName ref="pers:OTTY1">Mr. Otty</persName>,—I made no canvas.) Do I 
     <lb/>understand my learned friend to say that 
     <lb/>he did not speak to the electors of the 
     <lb/>County of Kings, and tell them that he 
     <lb/>was quite likely to run an election ? ( <persName ref="pers:OTTY1">Mr. 
     <lb/>Otty</persName>.—I deny it.) I was not present on 
     <lb/>the occasion,  and I must have been misin<lb break="no"/>formed. I am very glad to hear he did 
     <lb/>not expect it, for he would have been sure 
     <lb/>to have been disappointed. l was elect<lb break="no"/>ed to vote against Confederation, and I 
     <lb/>feel it my duty to vote against it, because 
     <lb/>elected on that ground. But in regard 
     <lb/>to my views on this matter, I will state 
     <lb/>that after giving the matter more serious 
     <lb/>consideration, my views are very materi<lb break="no"/>ally modified It is  my impression that 
     <lb/>the paragraph in the Speech concerning 
     <lb/>Confederation was put to there against 
     <lb/>the wishes of the Attorney General, but 
     <lb/>whether it was so or not, they have to 
     <lb/>take the responsibility of it. We cannot 
     <lb/>tell whether they intend to bring forward 
     <lb/>any scheme or not, for all information is 
     <lb/>witheld on that point.  Then the Address 
     <lb/>in the other branch of the Legislature re<lb break="no"/>garding Confederation had the sanction 
     <lb/>of the Government, and they have to take 
     <lb/>the responsibility of it. If they do not 
     <lb/>take the responsibility of it, they are not 
     <lb/>acting according to the principles of Re<lb break="no"/>sponsible Government. This question of 
     <lb/>Confederation has been  put into the 
     <lb/>Speech, and into the answer to the Ad<lb break="no"/>dress, and the Government submit to it 
     <lb/>sooner than resign their seats, thus acting 
     <lb/>in direct opposition to the principles of 
     <lb/>Responsible  Government. In conclusion 
     <lb/>I will call the attention of the House to 
     <lb/>an appointment to a St John Battallion 
     <lb/>of volunteers, of a gentlemen residing at 
     <lb/>Fredericton, who has been appointed Ma<lb break="no"/>jor, instant of selecting a person from that 
     <lb/>Battallion for the appointment. When 
     <lb/>the young men of this country go to the 
     <lb/>expense of furnishing accoutrements, and 
     <lb/>attend drill, if any appointments are to be 
     <lb/>made, these gentlemen ought to receive 
     <lb/>them, and the Government should take 
     <lb/>the responsibility. I will now thank the 
     <lb/>House for their attention, and close my 
     <lb/>remarks.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Mr. ANGLIN</persName>.—This debate has now 
     <lb/>been carried on for upwards of three 
     <lb/>weeks, and we are all very anxious to 
     <lb/>see it brought to a close. I would prefer 
     <lb/>not to occupy the time of this House, but 
     <lb/>I feel, under the  extraordinary circum<lb break="no"/>stances in which we are placed, that I 
     <lb/>would not be doing my duty to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of this country if I was not, on this 
     <lb/>occasion, to speak my sentiments. We 
     <lb/>find the Opposition very busy deliberating 
     <lb/>and determining where to find fault with 
     <lb/>the Address ; we find them, through their 
     <lb/>leader, giving notice of a particular 
     <lb/>amendment, and we find that when he 
     <lb/>moved that amendment. he had made con<lb break="no"/>siderable alteration in it. so that it now 
     <lb/>stands simply as a motion of want of 
     <lb/>
      

            <pb n="95" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_095.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 

<fw type="num">95</fw>

confidence. In all that Address, which,<lb/>they say, was prepared by pigmy politi<lb break="no"/>cians, the Opposition, with all their<lb/>talents, could not find one paragraph to<lb/>which they could make objection. It<lb/>stands there unobjectionable, according<lb/>to their own positive admission. I must<lb/>express my deliberate conviction, which<lb/>I believe to be the conviction of ninety-<lb break="yes"/>nine out of every one hundred people in<lb/>this Province, or in British North<lb/>America, that this debate, in what<lb break="no"/>ever light we may choose to regard<lb/>it, is a debate on the Quebec Scheme,<lb/>and nothing more or less. Many mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Opposition who have addressed<lb/>you, are still opposed to confederation.<lb/>I do not question the honesty or sincerity<lb/>of what they say, but I tell them they are<lb/>much mistaken if they imagine that there<lb/>are, in this House any but themselves of<lb/>the same opinion. I receive papers from<lb/>all parts of this Province, and the neigh<lb break="no"/>boring Provinces, and they all hold that<lb/>the Opposition are anxious for the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Scheme. It has been contended by <lb/>hon. members most anxious to upset the<lb/>Government, that this is a mere vote of<lb/>want of confidence, and they accuse them<lb/>of crimes of omission and commission.<lb/>They have acknowledged the crime of<lb/>omission, but the crimes of commission<lb/>will not amount to one serious charge,<lb/>even if you take the statements of the<lb/>hon. members themselves. We have<lb/>listened to the eloquence of my hon. col<lb break="no"/>league from St. John (Mr. Wetmore), who<lb/>has delighted the House for the last two<lb/>days with his eloquence ; but setting all<lb/>the rhetoric aside, and come to the sub<lb break="no"/>stance and what does it amount to ? He<lb/>takes extraordinary views. I will en<lb break="no"/>deavor to ascertain from his speech what<lb/>really are the charges which he brings<lb/>against the Government. He states that<lb/>in the formation of the Government they<lb/>had a great deal of trouble, and that<lb/>promises were made which were never<lb/>carried out. I have no hesitation in say<lb break="no"/>ing that great difficulty was found in<lb/>forming the Government. It is not every<lb/>day you find parties who have been op<lb break="no"/>posed to one another for years, brought<lb/>together to labor for the protection of the<lb/>country. My hon. friend (Mr. Kerr)<lb/>seemed to imagine that there was no<lb/>agreement among the members of the<lb/>Government, and that they were continu<lb break="no"/>ally quarreling with one another. He is<lb/>entirely mistaken ; from the day I joined<lb/>the Government until the day I left them,<lb/>I never heard in the Council, between the<lb/>members of the Government one harsh<lb/>word. We often differed in opinion, but<lb/>we argued the point in the most kindly<lb/>manner possible. I think my hon. friend<lb/>(Mr. W.) asked why Mr. Wilmot was not <lb/>appointed to the office of Provincial<lb/>Secretary. He declined the office not<lb/>because he was afraid to go back to the<lb/>people for re-election, but for private<lb/>reasons of his own. For my part I never<lb/>asked, nor expected to be, a member of<lb/>the Government, and when it was pro<lb break="no"/>posed that I should be a member of the<lb/>Government, I said I could, as a public<lb/>journalist, render the Government more<lb/>assistance out of the Government than I<lb/>could if I was in, and they had better<lb/>leave me out. They determined I should<lb/>become a member of the Government,<lb/>and my colleagues wanted me to take the<lb/>office of Provincial Secretary: this shows<lb/>how little they were afraid of opening a <lb/>constituency. It was said, why did they<lb/>not put Judge Allan on the Bench at once,<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
     

     and let Mr. Smith take the Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eralship. That was proposed by Mr.<lb/>Wilmot, and was one of his views in the<lb/>construction of the Government. He<lb/>(Mr. Wilmot) pressed the office of Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General upon Mr. Smith, who showed<lb/>not the slightest disposition to accept it.<lb/>He (Mr. Smith) said he wanted no office,<lb/>although every member of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment united in trying to induce him to<lb/>take it. My hon. colleague (Mr. Wet-<lb break="yes"/>more) spoke of some promise made to<lb/>him. There was some mention made of<lb/>his being made a member of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and some proposed that he should<lb/>be Solicitor General. My hon. friend<lb/>(Mr. Smith) at that time proposed that<lb/>after Mr. Allan became Judge, the office<lb/>of Attorney General should be offered to<lb/>my hon. colleague (Mr. Wetmore). I ap<lb break="no"/>peal to every member of the Government<lb/>if that was not the fact.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILM1">Mr. WILMOT</persName>.—I proposed that Mr.<lb/>Wetmore should be appointed Solicitor<lb/>General. The resignation of the Chief<lb/>Justice was then in hand. His Excellen<lb break="no"/>cy thought there was no necessity for ap<lb break="no"/>pointing Judge Allan to the office of At<lb break="no"/>torney General.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Mr. ANGLIN</persName>.—At the time the ap<lb break="no"/>pointment was made, the Chief Justice<lb/>had intimated his intention to resign, but<lb/>had not actually sent his resignation in.<lb/>I think it was after this time that His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency came down to the Council, and<lb/>read the resignation of the Chief Justice.<lb/>This resignation was not to take effect<lb/>until the September following. After<lb/>that vacancy had occurred, the Attorney<lb/>General again made the same proposal<lb/>that Mr. Wetmore should be Attorney<lb/>General. I said no : the interest of the<lb/>country requires that it shall not be. To<lb/>Mr. Wetmore personally, or as a lawyer,<lb/>I had no objections, but as a politician<lb/>and leader of the Government, I had<lb/>strong objections, for he had been but one<lb/>session in Parliament, and therefore had<lb/>not had political experience enough to be<lb/>the leader of the Government. I was one<lb/>of those who insisted that the present<lb/>Attorney General should take office. It<lb/>has been said that he was greedy for of<lb break="no"/>fice, and created the office of President of<lb/>the Council to suit himself. I proposed<lb/>that the office should be created, and it is<lb/>not considered the first office in the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil. In Canada the President of the<lb/>Council is not the Premier ; he is merely <lb/>the man who sits in the chair while the<lb/>Council is in session, and for that small<lb/>duty he receives $5000 a year. The Hon.<lb/>Attorney General refused the office of<lb/>Chief Justice, which was offered him at<lb/>the formation of the Government. The<lb/>man who has twice refused such a posi<lb break="no"/>tion is not the man to be held up before<lb/>the country as a man who seeks office,<lb/>who holds on to office, or who truckles<lb/>to the Governor, or any other man. Nei<lb break="no"/>ther the country nor the House will be<lb break="no"/>lieve it. Though my hon. colleague<lb/>(Mr. W.) and myself will vote on different<lb/>sides on this question, yet I hope we will<lb/>agree after it is over in carrying on the<lb/>business of the country. Among other<lb/>charges he brings up the question of the<lb/>Governor's salary. I hold strong grounds<lb/>on this subject myself ; but standing here<lb/>and knowing what I do, I say the present<lb/>Government are not to blame, and though<lb/>my hon. colleague appears to have a case,<lb/>in reality it is no case at all. The former<lb/>House, by rejecting the resolution of the<lb/>Attorney General, clearly, decided that<lb/>His Excellency had a right to draw this mo<lb break="no"/>
         

            <cb/>
        
ney as he does. All the warrants 
     <lb/>on the Casual and Territorial revenue<lb/>for the Civil List are not drawn<lb/>in the usual form. In the Civil List<lb/>arrangements, that was placed ab<lb break="no"/>solutely and entirely at the disposal of<lb/>the Lieut. Governor, who draws the mo<lb break="no"/>ney by his own warrant, but the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment have to take the responsibility, for<lb/>they are responsible for everything done<lb/>in this Province by the Governor or his<lb/>subordinates. Another point which my<lb/>hon. friend (Mr. W.) spoke upon was the<lb/>appointment of Judges. He went on to<lb/>state his belief in a great many things<lb/>that took place. His belief and his in<lb break="no"/>formation often led him astray, and he as<lb break="no"/>sumed things for facts which were in rea<lb break="no"/>lity not facts. I will inform the House<lb/>that I never saw that document<lb/>concerning the appointment of Judges,<lb/>which was signed by seventeen support<lb break="no"/>ers of the Government, but I heard on<lb/>board of the steamboat as I was coming<lb/>to Fredericton to attend a meeting of<lb/>Council, that there was such a document<lb/>got up by Mr. Wetmore himself.<lb/>He (Mr. W.) talks of the Government<lb/>truckling to other parties, when he was<lb/>the very man to get up that document and<lb/>get signature to it, and then send it in<lb/>to intimidate the Government. They, of<lb/>course, disregarded it. I said, as one<lb/>member of the Government, if it comes<lb/>before us, pay no attention to it whatever.<lb/>I stand here responsible for my acts, and<lb/>will do what I consider to be the best for<lb/>the interests of the country. I am pre<lb break="no"/>pared to hold myself responsible for what<lb/>I do when the House meets again. I<lb/>will allow no set of men to dictate to<lb/>me. If they think I have done wrong,<lb/>they can turn me out, and punish me so<lb/>far as they have the power, but they have<lb/>no right to express an opinion to one in<lb/>such a form as that. That document<lb/>never came before us when the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment was made. My hon. friend (Mr.<lb/>W.) says that document was presented<lb/>on the 8th of September. I believe the<lb/>Chief Justice was appointed prior to that.<lb/>( <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName>,—The paper was received<lb/>before the appointment was made.)<lb/>When His Excellency informed the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil of the resignation of Sir James Carter,<lb/>he put the question, who should be Chief<lb/>Justice, and there was but one expression<lb/>of opinion—that was, that Judge Parker<lb/>should be Chief Justice. His Excellency<lb/>undertook to offer the appointment to<lb/>Judge Parker, and I was authorized to<lb/>state it. Judge Parker at first refused to<lb/>accept the office, and there were several<lb/>telegrams passed between the Governor<lb/>and Judge Parker before the appointment<lb/>took place. Judge Parker stated distinct<lb break="no"/>ly that he could not in honor accept the<lb/>office of Chief Justice, unless it was un<lb break="no"/>derstood that, if he was not appointed,<lb/>Judge Ritchie could not get it. The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment declined to answer this, but<lb/>said, " We offer you the office ; will you<lb/>accept it ?" They declined to speak of<lb/>Judge Ritchie at all. They said to Judge<lb/>Parker, we wish you to take it, for the<lb/>interests of the Province requires it. The<lb/>answer came, that, under these circum<lb break="no"/>stances, he felt he could no longer re<lb break="no"/>fuse to take the office. This is the way<lb/>Judge Parker was appointed, and when<lb/>any hon. member says Judge Ritchie<lb/>cabaled, he must be misinformed. I think<lb/>the explanations I have given show that<lb/>there is no foundation for such a charge.<lb/>I am satisfied that the House will come to<lb/>the conclusion that if the Government had<lb/>
           

            <pb n="96" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-05_Page_096.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="num">96</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866</fw> 
  

     so much desire to give the office to Judge 
     <lb/>
     Ritchie, they would not have taken such 
     <lb/>
     pains to press it upon Judge Parker. 
     <lb/>
     After having offered it three times to 
     <lb/>
     Jukge Parker. and he refused to accept 
     <lb/>
     it, they might have said—You refuse to 
     <lb/>
     accept the office ; we will appoint the 
     <lb/>
     man we think, and you think, best to 
     <lb/>
     fill it.  
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>The House was then adjourned until 
     <lb/>10 A. M., the debate to be resumed by 
     <lb/>Mr. Anglin at 11 to-morrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">T. P. D. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2018-03-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


            <!--<p> FRIDAY, April 6. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MORNING SESSION. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The House went into committee of the 
     <lb/>
     whole on a Bill to facilitate the construc<lb break="no"/>tion of a deep sea wharf in the town of 
     <lb/>St. Andrews ; Mr. Lewis in the Chair. 
     <lb/>Agreed to.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     'The House went into committee of the 
     <lb/>
    whole on a Bill in amendment of the Act 
     <lb/> to incorporate the Digdeguash Lakes and 
     <lb/>Stream Driving Company. Mr. Bever<lb break="no"/>idge in the Chair. Agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     The House went into committee of the 
     <lb/>
     whole on a Bill to incorporate the Peo<lb break="no"/>ple's Street Railway Company in the City 
     <lb/>
     of Saint John. Mr. Lindsay in the 
     <lb/>
    Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     MR. CORAM was opposed to the Bill 
     <lb/>
     when it had been presented on a former 
     <lb/>
      occasion, because he believed the rights 
     <lb/>
     of the public were not properly guarded. 
     <lb/>
     Since that time, however, the present Bill 
     <lb/>
     had been thoroughly investigated by a 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Common Council, and 
     <lb/>
     he believed that the clause permitting the 
     <lb/>
     carrying freight on the line had been 
     <lb/>
     struck out of the present Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     MR. CUDLIP should oppose the Bill 
     <lb/>
     if the clause permitting the Company to 
     <lb/>
     carry freight were struck out. He saw no 
     <lb/>
     reason why they should be debarred this 
     <lb/>
     privilege, if they had proper depots for 
     <lb/>
     the purpose of receiving and discharg<lb break="no"/>ing . 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     HON MR. HATHEWAY had not read 
     <lb/>
     the Bill, but as one of the great benefits 
     <lb/>
     his people would receive by the passing 
     <lb/>
     of this Bill, would be that, whereas they 
     <lb/>
     now lose about ten or fifteen barrels by 
     <lb/>
     smashing from drays and jolting over 
     <lb/>
     rough roads, out of every one hundred 
     <lb/>
     sent from St. John, he should oppose the 
     <lb/>
     Bill if there was not a clause permitting 
     <lb/>
     the carriage of freight. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> was opposed to the dis<lb break="no"/>charge of freight upon the streets, as it 
     <lb/>
     would completely block the way, and stop 
     <lb/>
     all traffic. The previous Bill would have 
     <lb/>
     given to one man larger powers than had 
     <lb/>
     ever before been asked of this House. If 
     <lb/>
     proper depots were provided for the re<lb break="no"/>ception and discharge of freight, he could 
     <lb/>
     see no objection to the granting the right 
     <lb/>
     of carriage. There was no trouble about 
     <lb/>
     the means to carry on the work, for mo— 
     <lb/>
      ney would be forthcoming, as it would be 
     <lb/>
     a very paying business. It would be one 
     <lb/>
     of the greatest monopolies, and he was 
     <lb/>
     desirous to see the proper guards inserted 
     <lb/>
     to secure the rights of the people at 
     <lb/>
     large.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">MR. CONNELL</persName> thought the Bill 
     <lb/>
     should be sent to a select committee to 
     <lb/>
     report upon, so that every interest should 
     <lb/>
     be provided for. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     MR. GILBERT could not see why the 
     <lb/>
     traffic should be confined to passengers, 
     <lb/>
     to the exclusion of freight. He thought 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     this point would prove a great benefit to 
     <lb/>
     the public at large. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> had no doubt that 
     <lb/>
     the gentlemen applying for this Act 
     <lb/>
     would be very glad to be permitted to 
     <lb/>
     carry freight, but this was the first move<lb break="no"/>ment, and as the Common Council of St. 
     <lb/>
     John were opposed to the carrying of 
     <lb/>
     freight over the line, and although this 
     <lb/>
     was a step is the right direction, he 
     <lb/>
     should like to see the further power 
     <lb/>
     granted. The objections came from the 
     <lb/>
     members of the Common Council, who 
     <lb/>
     were probably influenced by the weight 
     <lb/>
     of the large number of persons who, as 
     <lb/>
     drivers of drays, now control the freight<lb break="no"/>ing of the city ; but as the Bill in its 
     <lb/>
     present form had been accepted by them, 
     <lb/>
     he thought it a should be passed by this 
     <lb/>
     House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> thought that the regula<lb break="no"/>tion of rates should be under the control 
     <lb/>
     of the Common Council, and with regard 
     <lb/>
     to the carrying of freight, the parties ap<lb break="no"/>plying would not only accept the permis<lb break="no"/>sion, but be very glad to have it granted, 
     <lb/>
     and he thought for all parties it would 
     <lb/>
     only be fair and equitable. And although 
     <lb/>
     it maybe said to interfere with the pri<lb break="no"/>vileges of the large and very respectable<lb/>body of truckmen in the city, yet there<lb/>were higher principles affecting the ques-<lb break="yes"/>of trade and commerce.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR HILL thought that the company<lb/>should not be limited to the payment of<lb/>a certain per centage, or be compelled to<lb/>fix a maximum rate of fare, and although<lb/>the hon. member from St. John (Mr.<lb/>Anglin) regarded this as a great mon<lb break="no"/>opoly, yet they had to enter into compe<lb break="no"/>tition with the natural means of transit,<lb/>and also with the omnibusses and cabs of<lb/>the city. With regard to carrying freight<lb/>in other cities, the horse railways do not<lb/>carry passengers and freight together, but<lb/>he could see not reason why they should<lb/>not carry freight after the passenger<lb/>traffic is over for the day.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. CORAM said the Committee for<lb/>the Common Council would be here on<lb/>Monday next, and he would move that<lb/>progress be reported.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. MCCLELLAN also thought that<lb/>it would be wrong to fix a maximum rate<lb/>of profit.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. MR. HATHEWAY could see no<lb/>reason why the company should be pre—<lb/>vented from running their line down upon<lb/>the South or North Market Wharves,<lb/>and giving an opportunity to the up<lb/>river people to load on their five or six<lb/>hundred barrels of flour, and run them<lb/>over for shipment ; and should oppose the<lb/>Bill if there were no clause giving the<lb/>company this permission.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. MR. SMITH differed from the<lb/>preceding member with regard to this<lb/>point, for none of the street railways he<lb/>had heard of carried freight, as it would<lb/>be a constant source of annoyance, from<lb/>their stopping every few minutes to dis<lb break="no"/>charge or take it in from the various<lb/>stores on the line.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> thought perhaps it<lb/>would be best that progress should be re<lb break="no"/>ported, and then submitted to a select<lb/>Committee. Progress reported.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Speaker in the chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> moved that this Bill<lb/>be submitted to a select Committee to re<lb break="no"/>port.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. MR. BOTSFORD thought as this<lb/>Bill was of a public character, some mem<lb break="no"/>bers outside of the City of St. John,<lb/>should be upon the Committee, so that<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     the interests of parties outside may be 
     <lb/>
     represented.    
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>This idea was supported by other mem<lb break="no"/>bers, when Messrs. Wetmore, Glazier, 
     <lb/>Hill and Connell were appointed to take 
     <lb/>the matter into consideration.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House went into Committee of the 
     <lb/> Whole on a Bill relating to the Justices 
     <lb/>of the City and County St. John ; Mr. 
     <lb/>Young in the chair.     
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> HON. MR. CUDLIP said this was a Bill 
     <lb/>emenating from the Justices of St. John 
     <lb/>themselves, and was intended to compel 
     <lb/>the attendance or those who would not 
     <lb/>attend the Sessions.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said the reason why 
     <lb/>they would not attend was because some 
     <lb/>four or five justices talked so incessantly, 
     <lb/>that they talked some others out of doors. 
     <lb/>It was true, that although there were 
     <lb/>some eighty or ninety Justices, yet the 
     <lb/>ordinary attendance was about five or 
     <lb/>six ; and with regard to the attendance of 
     <lb/>Jurors, hh thought that their non-atten- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>dance was also largely attributable to the 
     <lb/>babbling spirit which seems to be so pre<lb break="no"/>valent with certain parties at the present 
     <lb/>time. He did not see that this House 
     <lb/>should interfere in the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     HON. MR. HATHEWAY thought that 
     <lb/>
     if this Bill passed the next would be 
     <lb/>
     one to allow them to increase the size of 
     <lb/>
     the Court House, as, instead of some 
     <lb/>
     eighty or ninety, he believed there were 
     <lb/>
     some one hundred and forty Justices of 
     <lb/>
     the Peace. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     MR. WILMOT agreed with the last 
     <lb/>
     speaker, and thought that there was no 
     <lb/>
     reason why the House should interfere 
     <lb/>
     in the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     MR. CORAM explained that the Mag<lb break="no"/>istrates should be got together at least 
     <lb/>
     once a year, and perhaps it would be 
     <lb/>
     better to amend the Bill authorizing the 
     <lb/>
     calling together of all Magistrates un<lb break="no"/>der the age of fifty years to form a gen<lb break="no"/>eral Sessions. 
     <lb/>HON. MR. CUDLIP thought the idea 
     <lb/>a good one, and would therefore move 
     <lb/>that progress be reported to admit of 
     <lb/>time to take the matter into considera<lb break="no"/>tion. Progress reported. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     The House went into Committee of 
     <lb/>
     the Whole on a Bill to amend an Act 
     <lb/>
     relating to the granting of licenses to 
     <lb/>
    foreigners to transact business. Mr. 
     <lb/>Scovil in the Chair.    
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     
     MR. YOUNG explained, that at present 
     <lb/>foreigners could bring in their wares<lb/>
     and transact their business  without con<lb break="no"/>tributing tot he local taxes. He thought 
     <lb/>
     that they should be placed on, at least, 
     <lb/>
     the same footing as our own people. 
     <lb/>
     This Bill gives power to the Sessions 
     <lb/>
     and Municipalities to impose licenses 
     <lb/>
     and penalties upon foreigners doing 
     <lb/>
    business. Agreed to.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
      AFTERNOON  SESSION. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>MR. L. P. W. DESBRISAY seeing the 
     <lb/>Chief Commissioner of  the Board of 
     <lb/>Works in his place would ask if any, 
     <lb/>and what arrangement had been made 
     <lb/>by the Government with regard to put<lb break="no"/>ting a steamer upon the North Shore. 
     <lb/>The Spring was opening out now, and 
     <lb/>if anything was to be done it should be 
     <lb/>done at once.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. MR. HATHEWAY replied that 
     <lb/>no arrangement had yet been made. 
     <lb/>Mr Finlay, the agent, was here a few 
     <lb/>days ago, and they had given him ten 
     <lb/>days to go to Canada and see what ar<lb break="no"/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>