<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-04-03"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-04-03">3 April 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="99"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_085.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_086.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_087.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_088.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_089.hocr.html"/>
               </item>

            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-14">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_085">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_085.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_086">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_086.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_087">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_087.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_088">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_088.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_089">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_089.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="85" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_085.jpg"/>
            
     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  <fw type="num">85</fw> 
    


<!-- GL, 2018-03-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
           <!-- <p>
     ing the Commander-in-Chlief passed in 
     <lb/>
     1862, and endeavored to prove that the 
     <lb/>
     Governor in Council was only responsi<lb break="no"/>ble for the money which was expended 
     <lb/>
     for military purposes, an the Com- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     mander-in-Chief was alone responsible 
     <lb/>
     for any act of mis-feasance, mal-feas- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ance or the disposition of the troops ) In 
     <lb/>
     regard to Fenianism. I do not believe 
     <lb/>
     there is one native Fenian in the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince connected with any Circle or any 
     <lb/>
     Head Centre, aud I do not believe there 
     <lb/>
     everwill be one in this country. I do 
     <lb/>
     not believe it ever was the intention of 
     <lb/>
     any fillibusters in the United States to 
     <lb/>
     make raids upon any of the British 
     <lb/>
     Provinces. It is an old saying that "the 
     <lb/>
      dog that bites does not bark." Men 
     <lb/>
     don't make such boasts in order to ena<lb break="no"/>ble their opponents to be prepared. I 
     <lb/>
     do not believe that Roberts or O'Maho- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     ney ever dreamed of crossing the bor<lb break="no"/>der line of these Provinces. If they 
     <lb/>
     did, I have faith in the integrity of that 
     <lb/>
     great nation alongside of us to know 
     <lb/>
     that whatever wrong  she may have 
     <lb/>
     suffered at the hand of other nations, 
     <lb/>
     in their opinions and sympathies, she 
     <lb/>
     has too high an opinion ol her dig<lb break="no"/>nity as a nation, and of her stand<lb break="no"/>ing among the family of nations on the 
     <lb/>
     earth, to allow any fillibustering expedi<lb break="no"/>tion to cross her land to go to another 
     <lb/>
     country and raise the flag ot rebellion to 
     <lb/>
     overthrow the government of that coun<lb break="no"/>try. So long as that power stands, so long 
     <lb/>
     will she, in her own integrity and digni<lb break="no"/>ty, maintain that international law which 
     <lb/>
     is the life of the world. I do not believe 
     <lb/>
     in the doctrine of Fenianism, but I en<lb break="no"/>tertain my views in regard to the wrongs 
     <lb/>
     of Ireland. My hon. friend (Mr. Kerr) 
     <lb/>
     spoke of the Union of Scotland with Eng<lb break="no"/>land. It is a matter of history that the 
     <lb/>
     purse of Queen Anne was drained to the 
     <lb/>
     dregs to purchase the members of the 
     <lb/>
     Parliament of Scotland to sell their coun<lb break="no"/>try, and the names of the men who sold 
     <lb/>
     it are this day in eternal infamy. Scot<lb break="no"/>land at that time was crippled, for she 
     <lb/>
     had just come out of the great Darien 
     <lb/>
     expedition, and her ships and commerce 
     <lb/>
     were not protected by the British flag, 
     <lb/>
     but the moment she came into that union 
     <lb/>
     her commerce was extended and her ships 
     <lb/>
      protected by the Union Jack of old Eng<lb break="no"/>land. How was the Union with lreland 
     <lb/>
       effected ? By fraud and rapine. We are 
     <lb/>
     told this in history, and it cannot be ob<lb break="no"/>literated. Men in Ireland sold their par<lb break="no"/>liament for Lords, Earls, Dukes, and pal<lb break="no"/>try pelf. I do not say it was a natural 
     <lb/>
     consequence, but it stands as a beaccu 
     <lb/>
     light that scarely any one of them died a 
     <lb/>
     natural death. Scotland has benefitted 
     <lb/>
     by that Union, but let Scotland have what 
     <lb/>
     we now have here, a Parliament of our 
     <lb/>
     own, with an independent local self-govern- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
      ment, and you would see where she would 
     <lb/>
     be now.    
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Debate was now adjourned, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Needham to resume at 11 o'clock to-mor- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
     row, and the House was adjourned until 
     <lb/>
    10 A. M.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     T. P. D. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <head rendition="simple:right">
     TUESDAY, APRIL. 3rd. 
     <lb/>
     
            </head>

            <p>
     The House in Committee agreed to an 
     <lb/>
     Act to aid the construction of the Wood<lb break="no"/>stock Railway. After which the order 
     <lb/>
     of the day was taken up, viz :— 
     <lb/>
            </p>


            <cb/>
            
<div type="section">
<head rendition="simple:centre">
     ADJOURNED DEBATE ON MR. FISHER'S 
     <lb/>
     AMENDMENT. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName> resumed. I shall 
     <lb/>
     now quote my hon. colleague's (Mr.F:) 
     <lb/>
     Speech on a Want of Confidence mo<lb break="no"/>tion in 1854. which was published in 
     <lb/>
     what is called the " political primer," in 
     <lb/>
     which he gives his opinion of the Col<lb break="no"/>onial office, and despatches from that, 
     <lb/>
     office, I shall make very few comments. 
     <lb/>
     This speech was delivered when the 
     <lb/>
     Hon. John, A. Street was Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eral. He (Mr. F.) said, "a despatch, in his 
     <lb/>
     (the Attorney General's) estimation, was 
     <lb/>
     more of political value than the action of 
     <lb/>
     the Local Legislature," and again, " he 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. F ) would like to see an attempt 
     <lb/>
     to carry the despatch into effect ; he told 
     <lb/>
    Mr. Brown last spring, to pay no at<lb break="no"/>tention to it, and to come to the House 
     <lb/>if he wished. The Executive had al<lb break="no"/>lowed this to pass without remark or 
     <lb/>remonstrance, though it was a direct 
     <lb/>attempt to restrict them in the right to 
     <lb/>self-government." My hon. friend is 
     <lb/>not consistent here with the opinions he 
     <lb/>now expresses. He charges the seven 
     <lb/>with using strong language in their re<lb break="no"/>ply to Mr. Cardwell's despatches, and 
     <lb/>in 1854 he accuses  the Government of 
     <lb/>bowing down to the Colonial Office. 
     <lb/>Here was a despatch come out from 
     <lb/>home stating that a Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cillor could not leave unless his resigna<lb break="no"/>tion was accepted by Her Majesty, and 
     <lb/>that the Governor had no power to ac<lb break="no"/>cept it. This was not only in reference 
     <lb/>to a despatch from the Colonial Office, 
     <lb/>but it involved one of the Crown preroga<lb break="no"/>tives, which every man is supposed to 
     <lb/>submit to. But says my hon. colleague, 
     <lb/>though it be a royal prerogative, I say 
     <lb/>to you, Mr. Brown, pay no attention to 
     <lb/>the Queen's prerogative. Pay no atten<lb break="no"/>tion to the Colonial Office, but come to 
     <lb/>the House when you like. I hold he is 
     <lb/>bound in duty to his and my constitu<lb break="no"/>ents, and to the people of this Province, 
     <lb/>to show why, after having made such a 
     <lb/>treasonable expression, he now turns 
     <lb/>round and charges this Government 
     <lb/>with truckling to the Colonial Office. 
     <lb/>Then again, he says, " by allowing Sir 
     <lb/>Edmund Head to appoint Judge Cartier 
     <lb/>Chief Justice, the Council had quailed 
     <lb/>before him." It seems to he his idea 
     <lb/>that any Government in which he is not, 
     <lb/>quails before the British Government. 
     <lb/>He goes on. " They had allowed the 
     <lb/>Province to be governed by despatches, 
     <lb/>and inroad after inroad to be made upon 
     <lb/>the principles of self-government. " 
     <lb/>If these were then his views, has he 
     <lb/>abandoned Responsible Government 
     <lb/>now ? If we were to form our opinion 
     <lb/>of Responsible Government from its 
     <lb/>action in this country, and from the ac<lb break="no"/>tion of its supporters in this House, then 
     <lb/>in truth and verity is Responsible Go<lb break="no"/>vernment a humbug, while in reality it 
     <lb/>is not so. But I hold that if my hon.<lb/>colleague meant what he said on that<lb/>occasion, then his charges against this<lb/>Government, in respect to those des<lb break="no"/>patches, are utterly valuless. He con<lb break="no"/>tinues : " This discussion would put an<lb/>end to government by despatches."<lb/>Who revived the ghost and brought it<lb/>from the shades below ? My hon. friend,<lb/>he is the man who put him down, and<lb/>now he blows his trumpet and the ghost<lb/>appears. Then again he goes on : " It<lb/>would teach all future Governments to<lb/>act like men of spirit and independence<lb/>and not truckle to any Governor or<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
          

     
     Colonial Secretary." But now he says, 
     <lb/>
     how dare you do as I told  you ten years 
     <lb/>
     ago. That despatch, written by the im<lb break="no"/>mortal seven as they are called. is an 
     <lb/>
     evidence that they do not truckle to the 
     <lb/>
     Colonial Secretary. No man need be 
     <lb/>
     ashamed to sign that despatch, and the 
     <lb/>
     only regret that I have—if it is ever 
     <lb/>
     connected with the history of the coun<lb break="no"/>try as it ought to be—is, that I cannot 
     <lb/>
     constitutionally append my name to it. 
     <lb/>
     The Hon. Mr. Ritchie, who supported 
     <lb/>
     my hon. colleague in that debate, and 
     <lb/>
     assisted him to overthrow the then Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, says : " On the 28th April, 
     <lb/>
     1851. he (Mr. R.)moved the following 
     <lb/>
     resolution :—  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That while this House 
     <lb/>
     should always receive with respect, the 
     <lb/>
     
     House cannot but look on the extract of  
     <lb/>
     the despatch of Earl Grey, dated the 
     <lb/>
     25th day of November, 1850, submitted 
     <lb/>
     by His Excellency, by message of the 
     <lb/>
     13th day of February last, as a dictation 
     <lb/>
     inconsistent, not only with the interests 
     <lb/>
     of the country, but in direct opposition 
     <lb/>
     to the principles of self-government, 
     <lb/>
     heretofore conceded, and which, if suc<lb break="no"/>cessfully persisted in , makes Responsi<lb break="no"/>ble Government a mere mockery and 
     <lb/>
    delusion. "   
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Dame rumor said, that when that Go<lb break="no"/>vernment was formed my hon. colleague 
     <lb/>
     agreed with Judge Ritchie that he was 
     <lb/>
     to have the Judgeship, and my hon. col<lb break="no"/>league, the Attorney General—( <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Fisher</persName>—No such agreement) —there 
     <lb/>
     were many ways of coming to an un<lb break="no"/>derstanding and yet enabling the con<lb break="no"/>tractors to say it was not so. But, at 
     <lb/>
     all events, so the day happened Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Ritchie did get the Judgeship. My hon. 
     <lb/>
     colleague, the Attorney Generalship, 
     <lb/>
     just as Dame Rumor reported, in this 
     <lb/>
     instance, " common rumor was not a 
     <lb/>
     common liar." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I came into the House in 1851 to op<lb break="no"/>pose the then existing Government. My 
     <lb/>
     hon. colleague and Judge Wilmot were 
     <lb/>
     in the Government, and I was sent here 
     <lb/>
     by the Liberals of St. John, who believed 
     <lb/>
     in the doctrine of Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment—to oppose them because they had 
     <lb/>
     forfeited their right to be called Liberals, 
     <lb/>
     by abandoning Responsible Government, 
     <lb/>
     by shelving themselves in with parties 
     <lb/>
     who were their opponents, and having 
     <lb/>
     done so they could not say they did it 
     <lb/>
     with their eyes shut, because they knew 
     <lb/>
     that after Responsible Government was 
     <lb/>
     adopted in Nova Scotia, through the hard 
     <lb/>
     work of the Hon. Joseph Howe, they 
     <lb/>
     formed a coalaiion with the so-called 
     <lb/>
    Tory Government, and the result was 
     <lb/>that they smashed to pieces. When they 
     <lb/>attempted to do the same thing here, they 
     <lb/>must have known they would have fallen 
     <lb/>into the same dilemma. Messrs. Gray, 
     <lb/>Wilmot, Titley and myself were sent here 
     <lb/>to oppose that Government. I did it to 
     <lb/>the best of my ability. I opposed them 
     <lb/>right or wrong, and that is the way I like 
     <lb/>to see a Government opposed.I do not 
     <lb/>mean to say they should do this on ordi<lb break="no"/>nary measures, but they should oppose 
     <lb/>them on measures introduced as Govern<lb break="no"/>ment measures. lt is well known that I 
     <lb/>did it when I came to the House on that 
     <lb/>occasion, but for some reason or other we 
     <lb/>could not beat them. The next year 
     <lb/>Messrs. Wilmot and Gray joined that 
     <lb/>Government, and Messrs. Ritchie, Si<lb break="no"/>monds and They resigned, and they call<lb break="no"/>
          

            <pb n="86" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_086.jpg"/>
        
<fw type="num">86</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 


     ed upon me to do the same thing. I said, 
     <lb/>
     No! I do not see why you resigned ; why 
     <lb/>could not you hang on to the ship ; let us<lb/>act like men and fight out the matter. It<lb/>may be that they supposed they could not<lb/>do anything ; but that is not the way for <lb/>political men to act. If I was in the Op<lb break="no"/>position, and only had two men with me,<lb/>I would oppose them, and keep the snow<lb break="no"/>ball rolling, and it would gather in as it<lb/>went. I do not believe it was right for<lb/>those hon. members to resign, yet I got<lb/>all the obloquy for not resigning. When<lb/>I came to the House at the next session,<lb/>we appointed two of our party to deter<lb break="no"/>mine our platform, and when that was<lb/>drawn only two out of the seventeen Lib<lb break="no"/>erals signed it. I then said I would offer<lb/>no further factious opposition to the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. My hon. friend (Mr. Connell)<lb/>read a letter showing the necessity of<lb/>pitching into the Government. (Mr.<lb/>Needham then read a couple of letters<lb/>from his constituents, eulogizing the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, saying they had done their duty<lb/>faithfully, and continued.) I could give<lb/>you more of these, and they contain the<lb/>opinion of the men of York. My hon.<lb/>friend has made a charge against the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment in regard to the appointment of<lb/>the Judges. I believe if there are men<lb/>in this country whose names ought never<lb/>to be handled, or their actions made the<lb/>suject of debate, it is the Judges. It<lb/>has been the pride of this country, that its<lb/>Bench and Ermine have been kept spot<lb break="no"/>less. They have had men on that Bench<lb/>from its earliest history to the present<lb/>period, who by their integrity, honesty<lb/>of purpose, and knowledge of law, have<lb/>invariably covered that ermine with <lb/>glory. I never will be the man to say<lb/>or do anything to bring the Judges of<lb/>the country into disrepute. My hon.<lb/>colleague (Mr. F.) has charged the pre<lb break="no"/>sent Chief Justice with cabaling, and a<lb/>more gross charge cannot be made<lb/>against any Judge. I do not know a<lb/>solitary instance of any of the members<lb/>saying that in reference to Judge Wil<lb break="no"/>mot. I believe the Government did<lb/>right in appointing Judge Ritchie Chief<lb/>Justice. At the last session of the<lb/>Legislature, when the question of Con<lb break="no"/>federation was up, I referred to His<lb/>Honor Judge Wilmot, and I appeal<lb/>to the members of this House whether<lb/>I referred to him in a derogatory man<lb break="no"/>ner, yet I was represented as having<lb/>made a great boast about it. What I<lb/>say here I am prepared to say to Judge<lb/>Wilmot, and I do not want to be misre<lb break="no"/>presented in regard to the matter. My<lb/>hon. colleage has said he read out of the<lb/>same book with him. I can almost say<lb/>we were born in the same house ; we<lb/>ran and played in the same house, and<lb/>my feelings of friendhip for him were<lb/>and are very strong. I have gone<lb/>through mud and mire to canvass for<lb/>him, without his knowing it, because I<lb/>believed he was right, and I have ask<lb break="no"/>ed no favors at his hands ; and if I did<lb/>I would not get them. All I want as a <lb/>lawyer before him, is justice, and that<lb/>I will have. After the last session of <lb/>the Legislature, I signed a document to<lb/>the Government, asking them to ap<lb break="no"/>point Judge Parker Chief Justice, and<lb/>so on according to seniority. If I had<lb/>not believed that Judge Wilmost would<lb/>have made a good Chief Justice, I<lb/>would not have done so, and that is<lb/>enough in regard to his legal character.<lb/>It is no detraction to a great man to<lb/>say there is a greater. We know there<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
          
are stars differing in magnitude, and<lb/>that all flesh is not the same kind of<lb/>flesh. I acknowledge that Judge Wil<lb break="no"/>mot has done a great deal for the<lb/>country, and I acknowledge the coun<lb break="no"/>try has done a great deal for him. If I <lb/>devote twenty or thirty years to this<lb/>country, and, in consequence, am<lb/>placed on the Bench, with a competent<lb/>income to sustain me and my family, I<lb/>should consider the country had reward<lb break="no"/>ed me for my services to the fullest ex<lb break="no"/>tent. According to the principles of<lb/>Responsible Government, of which he<lb/>was the Gog and my hon. colleague was<lb/>the Magog, he might have stepped<lb/>from the Attorney Generalship to the<lb/>Chief Justiceship. He did not do it. If <lb/>the principles of Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment were as strong in them as the<lb/>principles of non-Confederation were in<lb/>the anti-Confederates, they would never<lb/>step to the Bench or anywhere else, un<lb break="no"/>til they had carried out those principles<lb/>to their legitimate consequence. To<lb/>carry out the principle of Responsible<lb/>Government, he should have claimed<lb/>the Chief Justiceship or remained on<lb/>the floors of the House until the people<lb/>put him there by acclamation. I feel<lb/>bound, and proud to say, that the lead<lb break="no"/>er of the present Government has re<lb break="no"/>fused the office of Chief Justice for the<lb/>sake of sustaining the principle of anti-<lb break="yes"/>Confederation against Confederation.<lb/>( <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName>.—Do you believe it?)<lb/>I do not utter things in this House<lb/>which I believe to be untrue. I have<lb/>undoubted authority for stating that<lb/>my hon. friend, the Attorney General,<lb/>might this day have been Chief Justice<lb/>had he chosen to accede to the offer of<lb/>those who could have given it to him.<lb/>He declined to accept that office because<lb/>he had embarked his all in this grand,<lb/>glorious, magnificient fight against sell<lb break="no"/>ing the country to the Canadians. This<lb/>will stand imperishable and indestructi<lb break="no"/>ble in the records of the country, and<lb/>when many of us are dead and forgot<lb break="no"/>ten, it will be told for the honor of New<lb/>Brunswick that we had one man who<lb/>sacrificed place and emoluments rather<lb/>than sell his country. When Chief Jus<lb break="no"/>tice Chipman resigned, my hon. col<lb break="no"/>league complained that the appointment <lb/>was arranged between the Home Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and Sir Edmund Head, and<lb/>my hon. colleague complained that<lb/>they had to submit to the over riding of<lb/>the Home Government, as they had not<lb/>given Judge Wilmot the place of Chief<lb/>Justice, but had directly interfered with<lb/>the principles of Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment by giving the place to Judge<lb/>Carter. Therefore, he did not refuse to<lb/>accept the office for the sake of carrying<lb/>out the principles of Responsible Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing was said in regard to the ap<lb break="no"/>pointment of the other Judges, therefore<lb/>I shall not say much about them, as I<lb/>must take it for granted that these ap<lb break="no"/>pointments have been received by the<lb/>country as correct and good, and futurity<lb/>will justify them. I did not blame Judge<lb/>Wilmot because on two occasions he ex<lb break="no"/>pressed his opinion on the great constitu<lb break="no"/>tional question of confederation. I did<lb/>not think it was prudent, but that was for<lb/>himself to judge. I do not think he made<lb/>himself a political partizan by doing so,<lb/>and I shall give him credit where I think<lb/>he was not blameable ; but while I am <lb/>quite willint to say this, I do contend that<lb/>the moment Judge Wilmot voted for Mr.<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
          
Fisher, an avowed opponent of this Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, he showed himself hostile to the<lb/>Government, and if any favors were to be<lb/>given to one Judge more than another—<lb/>if they had even acted upon the principle<lb/>of distributing their favors to their friends,<lb/>or upon the principle of carrying out the<lb/>doctrine long held in this country, that<lb/>" to the victors belong the spoils "—they<lb/>should have given those favors to Judge<lb/>Ritchie and not Judge Wilmot. Party<lb/>Government necessarily involves this<lb/>principle, they are bound to take care of<lb/>their friends, and let their enemies take<lb/>care of themselves. I am asked why my<lb/>friends did not carry this out ? There is<lb/>a great difference between a constitution<lb break="no"/>al question and a party political question.<lb/>Confederation involves no party politics,<lb/>for it is a great constitutional question,<lb/>and I hold that in a great question affect<lb break="no"/>ing our constitution, every man, whether<lb/>a Judge or a subordinate officer, has an<lb/>undoubted right as a British subject, and<lb/>a free man, to go the polls and calmly<lb/>and quietly vote on that question, either<lb/>for or against it, and that Government<lb/>would be wrong when they got into<lb/>power upon a question like this, to turn<lb/>a man out of office because he voted<lb/>against them. But on a party question,<lb/>when a man holding office under the<lb/>Government opposes that Government<lb/>and votes against them, I say he ought to<lb/>be turned out, and I believe no Govern<lb break="no"/>ment can sustain itself unless it does so.<lb/>I know it is a necessary concomitant of a<lb/>Federal Government, but I do not believe<lb/>that it was a necessary concomitant of<lb/>Responsible Government, though it seems<lb/>to be of party Government. I hold that<lb/>the former Government perpetrated a foul<lb/>wrong when they turned men out of office<lb/>for opposing them, without letting them<lb/>know that that was the principle they<lb/>were going to adopt. They set the ex<lb break="no"/>ample, and I fell this Government, or any<lb/>other Government that may come on the<lb/>floors of this House, that they never will<lb/>be able to sustain themselves unless they <lb/>do likewise. You have to sacrifice your<lb/>feelings to sustain your party. No mat<lb break="no"/>ter whether a man is a good officer or<lb/>not, if he is a political partizan you have<lb/>to give him the cold shoulder, and put a<lb/>man in his place, even if he is inferior to<lb/>him. That is the course which must now<lb/>be pursued, for the former Government<lb/>have set the example, and they must be<lb/>bound by it. Judge Wilmot would have<lb/>made a good Chief Justice, but when a<lb/>Judge, for views of his own, comes down<lb/>and opposes a Government by openly<lb/>voting for an opponent of that Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, he should not expect to receive<lb/>favors from them. The Attorney General<lb/>has stated that it was not upon those po<lb break="no"/>litical grounds at all that this appoint<lb break="no"/>ment was made, but was made at the<lb/>request of the late Chief Justice<lb/>Parker, a man whom you cannot eulogise<lb/>too highly, and of whom it might be said,<lb/>when he died in St. John, as it was said<lb/>of a King of Israel when he died, " This<lb/>day has a great man fallen in Israel. "<lb/>My hon. colleague said that the Hon.<lb/>John A. Street expressed an high opin<lb break="no"/>ion of Judge Wilmot, in reference to the<lb/>trial of a case in the County of Albert—<lb/>that was correct, for I heard him express<lb/>the same opinion—and he has so<lb/>high an opinion of the judgement<lb/>of Mr. Street, that he thinks that<lb/>was a <hi rendition="simple:italic">carte blanche</hi> for the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of Judge Wilmot to the Chief Jus<lb break="no"/>ticeship. We will now see what Mr.

            <pb n="87" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_087.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">87</fw> 
   

     Street said about my hon. colleague in 
     <lb/>the same primer, when speaking of the<lb/>
    School Law. He says: " He (Mr. 
     <lb/>Street) was glad to hear it, and therefore 
     <lb/>inferred that the hon. member approved 
     <lb/>of the law; but other hon. members of 
     <lb/>the opposition had censured it, and he 
     <lb/>(Mr. Fisher) had made sweeping charges 
     <lb/>against the Government, and against him 
     <lb/>(Hon. Attorney General) in particular,<lb/>stating that he had not a modern idea in 
     <lb/>his head, and knew nothing but law. He 
     <lb/>would reply, that if to possess modern 
     <lb/>ideas, it was necessary to square with the 
     <lb/>sentiments and opinions of the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber, he would pray from such modern 
     <lb/>ideal and opinions "Good Lord deliver 
     <lb/>him;" and as to the hon. member's opi<lb break="no"/>nion of his legal attainments, he would 
     <lb/>only remark, that the success which he 
     <lb/>had met with in his professional career 
     <lb/>was the most satisfactory proof of the 
     <lb/>opinion of the public on that score, and 
     <lb/>that he should feel much humbled indeed 
     <lb/>it be had nothing better to support his 
     <lb/>legal reputation than the opinion of the 
     <lb/>hon. member (Mr. F.)" This was the 
     <lb/>character of my hon. colleague, as <choice><sic>pour<lb break="no"/>trayed</sic><corr>portrayed</corr></choice> by Mr. Street at that time. He 
     <lb/>says he (Mr. Street) had not a modern 
     <lb/>idea in his head, and (Mr. S.) whom he 
     <lb/>now speaks of as a shining light, must in 
     <lb/>those days have been a dark lantern. 
     <lb/>Then we have the hon. Mr. Street's opi<lb break="no"/>nion of my hon. colleague. " What, he 
     <lb/>would ask, could any Government have 
     <lb/>done more for the furtliersnce of Rail<lb break="no"/>ways, and the internal government of the 
     <lb/>country at large. This was at all events 
     <lb/>more progressive than anything the hon. 
     <lb/>member (Mr. Fisher) had been guilty of 
     <lb/>and yet that hon. member had the auda<lb break="no"/>city. Well, if the word was unparliamen<lb break="no"/>tary, he would use a softer one, and as 
     <lb/>the hon. member had the presumption to 
     <lb/>say the Government was not progressive, 
     <lb/>and that he (Hon. Attorney General) had 
     <lb/>not a modern idea in his head. The hon. 
     <lb/>member (Mr. Fisher) no doubt had some 
     <lb/>modern idea in his head, and one of 
     <lb/>his most brilliant conceptions was that of 
     <lb/>trying by cunning not manœuvring to 
     <lb/>step into his (Hon. Attorney General's) 
     <lb/>shoes. This was the hon. member's great 
     <lb/>desideratum, and one of his progressive 
     <lb/>movements." This was a splendid move<lb break="no"/>ment, and he thinks the same thing should 
     <lb/>be done now. He wants to move out the 
     <lb/>Hon. Mr. Smith and get in his shoes, but 
     <lb/>I doubt if they are large enough for him. 
     <lb/>Then the Hon. Attorney General winds up 
     <lb/>by saying, "He did not pretend to be a great 
     <lb/>politician, but <hi rendition="simple:italic">if low cunning manœuvres, 
     <lb/>political tergiversation, and a readiness to 
     <lb/>accomplish his ends any and every 
     <lb/>means constituted</hi> a politician, he (Hon. 
     <lb/>Attorney General) was both glad and 
     <lb/>proud to say that he was not one, <hi rendition="simple:italic">although 
     <lb/>his successor</hi> (meaning Mr. Fisher) in <hi rendition="simple:italic">that 
     <lb/>sense might be</hi>." That was the opinion of 
     <lb/>the late Attorney General (Mr. Street), 
     <lb/>and if that opinion is worth what my hon. 
     <lb/>it is, in what position does my hon. friend 
     <lb/>say a colleague stand to-day. If that great 
     <lb/>light, before he died, pronounced that 
     <lb/>eulogy upon Judge Wilmot, I would ask 
     <lb/>my hon. colleague. when he re-reads 
     <lb/>this primer, whether he does not feel 
     <lb/>that is position was wrong in accepting 
     <lb/>the testimony of that great light, and 
     <lb/>give up this matter. I will now say a 
     <lb/>few words in regard to the Delegation, 
     <lb/>and then speak on the main point, which 
     <lb/>in Confederation. This Delegation which  
     <lb/>went home to England this last season, 
     <lb/>cost seven hundred and odd pounds. 
     <lb/>
        

            <cb/>
       

     My hon. colleague and another gentle<lb break="no"/>man went home on a Delegation to 
     <lb/>
     make some arrangements about Rail<lb break="no"/>roads, and the Delegation cost £787<lb/>
    18s. 4d. If the Confederation Delega<lb break="no"/>tion had jolly times, the Railway Dele<lb break="no"/>gation must have had jollier, for they spent 
     <lb/>£87 more. I thought this was a large 
     <lb/>sum, but I find there is a certain allow<lb break="no"/>ance for their pay, so much a day for 
     <lb/>one of them. If the Province sends a 
     <lb/>Delegation home, they should put them 
     <lb/>in a position that they would not he 
     <lb/>called upon to spend their own money. 
     <lb/>I have made a calculation of how much mo<lb break="no"/>ney my hon. colleague has received from 
     <lb/>the Province in these twenty-four years 
     <lb/>he has been here, and l find he has re<lb break="no"/>ceived fifty thousand dollars, there<lb break="no"/>fore I think the count has paid 
     <lb/>him pretty well for his services. I 
     <lb/>think if I had it I would be as mean as was 
     <lb/>possible in saying anything about dele<lb break="no"/>gations. The delegation to Quebec cost 
     <lb/>the Province $3337.97. This delega<lb break="no"/>tion was unauthorized and uncalled for, 
     <lb/>and it was not right to take that money 
     <lb/>out of the public chest. It was a public 
     <lb/>robbery, and they ought to pay it back, 
     <lb/>and if I had the power I would hold on 
     <lb/>to them until they disgorged it. What<lb break="no"/>ever it cost for the delegation to go to 
     <lb/>Prince Edward's Island they had a right 
     <lb/>to, but they had no right to one cent of 
     <lb/>the other. The only fault I have to find 
     <lb/>with the present Government about 
     <lb/>money matters is, that they are not 
     <lb/>generous enough. It is no wonder the 
     <lb/>late Government could have friends. 
     <lb/>when they spent $3337 without authori<lb break="no"/>ty, and without a vote of this Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture. There was a time in the history 
     <lb/>of this country when expenses of this 
     <lb/>kind were put under the head of shovel<lb break="no"/>ing snow; but days of greater light have 
     <lb/>come in, and an account has to be given 
     <lb/>of every root of the public money, to 
     <lb/>whom it is given, and how it is expend<lb break="no"/>ed. This House ought to pass a resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, calling upon those delegates to 
     <lb/>refund every shilling of that money. 
     <lb/>My hon. colleague (Mr. Fraser) refer<lb break="no"/>red to an important fact with regard to 
     <lb/>the Jackson contract. My hon. colleague 
     <lb/>(Mr. Fisher) and Mr. Robertson went 
     <lb/>on that delegation, which cost £800, to 
     <lb/>make an arrangement with Jackson, 
     <lb/>Peto &amp; Company. The original con<lb break="no"/>tract was not made by tho Tilley Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, but the moment they got in 
     <lb/>they thought they found some flaw in 
     <lb/>the contract, and they thought they 
     <lb/>would not be able to carry it out. This 
     <lb/>contract was drawn by Judge Ritchie, 
     <lb/>and revised by Messrs. Grey, Street and 
     <lb/>Hazen, the ablest lawyers in the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, yet this cry was got up, and those 
     <lb/>delegates were sent home to make ar<lb break="no"/>rangements with Jackson, Betts. Brassy, 
     <lb/>Peto and Company. When they re<lb break="no"/>turned, their report was laid before the 
     <lb/>House on the 11th day of March, and 
     <lb/>this matter was under the consideration 
     <lb/>of the House until the 27th of March, 
     <lb/>when it finally passed and it was a singu<lb break="no"/>lar fact that the original contract was in 
     <lb/>some pigeon-hole in the Secretary's of<lb break="no"/>fice, and was not found until the whole 
     <lb/>thing had passed through the House. 
     <lb/>( <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. Fisher</persName>,—The paper was mislaid in      
     <lb/>the Provincial Secretary's office, and 
     <lb/>the Government got from Mr. Gibbs a 
     <lb/>certfied copy of the orginial contract.) 
     <lb/>I now ask if any of the members who 
     <lb/>voted for annulling that contract, knew 
     <lb/>from the statements of my hon. colleague 
     <lb/>
   

            <cb/>
       

     that if they had allowed Jackson &amp; Co. 
     <lb/>
     to extend the time of their contract for 
     <lb/>
     three months, they would build the 
     <lb/>
     Road. I have heard Judge Allen say 
     <lb/>
     that he never heard it, yet a Bill was 
     <lb/>
     hurried through this House to give that 
     <lb/>
     company £90,000 of the people's money 
     <lb/>
     and release them of their contract, and 
     <lb/>
     £290,000 was spent in building that 
     <lb/>
     road above what it would have cost if it 
     <lb/>
     had been built by the Jackson Company. 
     <lb/>
     who only required the extension of the 
     <lb/>
     time of their contract for three months. 
     <lb/>
     This was an outrage perpetrated on the 
     <lb/>
     people of the country, resulting in the 
     <lb/>
     loss of £290,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     My hon. colleague made some other 
     <lb/>
     charges against the Government, and 
     <lb/>the one he considered the most import<lb break="no"/>ant he reserved until the last; that is, 
     <lb/>regarding the Export Duty Law. This 
     <lb/>was a mistake, placing $60,000 in 
     <lb/>jeopardy, but it was not half as big a 
     <lb/>sell as the "pigeon hole" That mis<lb break="no"/>take cost the Province £290,000. After 
     <lb/>all, this mistake about: the Export Duty 
     <lb/>Law amounts to nothing. It is a tem<lb break="no"/>pest in a teapot, for there was not a 
     <lb/>dollar lost to the revenue. I do not 
     <lb/>know who wrote the letter to Mr. Ling<lb break="no"/>ley in St. John. If he had received that 
     <lb/>letter a day sooner, he would have been 
     <lb/>a gainer, but the country would have 
     <lb/>lost. We say no wrong has been done; 
     <lb/>forgive us. And the House said, we 
     <lb/>forgive you. when they enacted the low 
     <lb/>to remedy the difficulty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

            <p>
     I will now come to the main point, 
     <lb/>
     which is Confederation. My hon. 
     <lb/>
     friends from the North say this is a pure 
     <lb/>
     question of Confederation, and if this 
     <lb/>
     Government had foreshadowed and 
     <lb/>
     come down with a scheme, they would 
     <lb/>
     have supported them. When they take 
     <lb/>
     that ground, I believe it is simply and 
     <lb/>
     purely a question of Confederation, and 
     <lb/>that if the present Government is turned<lb/>
    out, the Government that will come in 
     <lb/>to supplant them will be formed on a<lb/>Confederation basis of the worst kind.<lb/>If a majority of the House say they 
     <lb/>have no confidence in the present Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, they never need look to me 
     <lb/>again for support. if they do not dissolve 
     <lb/>the House and go to the people. I 
     <lb/>came to this House pledged to go 
     <lb/>against Confederation ; and knowing 
     <lb/>that under the present Government we 
     <lb/>are safe in this respect, I am prepared 
     <lb/>to sustain them at all hazards and risks. 
     <lb/>They say the Government have fore<lb break="no"/>shadowed a scheme in the Speech, but 
     <lb/>no construction of the English language 
     <lb/>can justify them in coming to that 
     <lb/>conclusion. This Confederation scheme 
     <lb/>was originated by an unauthorized 
     <lb/>delegation, and the resolutions were 
     <lb/>sent home by Lord Monck to the Colo<lb break="no"/>nial Ministers, and was agreed to by 
     <lb/>the British Ministry. It was stated we 
     <lb/>had to take it word for word. There 
     <lb/>could be on alteration made from the 
     <lb/>beginning to tho end; and it is pro<lb break="no"/>pounded now that that objectionable 
     <lb/>part, representation by population, is 
     <lb/>unalterable—that we will never have 
     <lb/>Confederation on any other basis. Mr. 
     <lb/>Cardwell did not faney it was unalter<lb break="no"/>able. The Imperial Legislature may 
     <lb/>legislate for us, and may alter what we 
     <lb/>dare not alter. We have hot to swallow<lb/>it down, body, bones, and all, but they<lb/>can change it and make it more palatable<lb/>to them. What kind of dcotrine is that<lb/>for free men holding the right of self-<lb break="yes"/>government to proclaim to the world?<lb/>
            </p>


            <pb n="88" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_088.jpg"/>
           

<fw type="num">88</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>


          

            <p>The very fact of the scheme coming in<lb/>that way to a free people is enough to<lb/>make them reject it. Those delegates<lb/>have been compared to the men who<lb/>signed the declaration of independence<lb/>in the United States. Those men took<lb/>their lives in their hands, and looked for<lb break="no"/>ward to jails and gibbets. Did those<lb/>men who went to Quebec and sat seven<lb break="no"/>teen long days in concocting this scheme<lb/>to ruin us, take their lives in their hands ?<lb/>I rather think they had a jolly good time ;<lb/>champage in the morning, sherry in the<lb/>afternoon, toast in the evening, and glo<lb break="no"/>rious times all the way through. The<lb/>Canadian politicians looked out for them<lb break="no"/>selves. They were justified in doing so,<lb/>and I find no fault with them for doing<lb/>so, but I find fault with the delegates<lb/>from the Maritime Provinces that they<lb/>appended their names to such a scheme.<lb/>Look at it, read it, and understand<lb/>it. The 64th Section says :—" In con<lb break="no"/>sideration of the transfer to the General<lb/>Parliament of the powers of taxation, an<lb/>annual grant in aid of each Province shall<lb/>be made equal to eighty cents per head<lb/>of the population." All our revenues go<lb/>to Canada. Those revenues amount in<lb/>round numbers to a million dollars a year,<lb/>and are collected at the different custom<lb/>offices in this Province, and the moment<lb/>it is deposited it finds its way into the<lb/>great maw of Canada. Where are our<lb/>eighty cents ? Up in Canada, and we<lb/>have to get it by an <hi rendition="simple:italic">annual vote of Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment</hi>, where we have fifteen members out<lb/>of one hundred and ninety-four, and they<lb/>tell us that is the best scheme they could<lb/>get. Suppose this great confederation<lb/>scheme is carried, and in our Legislature<lb/>we make a law that cows found on the<lb/>commons shall be impounded, that law<lb/>has to be taken to the General Parliament<lb/>to get their sanction. They come down<lb/>and say we want to extend our territory<lb/>and buy the North Pole, and we want<lb/>$3,000,000 a year, are you prepared to<lb/>tax New Brunswick for that ? No. Then <lb/>you shall not have your cows impounded.<lb/>Is that all ? No. You shall not have<lb/>your eighty cents per head. Could not<lb/>the Delegates have made a clause in the<lb/>constitution, that the different Provinces<lb/>should, by a warrant on their treasury,<lb/>draw that amount before it went to Cana<lb break="no"/>da ? Ought they not to have had it when<lb/>they are giving away a million dollars a<lb/>year to Canada, and if this Confederation<lb/>increases the population of this country,<lb/>as they say it will, our revenues will be<lb/>increased, and in a few years we will have<lb/>two millions to send away, but we only<lb/>receive back the same $200,000 for the<lb/>support of roads, schools, militia, and the<lb/>expenses of the local Government (if Par<lb break="no"/>liament chooses to give it). If these Mara-<lb break="yes"/>time Provinces were united to Canada<lb/>under that scheme, the men that originated<lb/>and sustained it, had better clear out of<lb/>the country before fifteen years, for they<lb/>would not be tolerated here, after having<lb/>absolutely sold us. I do not believe any<lb/>man in New Brunswick when he reflects<lb/>upon that clause in it, allowing them to<lb/>give us $200,000 or not, just as they<lb/>please, would go for confederation. An<lb break="no"/>other objection to this scheme is, that two<lb/>languages are to be used. One-half of<lb/>the members will get up and jabber<lb/>French, and not one of our members will<lb/>understand what they are saying. The<lb/>courts of law are conducted in French too.<lb/>In Lower Canada one lawyer talks to the<lb/>jury in French and another in English.<lb/>This is a system with which we want<lb/>nothing to do.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>It was asserted here during the election,<lb/>that by going into confederation they se<lb break="no"/>cured the seat of Government in Freder<lb break="no"/>icton for all time to come. My hon. col<lb break="no"/>league (Mr. F.) heard that assertion made<lb/>by a gentleman who was lecturing for his<lb/>benefit, and by his silence gave consent<lb/>to it. If we look at the fifty-third reso<lb break="no"/>lution, we will find that the seats of the<lb/>local Governments shall be as at pre<lb break="no"/>sent subject to any future action of the<lb/>respective local Governments. This<lb/>gentleman had the abominable audacity<lb/>to declare in the face of his own reso<lb break="no"/>lution—which, as Mr. Cartier says, was<lb/>signed by him and sworn to—that the<lb/>seat of Government was fixed for ever.<lb/>We can imagine that these Canadians<lb/>saw the difficulty about the eighty cents,<lb/>and they said let us put a bait on the<lb/>hook to catch these lawyers. A reso<lb break="no"/>lution was inserted stating that<lb/>" until the consolidation of the<lb/>laws of the different Provinces, the Judges<lb/>of these Provinces shall be selected from<lb/>their respective bars." That consolida<lb break="no"/>tion will take place when it suits the con<lb break="no"/>venience of the Canadians, and then the<lb/>Bench of New Brunswick will be filled<lb/>with Canadian lawyers. The bait was so<lb/>thin that it showed the hook, and they did<lb/>not catch all the lawyers. It seemed to be<lb/>the desire to invest Canada with all the<lb/>power they possibly could. It is hard in<lb/>that scheme to define the power given to<lb/>the local Parliament, or whether they<lb/>have any power at all. The General<lb/>Parliament shall have power to make<lb/>laws regarding public debt and property,<lb/>the regulation of trade and commerce,<lb/>the regulation of duties and the raising<lb/>of money by all <hi rendition="simple:italic">or any other modes or<lb/>systems</hi> of taxation. This is like the Cal<lb break="no"/>vinistic theology. It must have been a <lb/>lawyer that drew it, who was thinking of<lb/>the old form of indictment, which names<lb/>every part of the body and then says all<lb/>other parts. This General Parliament<lb/>will have the power to tax by all or any<lb/>other modes of taxation. There is some<lb break="no"/>thing underneath this that has not been<lb/>let out. Why did our great statesmen<lb/>who have been held up as the very<lb/>"solons" of this age, let them put in<lb/>such a clause as that. Mr. Galt, in<lb/>speaking to his own people, says " that<lb/>a union of the Provinces will relieve Can<lb break="no"/>ada from distress and depression, for at<lb/>this moment Canada, standing alone,<lb/>her credit is seriously depressed, but if<lb/>Confederation is gone into, will have<lb/>larger means to pledge for the security<lb/>of the public creditor." They want us to<lb/>pay for their defalcations. No wonder<lb/>there is a dead lock. We go into Con<lb break="no"/>federation with a debt of $7,000,000, and<lb/>Canada goes in with a debt of $62,000,<lb break="no"/>000, and they claim actual assets valued<lb/>at $70,000,000, from which they, two or<lb/>three years ago, received a return of<lb/>$471,461, which is a little more than one-<lb break="yes"/>half per cent. It follows as a necessary<lb/>consequence that a great part of that<lb/>debt is represented by unproductive pub<lb break="no"/>lic works, and a large proportion of bad<lb/>debts, which is no property at all. This<lb/>is not declamation, but is the honest truth.<lb/>The debt of the Province is $5,800,000.<lb/>We have nothing to show for $800,000 of<lb/>this, but for the $5,000,000, we have a<lb/>railroad paying $40,000 per annum<lb/>over and above working expenses,<lb/>and when Eastern and Western Ex<lb break="no"/>tension are built, which time is not<lb/>far distant, it will be a paying pro<lb break="no"/>perty. This is acknowledged by ev<lb break="no"/>
           

            <cb/>
          
ery man who pretends to know any thing<lb/>about railroads. If we go into Confe<lb break="no"/>deration, Canada assumes her portion of<lb/>our debt of $7,000,000, and we give her<lb/>property equal in value to it. At the<lb/>same time we assume our proportion of<lb/>her debt of $62,000,000, for which she<lb/>gives us $70,000,000 of unproductive pro<lb break="no"/>perty, part of which is comprehended in<lb/>the Grand Trunk Railroad, built by mo<lb break="no"/>ney filched from the widow and orphan<lb/>at home, and that money has never been<lb/>repaid, and never will be. If we had a <lb/>railroad built in that way I would rail<lb break="no"/>road it out of existence. How was that<lb/>money obtained from them ? Pamphlets<lb/>were written to induce the people of<lb/>England to think this road would pay<lb/>ten per cent., and the widows and orphans<lb/>of brave soldiers who fell defending the<lb/>honor of old England, withdrew their<lb/>money from the three per cents at home,<lb/>and invested it in the Grand Trunk Rail<lb break="no"/>road. Hundreds of those widows are<lb/>now living by the bounty of the Brit<lb break="no"/>ish Government, and have become the te<lb break="no"/>nants of the work houses and poor<lb/>houses at home, while Messrs. Galt and<lb/>Brown are revelling in their money in the<lb/>Grand Trunk Railroad. Our taxes aver<lb break="no"/>age 12 per cent., and our revenue is $1,<lb break="no"/>000,000, while Canada's taxes average 20<lb/>per cent., therefore, if we bring our taxes<lb/>up to the taxes of Canada, we would still<lb/>have to pay it all to Canada, yet we<lb/>would only get the same $200,000<lb/>back. This I think would be very unfair.<lb/>We have been charged with exaggeration<lb/>about Canada. I will read an extract<lb/>from a speech by Mr. Dunkin, in the<lb/>Canadian Parliament "<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" I do not care to see Upper and Lower<lb/>Canada more dissevered than they are.<lb/>On the contrary, I wish to see them<lb/>brought into closer union, and I am far<lb/>from regarding this scheme as cementing<lb/>more closely the connection of these Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces with the British Empire. I look<lb/>upon it as tending rather towards a not<lb/>distant disunion of these Provinces for<lb/>the British Empire. I look upon it as<lb/>tending rather towards a not distant dis<lb break="no"/>union of these Provinces from the Brit<lb break="no"/>ish Empire."<lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>Here the cry was you do not want to<lb/>preserve the union with the Mother Coun<lb break="no"/>try, because you do not go into Confede<lb break="no"/>ration. That is not only the language of<lb/>Mr. Dunkin, but it is the language of the<lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">Edinburgh Review</hi>, which is edited by the<lb/>most talented men in England, and they<lb/>regard this scheme as a direct strike at<lb/>independence from the Mother Country.<lb/>Mr. Dunkin says again :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" And now what have we ? Why,<lb/>the cry that the whole thing must be<lb/>passed, now or never. It will never<lb/>pass, we are told, if it does not pass<lb/>now. Was there ever a measure of this<lb/>magnitude before, on which the heart<lb/>of a country was set, the whole of which<lb/>was so wise and good as this scheme is<lb/>said to be ; and yet that had to be pass<lb break="no"/>ed (the whole of it) now or never ? We<lb/>are even told that it is a positive treaty,<lb/>made, however, by the way, by parties<lb/>who were never authorized to make any<lb/>treaty at all. I must say, for one, that<lb/>I cannot see in all this precipitancy the<lb/>unmistakable admission <hi rendition="simple:italic">de facto</hi> that the<lb/>Government themselves know and feel<lb/>that the feeling they have got up in fa<lb break="no"/>vor of this scheme is a passing feeling<lb/>
           

            <pb n="89" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-03_Page_089.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">89</fw> 
  

     of momentary duration, that they them<lb break="no"/>selves cannot rely upon."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     This gentleman's idea coincides with 
     <lb/>my own. That was the reason they<lb/>wanted us to swallow it now, for the<lb/>more it was looked into the more hide<lb break="no"/>ous it would appear. I lately read of a<lb/>ghost which appeared in the United<lb/>States, which had three descriptions of<lb/>heads and two descriptions of horns ; its<lb/>eyes were like fiery streams illuminating<lb/>all around with a greenish blue flame<lb/>That was the ghost of Confederation let<lb/>down there, and they did not know it.<lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. Cardwell said that Scheme could   
     <lb/>be altered, and this is what he writes<lb/>back to Lord Monck :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" Her Majesty's Government have gi<lb break="no"/>ven to your despatch and to the resolu<lb break="no"/>tions of the Conference, their most deli<lb break="no"/>berate consideration. They have re<lb break="no"/>garded them as a whole, and as having<lb/>been designed by those who framed them<lb/>to establish as complete and perfect a<lb/>union of the whole into one Government,<lb/>as the circumstances of the case and a<lb/>due consideration of existing interests<lb/>would admit. They accept them, therefore<lb/>as being in the deliberate judgment of<lb/>those best qualified to decide upon the sub<lb break="no"/>ject, the best framework of a measure to be<lb/>passed by the Imperial Parliament for at<lb break="no"/>taining that most desirable result."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>Mr. Cardwell acknowledges the Scheme<lb/>was right, because they were best quali<lb break="no"/>fied to decide upon it. Our Government<lb/>said to Mr. Cardwell, we will not adopt<lb/>it, for we are the best judges of it, but<lb/>Mr. Cardwell does not believe that, be<lb break="no"/>cause it does not suit his purpose, for he<lb/>thinks this union will be a most desirable<lb/>result, and will relieve him of a vast<lb/>amount of difficulty. He says it is the<lb/>best framework of a measure—our dele<lb break="no"/>gates told us it was a building perfect,<lb/>with foundation and superstructure all<lb/>complete. Why then does Mr. Cardwell<lb/>call it a framework set up, which has to<lb/>be finished ? He is perfectly satisfied<lb/>that if that Scheme was adopted, it would<lb/>add new burdens to the country. He says :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" Her Majesty's Government cannot<lb/>but express the earnest hope that the ar<lb break="no"/>rangements which may be adopted in this<lb/>respect may not be of such a nature as<lb/>to increase—at least in any considerable<lb/>degree—the whole expenditure, or to<lb/>make any material addition to the taxa<lb break="no"/>tion, and thereby retard the internal in<lb break="no"/>dustry or tend to impose new burdens on<lb/>the commerce of the country."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>Although willing for Confederation,<lb/>Mr. Cardwell puts on record that he gave<lb/>us warning, whether we choose to take it<lb/>or not. In regard to this $10,000,000 to<lb/>be spent in Railroads. How and when<lb/>do we get it and who is to pay for it.<lb/>Our revenue in ten years will amount to<lb/>$10,000,000, and we can have this ex<lb break="no"/>panded in the country year by year with<lb break="no"/>out going into Confederation. In Cana<lb break="no"/>da everything is taxed, and they have<lb/>even enacted a stamp act, and when we<lb/>go into Confederation our taxes will have<lb/>to conform to theirs. I will support the<lb/>Government as long as they are true to<lb/>anti–Confederate principles, and no man<lb/>can charge me with being inconsistent in<lb/>this matter. I hope to see the day come<lb/>
       

            <cb/>
    

         when this question will be settled and<lb/>settled for ever. I know there are men<lb/>whose souls soar away beyond us, who<lb/>are satiated with all the little New<lb/>Brunswick can give them, and they reach<lb/>forward to the celebrated towers and pa<lb break="no"/>laces of the far-off Ottawa ; for this they<lb/>would let New Brunswick go to the winds<lb/>and be lost for ever. Bring us near to<lb/>the darling of our souls, the far away Ot<lb break="no"/>tawa, with its miles of cornice and its<lb/>acres of plaster, and let us revel there in<lb/>vice-regal glory. But there are loyal<lb/>sons of New Brunswick who will not be<lb/>carried away by all this splendor, and when<lb/>the time comes, it will be seen that this<lb/>splendor has been like a dissolving view<lb/>to their eyes, become " the baseless fa<lb break="no"/>bric of a vision which leaves not a wreck<lb/>behind." In conclusion, I will thank the<lb/>members of the House for having listen<lb break="no"/>ed to me so long, for I felt I could not do<lb/>justice to myself and to the question if I<lb/>occupied less time than I have done. I<lb/>regret that it is out of my power to bring<lb/>before this House all that I would like to<lb/>bring before them, in order that the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of the country may understand the<lb/>question. I have shown enough I think<lb/>to satisfy hon. members that I have a<lb/>right to take the stand I do, that I have<lb/>a right to feel I am pursuing an honest<lb/>and disinterested course in sustaining<lb/>that Government, who have determined<lb/>with me to resist to the political death<lb/>any onslaught on the rights and liberties<lb/>of this free people ; and I, so far as I am<lb/>concerned in this matter, believe I stand<lb/>connected with men and with a party of<lb/>men who are quite willing to endorse the<lb/>principles of the Poet :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Strike till the last armed foe expires,<lb/>Strike for our altars and our fires,<lb/>Strike for the green graves of our aires,<lb/>For God and our native land.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
            <p>When I forget my country so far as to<lb/>sell it for Confederation, may my right<lb/>hand forget its cunning, and if I do not<lb/>prefer New Brunswick, as she is, to Ca<lb break="no"/>nada with all her glory, then let my<lb/>tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth.<lb/>When the day comes when we shall have,<lb/>according to the wish of my hon. friend<lb/>from Charlotte (Mr. Hill), Confederation<lb/>deposited in the grave, those that will be<lb/>there will not be there as mourners, but<lb/>as glorifiers, and they will sing, with<lb/>hearts elate with patriotic joy :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Then safely moored, our perils o'er,<lb/>We'll sing the songs of Jubilee,<lb/>For ever and for ever more,<lb/>New Brunswick, Land of Liberty.<lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>The House then adjourned until 10 A.M.<lb/>to-morrow.</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">T. P. D.<lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2018-03-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


            <!--<p>WEDNESDAY, APRIL 4.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of MR. OTTY, the House<lb/>went into committe on<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A BILL RELATING TO WEIGHTS."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. OTTY said the object of the Bill<lb/>was sufficiently explained by the Bill.<lb/>By it, instead of having 112 lbs to the<lb/>hundred weight, they would have the<lb/>decimal system, which would be much<lb/>more convenient in weighing all kinds of<lb/>produce. They had adopted it in Eng<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>land, after discussing it in Parliament for 
     <lb/>many years. It is upon the same princi<lb break="no"/>ple as an Act passed in Canada in 1858.<lb/>This Bill had been approved of by the<lb/>Agricultural Societies of King's County,<lb/>and also by the Apricultural Board, and<lb/>no doubt it will be approved of by the<lb/>people of the Province.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     COL. BOYD said the Bill was in favor 
     <lb/>of the seller and against the buyer.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     MR. ANGLIN said it was a Bill which 
     <lb/>they had had before them for several years.<lb/>He would ask what advantage there was<lb/>in having these continual changes. This<lb/>Bill was got up, not so much for simplifying<lb/>transactions, as to sell a smaller quantity<lb/>of produce by a measure which would<lb/>convey the idea to the buyers that they<lb/>were receiving a larger quantity. It did<lb/>not make any difference in the weighting<lb/>and the calculation whether they marked an<lb/>article 100 or 112. They had a law say<lb break="no"/>ing what weight should constitute a bushel<lb/>of potatoes, but it was disregarded. They<lb/>ought to be very careful in passing laws<lb/>which will be disregarded, because when<lb/>laws are disregarded it has a tendency to<lb/>bring all laws into contempt.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     MR. HILL believed the Bill did not go     
     <lb/>far enough. It ought to included potatoes<lb/>and all other things that are sold by<lb/>weight. We should simplify these things.<lb/>The old established usages are very well<lb/>in their place, but we should progress.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. LINDSAY moved an additional<lb/>section, that the standard weight of oats<lb/>be 33 1-3 lbs.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. MR. HATHEWAY saw no need<lb/>of the amendment, as the weight of the<lb/>oats always regulated the price. The<lb/>Bill would cause a great deal of incon<lb break="no"/>venience, as the weights throughout the<lb/>country were according to the present<lb/>method.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. KERR spoke against reducing the<lb/>standard weight of oats. If under Con<lb break="no"/>federation he would go for the Bill, but<lb/>did not think it was called for at present.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     MR. ANGLIN said hundreds and 
     <lb/>bushels were arbitrary sounds, which<lb/>from habit and practice convey certain<lb/>ideas. If they were so anxious to get rid<lb/>of the old system, they might as well do<lb/>away with it altogether. In the old<lb/>country everything is sold by weight,<lb/>which is the proper way. If we are going<lb/>to have decimals let us introduce the<lb/>whole system. If you introduce a revo<lb break="no"/>lution in these things, it would be some<lb/>time before it would be understood<lb/>throughout the country, and a great many<lb/>disputes would arise.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     MR. MCCLELLAN spoke in favor of the Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. WILMOT said that altering the<lb/>standard weights did not regulate the<lb/>price, for if they sold a less quantity they<lb/>were paid in proportion.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. GILBERT said that goods going<lb/>over the railway paid their freight on the<lb/>decimal system, and were bought and<lb/>sold by the old method, which led to con<lb break="no"/>siderable inconvenience and sometimes<lb/>to miscalculation.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. SCOVIL said the true principle<lb/>was that all produce should be weighed,<lb/>which was the only way of determining<lb/>the worth of the article, and this Bill<lb/>provided the most simple way of calcu<lb break="no"/>lating those weights.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. CONNELL said that oats in the<lb/>State of Maine were sold at thirty pounds<lb/>to the bushel. It was nonsense to think<lb/>that the standard weight of oats affected<lb/>the quality that would be grown in the<lb/>country. If a farmer raised good oats,<lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>