<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-06-28"
     xml:lang=""
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-06-28">28 June 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="33" to="41"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_033.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_034.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_035.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_036.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_037.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_038.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_039.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_040.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_041.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-05-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-05-08">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_033">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_033.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_034">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_034.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_035">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_035.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_036">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_036.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_037">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_037.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_038">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_038.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_039">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_039.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_040">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_040.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_041">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_041.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="33" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_033.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">33</fw>
            

<!-- GL, 2018-05-08, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 


<!--<p>
     
     And so it is said that we should have paid 
     <lb/>
     $140,000 more on the. article of Spirits 
     <lb/>
     alone, but the truth is we should only 
     <lb/>
     have paid the thirty cents a gallon, in<lb break="no"/>stead of the thirty-five centa as we did. 
     <lb/>
     In Newfoundland they pay a higher rate 
     <lb/>
     than we do, with a lower tariff, but in 
     <lb/>
     Canada they paid a lower rate with a 
     <lb/>
     higher tariff. In 1864, in Union, we 
     <lb/>
     should not have paid as much, for they 
     <lb/>
     only paid $2.60 to our $3.10. The tariff 
     <lb/>
     there is higher, but the rate lower, and 
     <lb/>
     why ? Because manufactures have in<lb break="no"/>creased, and importations decreased. 
     <lb/>
     " No," it is objected, " it is because they 
     <lb/>
     are a poorer country." But the fact is 
     <lb/>
     they consume much more in proportion 
     <lb/>
     to the population than we do. Of all the 
     <lb/>
     articles upon which they have a specific 
     <lb/>
     tariff there are only two that we use in 
     <lb/>
     larger quantities than they. The con<lb break="no"/>sumption of tea and molasses is much 
     <lb/>
     greater here than in Canada ? Why ? 
     <lb/>
     We know that during the late war in the 
     <lb/>
     United States the Government put a high 
     <lb/>
     rate upon tea, and the consequence was 
     <lb/>
     that much of the tea that paid duty here 
     <lb/>
     was consumed out of the country. Then 
     <lb/>
     in Canada they have Sugar Refineries, and 
     <lb/>
     they use the golden syrup instead of mo<lb break="no"/>lasses, because they can get it at a dollar 
     <lb/>
     a gallon, the same price they have to give 
     <lb/>
     for molasses ln Upper Canada, on ac<lb break="no"/>count of the expense of moving. The 
     <lb/>
     several rates for the Provinces in 1864 
     <lb/>
     was as follows : 
     <lb/>
     In Canada they paid  $2.56 per head 
     <lb/>
     " Nova Scotia they paid 2.69 " 
     <lb/>
     " New Brunswîck they paid 3.10 " 
     <lb/>
      " Newfoundland they paid 3.65 " 
     <lb/>
     " Prince Edward Island 
     <lb/>
     they paid 1.98 " 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The whole amount of the revenues 
     <lb/>
     raised in these Provinces in that year 
     <lb/>
     was $9,580,000. Apply to this the tariff 
     <lb/>
     of $3.10, and we get $1,670,000 more 
     <lb/>
     than was raised by all British North Am<lb break="no"/>erica out of the Union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With regard to the North-West Terri<lb break="no"/>tory and its admission into the Union, 
     <lb/>
     that will be a matter for discussion for 
     <lb/>
     the General Government. The surplus 
     <lb/>
     revenue will not be taken to purchase that 
     <lb/>
     territory, but go to meet the cost of the 
     <lb/>
     Intercolonial Railroad and the improve<lb break="no"/>ments in Canada for purposes of the Ge<lb break="no"/>neral Government. In Prince Edward<lb/>Island it is said they are opposed to the<lb/>Railroad, because they will not be direct<lb break="no"/>ly benefitted by it. But such an argu<lb break="no"/>ment cannot be used in this Province.<lb/>The Railroads now profided for under the<lb/>Subsidy Act are :<lb/>Western Extension, 88 miles.<lb/>St. Stephen Branch, 18 "<lb/>Woodstock " 12 "<lb/>Fredericton " 21 "<lb/>Eastward Extension, 30 "<lb/>Albert Branch, 2- "<lb/>Total say, 190 '<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>9<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     For the same rate which we paid per 
     <lb/>head in 1864 we can have the Intercolo-<lb break="maybe"/>nial Road and all these Branches<lb/>without the expenditure of a penny more<lb/>than we did.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of Mr. SUTTON the de<lb break="no"/>bate and House here adjourned till to<lb break="no"/>morrow morning at 9 o'clock.<lb/>J. M.<lb/>
            </p>-->


            <head rendition="simple:right">THURSDAY, JUNE 28.<lb/>
            </head>


            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> by leave brought in<lb/>the following bills.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill to revive and continue an Act<lb/>to amend the law for the relief of insol<lb break="no"/>vent Debtors."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A bill relating to the Registry of<lb/>Deeds and other instruments."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill to amend the law of evidence.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill to authorize the Justice of the<lb/>Supreme Court to preside at trials in<lb/>which the City of St. John is interested."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill relating to Debtors confined<lb/>in Jail or on the limits."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill to provide for the registration<lb/>of births and deaths."<lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CONTINUATION OF THE DEBATE ON MR. 
     <lb/>FISHER'S RESOLUTION FOR THE AP<lb break="no"/>POINTMENT OF DELEGATES.<lb/>
            </head>


            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Mr. TILLEY</persName> resumed.—I feel that I<lb/>am trespassing upon the patience of this<lb/>House in continuing my remarks upon<lb/>this resolution, for it is well known that<lb/>thirty-three of the members of this House<lb/>have been elected in favour of the princi<lb break="no"/>ples of this resolution now on the table,<lb/>and some of the remaining eight for<lb/>Union but against the Quebec Scheme.<lb/>My hon. friend (Mr. Smith) has taken<lb/>exception to a great many of the provi<lb break="no"/>sions of the Quebec Scheme, therefore I<lb/>feel myself called upon to occupy the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the House for a short time in<lb/>discussing this question, but before taking<lb/>up the principle points in the objections,<lb/>I desire to reiterate the financial state<lb break="no"/>ment made yesterday, because it has been<lb/>stated it was imaginary and there was<lb/>nothing real in it. In the first place can<lb/>there be any doubt about our being re<lb break="no"/>lieved from paying $420,000 annually, that<lb/>being the interest of our debt of $7,000,<lb break="no"/>000 ! Can there be any doubt about the<lb/>construction of the Intercolonial Railway<lb/>that under the arrangement of 1862 we<lb/>would have to pay 3 1/2 twelfths, whereas if<lb/>we go into Union we will have to pay but<lb/>one-thirteenth ? Can there be any doubt<lb/>but that the salaries of the Governor and<lb/>Judges and the expenses of the collection<lb/>and protection of the revenue will be paid<lb/>by the General Government. The deficien<lb break="no"/>cy in the Post Office will be paid by the<lb/>General Government, although it may be<lb/>that there will be a charge upon news<lb break="no"/>papers the same as in Canada. My hon.<lb/>friend (Mr. Smith) has not spoken upon<lb/>
       

            <cb/>
        

     these points because he knows that they 
     <lb/>are unanswerable. If he had had a leg to<lb/>stand upon he would have used the<lb/>same arguments here that he former<lb break="no"/>ly used in addressing his constituents.<lb/>The very fact that he himself has given<lb/>adhesion to Union upon some terms has<lb/>taken away a great deal of the arguments<lb/>which he used twelve months ago. I have<lb/>just been informed by the Postmaster<lb/>General that there is now a proposition<lb/>before the Canadian Legislature to do<lb/>away with the postage on newspapers.<lb/>( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. Smith</persName>—very opporture.) There are<lb/>many opportune circumstances which<lb/>have convinced the public mind of the<lb/>advantages of Union, while the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment have not been favored by Pro<lb break="no"/>vidential circumstances or anything else.<lb/>Let us look at some of the points which<lb/>the late Attorney General considers ob<lb break="no"/>jectionable. He says we have not a<lb/>sufficient number of representatives in<lb/>the upper branch of the Legislature.<lb/>There might be some concessions made<lb/>to us in this. When the arrangement was<lb/>made, and representation by population<lb/>was conceded, it was considered that<lb/>there was a great protection given to<lb/>the Maritime Provinces, for New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick was to have one representative for<lb/>every 25,000 of her population, Lower Ca<lb break="no"/>nada one to every 50,000, and Upper Ca<lb break="no"/>nada one to every 75,000. That was<lb/>twenty-four representatives for Upper<lb/>and twenty-four for Lower Canada, and<lb/>twenty-four for the Maritime Provinces,<lb/>and Newfoundland was to have four.<lb/>In every case the interests of the Mari<lb break="no"/>time Provinces are nearly identical, and<lb/>there is scarcely an important question<lb/>that can come up in which Lower Cana<lb break="no"/>da would not be with us. It has been<lb/>said that Upper Canada wishes to buy<lb/>the North West Territory, suppose such<lb/>a question came up, and a majority of<lb/>the people's representatives were in<lb/>favor of the measure. It would still<lb/>have to pass the Upper House, and<lb/>twenty-four representatives of Upper<lb/>Canada would vote for it, and the other<lb/>fifty-two members against it. Is there<lb/>not some protection in this? Again<lb/>there is a protection in the fact that the<lb/>number of representatives in the Upper<lb/>Branch cannot be increased by the<lb/>Crown. Suppose we had not that pro<lb break="no"/>tection, the Government could come<lb/>to the Upper Branch and say, unless<lb/>you pass this Act we will increase your<lb/>numbers and force it through. There<lb/>were some remarks made in reference<lb/>to the residence of the Legislative<lb/>Councillors. The sixteenth paragraph,<lb/>in reference to Lower Canada, says :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>Each of the twenty-four Legislative<lb/>Councillors representing Lower Canada<lb/>in the Legislative Council of the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Legislature, shall be appointed to<lb/>
         

            <pb n="34" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_034.jpg"/>
         

<fw type="num">34</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>


     represent one of the twenty-four Elec<lb break="no"/>toral Divisions mentioned in Schedule 
     <lb/>
      A of chapter first of the Consolidated 
     <lb/>
    Statutes of Canada, and such Council<lb break="no"/>lor shall reside or possess his qualifica<lb break="no"/>tion in the Division he îs appointed to 
     <lb/>represent.  
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

    

    
   
            <p>
     This paragraph was proposed. by the 
     <lb/>
     Lower Canadians, because there they 
     <lb/>
      have electoral districts for the Upper 
     <lb/>
     Branch, and their law requires that they 
     <lb/>
     should possess property and be residents 
     <lb/>
     of their several districts. I am quite 
     <lb/>
     sure that the delegates will see that the 
     <lb/>
     Scheme is amended so that the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives in the Upper Branch will be 
     <lb/>
     required to live and have their property 
     <lb/>
     qualification in the Province, although 
     <lb/>
     I do not think the evil would be so 
     <lb/>
      great as the late Attorney General has 
     <lb/>
     represented it. He says they would go 
     <lb/>
     to Ottawa to reside, and thus become 
     <lb/>
     representatives for Canada, and we may 
     <lb/>
     look for the same result here as has 
     <lb/>
     been produced in Ireland, in conse<lb break="no"/>quence of the Irish going to London. 
     <lb/>
     Do they go from Maine, Massachusetts 
     <lb/>
     or Rhode Island and settle in Washing<lb break="no"/>ton because it is the seat of Govern<lb break="no"/>ment? He (Mr. Smith) having him<lb break="no"/>self gone for Union should not point 
     <lb/>
     this out as an objection. He objects to 
     <lb/>
     representation by population. I was 
     <lb/>
     surprised to hear him take exception to 
     <lb/>
     that, for he was prepared even to go for 
     <lb/>
     that during the last session of this 
     <lb/>
      House. ( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. Smith</persName>—It is no such 
     <lb/>
     thing ) He admitted that no Union 
     <lb/>
      could be had if two principles were not 
     <lb/>
     affirmed, they were representation by 
     <lb/>
     population and a Federal Government, 
     <lb/>
     and his language conveyed no other 
     <lb/>
     idea but that he would go for Union, 
     <lb/>
     provided there were sufficient checks. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I stated distinctly that 
     <lb/>I never would go for the principle of 
     <lb/>representation by population unless 
     <lb/>neutralized by some checks in the 
     <lb/>scheme.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILM1">Hon. Mr. WILMOT</persName>.—I understood 
     <lb/> him to say that he would not go for it 
     <lb/>unless there were some checks in the 
     <lb/>Legislative Council.    
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I did not say that.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.—I should like to 
     <lb/>know how he is going to neutralize it 
     <lb/> except by checks in the Upper House. 
     <lb/> He says the revenues collected in the 
     <lb/>different Provinces should be for the 
     <lb/>benefit of each Province when collected, 
     <lb/>except a certain amount to be givin for 
     <lb/>the support of the General Government. 
     <lb/>That objection might emanate from a 
     <lb/> gentleman who had just come into po<lb break="no"/>litical life, but any person who knows 
     <lb/>anything would know that it never 
     <lb/>could be acted upon. If New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick and Nova Sootia are to be the 
     <lb/>frontage of a great back country they 
     <lb/>will collect all the import duties, and 
     <lb/>
         

            <cb/>
      

     Canada would never consent that we 
     <lb/>
     should take all the duties on imports 
     <lb/>
     collected on articles consumed in Cana<lb break="no"/>da, therefore not one check can be had 
     <lb/>
     except in the Legislative Council, and 
     <lb/>
     we thought that was secured   No ar<lb break="no"/>rangement can be made except upon 
     <lb/>
     the principle of representation by popu<lb break="no"/>lation. Have we heard any objection 
     <lb/>
     to representation by population on the 
     <lb/>
     floors of this House. The members for 
     <lb/>
     King's asked for an increase of repre<lb break="no"/>sentation because the population of their 
     <lb/>
     county is greater than the population 
     <lb/>
     of some other Counties, but you never 
     <lb/>
     saw the members for Queen's rising and 
     <lb/>
     saying, because Westmorland had four 
     <lb/>members Queen's should have four 
     <lb/>Governments generally try to do jus<lb break="no"/>tice to all parties in order to hold on 
     <lb/>to their power, for they know that 
     <lb/>members will come out in opposition if 
     <lb/>they do not. In this Union let any in<lb break="no"/>justice be perceived and no Govern<lb break="no"/>ment that permits it will be able to 
     <lb/>stand, for a very few members going 
     <lb/>into the Opposition can generally oust 
     <lb/>a Government, and in this lies our 
     <lb/>safety. It has been said  that all the 
     <lb/>Provinces should have equal represen<lb break="no"/>tation in the Upper House. ( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. 
     <lb/>Smith</persName>.—How is it in the United States.) 
     <lb/>The Senate in the States is an Execu<lb break="no"/>tive power, and is altogether different 
     <lb/>from ours. They are in a position to 
     <lb/>exercise executive functions, therefore 
     <lb/>in their executive position it is neces<lb break="no"/>sary for each State to have an equal 
     <lb/>representation. Their is no appoint<lb break="no"/>ment, even to a subordinate in the 
     <lb/>army, but has to go to the Senate and 
     <lb/>be ratified by them. We now come to 
     <lb/>another objection, and considering the 
     <lb/>long time the hon. member had to con<lb break="no"/>sider the scheme : the time he has de<lb break="no"/>voted to it, and the number of ad<lb break="no"/>dresses he has delivered upon the sub<lb break="no"/>ject, and we admit that he has great 
     <lb/>ability, but his ability lies in taking to 
     <lb/>pieces rather than constructing ; he is 
     <lb/>an admirable member of the Opposition, 
     <lb/>but as a member of the Government he 
     <lb/>is not so successful. After fifteen months 
     <lb/>study of the subject, he has come to the 
     <lb/>House and presented his objections to 
     <lb/>the Scheme, and they amount to very 
     <lb/>little. The mountain has brought forth 
     <lb/>but a mouse. He objects to the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Government and the local Legisla<lb break="no"/>tures each having power to legislate on 
     <lb/>the same subjects, for instance on the 
     <lb/>seacoast and inland fisheries, immigra<lb break="no"/>tion and agriculture. And he says the 
     <lb/>same power being given to each Go<lb break="no"/>vernment there would be no right of 
     <lb/>appeal at all.  It was desirable that the 
     <lb/>seacoast fisheries should be under the 
     <lb/>direction of the General Government, 
     <lb/>because the cost of protecting them 
     <lb/>
    

            <cb/>
       

     should be borne by the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, but the local Governments should 
     <lb/>
     have the power to make laws for the 
     <lb/>
     fisheries in the rivers of their respective 
     <lb/>
     Provinces. If, however, any one of the 
     <lb/>
     local Governments do not make laws 
     <lb/>
     sufficient to protect the fisheries in the 
     <lb/>
     rivers, where all this wealth originates, 
     <lb/>
     it was considered expedient that the 
     <lb/>
     General Government should have power 
     <lb/>
     to enact laws to protect them. Again : 
     <lb/>it was thought necessary that there<lb/>
    should be an Agricultural Bureau for 
     <lb/>the General Government, and the local 
     <lb/>Governments should control and regu<lb break="no"/>late their own Agricultural Societies. 
     <lb/>Then it was thought necessary for the 
     <lb/>General Government to have the con<lb break="no"/>trol of immigration, while, at the same 
     <lb/>time, it was desirable that the local 
     <lb/>Governments should have the power of 
     <lb/>arranging the locality of the immi<lb break="no"/>grants, therefore this power was given 
     <lb/>to both. The  forty-fifth paragraph 
     <lb/>says :   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     In regard to all subjects over which 
     <lb/>
     jurisdiction belongs to both the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral and Local Legislatures, the laws of 
     <lb/>
     the General Parliament shall control 
     <lb/>
     and supersede those made by the Local 
     <lb/>
     Legislature, and the latter shall be void 
     <lb/>
     so far as they are repugnant to or con<lb break="no"/>sistent with the former. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     This was prepared for the purpose of 
     <lb/>
     protecting the Fisheries, so that if the 
     <lb/>
     laws were not sufficient to  secure the origin 
     <lb/>
     of the great wealth of the country, the 
     <lb/>
     General Government could enact laws for 
     <lb/>
      that purpose. The next objection is to 
     <lb/>
     this paragraph.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     All such works as shall, although lying 
     <lb/>
     wholly within any Province, be specially 
     <lb/>
     declared by the Acts authorizing them to 
     <lb/>
     be to the general advantage. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     This produced considerable discussion 
     <lb/>
     at the Conference, and a decision was ar<lb break="no"/>rived at different from this, but the sub<lb break="no"/>ject was reconsidered upon the motion of 
     <lb/>
     the present Attorney General because we 
     <lb/>
     found that New Brunswick would get 
     <lb/>
     more benefit from it as it is, then if it was 
     <lb/>
     put in a different  way. Then in regard to 
     <lb/>
     beacons, buoys and lighthouses. we now 
     <lb/>
     collect this money and expend it among 
     <lb/>
     ourselves, and it is charged upon the ship<lb break="no"/>ping. In the Union you do not suppose 
     <lb/>the General Parliment will charge the 
     <lb/>shipping with anything more than is ne<lb break="no"/>cessary for this purpose ; if they brought 
     <lb/>foward a measure for that purpose Lower 
     <lb/> Canada would go against it as well as the 
     <lb/>Maratime Provinces. There might be a 
     <lb/>law passed by our combined influence to 
     <lb/>place this expense upon the General Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, as it is in the United States. He  
     <lb/>(Mr. Smith) also takes exception to the 
     <lb/>37th section.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
      " And generally respecting all matters 
     <lb/>
       

            <pb n="35" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_035.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">35</fw> 


     of a general character, not specially and 
     <lb/>exclusively reserved for the local govern<lb break="no"/>ments.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     There can be no reasonable objection 
     <lb/>
    taken to this. We had the experience of 
     <lb/>the United States before us, and had seen 
     <lb/>the working of their constitution. We had 
     <lb/>seen the difficulties that had arisen and the 
     <lb/>clashing of interests  that had taken place 
     <lb/>between Congress and the State Govern<lb break="no"/>ments. The people had delegated a por<lb break="no"/>tion of their power to the State Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture, another portion to Congress, and 
     <lb/>certain powers remained to the people 
     <lb/>themselves ; the States claiming certain 
     <lb/>rights which they did not possess in the 
     <lb/>Constitution, and this led to the United 
     <lb/>States war. The hon. gentleman (Mr 
     <lb/>Smith) has expressed himself in favour of 
     <lb/>a Legislative instead of a Federal Union. 
     <lb/>Then how can he object to this power 
     <lb/>being given to the General Government, 
     <lb/>for much more power would be given 
     <lb/>them under a Legislative Union. He has 
     <lb/>spoken of this Legislature becoming a 
     <lb/>mere corporation, with but limited powers, 
     <lb/>but under a Legislative Union all these 
     <lb/>towns and  counties would be municipali<lb break="no"/>ties, but they would have powers given 
     <lb/>them which would be clearly defined. St. 
     <lb/>John has certain corporate powers given 
     <lb/>to it, but there is no clashing with ours. 
     <lb/>He says that when Acts are passed by 
     <lb/>each Government which conflict there is 
     <lb/>no power to appeal to. Does not the 
     <lb/>Scheme say that the laws of the General 
     <lb/>Parliament shall control and supersede 
     <lb/>those made by the Local Legislature. 
     <lb/>Suppose they attempted to interfere with 
     <lb/>the rights and privileges of the Local 
     <lb/>Legislature, the Local Government would 
     <lb/>at once appeal to the Imperial Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and say, the General Parliament 
     <lb/>have exceeded their powers and ask them 
     <lb/>to interfere. This is the protection in 
     <lb/>this matter. Then he says we have to 
     <lb/>send the Bills we pass here to a political 
     <lb/>body for their approval. Do we not send 
     <lb/>them to a political body when we send 
     <lb/>them to the British Government, and no 
     <lb/>difficulties occur. Can it be supposed 
     <lb/>that more difficulties will arise in getting 
     <lb/>the assent of the General Parliament to 
     <lb/>our Bills, when we have representatives 
     <lb/>there who will make and unmake Govern<lb break="no"/>ments, than will arise in the Imperial  
     <lb/>Government where we have no direct 
     <lb/>voice in the matter. He takes exception 
     <lb/>to this : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     34. Until the consolidation of the laws 
     <lb/>
     of Upper Canada, New Brunswick, Nova 
     <lb/>
     Scotia, Newfoundland, and Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island, the judges at these Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces appointed by the general Govern<lb break="no"/>ment shall be selected from their respec<lb break="no"/>tive bars. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     35. The Judges of the Court of Lower 
     <lb/>
    Canada shall be selected from the Bar of 
     <lb/>Lower  Canada. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <cb/>
            <p>
     He says this implies that Judges might 
     <lb/>be selected from other Bars in any of the<lb/>other Provinces. I ask legal men if they<lb/>do not consider it an advantage for gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen to be taken from the Bar of New<lb/>Brunswick to be made Judges in Nova<lb/>Scotia, and <hi rendition="simple:italic">vice versa</hi>. Cases have oc<lb break="no"/>curred here where there was only one<lb/>Judge on the Bench who was not inter<lb break="no"/>ested in the matter. It was put down as<lb/>one of the most desirable propositions<lb/>that could be made, for it secures Judges<lb/>who have no local interests or political<lb/>bias in the Province to which they are ap<lb break="no"/>pointed. Is it to be said that the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the profession in New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick are to be confined simply to New<lb/>Brunswick. If you can put them in a<lb/>better position they have a right to it.<lb/>But this cannot take place unless our<lb/>laws are assimilated. If our laws are dif<lb break="no"/>ferent from those of Canada and Nova<lb/>Scotia there would be a difficulty in<lb/>having Judges appointed from other parts<lb/>to decide upon laws they are not conver<lb break="no"/>sant with. The Judges of Lower Canada<lb/>have to be selected from the bar of<lb/>Lower Canada, for they are under a<lb/>code of Laws secured to them at the<lb/>time of Union and they will not change<lb/>it. The French language being used<lb/>there it was the wish of the Lower Cana<lb break="no"/>dians that they should be selected from<lb/>Lower Canada. He then objects to the<lb/>way in which the basis of representation<lb/>by population was arranged. The basis<lb/>made was that Lower Canada was to have<lb/>sixty-five members upon which there<lb/>should be no increase. That was to pre<lb break="no"/>vent the number of representatives in<lb break="no"/>creasing in the General Parliament.<lb/>There is to be one representative for every<lb/>17,000 of the population. If the popu<lb break="no"/>lation of Lower Canada increases so that<lb/>she will have but one representatie for<lb/>every 20,000 of her population, none<lb/>of the other Provinces can get any in<lb break="no"/>crease unless they have 20,000 in addition<lb/>to her average of 20,000.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—Suppose you increase 
     <lb/>
     the representation thirty per cent., does 
     <lb/>
     not that give Canada a larger majority ? 
     <lb/>
     There is a provision that the number of 
     <lb/>
     members may at any time be increased 
     <lb/>
     by the General Parliament. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>—If that would be 
     <lb/>
     for the benefit of Upper Canada alone 
     <lb/>
     the representatives for Lower Canada and 
     <lb/>
     the Maritime Provinces would not sup<lb break="no"/>port it, and it could not be carried. 
     <lb/>
    Then again, Railway stock shall be the 
     <lb/>property of the General Government. 
     <lb/>Our Railway yields but three-fourths per 
     <lb/>cent., while the Railways of Canada, 
     <lb/>combined with the Canals, yields them 
     <lb/>one and a quarter per cent. The hon. 
     <lb/>member says that there is no protection 
     <lb/>that the different Provinces will receive 
     <lb/>this eighty cents per head which is to be 
     <lb/>
         

            <cb/>
   

     secured to them by an annual grand of 
     <lb/>the General Parliament, for he says they<lb/>may incur liabilities, and this eighty<lb/>cents per head might not be left for the<lb/>Local Governments. This might be<lb/>made a first charge upon the revenues of<lb/>the country. Do you imagine that a<lb/>
    Parliament representing the Provinces,  
     <lb/>the population of which are to get this  
     <lb/>eighty cents a head, would vote away 
     <lb/>the money that was to be appropriated 
     <lb/>for that purpose. Again, all engagements 
     <lb/>that may before the Union be entered 
     <lb/>into with the Imperial Government for  
     <lb/>the defence of the country, shall be as<lb break="no"/>sumed by the General Government. We  
     <lb/>will have to pay some $105,000 for the 
     <lb/>defence of New Brunswick during the 
     <lb/>late danger of a Fenian raid. In regard 
     <lb/>to the opening up of the North West 
     <lb/>Territory, there have been no arrange<lb break="no"/>ments made. The Hudson Bay Com<lb break="no"/>pany have bought that territory, and have 
     <lb/>£500,000 worth of property there, and 
     <lb/>those people will contribute not to the 
     <lb/>revenue of Canada, but to the revenue of 
     <lb/>the Union. He says that after communi<lb break="no"/>cating with Mr. Galt, he was satisfied that 
     <lb/>there could be little or no change made 
     <lb/>in the Quebec Scheme. I entertain a 
     <lb/>different view. I would have been will<lb break="no"/>ing to go into Union upon the terms 
     <lb/>named, but a large number of the people  
     <lb/>of New Brunswick think we should have 
     <lb/>a better scheme, and I am willing and 
     <lb/>anxious that we should get the best terms 
     <lb/>we can. He says that after a conversa<lb break="no"/>tion he had with Mr. Galt and Mr. How<lb break="no"/>land at Washington, he came to the 
     <lb/>conclusion that no changes could be 
     <lb/>made. Then I claim him an advocate 
     <lb/>for the Quebec Scheme. How was it 
     <lb/>that after he came back he had a confer<lb break="no"/>ence with His Excellency and agreed to 
     <lb/>go into Union. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—I told His Excellency 
     <lb/>
     that I was opposed to the Quebec Scheme. 
     <lb/>
     The correspondence explains how far I 
     <lb/>
     was in favour of Union, and I never com<lb break="no"/>mitted myself to any Scheme. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>—I will read from 
     <lb/>
     the Debates : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     We also discussed the question as to 
     <lb/>
     whether it had better be a joint commit<lb break="no"/>tee of both Houses or seperate committees 
     <lb/>
     of each. He told |me at one of our in<lb break="no"/>terviews that he thought he would go to 
     <lb/>
     Canada. When I saw him again, I think 
     <lb/>
     the next day, I asked him it he had de<lb break="no"/>termined to go to Canada ; he replied 
     <lb/>
     that he had, and asked me what objec<lb break="no"/>tions I had to the Quebec Scheme, and 
     <lb/>
     said that he would try and ascertain when 
     <lb/>
     there what modifications they would make. 
     <lb/>
     He rose and took the Journals of 1865, 
     <lb/>
     containing the Scheme, and I proceeded 
     <lb/>
     to enumerate the following as some of 
     <lb/>
     the objections, viz : 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>1. Representation by Population.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>2. That each Province should have an 
     <lb/>equal number of Legislative Councillors. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>3. That the Lower Provinces should be 
     <lb/>exempt from taxation for the Canals of 
     <lb/>
       

            <pb n="36" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_036.jpg"/>
          
<fw type="num">36</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>
         


Upper Canada, and for the purchase mo<lb break="no"/>ney and other expenditures connected<lb/>with the North West Territory.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>4. That the Revenues collected in the<lb/>different Provinces should be for the ben<lb break="no"/>efit of each Province when collected, ex<lb break="no"/>cept a certain amount to be given for<lb/>the support of the General Government.<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>Here was an understanding had with<lb/>His Excellency immediately after his re<lb break="no"/>turn from Washington. When His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency put the acceptance of Mr. Wil<lb break="no"/>mot's resignation on the grounds of<lb/>Union, he (Mr. Smith) told him that he<lb/>would go and consult his friends and col<lb break="no"/>leagues upon the question of Union.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I never was to consult<lb/>my friends with regard to Union. I was<lb/>to consult my friends as to whether they<lb/>would consent that a Select Committee<lb/>should be appointed to take the subject<lb/>into consideration after the despatches<lb/>had been laid before the House. They<lb/>were to take the whole subject into<lb/>consideration, and make such sugges<lb break="no"/>tions as they thought proper. I stated<lb/>distinctly in the House that we had no<lb/>Union policy to submit to the House.<lb/>This the Governor knew well, and so<lb/>did every member of the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>—I think if you<lb/>were to poll the country North and<lb/>South on this question of whether<lb/>the late Attorney General had commit<lb break="no"/>ted himself to Union or not, there<lb/>would not be one in fifty but would say<lb/>that he had.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—That impression has<lb/>been created by speeches which have<lb/>been made not founded on fact.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>—I will take the<lb/>Speech and the Address in answer to<lb/>the Speech as evidence.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—The Government in pre<lb break="no"/>paring that Speech did not commit<lb/>themselves to Union. The Governor<lb/>wanted us to put in something that<lb/>would have committed us, but we did<lb/>not. The Governor did not pretend to<lb/>say that we were committed to Union.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>—Then we have<lb/>no constitution in this country. It is the<lb/>opinion of every one who knows any<lb break="no"/>thing about Responsible Government<lb/>that they were committed to Union.<lb/>Some years ago the Governor had a<lb/>despatch from the Colonial Office which<lb/>he wished referred to in the Speech.<lb/>The Government objected to refer to it,<lb/>because it would make them responsi<lb break="no"/>ble, and they waited upon His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency, and had it struck out. This<lb/>Union was also referred to in the Ad<lb break="no"/>dress in answer to the Speech, which<lb/>was moved by Mr. Boyd, a representa<lb break="no"/>tive from Charlotte. In that it is stated<lb/>that any measure for Union submitted<lb/>to the House should receive attention.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—It is not any measure<lb/>submitted to the House. It is any<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
    

measure that should be proposed. I<lb/>want the Secretary, when he quotes<lb/>from these records, to read them.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>—Is there any dif<lb break="no"/>ference whether they used the word<lb/>propose or submit ? The way they<lb/>dealt with the subject was enough to<lb/>destroy any Government. To throw the<lb/>question upon a Committee with the un<lb break="no"/>derstanding that they should report fa<lb break="no"/>vorably when the hon. and learned mem<lb break="no"/>ber would be in a position to brow-beat<lb/>every member.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—I will not take such  
     <lb/>
    insinuations, for they are false. That 
     <lb/>language is unparliamentery. I have 
     <lb/>ever treated this House in a respectful 
     <lb/>manner.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>—If what he says 
     <lb/>was correct that at Washington he was<lb/>told by members of the Canadian Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment that no important change could<lb/>be made in the Scheme, what position<lb/>would he occupy entering into a nego<lb break="no"/>tiation for a change, when he was told<lb/>no change could be made ? I do not<lb/>want to create any ill-feeling, but I<lb/>want to put the matter just as I under<lb break="no"/>stand it. Was it treating His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency with candour to negotiate for<lb/>changes when he knew those changes<lb/>could not be made. I think they can<lb/>be made. When I read the cor<lb break="no"/>respondence relative to the resigna<lb break="no"/>tion of Mr. Wilmot, I felt the blood<lb/>rushing to my cheek to hear his mo<lb break="no"/>tives impugned—to hear them say that<lb/>they never heard him say anything about<lb/>Union until he went to Canada. But to<lb/>come down further in Mr. Smith's speech.<lb/>He says :<lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     The Council met at Fredericton about 
     <lb/>the third of March. His Excellency in<lb/>the meantime had returned from Canada.<lb/>He told me that he had seen Lord Monck<lb/>and some of the members of the Cana<lb break="no"/>dian Government, and he said he thought<lb/>they would be willing to make conces<lb break="no"/>sions.<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>This was after Mr. Smith had been told<lb/>that no concessions would be made.<lb/>Therefore there is some chance of get<lb break="no"/>ting concessions. I have taken up every<lb/>objection referred to by the ex-Attorney<lb/>General. I have taken up the finances<lb/>and shown that in Union with a uniform<lb/>tariff New Brunswick will not pay more,<lb/>if not as much, duties as other parts of Brit<lb break="no"/>ish North America, because we do not<lb/>consume as many dutiable goods. It<lb/>will give us more money for local pur<lb break="no"/>poses. It will secure the construction of<lb/>the Intercolonial Railway. $9,000,000 of<lb/>the money necessary to build this Rail<lb break="no"/>way will be expended in New Brunswick<lb/>thereby developing the resources of the<lb/>country. It gives us $1,400,000 for<lb/>Railway Extension, without costing us a<lb/>cent more than we paid in 1864. It<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
        

was these facts known by the great bulk<lb/>of the people that caused them to go for<lb/>Confederation. If the population of<lb/>Kent Westmorland, and Gloucester had<lb/>been a reading people, we would not have<lb/>had the pleasure of seeing some of the<lb/>hon. gentlemen who represent those<lb/>Counties, here in opposition to the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. They have been returned<lb/>because the French do not read as much<lb/>as the English population. The press<lb/>does not have the same influence upon<lb/>them, and public opinion does not reach<lb/>them.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     The late Attorney General comes here 
     <lb/>
     and appeals to the House upon this ques<lb break="no"/>tion, and tells the members that if they 
     <lb/>
     invest so much power in the delegates 
     <lb/>they cannot go back to their constituents<lb/>and say they have done their duty. I doubt<lb/>whether the leader of the Opposition—the<lb/>great anti-Confederate, now a Unionist,<lb/>can lead them astray. There are a thou<lb break="no"/>sand reasons why he should not, although<lb/>he has made some suggestions which may<lb/>be acted upon. The country has declared<lb/>against him both with reference to<lb/>his administration of the Government,<lb/>and with reference to his policy on this<lb/>question. A more inconsistent politician<lb/>does not live in New Brunswick. When<lb/>he was in the Government of which I was<lb/>a member we constructed a railway but<lb/>when he went out of the Government there<lb/>was not a man who denounced his own act<lb/>with as much power and force as he did.<lb/>When a proposition was before the House<lb/>to provide for the extension of our rail<lb break="no"/>ways, he opposed it, and said £200 a day<lb/>was sent out of the Province as interest,<lb/>and the country could not bear it ; but<lb/>now he says build these extensions and<lb/>our railway will pay six cent. His vote<lb/>is recorded against the Subsidy Act, but<lb/>he has put those extensions through and<lb/>even in one respect exceeded the autho<lb break="no"/>rity given him by law. He brought in<lb/>an Act to appropriate $10,000 for Mili<lb break="no"/>tary purposes when he was in the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and when out of it he voted that<lb/>that money should not be appropriated<lb/>for that purpose, but should be given to<lb/>the bye-roads. The next year he comes<lb/>in and asks for $30,000, for military<lb/>purposes, and is there not a letter pub<lb break="no"/>lished in which he tells us that after<lb/>Union with Canada we will have to heep<lb/>up an army and navy, and yet he came<lb/>down to the House when a member of the<lb/>Government and asked for a navy. He<lb/>is now a Unionist, although a short time<lb/>ago he was against any Union with the Ca<lb break="no"/>nadas. Great as may be his abilities he is<lb/>more successful when he is seeking to<lb/>break down, than when he is endeavoring<lb/>to build up. He is endeavouring to<lb/>delay this question with the hope that<lb/>something might possibly grow out of the<lb/>delay.<lb/>
            </p>


            <pb n="37" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_037.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">37</fw> 
   

   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—Is the thing in that state 
     <lb/>that it cannot stand the delay of a few<lb/>hours.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     
     
     
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">HON. Mr. TILLEY</persName>—The proposition 
     <lb/>
    is not for a delay of a few hours but for 
     <lb/>a delay which will render it impossible 
     <lb/>for that Act to come into the present Im<lb break="no"/>perial Parliament. The object of the pro<lb break="no"/>position is that it shall come back and be 
     <lb/>confirmed by the people before it goes to 
     <lb/>Parliament, with the hope that a Euro<lb break="no"/>pean war, .or a change of ministry might 
     <lb/>delay or defeat it, or that it might come 
     <lb/>into other hands to carry it out, so that it 
     <lb/>could be moulded and shaped to suit the 
     <lb/>purposes of those who are now in the Op<lb break="no"/>position.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
    

            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—Do you expect the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment will break down ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">HON. Mr. TILLEY</persName>—We do not. If 
     <lb/>
     we were to act as the late Government 
     <lb/>
     acted we would soon break down. We 
     <lb/>
     have made up our minds that when 
     <lb/>
    changes are to be made we will make 
     <lb/> them. I will not say as my hon. and 
     <lb/>learned friend said to me after we were 
     <lb/>defeated—" Tilley we have got you by 
     <lb/>the hair of the head for four years," for I 
     <lb/>do not consider it a party victory, but a 
     <lb/>national one.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—If any man says anything 
     <lb/>
     in a joke is it to be brought up in a seri<lb break="no"/>ous debate. I have no recollection of 
     <lb/>making this remark at all. If I did he 
     <lb/>must have understood it to be in a joke. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>—I was not speak<lb break="no"/>ing of it seriously. He asked me if I 
     <lb/>was afraid the Government would break 
     <lb/>down, and that remark brought it up. 
     <lb/>We are not going to make it a personal 
     <lb/>conflict, for it is a national question, 
     <lb/>inasmuch as the people of this country 
     <lb/>have felt that their connection with the 
     <lb/>British Empire depended upon this 
     <lb/>question. Canada is for it, and Nova 
     <lb/>Scotia is for it, and this brings to my 
     <lb/>mind a statement made by the ex-Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General that there was hope for them 
     <lb/>yet, and the hope was that the Imperial 
     <lb/>Parliament, when Mr. Howe appears be<lb break="no"/>fore them, will not consent to pass this 
     <lb/>Scheme. Whatever may be said in re<lb break="no"/>ference to the policy of Canada in this 
     <lb/>matter, I should like to know from him if, 
     <lb/>when he was in England, he heard any 
     <lb/>expression of dissatisfaction on the part 
     <lb/>of the British Government that it had 
     <lb/> passed through the Canadian Legislature 
     <lb/>without being left for the approval of the 
     <lb/>people. Did Mr. Cardwell say it could 
     <lb/>not be passed in the Imperial Parliament 
     <lb/>until the people of Upper Canada had 
     <lb/>passed upon it. Whatever may be the 
     <lb/>policy in Nova Scotia in regard to the 
     <lb/>question, it is perfectly constitutional. I 
     <lb/>have no doubt of the course the Imperial 
     <lb/>Parliament will pursue, even though 
     <lb/>Mr. Howe present all the arguments of 
     <lb/>which he is capable. It was thought<lb/>
     

            <cb/>
          

     a majority of the people of this country 
     <lb/>that if they did not go into Confederation<lb/>Annexation would follow. Those who<lb/>have been engaged in negotiating for the<lb/>extension of the trade of British North<lb/>America, know that peculiar difficulties<lb/>exist when negotiating out of Union,<lb/>compared with the facilities which would<lb/>exist in negotiating when united. It has<lb/>been said that the Reciprocity Treaty<lb/>could not be renewed with the United<lb/>States, because a large portion of the<lb/>members of Congress and members of<lb/>the Senate thought it was only necessary<lb/>to cripple the trade of British North Am<lb break="no"/>erica to bring about Annexation. Will<lb/>we not let them know that we are for<lb/>Union, and that our intention is to in<lb break="no"/>crease the power of the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. We are not as likely to have difficul<lb break="no"/>ty with the Fenians as if we had gone<lb/>against Union, because if we had gone<lb/>against Union, the opinion of the people<lb/>of the United States would have been that<lb/>we were in favor of annexation, and we<lb/>would have had hordes of men down here,<lb/>and had difficulties which will not now<lb/>exist, because the moral effect of this<lb/>Union is, that both the whole power of<lb/>the British Government and the whole<lb/>force of the nation will be put forth to<lb/>maintain our integrity. The people have<lb/>spoken emphatically that they desire this<lb/>Union to be consummated, and their re<lb break="no"/>presentatives will not accept any propo<lb break="no"/>sition to delay this Union, but knowing<lb/>the principles upon which they were el<lb break="no"/>ected, they will speak the opinions of the<lb/>electors who sent them here.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BABB1">Mr. BABBIT</persName>.—I shall take up very<lb/>few moments, for the subject has been<lb/>discussed over and over again, and the<lb/>people of the country have expressed<lb/>their opinion upon it. It would be en<lb break="no"/>tirely out of place for me, even if I had<lb/>the ability, to take up time in reviewing<lb/>it. We are informed that Government<lb/>intend to take the Quebec Scheme as a<lb/>basis, and delegates are to be appointed<lb/>to go to England to get the best terms<lb/>they can. When the subject was<lb/>brought before the people, after the<lb/>Quebec delegates had returned, the first<lb/>objection in our country was represen<lb break="no"/>tation by population, but after this sub<lb break="no"/>ject was ventilated, it was ascertained<lb/>that we could not get anything else, and<lb/>the public mind was directed to ascer<lb break="no"/>tain if a check could not be provided.<lb/>it was believed that an increased re<lb break="no"/>presentation would provide that check,<lb/>and my constituents now ask to have<lb/>the delegates instructed to endeavor to<lb/>secure increased representation in the<lb/>Legislative Council. I agree with the<lb/>remark made by the ex-Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, that if the Legislative Councillors<lb/>appointed to seats at Ottawa are simply<lb/>to have a property qualification here, it<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
    
will not amount to a great deal, because<lb/>some of them would remove to Canada,<lb/>and instead of looking after our interests<lb/>they would be looking after the interest<lb/>of the Canadians, for it is natural to<lb/>suppose that a man would be most in<lb break="no"/>terested in the place in which he re<lb break="no"/>sides. We should instruct our delegates<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     in unmistakable terms, that it should be 
     <lb/>
     provided in the Scheme, that our Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Councillors should both reside 
     <lb/>
     and have their property qualification in 
     <lb/>
     this Province. If this idea is not car<lb break="no"/>ried out I shall think it was the fault of 
     <lb/>
     our delegates and not of the Canadians, 
     <lb/>
     because it is immaterial to them whether 
     <lb/>
     they reside here or there. The next  
     <lb/>
     question the people have mentioned to 
     <lb/>
     me is the eighty cents question ; we feel 
     <lb/>
     that there should be some advance upon 
     <lb/>
     the eighty cents per head. I do not 
     <lb/>
     want this advance to apply to Canada, 
     <lb/>
     let it remain as it is there, but give us 
     <lb/>
     more. I may have narrow views upon 
     <lb/>
     this question, but I say if you increase 
     <lb/>
     it in Canada as well as here we will 
     <lb/>
     have to pay our proportional part of it, 
     <lb/>
     and there will be no gain ; but if you  
     <lb/>
     stop it there and give us the increase 
     <lb/>
     we will gain something. The next 
     <lb/>
     really important question is to define 
     <lb/>
     the action of these two Governments. 
     <lb/>
     I do not believe you can so define the 
     <lb/>
     power but what some little difficulties 
     <lb/>
     will arise, but it should be so defined 
     <lb/>
     that no difficulties should arise which 
     <lb/>
     can be prevented. The delegates should 
     <lb/>
     give that subject every consideration, 
     <lb/>
     so that there may not be a constant tur<lb break="no"/>moil and strife between the two powers. 
     <lb/>
     If we want to prosper, the Legislature 
     <lb/>
     must work in harmony with the General 
     <lb/>
     Government. I cannot agree with the 
     <lb/>
     remarks made by my hon. friend from 
     <lb/>
     Westmorland, (Mr. Smith,) that the 
     <lb/>
     Canadians are prepared to give us 
     <lb/>
     everything rather than not have Con<lb break="no"/>federation, and that we should demand 
     <lb/>
     everything from them. I only ask that 
     <lb/>
     the bargain shall be fair. These are 
     <lb/>
     some of the main things that should be 
     <lb/>
     taken into consideration by the dele<lb break="no"/>gates, and I trust they will go unbiassed 
     <lb/>
     and agree to a Scheme calculated in 
     <lb/>
     their judgment to promote the welfare 
     <lb/>
     of the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> —I am not sorry that 
     <lb/>
     this discussion has taken place upon 
     <lb/>
     this question. I think that if we had 
     <lb/>
     passed the resolution without any dis<lb break="no"/>cussion it would not have been so satis<lb break="no"/>factory to the country. Whether we 
     <lb/>
     adopt the Scheme in its entirety or have 
     <lb/>
     it modified, the country expects a dis<lb break="no"/>cussion to arise to give them informa<lb break="no"/>tion in regard to the details of the 
     <lb/>
     Scheme. Those of us who were re<lb break="no"/>jected fifteen months ago for having 
     <lb/>supported Confederation, now come<lb/>
          

            <pb n="38" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_038.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="num">38</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 
   

from the great battle, and I feel proud<lb/>to take my place here where another<lb/>conflict is going on. If there is one<lb/>man who should feel more proud than<lb/>another, it is that man who from con<lb break="no"/>scious merit, when he sees that the peo<lb break="no"/>ple are running against the views which<lb/>he is conscious are right, takes his<lb/>stand and breasts the tide, and when<lb/>after the lapse of time these people who<lb/>were against him come round and em<lb break="no"/>brace his views, that ought to be the<lb/>proudest day of his life. We come here<lb/>after a conflict with renewed vigor, be<lb break="no"/>cause when this Scheme was rejected<lb/>before, it was enough to daunt the<lb/>hearts of any one, that the ablest men<lb/>in the Province were rejected upon that<lb/>question. These men were strong in<lb/>their belief that this question was sound<lb/>in principle, had truth as its basis, and<lb/>that it must come in and prevail.<lb/>Though the trial might have been<lb/>severe, though you could not see<lb/>through the cloudy vista any ray of the<lb/>sunlight of promise breaking in upon<lb/>that gloom, yet we believed that the<lb/>time would come when if it was a pro<lb break="no"/>per principle it would prevail. "Truth<lb/>crushed to earth will rise again."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>So it is in every question that has taken<lb/>place in history, I refer you to the great<lb/>emancipation of slaves ; when Britain was<lb/>agitated from its centre to its circumfer<lb break="no"/>ence. Still men stood strong in the be<lb break="no"/>lief that Britain would at last accede to the<lb/>justice of their cause and that the mana<lb break="no"/>cles of the manumitted slaves would fall<lb/>powerless to the ground. Need I refer<lb/>to the Reform Bills, and the repeal of the<lb/>Corn Laws. Though they were sup<lb break="no"/>ported only by a few leading men of the<lb/>day, they knew their principles to be<lb/>correct, and their glory was, what we now<lb/>ourselves can experience, when the tide<lb/>of public opinion turned in their favour.<lb/>History in these questions but repeats<lb/>itself, and it is repeating itself at this mo<lb break="no"/>ment. Strange as it may appear, fifteen<lb/>months ago the people rose in their might<lb/>and rejected Union, but now they come<lb/>round and adopt it by large majorities ;<lb/>just as we have seen and experienced in<lb/>past time. Let us enquire for one mo<lb break="no"/>ment into the causes of this change, for<lb/>certainly there must hve been a reason<lb/>for it. Had it been a neck and neck race<lb/>so to speak, then it might have been said<lb/>that those who possessed the greatest<lb/>amount of means and money at their<lb/>command would have had the advantage,<lb/>and by this means accomplished their<lb/>purpose ; but when we find that it was not<lb/>carried by a neck and neck race, but by<lb/>an overwhelming majority, we must be<lb break="no"/>lieve it was because the people had an<lb/>attachment for the institutions of their<lb/>country. Did they adopt a scheme of<lb/>Union which they once rejected. I deny<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
          
that the scheme of Union as such was<lb/>what they rejected. Any why ! Because<lb/>we all know that many of us who had<lb/>taken the Scheme in our hand, wanted<lb/>time to consider it in detail, and how were<lb/>we to expect the people of the country to<lb/>be more ready to understand the Scheme<lb/>than we were. What was the result ?<lb/>The people being frightened, and think<lb break="no"/>ing they were well enough as they were<lb/>took the wisest and best course for them<lb/>to take. That was to reject the Scheme,<lb/>and they did this from the act that it was<lb/>hurriedly brought upon them, and there<lb/>were many of those who were unprinci<lb break="no"/>pled enough to take advantage of that,<lb/>to circulate throughout the country the<lb/>most falacious stories, and taxation was a<lb/>hobby which they rode to death. Our<lb/>hens would be taxed and the very eggs<lb/>they laid would be taxed. They told the<lb/>poor man who had ten children that<lb/>he would have to pay $30 because the<lb/>tax would be three dollars a head ; was<lb/>it to be wondered at that they rejected<lb/>it upon those representations. The cry<lb/>was raised throughout the Province that<lb/>we were going to sell ourselves to Can<lb break="no"/>ada : we were going to be connected with<lb/>a set of political rogues. If all that was<lb/>said about them were true, they would be<lb/>the most horrible people upon the face of<lb/>the earth. We had men among us who<lb/>would go to the humble abode of a poor<lb/>woman, and clap her child upon his head,<lb/>and say, what a pity that son of yours<lb/>will have to be sent to Canada as a sol<lb break="no"/>dier to fight for her defence. One of<lb/>the great reasons brought forth why this<lb/>Scheme should be looked upon with ab<lb break="no"/>horrence was because it was originated<lb/>by designing men who were seeking their<lb/>own aggrandizement, and that Mr. Tilley<lb/>wished to be Governor, and Mr. Gray<lb/>Judge of Appeals. Whilst these things<lb/>were being said, people began to suspect<lb/>the originaors of the crime, and they<lb/>rose up in their wrath and almost desired<lb/>to annihilate them. Such was the fear<lb break="no"/>ful daubing that was given to this<lb/>Scheme, that it has taken fifteen months<lb/>for intelligent men, with all the scrubbing<lb/>brushes they could get together, to wipe<lb/>away the dust from it. The opponents<lb/>of the Scheme said it could not have been<lb/>the wish of Her Majesty that we should<lb/>adopt this Scheme, for we could not put<lb/>our hand upon any despatch to show<lb/>that the Imperial Government desired it.<lb/>It was called the Quebec Scheme, and this<lb/>provided arguments for our opponents,<lb/>simply on account of its name. If it had<lb/>been called the New Brunswick, or the<lb/>Nova Scotia Scheme, it would not have<lb/>met with so much opposition. As it was<lb/>called the Quebec Scheme, they said it<lb/>had its origin and emanated from those<lb/>reckless men in Canada, and people<lb/>looked upon it with suspicion, and said<lb/>
       

            <cb/>
          

if that is the case, we had better remain<lb/>as we are. It was said let well enough<lb/>alone, and it was amusing to find all<lb/>those fossil putrefactions in the shape of<lb/>human beings rise up in those days, and<lb/>take advantage of all the old fogies who<lb/>felt they were well enough as they were,<lb/>in the Province of New Brunswick, as<lb/>hewers of wood and drawers of water,<lb/>and ought to be content with their po<lb break="no"/>sition. I am drawing no picture of fan<lb break="no"/>cy when I say these were some of the<lb/>reasons why the Scheme of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion was rejected. When the people had<lb/>these reasons urged upon them, and be<lb break="no"/>lieved them to be true, it is unfair to<lb/>say that fifteen months ago this Union<lb/>was rejected. I find that fifteen months<lb/>has made a great change in the minds<lb/>of the people. What has been the<lb/>cause of this change ? Within the last<lb/>fifteen months there has been a discus<lb break="no"/>sion within these walls, and printed<lb/>matter circulated throughout the country,<lb/>and people have read for themselves.<lb/>This victory is not one party triumphing<lb/>over another, but it is the noblest<lb/>victory human nature can achieve. It<lb/>is the victory of sound reason and ma<lb break="no"/>ture judgment, that is the triumph that<lb/>does honor to humanity. If the people<lb/>have considered this and given their<lb/>verdict in favor of Union, I say we<lb/>stand here responsible to carry that<lb/>out, and not to allow any delay to take<lb/>place to thwart that great principle. If<lb/>we were to clog the delegates who go<lb/>home with instructions, and require<lb/>them to return and report to the As<lb break="no"/>sembly or people, we might be taking<lb/>what we consider a desirable course if<lb/>practicable, but we would be doing<lb/>what the people did not send us here to<lb/>do, that is, to endanger the passage of<lb/>Union. Let us look at some of the<lb/>other causes which have produced this<lb/>change in the people's minds. We<lb/>know that there is a large revolving<lb/>wheel in the world moving onward, we<lb/>cannot know all the details of what is<lb/>reolving on that revolving wheel. If<lb/>there is anything to be accomplished, at<lb/>the very nick of time when it does come<lb/>round, all the power of man is powerless<lb/>to arrest its force. We are just in that<lb/>position at present, while we might de<lb break="no"/>sire to be let alone, and think we would<lb/>be better off as we are, there is a pres<lb break="no"/>sure of surrounding circumstances that<lb/>impels us to take to the ship, or lie<lb/>down and be destroyed. My hon.<lb/>friend (Mr. Smith) has said the people<lb/>were in a state of political intoxication.<lb/>If that is the case now what were they<lb/>fifteen months ago ? Has it been one<lb/>continual drunk, or has there not been<lb/>time to sober off during the intervals.<lb/>Is it not generally found that when the<lb/>drunk is over that reason returns. He<lb/>
          

            <pb n="39" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_039.jpg"/>
         
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">39</fw>


says again that Fenianism had much to<lb/>do with this change in the people's<lb/>minds. I agree with him. It had much<lb/>to do with it in this way : Mr. Killian<lb/>and his brother would tell the people<lb/>within the neighboring border, that if<lb/>the people of New Brunswick did not<lb/>wish to go into Confederation they had<lb/>only to call upon him, and he was ready<lb/>to come with his band to do the bidding<lb/>of the disaffected. This sunk into the<lb/>hearts of loyal people, and if ever New<lb/>Brunswick did honor to herself, she did<lb/>it when she threw aside all considera<lb break="no"/>tions of mere dollars and cents, and<lb/>said that rather than join herself to<lb/>them, or sail in the same boat with<lb/>those that held their doctrines, she<lb/>would sacrifice a great deal and go in<lb/>for Union under any circumstances. I<lb/>have heard people say, that now the<lb/>elections are over we will hear no more<lb/>of Fenianism in the Province. If we<lb/>do not, its death blow was struck when<lb/>we showed unmistakably that we were<lb/>in favor of Confederation. Another<lb/>reason for this change was the repeal<lb/>of the Reciprocity Treaty. We found<lb/>that we were to be placed at the mercy<lb/>of our neighbors across the border, and<lb/>that our supply of flour and breadstuffs<lb/>might easily be cut off, but if we were<lb/>united we would be independent of<lb/>them. We found that many of those<lb/>people in the Province who had annexa<lb break="no"/>tion proclivities and desires were most<lb/>violently opposed to the Scheme, while<lb/>those who desired to maintain British<lb/>connection were in favor of it. The ex-<lb break="yes"/>Attorney General alludes to back-stairs<lb/>influence in carrying these elections,<lb/>and speaks of what he calls the<lb/>treachery and unconstitutional conduct<lb/>of the Governor. Any man who brings<lb/>a charge against the Queen's represen<lb break="no"/>tative ought to see that his own gar<lb break="no"/>ments are perfectly clear. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment found they must adopt a Union<lb/>policy or resign their seats. When that<lb/>confidential memorandum came out, we<lb/>found that the Government had had<lb/>several communications with the then<lb/>Premier of the Government, and that<lb/>His Excellency was desirous of espress<lb break="no"/>ing his views on Union at the opening<lb/>of the House. This correspondence<lb/>discloses what the policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was, that these despatches were<lb/>to be submitted to a Committee who<lb/>were to report in favor of Union. The<lb/>Government did not desire to take the<lb/>responsibility upon their own shoulders,<lb/>but that they might more easily effect<lb/>their purpose and relieve themselves<lb/>from embarrassments, they were going<lb/>to throw the responsibility upon the<lb/>House. They call themselves constitu<lb break="no"/>tionalists, because they say the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor acted in an unconstitutional manner<lb/>
           

            <cb/>
         

     in not consulting with his Council. If 
     <lb/>he had consulted his Council, and they<lb/>had not endorsed his reply to the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Council, they would have had to<lb/>resign, and His Excellency would have<lb/>had to diasolve the House in conse<lb break="no"/>quence ; but if they had endorsed it,<lb/>this Union policy would have been car<lb break="no"/>ried out, and the leader of the late<lb/>Government would have received honor<lb/>for it. When Sir Robert Peel, who<lb/>occupied a high position at home, found<lb/>it necessary to alter his policy, and<lb/>stood forth ready to sacrifice place,<lb/>power, and position for the time being,<lb/>conscious of his own rectitude, there<lb/>never was a time when he stood higher<lb/>as a statesman than when he came<lb/>manly forth with no covered scheme<lb/>and no desire to shirk responsibility,<lb/>but took it upon himself, with a few<lb/>followers, to advocate his changed<lb/>policy. Had this been the policy of the<lb/>late Attorney General, there is no doubt<lb/>but that he would have made himself<lb/>one of the foremost men in the Province ;<lb/>but instead of this he adopted what<lb/>might be termed a cowardly policy.<lb/>We came here not to act in that cow<lb break="no"/>ardly spirit, but determined to advocate<lb/>Union, and to carry out the principle of<lb/>Union in all its integrity. We have<lb/>been cautioned to act with solemnity,<lb/>and not to surrender our judgment to<lb/>the guidance of others. I think it was<lb/>scarcely necessary to ask us not to<lb/>surrender our judgment and follow a<lb/>leader who would leave us wan<lb break="no"/>dering in an inconsistent path,<lb/>one who was opposed to this<lb/>
    Scheme of Union, and whose policy 
     <lb/>was a  vacilating policy. We will 
     <lb/>follow these statesmen on the floors of 
     <lb/>the House who have been an honor to 
     <lb/>the country, and the country have honor<lb break="no"/>ed them, and are only climbing that steep 
     <lb/>ascent where their names shall rest when<lb/>they are no more. We are told that our<lb/>Local Legislatures will dwindle away.<lb/>Are we to remain as we are, and never<lb/>increase in population ? Has it not been<lb/>shown that there would be very few bills<lb/>that we would not still have to discuss<lb/>here ? Suppose our Local Legislature 
     <lb/>were to fall into comparative insignifi<lb break="no"/>cance, must we sacrifice this grand idea 
     <lb/>for the sake of a Local Legislature ? 
     <lb/>Are we to sacrifice the interests of three 
     <lb/>millions of people for the sake of a Lo<lb break="no"/>cal Legislature. All we want of it is to 
     <lb/>manage the affairs of the Province. It 
     <lb/>was said that the Legislative Councillors 
     <lb/>would reside in Canada. Could they 
     <lb/>imagine that men with a property qualifi<lb break="no"/>cation of $4000 would remove to Canada<lb/>and reside among men whom they termed<lb/>French Canadians and reckless and cor<lb break="no"/>rupt politicians. A man would not take<lb/>all his equipage and remove to Ottawa<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
   

     for the sake of being there three months<lb/>with a paltry salary of about £250.  
     <lb/>
    There is another objection made to the 
     <lb/>Scheme which really has much force in it. 
     <lb/>It is said we should have an increased 
     <lb/>representation in the Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cil. This, if it can be obtained, would 
     <lb/>provide the necessary cheeks against any 
     <lb/>action taken in the Lower House detri<lb break="no"/>mental to our interest ; but as it is, the 
     <lb/>terms are more favorable to New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick than to Canada, because, according 
     <lb/>to population, we have two representa<lb break="no"/>tives  in the Upper House to Canada's 
     <lb/>one. It is said that in the United States 
     <lb/>each State sends an equal number of re<lb break="no"/>presentatives to the Upper House, and  
     <lb/>that it should be the same here. The 
     <lb/>Senate of the United States exercises the 
     <lb/>functions of an executive body, and there<lb break="no"/>fore the same reasons for an equal repre<lb break="no"/>sentation does not apply here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Were we elected to support Union in 
     <lb/>
     the abstract, or Union under the basis of 
     <lb/>
     the Quebec Scheme, hoping to get im<lb break="no"/>provements ? The main question which 
     <lb/>
    agitated the minds of the people of New  
     <lb/>Brunswick was this : was  it Imperial 
     <lb/>policy ? If we cast our vote, will we not 
     <lb/>be casting our vote for or against that 
     <lb/>policy ?  The people believed the Queen 
     <lb/>and the British nation desired it, and they 
     <lb/>said they would not cast their votes 
     <lb/>against the policy of the British Empire, 
     <lb/>lest the construction might be put upon 
     <lb/>it that they were disloyal to the British 
     <lb/>Crown. The cry has been raised through<lb break="no"/>out the country that the Quebec Scheme 
     <lb/>was not a good Scheme. Many people 
     <lb/>said they would agree to Union, but 
     <lb/>could not agree to the Quebec Scheme, 
     <lb/>and when I asked them to point out their 
     <lb/>objections to it they could not do it. 
     <lb/>This was an easy way of letting them<lb break="no"/>selves down; they had formerly opposed all 
     <lb/>Union, and now they would go for Union 
     <lb/>but would oppose the Quebec Scheme. 
     <lb/>They do this because they think it de<lb break="no"/>grading to change their views. Why 
     <lb/>should a man be always crying out against 
     <lb/>a building when he has the power to re<lb break="no"/>move it, and build better superstructure 
     <lb/>if he can. Any fool can cry down but it 
     <lb/>is the part of a wise men to build up. If 
     <lb/>the ex-premier does not like the Scheme 
     <lb/>why does he not bring in a better. If he 
     <lb/>would bring in a Scheme we should  bind 
     <lb/>it round with silks and ribbons, and crown 
     <lb/>it with a high cocked hat. If he would 
     <lb/>only bring it in and present it as his first<lb break="no"/>born, in the present emergency we would 
     <lb/>render it due obeisance. It may show 
     <lb/>itself but until, it comes we will take the 
     <lb/>liberty of dealing with the one we have. 
     <lb/>We have been told that if we went for 
     <lb/>this Scheme of Union we would be cut<lb break="no"/>ting the last connecting link which binds 
     <lb/>us to the mother country. If it is sim<lb break="no"/>ply the appointment of our Lieutenant 
     <lb/>
        

            <pb n="40" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_040.jpg"/>
           

     <fw type="num">40</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 


     Governor that binds us to the British 
     <lb/>
     Crown our connection must be weak in<lb break="no"/>deed The ex-premier would have had 
     <lb/>
     no objections to have had a Governor ap<lb break="no"/>pointed even from our own Province, for 
     <lb/>
      it would have relieved him from embaras<lb break="no"/>sing difficulties, having come in contact 
     <lb/>with the present Governor.  The Gover<lb break="no"/>nor-General will still be appointed by the 
     <lb/> Home Government and the Local Gover<lb break="no"/>nors will be appointed by him. How 
     <lb/>easy it is to raise the warning voice—to 
     <lb/>act upon people's sympathies, and even 
     <lb/>frighten them out of their very senses. 
     <lb/>The eloquent voice and the deep tone will 
     <lb/> affect the heart and reach even the under<lb break="no"/>standing. I am told that the reason given 
     <lb/>for this warning is, that we will bitterly 
     <lb/>regret our adoption of this Scheme which 
     <lb/>is fraught with ruin to our country. Is 
     <lb/>he certain of this ? Has he lived so in 
     <lb/>the future as to know it. True he is jus<lb break="no"/>tified on the floors of the House in doing 
     <lb/>all he can to frustrate what he believes to 
     <lb/>be fraught with ruin to the country. But 
     <lb/>whilst he believes this measure to be at<lb break="no"/>tended with such disastrous consequen<lb break="no"/>ces, it has occurred to me that instead 
     <lb/>of regretting the action now taking place, 
     <lb/>the time is not distant when the people of 
     <lb/>this Province will praise the men who 
     <lb/>aided in raising this mighty fabric. Why 
     <lb/> is it that it looms so brightly in the future, 
     <lb/> and has a response in every heart that de<lb break="no"/>sires to see the country rise from its state 
     <lb/>of isolation. It is because we are to 
     <lb/>have free intercourse in commercial com<lb break="no"/>modities ; and having our mines, miner<lb break="no"/>als and all that make a country great, is 
     <lb/>there not reason for any one to judge that 
     <lb/>what has taken place in other countries 
     <lb/>will take place in our own, when that<lb/>Union takes place. Is it to be wonder<lb break="no"/>ed at that in our isolated position the<lb/>country does not grow as rapidly as other<lb/>countries. Our manufacturers will<lb/>tell you they want a larger market. I need<lb/>not enter into this subject which has been<lb/>travelled over so often and so well.<lb/>I ask this House should we not consum<lb break="no"/>mate that Union immediately ? Why<lb/>should be delay when we have been sent<lb/>here for that purpose ? We should go<lb/>for Union as speedily as possible, and<lb/>endeavor to get the best terms we can.<lb/>Who are to be the Delegates ? I trust<lb/>they will be men true to their trust, car<lb break="no"/>rying out the wishes of the people, ex<lb break="no"/>pressed through their representatives,<lb/>and endeavor to get a larger representa<lb break="no"/>tion in the Legislative Council, and as<lb/>many other improvements as possible, but<lb/>I for one, on behalf of my constituents,<lb/>say that if by insisting upon them, you<lb/>fail in obtaining a Scheme, then abandon<lb/>your insistance and go for the Quebec<lb/>Scheme. I will refer for one moment to<lb/>what is said about Canada ; it has been<lb/>called a bankrupt country, and then again<lb/>
          
    
            <cb/>
     

     we have been told that the Canadians 
     <lb/>
     have given $50 a head to every Fenian 
     <lb/>
     that came to our borders, in order to aid 
     <lb/>
     the Confederate cause. I heard an elec<lb break="no"/>tion story, wherein  it was urged that 
     <lb/>
     we should  not go into Confederation 
     <lb/>
     because Canada was a poor country, 
     <lb/>
     and contained more fiddles than 
     <lb/>ploughs. We find that the agricultural<lb/>
    implements of Canada is more than suf<lb break="no"/>ficient to pay the debts of the Lower 
     <lb/>Provinces. It is a country that will 
     <lb/>draw the weaker Provinces towards it, 
     <lb/>and give strength to them. The geo<lb break="no"/>graphical lines of distinction between 
     <lb/>the Provinces will be swept away, and 
     <lb/>we shall be amalgamated as one people. 
     <lb/>We shall all be bound together, so that 
     <lb/>if you touch the smallest member of the 
     <lb/>body the heart will feel the throb, and 
     <lb/>send forth all its power to protect it. 
     <lb/>We look with ardent hope for the estab<lb break="no"/>lishment of this glorious Empire, whose 
     <lb/>greatness shall be measured only by 
     <lb/>comparison, and who in a few short 
     <lb/>years shall rival the parent stem from 
     <lb/>which it sprung.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr. HIBBARD</persName>—I intend to vote 
     <lb/>
     against the amendment. This is a mea<lb break="no"/>sure that rises above all party consider<lb break="no"/>ations. All party lines should be oblit<lb break="no"/>erated, and every man should come 
     <lb/>
     here to help in every reasonable way 
     <lb/>
     he can to bring about a measure so well 
     <lb/>
     calculated to promote the general good. 
     <lb/>If the Delegates from the different Provin<lb break="no"/>ces were here we might have some altera<lb break="no"/>tions made ; but I think it would be 
     <lb/>
     asking too much to ask three million 
     <lb/>
     people to do just as we say. I had the 
     <lb/>
     opinion that the Constitution agreed 
     <lb/>
    upon by the Delegates should not be 
     <lb/>finally consummated until it had been 
     <lb/>submitted to the Legislature, but I think 
     <lb/>now that as the people have decided in 
     <lb/>favor of  Confederation, and ask that a 
     <lb/>constitution may be consummated, it 
     <lb/>would be unwise to delay the matter by 
     <lb/>such a course. There is a difference of 
     <lb/>opinion on this question between two 
     <lb/>of the ablest speakers in the Province, 
     <lb/>and their arguments confuse my mind, 
     <lb/>for I am not as well versed in the work<lb break="no"/>ings of that Scheme as I ought to be. 
     <lb/>My hon. friend from Westmorland (Mr. 
     <lb/>Smith) says the object of Canada is to 
     <lb/>get the Lower Provinces into connec<lb break="no"/>tion with them in order that their reve<lb break="no"/>nue may be applied to the improve<lb break="no"/>ment of the canals of Canada. I 
     <lb/>think that when we enter into Confede<lb break="no"/>ration the Canals and Railroads of Ca<lb break="no"/>nada will belong as much to New 
     <lb/>Brunswick as they will to Canada. I 
     <lb/>believe the day is not far distant when 
     <lb/>from the first of May until the last of 
     <lb/>September the working capacity of the 
     <lb/> Canals of Canada and the Intercolonial 
     <lb/>Railroad will be taxed to the fullest ex<lb break="no"/>
       

            <cb/>
           
tent. I say New Brunswick ought to 
     <lb/>
     bear its portion of the tax necessary 
     <lb/>
     for the general improvement of British 
     <lb/>
     North America. I have made this a 
     <lb/>
    matter of calculation, and have not  
     <lb/>come blindfolded into the Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion Scheme. I have looked at too vast 
     <lb/>opening that lies before us in the con<lb break="no"/>summation of this Union, and asked  
     <lb/>myself what benefit will it be to New 
     <lb/>Brunswick. I look around, and see 
     <lb/>our public domain teeming with the 
     <lb/>treasures of the forest, the vast mineral 
     <lb/>wealth, the fisheries, and the agricultu<lb break="no"/>ral capabilities of the Province, and I 
     <lb/>say that entering into Union would de<lb break="no"/>velop those resources and increase our 
     <lb/>wealth. Under Union we would ad<lb break="no"/>vance more rapidly in science and liter<lb break="no"/>ature, in railroads and telegraphs, 
     <lb/>in civilization and religion, than 
     <lb/>we do at present. I believe that 
     <lb/>when the General Assembly meets 
     <lb/>at Ottawa they will not infringe 
     <lb/>the rights of New Brunswick, for 
     <lb/>we will form one people, and our interest 
     <lb/>will be their interest. We will start in 
     <lb/>the race of national greatness, and go out 
     <lb/>to the world as competitors with those 
     <lb/>who will compete with us. I feel a diffi<lb break="no"/>dence in addressing this Assembly, for I 
     <lb/>have not the necessary legislative educa<lb break="no"/>tion, or legal knowledge, that the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the profession have, but I do not 
     <lb/>envy them. I am going to vote for the 
     <lb/>appointment of delegates  to meet with 
     <lb/>other delegates, and I hope they will 
     <lb/>never leave London until they have set<lb break="no"/>tled the constitution of this Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. My hon. friends who oppose this 
     <lb/>Scheme are going to shake off the respon<lb break="no"/>sibility but at the same they will reap all 
     <lb/>the benefits. This is a very comfortable 
     <lb/>position to be placed in, and if we should 
     <lb/>err how nicely they can take the advan<lb break="no"/>tage of us. If we should unfortunately 
     <lb/>commit an error, it will be a fearful one. 
     <lb/>I will not take the responsibility of it, but 
     <lb/>will throw it back upon my constituents. 
     <lb/>Though I endorse their sentiments they 
     <lb/>have an equal responsibility. But pre<lb break="no"/>suming the constitution is made, will 
     <lb/>there never be a means of amending it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—The American Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion has a provision for amendment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr. HIBBARD</persName>—Perhaps the dele<lb break="no"/>gates will see that a provision for that is 
     <lb/>
     inserted in ours. It has been said that 
     <lb/>
     Fenianism has had something to do with 
     <lb/>
     the result of the elections. I believe it 
     <lb/>
     has, but if this Fenian excitement had not 
     <lb/>
     occurred we would still have had a ma<lb break="no"/>jority. Am I colouring the picture too 
     <lb/>
     highly when I say that thousands of the 
     <lb/>
     surplus population of Europe will be glad 
     <lb/>
     to find a home in British North America, 
     <lb/>
     and at the end of  eighty-eight years is it 
     <lb/>
     unreasonable to suppose that our popu<lb break="no"/>lation would be 20,00,000. If a man 
     <lb/>
         

            <pb n="41" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-28_Page_041.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">41</fw> 
 

     had said eighty-eight years ago that the 
     <lb/>
     neighboring republic would have been 
     <lb/>
     what it is now, he would have been 
     <lb/>
     stamped as a fanatic. Would New 
     <lb/>
     York ever have stood in the rank of 
     <lb/>
     cities which she now does, if it had 
     <lb/>
     not been for the great western coun<lb break="no"/>try ? If we can get these inland lines, 
     <lb/>and compete for a portion of that trade, 
     <lb/>and pass it through our canals and from 
     <lb/>thence to Britain will it make any differ<lb break="no"/>ence to us if the tolls go into the Cana<lb break="no"/>dian revenue. The Welland Canal a year 
     <lb/>or two ago after paying working expenses 
     <lb/>yielded $200,000 revenue to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. I think Canada will  reap no more 
     <lb/>from us than we will from them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. BOTSFORD</persName>.—The hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man who proceded me has said, that in 
     <lb/>speaking on a subject of such vital im<lb break="no"/>portance to the country, we should di<lb break="no"/>vest ourselves of party  spirit and party 
     <lb/>feelings. It would be desirable not to 
     <lb/>have such observations made in the 
     <lb/>course of this discussion as were made 
     <lb/>with reference to my hon colleagues in 
     <lb/>the late Government and mysel f; when 
     <lb/>he applies to that  body the word 
     <lb/>treachery, he may be familiar with the 
     <lb/>epithet, but I think it more applicable 
     <lb/>to his political actions and the actions 
     <lb/>of the late Government, of which he 
     <lb/>formed a part. The late Government, 
     <lb/>of which I was a member. acted both 
     <lb/>politically and sociably a fair, honora<lb break="no"/>ble course with the Governor, and they 
     <lb/>treated him with respect and courtesy. 
     <lb/>I have yet to learn that when His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency  chooses to enter the arena of 
     <lb/>the public press and brand  his Council 
     <lb/>with feloniously pilfering a paper from 
     <lb/>the archives of the Council, that they 
     <lb/>have not a right to hurl that imputation 
     <lb/>back, no matter how high the source it 
     <lb/>comes from. I would be wanting the 
     <lb/>the feelings of a man, if I did not reply 
     <lb/>to so gross an imputation. As the 
     <lb/>previous speakers have chosen to take 
     <lb/>ground that the late Executive 
     <lb/>Council have acted with treachery in 
     <lb/>their intercourse with the Lieutenant- 
     <lb break="yes"/>Governor, I will draw the attention of 
     <lb/>the House to a few preliminary facts. 
     <lb/>The Provincial Secretary told us that 
     <lb/>we, in endorsing the answer to the ad<lb break="no"/>dress of the Legislative Council, bound 
     <lb/>ourselves to a Union policy, and that it 
     <lb/>made no matter whether the Governor 
     <lb/>consulted us or not, he was justified in 
     <lb/>answering the address of the Legislative 
     <lb/>Council, praying tor the Imperial Par<lb break="no"/>liament to pass an Act for Union based 
     <lb/>upon the Quebec Scheme. If I under<lb break="no"/>stand the Constitution of the country, it 
     <lb/>is simply this, that when the Governor 
     <lb/>speaks on behalf of Her Majesty the 
     <lb/>Queen, or with reference to the Im<lb break="no"/>perial policy, it is not binding upon the 
     <lb/>Executive of the Province, but if he 
     <lb/>


            <cb/>
     

     chooses to speak on behalf of himself or  
     <lb/>
    his Government, then the Executive 
     <lb/>Council become responsible, under our 
     <lb/>Constitution, for what he says. In the 
     <lb/>first reply to the Legislative Council he 
     <lb/>speaks on behalf of Her Majesty, but 
     <lb/>in the second reply he speaks on behalf 
     <lb/>of himself, and makes his Government 
     <lb/>responsible when there was no need 
     <lb/>for his doing so, for the address was for 
     <lb/>the Queen and not an address to the 
     <lb/>Governor at all. I am accused of pur<lb break="no"/>loining a paper. ( <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Speaker</persName>.—The 
     <lb/>Governor is not responsible for what 
     <lb/>he says ) If the Governor chooses in 
     <lb/>the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Royal Gazette</hi> to blacken my char<lb break="no"/>acter and parade his name, not in con<lb break="no"/>nection with his Executive Council, I 
     <lb/>think I have a right to make use of 
     <lb/>such language as will clear my skirts. 
     <lb/>I shall make use of the word intrigue, 
     <lb/>unless the House says I am not in 
     <lb/>order. ( <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. Speaker</persName>.—That is not 
     <lb/>Parliamentary language.) Then I will 
     <lb/>qualify it by saying political intrigue. 
     <lb/>His Excellency charges his late advisers 
     <lb/>with having improperly taken from the 
     <lb/>files of the Executive Council a docu<lb break="no"/>ment which should have been there. 
     <lb/>That document was what? It was the 
     <lb/>absolute acceptance of our resignation, 
     <lb/>and the moment that paper was given 
     <lb/>to us we ceased to be Executive Coun<lb break="no"/>cillors, and we had no rght to go to 
     <lb/>the Executive Council Chamber, and it 
     <lb/>was our paper. I say that was a gross 
     <lb/>charge against us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">His Honor the SPEAKER</persName>.—This is 
     <lb/>
     contrary to Parliamentary rule. The 
     <lb/>
     communication in which the expression 
     <lb/>
     was made was addressed to his present 
     <lb/>
     advisers, and they are responsible. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. BOTSFORD</persName>. —If the Governor 
     <lb/>
     in Council had laid that communication 
     <lb/>
     before the Council, that would have 
     <lb/>
     been the view to take of it. But this 
     <lb/>
     was published in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi> and signed 
     <lb/>
     by Arthur Gordon, therefore I treat 
     <lb/>
     him as an individual. I wish to give 
     <lb/>
     the representative of Her Majesty all 
     <lb/>
     due deference, and I shall try to keep 
     <lb/>
     within the bounds of Parliamentary 
     <lb/>
     language, so as not to give offence to 
     <lb/>
     you and the House, and shall err in 
     <lb/>
     judgment  alone. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The debate was then adjourned until 
     <lb/>
     after the Journals were read to-morrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The House in Committee agreed to a 
     <lb/>
     Bill introduced by Mr. Kerr, entitled 
     <lb/>
     " A Bill to incorporate the Provincial 
     <lb/>
     Oil Company " 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The following Bills were then brought 
     <lb/>in :<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     "A Bill to amend a law relating to 
     <lb/>
     water supply and sewerage in the City 
     <lb/>
     of St. John, on the Western side of the 
     <lb/>
     Harbor." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " A Bill to incorporate the Caulkers' 
     <lb/>
     Association in the City and County of 
     <lb/>
     St. John." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     " A Bill relating to Warehousing 
     <lb/>
     goods " 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     " A Bill to incorporate the Ship<lb break="no"/>wrights' Union in the City and County 
     <lb/>
     of St. John."   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The House adjourned until 9 A. M. 
     <lb/>
     tomorrow.</p>  

<p rendition="simple:right">J. P. D.  
  
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2018-05-08, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
   
           <!-- <p>
     FRIDAY, June, 29th. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>DELEGATION ON UNION.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. BOTSFORD</persName> resumed—When 
     <lb/>
     the debate was adjourned yesterday I 
     <lb/>
     was replying to the charges, and asking 
     <lb/>
     explanations with regard to the state<lb break="no"/>ments of the Hon. Provincial Secretary, 
     <lb/>
     and the hon. member for Charlotte, (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Stevens,) and notwithstanding the At<lb break="no"/>torney General does not see what this 
     <lb/>
     has to do with the subject before the 
     <lb/>
     House, I shall go into this matter, con<lb break="no"/>ceiving as I do that as a member of the 
     <lb/>
     late Government I should be wanting in 
     <lb/>
     the duty I owe myself and my late col<lb break="no"/>leagues, if, after the remarks of the hon. 
     <lb/>member from Charlotte I did not go into 
     <lb/>an explanation of the whole matter. I 
     <lb/>was speaking, Sir, on the differences 
     <lb/>which occurred in the answers of the Le<lb break="no"/>gislative Council in their memorandum 
     <lb/>of resignation ; the Government charged 
     <lb/>His Excellency with advising with mem<lb break="no"/>bers and persons in the Opposition, and 
     <lb/>this was not denied. The Governor ad<lb break="no"/>mits having held consultations with Mr. 
     <lb/>Mitchell. But, Sir, the time referred to 
     <lb/>was not the only time. Whilst Mr. 
     <lb/>Smith, the leader oft he Government was 
     <lb/>away on a delegation to Washington, we, 
     <lb/>the other members of the Government, 
     <lb/>knew that he was in communication with 
     <lb/>Government House. On the return of 
     <lb/>Mr. Smith, we informed him of the fact, 
     <lb/>and in his next interview with His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency, he charged it home upon him. 
     <lb/>We knew what was going on, and His 
     <lb/>Excellency could not and did not deny the 
     <lb/>charge. But there is another point he 
     <lb/>also admits, and that is that he did not  
     <lb/>consult with his Council on the answer 
     <lb/>he intended, and did give to the address 
     <lb/>of the Legislative Council. On the 
     <lb/>seventh of April, after a night's reflection 
     <lb/>on the first resolution with regard to the 
     <lb/>address the Legislative Council withdrew 
     <lb/>that and substituted the other. This I 
     <lb/>presume was the time when the Provin<lb break="no"/>cial Secretary was consulted by Mr. 
     <lb/>Mitchell. Then Messrs. Botsford and 
     <lb/>Chandler were appointed a committee to 
     <lb/>wait on His Excellency to know when he 
     <lb/>would receive them with the address, and 
     <lb/>here occurred a case unparalleled in the 
     <lb/>history of our Province. Hie reply was 
     <lb/>that he would receive them in two hours 
     <lb/>from that time. This was at one o'clock . 
     <lb/>At twenty minutes to three a note was 
     <lb/>brought into this House from His Excel<lb break="no"/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>