<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1865-05-25"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-05-25">25 May 1865</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1865</title>.
                    


     <date when="1865"/>.  



          <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="87" to="89"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-25_Page_0087.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-25_Page_0088.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-25_Page_0089.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-02-27">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-02-27">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-25_Page_0087">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-25_Page_0087.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-25_Page_0088">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-25_Page_0088.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-25_Page_0089">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-25_Page_0089.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="87" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-25_Page_0087.jpg"/>
           
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>  <fw type="num">87</fw>


        <head rendition="simple:right">Thursday, May 25, 1865.</head>        
  

   
            <p>
     
     
         The House in a Committee of the     
     <lb/>Whole agreed to a Bill introduced by<lb/>Col. Boyd, entitled " An Act to Incor<lb break="no"/>porate the Digdeguash Lake and Stream<lb/>Driving Company."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    The Committee to whom was referred <lb/>the following Bills - " A Bill for the pro<lb break="no"/>tection of Moose," and " A Bill to amend<lb/>the law relating to the destruction of<lb/>Moose," made the following report.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>    The Committee have examined the <lb/>Bills very carefully, and have also ex<lb break="no"/>amined the Laws of Canada and Nova<lb/>Scotia, in regard to the preservation of<lb/>Moose, and have given the question<lb/>their best consideration. This subject<lb/>is one which is very difficult in dealing<lb/>with, and in bringing offenders to justice<lb/>great difficulties arise, as the offences are<lb/>committed in the forest by non-residents,<lb/>far beyond the means of obtaining tes<lb break="no"/>timony and the reach of judicial tribun<lb break="no"/>als ; the offenders generally escape be<lb break="no"/>fore they can be prosecuted ; in this way<lb/>the Moose are slaughtered by whole<lb break="no"/>sale, and the offenders escape the pun<lb break="no"/>ishment they so richly deserve. The<lb/>Committee are fully impressed with the<lb/>fact that unless legislation can be so<lb/>made as to reach the offenders, and stop<lb/>the wholesale slaughter, that within a<lb/>few years these useful animals will be<lb break="no"/>come extinct. With these facts in view<lb/>the Committee have prepared another<lb/>Bill on this subject, entitled " A Bill for<lb/>the protection of Moose"; having very<lb/>stringent regulations, and which the<lb/>Committee believe, if strictly enforced,<lb/>will protect the Moose, and therefore<lb/>recommend the Bill to the favorable<lb/>consideration of the House.<lb/>        Edward Williston,<lb/>        John Costigan,<lb/>                                      } Committee  <lb/>        Geo. Otty,<lb/>        W. Needham,<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    The House then went into a Commit<lb break="no"/>tee of the Whole to take into considera<lb break="no"/>tion the foregoing Bill entitled- <lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">

<head rendition="simple:centre">A BILL FOR THE PROTECTION OF MOOSE.</head>

    
   
            <p>    Mr. Cudlip. - I do not believe the <lb/>Bill is worth the paper on which it is<lb/>written ; laws of this kind never did<lb/>work in any country, and they will not<lb/>work here.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. Costigan. - I do not agree to all  
     <lb/>the provisions of this Bill, for it will pre<lb break="no"/>vent the settler from killing any Moose<lb/>at all, the winter season being the only<lb/>time in which he can kill them, while a<lb/>man who does not belong to the coun<lb break="no"/>try can kill them by hundreds, leaving<lb/>the meat to be destroyed ; and by so do<lb break="no"/>ing be in no danger of incurring a fine<lb/>at all. In my opinion we should either<lb/>introduce a Bill to prevent any person<lb/>from killing them during the next four<lb/>or five years, or a Bill to prevent the<lb/>traffic and exportation of hides, the traf<lb break="no"/>fic in hides being the chief inducement<lb/>to parties to kill them.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. Beveridge. - If you allow men 
     <lb/>to kill them for nine months a great<lb/>quantity will be destroyed. Parties can<lb/>come from Quebec and the State of<lb/>Maine to kill the moose and convey their<lb/>hides through the woods to those coun<lb break="no"/>tries. I have known parties who have<lb/>killed 100 moose this winter and taken<lb/>their hides to Canada. They should<lb/>not be killed at all for several years, or<lb/>until they increase and become plenti<lb break="no"/>ful. According to this Bill a man is al<lb break="no"/>lowed to kill two. I do not think this<lb/>will be any protection, for if there is half<lb/>a dozen in the family, each one will<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
     

     have his two moose, perhaps all being 
     <lb/>killed by the same person.<lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. Needham. - I would not oppose a  
     <lb/>Bill to prevent their being killed at all,<lb/>provided the Indians are excepted.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. Williston. - We have examined  
     <lb/>the Laws of Upper and Lower Canada,<lb/>and also the State of Maine, and find<lb/>that the Indians are exempt from any<lb/>Laws relating to the protection of moose.<lb/>Under these circumstances the Comm<lb break="no"/>mittee thought that to deprive the In<lb break="no"/>dians, - who have no other means of<lb/>subsistence except the animals caught<lb/>in the woods, - of the liberty of killing<lb/>these moose would be doing them a <lb/>great injustice.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Otty. - The Indians will never <lb/>kill any more moose than is requisite for<lb/>their own subsistence. They have al<lb break="no"/>ways spoken against the Traders and<lb/>Frenchmen coming from Canada and<lb/>the State of Maine in order to obtain<lb/>these hides for exportation. They wish<lb/>the moose protected for their own use<lb/>and the natural subsistence of their<lb/>families.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Costigan. - The hon. member for <lb/>King's has stated that the Indians never<lb/>kill more than they can take care of, and<lb/>don't allow the carcass to lie in the<lb/>woods to be destroyed. I know the In<lb break="no"/>dians do kill large quantities and leave<lb/>their carcasses to be destroyed in the<lb/>woods. Within a few miles of the camp<lb/>where I was working, two Indians had<lb/>killed seventy moose. I asked one of<lb/>them if he did not think it was wrong<lb/>to kill those moose and leave the meat<lb/>to be destroyed. The Indian pointed to<lb/>a large pine tree, and said, the white<lb/>man will come and cut down that tree,<lb/>take a certain portion and leave the rest<lb/>to rot in the woods because it is no use<lb/>to them ; we do the same as the white<lb/>man, we take the hides because we can<lb/>turn them into money, but the rest we<lb/>leave to rot on the ground. I would<lb/>like to go for a Bill to prohibit killing<lb/>them at all, others want the Indians ex<lb break="no"/>cepted. It might be done in this way. <lb/>The Bill could prohibit all persons from<lb/>killing them for three years, except the<lb/>Indians, and no traffic allowed in the<lb/>hides. Then the Indians would have<lb/>no inducement to kill more than they<lb/>wanted for their own use, but if you<lb/>simply prohibit killing, and except the<lb/>Indians, you leave the traffic entirely in<lb/>their hands.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    This Bill was agreed to. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Hon. Mr. Smith said that as the Leg<lb break="no"/>islature of Nova Scotia had passed a re<lb break="no"/>solution to appoint delegates to confer<lb/>with other delegates from the Maritime<lb/>Provinces regarding a commercial or<lb/>Legislative Union between the Provin<lb break="no"/>ces of Nova Scotia, New Brunswick and<lb/>Prince Edward's Island, he had prepar<lb break="no"/>ed a resolution authorizing the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, in case the Government of Nova<lb/>Scotia appoint these delegates, to ap<lb break="no"/>point a delegation also ; but he thought<lb/>it was premature to discuss this ques<lb break="no"/>tion, as this delegation which they pro<lb break="no"/>posed to appoint would have no power<lb/>to bind the House, but should be ap<lb break="no"/>pointed as a matter of courtesy to Nova<lb/>Scotia ; he would therefore give notice<lb/>of the following resolution "<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Whereas, the Lieut. Governor of this  
     <lb/>Province has received from the Lieut.<lb/>Governor of Nova Scotia copies of re<lb break="no"/>solutions passed by the Legislative<lb/>Council, and House of Assembly, of<lb/>that Province, expressing a wish to re<lb break="no"/>new the negotiation for a Union of the<lb/>Maritime Provinces ;<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>    And whereas, it is desirable to ascer- <lb/>tain whether a Legislative or Com<lb break="no"/>mercial Union of these Provinces, on<lb/>terms advantageous to all, is practic<lb break="no"/>able ;<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Therefore resolved, that a humble<lb/>address be presented to His Excellency<lb/>the Lieut. Governor, requesting him to<lb/>appoint delegates, not to exceed five, to<lb/>confer with a delegation to be appointed<lb/>by the Governments of Nova Scotia and<lb/>Prince Edward's Island, on the subject<lb/>of such Union.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Connell. - I do not rise for the <lb/>purpose of discussing this resolution, for<lb/>I am not aware what the opinion of the<lb/>House is in reference to it, but it is a<lb/>most important matter, and they should<lb/>express an opinion upon it. It is a ques<lb break="no"/>tion that should be fully discussed, and<lb/>if we are going to have a Confederation<lb/>on a small scale we should understand<lb/>it, and the Government should be pre<lb break="no"/>pared to give some reasons why a dele<lb break="no"/>gation of this kind should be appointed,<lb/>when a delegation which was appointed<lb/>last year reported against the measure.<lb/>I think the question had better stand<lb/>over until this afternoon so that we will<lb/>have time to consider the matter, and I<lb/>shall give my reasons why I am opposed<lb/>to it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Hon. Mr. Smith. - I cannot see any<lb/>use in allowing this matter to stand over.<lb/>I think it is due as a matter of courtesy<lb/>to Nova Scotia that this delegation<lb/>should be appointed. My hon. friend<lb/>knows that when the last delegation<lb/>met at Charlottetown their attention was<lb/>absorbed by the grander union, that this<lb/>union faded into insignificence, and they<lb/>paid no attention to it at all. If this<lb/>delegation which we propose to appoint<lb/>meet and agree upon any union, whether<lb/>legisltive or commercial, then it would be<lb/>submitted to the House, and the<lb/>country could take time to consider it.<lb/>Last year a resolution of this kind was<lb/>moved by the Provincial Secretary, and<lb/>we had little discussion upon it ; now<lb/>we propose to do the same thing with<lb break="no"/>out committing hon. members upon the<lb/>question ; but leave it until next session,<lb/>when it will be for the House to deter<lb break="no"/>mine whether to adopt or reject the re<lb break="no"/>port of the Committee.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Lindsay. - The first thing neces<lb break="no"/>sary to be done is to ascertain whether<lb/>the House desires this union or not ; if it<lb/>does not, it is unnecessary to appoint<lb/>this delegation and put the country to<lb/>this expense for no purpose, when the<lb/>finances are so limited, and they are re<lb break="no"/>quired for improvements in the country.<lb/>Although I am in favor of the union of<lb/>all the British North American Provin<lb break="no"/>ces, yet I am opposed to this union of the<lb/>Maritime Provinces, and want to record<lb/>my vote against it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Otty. - The hon. gentleman has <lb/>misapprehended the question, which is<lb/>merely a matter of courtesy to Nova<lb/>Scotia ; because Nova Scotia has passed a<lb/>resolution of this kind, it is a matter of<lb/>courtesy that we should do so too, and<lb/>the discussion of the subject can come up<lb/>hereafter.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. McClellan. - I suppose there can <lb/>be no objection if it is a matter of courte<lb break="no"/>sy ; but I should like to see the members<lb/>of the Government in their places, be<lb break="no"/>cause the hon. Provincial Secretary made<lb/>a remark when passing the suppplies which<lb/>made me suppose that no delegation<lb/>would be required ; but I see those pleas<lb break="no"/>ant little excursions will be provided for<lb/>the same as usual.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
    

            <p>     Mr. Cudlip. - I am not prepared to say <lb/>
         


    
            <pb n="88" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-25_Page_0088.jpg"/>
         <fw type="num">88</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>


whether I shall vote for or against this <lb/>
Union when the question comes up ; but <lb/>
I am glad to see a movement taking place <lb/>
in this direction, but I think there need <lb/>
not be much expense attending this dele<lb break="no"/>gation, for the distance being
short, the <lb/>
Nova Scotia delegation may come over to <lb/>
St. John. The members of the House <lb/>
can vote for this resolution without being <lb/>
obliged to vote for any union
the delega<lb break="no"/>tion might propose. Some gentlemen say <lb/>
if they cannot have a large union they <lb/>
do not want a small one ; but I
think this<lb/>
small union may be a benefit, while it <lb/>
might not be desirable to have a union of <lb/>
all the British possessions in the world. <lb/>
The appointment of this delegation may <lb/>
be the means of bringing about a com<lb break="no"/>mercial union, which would be a benefit <lb/>
to these Maritime Provinces. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Col. BOYD</persName> —It is very desirable to have <lb/>
a union of these Maritime Provinces, <lb/>
either commercial or Legislative. I would <lb/>
rather see a Legislative Union, because <lb/>
one Legislature would answer in place of <lb/>
three. If the gentlemen who were
ap<lb break="no"/>pointed last year to confer on this subject <lb/>
had done their duty, we might have been <lb/>
united now. It is very desirable that we <lb/>
should have one tariff, one
currency, and <lb/>
the same postal arrangements in the three <lb/>
Provinces. After we have this
union, and <lb/>
it is found to work well, we
might have <lb/>
Confederation with Canada, if the Cana<lb break="no"/>dians would make reasonable propositions ; <lb/>
but at present we should creep
before we <lb/>
walk. <lb/>
            </p>
  
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. MCMILLAN</persName>.—I
think in courtesy <lb/>
to Nova Scotia, we should not
object to <lb/>
passing this resolution ; but I do not see <lb/>
any benefits arising from this small union, <lb/>
which would not have been much greater <lb/>
in the larger union. This small union <lb/>
was abandoned last year, but I do not
<lb/>
think it was abandoned until the delega<lb break="no"/>tion was satisfied that it could not be <lb/>
carried out. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:FRAS1">Mr. FRASER</persName>.—I
do not think this is a <lb/>
proper time to discuss this matter, as we <lb/>
are voting for this resolution as a matter <lb/>
of courtesy. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName>.—The
interests of these <lb/>
Lower Provinces are identified in every <lb/>
possible way, and this delegation may <lb/>
lead to some beneficial results. I cannot <lb/>
see how the Government could well get <lb/>
clear of co-operating with Nova Scotia in <lb/>
discussing this matter. I shall support <lb/>
the resolution. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HILL1">Mr. HILL</persName>—It is said this resolution is <lb/>
a mere matter of courtesy to Nova Scotia. <lb/>
I do not see that it is any more so than a <lb/>
similar resolution which we passed last <lb/>
year, the result of which certainly went <lb/>
beyond what we intended when we passed <lb/>
that resolution. It would be premature <lb/>
to take sides on this question now, inas<lb break="no"/>much as our minds would be liable to<lb/>
change when we receive further informa<lb break="no"/>tion on the subject. Although I am <lb/>
somewhat in favor of this resolution, think<lb break="no"/>ing this union will come to pass in a few <lb/>
years, yet I should like to hear
the argu<lb break="no"/>ments for and against it, in order to ac<lb break="no"/>quire further information. When
the <lb/>
Canadian union was first moved, I was <lb/>
rather in favor of it ; but the
more I <lb/>
looked into it the more I opposed
it. <lb/>
'There is no subject which can come be<lb break="no"/>fore the Legislature this
Session that I <lb/>
would more gladly listen to than
a union <lb/>
of these Lower Colonies. Some
such <lb/>
preliminary discussion should take place, <lb/>
in order that we may be fully prepared <lb/>
to discuss the question when it comes up. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.—I am in favor of this reso<lb break="no"/>lution, because by negotiating
with the <lb/>
Lower Colonies we have already been
<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
          
 benefitted to a considerable extent. I <lb/>
recollect the time when there was a duty <lb/>
of two pounds on every horse that was <lb/>
imported from Prince Edward Island;
but <lb/>
by an arrangement entered into
the <lb/>
Governments of the respective
Provinces, <lb/>
the productions of the different Colonies <lb/>
are entered at a uniform rate. I imported <lb/>
a carriage from the United States and paid <lb/>
17 1/2 per cent. duty in this Province. If I<lb/>
had taken it to Nova Scotia I would have <lb/>
had to have paid but 6 per cent., and<lb/>
could have brought it home from there <lb/>
just as easily, and thereby escaped the <lb/>
extra duty. Merchants like to get their <lb/>
goods into the country at the lowest pos<lb break="no"/>sible rate, and it is very desirable that <lb/>
such an arrangement may be made as will <lb/>
remove all the restrictions upon our trade, <lb/>
so that the importations into the various <lb/>
Colonies may be admitted at the
same <lb/>
rate of duty. The heads of departments <lb/>
should meet and discuss this matter of a <lb/>
Legislative or Commercial Union, and the <lb/>
resolution which they adopt can be fully
<lb/>
discussed in the House next winter. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>
moved that this resolu<lb break="no"/>tion be postponed for three months, and <lb/>
said :—If this resolution is a mere matter <lb/>
of courtesy, and no result to be arrived <lb/>
at, what is the use of appointing a delega<lb break="no"/>tion ? It is a matter which can
be very <lb/>
well undertaken by the
Government, and <lb/>
it is very right for them to do so, laying <lb/>
such information as they receive before <lb/>
the Legislature next winter. It has been <lb/>
said that we would have been swamped <lb/>
in uniting with Canada ; but the same <lb/>
argument will apply to a union of these <lb/>
Lower Colonies. I should like to have <lb/>
seen the President of the Council
go into <lb/>
an elaborate discussion of this matter, as <lb/>
they have done in Nova Scotia,
not only <lb/>
in reference to a union of the Lower Colo<lb break="no"/>nies,
but also the larger union with Cana<lb break="no"/>da. I should like the opinion of the <lb/>
country to be expressed on this question, <lb/>
as it might have an influence upon this <lb/>
delegation. If there is no
movement <lb/>
made to discuss this question, how is the <lb/>
country to get information ? No action <lb/>
should be taken until the country has had <lb/>
an opportunity to express an opinion upon <lb/>
the subject. In reference to Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, I always expressed my opinion in <lb/>
the strongest terms, that the
measure <lb/>
should never be submitted to the House <lb/>
for its final passage without being first <lb/>
left to the people. <lb/>
            </p>



            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—We might have a <lb/>
dissolution of the House upon the ques<lb break="no"/>tion.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>—I
should like to see it. <lb/>
With reference to Confederation it was a <lb/>
great mistake that the matter had
not <lb/>
been brought before the Legislature and <lb/>
discussed, just as I say this
matter
should <lb/>
be discussed before a delegation is ap<lb break="no"/>pointed to go to Nova Scotia. If that <lb/>
had been the case the people
would not <lb/>
have been misled the way they
have been <lb/>
on this question of Confederation,
and <lb/>
would have arrived at a different
result, <lb/>
for I believe a large majority
of the coun<lb break="no"/>try are in favor of Confederation. I do <lb/>
not see any advantage to be
derived from <lb/>
this connection with Prince Edward<lb/>
Island, Nova Scotia and Newfoundland, <lb/>
but think it would be decidedly injurious <lb/>
so far as Agriculture is
concerned. I <lb/>
think it would be great injustice to the <lb/>
people of this Province to have the Seat <lb/>
of Government removed to Halifax, for it <lb/>
is there where it would have
to go. I <lb/>
suppose the President of the Council <lb/>
thinks it will go to Dorchester, but he may <lb/>
rest assured that it will not, for we will <lb/>
have but a small minority in the
House, <lb/>


            <cb/>
        
and consequently cannot locate the Seat <lb/>
of Government where we choose. <lb/>
            </p>



            <p> <persName ref="pers:THOM1">Dr. THOMPSON</persName>.—There
is no basis <lb/>
upon which to rest a discussion.
If the <lb/>
delegates agree upon anything before
the <lb/>
next Session, that will be the
time to dis<lb break="no"/>cuss it. We will have one Legislature <lb/>
instead of three if we adopt this Union, <lb/>
and consequently can reduce our number <lb/>
of representatives
from each County, or <lb/>
form electoral districts. There will be an
<lb/>
advantage in uniting the seaboard Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces where the trade is all of the same <lb/>
kind, whereas if we united in
Canada we <lb/>
would have nothing in common, for we <lb/>
could take nothing to them, and receive <lb/>
nothing from them except provisions. <lb/>
This delegation may suggest
something <lb/>
in regard to trade that will be an advan<lb break="no"/>tage, but it will be time enough
to discuss <lb/>
the subject when their report is brought
<lb/>
before us. <lb/>
            </p>










            <p> The House decided in favor of the reso<lb break="no"/>lution. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion of <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>, the <lb/>
House went into a Committee of
the whole <lb/>
to take into consideration  <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre"> A BILL TO PROVIDE FOR THE PAYMENT OF<lb/>
DEBENTURES ISSUED UNDER AN ACT<lb/>
RELATING TO THE SAVINGS' BANK AND<lb/>
OTHER PROVINCIAL LIABILITIES.<lb/>
            </head>






            <p> <persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. COSTIGAN</persName> in the Chair. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—In 1856 the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture passed a law authorizing the Governor <lb/>
in Council to issue debentures to the <lb/>
amount of £90,000. In 1862 an Act was <lb/>
passed enlarging the grant to $500,000,
<lb/>
and the late Government have
issued de<lb break="no"/>bentures to that extent ; but £30,000 <lb/>
sterling of those debentures remain in the <lb/>
hands of the Messrs. Baring in
London ; <lb/>
the object of which was to meet any call <lb/>
upon Savings' Bank deposits. The
time <lb/>of those debentures was limited to ten <lb/>
years, that time expires next May. The <lb/>
object of this Bill is to provide for the <lb/>
issue of debentures to the extent of $500,<lb break="no"/>000, to meet those debentures
when they <lb/>fall due. In this Bill I have given a dis<lb break="no"/>cretionary power to the Government, hav<lb break="no"/>ing put in no limitation as to time ; we <lb/>
can pay at such, whether in sterling or <lb/>
currency, as may seem most advantageous <lb/>
to the public interest.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>. —There are now already
de<lb break="no"/>bentures to the extent of £30,000 sterling <lb/>
in the hands of the Messrs. Barings lying  <lb/>
unsold, which were issued under the Act <lb/>
providing for the issue of $500,000. Be<lb break="no"/>fore these new debentures are issued <lb/>
there should be some provision made to <lb/>
satisfy the country that these debentures <lb/>
lying in the Messrs. Baring's hands would <lb/>
be destroyed, so that the amount would<lb/>
not be charged against the Province with <lb/>
               <lb/>

the amount authorized to be issued. We <lb/>
are all aware that the Bank of England 
<lb/>
always destroy their notes when received,
<lb/>
and never issue them a second time. In <lb/>
Nova Scotia also, the Provincial notes are <lb/>
destroyed in the presence of a Joint Com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the Legislature. A
section <lb/>
should be added to this Bill providing for <lb/>
them to be destroyed, and stating in whose<lb/>
presence it should be done. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I do not see any <lb/>
necessity for an amendment of
that kind, <lb/>
for these debentures are to be withdrawn <lb/>
and the Government will see
them des<lb break="no"/>troyed ; if they are withdrawn, it
is just <lb/>
the same as if, they were never issued, for <lb/>
they cannot be sold alter they are over<lb break="no"/>due.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.—I entirely differ from
my <lb/>
hon. friend. It may be that after
they <lb/>
are
due they are not saleable, but they <lb/>
might be transferred from hand to hand. <lb/>
            </p>























            <pb n="89" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-25_Page_0089.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">89</fw>

            <p>It might happen that these debentures <lb/>
would not be all taken up when they are <lb/>
due, and if any of those unsold deben<lb break="no"/>tures should fall into the hands of a <hi rendition="simple:italic">bona <lb/>
fide</hi> holder, will not this Province feel <lb/>
bound to pay them. I think it is neces<lb break="no"/>sary for this Province that as many of<lb/>
these debentures should be issued here<lb/>
as possible, so that the interest can be<lb/>
saved in the country, which at present<lb/>
is a great drain upon our resources.
<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>.—I have no objection to <lb/>
this Bill further than this, that some pro<lb break="no"/>vision should be made to prove that <lb/>
those bonds had been destroyed, and <lb/>
some record kept here specifying those <lb/>
bonds that have been taken up. I
un<lb break="no"/>derstand by the Bill that the whole <lb/>
amount of debentures to the extent of <lb/>
$500,000 can be issued if the
Govern<lb break="no"/>ment think proper. <lb/>
            </p>
 
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—It
is the intention <lb/>
of the Government to leave $30,000
in <lb/>
the hands of the Messrs. Baring,
to pro<lb break="no"/>vide for any run which may be made<lb/>
upon the Savings' Bank deposit. There <lb/>
is some weight in the objection taken in <lb/>
regard to having those bonds destroyed, <lb/>
and there should be some provision made <lb/>
for it. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> moved the following addi<lb break="no"/>tional section to the Bill which was <lb/>
carried : <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> " The debentures issued under the <lb/>
said security acts, and remaining unsold, <lb/>
shall be cancelled or destroyed before <lb/>
any debentures shall be issued beyond <lb/>
the amounts now actually in the hands <lb/>
of purchasers ; evidence of such
cancel<lb break="no"/>ling or destroying to be made appear<lb/>
to the satisfaction of the
Governor in <lb/>
Council." <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> The Bill was then agreed to as <lb/>
amended. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName> moved the House in<lb break="no"/>to Committee to take into Consideration <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre"> AN ACT IN ADDITION TO AN
ACT RELATING <lb/>
TO THE CONSTRUCTION OF RAILWAYS. <lb/>
            </head>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—It
has been stated <lb/>
in the House that Mr. Levesey,
on be<lb break="no"/>half of the International Railway Com<lb break="no"/>pany, made a proposition to the late<lb/>
Government regarding the construction <lb/>
of the railway from Moncton to the Nova <lb/>
Scotia boundary. There is reason
to <lb/>
believe that some effectual arrangement <lb/>
may be made with him during the
com<lb break="no"/>ing season, and this Bill provides for the <lb/>
taking of land for that purpose ; there be<lb break="no"/>ing no provision of that kind now
made. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CUDL1">Mr. CUDLIP</persName>.—I am not willing to vote<lb/>
for building a railway to Nova Scotia.,<lb/>
unless as part of the great
highway to <lb/>
the United States. The Government <lb/>
should have the power to stay proceed<lb break="no"/>ings on that line until Western Exten<lb break="no"/>sion is undertaken by Government or a <lb/>
Company. I am not willing
to tax the <lb/>
people of this Province to build a mere <lb/>
section of the road, unless it is built as <lb/>
part of the great whole <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—Does the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber mean to say that if Mr.
Levesey <lb/>
choose to build this portion of
the line, <lb/>
Government should be called upon to <lb/>
build Western Extension. If any com<lb break="no"/>pany choose to build this road under the<lb/>
Facility Bill of last year we could not<lb/>
stop them.<lb/>
            </p>
  
            <p> <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.—If
I understand this Bill<lb/>
it makes every necessary provision to <lb/>
enable any company to construct any of <lb/>
the lines provided under the Facilities <lb/>
Bill. My hon. friend from St. John <lb/>
stated he would not consent to build <lb/>
that portion of the line between Monc<lb break="no"/>ton and Nova Scotia boundary, un<lb break="no"/>
        

            <cb/>   
          
 less it was concurrent with Western Ex<lb break="no"/>tension. I might, with with equal
justice, <lb/>
say I would not consent unless
the
line <lb/>
on the North Shore was built. If a com<lb break="no"/>pany could be induced to build it they <lb/>
should have the same facilities
as any <lb/>
other portion of the line, for I think it
is <lb/>
very unfair to hold out an inducement of <lb/>
$10,000
a mile , and then tell the Com<lb break="no"/>pany they cannot enter upon the line. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On a
division of the House on this Bill <lb/>
was agreed to.</p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">AFTERNOON SESSION.<lb/>
            </head>






            <p> Messrs.
<persName ref="pers:LEWI1">LEWIS</persName>, <persName ref="pers:DESB1">A. C. DESBRISAY</persName>, <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:YOUN1">YOUNG</persName>, and <persName ref="pers:CORA1">CORAM</persName>, requested to have <lb/>
their names recorded on the journals as <lb/>
voting in favor of the
resolution for the <lb/>
appointment of delegates to confer with  <lb/>
other delegates on the subject of the <lb/>
Union of the Maritime Provinces. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName>.—I
certainly
think that <lb/>
when that resolution came up members <lb/>
necessarily absent on business in
the <lb/>
Committee Room should have been call<lb break="no"/>ed, for it is a subject of the greatest im<lb break="no"/>portance, and more particularly affects <lb/>
the County of York than any other Coun<lb break="no"/>ty in the Province. I am decidedly
op<lb break="no"/>posed to it, for I do not think any such<lb/>
union can be effected that will be a bene<lb break="no"/>fit to New Brunswick ; on the contrary <lb/>
it would materially injure the Province. <lb/>
With regard to a commercial union or <lb/>
the adoption of a uniform tariff, and <lb/>
postal
rates, I have no objection ; if we <lb/>
can assimilate our tariff, postal arrange<lb break="no"/>ments and currency, it will, no doubt <lb/>
be a benefit to the colonies, but I nev<lb break="no"/>er will consent to a legislative
union, <lb/>
which is part and parcel of this resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, which certainly commits the
mem<lb break="no"/>bers of this House ; for if this
delegation <lb/>
agrees to a Legislative union, how can <lb/>
any member get up and oppose it
after <lb/>
having voted for this resolution. Now, <lb/>
as a matter of courtesy, when a proposi<lb break="no"/>tion is made by one Province to another, <lb/>
I am willing to extend all the courtesy <lb/>
I can, consistent with my duty, but I am <lb/>
not willing to have a delegation go
there
<lb/>
and determine whether we shall have a <lb/>
legislative or commercial union, for <lb/>
those who vote for it will be bound by <lb/>
it. I believe that a legislative union <lb/>
would be more destructive to this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince than that grand Confederation <lb/>
scheme, and if we must choose between <lb/>
two evils we had better choose the least. <lb/>
If I had to choose between a
Legislative <lb/>
Union of the Lower Colonies, or this <lb/>
grand Confederation scheme which
I do <lb/>
not believe in, I would say, give me the <lb/>
Confederation scheme ten to one. This <lb/>
Union of the Lower Colonies would <lb/>
dwindle us down into absolute insigni<lb break="no"/>ficance;  it would deprive us of our seat <lb/>
of Government, and render the whole<lb/>
Province less than a municipality. I <lb/>
confess I feel strongly on this subject, <lb/>
and do not wish to be misunderstood. <lb/>
I want to record my vote against it, but <lb/>
I do not want to record a silent vote. <lb/>
We do not know what this delegation<lb/>
may do, when they get there, but I do<lb/>
not feel disposed to give them
the power <lb/>
to legislate for a Legislative Union. <lb/>
Some persons might say because I was <lb/>
away from my seat that I shirked the
<lb/>
question. Perhaps I may be rather too <lb/>
bold, but I never shirk. I am prepared <lb/>
to speak, vote and act as I think, <lb/>
whether it is right or wrong,
and then I <lb/>
am responsible for what I do. If the <lb/>
word Legislative Union had not
been <lb/>
there I would have voted for the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, for we ought to have a delegation<lb/>
to consider a Commercial Union ; but I<lb/>
           

   <cb/>

 would not give them any power to dis<lb break="no"/>cuss whether we should have a Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive Union or not. If those power were<lb/>
contained in the resolution I trust the<lb/>
House will allow me to record my vote<lb/>
against it. I feel that I am bound by<lb/>
every principle of honor and integrity<lb/>
to carry out the principle which I was<lb/>
sent to this House to sustain, as I be<lb break="no"/>lieve my constituents, men, women and<lb/>
children, would rise up and condemn<lb/>
me, were I to assent to a proposition<lb/>
which I have so often attempted to show<lb/>
would be to the detriment and injury<lb/>
of the Province.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName>.—I wish my name<lb/>
recorded in favor of this delegation,<lb/>
and if they come to the conclusion that<lb/>
a Legislative Union is necessary, I have<lb/>
not the slightest hesitation in saying I<lb/>
shall go cheerfully for it. My impres<lb break="no"/>sion is rather in favor for it ; but, how<lb break="no"/>ever, it is better to have the matter dis<lb break="no"/>cussed by the delegation, and let them<lb/>
recommend what they consider the best<lb/>
for the country.</p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—One of the mem<lb break="no"/>bers for York (Mr. Fraser) was present<lb/>
when this discussion came up, and he<lb/>
expressed himself favorable to a Com<lb break="no"/>mercial Union, but I was to be taken<lb/>
upon the subject at all.</p>
            <p>The House in Committee agreed to<lb/>
" A Bill to amend an Act to provide for<lb/>
the erection of an Alms House Work<lb/>
House, and to establish a Public Infirm<lb break="no"/>ary in and for the City and County of<lb/>
St. John."<lb/>

            </p>


            <p> Also, " An Act to explain certain sec<lb break="no"/>tions in a Bill relating to Sewerage."
<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Also, " A Bill relating to marriage." <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Also, " A Bill to establish
a Police <lb/>force in the Town of Chatham." <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Also, " A Bill to amend an Act to In<lb break="no"/>corporate the Trustees of the St. John <lb/>
Church in Chatham, in connection with <lb/>
the Presbyterian Church of Nova Scotia. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
House adjourned to meet
to-morrow, <lb/>
at. 9, A. M.   T. P. D. <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2018-02-27, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


           <!-- <p> FRIDAY,
May 26.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
COLE'S ISLAND BRIDGE. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Mr. WILLISTON moved the House into <lb/>
Committee of the whole on the corres<lb break="no"/>pondence laid before the House in reply <lb/>
to an Address to His Excellency, relating
<lb/>
to the Bridge across the Washademoak, at <lb/>
Coles' Island. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. MCCLELLAN
in the chair. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The correspondence having been read <lb/>
by the chairman, Mr. WILLISTON moved <lb/>
the following resolution : <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Whereas, the House of Assembly being<lb/>
in Committee of the whole on the 28 <lb/>
March, 1864, the following
resolution was <lb/>
moved : <lb/>
            </p>




            <p> " Whereas. It is believed that internal <lb/>
communication
on the Eastern side of the <lb/>
River St. John would be greatly facilitat<lb break="no"/>ed, and business on the European and <lb/>
North American Railroad much augment<lb break="no"/>ed by the erection of a Bridge over
the <lb/>
North-west
channel of the Washademoak, <lb/>
from Coles' Island to the main
land on <lb/>
that side, and that the erection of said <lb/>
Bridge would not be attended with
a large <lb/>expenditure of money. Therefore
Re<lb break="no"/>solved, As in the opinion of this Com<lb break="no"/>mittee, that an Humble Address should <lb/>
be presented to His Excellency the Lieu<lb break="no"/>tenant Governor, praying His Excellency's <lb/>
favorable consideration of the matter, and <lb/>
that he may be pleased lo direct the at<lb break="no"/>tention of the Board of Works to this very, <lb/>
desirable and necessary object, with a
<lb/>
view its erection at an early day." <lb/>
            </p>







            <p/>-->


        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>