<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1865-06-03"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-06-03">3 June 1865</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1865</title>.
                    

          <date when="1865"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
                    

          <biblScope unit="page" from="129" to="134"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_129.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_130.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_131.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_132.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_133.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_134.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-04-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-08">Created this document, completed metadata.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_129">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_129.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_132">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_130.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_131">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_131.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_130">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_132.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_133">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_133.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_134">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_134.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="129" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_129.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">129</fw>

<!-- GL, 2017-04-20, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

            <!--<p> the hon. member for St. John,<lb/>

who introduced the Treasury Note
Bill ;<lb/>
 and the Patriotic corner so ably
repre<lb break="no"/>sented by the other hon. member for St.<lb/>
John in the Government. It will be seen <lb/>
the Council, and the Hon. Provincial<lb/>
Secretary ; they are not corner stones, and<lb/>
should not be in it at all, and I hope they<lb/>
will attach themselves to some other party<lb/>
and work in a different manner—more in<lb/>
accordance with their political antecedents.<lb/>
But there is a military point of view in<lb/>
which this matter should be viewed. I<lb/>
trust there will be no difficulty with the<lb/>
United States ; I have favored the North<lb/>
all through their struggle, but we all<lb/>
know that the Americans are avaricious of<lb/>
increased territory. We know that un<lb break="no"/>der the Ashburton Treaty they took a<lb/>
good slice off us, and that would not have<lb/>
been done it we had been united. Then<lb/>
on the Pacific Coast it was the same, and<lb/>
now they are casting longing eyes and<lb/>
would very much like to get a slice of the<lb/>
fertile belt of the Red River Settlement.<lb/>
They have 10,000 miles of Railways pro<lb break="no"/>jected, and it is stretching out to cover<lb/>
the continent ; but if united these en<lb break="no"/>croachments would cease at least in our<lb/>
direction.</p>
            <p>J. M.<lb/>
            </p>-->
 
            <head rendition="simple:right">SATURDAY, June 3rd.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p> Mr. MCCLELLAN resumed.—There<lb/>
were some remarks made by my hon.<lb/>
friend from Charlotte, (Dr. Thomson)<lb/>
during the interruption yesterday, in re<lb break="no"/>ference to as statement I had made about<lb/>
the influence of the clergy at the late<lb/>
elections. I did not design any disre<lb break="no"/>spect to any denomination, and do not<lb/>
think any member could say I made use<lb/>
of offensive language at all. My hon.<lb/>
and learned friend from the City of St.<lb/>
John, (Mr. Wetmore) during the inter<lb break="no"/>ruption, made some covert insinuation,<lb/>
that members who undertook to address<lb/>
this House after having been crammed<lb/>
the night before, were not entitled to<lb/>
great consideration. I did not clearly<lb/>
understand the inuendo at the time, at<lb/>
first I thought he referred to the splen<lb break="no"/>did social affair at the Exhibition build<lb break="no"/>ing the night before, and possibly the<lb/>
hon. member himself may have satisfied<lb/>
himself to expletion on that occasion,<lb/>
as for me, I was not present, and did not<lb/>
participate in those festivities. If he<lb/>
referred to intellectual as cramming, I<lb/>
can only tell him <hi rendition="simple:italic">confidentially</hi>, for this<lb/>
matter does not concern the public at all,<lb/>
that on his part it is all a matter of fancy,<lb/>
not of fact. It is better for hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers to express themselves frankly and<lb/>
openly, and not deal in such ambiguous<lb/>
allusions, and if my hon. and learned<lb/>
friend thinks he can suppress discussion<lb/>
by interruptions of that kind he is very<lb/>
much mistaken ; it may be well to resist<lb/>
discussion upon important questions at<lb/>
an election, but it will not be so easy to<lb/>
strangle free discussion on the floors of<lb/>
the Legislature. My learned friend<lb/>
(the Dr.) has taken occasion to proclaim<lb/>
himself a representative of the Tory ele<lb break="no"/>ment ; he frankly avows his sentiments ;<lb/>
he said the duties and attributes of Tories<lb/>
were to " fear God, honor the King, and<lb/>
deal uprightly with all men" ; and it was<lb/>
upon that his political principles were<lb/>
founded. I recollect a story told to il<lb break="no"/>lustrate the principles of toryism. A<lb/>
Tory was represented as being like a<lb/>
toad which had been buried in the solid<lb/>
    

            <cb/>
     
rock for a hundred years, but upon ex<lb break="no"/>posing him to the light of day and the<lb/>
vivifying beams of the sun he would,<lb/>
with twinkling eyes, pop out from his<lb/>
hiding place to the other toads, his com<lb break="no"/>peers, and perfectly oblivious of the fact<lb/>
that he is a hundred years behind the<lb/>
age. I do not wish to apply this to the<lb/>
learned Dr. from Charlotte. I am not<lb/>
saying that he is hopping along with<lb/>
the other toadies. I merely refer to this<lb/>
to show the sentiments and principles<lb/>
of Torryism. The resolution before you<lb/>
says Confederation will be politically,<lb/>
commercially and financially injurious<lb/>
to this Province. I shall not speak now<lb/>
upon the financial part of the subject,<lb/>
because that has been gone into by the<lb/>
hon. gentlemen from Carleton and Res<lb break="no"/>tigouche. I think that aspect of the<lb/>
question has been met, and the opposi<lb break="no"/>tion to the measure have failed to show<lb/>
such results would follow this union as<lb/>
would justify the appointment of this<lb/>
delegation. I feel confident that Con<lb break="no"/>federation can be sustained upon finan<lb break="no"/>cial grounds alone, without regard to<lb/>
the benefits arising from the construc<lb break="no"/>tion of the Inter-colonial railway, which<lb/>
gives us 200 miles of railway, bringing<lb/>
the traffic of the West into New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick. Immense advantages will flow<lb/>
from that road, uniting, as it does, the<lb/>
coal fields of the Eastern section with<lb/>
the metaliferous regions of the Western<lb/>
part of the Province and Canada. This<lb/>
road is not to be built with our own<lb/>
money, but the money of a people who<lb/>
have beeen denominated by many in this<lb/>
House as strangers. They are not<lb/>
strangers, but brother colonists, united<lb/>
and bound one colony to another. We<lb/>
should have that feeling of regard for<lb/>
them as would induce us to legislate<lb/>
for their interests as well as our own.<lb/>
It is the correct principle for any peo<lb break="no"/>ple to so legislate that they will place<lb/>
themselves in a position to buy in the<lb/>
cheapest market and sell in the dearest.<lb/>
This road will not only give us an ex<lb break="no"/>tended market, but will enable us to re<lb break="no"/>ceive the surplus productions of West<lb break="no"/>ern Canada ; it will produce benefits of<lb/>
which we have at present no conception.<lb/>
A person would suppose from listening<lb/>
to the remarks of some of the hon<lb break="no"/>orable gentlemen that they wished to<lb/>
re-enact the old protection laws, which<lb/>
were abolished years ago. They<lb/>
tell us that those men who signed a<lb/>
document in St. John expressing their<lb/>
views on this question, were men of no<lb/>
influence. They were men doing a large<lb/>
business, and were favorable to the exten<lb break="no"/>sion of the principles of free trade and<lb/>
fair competition with their neighbours, for<lb/>
they felt confidence in the resources of<lb/>
New Brunswick. The Hon. President of<lb/>
the Council alluded to a statement which<lb/>
I had made, that in six months there would<lb/>
be a change in the opinions of the people<lb/>
on this question, and there would be a<lb/>
large majority of the people of this coun<lb break="no"/>try in favor of Confederation ; he took the<lb/>
opposite ground, and did not believe that<lb/>
this would be the case. I said " try it."<lb/>
he answered that the cause of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion was desperate, and we were willing<lb/>
to try anything. I did not in my allusion<lb/>
refer to a dissolution of the House, but I<lb/>
referred to putting the matter before the<lb/>
country as a distinct question, outside of<lb/>
party difficulties and troubles altogether,<lb/>
so that the people could vote yea or nay<lb/>
upon the question, free from the entangle<lb break="no"/>ments of politics ; if it was so submitted,<lb/>
and means of instruction afforded them<lb/>
upon this question, I said they would have<lb/>
          
            <cb/>
          
a two-thirds majority in a very short time<lb/>
in favor of this measure. The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber says that was my opinion before ; I<lb/>
says I never was very sanguine of carrying<lb/>
this question before, for I knew the<lb/>
strength and ability of my learned friend<lb/>
—I knew his declamation powers—I knew<lb/>
his influence in the County of Albert, and<lb/>
I feared the effect of that declamation ;<lb/>
but in that County they took hold of the<lb/>
question and sifted it to the bottom, and<lb/>
they came to the conclusion that Confed<lb break="no"/>eration would build up this country, and<lb/>
it would prove a benefit to them whether<lb/>
they were miners, farmers, or fishermen.<lb/>
My hon. friend says my eyes were in Ot<lb break="no"/>tawa. I can tell him that I had no aspira<lb break="no"/>tions of that kind. I had no idea of go<lb break="no"/>ing into a new arena, but was content to<lb/>
serve my country in that Legislature,<lb/>
which, to adopt their own style of argu<lb break="no"/>ments, would be a mere municipality ;<lb/>
therefore, I cannot see how they can stig<lb break="no"/>matize as being actuated by any views<lb/>
of self-aggrandizement. He has put for<lb break="no"/>ward his great magnanimity in resigning<lb/>
his large salary and giving up a high posi<lb break="no"/>tion to protect the country from a great<lb/>
infliction, as he expressed it a that time ;<lb/>
and he considers that a reason why the<lb/>
people should give him credit for being<lb/>
the most patriotic man in the country.<lb/>
Although I never was in a position to<lb/>
give up a salary, or an office, yet I have<lb/>
been in a position to refuse to accept of<lb/>
one ; when parties were evenly balanced<lb/>
in this Legislature, I was offered one of<lb/>
the highest positions in the country, if I<lb/>
would desert my political principles, but<lb/>
I felt that while men were only for the<lb/>
passing hour, principles were undying. I<lb/>
hope that when this delegation—or this<lb/>
little pleasure excursion—goes to Eng<lb break="no"/>land at the expense of both Confederates<lb/>
and Anti-Confederates, they will repre<lb break="no"/>sent to the British Government the true<lb/>
state of feeling in this country, had state<lb/>
that a large majority of the other branch<lb/>
of the Legislature are in favor of the<lb/>
Scheme. When they arrive in England<lb/>
they will receive very little sympathy<lb/>
from the English people, or ministry. The<lb/>
British Government will reply to them in<lb/>
this way : "Gentlemen, we knew this be<lb break="no"/>fore ; we have received information that<lb/>
the people of New Brunswick have reject<lb break="no"/>ed this Union, therefore we do not see the<lb/>
object of your mission." After they have<lb/>
received this rebuff they had better<lb/>
lengthen their excursion, and go to Africa.<lb/>
There, according to Dr. Livingston or<lb/>
Capt. Spoke, they will find little kingdoms<lb/>
with about 20,000 inhabitants holding<lb/>
their Courts with all the ceremony of lar<lb break="no"/>ger kingdoms, their interests all being<lb/>
centered in themselves, each one of these<lb/>
having its own peculiar habits and cus<lb break="no"/>toms, and it is their particular care to<lb/>
keep these distinctions up. There they<lb/>
will find the exact exemplification of the<lb/>
principles enunciated here. They are not<lb/>
willing to break down the barriers of trade<lb/>
and carry out the principles of liberalism<lb/>
and reform, neither are they willing to<lb/>
unite these Colonies and make them the<lb/>
germ of a mighty nation. They are not<lb/>
willing to do what would advance our best<lb/>
interests and prove a lasting benefit ; for<lb/>
to unite would prove a benefit whether we<lb/>
remain as a great Colonial Confederacy<lb/>
united under the British Government, or<lb/>
whether we adopt the other alternative<lb/>
and drift into Annexation. I can imagine<lb/>
the feelings of this delegation on their re<lb break="no"/>turn, after finding the matter had been<lb/>
fairly discussed in the House of Commons.<lb/>
Homeward bound, they will repeat the old<lb/>
nursery rhyme:—
</p>

            <pb n="130" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_130.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">130</fw>   <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>         

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p> " The
King of France with twenty thous<lb break="no"/>and men,<lb/>
Marched up the hill and then marched<lb/>
down again."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p> It has been stated that those gentlemen <lb/>
who have taken a prominent part
in advo<lb break="no"/>cating this Scheme, are consulting their <lb/>
own interests by so doing ; it that is an <lb/>
argument, to be used against Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, it might as well apply to the people <lb/>
who voted for Union, which was to make <lb/>
these united Provinces one of
the bright<lb break="no"/>est jewels in the British Crown,
because <lb/>
by doing so they are advancing
their own <lb/>
interest. The hon. member from
St. John <lb/>
(Mr. Anglin) alluded to conspirators, and <lb/>
hidden intrigue. Now, I know no
such <lb/>
imputation applicable to any of the dele<lb break="no"/>gates ; it is true it was rumored at one<lb/>
time that a countryman of the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber's, and a man of brilliant talents, Mr. <lb/>
D'Arcy McGee, was at some former<lb/>
period of his history concerned in sedi<lb break="no"/>tious movements in Ireland ; that gentle<lb break="no"/>man has made the <hi rendition="simple:italic">amend honourable</hi>, and <lb/>
has well redeemed his character for
loyal<lb break="no"/>ty. Conspiracy ! treason and stratagems
! <lb/>
cries the hon. member. My belief
is, that <lb/>
if there exists any treasons and stratagems, <lb/>
they are connected with the <hi rendition="simple:italic">spoils</hi>
at the<lb/>
present time. It is all a false alarm. <lb/>
Like <choice><sic>Shakspear</sic></choice><corr>Shakespeare</corr>'s Macbeth : <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p> " Is this a dagger, which I see before me,<lb/>
The handle toward my hand? Come let <lb/>
me clutch thee ;<lb/>
I have thee not, and yet I see thee still.<lb/>
Art thou.not, fatal vision, sensible<lb/>
To feeling as to sight ? or art thou
but<lb/>
A dagger of the mind ; a false creation<lb/>
Proceeding from the heat oppressed
brain?<lb/>
I see thee yet, In form as palpable<lb/>
As <hi rendition="simple:italic">this</hi> whish now <hi rendition="simple:italic">I</hi> draw." <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p> There is nothing to be gained by send<lb break="no"/>ing this delegation to England to
express <lb/>
the state of public feeling, because that <lb/>
expression is known there, and
it has been <lb/>
stated in the London <hi rendition="simple:italic">Times</hi> that
there is <lb/>
no intention to coerce the people of this <lb/>
Province. Then why is it that
150,000 <lb/>
Confederates are to be taxed to send a <lb/>
delegation home to misconstrue their <lb/>
opinions ? What great measure, in
so <lb/>
short a period of time has ever taken such <lb/>
a firm hold upon the people of the country <lb/>
as this has ? This great measure, im<lb break="no"/>proving the constitution of a country,
has <lb/>
received the approval of nearly one-half <lb/>
of the people of this Province, and in a <lb/>
short time there will be a majority in <lb/>
favor of it. We have shown that this <lb/>
Confederation would be a benefit to the <lb/>
people of this Province, politically,
com<lb break="no"/>mercially, financially and socially ; there<lb break="no"/>fore this delegation is
unnecessary. If <lb/>
these resolutions had to be passed in the <lb/>
Legislative Council, they would probably <lb/>
meet with the same fate as other mea<lb break="no"/>sures that have been tried to be foisted
<lb/>
upon the country during the
present year. <lb/>
We are not in a position to express by
a <lb/>
delegation of this Legislature, the exact <lb/>
state of public feeling which now exists, <lb/>
and which will exist six months
hence. <lb/>
A large majority of British North Ameri<lb break="no"/>ca have spoken out in favor of
this <lb/>
Scheme ; we are not in a position
to ex<lb break="no"/>press our views ; we have placed ourselves <lb/>
right in regard to our loyalty
by voting <lb/>
$30,000 for Militia purposes ; we are re<lb break="no"/>covering our positions and there is no
need<lb/>
of sending two or three men home to tell<lb/>
them what they know already. " Unless<lb/>
we can do a noble deed, in heaven's name<lb/>
let us be silent."</p>
            <p>Mr. OTTY.—I
think a part of <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
                 
from Shakespeare <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
              
            <cb/> 
         
 friend
has made is very applicable to the<lb/>
Scheme of Confederation, for I think Con<lb break="no"/>federation is <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p> — — " a false creation, <lb/>
Proceeding from the heat-oppress'd
brain." <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>I do not think it necessary to take long <lb/>
to discuss this subject. Some
years ago, <lb/>
when a proposition was made
by Mr.<lb/>
Howe for a Union of the North
American<lb/>
Colonies,
I thought it would be a benefit <lb/>
to us, by raising these
Provinces into a <lb/>
nationally. I was glad also when
I heard <lb/>
that this delegation had proceeded to <lb/>
Quebec to take into consideration this <lb/>
question ; but afterwards on
reflection I <lb/>
thought there would be found something
<lb/>
wrong in the details of the Scheme, for <lb/>
those thirty-three men had taken only <lb/>
seventeen days to consider a
subject of <lb/>
such vast importance, and those days <lb/>
were interspersed with feasting. This<lb/>
was a very short time compared with the<lb/>
time taken by the United States to frame<lb/>
their Constitution, they being four months
<lb/>
in actual session, therefore I
considered <lb/>
there would be some details in the Scheme <lb/>
that would not bear the light. I was <lb/>
more confirmed in this view when I read <lb/>
the resolutions which they had adopted <lb/>
carefully and considerately, for I found <lb/>
that New Brunswick would be swamped <lb/>
in the Legislative Assembly, we
being <lb/>
only allowed the small number of fifteen
<lb/>
members, the whole number of members <lb/>
being 194. But the advocates of
the <lb/>
Scheme say there is a check to this in<lb break="no"/>fluence in the Legislative Council ; but if <lb/>
you read the l4th Section of these reso<lb break="no"/>lutions you will find only the first selec<lb break="no"/>tion of Councillors are to be taken from <lb/>
the Legislative Councillors of
the Prov<lb break="no"/>inces, and any subsequently appointed <lb/>
may be selected from Canada to represent <lb/>
the Lower Provinces. The 16th Section <lb/>
says : " Each of the twenty-four Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive Councillors representing Lower Cana<lb break="no"/>da in the Legislative Council of the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Assembly shall be
appointed to repre<lb break="no"/>sent one the twenty-four
Electoral <lb/>
Divisions. * * * and shall reside or <lb/>
possess his qualification in the division he <lb/>
is appointed to represent." That clause <lb/>
affects Lower Canada only. The
Coun<lb break="no"/>cillors of every other section of the Union <lb/>
may be appointed—after the death
of the <lb/>
present Councillors—from
the residents of <lb/>
Canada. That is a very serious defect in <lb/>
the Scheme, for it allows Councillors to <lb/>
be selected from any district, and they <lb/>
may have no interest in the
Province they <lb/>
represent. In the United States
their <lb/>
Senators are elected from their represen<lb break="no"/>tatives, and they are well fitted
to repre<lb break="no"/>sent their own particular State.
It is <lb/>
said that the people are not educated on <lb/>
this subject. In the County
of King's, <lb/>
during the late election, every means was <lb/>
taken to provide information for the <lb/>
people, and it speaks well for that Coun<lb break="no"/>ty, that when I, a new man, who had never <lb/>
taken any interest in political life, came <lb/>
before them as a candidate for their suf<lb break="no"/>frages, they returned me, giving me nearly <lb/>
300 votes over their favorite
candidate, <lb/>
who had represented them so many years. <lb/>
This shows the opinion of the people
in <lb/>
that County on Confederation. To
go <lb/>
over all the arguments against
this <lb/>
Scheme would take more time than we
<lb/>
have at our disposal ; but there
is one item <lb/>
particularly objectionable, that is the 51st <lb/>
Section. According to that, any law which<lb/>
we may pass, if it happen to conflict with<lb/>
the interest of Canada, can be disallowed<lb/>
at any time within one year after it has<lb/>
passed our Legislature. We give up our<lb/>
dearest right, the right of taxation, over<lb/>
          

            <cb/>

        
 which we have no control. for it would 
<lb/>
pass into the hands of Canada, and she <lb/>
could use such a system of taxation as she <lb/>
pleased. We get eighty cents per
head <lb/>
for giving up all our revenue. This is <lb/>
not enough to support our roads, schools,<lb/>
and bridges, therefore we will have to re<lb break="no"/>sort to direct taxation. <lb/>
            </p>


            <p> Mr.HILL.—I
rise for the purpose of <lb/>
replying to some of the remarks
made by <lb/>
my hon. friend from the County of Albert, <lb/>
(Mr. McClellan). I do not intend to go <lb/>
over them all, for at least two-thirds to go<lb/>
his speech has been upon matters entirely <lb/>
foreign to the subject under consideration. <lb/>
He has dealt with matters connected with <lb/>
himself and the President of the Council ; <lb/>
it will not be expected that I will follow<lb/>
him upon those points. I will reply now <lb/>
to one allusion which he made. He
ad<lb break="no"/>vised the delegates to extend their trip to <lb/>
Africa. I think that comparison
will <lb/>
scarcely apply, because even
under this <lb/>
Union these little courts will be held, <lb/>
having less influence than they now have.
<lb/>
His proposed Confederation will be very <lb/>
much like the case of Austria, which is <lb/>
burdened down by a heavy debt which has <lb/>
not been caused by external war, but by <lb/>
internal dissention. The Empire is com<lb break="no"/>posed of Provinces, with different interests <lb/>
and different languages, and they do not <lb/>
work harmoniously together. We find <lb/>Hungary and Italy breaking out into re<lb break="no"/>bellion ; we find the country loaded down <lb/>
with debt, simply because they are con<lb break="no"/>federated together, with no interests in <lb/>
common, but alienated one from another. <lb/>
He (Mr. McClellan) said that the delega<lb break="no"/>tion had as much right to confer on a <lb/>
Union of the Colonies making a total <lb/>
change in our position as a people, as a <lb/>
delegation had to go to England to make <lb/>
arrangements on railway matters. If a <lb/>
delegation went to England to
make ar<lb break="no"/>rangements on railway matters, it was to <lb/>
make arrangements for the construction of
<lb/>
a railway, already authorized by the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, and had there been the
subject of <lb/>
discussion. It was entirely different from <lb/>
the delegation going to Quebec to take <lb/>
into consideration the making of arrange<lb break="no"/>ments which were to change our whole <lb/>
political condition. I have doubts as to <lb/>
the constitutionality of the course taken <lb/>
by the late Government and delegates in <lb/>
this matter. The hon. gentleman says <lb/>
we have not a written Constitution, and <lb/>
it is liable to be changed—every Act of <lb/>
the Legislature being a change.
This is <lb/>
true, and it is true of the British Consti<lb break="no"/>tution ; but was any Constitution ever <lb/>
changed by the action of self-appointed <lb/>
delegates. My hon. friend says this <lb/>
Scheme was defeated on account of
the <lb/>
unpopularity of the Government. This
<lb/>
has only lately been discovered. 
<lb/>
            </p>




            <p>Mr. MCCLELLAN.—I did not make that<lb/>
statement. I was replying to a statement <lb/>
of the President of the Council, and I <lb/>
said that as a distinct question outside of <lb/>
politics, when the people understood it, <lb/>
they would sustain it by a large majority. <lb/>
            </p>




            <p> Mr. HILL.—With
regard to the un<lb break="no"/>popularity of the Government, I do
not<lb/>
know whether they had any influence in <lb/>
the County of Albert ; but I
know Con<lb break="no"/>federation received a large
amount of <lb/>
support from the people
throughout the <lb/>
Province in consequence of the
influence <lb/>
of the Government. I do not accuse that <lb/>
Government of sinister motives. I do not<lb/>
believe they really wanted to sell the<lb/>
country ; and I think if they had be<lb break="no"/>lieved that the measure would really have<lb/>
been injurious, they would not have urged<lb/>
it upon the country : but I believe the<lb/>
views of men are modified by views of<lb/>
         


            <pb n="131" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_131.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">131</fw>

          their own interest, and they took a view<lb/>
of this question from a wrong stand-point.<lb/>
The Government had a strong influence<lb/>
in support of Confederation, even when<lb/>
not directly exercised, because men who <lb/>
did not understand the question would sup<lb break="no"/>port the measure as they considered that<lb/>
it must be a good Scheme, for the members<lb/>
of the Government who had given the<lb/>
subject every consideration had
supported<lb/>
it. The hon. member has also said that<lb/>
the influence of the President of the <lb/>
Council was as great in regard to pro<lb break="yes"/>mising offices as the late
Government. <lb/>
There was no influence in this respect,<lb/>
for it was prophesied from the beginning <lb/>
of the election campaign that Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion would be carried ; the newspapers<lb/>
said that there would be twenty-six return<lb break="no"/>ed in favor of it at the very least, and even<lb/>
those opposed to the Scheme feared it<lb/>
would be carried. The Reverend Editor<lb/>
of a paper told us that a
majority would<lb/>
be returned in favor of Confederation,<lb/>
whether Charlotte elected men in support <lb/>
of it or not, and others said that if we
<lb/>
wished any favors from the Government, <lb/>
we must return men who would support<lb/>
them, as they were sure to be elected and<lb/>
have a majority in the House. This had<lb/>
a great effect in influencing the votes of<lb/>
the people in favor of the Scheme. Again, <lb/>
reference has been made to eclesiastical<lb/>
influence. In our County I am not aware <lb/>
of any clergyman taking any part in the<lb/>
elections ; but in the City of St. John, the<lb/>
organs of religious denominations were in<lb/>
favor of Confederation. They raised an<lb/>
issue that it was a question in which reli<lb break="no"/>gion was largely involved, and they had<lb/>
an influence among the people throughout<lb/>
the country. The hon. gentleman from<lb/>
Albert says why should we send this de<lb break="no"/>legation home, as Confederation is dead.<lb/>
I say we want to bury it and carry it face<lb/>
downwards, so deep that ti can never be<lb/>
resuscitated. I do not think it right that<lb/>
we should burden ourselves with debt,<lb/>
and deprive ourselves with all power to<lb/>
regulate our own affairs for the sake of<lb/>
giving twenty-five men a larger field in<lb/>
which to exhibit themselves. The more<lb/>
this Scheme is discussed the less favor it<lb/>
will find. The Government chose their<lb/>
own time ; they made their statements to<lb/>
the public first, they had the press in their<lb/>
favor, and they used every opportunity to<lb/>
bring their views before the country.<lb/>
The election took place in winter when<lb/>
the lumbermen were absent, and those <lb/>
who got to the polls had little informa<lb break="no"/>tion on this subject, therefore they had<lb/>
every advantage which their influence and <lb/>
position could give them. The proper <lb/>
method would have been to have submit<lb break="no"/>ted the question to a direct vote of the <lb/>
people, apart from all political
considera<lb break="no"/>tions,or the popularity of this or that <lb/>
candidate. My hon. friend said the ex<lb break="no"/>tension of the Canals in Canada
might <lb/>
be as popular in New Brunswick as in<lb/>
Canada. He has given us credit for a<lb/>
great deal of disinterestedness in stating<lb/>
that we would be willing to help build<lb/>
those Canals, which will have the effect of<lb/>
carrying the trade away from us. We are<lb/>
not generally so disinterested; the people<lb/>
of the North are not willing to be taxed<lb/>
to build Western Extension, unless it is<lb/>
to get something in return. The hon.<lb/>
gentleman says we should rise above the<lb/>
position of politicians into the position of<lb/>
statesmen ; he would have us rise above<lb/>
all considerations of the interests of our<lb/>
own Province. I say it is the duty of the<lb/>
statesmen of New Brunswick to look af<lb break="no"/>ter the welfare of their own Province.<lb/>
So far as business is concerned, Canada is<lb/>
       

            <cb/>      
 
     a foreign country to us. He says that<lb/>
we stand in the same position to Canada<lb/>
that the seaboard in the United States<lb/>
does to the great West. He must give<lb/>
us credit for a great deal of geographical<lb/>
ignorance in regard to the United States<lb/>
and Canada Railways. It is only 469<lb/>
miles from the City of Toronto to New<lb/>
York ; but it is by the Intercolonial Rail<lb break="no"/>way 1,100 miles to St. John, and goods<lb/>
will be sent to the nearest outlet. We are<lb/>
told this Intercolonial Railway is to cost<lb/>
us nothing, and it will develop our mines<lb/>
and minerals of Albert and Carleton<lb/>
Counties. I would ask what route it will<lb/>
take ? I have understood that it will take<lb/>
the central route, then it will pass through<lb/>
neither of these Counties. It has been<lb/>
said by a Canadian statesman that after<lb/>
the Intercolonial Railway was built, he<lb/>
would not undertake to run it, for the<lb/>
whole revenue of one of the Lower Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. My hon. friend dwelt upon the<lb/>
great advantage that would accrue to the<lb/>
people of this Province from the increas<lb break="no"/>ed market which we would have for man<lb break="no"/>ufactured articles ; but the fact is, that<lb/>
the manufactured articles of Canada sell<lb/>
on the upper St. John now at cheaper<lb/>
rates than those of home manufacture,<lb/>
notwithstanding the cost of transport and<lb/>
duty upon them. They can manufacture<lb/>
cheaper than we can, because labor and<lb/>
food are cheaper ; in addition to that they<lb/>
can get their raw material, iron and coal<lb/>
cheaper than we can ; inasmuch as many<lb/>
vessels leaving ports in England to go to<lb/>
Quebec, for the purpose of getting a cargo<lb/>
of timber, take out coal and iron at low<lb/>
freight as ballast ; therefore we find they<lb/>
are quoted cheaper there than in St. John,<lb/>
besides that they have the market and<lb/>
the consumers at their own door. I do<lb/>
not believe the manufacturers who signed<lb/>
that circular in St. John, had any idea of<lb/>
sending their goods to Canada, but they<lb/>
may have thought of sending them to<lb/>
Nova Scotia. All the advantages that<lb/>
would be gained by this Union, would be<lb/>
gained by free trade among the Lower<lb/>
Provinces, or a maritime Union. Great<lb/>
stress is laid upon the fact, that we obtain<lb/>
our flour from Canada. It was said by<lb/>
the hon. member from the County of Al<lb break="no"/>bert, that we would buy in the cheapest<lb/>
market and sell in the dearest. Quebec<lb/>
never will be the cheapest market for us<lb/>
to buy in, taking into consideration the<lb/>
cost of transport, and the fact that Lower<lb/>
Canada is not a grain producing country.<lb/>
If we wish to obtain it from Montreal we<lb/>
have to transport it a distance of 550<lb/>
miles, if we bring it by the Intercolonial<lb/>
Railway ; but it can be brought much<lb/>
cheaper to Portland, as the distance by<lb/>
the Grand Trunk Railway is but 290 miles<lb/>
and from there to St. John it can be<lb/>
brought at an additional cost of twen<lb break="no"/>ty-five cents per barrel. It is said they<lb/>
may put on certain restrictions that will<lb/>
prevant Canadian goods from finding an<lb/>
outlet. It is not to be supposed that the<lb/>
people of the United States will be so<lb/>
blind to their interests as to prevent the<lb/>
expenditure of millions of money in the<lb/>
transport of Canadian goods. It has been<lb/>
stated that this Scheme was rejected on<lb/>
account of the unpopularity of the late<lb/>
Government, this is not the case in our sec<lb break="no"/>tion of the country, for the Liberal party<lb/>
are there very popular ; but when this<lb/>
Scheme came up, our people said they<lb/>
would sacrifice the Liberal party for the<lb/>
sake of opposing Confederation. I am<lb/>
desirous of seeing this delegation because<lb/>
it is necessary to make use of some such<lb/>
means to correct the misrepresentations<lb/>
that have been made there by the Cana<lb break="no"/>
        

            <cb/>
           

dian delegates. There is one point on<lb/>

which I can agree with my hon. friend<lb/>
from the County of Albert, that is, in his<lb/>
choice of delegates ; he thinks the hon.<lb/>
Mr. Smith and the hon. Mr. Anglin<lb/>
are the proper persons to go on this dele<lb break="no"/>gation. There are no two men who so<lb/>
well represent the sentiments of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of New Brunswick on this question,<lb/>
and there are no two men who have done<lb/>
so much to oppose this Scheme, which<lb/>
would have brought so much evil upon<lb/>
the people of this Province. It has been<lb/>
said that the hon. President of the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil might have allowed a desire for posi<lb break="no"/>tion to influence his course. It is well<lb/>
known that this is not the case. He has<lb/>
made a sacrifice of his time and money<lb/>
for the good of the country ; he has de<lb break="no"/>voted his time and his ability to enlighten<lb/>
the people. If it is ambition, to have la<lb break="no"/>bor, care and anxiety for the benefit of the<lb/>
public without any remuneration, it is of<lb/>
an unblamable kind, and I wish we had<lb/>
more of it.</p>
            <p>Mr. MCCLELLAN.—I did not charge<lb/>
him with that. I said he was just as open<lb/>
to the charge of ambition as any other<lb/>
man.<lb/>

            </p>


            <p> Mr. HILL.—They tell us that anti-Confe<lb break="no"/>deration had but four or six hundred<lb/>
majority, and that is reported and<lb/>
reiterated and adopted as being the<lb/>
true state of things. It appears that<lb/>
the mantle of prophesy has fallen<lb/>
upon these gentlemen ; they tell us now<lb/>
as they they told us before the election<lb/>
that Confederation is sure to be carried.<lb/>
They are like Miller prophesying the de<lb break="no"/>struction of the world ; when the time<lb/>
comes for the prophesy to be fulfilled they<lb/>
prophesy anew. These gentlemen imi<lb break="no"/>tate the rallying cry of Mahomet, " Great<lb/>
is Allah and Mahomet is his Prophet,"<lb/>
and substitute " Great is Confederation<lb/>
and many are its profits." But the profits<lb/>
would be to Canada and the expense to New<lb/>
Brunswick and the other Maratime Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. Much stress has been laid by the ad<lb break="no"/>vocates of Confederation upon the military<lb/>
and defence portion of the question. We<lb/>
have been told that we were in danger of<lb/>
being swallowed up by the United States,<lb/>
and that we must unite with Canada in<lb/>
order to place ourselves in a position to<lb/>
repel any attack from that quarter. The<lb/>
Monroe doctrine, in all its terrors, has<lb/>
been harped upon. Do these gentlemen<lb/>
know what the doctrine is, and where it<lb/>
originated ? Do they know that it emu<lb break="no"/>lated from the British Government, and<lb/>
that its promulgation was urged by that<lb/>
Government through its Minister at Wash<lb break="no"/>ington upon the Cabinet of President<lb/>
Munroe. France had formed an alliance<lb/>
with Spain, and one of the objects of that<lb/>
alliance was the reconquest of the Spanish<lb/>
American Colonies, for the purpose of<lb/>
again bringing them under the domina<lb break="no"/>tion of the Latin races. The British<lb/>
Ministry, anxious to prevent the success<lb/>
of this Scheme, strongly pressed upon the<lb/>
American Government the adoption of<lb/>
that policy, which was almost immediate<lb break="no"/>ly accepted by President Monroe, and em<lb break="no"/>bodied in his famous message to Con<lb break="no"/>gress. This policy, then first declared, was<lb/>
that the United States would not consent<lb/>
to the establishment of any Foreign<lb/>
Power upon American soil, and that they<lb/>
would not, without resistance, allow any<lb/>
European nation to obtain <hi rendition="simple:italic">further</hi> foothold<lb/>
in America beyond that <hi rendition="simple:italic">already existing</hi>.<lb/>
And now, while the establishment of<lb/>
Maximilian by French aid in Mexico is<lb/>
an infringement of policy so laid down,<lb/>
the British North American Provinces do<lb/>
not come within its restriction and it was

            <pb n="132" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_132.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">132</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>

        never intended to be applied to them. I<lb/>
do not believe that we are in danger of <lb/>
being attached by the United States. <lb/>
Every expression of sentiment by
the <lb/>
leaders of public opinion in that country <lb/>
is opposed to such a course. We heard <lb/>
Henry Ward Beecher, on the first day of
<lb/>
the present year, saying to his congrega<lb break="no"/>tion : " I am not for war with any nation, <lb/>
and that man is not my friend
who de<lb break="no"/>clares war against the people of our <lb/>
Fatherland. All that is dearest to us, of <lb/>
what we brought hither, we
brought from <lb/>
thence, Laws and Institutions, and Chris<lb break="no"/>tian civilization, and woe be to the day <lb/>
that begets estrangement between the <lb/>
Christians of England and the Christians <lb/>
of America !" We hear Secretary Seward, <lb/>
when addressing the crowd who were <lb/>
congratulating him on the surrender of <lb/>
General Lee, saying that as long as Cana<lb break="no"/>da preferred remaining under the rule of <lb/>
her noble Queen, to voluntary
incorpora<lb break="no"/>tion in the United States, she
was safe <lb/>
from attack from them. But in case of <lb/>
invasion, how shall we be secured in Con<lb break="no"/>federation. It is proposed to
expend a <lb/>
million dollars for defence. Why that is <lb/>
just about six hours of the expenditure by <lb/>
the American Government during the last
<lb/>
two years—they have averaged
over two <lb/>
millions per day; during the last week the <lb/>
tramps of two hundred thousand men has
<lb/>
resounded thro' the streets of Washington, <lb/>
besides the tens of thousands of soldiers <lb/>
scattered from Maine to the Rio Grande.
<lb/>
We should have two thousand miles of <lb/>
sea coast, and three thousand miles of <lb/>
land and lake frontier. Can Canada send <lb/>
us assistance when she has two
and a half <lb/>
millions of people, and the very States <lb/>
touching her frontier contain twelve mil<lb break="no"/>lions ? Can we in Confederation
with <lb/>
three millions of people defend ourselves <lb/>
against thirty millions, who have, by so <lb/>
many railroads and other means of com<lb break="no"/>munication such power of concentrating
<lb/>
their forces on our borders ? If
they have <lb/>
ten times our population have they not <lb/>
far more than ten times our power in all <lb/>
other resources of war, wealth and <lb/>
supplies, and all the vast implements
<lb/>
and machinery for warfare. But
shall <lb/>
we fall back on the old exploded false<lb break="no"/>hood, that the Yankees will not fight ? <lb/>
that one Englishman or Provincial would <lb/>
be equal to three. Has history taught us <lb/>
nothing ? Are we not descended from <lb/>
the one race ? A branch of that great Ar- <lb break="yes"/>
gan race, who from its earliest traditions in <lb/>
remote antiquity were a fighting people. <lb/>
Starting from the remote regions of Cen<lb break="no"/>tral Asia, whither in their migrations they <lb/>
overran the plains of Hindostan, or the <lb/>
forests of Germany, wherever they
laid <lb/>
their hands upon a people, it was the <lb/>
hand of a conqueror. And is not the <lb/>
Anglo Saxon the noblest branch from that <lb/>
race, either in the arts of war or of peace. <lb/>
I could never see why the Englishman,
<lb/>
the Irishman, the German, would not, <lb/>
with the same discipline fight as
well upon<lb/>
the western shore of the Atlantic, as upon <lb/>
the Eastern ; and I could never
see why <lb/>
an imaginary line of frontier
should make <lb/>
the Provincials so much better men than <lb/>
their American neighbors. But
because <lb/>
with such heavy odds against us,
I do not <lb/>
think that we should be able to repel an <lb/>
invasion from the United States.
I do <lb/>
not wish the gentlemen upon the opposite<lb/>
side of this question to think that the <lb/>
wish is father to the thought. I would <lb/>
that it were otherwise, more than any<lb break="no"/>thing earthly. I could desire that my<lb/>
own Province and country was strong <lb/>
enough to defy attack from any quarter.<lb/>
I would
go into Confederation with any 
            
            <cb/> 


sacrifice of political or financial
interests<lb/>
if I thought it would accomplish
this. I <lb/>
believe that I would gladly lay down my <lb/>
own life, if by so doing I could prevent <lb/>
the subjection of my country. But I <lb/>
cannot shut my eyes to facts that are pa<lb break="no"/>tent as the noon day sun. If it is loyalty <lb/>
to bury one's head like the ostrich and <lb/>
refuse to see what is clear to
all others, <lb/>
then am I open to the charge of disloyal<lb break="no"/>ty. But if it is loyalty to have
a strong <lb/>
love and admiration for England, for her <lb/>
history, her institutions and her literature, <lb/>
and to hope that her flag may always float  <lb/>
over these Provinces, and that I may al<lb break="no"/>ways live under her sway, then I am <lb/>
loyal. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr.
WETMORE.—I do not wish to be <lb/>
understood as stating my own merits, but <lb/>
having been returned by the grand empo<lb break="no"/>rium of this Province, I feel I
would but <lb/>
ill discharge my duty, being
placed to the <lb/>
high position which I occupy, did I not <lb/>
express my views on this great scheme of <lb/>
Confederation. It is true the matter
has <lb/>
been handled politically, commercially, <lb/>
and financially, very ably by the hon. <lb/>
gentlemen who have spoken on the
ques<lb break="no"/>tion. I will not take up the time by go<lb break="no"/>ing into minute details, but
shall express <lb/>
my views briefly and generally against the <lb/>
Scheme. In the first place it is said that <lb/>
there is no need of a delegation,
because <lb/>
the people of England are aware that the <lb/>
grand scheme of Confederation has
been <lb/>
defeated. It might be sufficient that the <lb/>
British Government in the exercise of <lb/>
their powers will have a consideration
for <lb/>
the constitutional rights which we have. <lb/>
But this is a matter on which discretion <lb/>
is to be exercised. It is said the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of this delegation is a concession to <lb/>
Confederation ; in like manner the build<lb break="no"/>ing of Penitentiaries is a concession to <lb/>
criminals. We have a law in this land to <lb/>
prevent the commission of crime ; but <lb/>
would a man, if he thought his house <lb/>
was going to be destroyed, if he did not <lb/>
take a reasonable means of defence, lie <lb/>
down on his bed satisfied as if the law was <lb/>
going to protect him ? I feel that where <lb/>
the constituency of this country has been <lb/>
maligned every effort should be
made to <lb/>
protect our rights and our homes in the <lb/>
land in which we live. It has
been
said <lb/>
by several hon. gentlemen that those who <lb/>
have been returned on the Anti-Confeder<lb break="no"/>ate ticket have been returned by the rab<lb break="no"/>ble. Several times this basest of slanders <lb/>
has been uttered. I have been returned <lb/>
as one of the representatives of
St. John, <lb/>
and I can say I have not been returned <lb/>
by a rabble. I represent more intelligence, <lb/>
wealth and independence than the Con<lb break="no"/>federation party can begin to boast of. It <lb/>
is a base, malignant slander, got up for <lb/>
the basest of purposes. I possess little <lb/>
influence in St. John, and was opposed to<lb/>
men who held high positions, men of po<lb break="no"/>litical standing who brought political and<lb/>
monetary influence to bear, and who had<lb/>
experience in elections for a number of<lb/>
years ; therefore it required a large amount<lb/>
of intelligence to return me to this posi<lb break="no"/>tion which I have the honor to hold. The<lb/>
election was not held upon any backsliding<lb/>
of the former Government ; it was con<lb break="no"/>ducted upon the question of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, or no Confederation. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had some slight amount of backslid<lb break="no"/>ings, but they sunk into insignificance and<lb/>
were never spoken of during the election ;<lb/>
our thoughts then were to protect our<lb/>
homes where we lived, for we felt they<lb/>
were about to be sacrificed. It may have<lb/>
been that the Government thought this<lb/>
Scheme was absolutely necessary for the<lb/>
interests of the people, or it may have<lb/>
   

            <cb/>   

 been that
designing men were seeking to<lb/>
aggrandize themselves at the expense of<lb/>
the dearest rights of the people ; that was<lb/>
the question, and it was the all-absorbing<lb/>
question, and fair, reasonable, and proper<lb/>
men were taken to explain to the people<lb/>
the nature of this Confederation, and the<lb/>
effect it would have upon the community.<lb/>
It was said that the Hon. President of the<lb/>
Council went about the country promis<lb break="no"/>ing offices to people to support his<lb/>
party, but wherever that gentleman's<lb/>
voice was heard, there was a declaration<lb/>
made in the papers that all he said<lb/>
amounted to nothing, and the people <lb/>
that advocated that scheme were
the <lb/>
people that must be returned to repre<lb break="no"/>sent the interests of this Province. If <lb/>
that was the case, is it a reasonable pro<lb break="no"/>position to suppose that any individual<lb/>
could hold out inducements to persons <lb/>
to join the opposition. There
was a fair <lb/>
canvass. I had something to do
with <lb/>
the election in St. John, and I never <lb/>
knew a fairer canvass conducted in my <lb/>
life. Public Meeetings were held by <lb/>
each party. While I say there was no <lb/>
influence on the part of the opposition, <lb/>
I may say all the Government influence
<lb/>
was used ; every thing was done that <lb/>
could be done to retain the
offices which <lb/>
they held. Was not this
celebrated <lb/>
"Cole's Island" operationa Government <lb/>
influence. Were these men aware
that <lb/>
the voice of the people should be the<lb/>
voice of the Government? Where the <lb/>
people had expressly declared
that no <lb/>
such undertaking would be conducive <lb/>
to the interests of the people. I cannot <lb/>
conceive how men, elected under the <lb/>
principles of responsible Government, <lb/>
can prostrate that influence, and use the <lb/>
people's money for electioneering pur<lb break="no"/>poses. It is said that the views
of the <lb/>
people of this Province have entirely <lb/>
changed on this question ; it is very well
<lb/>
to put forth this assertion, but we have <lb/>
to exercise our own judgement
whether <lb/>
to believe it or not. The late Solicitor <lb/>
General, in the City in which he lives, <lb/>
was proverbial for his popularity, and <lb/>
the greatest amount of sympathy was
<lb/>
felt for him when he lost his election <lb/>
and had to give up his office ; since then <lb/>
he was a candidate for the office of May<lb break="no"/>or in St. John ; his talents, integrity, and <lb/>
the length of time he had lived there <lb/>
gave him great influence, every effort <lb/>
was made to secure his election ; at the <lb/>
election of representatives he received <lb/>
1400 votes in the City of St. John, but <lb/>
now after this Confederation
scheme <lb/>
has been defeated, and the influence of <lb/>
the Government withdrawn, he received <lb/>
but 300 votes. Does this show
that those <lb/>
who were Confederates have altered <lb/>
their opinions and are now against the  <lb/>
scheme? It has been said by my hon.  <lb/>
friend from the County of Albert that<lb/>
the election was a matter of accident.<lb/>
I think it was so. I believe it was the<lb/>
intention of the leader of the Government<lb/>
not to submit this to the consideration of<lb/>
the people at all. It has been said that<lb/>
when these delegates returned from Can<lb break="no"/>ada they anticipated that there was a ma<lb break="no"/>jority in the House of Assembly who<lb/>
would carry this measure through. If it<lb/>
was the intention to submit it to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple, why was this election held over in the<lb/>
County of Northumberland ? It is said
<lb/>
that this delegation is not required ; that <lb/>
the Home Government know that the
peo<lb break="no"/>ple of this Province have pronounced <lb/>
against the Scheme. It might as well be <lb/>said, what is the use of the Canadians <lb/>
sending home a delegation ? The  Home <lb/>
Government know that the Canadians have <lb/>
            

            <pb n="133" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_133.jpg"/>
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">133</fw>          

passed
resolutions concerning a Federal<lb/>
Union, and they can be signed and for<lb break="no"/>warded to them. When the Canadian<lb/>
delegates met at Halifax there was a torch<lb/>
light procession took place ; what had they<lb/>
done for Nova Scotia that they should be<lb/>
accorded this honor ? Was it not done<lb/>
to influence the public in England, and<lb/>
lead them to believe that a reaction had<lb/>
taken place ? Why did not the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Nova Scotia bring in the ques<lb break="no"/>tion, and propound it as a Government<lb/>
measure? or if they were not satisfied<lb/>
without submitting it to the people, why<lb/>
did not they dissolve the House, and get<lb/>
an expression of opinion from the people ?<lb/>
It was because they knew beyond the<lb/>
shadow of a doubt, that it must be de<lb break="no"/>feated. Then in regard to the Intercolo<lb break="no"/>nial Railway ; a fair and equitable arrange<lb break="no"/>ment as could be made between man and<lb/>
man was made between the Provinces for<lb/>
the construction of that road. This road<lb/>
would have been of great advantage to<lb/>
the people of Nova Scotia, though I doubt<lb/>
whether it would help us much ; yet that<lb/>
agreement having been made, it was bind<lb break="no"/>ing upon all parties, but Canada violated<lb/>
her trust, and her honor politically had<lb/>
been scattered to the winds. Then what<lb/>
had these Canadian delegates done for<lb/>
Nova Scotia, that they should be honored<lb/>
with a torch-light procession ? One of<lb/>
our distinguished men was among that<lb/>
party, and he was honored in the same<lb/>
way. What had he done for Nova Scotia ?<lb/>
What was his position then? Defeated<lb/>
in his election ; the people had spoken in<lb/>
a voice of thunder, and said they had no<lb/>
confidence in his party. Why then this<lb/>
" torch-light procession?" It was done<lb/>
that a great outcry might be raised on<lb/>
the other side of the water ; that the op<lb break="no"/>position go their election by accident ;<lb/>
that the voice of the people was against<lb/>
them ; that if the question of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion was again submitted to the people<lb/>
their position would be reversed. This<lb/>
being the case, is it a proper course to be<lb/>
silent, because we have expressed our<lb/>
opinion, and allow those men to make mis<lb break="no"/>representations concerning the state of<lb/>
feeling in this country on that question,<lb/>
with nobody to counteract their influence;<lb/>
we must not trust to existing right alone,<lb/>
but we must take all reasonable precau<lb break="no"/>tion. What is the use of troops if people<lb/>
are to depend upon mere existing right,<lb/>
without taking means to enforce that right?<lb/>
Therefore, to send a delegation is a mat<lb break="no"/>ter of the greatest importance. I only re<lb break="no"/>gret that this delegation had not been sent<lb/>
a little earlier. With reference to the re<lb break="no"/>solutions which authorized those gentle<lb break="no"/>men to go to Prince Edward Island to<lb/>
meet other delegates to discuss a Union<lb/>
of the Maritime Provinces, I would say<lb/>
that when I find men disposed to violate<lb/>
one right, I would be loth to put trust in<lb/>
them again. We find these men who<lb/>
were elected on the principles of Respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government, and who boasted that<lb/>
they entertained the confidence of the<lb/>
people, go forth with the resolutions of<lb/>
the House of Assembly, and, through<lb/>
Canadian influence, treat those resolutions<lb/>
with the most consummate contempt. These<lb/>
delegates then proceeded to Quebec,<lb/>
where a meeting took place, not autho<lb break="no"/>rized by the people of the Province or by<lb/>
the British Government, as the Hon. ex-<lb break="yes"/>
Surveyor says, for they had left for Que<lb break="no"/>bec before the dispatch came out.</p>
            <p>Mr. MCMILLAN.—I did not refer to that<lb/>
dispatch. I referred to a despatch sent<lb/>
out in 1862 regarding a Union of these<lb/>
Colonies.</p>
            <p>Mr. WETMORE.—The Governor of Nova

            <cb/>
          
 Scotia did feel
authorized to send<lb/>
delegates without the express direction of<lb/>
the Colonial Secretary, but they had de<lb break="no"/>parted before they received a dispatch<lb/>
authorizing them.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> Mr. MCMILLAN.— By what power were<lb/>
they appointed ; if the Governor did not<lb/>
appoint them, who did ? <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Hon. Mr. ANGLIN.—The Lieutenant<lb/>
Governor of Nova Scotia when appealed<lb/>
to by the Governor General, at first re<lb break="no"/>fused to send delegates until he could get<lb/>
authority from Mr. Cardwell. Afterwards<lb/>
he wrote to
the Colonial Secretary, stating<lb/>
that he was satisfied that the Governor<lb/>
General was acting with the knowledge<lb/>
and sanction of the Imperial Government ;<lb/>
therefore, he had complied with his invita<lb break="no"/>tion, and sent delegates to the Conference.<lb/>
because if he had withheld his consent,<lb/>
Nova Scotia could not have been repre<lb break="no"/>sented. </p>
            <p>Mr. MCMILLAN.—Was he not aware of<lb/>
the fact that he was acting under the dis<lb break="no"/>patch of 1862?</p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. ANGLIN.—Although the Lieu<lb break="no"/>tenant Governor of Nova Scotia knew<lb/>
that despatch was in existence, still he<lb/>
did not feel authorized to send them.</p>
            <p>Mr. WETMORE.—The action of those de<lb break="no"/>legates was a direct violation of the princi<lb break="no"/>ples of Responsible Government, for it<lb/>
was their business and duty to attend to<lb/>
what the people sent them to look after,<lb/>
and that consideration was not given that<lb/>
should have been given to the voice of the<lb/>
people of this Province. They treated<lb/>
those resolutions with the greatest con<lb break="no"/>tempt, and in direct violation of them they<lb/>
go to Canada at great expense to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of this Province, and there mature a<lb/>
scheme to destroy and sacrifice the coun<lb break="no"/>try in which they live. I believe it was<lb/>
those delegates' intention to cram the<lb/>
scheme down the throats of the people of<lb/>
this Province ; therefore, there was an<lb/>
unpardonable violation of our rights, and<lb/>
the people did well to express their opin<lb break="no"/>ion at the polls. It is said the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the present day is a matter of<lb/>
accident ; but I consider it a most fortu<lb break="no"/>nate circumstance, for it saved the coun<lb break="no"/>try. In reference to this Intercolonial<lb/>
Railway going to be of so much advantage<lb/>
to us, I have listened with great attention<lb/>
to the arguments of many public men ex<lb break="no"/>pressed at public meetings at St. John,<lb/>
and I have endeavored to bring the best<lb/>
judgment I could to bear upon the sub<lb break="no"/>ject, but I failed to discover that we would<lb/>
commercially derive any benefit from it.<lb/>
It is said that there is a large amount of<lb/>
money to be expended upon this road if<lb/>
we go into Confederation, and it will cost<lb/>
us a very small amount indeed, but what<lb/>
is the difference who pays the cost, as they<lb/>
are going to take our money from us.<lb/>
Suppose they do expend a large sum of<lb/>
money in the country, it will be spent<lb/>
among the railway navvies and contrac<lb break="no"/>tors, creating extravagant habits and<lb/>
causing drinking shops to be set up, thus<lb/>
doing a wrong and an injury to the<lb/>
country. What are we going to carry<lb/>
upon that Railway ? I have listened with<lb/>
patience, but have listened in vain, to hear<lb/>
any arguments to prove that we will de<lb break="no"/>rive any commercial benefit from it. My<lb/>
impression is, that it will go by the North<lb/>
Shore route ; my hon. friend from St.<lb/>
John thinks it will go by the middle<lb/>
route. If the Government did not know<lb/>
by which route it was going, was it fair<lb/>
between man and man to state to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of the North Shore that it was going<lb/>
by that route? If it was true, I do not<lb/>
blame them for getting the benefit of it;<lb/>
but if it was false, and there was no rea<lb break="no"/>
       

            <cb/>
       

sonable ground for the statement, was it a<lb/>
fair canvass to make the statement when<lb/>
they knew it to be false ? Then, again :<lb/>
was there any thing to justify the asser<lb break="no"/>tion that it was going by the Sussex route?<lb/>
This question of the railway route was a<lb/>
political fiddle with three strings: there<lb/>
was the North Shore string, the Central<lb/>
string, and the Southern string; put that<lb/>
and the Coles'
Island operation together, <lb/>
and I say it was not a fair
canvass, for the <lb/>
question was not treated on the broad <lb/>
principles of
Confederation alone. Then <lb/>
in reference to the trade on the Interco<lb break="no"/>lonial Railway, we have nothing to send<lb/>
to Canada that they do not have.
It has<lb/>
been said that our shipping interest will <lb/>
be increased.. Who ever heard of a Ca<lb break="no"/>nadian buying a New Brunswick
ship, or <lb/>
a New Brunswicker buying a Canadian <lb/>
ship? We cannot compete with Cana<lb break="no"/>dian manufactures, for ours are in an in<lb break="no"/>fant state ; this opinion was expressed in <lb/>
1862 by some of the most prominent ad<lb break="no"/>vocates of the present scheme. Suppose <lb/>
I have a mill on one side of the Resti<lb break="no"/>gouche River, and have to pay a heavy <lb/>
debt,
and my hon. friend from that county <lb/>
has a mill on the other, free
from debt, <lb/>
can I compete with him under those cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances, and sell my lumber as cheap <lb/>
as he can ? If we employ the same num<lb break="no"/>ber of hands and the same amount of <lb/>
capital, and he gets his logs near his
mill <lb/>
and I have to bring mine
from a distance, <lb/>
I cannot begin to compete
with him. <lb/>
Suppose we have
manufacturers in this <lb/>
country,
with the same facilities and same<lb/>
number of hands employed as the Cana<lb break="no"/>dians, we cannot sell as cheap as they do, <lb/>
from the fact that the
market is in Canada <lb/>
and we have to pay the cost of
transport. <lb/>
We have to get our flour from Canada, <lb/>
and have to pay so much money for it ; <lb/>
that is the same as if we had to pay so <lb/>
much debt. But in Canada they produce <lb/>
their own flour ; therefore, we cannot feed <lb/>
our operatives as cheaply as they can in <lb/>
Canada, where they have their flour and <lb/>
market at their own door. Therefore, we <lb/>
can send nothing to Canada on this In<lb break="no"/>tercolonial Railway—neither
will the Ca<lb break="no"/>nadians send their flour by
that route, be<lb break="no"/>cause they can send it much cheaper by <lb/>
way
of Portland. Then we are told
that, <lb/>
in a military point of view, it is im<lb break="no"/>portant
that this road should be <lb/>
constructed, because
the Yankees are <lb/>
going to gobble us up. It
was anticipated <lb/>
that the revolution in America was draw<lb break="no"/>ing to a close ; and, while they had this <lb/>
large army unemployed, they would make <lb/>
an onslaught on these
Provinces. I do <lb/>
not believe for one moment that that great <lb/>
nation, because
they had the power, would <lb/>
make power right, and attempt to invade <lb/>
us. What object would it be
to that <lb/>
mighty
nation to invade these insignificant <lb/>
Provinces ; we were told that the
Ameri<lb break="no"/>cans were to be upon us immediately, and <lb/>
we wanted this railway for military pur<lb break="no"/>poses. How long would it take to
con<lb break="no"/>struct that railway ? It could
not, and <lb/>
would not be done in ten years ; and it is <lb/>
not to be supposed that the Americans, if <lb/>
were rapacious enough to invade
us, <lb/>
would put their soldiers in camp and feed <lb/>
them for ten years in order that we could <lb/>
get our railway built, so that we
could send <lb/>
our soldiers up to Canada to have a fight.
<lb/>
We are told that " Union is strength
;" <lb/>
no doubt some kinds of union are
strength. <lb/>
I will call the attention of the hon. Pre<lb break="no"/>sident of the Council to that fact ; but <lb/>
there is a union that is not strength. I
<lb/>
believe a Commercial Union between<lb/>
New Brunswick and Nova Scotia would<lb/>
strength us, as we have been in the  ha<lb break="no"/>
        

            <pb n="134" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-03_Page_134.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">134</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>
     
bit of dealing and trading with each <lb/>
other, and no inconvenience would arise <lb/>
from this union. If you take two bean <lb/>
poles and bind them together, you <lb/>
strengthen them, but if you put them <lb/>
end to end, it does not increase their <lb/>
strength. This Union between Upper and <lb/>
Lower Canada, has been like a cat
and <lb/>
dog union ; and they want to get
us to <lb/>
help them out of the scrape. The
popu<lb break="no"/>lation of Upper Canada increases very<lb/>
rapidly, and as representation
is by pop<lb break="no"/>ulation, we would soon be entirely <lb/>
swamped, and if the Canadians
wished to <lb/>
make an advantageous bargain with the <lb/>
United States, they could give up the <lb/>
fisheries of New Brunswick for the sake <lb/>
of getting an additional advantage for <lb/>
themselves. We are promised eighty <lb/>
cents a head on the population. We are <lb/>
to have $63,000 for ten years, our debt is <lb/>
to be increased to $7,000,000,
and a large <lb/>
amount of money is to be expended on the <lb/>
Intercolonial Railway ; but what security <lb/>
have we that those promises will be per<lb break="no"/>formed ? Ireland was induced to
unite <lb/>
with England in consequence of
certain <lb/>
inducements being held out. They
were <lb/>
promised Catholic emancipation, but how <lb/>
many years was it before they got it, and <lb/>
at what an expense of
heart-burnings be<lb break="no"/>fore it was accomplished, twenty-nine <lb/>
years after this union was established. <lb/>
This union was with a power celebrated <lb/>
for its integrity, but it was only after the <lb/>
most desperate efforts that Ireland
could <lb/>
succeed in getting what she was promis<lb break="no"/>ed as a condition for her entering this <lb/>
union. We, on the contrary, are
asked <lb/>
to unite with a people, that have tricked <lb/>
us once in regard to this Intercolonial
<lb/>
Railway, and should not trust their <lb/>
promises again. Then in reference
to this <lb/>
eighty cents a head ; as our population
in<lb break="no"/>creases, our wants increase, and we re<lb break="no"/>quire a larger expenditure for roads, <lb/>
schools and bridges ; but
instead of get<lb break="no"/>ting more we actually get less,
for we get <lb/>
$63,000 a-year for ten years, and is it to <lb/>
be supposed we will not want it eleven <lb/>
years hence. In a hundred years
hence, our <lb/>
population will have increased very large<lb break="no"/>ly, and our revenues will have increased <lb/>
immensely, for the people of this-Province
<lb/>
consume more duitable articles than
Ca<lb break="no"/>nada ; therefore, it is an
outrage to say <lb/>
we shall receive only this small
amount, <lb/>
eighty cents a head on the population of <lb/>
1861. It is our duty to legislate for those <lb/>
who come after us ; and it is
our duty as <lb/>
statesmen not to give up our country to <lb/>
gratify a few vain individuals. When we <lb/>
find men, who, instead of
looking after <lb/>
the interests of the people who have ele<lb break="no"/>vated them to a high position,
attempt to <lb/>
fly to still higher, their flight
is generally <lb/>
downwards, like that of a man who went <lb/>
to the top of a house with paper
wings to <lb/>
make a bird of himself. This has been <lb/>
the case with statesmen before, and will <lb/>
be so again. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">T. P. D. 
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2017-04-20, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
  
            <!--<p> MONDAY, June 5. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. LANDRY.—I
did not intend to say a <lb/>
word on this subject, and should
not do <lb/>
so now but to reply to a statement put
<lb/>
forth by the hon. member for
Albert, (Mr. <lb/>
McClellan) that the priests used their in<lb break="no"/>fluence with the people to get them to <lb/>
oppose
Confederation at the last elections. <lb/>
I know that it was not so in Westmorland
<lb/>
at any rate, for there they took no part <lb/>
whatever, either for or against. Some <lb/>
great men from St. John came up round <lb/>
our County, lecturing and talking
to the <lb/>
people to get them to support the Scheme, <lb/>
and they went on so that the
people <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p> thought they were mad. It has been <lb/>
said that if the question were to be sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to the people again in six months <lb/>
there would be a change. I think there <lb/>
would be too, but the change would be<lb/>
that there would be more opposed to the<lb/>
measure than ever.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> Mr. KERR.—A
great deal of time has<lb/>
been taken up in this discussion,
and a<lb/>
large amount of money lost to the country<lb/>
by it. I thought that the country had<lb/>
spoken out so loudly that Confederation<lb/>
was not only dead but buried face down<lb break="no"/>ward, and so deep that, as the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Charlotte said, it would not appear<lb/>
again at least for a long time. It seems,<lb/>
however, that it is not so from these reso<lb break="no"/>lutions, and the appointment of new dele<lb break="no"/>gates. In Northumberland there were<lb/>
seven candidates in the field ; six for Con<lb break="no"/>federation and one against. I
conceived<lb/>
at that time that from the threats made <lb/>
against us by the neighbouring republic,<lb/>
and the intimation that the protection of<lb/>
the mother country would likely be with<lb break="no"/>drawn from us in care of difficulties aris<lb break="no"/>ing, that it was necessary we
should con<lb break="no"/>tinue our united emerges to establish a<lb/>
power in these Colonies whose influence<lb/>
might be felt. Under these circumstances,<lb/>
I was constrained to support a Scheme <lb/>
that would not only thus unite us, but con<lb break="no"/>tinue to us that powerful protection
that<lb/>
we so much need. I have not changed<lb/>
my opinions since then. I believe that<lb/>
Canada is destined to be a great country ;<lb/>
she already pays half a million of dollars<lb/>
to support a line of Steam Ships to and<lb/>
from England, and then look at the mag<lb break="no"/>nitude of her public works. It has
been<lb/>
put forth by those opposed to Union that<lb/>
she is heavily in debt ; there
is no doubt <lb/>
of that, but then she has claims on the <lb/>
different Railways and other works of <lb/>
$40,000,000 or $50,000,000, and
the<lb/>
amount really due her is more than the<lb/>
interest on her whole debt. I believe that<lb/>
both the evils and benefits that would<lb/>
arise from a Union have been very much<lb/>
exaggerated. Let us now come down
to<lb/>
the Resolutions before us. Since Res<lb break="no"/>ponsible Government was first established <lb/>
here, we have never been called to delib<lb break="no"/>erate on such a Resolution. I say there<lb/>
has never been a case where the House<lb/>
has been asked to appoint delegates to go<lb/>
to England to lay before that people and <lb/>
Government the position and
state of this<lb/>
Province. Last Session delegates were<lb/>
appointed to take into
consideration a<lb/>
Union of the Maritime Provinces,
and a<lb/>
few days ago the Hon. President of the<lb/>
Council brought in a Resolution to con<lb break="no"/>tinue those negociations ; but notwith<lb break="no"/>standing the principle of the
Initiation of<lb/>
money grants being entirely in the hands<lb/>
of the Government, we now find a private<lb/>
member of the House comes forward with<lb/>
Resolutions which, if carried, involves <lb/>
the expenditure of a large sum
of money,<lb/>
we do not know how much. I say it is<lb/>
against the principle established by this<lb/>
House that a matter of this kind should<lb/>
be taken out of the hands of
Government.<lb/>
With regard to what has been said about
a<lb/>
power to be brought to bear on
us to force<lb/>
us into this Union, I do not
believe any<lb break="no"/>thing of the kind is
contemplated. Eng<lb break="no"/>land never did bring any power to bear <lb/>
to force her dependencies or
colonies to<lb/>
unite either with her or among themselves.<lb/>
In Scotland the matter was left
entirely in<lb/>
the hands of the Local Government, and <lb/>
the same in Ireland ; no power
was brought <lb/>
to bear upon them to force them to unite<lb/>
with England. <lb/>
            </p>
  



            <p>Hon. Mr.
ANGLIN.— Only a strong
out<lb break="no"/>side pressure. <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p> Mr. KERR.—Neither Nova Scotia nor<lb/>
Prince Edward Island, have appointed<lb/>
delegates to go Home, and why should<lb/>
we ? I do not believe that having conce<lb break="no"/>ded to us the power of self-Government,<lb/>
the Imperial Parliament will compel us to<lb/>
take any action with regard to Union that<lb/>
is opposed to the wishes of the people. I<lb/>
do not agree with the statement set forth<lb/>
in the Resolution that a Union of these<lb/>
Colonies would be politically, financially,<lb/>
and commercially disastrous, neither do I<lb/>
believe that having passed a Militia Bill<lb/>
that it is necessary to send Home a dele<lb break="no"/>gation to show that we are willing to do<lb/>
all we can to defend ourselves. As to our<lb/>
loyalty, that is a truism which nobody<lb/>
doubts, and therefore the delegates are not<lb/>
needed to prove it. The seventh Section<lb/>
of the preamble states that it is to be fear<lb break="no"/>ed that the Government and people of<lb/>
Great Britain are not aware of the true<lb/>
state of feeling here on the question of<lb/>
Confederation. If this is so, which I do<lb/>
not for a moment believe, why cannot<lb/>
they be informed without a delegation ?<lb/>
Above all, however, why does the Govern-<lb break="maybe"/>
ernment come to this House to ask our<lb/>
sanction to the appointment ? When we<lb/>
were sold to Jackson &amp; Co. for <unclear n="can't format the British pound symbol">?</unclear>90,000,<lb/>
did the Government come to this House,<lb/>
and on all the other delegations to Great<lb/>
Britain, Canada, and elsewhere, did they<lb/>
ask for sanction to appoint delegates? No,<lb/>
this is the first time since the year 1833, that<lb/>
such as course has been taken. Then, be<lb break="no"/>fore the principle of Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was recognized, and when a feeling<lb/>
was going about that the people of these<lb/>
Colonies were disloyal, Judge Street mov<lb break="no"/>ed for a delegation to England to lay be<lb break="no"/>fore the British Government the true state<lb/>
of feeling in this Province. But the pre<lb break="no"/>sent action is unprecedented—a private<lb/>
member brings in a Government measure,<lb/>
and to day the Hon. President of the<lb/>
Council moves to take up the order of the<lb/>
day. I believe that any course of action<lb/>
taken by the whole Government by des-<lb break="maybe"/>
patches would have more influence with<lb/>
the Imperial Government than anything<lb/>
which two delegates might be able to do<lb/>
by going Home. And when I see that<lb/>
anything which affects us must in like<lb/>
manner affect the other Provinces, and<lb/>
they have not appointed delegates, I do<lb/>
not see why we should take such a step.<lb/>
I shall therefore oppose the Resolutions.</p>
            <p>Mr. LEWIS.—I believe that this Union<lb/>
of the Provinces is a great Scheme, which<lb/>
would result in great good to this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. A great deal has been said and<lb/>
written on the subject, it has been can<lb break="no"/>vassed and recanvassed, it has been be<lb break="no"/>fore the people in every position in which<lb/>
it could be represented, and the people<lb/>
have spoken out upon it. I looked upon<lb/>
it with great favor, for I believed that it<lb/>
would tend to build us up and make us a<lb/>
great people. The great want we have<lb/>
always experienced was the absence of<lb/>
great public works, and these a Union<lb/>
would have given us. We wanted a Rail<lb break="no"/>road running through the heart of our<lb/>
country, opening up our wild lands, pre<lb break="no"/>paring the way for a system of coloniza<lb break="no"/>tion, and connecting us directly with Can<lb break="no"/>ada, and this the Scheme would have<lb/>
given to us on much better terms than we<lb/>
can get it without. I believed also that<lb/>
it would be the means of promoting and<lb/>
fostering our manufactories. It has been<lb/>
said that we cannot manufacture for Can<lb break="no"/>ada ; but if our infant manufactories were<lb/>
encouraged, and a field opened up for the<lb/>
produce of them in the other Provinces,<lb/>
we should soon be able to compete with<lb/>
any other country. It has been said that<lb/>
            </p>
-->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>