<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-03-21"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-03-21">21 March 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1866</title>.
                    
 

                    

          <date when="1866"/>.  
          

           <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="38" to="42"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_038.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_039.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_040.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_041.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_042.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-17">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_038">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_038.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_039">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_039.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_040">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_040.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_041">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_041.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_042">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_042.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="38" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_038.jpg"/>
           
<!-- GL, 2016-11-17, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->

 <!--<p> Hon.
Mr. Hatheway proceeded to make<lb/>
some further personal remarks, and then <lb/>
spoke against the Quebec Scheme, and<lb/>
said that but for the influences brought to <lb/>
bear upon the Hon. Mr. George Brown,<lb/>
they would have had much better terms<lb/>
of union offered them than those propos<lb break="no"/>ed by that scheme, and he did not think<lb/>
the country was yet prepared to adopt it.<lb/>
He then concluded by saying he had en-<lb break="maybe"/>
deavored to justicy the course he had<lb/>
taken.</p>
            <p>MR. MCCLELAN.—There was one<lb/>
count, the hon. member said, the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment plead guilty to. What was that?</p>
            <p>HON. MR. HATHEWAY.—The Ex<lb break="no"/>port Duty Law.</p>
            <p>MR. MCMILLAN.—Should the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment agree to a scheme of union,<lb/>
would they require the route of the Inter-<lb break="yes"/>
Colonial Railway to be defined?</p>
            <p>HON. MR. HATHEWAY.—As a mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the Government, he would give him<lb/>
the necessary information that day <lb/>
week.</p>
            <p>The Debate was then adjourned over<lb/>
until to-morrow at eleven.</p>
            <p>The motion being put the House was <lb/>
then adjourned over until to-morrow at<lb/>
ten o'clock.</p>
            <p>
               <lb/>
            </p>-->


            <fw type="dateline">WEDNESDAY, MARCH 21.</fw>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:FISH1">MR. FISHER</persName> said he had only dis<lb break="no"/>covered yesterday, that the practice in<lb/>
this House had been not to send Bills<lb/>
to the Legislative Council until after<lb/>
the Address had passed. He could see<lb/>
no reason why they should not go to<lb/>
get on with the business, so that there <lb/>
should not be a rush of business at the <lb/>
close of the Session. He would, there<lb break="no"/>fore, move that the Bill to incorporate <lb/>
the Fredericton Railway Company be<lb/>
read a third time, in order that it could<lb/>
be sent to the Council.</p>
            <p>Several other hon. members expressed<lb/>
themselves in favor of the motion, <lb/>
which was carried.</p>
            <p>The House then went into Committee<lb/>
on a Bill to facilitate the construction of<lb/>
a Railway to Fredericton, which was<lb/>
agreed to. </p>
            <p>The time for taking up the order of<lb/>
the day having arrived, it was proposed<lb/>
to adjourn the debate until two o'clock,<lb/>
as Mr. McClellan—who, it was under<lb break="no"/>stood, was to be the next speaker upon<lb/>
the question—was not prepared to speak<lb/>
in consequence of being unwell.</p>
            <p>The HON. MR. SMITH and others<lb/>
urged, because the members of the<lb/>
House would not give the other business<lb/>
proper attention while a question of so<lb/>
much importance to the coutnry was<lb/>
not decided. Some of the members of <lb/>
the Opposition ought to be prepared to <lb/>
go on with the debate, or have the vote<lb/>
taken. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. LINDSAY expressed his willing<lb break="no"/>ness to make a few remarks in the after<lb break="no"/>noon, but was not prepares at present.</p>
            <p>MR. WETMORE thought the same<lb/>
courtesy should be extended to the hon. <lb/>
Surveyor General—the debate having<lb/>
been adjourned on Saturday in conse<lb break="no"/>quence of his being unwell.</p>
            <p>HON. MR. CUDLIP though, if they <lb/>
had less speaking, the country would<lb/>
           
            <cb/>
        
 be better off. He had always made up<lb/>
his mind on the great questions of the <lb/>
day before he came to the House. They<lb/>
had better have the division, so they<lb/>
could attend to the business of the <lb/>
country.</p>
            <lb/>

<div type="section">
            <head>A BILL RELATING TO THE SETTLEMENT<lb/>
AND SUPPORT OF THE POOR IN THIS <lb/>
PROVINCE.</head>
            <lb/>
            <p>MR. LINDSAY moved the House<lb/>
into Committee on the above Bill, and<lb/>
said, that it was a copy of a Bill intro<lb break="no"/>duced by his hon. friend from Northum<lb break="no"/>berland, some years ago, which had <lb/>
passed through the House, but had<lb/>
been rejected in the Upper House. Its<lb/>
object was to define where the poor<lb/>
legally belonged.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>COL. BOYD was in favour of the Bill,<lb/>
for such a law was very much needed.<lb/>
In St. Andrews, and on the borders,<lb/>
numbers of poor persons come from<lb/>
the United States and get relief from<lb/>
the Parish. This Bill provides that a<lb/>
person shall be a resident of the Parish<lb/>
for twelve months before he can claim<lb/>
relief. He thought one Parish should<lb/>
not support the poor of the neighboring<lb/>
Parishes.</p>
            <p>MR. ANGLIN was inclined to support<lb/>
the Bill. He believed that, although<lb/>
the City members supported it, several<lb/>
members of the country districts opposed<lb/>
it ; and though it was not right to pro<lb break="no"/>tract matters, yet the Bill should not be<lb/>
pressed on when so many members<lb/>
were absent, for he would like to give<lb/>
any member who opposed it a fair<lb/>
chance.</p>
            <p>MR. YOUNG though it was an im<lb break="no"/>portant Bill, and advised the mover to<lb/>
report progress on the Bill, for he would<lb/>
like to know more about it before he<lb/>
agreed to it.</p>
            <p>MR. LINDSAY said, the Bill was <lb/>
well known to the members of the <lb/>
House—it having passed the House<lb/>
nce or twice, and the Legislative<lb/>
Council had it published in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Royal<lb/>
Gazette</hi>. If a pauper came from one <lb/>
Parish into another, there would be no<lb/>
injustice in sending him to the Parish<lb/>
from which he came.</p>
            <p>MR. HILL had no objection to that<lb/>
section of the Bill, but he had great ob<lb break="no"/>jection to the manner in which the Bill<lb/>
was passing through this House. With<lb/>
one or two exceptions, there was not a<lb/>
member who had heard it read, and not<lb/>
half a dozen members knew the provi<lb break="no"/>sions of the Bill. If this was their sys<lb break="no"/>tem of passing Bills, any Bill could be<lb/>
got through the House. It was an un<lb break="no"/>safe method of legislating, although the<lb/>
Bill may be all right.</p>
            <p>MR. KERR said this Bill was a copy of <lb/>
a Bill which he had taken a considerable<lb/>
amount of the pains to frame, and which had<lb/>
passed the House unanimously. The<lb/>
Council thought it a Bill of importantce,<lb/>
and published it in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Royal Gazette</hi>.
It<lb/>
comprehends the principles of the State <lb/>
of Maine and the State of New York<lb/>
poor laws. He was glad to see it dis<lb/>
cussed, and thought it would be a great<lb/>
imporvement upon the existing state of<lb/>
things, for they now had no law for the re<lb break="no"/>moval of the poor to their own parish.</p>
            <p>HON. MR. SMITH said there was no <lb/>
law for the poor at all at present. A gen<lb break="no"/>tleman in Prince Edward Island had<lb/>
written to him for a copy of this Bill,<lb/>
which he supposed was the law. He had<lb/>
written back that we had no law : we on<lb break="no"/><cb/>ly had some custom which had been taken<lb/>
from an English law. They should un<lb break="no"/>derstand what the law was relating to <lb/>
this subject. He thought that Bill was<lb/>
well adapted to this country, therefore<lb/>
he should support it.</p>
            <p>Progress was then reported. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <lb/>
            </p>
</div>
<div type="section">
            <head>AFTERNOON SESSION.</head>
            <lb/>
            <p>ADJOURNED DEBATE ON MR. FISHER'S<lb/>
AMENDMENT.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>MR. LINDSAY. As the hon. member<lb/>
from the County of Albert (Mr. McCle<lb/>
lan) is not in his place, I will make a few<lb/>
remarks, but I will not occupy much <lb/>
time. The people take a great interest in <lb/>
this question, for they attend here anxious<lb/>
to know what is going on. I am pleased<lb/>
to see them, for I think it is the duty of<lb/>
the constituency to keep their eye on the<lb/>
Government, and to see that the men who<lb/>
come here to represent them do not mis<lb break="no"/>represent them. I think that public men<lb/>
are public property, and we have a right<lb/>
to refer to their public acts as long as we<lb/>
do not misrepresent them. When a ques<lb break="no"/>tion was asked a few days ago about the<lb/>
defence of the Province, I stated there <lb/>
was something in common between Antis<lb/>
and Fenians. The Attorney General<lb/>
thought I insinuated that the Anti-<lb break="yes"/>
Confederate member of the Legislature<lb/>
sympathized with the Fenians. I did not <lb/>
mean any such thing. I will call atten<lb break="no"/>tion to why I consider Antic and Fenains<lb/>
agree. I will read an extract from the<lb/>
New York <hi rendition="simple:italic">Irish People</hi>, a
Fenian organ,<lb/>
dated Feb. 17, which refers to the Reci<lb break="no"/>procity Treaty, and gives a reason why<lb/>
the American Government should not ne<lb break="no"/>gotiate a treaty :</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>"Another reason which should have its<lb/>
weight with every well-wisher of Ameri<lb break="no"/>ca is this? <hi rendition="simple:italic">Why should be negotiate
a trea<lb break="no"/>ty with the very men who are to-day con<lb break="no"/>cocting the plan of a Confederation of the <lb/>
British Colonies</hi>, in order to erect a bar<lb break="no"/>rier against the expansion of the Ameri<lb break="no"/>can nation, to transplant a viceeregal<lb/>
court nroth of us, where the admirers<lb/>
and the flatterers of the aristocratic re<lb break="no"/>gime may go and parage their pretentious<lb/>
individuality? No, let there be no trea<lb break="no"/>ty whatever!"</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>That was to prevent the Confederate<lb/>
Union that would raise a barrier to the<lb/>
further extension of the American Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. Another paper takes the same<lb/>
view of it :</p>
            <p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">It will
be dangerous to given encourage<lb break="no"/>ment, even temporarilty, to
the inter-Colo<lb break="no"/>nial feeling which certain influential men,<lb/>
both in Britain and in Canada, are
doing<lb/>
all in their power to cultivate</hi>. The sus<lb break="no"/>pension of reciprocal trade will be a co<lb break="no"/>gent argument with the Canadians in <lb/>
favor of the building of the inter Colonial<lb/>
Railway, WHICH EVERY INHABITANT OF<lb/>
NEW ENGLAND SHOULD SEEK TO PREVENT<lb/>
BY ALL PROPER MEANS, and which, with<lb/>
the continuance of reciprocity, and the<lb/>
prosecution of the international line,<lb/>
will, in our opinion, never be built.<lb/>
Closely allied to his is the political Con<lb break="no"/>federation of the Provinces, which can<lb/>
never be brought to pass unless an un<lb break="no"/>friendly policy on the part of the United <lb/>
States <hi rendition="simple:italic">shall force them, for their
mutual<lb/>
protection and prosperity, into a closer<lb/>
compact and alliance than now exists.</hi>"<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_039.jpg"/>
            
            
            <p>
               I said that the Fenians sympathised<lb/>
with the Antis, and not that the Antis<lb/>
sympathised with the Fenians. The At<lb break="no"/>torney General then jumped up in a great<lb/>
rage and said, "I see the hon. gentleman<lb/>
is opposed to the Government." I made<lb/>
those remarks not with an reference to<lb/>
anything brought before the House. He<lb/>
said I was not worthy of a place in the <lb/>
Legislature. I thought it would be very<lb/>
convenient for the hon. member to keep<lb/>
me out until this question was disposed <lb/>
of. Something was said about our being<lb/>
in the mud. It reminds me of the allu<lb break="no"/>sion made last year, comparing the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment to Nebuchadezzar's image, <lb/>
which was made of iron, clay, brass,<lb/>
gold and silber. If reports are true, <lb/>
the silver is gone and the gold with it.<lb/>
Some say the clay is gone too. I should<lb/>
think it was, as I see here a large quan<lb break="no"/>tity of brass, or perhaps it was meant that<lb/>
the clay and brass had been mixed to<lb break="no"/>gether and converted into mud. I do<lb/>
not know what to call my hon. friend, <lb/>
whether to call him President of the <lb/>
Council, or Attorney General, or Leader<lb/>
of the Government, or Plenipotentiary<lb/>
extraordinary. I do not know who<lb/>
is the Leader of the Government<lb/>
It was said that the hon. member<lb/>
for St. John, (Mr. Wilmot) in con<lb break="no"/>nection with the Hon Mr. Smith, <lb/>
were appointed to form a Government.<lb/>
The hon. Chief Commissioner said his<lb/>
Excellency called upon him. I do not<lb/>
know whether he is the leader, or<lb/>
whether he brings up the rear. He<lb/>
quoted from the Litany. My mind<lb/>
would lead me to quote from the gener<lb break="no"/>al confession. "They have done the<lb/>
things they ought not to have done, and<lb/>
left undone the things they ought to have<lb/>
done," <hi rendition="simple:italic">and we have no confidence in them</hi><lb/>
I have heard it intimated outside that<lb/>
they have one office promised to two or<lb/>
three members, and they have some of<lb break="no"/>fices up stairs which they keep as bait<lb/>
for their supporters. Then again, they<lb/>
intimidate some by saying, if they vote<lb/>
against the Government there will be a <lb/>
dissolution and they will have to go<lb/>
back to their constituents. In any thing<lb/>
that concerns the interests of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, or the rights of the people, I should<lb/>
have no hesitation in going back to my<lb/>
constituents. I will now call attention<lb/>
to things that ought not to have been <lb/>
done. He has allowed His Excellency<lb/>
to draw the same amount of slary that<lb/>
his predecessors did, and for which he<lb/>
condemned them. He says that is paid<lb/>
back ; that is not the question. The <lb/>
question is, has he a right to draw it?<lb/>
If he had a right to draw it, had has a <lb/>
right to keep it. My hon friend agrees<lb/>
with me on that, we voted on the same <lb/>
side on the resolution which was carried<lb/>
in 1864. I will read the resolution :</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>"Resolved, As the opinion of this<lb/>
Committee that the amount the Lieuten<lb/>
and Governor is entitled to receive, as <lb/>
salary, is £3461 10s. 8d per annun,<lb/>
and the Solicitor General and Provinvial<lb/>
Secretary £230 15s. 4d each," and fur<lb break="no"/>ther</p>
            <p>"Resolved, That the amount paid be<lb break="no"/>yond these sums were improperly paid, <lb/>
and without sufficient authority."</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>Yeas—Kerr, Willis on, Vail, Costi<lb break="no"/>gan, McClelan, Skinner, Smith, Mc<lb break="no"/>Phelim, Scovil, Ferris, Lindsay, Ang<lb break="no"/>lin, W. J. Gilbert, S. H. Gilbert, Cud-<lb break="yes"/>
lip, Gilmur, Boyd. <lb/>
 
               </p>
<cb/>
            
           
            <p>
               He has thus allowed His Excellency<lb/>
to do what he thought was wrong in<lb/>
his predecessor's office. Another thing<lb/>
he ought not to have done was, with<lb break="no"/>holding the despatches sent out here for<lb/>
the information of the Legislature. Mr. <lb/>
Lindsay then read a despatch dated the<lb/>
12th of April, which he said should have<lb/>
been received here the 26th of April, <lb/>
and which contained information of im<lb break="no"/>portance respecting military defence<lb/>
and Confederation, that should have<lb/>
been laid before the Legislature at that<lb/>
time assembled, but which was not laid<lb/>
before them at all. The next thing they<lb/>
ought not to have done was, they should<lb/>
not have written that despatch, dated<lb/>
July 12th, which was insulting to Her<lb/>
Majesty's Government, and which was<lb/>
signed by the immortal seven and as<lb/>
the President of the Council has en<lb break="no"/>dorsed it, he, with the late Attorney<lb/>
General, will make the immortal nine.<lb/>
The President of the Council said the<lb/>
despatch justified them in using such<lb/>
language as they did. He then read<lb/>
the despatch dated June 24th, 1865, to <lb/>
which the other was an answer, and said<lb/>
he could see nothing in it to justify them<lb/>
in returning such an answer, and con<lb break="no"/>tinued : the President of the Council<lb/>
said, he only knew of two persons, out<lb/>
side of Parliament, who knew any thing<lb/>
about the scheme. I cannot suppose<lb/>
that when the British Parliament, con<lb break="no"/>sisting of six hunfred and fifty-six mem<lb break="no"/>bers, were acquainted with this scheme,<lb/>
no one outside would know anything<lb/>
about it. It was said, if we went into <lb/>
Confederation we would have to pro<lb break="no"/>vide a navy. An Act passed this Legis<lb break="no"/>lature a few days ago to provide one or<lb/>
two vesseles for defence. Here is a navy <lb/>
which we have to provide alone. If we<lb/>
went into Confederation we would only<lb/>
have one-thirteenth part to pay, and but<lb/>
few vessels would be wanted. We have<lb/>
been taken care of for seventy-five years,<lb/>
and we should begin to try to do some<lb break="no"/>thing for ourselves, and it should not be<lb/>
thought an insult for Her Majesty's<lb/>
Ministers to refer to it. and I do not<lb/>
think the people of the country consider<lb/>
it so. It has been said that union is not<lb/>
strength. Who can beieve that uniting<lb/>
these Colonies would weaken them. <lb/>
The only thing I know of that will be<lb/>
weakened by uniting is rum and water.</p>

            <p>The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Times</hi> says, that by refusing to <lb/>
unite together we showa want of loyal<lb break="no"/>ty, and this Government says in the Min<lb break="no"/>ute of Council : "When a wish is ex<lb break="no"/>pressed by Her Majesty's Government,<lb/>
it will be received with that federence<lb/>
which is due to suggestions emanating<lb/>
from so high a source, and will be con<lb break="no"/>sidered with an anzious desire to meet <lb/>
the views of Her Majesty's advisers ;<lb/>
but if such views should unfortunately<lb/>
not coincide with the views of those on <lb/>
whom alone the responsibility of action<lb/>
in the Province fallsm the Committee<lb/>
feel assured that Her Majesty's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will expect and desire that the Go<lb/>
vernment of this Province should act<lb/>
according to their own convictions of<lb/>
right." They will act according to their<lb/>
own convictions ; but when a foe in<lb break="no"/>vades the country they will send a des<lb break="no"/>patch as quick as possible to England, <lb/>
and ask them to send soldiers and ships<lb/>
to protect men who claim the right to<lb/>
do as they like, when Her Majesty sug<lb break="no"/>gests that we should unite under one<lb/>
Government. The Government tell us<lb/>
how loyal they are. Loyalty does not<lb/>
 
       <cb/>

consists in lip service, but in obedience.<lb/>
A refractory man is not a good subject<lb/>
to an country.</p>
            <p>Mr. Lindsay then read the reply of the<lb/>
Colonial Secretary to those immortal<lb/>
nine, and continued. This reply was<lb/>
just as much as to say : I cannot be<lb break="no"/>lieve the loyal men of New Brunswick<lb/>
endorse the views expressed by those<lb/>
immortal nine. These are things they <lb/>
ought not to have done. I will now<lb/>
speak of things they ought to have left<lb/>
undone  I believe when a man is paid<lb/>
$2400 a year to fill an office, he should<lb/>
attend to his duties and not have to<lb/>
make excuses for sins of omission. It <lb/>
is the old story—Adam left the blame<lb/>
on his wife and his wife left it on the<lb/>
devil. (Laughter.) The President of<lb/>
the Council says the late Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eral ought to have known the Export<lb/>
Duty law was to expire. Another says<lb/>
the Provincial Secretary ought to have <lb/>
known it. Another, that Fisher found<lb/>
it out and should have told them, and<lb/>
another that the late Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary ought to have told his predecessor<lb/>
of it. They thus acknowledge that they <lb/>
are not fit to attend to the business, for<lb/>
they tried till they got a man out of of<lb break="no"/>fice, and then found fault because he<lb/>
did not do the work for them. The peo<lb break="no"/>ple complain they cannot find a member<lb/>
of the Government at Fredericton, there<lb/>
were so many pleasure excursions. Two<lb/>
of them off to England to tell Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's Government what they knew be<lb break="no"/>fore ; but, in order to say they had done<lb/>
something for the £800 they received,<lb/>
they made an arrangement for the Rail<lb break="no"/>way in Westmorland  The Attorney<lb/>
General made it under a Bill which he<lb/>
had done all he could to defeat when it<lb/>
was before the House. The Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner of the Board of Works, and my<lb/>
hon. friend from St. John (Mr. Anglin)<lb/>
went to Canada. I do not know whether<lb/>
they went voluntarily or whether they <lb/>
were paid for it. (Mr. Anglin—I paid<lb/>
my own expenses as I always do.) That<lb/>
is all very well. Suppose I went to<lb/>
your House and said I believe you are a<lb/>
humbug, and a bankrupt, and I don't <lb/>
want to have any thing to do with you ;<lb/>
we would have a social time would we<lb/>
not? It was in this spirit they went to<lb/>
Canada ; they said we did not want a <lb/>
closer union with you, for we believe<lb/>
you are bankrupt, and are trying to take<lb/>
advantage of us. What a fraternal<lb/>
meeting that must have been. Then<lb/>
they had another pleasure excursion to<lb/>
the United States. My hon. friend (Mr. <lb/>
Wilmot) was one of the immortal nine.<lb/>
It is said, "evil communications corrupt<lb/>
good manners" He was led to do<lb/>
something he ought not to have done,<lb/>
but, I believe, if my friend repents he<lb/>
has a right to expect mercy, and if som-<lb break="yes"/>
other of my hon. friends would come<lb/>
round in the same way we would have<lb/>
mercy for them. The hon Attorney<lb/>
General stated here last Session that he<lb/>
was sorry that his hon. friend (Mr. <lb/>
Fisher) who was one of the delegates<lb/>
who went to Quebec, was not on the<lb/>
floors of the House, so that he could con<lb break="no"/>front him ; but not he has his wish,<lb/>
he is not satisfied. He says that when a <lb/>
division was taken upon the question<lb/>
abolishing the office of Postmaster Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, there were thirty for it and nine <lb/>
against it. That was because, when a<lb/>
question came up, they got up the rallying<lb/>
cry, that every man who was elected a<lb/>
Confederate was violating his principle<lb/>
        

            <pb n="40" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_040.jpg"/>

if he did not vote with the Government<lb/>
A cry is now raised, that is they vote<lb/>
against the Government the House will<lb/>
be dissolved. I never was into a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and do not care about going in,<lb/>
neither do I care much about having a<lb/>
seat in the Legislature. When I was <lb/>
first requested to offer, some person said<lb/>
I would not get three hundred votes, but<lb/>
the event proved he was wrong, and if<lb/>
the House was dissolved to-morrow, I am <lb/>
ready to run again, so they need not <lb/>
think dissolving the House will have <lb/>
much effect with me. There is another<lb/>
thing ought not to have been done—that<lb/>
is, speculating in land. I consider that <lb/>
the greatest sin the Government have<lb/>
been guilty of. I believe no greater evil<lb/>
can be inflicted upon a community than<lb/>
allowing one man to monopolize that lands<lb/>
of the country. I will quote a report of<lb/>
the Earl of Durham, who was at that<lb/>
time Governor General of British North<lb/>
America. At the 159h page of his<lb/>
report he says :—<lb/></p>


            <p>"In Upper Canada, a very small pro<lb break="no"/>portion—perhaps less than a tenth—of<lb/>
the land thus granted has been even occu<lb break="no"/>pied by settlers, much less reclaimed and<lb/>
cultivated. In Lower Canada, with the <lb/>
exception of a few townships bordering<lb/>
on the American frontier, which have <lb/>
been comparatively well settled, in despite<lb/>
of the proprietors by American squatters<lb/>
it may be said that nineteen-twentieths of
<lb/>
these grants are still unsettled, and in a
<lb/>
perfectly wild state."</p>




            <p>"No other result could have been ex<lb break="no"/>pected in the case of those classes of<lb/>
grantees whose station would preclude <lb/>
them from settling on the wilderness, and <lb/>
whose means would enable them to avoid<lb/>
exertion for giving immediate value to<lb/>
their grants ; and, unfortunately, the <lb/>
land which was intended for persons of<lb/>
a poorer order, who might be expected to<lb/>
improve it by their labor, has, for the <lb/>
most part, fallen into the hands of land<lb/>
jobbers of the class just mentioned, who<lb/>
have never thought of settling in person,<lb/>
and who retain the land in its present<lb/>
wild state, speculating upon its acquiring<lb/>
value at some distant day when the de<lb break="no"/>mand for land shall have increased<lb/>
through the increase of population."</p>
            <lb/>



            <p>This coincides with my own views in<lb/>
this matter. I am opposed to any Govern<lb break="no"/>ment who will allow men to purchase<lb/>
large blocks of land, which the poor man<lb/>
has to go through and make roads, as<lb/>
this interferes with the prosperity of the
<lb/>
country. Why should a poor man be<lb/>
compelled to make roads through another<lb/>
man's property ; that land having been<lb/>
obtained for two shilings, and kept<lb/>
until it is worth four dollars an acre,<lb/>
in consequence of the settlements around<lb/>
it. It had been said here that when they<lb/>
received from timber licences. I contend<lb/>
the country would be a gainer if no man<lb/>
got land without the principle of actual<lb/>
settlement being attached to it, for it has<lb/>
been calculated that every settler is worth<lb/>
three dollars a year to the revenues of<lb/>
the country. This and the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment blame each other in regard to this,<lb/>
but I do not care who is in the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, I should blame them for this,<lb/>
(Hon. Mr. Smith.—Which Government<lb/>
was most to blame) All the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment did was to order the survey.<lb/>
(Mr. Wetmore.—Was the money paid.)<lb/>
The ex-Surveyor General said it was not<lb/>
           <cb/>
 said. Why did the Government come to<lb/>
the conclusion that the Intercolonial<lb/>
Railroad was given up, when the survey<lb/>
was made only ten months ago? If there<lb/>
was any reason why the public lands<lb/>
should be sold to others than actual<lb/>
settlers, notice should have been given to<lb/>
the Deputies. I know that men made<lb/>
application for land in my County, and <lb/>
could not get it. I believe in equal<lb/>
rights for all. It was not right that a few<lb/>
men should have been informed of what<lb/>
was going on, and the rest kept in ig<lb break="no"/>norance. There was five thousand acres<lb/>
purchased in fictitious names, and then<lb/>
the resolution was rescinded, and he got<lb/>
ten thousand more ; previous to this he<lb/>
got a three year license to cut the lum<lb break="no"/>ber on it, and if any one else had bought<lb/>
it he could cut all the lumber off of it.<lb/>
Then again they said, by doing away<lb/>
with the political character of the Post<lb break="no"/>master General, they would make a great<lb/>
saving. If the political head of the de<lb break="no"/>partment was abolished, would not the <lb/>
chief business be done in St. John? It<lb/>
was said Mr. Howe would be the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, but it was hinted outside that a<lb/>
gentleman in St. John had the promise<lb/>
of an office to be called Post Office In<lb break="no"/>spector. He would have the salary and <lb/>
pickings, without the privilege of having<lb/>
"General" attached to his name. This<lb/>
was the saving that was to ve effected by <lb/>
doing away with the political head of the<lb/>
department, and to carry their measure,<lb/>
they got up their rallying cry of Confede<lb break="no"/>ration. I was almost discouraged, but I <lb/>
believed that "he is thrice armed who <lb/>
has his quarrel just." I am glad there <lb/>
are some hon. gentlement now who will<lb/>
look after the interests of the coutnry and<lb/>
not be drummed up with the cry of Conf<lb break="no"/>ederation anfd anti-Confederation.</p>
            <p>In regard to the appoinment og Judges,<lb/>
my hon. friend referred to what Judge<lb/>
Wilmot had said and done, and how he<lb/>
had voted, thus admitting the truth of<lb/>
the charge brought against them that they<lb/>
had made politics their rule for their ap<lb break="no"/>pointments on the Bench. I do not be<lb break="no"/>lieve in Judges interfering in the
political<lb/>
questions which are before the country.<lb/>
They should arise far above that ; but this<lb/>
was a question whether we were going to<lb/>
maintain out connection with the mother<lb/>
country or not. Confederation in a ques<lb break="no"/>tion that has occupied the minds of men<lb/>
for sixty-five years. Judge Wilmot held <lb/>
those views when on the floors of this <lb/>
House, and he is a credit to the country<lb/>
which gave him birth, and I contend it<lb/>
was unfair to pass over him and appoint<lb/>
a junior Judge to the office. I do not<lb/>
know much about the gentleman who has<lb/>
been said that they might have found a per<lb break="no"/>son qualified without going to Insurance<lb/>
Offices. He was appointed on political<lb/>
grounds, which is a principle they have <lb/>
carried down to the offcials on the rail<lb break="no"/>way, and I don't know how much further<lb/>
they would have carried it, if His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency had not interfered. It had been<lb/>
said that they are going to change their <lb/>
base, and take another course on Confed<lb break="no"/>eration. If that is the case, it is not
right<lb/>
for me to say anything, for they may come<lb/>
round al right. I think by what is fore<lb break="no"/>shadowed in the Speech, that they are go<lb break="no"/>ing to get up another delegation and have<lb/>
another pleasure excursion, for the Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General says he is willing to go for<lb/>
some Scheme. He said when we advoca<lb break="no"/>ted a Scheme of Union, that we were<lb/>
"political schemers" and "conspirators."<lb/>
            </p>
<cb/>

<p>
Now they are going to get up a poli<lb break="no"/>tical scheme, but I do not know whether<lb/>
they are going to "conspirit" or not. They
<lb/>
c<unclear n="illegible lettering.">?</unclear> a man that was going to carry out<lb/>
the wishes of his Sovereign a "conspira<lb break="no"/>tor." I heard it stated on good authority,<lb/>
and I need not go off the floors of this<lb/>
Legislature to prove it, that the Chief<lb/>
Commissioner, on being asked whe<lb break="no"/>ther he had read the Minate of Council,<lb/>
said he was sorry it did not go further,<lb/>
that they had not made use of stronger<lb/>
language, using an expression I am a<lb break="no"/>shamed to repeat. These are the loyal<lb/>
men, and we are the conspirators.<lb/>
My hon. friend (Mr. Wilmot) said in<lb/>
Canada, that he was not opposed to a<lb/>
union, but he was not satisfied with the<lb/>
Quebec Scheme. Mr. George Brown<lb/>
said there were some things in the scheme<lb/>
they did not like either, they would <lb/>
meet him half way in considering a <lb/>
union, for they did not wish to take <lb/>
any unfair advantages of their fellow-<lb break="yes"/>
colonists. I am in favor of a union and<lb/>
I do not see how any British subject<lb/>
can be opposed to it, but to agree upon a<lb/>
scheme of union, we must all make some <lb/>
concessions or we will never agree to any<lb/>
terms. My hon. friend (Co'. Boyd) made a <lb/>
speech in Canada in favor of union. (Col. <lb/>
Boyd, not in favor of the Quebec Scheme.)<lb/>
I did not say it was, but I heard him speak<lb/>
strongly in favor of a union ; but he is one<lb/>
of those men who believe nothing good<lb/>
can come out of Nazareth, and that a man<lb/>
must belong to certian families of he will<lb/>
not be fit for office. I believe in freedom<lb/>
and equal rights for all. There are a great<lb/>
many things in the scheme which are com<lb break="no"/>plained of in Canada and it is doubtful, if<lb/>
we get a new scheme, whether we would <lb/>
come off as well as we did before. They<lb/>
complain that New Brunswick is to get <lb/>
$63,000 a year for ten years. (Mr. Need-<lb break="yes"/>
ham,—That is contingent, that unless we<lb/>
run into debt to the extent of $7,000,000<lb/>
we were not to get it.) If we built our <lb/>
railroads under the Subsidy Act, our debt<lb/>
would soon reach that amount, and Cana<lb break="no"/>da does not come in with a debt equal to <lb/>
ours, if we take the population of Canada<lb/>
into consideration. We would have more<lb/>
money for local purpose than we have<lb/>
now, and have the Inter-Colonial Railway<lb/>
and Western Extension built besides. In <lb/>
a time of war we could come to the as<lb break="no"/>sistance of each other and would not<lb/>
require half the number of troops that we<lb/>
do now in our isolated position.</p>
            <p>DR. THOMPSON said he had taken <lb/>
no notes, and would, therefore, make but<lb/>
a short speech. At the last election two-<lb break="yes"/>
thirds of the poeple in this Province de<lb break="no"/>clared they were opposed to Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. It has been said that, by signing<lb/>
this Minute of Council, the Government <lb/>
have insulted Her Majesty's Ministers.<lb/>
He did not believe that, and he had<lb/>
as great a respect for the United <lb/>
Kingdom as any other man in the Prov<lb break="no"/>ince. At the same time, he did not like<lb/>
to bow in slavish obedience to what<lb break="no"/>ever set of men was put in as rulers<lb/>
of that country, and if he has his say, the<lb/>
present rulers would not be sustained in<lb/>
their position very long. Since the great<lb/>
man (Lord Palmerston), who was at the<lb/>
head of the Government, is gone, they<lb/>
have scarcely a man fit to retain office.<lb/>
In regard to Confederation, it is not go<lb break="no"/>ing to benefit us, for we would have to<lb/>
be at the espence of keeping up two Le<lb break="no"/>gislatures, besdies this great Parliament.<lb/>
If they must unite together, they had <lb/>
better unite under one Legislature, which<lb/>
          
            <pb n="41" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_041.jpg"/>

 could
attend to their local business with<lb break="no"/>out their being at so much expense. He<lb/>
could not see how members of this House<lb/>
could be so shame-faced as to attempt<lb/>
to do any thing of that kind. Some of<lb/>
them would never have had a chance to<lb/>
come to this House if they had not been<lb/>
anti Confederate, and why then should<lb/>
they turn traitors to the trust reposed in<lb/>
them ; in his opinion, it would be wrong<lb/>
and unjustifiable to do so. We have<lb/>
been here eighty years and the country<lb/>
has improved. We have got along very<lb/>
well, and all we ask is to be let alone.<lb/>
He believed that an affectionate feeling<lb/>
for the Mother Country was true Con<lb break="no"/>federation. It is said here, that they<lb/>
should enter into Confederation as a <lb/>
means of defence, but he considered<lb/>
that the money required for keeping up<lb/>
this great Parliament would be a means<lb/>
of defence in itself. It has been said<lb/>
that under Confederation, if an attack<lb/>
was made we could send our troops<lb/>
from one point to another. We can do<lb/>
that now. Did we not pass a resolution<lb/>
for putting all the available resources<lb/>
of the country in the hands of the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, and could we not pass a re<lb break="no"/>solution to move all our available forces<lb/>
in or out of the Province, if we con<lb break="no"/>sidered it best to fight upon a foreign<lb/>
land. He was satisfied to see the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor appointed by the Crown. If he was<lb/>
appointed by the Government of Cana<lb break="no"/>da, in a short time there would not be a <lb/>
drop of loyalty left. If had been said<lb/>
that the Government had left things un<lb break="no"/>done, they had allowed a law to expire<lb/>
without being aware of it. This House, <lb/>
in former times, would have taken care<lb/>
of that, because a Committee of the<lb/>
House used to be appointed to see if<lb/>
any Bills were going to expire ; there<lb break="no"/>fore, the onus is as much on us as it is <lb/>
on them. A Bill has been passed to re<lb break="no"/>medy the omission, which was caused<lb/>
by the difficulties the present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had to contend with, and the short<lb/>
time which they had for entering into<lb/>
details, as they ought to have done it<lb/>
they had more time. The result of the <lb/>
charges made against them is, that they<lb/>
have stopped things from being done that<lb/>
other parties wanted done. In regard to <lb/>
the appointment of Judges, he did not<lb/>
think they could have made better ap<lb break="no"/>pointments. The Chief Justice is a pious<lb/>
and just man, and man of high legal<lb/>
knowledge ; he has stood high as a man,<lb/>
and that is saying everything that is re<lb break="no"/>quired. He could not see that it was<lb/>
unfair to appoint Judge Ritchie to the<lb/>
office of Chief Justice. He had a high<lb/>
respect for Judge Wilmot, who was a <lb/>
man of great legal knowledge, but then<lb/>
if a person has a political bias, and the<lb/>
hon. gentlemen of the Opposition had the<lb/>
power of the Government, they would not<lb/>
appoint him. It was not human nature<lb/>
to do so, and it was not his nature. He<lb/>
then referred to Judge Weldon, whom he<lb/>
said was the oldest barrister in the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, with the exception of Mr. Saunders,<lb/>
and they did not overstep the eldest per<lb break="no"/>son and put in a younger. He was a man<lb/>
of their own political opinion, and they<lb/>
should appoint him to office as well as<lb/>
any one else.</p>



            <p>For the purpose of keeping up loyalty,<lb/>
a small colony was better than a great<lb/>
one, because they would have a British<lb/>
Governor, who would be a tie between<lb/>
them and the mother country. But in a<lb/>
large colony, if everything does not please<lb/>
them, they will say we are not going to<lb/>

<cb/>
submit to this, and they do not feel that<lb/>
loyalty that a smaller colony does. This<lb/>
confederation scheme cannot benefit our<lb/>
trade. We have not a single article we<lb/>
can send to Canada. The fishermen in<lb/>
Charlotte County say they can send their<lb/>
fish there, but they have far more fish<lb break="no"/>eries on the Canadian shore than we have<lb/>
in Nova Scotia and New Brunswick. We<lb/>
cannot take deals and boards there, we<lb/>
have no manufactures to send there, for<lb/>
we cannot manufacture our own bread.<lb/>
We cannot compete with them, they can<lb/>
get bread cheap, and can get labor for<lb/>
almost nothing. They say we have more <lb/>
coal here then they have in Canada, but<lb/>
coal is much cheaper there than it is here.<lb/>
We would soon have all our offices
filled<lb/>
with the employees of the Canadian<lb/>
Government, while we would have to pay<lb/>
three times the taxes in proportion to our<lb/>
numbers for the French scarcely con<lb break="no"/>sume any dutiable articles, the very sugar<lb/>
they use they produce from the maple.<lb/>
Then, as regards the prosperty of some<lb/>
parts of Canada ; the people are going<lb/>
from the town of Hamilton by shiploads,<lb/>
you can get a house there by paying the<lb/>
taxes. If they had the control of us,<lb/>
they would tax us until we could not stand<lb/>
it. It would not be like a bad law passed<lb/>
this year and repealed the next, but we<lb/>
would be fixed there where we could not<lb/>
hope to get a reprieve. We would be<lb/>
worse than the slaves, for they have a <lb/>
hope of getting something done for them,<lb/>
while we would have none. If they could<lb/>
enter into some fair principle of union,<lb/>
such as was entered into between Eng<lb break="no"/>land, Scotland and Ireland, which was<lb/>
not the question of the day or a year, but<lb/>
here we had a scheme brought forward<lb/>
of which we knew nothing, and we were<lb/>
expected to pass it at once. He con<lb break="no"/>demned the act but not the persons who<lb/>
made it, and he though they could have<lb/>
free trade with the other colonies if they<lb/>
wished it without going into confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. This Quebec Scheme was framed<lb/>
upon the spur of the moment, and they only<lb/>
had a few days to consider it. It was not<lb/>
like the union between Ireland and<lb/>
England, for Ireland was an integral part<lb/>
of the kingdom, and if we could have any<lb/>
thing approximating to a like union, it<lb/>
would be to have at some future time one<lb/>
or two members to go home as our re<lb break="no"/>presentatives in the British Parliament ; <lb/>
in former times we could not have this,<lb/>
but now we could go over there in ten<lb/>
days, being one-quarter of the time it<lb/>
used to take the members to come from<lb/>
the nroth of Scotland by land. He would<lb/>
strongly suggest the propriety of every<lb/>
colony having a representative in the <lb/>
British Parliament. He did not think<lb/>
representation by population was alto<lb break="no"/>gether fair. A County with varied in<lb break="no"/>terests required a larger representation.<lb/>
The city of St. John of the County of<lb/>
Charlotte required a larger representation<lb/>
than the interior Counties. The question<lb/>
now was, whether they should remove the<lb/>
Government or let them live a little<lb/>
longer. His opinion was they had better<lb/>
let them live a little longer. (A member<lb/>
—How long do you go for.) That would<lb/>
depend upon their behavior, but he<lb/>
thought they should not condemn them<lb/>
so soon. We should give them an op<lb break="no"/>portunity to forsake their sins of commis<lb break="no"/>sion and omission, and allow them to go<lb/>
on and show that their conduct in the<lb/>
future will be such as will gratify the<lb/>
persons who now oppose them. We<lb/>
ought to have faith, hope and charity.</p>

<cb/>

            <p> He had faith to believe they would do<lb/>
better. Where is the Government that<lb/>
has not been overhauled, more particu<lb break="no"/>larly since the establishment of responsi<lb break="no"/>ble and departmental Government. He<lb/>
had made up his mind to go for the<lb/>
address as it stood. Let the Government<lb/>
live and breathe, and see wherein they<lb/>
have done wrong and do so no more, so<lb/>
that when difficulties assail us, they may<lb/>
carry out the views of the Legislature.<lb/>
            </p>


            <p>MR. FRASER said he would make a <lb/>
few remarks, but had made no arrange<lb break="no"/>ments, and was not going to reply to any <lb/>
member. Certain charges had been made<lb/>
against the Government, but he believed<lb/>
those charges were mere sham. The<lb/>
real question was Confederation. Of this<lb/>
there could be no doubt. Why, then, did<lb/>
they not move the amendment on a para<lb break="no"/>graph that would test it. If they were<lb/>
going to agitate the country, let them<lb/>
do it in a fair, open, manly, straightfor<lb break="no"/>ward way, and not try it upon the question<lb/>
of Fenianism, or any other ism. He would<lb/>
ask the hon. mover of the amendment, if<lb/>
he did not believe, when he struck out<lb/>
that part which he feared would offend<lb/>
the United States, that he could not get<lb/>
the votes upon it. (Mr. Fisher,—I made<lb/>
it one of the grounds of my complaint<lb/>
against the Government.) He should not<lb/>
have struck it out. He could quote author<lb break="no"/>ity from the Speaker of the House of Com<lb break="no"/>mons. (Mr. Fisher,—That was a different<lb/>
case. In this I was not obliged to give
notice <lb/>
at all.) Very well, he would not say any<lb/>
thing more in reference to that. He did <lb/>
not wish to make any personal attack.<lb/>
His hon. friend and him agreed as well <lb/>
as any men in the country, but in matters<lb/>
of a political nature he had a right to<lb/>
take his side ; and his hon. friend could<lb/>
take his. He did not intend to make an<lb/>
attack upon him. He would merely ad<lb break="no"/>vance some arguments which could go for<lb/>
what they were worth. He charged the<lb/>
Opposition with intending to get up a reli<lb break="no"/>gious discussion in the House, by attack<lb break="no"/>ing the Government. Why did not they<lb/>
attack them on the clause relating to<lb/>
Confederation?</p>




            <p>MR. FISHER.—I thought this was<lb/>
the most assailable point. I was not dis<lb break="no"/>posed to raise a question on Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. A vote of want of confidence was<lb/>
outside of that question.</p>


            <p>MR. FRASER.—Why did you with<lb break="no"/>draw the latter part of the amendment?</p>
            <p>MR. FISHER.—I withdrew it for the <lb/>
reason I stated at the time. I said I in<lb break="no"/>tended to make that part of my charge<lb/>
against them, and I did so.</p>



            <p>MR. FRASER said his hon. friend and<lb/>
the House had assisted the Government<lb/>
in defending the country. If the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment come in and do not satisfy us that <lb/>
they have defended the country, it will be<lb/>
our duty to vote against them. We are<lb/>
put down as traitors. He never was oppos<lb break="no"/>ed to the abstract principle of a union of<lb/>
the Colonies. He had taken the first sec<lb break="no"/>tion of the scheme, and said he would go<lb/>
for that, and that was the only section in<lb/>
the scheme that was carried unanimous<lb break="no"/>ly. One of the charges brought against<lb/>
the Government is, that dispatched were<lb/>
withheld. He would tell them that a<lb/>
system had been pursued of publishing<lb/>
those dispatches in the neighboring colo<lb break="no"/>nies, before the English mail arrived<lb/>
here. He thought the people of New<lb/>
          

            <pb n="42" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-21_Page_042.jpg"/>
        
 Brunswick were the best judges of whe<lb break="no"/>ther Confederation was for their interest<lb/>
or not. It was not for the people of Ca<lb break="no"/>nada or the people of England, to tell<lb/>
them what was for their interest, but<lb/>
they would give due consideration to<lb/>
anything emanating from the Colonial<lb/>
Office. We are told that "union is<lb/>
strength." No one desies that ; but a<lb/>
union, to be strong, must have no discord<lb break="no"/>ant elements. In the abstract, he was in<lb/>
favor of union ; but if he disapproved of<lb/>
the grounds they went on, he would fight<lb/>
against it through thick and thin. He had<lb/>
heard them talk about loyalty. He could<lb/>
say that some of his ancestors had shed<lb/>
their blood under General Wolfe, at the<lb/>
taking of Quebec ; and if the time now<lb/>
came for a fight, and they got him in a<lb/>
corner, he would be found giving a kick<lb/>
for a kick, and a blow for a blow. The<lb/>
next charge brought against them was<lb/>
the President of the Council wished to <lb/>
remove the seat of Government. He <lb/>
then referred to the Journals of 1858 to<lb/>
show who voted for the removal of the<lb/>
seat of Government at the time.</p>
            <p>MR. MCMILLAN said he had never,<lb/>
here or elsewhere, given as a reason for<lb/>
a vote of want of confidence, that they<lb/>
wished to remove the seat of Government.<lb/>
A charge was made against the mover of<lb/>
the amendment, that he had charged the<lb/>
President of the Council who doing away<lb/>
with the Post Office Department, was a<lb/>
first step towards the removal of the seat<lb/>
of Government. I said I stated last year<lb/>
in my place, when the subject was under<lb/>
consideration, that it was a first step to<lb break="no"/>wards doing away with Departmental and<lb/>
Responsible Government. I did not give<lb/>
a reason that I would go against the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment because I opposed them upon<lb/>
that last year.</p>
            <p>MR. FRASER said it was put forward<lb/>
in the County of York as a canvass<lb/>
against Mr. Pickard, that he was a sup<lb break="no"/>porter of Mr. Smith, who was going to<lb/>
remove the seat of Government. The<lb/>
hon. mover of the amendment had stated<lb/>
that he never stirred from his office, but<lb/>
he had canvassers who went through the<lb/>
country.</p>
            <p>MR. FISHER.—There never was a<lb/>
man went through the country by my <lb/>
directions.</p>
            <p>MR. FRASER then slated that in one<lb/>
of the settlements of the County a gen<lb break="no"/>tleman, who was an ex-member of great<lb/>
ability and ingenuity, told the inhabitants<lb/>
in language that conveyed to their minds<lb/>
the impression that Mr. Smith intended to<lb/>
remove the Seat of Government. Ano<lb break="no"/>ther chrage is that they failed to discover<lb/>
that the Export Duty Law had expired ;<lb/>
all he would say in regard to this was,<lb/>
that it was the duty of the out-going Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to communicate to an in-coming<lb/>
one every thing that concerns the inter<lb break="no"/>ests of the people or the business of the <lb/>
country. This was done in England. If<lb/>
the out-going Government knew of it,<lb/>
they should have told it, and if<lb/>
they did not know it, they were<unclear n="">
                  <lb/>
?</unclear> in the duty. Shortly af<lb/>
               <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>here last
session, he had<lb/>
               <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>a rumour
outside that the revenue<lb/>
               <unclear reason="illegible">[?]<lb/>
[?]<lb/>
[?]<lb/>
[?]<lb/>
[?]<lb/>
[?]<lb/>
[?]</unclear> They should not condemn the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment for that, for the money was all<lb/>
in the Treasury now. They must consi-</p>
            <cb/>


            <p>der the peculiar situation of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. They were running all those elec<lb break="no"/>tions in the month of March, and had<lb/>
many difficulties to contend with. Ano<lb break="no"/>ther ground of complaint is : they have<lb/>
been guilty of land jabbing. He thought<lb/>
if they had twenty such land jabbers as<lb/>
Mr. Gibson, the people of York would<lb/>
not complain, and he did not think the<lb/>
people fo the Spruce County of Resti<lb break="no"/>gouche would complain either. The late<lb/>
Government undertook to seel Mr. Gob-<lb break="yes"/>
son 15,000 acres of land without condi<lb break="no"/>tions of actual settlement attached. Five<lb/>
thousand acres of this, Mr. Lindsay says,<lb/>
was applied for under ficticious names.<lb/>
He (Mr. Fraser) said they were all <hi rendition="simple:italic">bona<lb/>
fide</hi>
names<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. LINDSAY—If application is made</p>
            <p>for land in one man's name, and another<lb/>
man gets the land, is it not using ficti<lb break="no"/>tious names?</p>
            <p>MR. FRASER—The whole lumbering<lb/>
business is done in that way. If the hon. <lb/>
member for Kent was to go to St. John<lb/>
to purchase molasses, and went to his<lb/>
friends and said, if I go and buy it, the<lb/>
dealer will take advantage of me, but if<lb/>
you go, he will not know who is buying<lb/>
it. They say the late Government did<lb/>
not undertake to sell the land. They or<lb break="no"/>dered a survery, and when a man gets an<lb/>
order to survey, he believes the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment is going to bring that land to sale.</p>
            <p>The debate was then adjourned until<lb/>
to-morrow at 11 o'clock.</p>



            <p>MR. NEEDHAM called the attention<lb/>
of the House to a report in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Morning<lb/>
Telegraph</hi>
of a speech made by him, in<lb/>
which this passage appears : "He states<lb/>
he was not surprised at the view taken<lb/>
by that 'great big toady.' Dr. Thompson,<lb/>
but it was no use for him 'or any other<lb/>
man' to try to stop the progress of every<lb/>
great political principle." He did not<lb/>
want to be misrepresented, for he did not<lb/>
make use of the words "great big toa<lb break="no"/>dy," nor the words that follow either. He<lb/>
believed it was not a misprint, but a mis<lb break="no"/>representation. He spoke this in the <lb/>
hearing of their paid reporter, in order<lb/>
that he should notice that he gave this a<lb/>
flat contradiction.</p>

            <p>House adjourned until 10 A. M. to-mor<lb break="no"/>row.</p>
            <p>       
           
           
           
    T. P. D.</p>


<!-- GL, 2016-11-18, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

<!--
            <p>THURSDAY, MARCH 22.</p>






            <p>The House, moved by Mr. Anglin, went<lb/>
into Committee of the Whole (Mr. Scovil<lb/>
in the Chair) on a Bill for the purpose of<lb/>
winding up the affaird of the Caledonia<lb/>
Mining and Manufacturing Company.<lb/>
Bill passed without discussion or amend<lb break="no"/>ment.</p>
            <p>At eleven the adjourned debate on the<lb/>
amendment to the 4th paragraph in the<lb/>
address, was taken up.</p>











            <p>MR. FRASER resumed his speech<lb/>
from yesterday afternoon. He said that <lb/>
there was the charged of which the House<lb/>
was <unclear n="">? </unclear> Government<lb/>
and it was a very <unclear n="">? </unclear> subject <unclear n="">?<lb/>
?<lb/>
?<lb/>
?<lb/>
?<lb/>
?</unclear>
               <lb/>
felt bound to say that the Government<lb/>
could not have appointed Judge Wilmot</p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>


















































            <p>to the position of Chief Justice and done<lb/>
justice to themselves. The hon. member<lb/>
of York (Mr. Fisher) said that there was<lb/>
no great political excitement at the time<lb/>
Judge Wilmot addressed the Grand Jury<lb/>
in Fredericton on the subject of Confede<lb break="no"/>ration. He wished to show that the poli-<lb break="maybe"/>
cal excitement was running very high at<lb/>
the time. The coutnry was agitated on<lb/>
the question of the Quebec Scheme. Mr.<lb/>
Fisher himself, who was the first who be<lb break="no"/>gan the discussion, he spoken in Carle<lb break="no"/>ton ; he was followed by his friend Mr. <lb/>
Needham. Mr. Tilley and Mr. Gray<lb/>
not long afterwards repeatedly addressed<lb/>
crowded audiences in the Mechanics In<lb break="no"/>stitute, St. John, and in Carleton. The<lb/>
excitement throughout the country was,<lb/>
there could be no doubt, running high. A<lb/>
keen political contest was looked forward<lb/>
to, for it was pretty well understood that<lb/>
the Governor was going to dissolve the<lb/>
House. It was amidst all this excite<lb break="no"/>ment that Judge Wilmot addressed the<lb/>
Grand Jury in Fredericton. His hon.<lb/>
colleague (Mr. Fisher) said that it was a<lb/>
common practice for Judges in their ad<lb break="no"/>dresses to speak on the topice of the day,<lb/>
and he had pointed to a precedent in the <lb/>
case of the late Chief Justice Parker.<lb/>
But there was a great difference between<lb/>
Judge Parker addressing a Jury on a<lb/>
School Law, and that of Judge Wilmot<lb/>
speaking with all the judicial authority of<lb/>
the Bench on a question affecting the very<lb/>
constitution of the coutnry. He denied<lb/>
his right to throw himself into the politi<lb break="no"/>cal excitement of the time, and his say<lb break="no"/>ing that he would, in case it was neces<lb break="no"/>sary to carry the Scheme of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, resign his seat up on the Bench and<lb/>
contest the County of York, was sufficient<lb/>
to condemn him in his mind. Further<lb/>
than that, Judge Wilmot voted against<lb/>
the Government of the day. If he (Judge<lb/>
W. chose to mix himself up with the po<lb break="no"/>litics of the day, he must as men i nthe
hum<lb break="no"/>bler situations of public trust, take the<lb/>
consequences : considering his position, <lb/>
he was bound to preserve a dignified<lb/>
silence.</p>


































            <p>Mr. Fraser then proceeded to speak on<lb/>
the charge against the Government for<lb/>
not fillinf up the office of Auditor Gene<lb break="no"/>ral, and referred to the late Auditor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, a gentleman who was well known to<lb/>
be a great financier, but equally well<lb/>
known for several years before his death<lb/>
to be incapable to discharge the duties of<lb/>
his offie. He was not pleased, he con<lb break="no"/>fessed, that the Government had filled up<lb/>
that office before this time, but was he to<lb/>
turn round, because they had not done so,<lb/>
and oppose them, and help probably to<lb/>
being in a Government that would inflict<lb/>
the Quebec Scheme upon the country. But<lb/>
he would say that as far as the business<lb/>
of the Audit Office was concerned, he had<lb/>
no fault to find with the Government. He<lb/>
never knew the public accounts to be pre<lb break="no"/>sented in such a clear, plain, mercantile<lb/>
manner as they had been this year. With<lb/>
regard to the Solicitor Generalship. As<lb/>
far as he himself was consulted in the<lb/>
Crown business, he had given good ad<lb break="no"/>vice, that is, in <unclear n="">? </unclear> judgment, <unclear n="">? </unclear>
               <lb/>
               <unclear n="">?<lb/>
? </unclear>
               <lb/>
               <unclear n="">? </unclear>
               <lb/>
               <unclear n="">?<lb/>
? </unclear>
               <lb/>
               <unclear n="">the country ? </unclear>
               <lb/>
               <unclear n="">?<lb/>
? the Government had not made the</unclear>
               <lb/>
appointment, particularly if the pay of<lb/>
the gentlemen employed did not exceed<lb/>
            </p>-->
     </div>    </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>