<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1865-06-05"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-06-05">5 June 1865</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1865</title>.
                    

          <date when="1865"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="134" to="139"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_134.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_135.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_136.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_137.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_138.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_139.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-08">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-08">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-21">Marked-up people</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_134">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_134.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_135">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_135.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_136">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_136.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_137">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_137.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_138">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_138.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_139">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_139.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="134" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_134.jpg"/>

<fw type="num">134</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> 

<!-- GL, 2016-11-01, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->         

   <!--<p> bit of dealing and trading with each <lb/>
other, and no inconvenience would arise <lb/>
from this union. If you take two bean <lb/>
poles and bind them together, you <lb/>
strengthen them, but if you put them <lb/>
end to end, it does not increase their <lb/>
strength. This Union between Upper and <lb/>
Lower Canada, has been like a cat
and <lb/>
dog union ; and they want to get
us to <lb/>
help them out of the scrape. The
popu<lb break="no"/>lation of Upper Canada increases very<lb/>
rapidly, and as representation
is by pop<lb break="no"/>ulation, we would soon be entirely <lb/>
swamped, and if the Canadians
wished to <lb/>
make an advantageous bargain with the <lb/>
United States, they could give up the <lb/>
fisheries of New Brunswick for the sake <lb/>
of getting an additional advantage for <lb/>
themselves. We are promised eighty <lb/>
cents a head on the population. We are <lb/>
to have $63,000 for ten years, our debt is <lb/>
to be increased to $7,000,000,
and a large <lb/>
amount of money is to be expended on the <lb/>
Intercolonial Railway ; but what security <lb/>
have we that those promises will be per<lb break="no"/>formed ? Ireland was induced to
unite <lb/>
with England in consequence of
certain <lb/>
inducements being held out. They
were <lb/>
promised Catholic emancipation, but how <lb/>
many years was it before they got it, and <lb/>
at what an expense of
heart-burnings be<lb break="no"/>fore it was accomplished, twenty-nine <lb/>
years after this union was established. <lb/>
This union was with a power celebrated <lb/>
for its integrity, but it was only after the <lb/>
most desperate efforts that Ireland
could <lb/>
succeed in getting what she was promis<lb break="no"/>ed as a condition for her entering this <lb/>
union. We, on the contrary, are
asked <lb/>
to unite with a people, that have tricked <lb/>
us once in regard to this Intercolonial
<lb/>
Railway, and should not trust their <lb/>
promises again. Then in reference
to this <lb/>
eighty cents a head ; as our population
in<lb break="no"/>creases, our wants increase, and we re<lb break="no"/>quire a larger expenditure for roads, <lb/>
schools and bridges ; but
instead of get<lb break="no"/>ting more we actually get less,
for we get <lb/>
$63,000 a-year for ten years, and is it to <lb/>
be supposed we will not want it eleven <lb/>
years hence. In a hundred years
hence, our <lb/>
population will have increased very large<lb break="no"/>ly, and our revenues will have increased <lb/>
immensely, for the people of this-Province
<lb/>
consume more duitable articles than
Ca<lb break="no"/>nada ; therefore, it is an
outrage to say <lb/>
we shall receive only this small
amount, <lb/>
eighty cents a head on the population of <lb/>
1861. It is our duty to legislate for those <lb/>
who come after us ; and it is
our duty as <lb/>
statesmen not to give up our country to <lb/>
gratify a few vain individuals. When we <lb/>
find men, who, instead of
looking after <lb/>
the interests of the people who have ele<lb break="no"/>vated them to a high position,
attempt to <lb/>
fly to still higher, their flight
is generally <lb/>
downwards, like that of a man who went <lb/>
to the top of a house with paper
wings to <lb/>
make a bird of himself. This has been <lb/>
the case with statesmen before, and will <lb/>
be so again. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>T. P. D. <lb/>
            </p>-->
  
            <head rendition="simple:right"> MONDAY, June 5. <lb/>
            </head>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:LAND1">Mr. LANDRY</persName>.—I
did not intend to say a <lb/>
word on this subject, and should
not do <lb/>
so now but to reply to a statement put
<lb/>
forth by the hon. member for
Albert, (Mr. <lb/>
McClellan) that the priests used their in<lb break="no"/>fluence with the people to get them to <lb/>
oppose
Confederation at the last elections. <lb/>
I know that it was not so in Westmorland
<lb/>
at any rate, for there they took no part <lb/>
whatever, either for or against. Some <lb/>
great men from St. John came up round <lb/>
our County, lecturing and talking
to the <lb/>
people to get them to support the Scheme, <lb/>
and they went on so that the
people <lb/>
   
<cb/>       
   
       thought they were mad. It has been <lb/>
said that if the question were to be sub<lb break="no"/>mitted to the people again in six months <lb/>
there would be a change. I think there <lb/>
would be too, but the change would be<lb/>
that there would be more opposed to the<lb/>
measure than ever.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.—A
great deal of time has<lb/>
been taken up in this discussion,
and a<lb/>
large amount of money lost to the country<lb/>
by it. I thought that the country had<lb/>
spoken out so loudly that Confederation<lb/>
was not only dead but buried face down<lb break="no"/>ward, and so deep that, as the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Charlotte said, it would not appear<lb/>
again at least for a long time. It seems,<lb/>
however, that it is not so from these reso<lb break="no"/>lutions, and the appointment of new dele<lb break="no"/>gates. In Northumberland there were<lb/>
seven candidates in the field ; six for Con<lb break="no"/>federation and one against. I
conceived<lb/>
at that time that from the threats made <lb/>
against us by the neighbouring republic,<lb/>
and the intimation that the protection of<lb/>
the mother country would likely be with<lb break="no"/>drawn from us in care of difficulties aris<lb break="no"/>ing, that it was necessary we
should con<lb break="no"/>tinue our united emerges to establish a<lb/>
power in these Colonies whose influence<lb/>
might be felt. Under these circumstances,<lb/>
I was constrained to support a Scheme <lb/>
that would not only thus unite us, but con<lb break="no"/>tinue to us that powerful protection
that<lb/>
we so much need. I have not changed<lb/>
my opinions since then. I believe that<lb/>
Canada is destined to be a great country ;<lb/>
she already pays half a million of dollars<lb/>
to support a line of Steam Ships to and<lb/>
from England, and then look at the mag<lb break="no"/>nitude of her public works. It has
been<lb/>
put forth by those opposed to Union that<lb/>
she is heavily in debt ; there
is no doubt <lb/>
of that, but then she has claims on the <lb/>
different Railways and other works of <lb/>
$40,000,000 or $50,000,000, and
the<lb/>
amount really due her is more than the<lb/>
interest on her whole debt. I believe that<lb/>
both the evils and benefits that would<lb/>
arise from a Union have been very much<lb/>
exaggerated. Let us now come down
to<lb/>
the Resolutions before us. Since Res<lb break="no"/>ponsible Government was first established <lb/>
here, we have never been called to delib<lb break="no"/>erate on such a Resolution. I say there<lb/>
has never been a case where the House<lb/>
has been asked to appoint delegates to go<lb/>
to England to lay before that people and <lb/>
Government the position and
state of this<lb/>
Province. Last Session delegates were<lb/>
appointed to take into
consideration a<lb/>
Union of the Maritime Provinces,
and a<lb/>
few days ago the Hon. President of the<lb/>
Council brought in a Resolution to con<lb break="no"/>tinue those negociations ; but notwith<lb break="no"/>standing the principle of the
Initiation of<lb/>
money grants being entirely in the hands<lb/>
of the Government, we now find a private<lb/>
member of the House comes forward with<lb/>
Resolutions which, if carried, involves <lb/>
the expenditure of a large sum
of money,<lb/>
we do not know how much. I say it is<lb/>
against the principle established by this<lb/>
House that a matter of this kind should<lb/>
be taken out of the hands of
Government.<lb/>
With regard to what has been said about
a<lb/>
power to be brought to bear on
us to force<lb/>
us into this Union, I do not
believe any<lb break="no"/>thing of the kind is
contemplated. Eng<lb break="no"/>land never did bring any power to bear <lb/>
to force her dependencies or
colonies to<lb/>
unite either with her or among themselves.<lb/>
In Scotland the matter was left
entirely in<lb/>
the hands of the Local Government, and <lb/>
the same in Ireland ; no power
was brought <lb/>
to bear upon them to force them to unite<lb/>
with England. <lb/>
            </p>
  



            <p> <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr.
ANGLIN</persName>.— Only a strong
out<lb break="no"/>side pressure. <lb/>
            </p>
            
<cb/>
           
 <p> <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.—Neither Nova Scotia nor<lb/>
Prince Edward Island, have appointed<lb/>
delegates to go Home, and why should<lb/>
we ? I do not believe that having conce<lb break="no"/>ded to us the power of self-Government,<lb/>
the Imperial Parliament will compel us to<lb/>
take any action with regard to Union that<lb/>
is opposed to the wishes of the people. I<lb/>
do not agree with the statement set forth<lb/>
in the Resolution that a Union of these<lb/>
Colonies would be politically, financially,<lb/>
and commercially disastrous, neither do I<lb/>
believe that having passed a Militia Bill<lb/>
that it is necessary to send Home a dele<lb break="no"/>gation to show that we are willing to do<lb/>
all we can to defend ourselves. As to our<lb/>
loyalty, that is a truism which nobody<lb/>
doubts, and therefore the delegates are not<lb/>
needed to prove it. The seventh Section<lb/>
of the preamble states that it is to be fear<lb break="no"/>ed that the Government and people of<lb/>
Great Britain are not aware of the true<lb/>
state of feeling here on the question of<lb/>
Confederation. If this is so, which I do<lb/>
not for a moment believe, why cannot<lb/>
they be informed without a delegation ?<lb/>
Above all, however, why does the Govern<lb break="no"/>ernment come to this House to ask our<lb/>
sanction to the appointment ? When we<lb/>
were sold to Jackson &amp; Co. for ?90,000,<lb/>
did the Government come to this House,<lb/>
and on all the other delegations to Great<lb/>
Britain, Canada, and elsewhere, did they<lb/>
ask for sanction to appoint delegates? No,<lb/>
this is the first time since the year 1833, that<lb/>
such as course has been taken. Then, be<lb break="no"/>fore the principle of Responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was recognized, and when a feeling<lb/>
was going about that the people of these<lb/>
Colonies were disloyal, Judge Street mov<lb break="no"/>ed for a delegation to England to lay be<lb break="no"/>fore the British Government the true state<lb/>
of feeling in this Province. But the pre<lb break="no"/>sent action is unprecedented—a private<lb/>
member brings in a Government measure,<lb/>
and to day the Hon. President of the<lb/>
Council moves to take up the order of the<lb/>
day. I believe that any course of action<lb/>
taken by the whole Government by des<lb break="no"/>patches would have more influence with<lb/>
the Imperial Government than anything<lb/>
which two delegates might be able to do<lb/>
by going Home. And when I see that<lb/>
anything which affects us must in like<lb/>
manner affect the other Provinces, and<lb/>
they have not appointed delegates, I do<lb/>
not see why we should take such a step.<lb/>
I shall therefore oppose the Resolutions.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:LEWI1">Mr. LEWIS</persName>.—I believe that this Union<lb/>
of the Provinces is a great Scheme, which<lb/>
would result in great good to this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. A great deal has been said and<lb/>
written on the subject, it has been can<lb break="no"/>vassed and recanvassed, it has been be<lb break="no"/>fore the people in every position in which<lb/>
it could be represented, and the people<lb/>
have spoken out upon it. I looked upon<lb/>
it with great favor, for I believed that it<lb/>
would tend to build us up and make us a<lb/>
great people. The great want we have<lb/>
always experienced was the absence of<lb/>
great public works, and these a Union<lb/>
would have given us. We wanted a Rail<lb break="no"/>road running through the heart of our<lb/>
country, opening up our wild lands, pre<lb break="no"/>paring the way for a system of coloniza<lb break="no"/>tion, and connecting us directly with Can<lb break="no"/>ada, and this the Scheme would have<lb/>
given to us on much better terms than we<lb/>
can get it without. I believed also that<lb/>
it would be the means of promoting and<lb/>
fostering our manufactories. It has been<lb/>
said that we cannot manufacture for Can<lb break="no"/>ada ; but if our infant manufactories were<lb/>
encouraged, and a field opened up for the<lb/>
produce of them in the other Provinces,<lb/>
we should soon be able to compete with<lb/>
any other country. It has been said that<lb/>
    

            <pb n="135" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_135.jpg"/>

<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">135</fw>

this Scheme was got up for the purpose ofs <lb/>
making some of our great
gentlemen Gov<lb break="no"/>ernors of these Provinces. Well I think <lb/>
that a praiseworthy object. (Laughter.)<lb/>
The Hon. President of the Council may<lb/>
laugh, but I believe that he would do <lb/>
honor to such a position. We should not <lb/>
be any the less loyal, because we had a<lb/>
few
of our leading me in such offices,<lb/>
and the Governor General would still be<lb/>
the tie binding us to the mother country.<lb/>
With regard to the elections in Albert, I<lb/>
may say that the question turned
exclu<lb break="no"/>sively on Confederation. There were <lb/>
some discontented spirits who came <lb/>
among us to stir up strife, but
they did<lb/>
not do much. There wero seven candi<lb break="no"/>dates in the field, and five of them were <lb/>
Confederates, and out of the 1,350 votes,<lb/>
about 600 were cast for
Confederation. <lb/>
But that question is dead the
present,<lb/>
and I now come here to do my duty as a <lb/>
representative of the country, and if
this <lb/>
Government introduce measures that I<lb/>
conceive to be beneficial, I shall support<lb/>
them. With regard to the Resolutions<lb/>
now before us, I believe that it is known<lb/>
in England just as well as it is here, that<lb/>
Confederation is gone, and they also know<lb/>
that we are, and always have been, a<lb/>
loyal people, and there is therefore no ne<lb break="no"/>cessity to send Home hon. gentlemen just<lb/>
to flourish round through England, and<lb/>
over the continent for no real good. I<lb/>
think it would be much better to take the<lb/>
money that will be thus expended, and put<lb/>
it on the bye-roads of the Province. I<lb/>
am opposed to the Resolutions.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName> —Before the debate<lb/>
closes I wish to offer a few remarks in ad<lb break="no"/>dition to what I have already said : In<lb/>
the County of Restigouche notwithstand<lb break="no"/>ing that Confederation was gone, and the<lb/>
leading members of the Government were<lb/>
overthrown before the election came off,<lb/>
yet the people cast their votes in favor<lb/>
of that Scheme. No Anti-Candidate need<lb/>
offer for that County. I may say that I<lb/>
feel under some difficulties in addressing<lb/>
the House again on this subject ; it is<lb/>
well-known that I have occupied more time<lb/>
this Session than ever I did before, and I<lb/>
have been forced to it by the fact that the<lb/>
hon. member for Sunbury and myself, are<lb/>
the only members of the late Government<lb/>
now left on the floors of this House. I<lb/>
shall, however, glance at the arguments<lb/>
which have been brought by those oppo<lb break="no"/>sed to this Scheme. And first in reply to<lb/>
the hon. member for the County of Saint<lb/>
John (Mr. Anglin). He has made use of<lb/>
strong language in reference to the Cham<lb break="no"/>ber of Commerce ; has said they were<lb/>
moved by some " hidden hand," and that<lb/>
falsehood and misrepresentation has been<lb/>
the order of the day. This " hidden hand"<lb/>
has come to be a familiar term, yet it<lb/>
seems to be a ghost to the present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, that frightens and terrifies them,<lb/>
and if they could by any possibility lay it<lb/>
as low, and bury it as deep as the hon<lb/>
member for Charlotte would have Con<lb break="no"/>federation buried, yet it would rise to ap<lb break="no"/>pal them. But I am happy to state that<lb/>
that hand is still under the control of a mind,<lb/>
and a grasp of intellect that has a power<lb/>
to make his opponents afraid and tremble.<lb/>
The dissolution of the House has been<lb/>
characterized as cruelty and oppression ;<lb/>
it might, certainly, appear like tyranny<lb/>
to those who did not wish to appeal to the<lb/>
people, but not to the people themselves.<lb/>
True, the season of the year was inclem<lb break="no"/>ent, but then it took none of the people<lb/>
from their duties ; and that it was not felt<lb/>
to be oppressive is clear from the fact that<lb/>
a larger vote was polled than ever before.<lb/>
Next is the Canadian tariff as compared<lb/>
         
            <cb/>  
    
with ours ; there it is 20 per cent,
whilst<lb/>
here it is only 15, and it is argued that<lb/>
we should have to come up to them. We<lb/>
admit 32 articles free of duty, and Canada<lb/>
44, and this, it is affirmed, would lower<lb/>
our revenue. But the way to arrive at a<lb/>
just conclusion on this point is to take<lb/>
the imports of the two countries and<lb/>
compare them, and we shall then find that<lb/>
whereas in Canada in 1863 it was 11 per<lb/>
cent., in New Brunswick it was 10 1.8 per<lb/>
cent. ; why then frighten the people with<lb/>
the cry of the tremendous difference in the<lb/>
tariff. Another point : it was said that<lb/>
the difference in 1863, if we had been in<lb/>
Confederation, would have been $250,000,<lb/>
and he said Mr. Tilley had made it<lb/>
$211,000.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLIN</persName>.—Mr. Tilley said we<lb/>
could abandon our use of brandy and<lb/>
spirits and save the duty on these ; we<lb/>
could save 10 cents a pound on tobacco<lb/>
by manufacturing it here, and in this way<lb/>
he tried to make up the amount ; but I<lb/>
challenge the hon. ex-Surveyor General<lb/>
to take the free list of Canada and make<lb/>
up anything like an amount equal to the<lb/>
$250,000.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. MCMILLAN</persName>.—I do not think that<lb/>
is the right way to take it. I think the<lb/>
proper plan is to average the imports of<lb/>
the two Provinces. Canada has so far<lb/>
advanced that she can support her local<lb/>
manufactures and save importation to a<lb/>
large extent, and this is an argument in<lb/>
favor of Union, as we should go on with<lb/>
her and be able to support our manufac<lb break="no"/>tories, and get an increase of customers.<lb/>
While I am not prepared to say that our<lb/>
local expenditure would not be increased,<lb/>
I do not believe they would increase to<lb/>
to the extent that has been said. The<lb/>
general government would have to deal<lb/>
with general and large matters, and the<lb/>
time occupied in their discussion would<lb/>
be shorter than now, and the same in the<lb/>
local legislatures, where they would only<lb/>
discuss local matters ; and, while the ex<lb break="no"/>pense would be, perhaps, somewhat in<lb break="no"/>creased, a great saving would be made in<lb/>
the time occupied in Session. It has been<lb/>
said that under Confederation we should<lb/>
dwindle down to a mere municipality, yet<lb/>
this Session only two measures have come<lb/>
before us—the Treasury Note Bill and the<lb/>
Post Office Bill—that would not be dis<lb break="no"/>cussed in the local legislature. But,<lb/>
it is asked, who would come here<lb/>
as a representation under Confed<lb break="no"/>eration? I reply that our young men<lb/>
of intellect and power would come here<lb/>
to obtain a political education, to fit<lb/>
them for positions in the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and for a Governorship of the<lb/>
Colonies. It is a high and a grand prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of ambition implanted in the hu<lb break="no"/>man heart and soul that would animate<lb/>
our young men to raise themselves to<lb/>
positions of rank and power. The hon.<lb/>
member for St. John further said that<lb/>
the 80 cents a head was a high sum for<lb/>
Canada to receive, but small for New<lb/>
Brunswick. I do not understand how<lb/>
this can be. I ask if ten years ago we<lb/>
did not get more for local purposes than<lb/>
we do now? Yes, and why? Be<lb break="no"/>cause we have paid out large sums for<lb/>
our great public works, and therefore<lb/>
have not the money for local purposes.<lb/>
But under Confederation we should re<lb break="no"/>ceive 80 cents a head for all time to come<lb/>
to add to our revenue for these works.<lb/>
And then there is the question of taxa<lb break="no"/>tion. Out of Confederation what are<lb/>
we to do ? In a few days we are to have<lb/>
up the resolutions relative to the West<lb break="no"/>ern Extension, and for that purpose shall<lb/>
be called on to vote $260,000 or $270,<lb break="no"/><cb/>000 to commence the work, and if this<lb/>
be done how are the appropriations for<lb/>
schools, roads, bridges, to be upheld but<lb/>
by direct taxation. There will be no 80<lb/>
cents a head to fall back upon. It is as<lb/>
clear as noonday that if we are to have<lb/>
direct taxation it would be farther off,<lb/>
at least in union, than out of it. Then<lb/>
for militia purposes we should have<lb/>
$1,000,000, and it is said that this is<lb/>
nothing at all. Then, I would ask,<lb/>
what is the $30,000 we granted the other<lb/>
day, for us separated, and a frag<lb break="no"/>ment as now ; but united under one<lb/>
power, one interest, animated by one<lb/>
common feeling I believe that $1,000,<lb break="no"/>000 would be something. Our propor<lb break="no"/>tion of that sum would be $70,000, more<lb/>
than double what we now give. How<lb/>
then can it be said that $1,000,000 is so<lb/>
small? It is not expected by the British<lb/>
Government that we are to do all to<lb break="no"/>ward our own defence. They do not<lb/>
look for it, and it is but right and manly<lb/>
and independent that we should contri<lb break="no"/>bute something. What does the Col<lb break="no"/>onial Secretary say in his despatches :<lb/>
he hopes that operations can be carried<lb/>
on without imposing a tax upon the peo<lb break="no"/>ple ; shewing that the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment do not wish to saddle the country<lb/>
with more than we are able to bear.<lb/>
The hon. President of the Council has<lb/>
referred to the difference in race and<lb/>
creed in the people of Canada. I will<lb/>
quote on this subject an extract from one<lb/>
of the most eloquent men on this contin<lb break="no"/>ent, Mr. D'A. McGee :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p> " I venture, in the first place, to ob<lb break="no"/>serve that there seems to be a good deal<lb/>
of exaggeration on the subject of race,<lb/>
occasionally introduced both on the one<lb/>
side and the other in this section of our<lb/>
country. This theory of race is some<lb break="no"/>times carried to an anti-christian and<lb/>
unphilosophical excess. Whose words<lb/>
are those—" God hath made of one<lb/>
blood all the nations that dwell on the<lb/>
face of the earth."<lb/>
            </p>
</quote>


            <p> This is the right view to take of this<lb/>
question. Look at the position of affairs<lb/>
in the Mother Country ; there they are<lb/>
composed of all peoples, and yet they go<lb/>
on quietly and harmoniously. Then an<lb break="no"/>other point taken up is our trifling trade<lb/>
with Canada. Why, the same cry was<lb/>
raised in Canada ; there it was said that<lb/>
the Lower Provinces were so poor that<lb/>
they were not worth the expense that<lb/>
would be incurred by Canada. The<lb/>
Hon. Mr. Brown says:</p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" I hold in my hand a return of arti<lb break="no"/>cles purchased by the Maritime Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces from the United States in 1863,<lb/>
which Canada could have supplied. I<lb/>
will not detain the House by reading it,<lb/>
but any member who desires can have<lb/>
it for examination. The total value of<lb/>
products which the Lower Provinces<lb/>
might have bought more advantageous<lb break="no"/>ly from us, summer up to over seven<lb/>
millions of dollars."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>It is the want of direct trade that makes<lb/>
the hard feelings, and if these were<lb/>
broken down we should be much better<lb/>
off. Then the Hon. Mr. Ferrier shows<lb/>
what the Inter-colonial railroad would<lb/>
do that a trade in produce would spring<lb/>
up, and a large traffic would pass over<lb/>
it every day in the year. He shows that<lb/>
we import from the United States $2,000,<lb break="no"/>000 worth more produce than we export<lb/>
there. If we had this road we should<lb/>
bring direct from Canada, whereas now<lb/>
           

            <pb n="136" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_136.jpg"/>

<fw type="num">136</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> 
        
 we bring
a large amount of the articles <lb/>
we use down from Canada to
Portland, <lb/>
thence by boat to St. John, and
then by <lb/>
rail and boat again almost up to
Canada <lb/>
again. How much cheaper and better <lb/>
would it be to bring the articles direct. <lb/>
Then it has been said that the
railroad <lb/>
would be of little good for the
purpose <lb/>
of defence. This is the first time I have <lb/>
heard such a statement put
forth, and I <lb/>
think that all experience is opposed
to <lb/>
such an idea. I regret to hear it used <lb/>
as an argument against this union that <lb/>
we should be dragged up to Canada to <lb/>
fight her battles. I think it a very nar<lb break="no"/>row and contracted view to take of the <lb/>
question. Is it not our duty, as British <lb/>
subjects, if the enemy's foot is
planted <lb/>
at Niagara or in Nova Scotia, to march <lb/>
to the assistance of our
neighbors in <lb/>
their troubles. Again it has been said <lb/>
that an effort will made to force us <lb/>
into Confederation. This would be di<lb break="no"/>rect violation of that principle of self- <lb break="yes"/>
government which has been
accorded <lb/>
to us. Why then put it abroad
that the <lb/>
British Government will try and coerce <lb/>
us into a union against our
wishes? I<lb/>
feel that it is my duty to raise
my voice, <lb/>
feeble though it may be, to contradict
<lb/>
any such statement, inasmuch as we <lb/>
have the despatch of the Colonial Sec<lb break="no"/>retary, in which it is emphatically
stated <lb/>
that it cannot be. Then the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the Government for St.
John <lb/>
(Mr. Anglin) insinuates that the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment have received some informa<lb break="no"/>tion that a delegation is necessary to <lb/>
counteract the action of schemers, con<lb break="no"/>spirators, and so forth. Why not <lb/>
then lay the information before the- <lb break="yes"/>
House? I think such remarks are <lb/>
entirely uncalled for, and at any <lb/>
rate should not come from such a
source. <lb/>
It is said that the leaders of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion were animated by feelings of sel<lb break="no"/>fishness in their action ; but
are not the <lb/>
opponents of the scheme as liable
to the <lb/>
same charge? The hon. President
of the <lb/>
Council said that Mr. Tilley had chang<lb break="no"/>ed. Is he not as open to such
an intima<lb break="no"/>tion as any other man in this Province? <lb/>
Does he undertake to say that
all politi<lb break="no"/>cal honesty is concentrated: in
Dorches<lb break="no"/>ter Corner? I do not say Confederation <lb/>
will come in six months or in two years, <lb/>
but I believe it will come. If the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of isolation and stagnation which <lb/>
is now upheld be a correct one, how is<lb/>
it that the United States has spent so<lb/>
much treasure and spilt so much blood<lb/>
to preserve their union? If it is a true<lb/>
principle then must we charge them with<lb/>
folly after eighty years' experience, and<lb/>
having grown to a people numbering<lb/>
some of 30,000,000 ; and with consummate<lb/>
ignorance in doing what they have to<lb/>
save a Union which we pronounce to be<lb/>
politically, commercially, and financially<lb/>
disastrous. The President of the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil goes on to say that we cannot find a<lb/>
parallel for the action taken by us. Sup<lb break="no"/>posing we had done as they did in Cana<lb break="no"/>da, then we might be charged whit<lb/>
striving to force the measure upon the<lb/>
people, but we never attempted anything<lb/>
of the kind.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName>.—I said that there<lb/>
was no parallel in history where men<lb/>
without any authority from the people<lb/>
attempted to render up the independence<lb/>
of the country.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">MR. MCMILLAN</persName>.—In the point of in<lb break="no"/>depence I cannot agree with him. But<lb/>
does he lay it down that we should not<lb/>
meet and mature plans for the benefit<lb/>
of the people? And if this be done can<lb/>
we be charged with forcing any measures<lb/>
       
            <cb/>            
        
upon the people? It seems to me a <lb/>
strange coincidence that in the counties <lb/>
of York and St. John where the officers <lb/>
were opposed to the scheme that the <lb/>
elections were appointed to come off
<lb/>
first. The hon. President further says <lb/>
that according to the amount given to <lb/>
roads and bridges in Canada we should <lb/>
only get $15,000 for the same
purpose. <lb/>
This was met and answered by Mr.
<lb/>
Steadman at Salisbury, but I will show <lb/>
that by the eighty cents a head arrange<lb break="no"/>ment we should get more. <lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre"> LOCAL
INCOME FOR NEW
BRUNSWICK IN<lb/>
CONFEDERATION<lb/>
            </head>

<table>
<row><cell>Subsidy from General Gov't,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$201,600 </cell></row>
<row><cell>Export Duty and Council<lb/>
Revenue,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">90,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Supreme Court Fees,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">4,600</cell></row>
<row><cell>Auction Duties,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">800</cell></row>
<row><cell>Interest on difference be<lb break="no"/>tween real debt and <lb/>
assumed
debt,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">65,000</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$361,800</cell></row>
<row><cell>In case the debt is increased <lb/>
to the amount assumed <lb/>
then we get $63,000 for <lb/>
ten years.</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"></cell></row>
<row><cell>Civil list,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$30,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Legislative expense,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">30,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Fisheries,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">700</cell></row>
<row><cell>Agriculture,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">10,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Penitentiary,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">6,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Lunatic Asylum,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">16,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Public Health,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">4,800</cell></row>
<row><cell>Pensions,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Judicial expense,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">8,800</cell></row>
<row><cell>Emigration,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">1,000</cell></row>
<row><cell>Unforseen expense,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right"><hi rendition="simple:underline">2,000</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell></cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$109,300 <hi rendition="simple:underline">109,300</hi></cell></row>
<row><cell>Balance left for our Schools,<lb/>
Roads and Bridges,</cell><cell rendition="simple:right">$251,500</cell></row>
</table>

</div>

<div type="section">
          
  <p> This
is a much larger sum than we <lb/>
have given this year, but in
reality we <lb/>
have nothing to do with what Canada<lb/>
does ; she can use her 80 cents a head as<lb/>
she likes. The next point is the debt of<lb/>
Canada. He says that she has exhaust<lb break="no"/>ed all her means and had to fall back <lb/>
upon the stamp duties. Here is a finan<lb break="no"/>cial statement of Canada. (Mr. McMil<lb break="no"/>an here read the tables which already <lb/>
appear in the speech of Mr. Connell, to<lb/>
shew the comparative position of the<lb/>
two countries. The debt of Canada,<lb/>
per head, is ther given as $20.93 ;<lb/>
whilst that of New Brunswick. per head,<lb/>
is $20.91.)<lb/>
            </p>


            <p> This is
their indebtedness per head,<lb/>
with their immense resources, only two<lb/>
cents per head difference between them<lb/>
and us. The hon. President of the<lb/>
Council says there is one railway that is<lb/>
going to pay six per cent. I heard him<lb/>
make a very different statement some<lb/>
time ago. Then he remarked that every<lb/>
passenger that went over that line cost<lb/>
the country $20. I say this just to show<lb/>
that he too changes.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I never said that<lb/>
one railway would not pay six per cent.<lb/>
20 year hence.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. MCMILLAN</persName>.—I will now give the<lb/>
opinion of a celebrated Anti in Canada<lb/>
on the railway. The Hon. Mr. Rierson<lb/>
says :—</p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"Why, this Intercolonial Railway is to<lb/>
be built out of the funds of the Interco<lb break="no"/>lonial Government that is proposed to<lb/>
be established, so that instead of Canada<lb/>
having to pay only five-twelfths of the<lb/>
           
            <cb/>
        
whole cost she will have to pay ten- <lb break="yes"/>
twelfths. This will involve five to seven <lb/>
millions of dollars of an expense more<lb/>
than we had any occasion for incurring, <lb/>
for the other Provinces were all willing <lb/>
to have been responsible for the rest, <lb/>
and there is very good reason
why they <lb/>
should. The countries to be benefited <lb/>
by the Intercolonial Railway are New <lb/>
Brunswick and Nova Scotia, but especi<lb break="no"/>ally the former. In that Province there
<lb/>
is an extensive wilderness with
some <lb/>
valuable lumber limits if not much <lb/>
farming land through which this road <lb/>
will have to pass and every acre of <lb/>land within twenty or thirty miles of the<lb/>
Road will be largely increased in value. <lb/>
New Brunswick would gain that advan<lb break="no"/>tage, while as for Nova Scotia,
Halifax, <lb/>
its chief port, will be made an outlet by <lb/>
the construction of the line and
will of <lb/>
course be largely benefited, so that they<lb/>
equitable. But in coming down with a <lb/>
scheme which involves us in twice as <lb/>
great an expenditure as was formerly 
<lb/>
contemplated, they seem not to have <lb/>
been satisfied unless we handed over to <lb/>
the Federal Government our public <lb/>
works. These, hon. gentlemen, are
of <lb/>
immense value to Canada. By imposing<lb/>
tolls on our canals to an extent which <lb/>
they would easily bear and which would <lb/>
not prevent us carrying on the same <lb/>
immense trade as at present, we could <lb/>
readily raise half a million of dollars a <lb/>
year. The Welland Canal alone has<lb/>
produced a revenue of $200,000 a year  <lb/>
Well, all such sources of income are to <lb/>
be thrown into the hands of the Federal <lb/>
Government, while New Brunswick is <lb/>
to give us a Railway which only pays <lb/>
three-eighths of one per cent.
over its <lb/>working expenses. This small sum, re<lb break="no"/>member too, is what is paid now — two <lb/>
or three years after the construction of  <lb/>
the line. But when the rolling stock <lb/>
get out of repairs, the rails want renew<lb break="no"/>ing, and other matters usual
after a <lb/>
railroad has been some time working <lb/>
have to be attended to. The expenses <lb/>
of this line to the Federal Government <lb/>
will constantly increase. The road will <lb/>
be a drag, and I say to hon. gentlemen <lb/>
we are opening an account without <lb/>
knowing when it will be closed. By en<lb break="no"/>gaging in the construction of the Inter- <lb break="yes"/>
colonial Railway and the assumption of <lb/>
the New Brunswick and Nova Scotia<lb/>
lines, we are entering upon undefinite<lb/>
liabilities., the whole being non-paying<lb/>
property in which we shall find a heavy<lb/>
bill of expense.</p>
            <p>Then, if not satisfied with this, we are<lb/>
giving a sort of <hi rendition="simple:italic">Regium donum</hi> of $63<lb break="no"/>000 for ten years to the Province of New<lb/>
Brunswick."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>If I recollect well the President of the <lb/>
Council made use of the same argument <lb/>
in 1863, with regard to the payment of <lb/>
Railways as this gentleman does.  It is <lb/>
clearly evident that they think they are<lb/>
giving us a much better bargain than they <lb/>
gain. I wish to put a question to the<lb/>
Hon. Chief Commissioner of the Board of <lb/>
Works, and I am sure he will answer it. <lb/>
All manner of insinuations have been <lb/>
thrown out that the leader of the late Go<lb break="no"/>vernment intended to force the question <lb/>
through the House ; I now ask him
if when <lb/>the question was asked, "What was to be <lb/>
done" he did not reply, "That is
left <lb/>
to each Government to decide ?"   <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:HATH1">Hon Mr. HATHEWAY</persName>.—The
reply of the <lb/>
Provincial Secretary was most decided<lb break="no"/>ly. It was on the 16th of November
that <lb/>
he told us, and Mr. Fisher, Mr. Galt, Mr.<lb/>
         
            <pb n="137" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_137.jpg"/>

<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">137</fw>
      
Cartier. and Dr. Tupper, made a similar<lb/>
statement in their respective Provinces. </p>
            <p>
<persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. MCMILLAN</persName>.—A compliment has <lb/>
been paid to me by the statement that <lb/>
when the matter came before the Council<lb/>
I was the one to stand out against its not <lb/>
being submitted to the people.
But I<lb/>
now state that there was not a dissenting<lb/>
voice in the whole Council. The
Hon <lb/>
Chief Commissioner has said that
when<lb/>
he was in Canada he found that
they<lb/>
would not agree that the Intercolonial<lb/>
Railroad should go by any other route<lb/>
than by the North Shore, and that this <lb/>
was decided in Nova Scotia and in
Eng<lb break="no"/>land.
<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:HATH1">Hon. Mr. HATHEWAY</persName> —While
in Can<lb break="no"/>ada, I heard that the Duke of Newcastle<lb/>
had told Mr. Tilley that no line
would go <lb/>
within 15 miles of the river Saint John.<lb/>
as i was not considered safe in
case of <lb/>
difficulties with the United States.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. MCMILLAN</persName>.—I never knew that<lb/>
any particular route was decided on ; I<lb/>
thought it was to be left to England to<lb/>
decide. I wished, very naturally, that it<lb/>
should go by the North Shore ; but I did<lb/>
not know it was settled on. Then, it is<lb/>
said, there were a good many disappointed<lb/>
politicians who expected to go to Ottawa ;<lb/>
but I will not say anything about that.<lb/>
Now for the hon. member for St. John<lb/>
(Mr. Wetmore): he delivered a speech<lb/>
that, from the style of its delivery and its<lb/>
beautifully rounded periods, must have<lb/>
been thoroughly prepared. If unuendo,<lb/>
if the imputing of all manner of motives,<lb/>
are arguments against Confederation, then<lb/>
his speech is unanswerable ; but if the<lb/>
points are that Confederation is commer<lb break="no"/>ciall, financially and politically disastrous.<lb/>
then his speech is a great failure. He<lb/>
took up the Coles' Island Bridge, Mr.<lb/>
Watters' election as Mayor of St. John,<lb/>
and how the would-be Mayor was caught<lb/>
in a trap, and money interests at elections;<lb/>
what have these to do with Confederation?<lb/>
But another point that he seemed to<lb/>
imagine was most convincing was the ex<lb break="no"/>port duty from Canada. It appeared to be<lb/>
very funny, but it had little to do with the<lb/>
question before us. I will now only make<lb/>
a few general remarks in conclusion. I<lb/>
have referred to the history and experi<lb break="no"/>ence of the United States, and the efforts<lb/>
they have put out to sustain their union,<lb/>
but we, in our wisdom and with our popu<lb break="no"/>lation of 250,000, repudiate any such<lb/>
idea as union. Instead of bringing a<lb/>
charge against our public men, that they<lb/>
aspire to be Governors of Provinces and<lb/>
are actuated only by selfish and wrong<lb/>
motives, the idea ought to be fostered<lb/>
and encouraged. This charge came first<lb/>
from the hon. President of the Council,<lb/>
and it has been echoed by his satellites<lb/>
all over the country ; but it should not<lb/>
have any influence in such a question as<lb/>
this. Then what has the Government<lb/>
now to depend on to raise the resources<lb/>
of the country—what is there but lumber<lb/>
to depend on ? But in Confederation we<lb/>
should not be so dependent as now ; if<lb/>
lumber fails, we could fall back on the<lb/>
crops of Canada, and the Provincial Sec<lb break="no"/>retary would not have the difficulty he<lb/>
now experiences in making up his budget.<lb/>
I feel that I am not able for this great<lb/>
matter ; but, having been associated with<lb/>
a man who, although charged with being<lb/>
a "conspirator" and as using a " hidden<lb/>
hand" to work out his designs, has yet<lb/>
an intellect and financial abilities that<lb/>
would fit him for a high position and do<lb/>
honor to any land, I feel called on to speak<lb/>
out in his behalf. It may be said that<lb/>
those in favor of this scheme are subject<lb/>
to "cramming," but that is not likely to<lb/>
           
            <cb/>
       
deter me from my purpose. I regret he is<lb/>
not on the floors of the House to raise his<lb/>
voice in answer to the opponents of this<lb/>
measure , then there would be less said<lb/>
then there has been on this question, and<lb/>
the hon. President of the Council might<lb/>
again decline to enter into an argument<lb/>
with him.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—Now I wish to say,<lb/>
once for all, that I did not refuse to enter<lb/>
into an argument with Mr. Tilley. That<lb/>
gentleman, I believe, stated that he chal<lb break="no"/>lenged me to speak at Lingley Hall, in<lb/>
Sackville, but it was thus : I received an<lb/>
invitation from the Secretary, but he stat<lb break="no"/>ed that I should not be allowed to speak.<lb/>
When the statement was made that I had<lb/>
refused to meet Mr. Tilley, I wrote to the<lb/>
papers—both the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Freeman</hi> and the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Tele<lb break="no"/>graph</hi>—that it was not true.
</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. MCMILLAN</persName>.—I
took my informa<lb break="no"/>tion from the papers, but it is
no matter. <lb/>
Now for the resolutions—what are they ? <lb/>
I have no hope that any thing I
may say <lb/>
will change the views of any one on the <lb/>
floors of this Honse, They state that an <lb/>
election has taken place—that an
appeal <lb/>
has been made to the people—that they <lb/>
have decided against
Confederation—that <lb/>
they know every attention will
be paid to <lb/>
the expression of the people,
and then, in <lb/>
the face of all this, they
ask
that a dele<lb break="no"/>gation be sent home to tell the
people of <lb/>
England all this that they
already know <lb/>
as well as we do. There are intimations<lb/>
that in Canada, in Nova Scotia, and in<lb/>
this Province there is some " hidden<lb/>
hand," and yet they do not lay their<lb/>
information before the House. We know<lb/>
that Confederation will not be forced upon<lb/>
us, and yet we must send men home to<lb/>
ask that it be not. Suppose they go, the<lb/>
Imperial Cabinet will ask, "What is your<lb/>
business, Mr. President?" "Oh, we hear<lb/>
that there is some underhanded work<lb/>
going on, and we came over to let you<lb/>
know that we have decided against Con<lb break="no"/>federation." This would, certainly, be<lb/>
very satisfactory, and well worthy of the<lb/>
expense to be incurred. I am opposed to<lb/>
the Resolutions.<lb/>
            </p>


            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">Hon. Mr. GILLMOR</persName>.—I claim to be a<lb/>
good listener, but have no pretensions to<lb/>
being a good speaker. I have listened<lb/>
attentively to the speeches made upon<lb/>
these resolutions. The hon. ex-Surveyor<lb/>
General has made several long speeches ;<lb/>
he has now made a sort of general reply<lb/>
to several hon. members, so I shall not<lb/>
attempt to follow him ;—their speeches<lb/>
will appear, and the public can judge of<lb/>
the arguments. He asks me how I feel ?<lb/>
In reply, I beg to inform him that I am quite<lb/>
well, both physically and politically ; and<lb/>
if we can succeed in getting a few matters<lb/>
set right on the other side of the water,<lb/>
in reference to Confederation, all will be<lb/>
well. I do not think it important that<lb/>
the question of Confederation should now<lb/>
be fully discussed ; it has been ably han<lb break="no"/>dled, both through the press and upon<lb/>
the platform, and the people in this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince have given their verdict, and it has<lb/>
been so decidedly in condemnation of the<lb/>
scheme that a wayfaring man, through a<lb/>
fool, need not fail to understand. The<lb/>
friends of this scheme had it in their own<lb/>
hands, and managed it in their own way ;<lb/>
and yet, was there ever a question upon<lb/>
which the people of this or any other<lb/>
country spoke out more plainly, and gave<lb/>
a decision more conclusive ? The hon<lb/>
member for Albert says, this question of<lb/>
Confederation is not new. I have been a<lb/>
member of the Assembly for ten years,<lb/>
and neither I nor any other member ever<lb/>
heard it discussed in this Assembly. I<lb/>
remember to have read a discussion had<lb/>
      
            <cb/>
        
between the Hon. Joseph Howe and, I <lb/>
think, a Mr Uniack, some ten years ago, <lb/>
and occasionally Judge Wilmot
has allud<lb break="no"/>ed
to it in some of his speeches ; and, ex<lb break="no"/>cept occasional allusions of this kind, it <lb/>
is new to the people, and not one in a <lb/>
hundred of the electors knew
anything <lb/>
about this until after the delegates re<lb break="no"/>turned from Quebec. This scheme had <lb/>
its origin in Canada ; their necessities <lb/>
called for it, not ours. An idea of this <lb/>
scheme was communicated to the leading
<lb/>
politicians of the Lower
Provinces, and <lb/>
they went to Quebec and held the
Con<lb break="no"/>ference. I shall make no reference to the <lb/>
constitutionality of this
delegation, but I <lb/>
do know that the people did not send <lb/>
them. Now, if there is any class
of per<lb break="no"/>sons that are calculated to impose upon<lb/>
the people more than another, it is the <lb/>
makers and venders of quack medicine. <lb/>
These doctors went there, and in the space <lb/>
of seventeen days they prepared what I call <lb/>
a quack medicine ; having got it
prepared, <lb/>
they next had to return and make the <lb/>
people feel that they were sick. They <lb/>
might have labelled it, "health and ? <lb/>
fort for all ;"
so they told them that they <lb/>
were financially
distressed and commer<lb break="no"/>cially depressed ; that they
could not get<lb/>
along or expand unless they took this <lb/>
medicine. So they went to work recom<lb break="no"/>mending the panacea, and some of the <lb/>
people soon began to feel sick, but many <lb/>
began
to ask how much the medicine
was <lb/>
going to cost. If you look into the scheme, <lb/>
you will see a medicine fixed up for all the <lb/>
politicians ; they had certain ends to <lb/>
work out, and
so they put into this medi<lb break="no"/>cine a larger
amount of <hi rendition="simple:italic">Soothing Syrup</hi>, <lb/>
and this was especially intended for the <lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">House of
Lords</hi> ; and it had its effect
as <lb/>
forcibly upon men as it does upon child<lb break="no"/>ren, as recent events have
proved, and <lb/>
they expected it would so
operate upon <lb/>
all the people. This matter was argued <lb/>
out by the candidates upon both sides. <lb/>
and in Charlotte County the Confederates
<lb/>
had an advocate, who, for eloquence and <lb/>
fluency, was not inferior to the ablest ad<lb break="no"/>vocate in this Province ; and yet, in a <lb/>
constituency
of some 3,200 voters. I do <lb/>
not think there were more than 600
out-<lb/>
and-out Confederates. In this I may be<lb/>
mistaken, but that is my opinion. The <lb/>
arguments in favor of the scheme were <lb/>
vague and indefinite. They said our <lb/>
young men were going away, and this
<lb/>
was going to keep them all at
home ; <lb/>
adopt this, and no fond mother was ever <lb/>
to weep for an absent son, and no tender <lb/>
lover was ever again to part from his <lb/>
sweetheart. The people, however,
had <lb/>
no idea it was going to produce
such re<lb break="no"/>sults ; in Charlotte, this quest on, at least,
<lb/>
was fairly tried. During the ten years I <lb/>
have been in politics, I have given the late <lb/>
Government my support ; and, although <lb/>
I have voted against some of their mea<lb break="no"/>sures, up to the time of the last proroga<lb break="no"/>tion I would not have voted
against them <lb/>
in a direct vote of want of
confidence. <lb/>
Now, if this Confederation scheme was <lb/>so old and so good, why was it never dis<lb break="no"/>cussed upon the floors of this House ;<lb/>
during that long term they had not dis<lb break="no"/>covered that we were such an
insignificant <lb/>
people and that our resources were so <lb/>
limited. On the contrary, they were con<lb break="no"/>tinually telling us that we had vast re<lb break="no"/>sources, and were all right, both politi<lb break="no"/>cally and financially, and it was a favorite <lb/>
expression of one of the delegates. "that <lb/>
he had an abiding faith in the people." I <lb/>
do not know exactly what he thinks of <lb/>
that now. When the late Government <lb/>
came into power ten years ago
this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince was really free from debt.
It was <lb/>
          
            <pb n="138" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_138.jpg"/>

<fw type="num">138</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> 
  
 thought
we wanted public works, and I<lb/>
supported them in their Railway Scheme<lb/>
of 1856 ; that undertaking involved us,<lb/>
with other liabilities, to the extent of six<lb/>
millions of dollars. This, in their opin<lb break="no"/>ion, was not all we could stand, so they<lb/>
undertook 3 1 2 12ths of the Intercolonial<lb/>
road, estimated to cost three million<lb/>
pounds sterling. According to the cost<lb/>
of the St. John and Shediac road, as com<lb break="no"/>pared with the cost, that amount might be<lb/>
doubled ; but we are safe in saying it<lb/>
would cost fourteen millions of dollars, our<lb/>
part of that would be $5,833,000. Not<lb/>
thinking, even then, that our resources<lb/>
would be exhausted, at the last Session<lb/>
they introduced and carried their Subsidy<lb/>
Bill, providing $10,000 per mile for 188<lb/>
miles of road, involving an additional lia<lb break="no"/>bility of $1,780,000 more-making in all<lb/>
at close of last Session $13,613,000.<lb/>
These acts were upon the statute book,<lb/>
and, of course, they thought and said we<lb/>
were able to carry all this out ; if so it ill<lb/>
becomes them to speak of us as very in<lb break="no"/>significant and poor and isolated. I<lb/>
thought then, and I think now, they over<lb/>
estimated our resources, and if there were<lb/>
any political trouble, they had time and<lb/>
power to have remedied them—but the<lb/>
discovery was made just when they wanted<lb/>
this great change. I do not profess to be<lb/>
well acquainted with the history of Can<lb break="no"/>ada, but it is well known that for many<lb/>
years there has been a great deal of poli<lb break="no"/>tical discord there, and to remedy this I<lb/>
think this scheme was originated. My<lb/>
hon. friend from Albert says they are our<lb/>
brother colonists, and we ought to go in<lb/>
and help them out of their difficulties. It<lb/>
reminds me of a little story told by my<lb/>
colleague, Mr. Hill ; A steamboat was<lb/>
coming down the Mississippi ; there was<lb/>
on board a tall, grave young man—so<lb/>
grave and sober that he was observed by<lb/>
all the passengers. When the boat ar<lb break="no"/>rived at Vicksburg and the passengers<lb/>
landed on the wharf, there was a great<lb/>
fight going on there. This young man<lb/>
brightened up, and asked some of the by<lb break="no"/>standers if it was a free fight? They said<lb/>
" Yes." Says he, " Has any one a right<lb/>
to go in?" "Yes." said they. He took<lb/>
off his coat and pitched in. In a short<lb/>
time he returned to the boat, with a pair<lb/>
of black eyes and his nose considerably<lb/>
canted, very strongly convinced that it<lb/>
would have been for his interest to have<lb/>
remained out of the fight. Now this man<lb/>
got served as we should had we gone into<lb/>
this Union, with this exception—he got<lb/>
out, we would have had to remain in. It<lb/>
has been stated by some of the advocates<lb/>
of this scheme, that when the Delegates<lb/>
left the Conference, the Governments of<lb/>
each of the Provinces were to use such<lb/>
measures as they thought best to secure<lb/>
its passage in the different Colonies.<lb/>
Those who could get it passed without<lb/>
submitting it to the people were to do so ;<lb/>
those who felt sure of carrying it by<lb/>
going to the country were to do so. This,<lb/>
certainly, was not a very uniform mode of<lb/>
commencing this great nationality. I am<lb/>
not aware of what the intention of our<lb/>
Government was on their return home ; at<lb/>
the time I thought they would call the<lb/>
Legislature together at the usual time,<lb/>
discuss the question, and decide it at the<lb/>
General Election which would have been<lb/>
this summer ; and not until a very few<lb/>
days before the dissolution did I believe<lb/>
the House was to have been dissolved. It<lb/>
was stated that Mr. Tilley, in answer to<lb/>
a question put to him by Mr. McShane,<lb/>
in Carleton, as to his intention to appeal<lb/>
to the people, said that it would not be<lb/>
decided without an appeal to the people.<lb/>
            </p>
            
<cb/>
            
<p> Had I been present, I should certainly <lb/>
have concluded from that reply
that he did <lb/>
not intend to dissolve the House ;
but the <lb/>
answer was a perfectly safe one.
If he <lb/>
intended to dissolve at once, as he did, he <lb/>
was all
right ; and if he intended to dis<lb break="no"/>cuss it, and appeal to the people at
the <lb/>
General
Election, then he was all
right,<lb break="no"/>but which he
intended no one but himself
<lb/>
knew, but certainly he was not
very frank <lb/>
and candid. The advocates of Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation had in this Province a
decided ad<lb break="no"/>vantage.
They had some of the ablest
<lb/>
men as lecturers, and certainly
they im<lb break="no"/>proved
the time. They had the influence <lb/>
of
the Government, which is certainly <lb/>
very
great. They had, I think, four-fifths <lb/>
of the entire Press of the Province.
They <lb/>
had that disposition
in man, a desire to <lb/>
change, which is very common,
and a great <lb/>
many believe their condition is a hard
<lb/>
one, and any change would be for the bet<lb break="no"/>ter, and they made the best use of all <lb/>
theses advantages ; but the
people
had some <lb/>
common sense and some
judgment, and <lb/>
rejected a scheme which would certainly, <lb/>
in my opinion, if adopted, have <lb/>
been destructive to our best interests. <lb/>
One very singular feature in this scheme <lb/>
was, that every colony had got
the <lb/>
best of the bargain. Mr. Tilley had <lb/>
in finance outwitted all the
rest. <lb/>
In Upper Canada the politicians had made <lb/>
so good a bargain, that they could afford <lb/>
to build several Intercolonial Railroads <lb/>
and then make in the transaction. Nova <lb/>
Scotia and Newfouudland, all had made a <lb/>
wonderful good trade ; how all
could <lb/>
have got the best of the arrangement and <lb/>
no party the worst, I cannot understand. <lb/>
It might be considered smart to
get the <lb/>
best of the bargain, but if it
were done <lb/>
knowingly, it could badly be considered
<lb/>
honest, and if discovered, not
calculated <lb/>
to add much to the harmony of the Union. <lb/>
One great argument, and one
which was <lb/>
used to good effect, was the Railroad.
<lb/>
Now, I am free to admit, that the chances <lb/>
were that the road would have been
built <lb/>
in Confederation ; but not, I
think, quite <lb/>
so soon as some people imagined. It de<lb break="no"/>pended entirely upon what a majority of
<lb/>
the Federal Parliament concluded after
<lb/>
the Constitution was complete ; it de<lb break="no"/>pended upon what a majority of that Par<lb break="no"/>liament might think necessary. They <lb/>
might conclude that the finances were not <lb/>
just at that time in a state to
warrant the <lb/>
undertaking. They in Canada
played <lb/>
false, so Mr. Tilley said, and they might <lb/>
do so again ; but I think they would have <lb/>
built it, and I think further that
it would <lb/>
not have paid either them or us after
it <lb/>
was built. The immense traffic and the <lb/>
terrible increase of manufactories were <lb/>
all or nearly so in the imagination
of the <lb/>
Confederates. This Confederate Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment was to be conducted by men of the
<lb/>
first talent from all the Colonies. Our <lb/>
fifteen representatives would have little
<lb/>
influence there, even if they were
all uni<lb break="no"/>ted ; these fifteen gentlemen could do a <lb/>
great deal more for New Brunswick in <lb/>
our own Parliament, and would be quite
<lb/>
as well able to consider these general <lb/>
matters here as there. I have never known<lb/>
this Assembly to decline the considera<lb break="no"/>tion of any question on account of its<lb/>
magnitude, particularly the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment ; and we have no right to suppose<lb/>
that our fifteen members would be united<lb/>
in their politics, they would represent<lb/>
both political parties. Human nature<lb/>
would not be changed, and party feelings<lb/>
would not be removed by the new order<lb/>
of things. The hon. member for Resti<lb break="no"/>gouche says parties would be so evenly<lb/>
divided that our men by going to either<lb/>
            
            <cb/>
     
side could effect their object, that
would <lb/>
not be a very moral way to get what we <lb/>
thought belonged to us, to ask
our re<lb break="no"/>presentatives to join any party, right or <lb/>
wrong. That hon. member said the Con<lb break="no"/>ference had tried to copy after
both the <lb/>
Constitution of Britain and the United <lb/>
States. They have succeeded in getting <lb/>
a good deal of what is not
perfect in <lb/>
both, and not a great deal of the good <lb/>
qualities of either. The truth is, Mr. <lb/>
Chairman, that an long as we
remain Co<lb break="no"/>lonies of England, we do not
want any <lb/>
such expensive establishment : we
want <lb/>
no such power between the Colonial Le<lb break="no"/>gislatures and the Crown. If we are to <lb/>
become separate, then we may copy
after <lb/>
the Federal Union, and perhaps
improve <lb/>
some upon their system ; but until we are <lb/>
seperate, we do not want this fifth wheel
to <lb/>
our coach. I think there is not a desire <lb/>
in this Province to become independent
<lb/>
of England. There may be such desire <lb/>
in Canada West. It has been urged <lb/>
that this arrangement was to bind us <lb/>
more closely to the Mother Country. I <lb/>
think it would have an entirely opposite <lb/>
effect. Union they say is strength. They <lb/>
have had for twenty-five years a union of <lb/>
Upper and Lower Canada. They have <lb/>
had great difficulties, and at last come <lb/>
almost to a stand still. And
this Union <lb/>
of the Colonies was the only remedy the <lb/>
politicians of Canada could think
of, and <lb/>
it was their troubles, and not ours, that <lb/>
suggested it. In the appointment of the <lb/>
Delegates they commenced a Coalition. <lb/>
The late Government of New Brunswick  <lb/>
never used to think any advice or assis<lb break="no"/>tance necessary to manage the affairs of <lb/>
the country ; in fact the thought the op<lb break="no"/>position had mismanaged it, but now there <lb/>
was a matter to be carried out that would <lb/>
suit all the political leaders. The unani<lb break="no"/>mity of the delegates, and the different <lb/>
Governments was certainly most remarka<lb break="no"/>ble, and only by accident did we disco<lb break="no"/>ver that any difference of opinion existed : <lb/>
but we have heard that in the Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion of the Federal Council there was a <lb/>
difference, and that part of
the Scheme <lb/>
was carried by the casting vote of the <lb/>
Chairman, who was Mr. Tilley.
I think <lb/>
that body should at first at least
have <lb/>
been elected, so that the people in the first<lb/>
instance could have chosen that branch <lb/>
of the Legislature, a branch powerful <lb/>
enough if they chose, to stop all legisla<lb break="no"/>tion. Canada did some seven years ago <lb/>
adopt the elective principle for their Le<lb break="no"/>gislative Council, and the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment evidently thinks it should be so in <lb/>
this Scheme, and suggests it. The Co<lb break="no"/>lonial minister objects to two most im<lb break="no"/>portant principles in this
Scheme, said <lb/>
to be so perfect, and hints strongly that <lb/>
there are a goodly number of smaller de<lb break="no"/>fects ; but here it was to be taken just as<lb/>
it was, being humanly speaking, perfect,<lb/>
—and in the Federal Executive Council <lb/>
it would be exceedingly difficult to so <lb/>
compose it with the local and
sectional <lb/>
differences as to make it work harmoni<lb break="no"/>ously, and in fact I think it would not <lb/>
have worked at all, and am pleased thus
<lb/>
far that the people have not decided to let <lb/>
them try it. The Scheme does not pro<lb break="no"/>vide how the local Governments are to be <lb/>
constituted. They are to have a Lieute<lb break="no"/>nant Governor,,who shall be appointed <lb/>
by the Governor General ; the
local Go<lb break="no"/>vernment and Legislature of each Pro<lb break="no"/>vînce shall be constructed in such
man<lb break="no"/>ner as the existing Legislature
of each <lb/>
Province shall provide, so each can have <lb/>
about what they like, no uniformity is <lb/>
provided for all the Colonies.
This great  <lb/>
Confederation was to amalgate the whole ; <lb/>
           
            <pb n="139" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-06-05_Page_139.jpg"/>

<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">139</fw>
     
 all races
and creeds were to be united. <lb/>
Certain exceptions as to education are <lb/>
provided for in Canada, the ministers <lb/>
there are provided for in the arrangement. <lb/>
Why not provide for Catholic or Protes<lb break="no"/>tant ministers in other Colonies. if neces<lb break="no"/>sary in Canada ? Why not in New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, Nova Scotia, and all the other
Provin<lb break="no"/>ces ? The Delegates look with
favor upon <lb/>
this scheme ; but so far as the
people have <lb/>
had a chance to speak out it has been con<lb break="no"/>demned. The British Government, I re<lb break="no"/>gret to say, favors it, and as much as I <lb/>
regard our connection with the
Mother <lb/>
Country and prize the relation, I do not <lb/>
choose that they shall decide
our desti<lb break="no"/>nies in this matter ; and it is because that <lb/>
I think matters have been wrongly repre<lb break="no"/>sented, that I think it important a Dele<lb break="no"/>gation should go
home. There is no rea<lb break="no"/>son why this Union should be entered into, <lb/>
but there are strong reasons why it should <lb/>
not ; the time may come when a Federal <lb/>
Union will be necessary. The hon.
<lb/>
member for Carleton says, if we had this <lb/>
and if we had that we should be a won<lb break="no"/>derful people. If that gentleman's aunt<lb/>
had been a man, she would have been his<lb/>
uncle. The Hon. President of the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil, in reply to some hon. member, said he<lb/>
could not understand him, unless upon<lb/>
the principle that the more a man owed<lb/>
the less it required to pay his debts.<lb/>
That is really the case when men are not<lb/>
satisfied with living and doing business<lb/>
within their means ; they usually become<lb/>
involved in difficulties, and, in many cases,<lb/>
pay twenty shillings with five. There are<lb/>
certain principles which govern the<lb/>
growth of nations as well as individuals,<lb/>
which cannot be changed without great<lb/>
injury. We had better not try to put on<lb/>
false appearances, or pretend to be what<lb/>
we are not. If my hon. friend from<lb/>
Carleton was to sit for his photograph<lb/>
and try to look like the Duke of Wel<lb break="no"/>lington—for the Duke was every inch a<lb/>
soldier—he would try in vain to look like<lb/>
him ; he also had a frank and honest<lb/>
countenance, and in that the failure would<lb/>
be as great. I would not have spoken on<lb/>
these resolutions at all, but the time would<lb/>
have been occupied by others. Really,<lb/>
no good can arise on this discussion. The<lb/>
Confederates have failed before the peo<lb break="no"/>ple to make out a case, and I think have<lb/>
as signally failed here.<lb/>
            </p>
    
            <p>On motion, the Committee then divided <lb/>
on the Resolutions : Yeas, 27 ; Nays, 9.
<lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">REPORT OF THE SUPERINTENDENT OF THE<lb/>
EUROPEAN AND NORTH AMERICAN RAIL<lb break="no"/>WAY ON THE RUNNING OF TRAINS, LAID<lb/>
BEFORE THE HOUSE BY THE HON. MR.<lb/>
SMITH ON THE 2ND DAY OF JUNE.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p> The
Steamer arrives at Point DuChene
<lb/>
from the Island on Tuesday about 9 A. <lb/>
M. The train leaves Point DuChene for <lb/>
St. John 10 45 A. M. The steamer <lb/>
leaves for the North Shore at 10 A. M. <lb/>
Passengers going by the steamer
now <lb/>
leaver St. John on Monday morning
<lb/>
at 8 30 and remain at <hi rendition="simple:italic">Shediac</hi>
all night. <lb/>
If the Steamer would wait until 11 A. M., <lb/>
passengers could stay in St. John
until <lb/>
5 15 P. M. on Monday, stay at <hi rendition="simple:italic">Sussex</hi> all <lb/>
night, arriving at Point DuChene at 10 40
<lb/>
on Tuesday morning, and take the steam<lb break="no"/>er at once. That this connection is not
<lb/>
better is therefore the fault of the Steam<lb break="no"/>er, not of the Railway.</p>
            <p>The Steamer arrives at Point DuChene<lb/>
on her return from the North Shore on<lb/>
Wednesday about 2 P. M., in fine weath<lb break="no"/>er, but 3 P. M. would probably be the<lb/>
average time of arrival. No <hi rendition="simple:italic">through</hi><lb/>
train could be detained at Point DuChene<lb/>
  
            <cb/>
         
after 2 P. M,, as it would make the arri<lb break="no"/>val in St. John too late to suit the local
<lb/>
traffic. The freight train for Sussex <lb/>
leaves Shediac at 3 P. M., and at any <lb/>
time that there were twenty passengers<lb/>
they could be expressed Sussex
to  <lb/>
St. John in time for the American Boat <lb/>
of Thursday morning. Passengers from <lb/>
the Island having come down on Tues<lb break="no"/>day or Wednesday by the express train<lb/>
are in plenty of time for Thursday's<lb/>
Boat.</p>

            <p>The Steamer leaves Point DuChene<lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">for</hi> the Island at 3 P. M. on Wednesday<lb/>
and Saturday, the express train from St.<lb/>
John reaching Point DuChene at 2 30 P.<lb/>
M. The Steamer arrives at Point Du<lb break="no"/>Chene <hi rendition="simple:italic">from</hi> the Island on Friday
even<lb break="no"/>ing about 6 o'clock. Passengers take <lb/>
the train on Saturday
morning for St.<lb/>
John in time for the American
Boat of<lb/>
Monday morning.<lb/>

            </p>


            <p>In consequence of the train leaving <lb/>
Shediac at 11 o'clock, passengers from <lb/>
Chatham and Richibucto, from Amherst, <lb/>
Sackville and Dorchester, from Hills- <lb break="yes"/>
borough and Harvey can reach the<lb/>
down express
train without travel<lb break="no"/>ling at night, as they would have to do<lb/>
if the train left at eight. Passengers by<lb/>
the express train arrive in St. John at 4<lb/>
45 P. M., in time to take the night boat<lb/>
to Fredericton if they wish.</p>
            <p>The excursion trains, three times a<lb/>
week, will, in all probability, accommo<lb break="no"/>date what is called the " pleasure travel"<lb/>
out of St. John. These trains are run at<lb/>
very little expense as no extra hands are<lb/>
necessary.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Next,
as to the cattle, &amp;c.,
remaining<lb/>
all night at Sussex. They are in the cars<lb/>
only 17 hours from Moncton, a mnch<lb/>
shorter time than cattle on some of the <lb/>
long roads in the States are confined. <lb/>
The cattle cars are well ventilated, and<lb/>
much more comfortable than the ordin<lb break="no"/>ary barns in which cattle are kept. If<lb/>
the cattle are <hi rendition="simple:italic">crowded</hi> into the cars they<lb/>
may suffer, but this would be equally the<lb/>
case with any arrangement, and is the<lb/>
fault of the owners themselves. The<lb/>
sheep, calves, and pigs are carried in<lb/>
cars, the sides of which are formed of<lb/>
iron or wooden gratings, so that they are<lb/>
quite cool. They are not in nearly so<lb/>
bad a position as cattle, sheep, &amp;c.,<lb/>
brought across the bay in schooners.<lb/>
Moncton is the most distant station from<lb/>
which cattle are brought. They are put<lb/>
on board say at 4 30 P. M. and arrive in<lb/>
St. John at 9 30 the next morning, so<lb/>
that they are carried during the coolest<lb/>
parts of the day. For the shorter dis<lb break="no"/>tances the arrangement is of course less<lb/>
objectionable.</p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:right">JUNE 5th.</head>

            <p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName> the House<lb/>
went into Committee on the papers re<lb break="no"/>lating to the claim of Robert Custance,<lb/>
and others, against the St. Andrews and<lb/>
Quebec Railway Company.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName> explained the case and<lb/>
offered the following resolution :</p>
            <p>Resolved that an humble address be<lb/>
presented to His Excellency the Lieu<lb break="no"/>tenant Governor, praying that His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency will be pleased to cause an<lb/>
investigation to be had, during the re<lb break="no"/>cess of the Legislature, into the Petition<lb/>
of Robert Custance, and others, who al<lb break="no"/>lege to have claims against the St. An<lb break="no"/>drews and Quebec Railway Company,<lb/>
and will cause the result of such inves<lb break="no"/>tigation to be laid before this House at<lb/>
its next sittings ; or that such action be<lb/>
taken by His Excellency and Council, <lb/>
          
            <cb/>

after such investigation, as will preserve<lb/>
the
just rights of the claimants.</p>
            <p>The following Petition and statement<lb/>
of claims against the Company were put<lb/>
in :</p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>(Copy.)</p>
            <p>To His Excellency the Honorable AR<lb break="no"/>THUR HAMILTON GORDAN, C. M. G.,<lb/>
Lieut. Governor, and Commander-in-<lb break="yes"/>
Chief of the Province of New Bruns<lb break="no"/>swick, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Petition of the undersigned in<lb break="no"/>habitants of the Parish of Richmond, in<lb/>
the County of Carleton,</p>

            <p>MOST HUMBLY SHEWETH—</p>

            <p>That your petitioners have done work<lb/>
and labor, and furnished and provided<lb/>
materials, &amp;c,, for the use of the St.<lb/>
Andrews and Quebec Railway and Land<lb/>
Company, and at the request of their duly<lb/>
authorized agents.</p>
            <p>That there are large amounts due and<lb/>
owing the undersigned from said Com<lb break="no"/>pany, which your petitioners are much<lb/>
in need of, and have no way of obtaining<lb/>
the same.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Your petitioners are aware that your <lb/>
Excellency protected the labourers that <lb/>
worked on the railroad belonging to said
<lb/>
Company during the part of the
year A.
<lb/>
D., 1862. That your Petitioners did not
<lb/>
wish to make any trouble at that time <lb/>
to embarrass the parties concerned in <lb/>
said Road, and therefore did not make  <lb/>
their claim against the Company, think<lb break="no"/>ing and hoping that the Company would <lb/>
fairly and honorably meet their engage<lb break="no"/>ments and promises with your petition<lb break="no"/>ers.<lb/>
            </p>




            <p> That the Manager of the said Railway<lb/>
gave acceptances to many of your peti<lb break="no"/>tioners, and supposed that he would pay <lb/>
them, and therefore did not take
legal <lb/>
proceedings against said Company. <lb/>
That since said acceptances
have been <lb/>
made the Manager has refused to pay <lb/>
the demand of your petitioners, and have <lb/>
now no way of obtaining the same. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Your petitioners are informed, and <lb/>
believe, that the provisions of
the Act of <lb/>
Assembly giving time to complete
the <lb/>
said Railroad to Woodstock has expired <lb/>
and that they have now no legal right<lb/>
to any further grant of land. or to be<lb/>
paid any money secured by any Facility <lb/>
Bill respecting or relating to
the said <lb/>
Railway.</p>
            <p>Your petitioners, therefore, pray that<lb/>
no payment be made, or allowed to be<lb/>
paid, by the Province to said Company,<lb/>
nor any grant of land be issued, nor any<lb/>
further privileges be given to said Com<lb break="no"/>pany until an investigation of your peti<lb break="no"/>tioners' claims be made, and payments<lb/>
made them for the amounts still due and<lb/>
unpaid to them.</p>
            <p>That the Schedule hereunto annexed<lb/>
is a true and proper schedule of the<lb/>
amounts due your petitioners.</p>
            <p>And, as in duty bound,</p>
            <p>Will ever pray,</p>
            <p>(Signed.)</p>
            <p>Alex Kirkpatrick, Samuel Hemphill,<lb/>
Geo. DeBeck, Jas. Dugan,<lb/>
Robt. M. Bailey, Isaac Dougherty,<lb/>
Mr. Benj. Dougherty, Mrs. Fleming,<lb/>
Joesph Harvey, Mr. Edward Cain,<lb/>
Wm. Crawford, David Alexander,<lb/>
Chas. Crawford, St. T . Plummer,<lb/>
Oliver Hemphill, John Breen,<lb/>
Robert Carmont.</p></quote>

            <p>The following schedule of the amounts<lb/>
due the parties who signed the petition<lb/>
hereunto annexed, and the amounts due.<lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
