<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-03-16"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-03-16">16 March 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1866</title>.
                    
 

          <date when="1866"/>.
          

          <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="24" to="29"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
   <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_024.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_025.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_026.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_027.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_028.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_029.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-05-01">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-05-01">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
 <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_024">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_024.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_025">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_025.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_026">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_026.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_027">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_027.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_028">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_028.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_029">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_029.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">

<pb n="24" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_024.jpg"/>
    <fw type="num">24</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  
<p rendition="simple:right">FRIDAY, MARCH 16.</p>


<p>
          On motion of <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">COL. BOYD</persName>, the House<lb/>
          went into Committee to take into consi<lb break="no"/>deration. A Bill to incorporate the St.<lb/>
        Andrew's Friendly Society.</p>

        <p>COL. BOYD in explaining the object<lb/>
          of the Bill, said, that there was another<lb/>
          Society in St.Andrews called the St.<lb/>
          Andrew's Benefit Society, which Society<lb/>
          had lost a considerable amount of<lb/>
          money which they had invested in Char<lb break="no"/>lotte County Bank Stock. That Society<lb/>
          was still in existence, and this Society<lb/>
          is formed for the same object—viz: a<lb/>
          Society to render mutual assistance to<lb/>
          its members, and to enable them to in<lb break="no"/>vest their money in Provincial Deben<lb break="no"/>tures.</p>


        <p><persName ref="pers:GILL1">HON. MR. GILMOR</persName> laid on the table<lb/>
        a Report on Public Accounts.</p>

<div type="section">
        <head rendition="simple:centre">A BILL TO ABOLISH PROPERTY QUALIFICA<lb break="no"/>TION OF MEMBERS OF THE HOUSE OF<lb/>
        ASSEMBLY.</head>


        <p><persName ref="pers:COST1">MR. COSTIGAN</persName> moved the House<lb/>
          into Committee on the above Bill and<lb/>
          said, he always had doubts about the<lb/>
          propriety of that portion of the law pro<lb break="no"/>viding for a property qualification of<lb/>
          members serving in the Assembly. He<lb/>
          had prepared a Bill somewhat different<lb/>
          from this, but, upon speaking to several<lb/>
          members of the House, he found there<lb/>
          was a general willingness that the pro<lb break="no"/>perty qualification should be done away<lb/>
          with entirely. The law requires that<lb/>
          the candidate, before coming before the<lb/>
          constituency, shall possess an estate<lb/>
          valued at £300 over and above his lia<lb break="no"/>bilities. The spirit of the law is, that<lb/>
          no person can represent a constituency<lb/>
          in this Assembly unless he is possessed<lb/>
          of an estate of £300. Suppose a mem<lb break="no"/>ber of this House has a ship at sea, and<lb/>
          by some accident the ship was lost, and<lb/>
          the loss of that ship placed him in a<lb/>
          position that enabled his creditors to<lb/>
          come down upon him, so that he would<lb/>
          not be possessed of £300 of real estate;<lb/>
          to carry out the spirit of the law, he<lb/>
          should resign his seat in the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture, because the law says no man shall<lb/>
          be qualified to represent any constitu<lb break="no"/>ency uless possessed of that sum. In<lb/>
          the debates which took place on this<lb/>
          question in the Parliament of England,<lb/>
          some of the most able men on the other<lb/>
          side of the Atlantic, took strong grounds<lb/>
          in favor of doing away with this pro<lb break="no"/>perty qualification. He would read the<lb/>
          arguments put forth by one of them<lb/>
          which will corroborate the arguments<lb/>
          he had made use of. He then read<lb/>
          from Lord John Russell's speech on<lb/>
        this question.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:BOYD1">COL. BOYD</persName> said, the property quali<lb break="no"/>fication was a very small one, and any<lb/>
          person could not expect to represent<lb/>
          the people of this country without ha<lb break="no"/>ving some interest in the country. He<lb/>
          considered the property qualification as<lb/>
          entirely too low now, and he would<lb/>
        therefore oppose the Bill.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:CUDL1">HON. MR. CUDLIP</persName> said, he was in<lb break="no"/>clined to support the principle of the Bill,<lb/>
          but he should not support the Bill with<lb break="no"/>out it went further. It should take from<lb/>
          the members all the privileges they have,<lb/>
          as members all the privileges they have,<lb/>
          as members, over other men. They<lb/>
          should be liable to be arrested for debt,<lb/>
          except during the meeting of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, and for twenty days before and<lb/>
          twenty days after it has met. The law<lb/>
          of property qualification, which they had,<lb/>
          <cb/>
          was of no service, as it is so often<lb/>
        evaded.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said, it was a matter of<lb/>
          little important whether it passed or<lb/>
          not. They ought to study not to teach<lb/>
          the people to violate the laws, or not to<lb/>
          teach them they are something that could<lb/>
          be violated. This law is scarcely ever<lb/>
          regarded at all. If you go back to the<lb/>
          history of the formation of the British<lb/>
          Parliament, you will find the reason why<lb/>
          it was required. At that time, when the<lb/>
          King of England called a Parliament, he<lb/>
          found it very difficult to get the members<lb/>
          to attend, and he had to compel the at<lb break="no"/>tendance of persons in distant districts,<lb/>
          for they did not like to come to London,<lb/>
          and spend their time, besides being to a<lb/>
          considerable expense, which they could<lb/>
          not afford. They did not have as much<lb/>
          relish for Parliamentary life as the people<lb/>
          of the present day; and, as they received<lb/>
          no pay for their services, it was necessary<lb/>
          they should have a certain income of their<lb/>
          own, to enable them to attend. This is<lb/>
          the reason a law was made requiring a<lb/>
          property qualification, but it is now abo<lb break="no"/>lished, and it is absured that we should<lb/>
          require a property qualification when it is<lb/>
          not required in England. The law is so<lb/>
          easily evaded that it is of no effect, and<lb/>
          only serves to bring the law into con<lb break="no"/>tempt.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:THOM1">DR. THOMPSON</persName> thought they should<lb/>
          get the opinion of their constituents upon<lb/>
          a Bill of that kind. He did not think it<lb/>
          right to pass a law to lower the property<lb/>
          qualification of the voters, or the person<lb/>
          voted for. There were very few candi<lb break="no"/>dates for a seat in that House who were<lb/>
          not possessed of £300 worth of property.<lb/>
          As to the qualification of voters, it gives<lb/>
          poor men a kind of stimulus, and induces<lb/>
          them to strive to acquire property for the<lb/>
          purpose of enabling them to vote, thus<lb/>
          acquiring a habit of industry which ena<lb break="no"/>bles them in time to become well off.<lb/>
          He thought the Bill had better stand over<lb/>
          until they had a revision of the election<lb/>
          law, for he would like to see a good elec<lb break="no"/>tion law made, which would commend<lb/>
          itself to the views of all; for these reasons<lb/>
          he thought they had better report pro<lb break="no"/>gress.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">MR. NEEDHAM</persName> said, that a law rela<lb break="no"/>ting to elections had been introduced, and<lb/>
          another for the registration of votes.<lb/>
          They had better let them all go together,<lb/>
        and they might be incorporated in one.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:COST1">MR. COSTIGAN</persName> remarked that the<lb/>
          more they took off restrictions from the<lb/>
          candidate, the more they increased the<lb/>
          privileges of the elector, because they<lb/>
          gave them a larger field from which to<lb/>
        select their representatives.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">MR. NEEDHAM</persName> had no doubt but a<lb/>
          great deal could be said on both sides;<lb/>
          but he thought the fair, honest, legitimate<lb/>
          principle was this: the qualification of a<lb/>
          member of the House should be the same<lb/>
          as that of the elector. The idea of pro<lb break="no"/>perty qualification ought to have been<lb/>
          buried long ago. When the election law<lb/>
          was brought forward by the former Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment he went for universal suffrage<lb/>
          will be adopted. That is the principle of<lb/>
          the sound constitutional lawyer. Black<lb break="no"/>stone, who speaks, though he is dead.<lb/>
        <cb/>
          When he had heard that Nova Scotia had<lb/>
          passed that law and then went back, it<lb/>
          reminded him of "the dog that went to his<lb/>
          vomit, and the sow to her wallowing in<lb/>
        the mire."</p>
        <p>Progress was reported upon this Bill.</p>
</div>

<div type="section">
        <head rendition="simple:centre">QUESTION CONCERNING VOLUNTEERS.</head>
        <p><persName ref="pers:DESB2">MR. L. P. W. DESBRISAY</persName> asked the<lb/>
          Government whether several companies<lb/>
          of volunteers had not been called out. If<lb/>
          so , to what part have they been called,<lb/>
        and to what extent.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName> doubted the pro<lb break="no"/>priety of making public everything done<lb/>
          in reference to the defence of the country.<lb/>
          He could only assure this House that the<lb/>
          most active and energetic steps are being<lb/>
          taken for the defence of the country.<lb/>
          The military authorities are vigilant, and<lb/>
          the volunteers are being organized and<lb/>
        drilled in different places.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">MR. LINDSAY</persName> did not think it would<lb/>
          do any harm to let the people know<lb/>
          whether there will be a force sent to the<lb/>
          frontier to prevent an invasion of our<lb/>
          borders. It had been stated that a large<lb/>
          number of arms had been sent to Wood<lb break="no"/>stock. He found that it was not the case.<lb/>
          A company had been formed there, one<lb/>
          hundred strong, and they had never re<lb break="no"/>ceived any arms.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName> replied that there<lb/>
          were 500 rifles in the County of Carleton,<lb/>
          in the hands of men able to use them. He<lb/>
          would further inform him that so far as<lb/>
          information has been received from<lb/>
          abroad from those persons best able to<lb/>
          form an opinion on the subject, that<lb/>
          Woodstock is not in danger at all, for it<lb/>
          is not the intention of any parties to make<lb/>
        a raid upon it.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">MR. LINDSAY</persName> wished information in<lb/>
          regard to a company of Home Guards,<lb/>
          which had been organized two months<lb/>
          ago at Woodstock, and of which he had<lb/>
          the honor of being elected captain, but<lb/>
        which had never received a gun.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName> asked whether<lb/>
          there had not been some local difficulty<lb/>
        regarding them.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">MR. LINDSAY</persName> was not aware of any.<lb/>
          They had requested to have arms, but<lb/>
          had never received a reply whether they<lb/>
        could have them or not.</p>
        <p><persName ref="pers:HILL1">MR. HILL</persName> could scarcely understand<lb/>
          why there should be so much alarm felt<lb/>
          in the County of Carleton, as the nearest<lb/>
          point from which it could be reached was<lb/>
          from Bangor, which was about one hun<lb break="no"/>dred mile from Houlton Village, which<lb/>
          contained about one thousand inhabitants,<lb/>
          and where it was not at all probable that<lb/>
          any Fenian organization existed, it being<lb/>
          so far from the centre. In Bangor he be<lb break="no"/>lieved the organization did exist, but to<lb/>
          reach Houlton they would have to travel<lb/>
          one hundred miles, and we would receive<lb/>
          notice of it from the American authori<lb break="no"/>ties. They would not invade us from that<lb/>
          quarter when they could reach Calais so<lb/>
          much easier, and be met by others from<lb/>
          Boston and New York; but for all this,<lb/>
          they did not feel any great alarm there.<lb/>
          They try to embarrass the Government<lb/>
          by questions. He did not think informa<lb break="no"/>tion of this kind should be put in the<lb/>
          newspapers, for it would not be wise poli<lb break="no"/>cy to tell the enemy just what we intended<lb/>
          to do. He did not think the Government<lb/>
          knew just what they were going to do.<lb/>
          (Laughter.) He would venture to say<lb/>
          if the Government expended $200,000 for<lb/>
          the defence of the country, as certain<lb/>
        gentlemen seem desire is they should do,<lb/>

            <pb n="25" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_025.jpg"/>

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  <fw type="num">25</fw>
         


     after the danger had passed away, the 
     <lb/>gentlemen would turn round and abuse<lb/>the Government upon the other tack, and<lb/>say the money was not wisely expended.<lb/>He believed the Government would do all<lb/>in their power to prevent invasion. He<lb/>would rest satisfied in the ability of the<lb/>Government and Commander-in-Chief to<lb/>provide for the defence of the Province.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Mr. McClelan</persName> thought the hon.<lb/>member, when he accuses members of the<lb/>House of asking questions to embarrass <lb/>the Government, should remember that it<lb/>was announced by the leader of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment that this was a time of emergen<lb break="no"/>cy ; that a crisis had arrived in which the<lb/>Government should not be engaged in<lb/>party politics ; therefore, the people have<lb/>a right to be alarmed, and to know what<lb/>means are to be taken for their defence.<lb/>It is not right for the Government to<lb/>withhold that information, for there is no<lb/>reason why they should not tell us how<lb/>many volunteers they have attached to<lb/>the service, and what the service is to be.<lb/>He did not expect them to state where<lb/>they were going to concentrate those vol<lb break="no"/>unteers ; that would be no object with the<lb/>people of the country, if assured that a<lb/>certain amount of forces are available, and<lb/>certain means and precautions are being<lb/>taken to provide against invasion.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName> - Should fancy that   
     <lb/>the Attorney General did not feel much<lb/>anxiety as to what has been done for the<lb/>defence of the country, as he did not have<lb/>a very large family ; but it was different<lb/>with those who had wives and homesteads<lb/>to look after. If his hon. friend had re<lb break="no"/>ceived such letters from home as he had<lb/>received, he might feel some anxiety.<lb/>The question was not put to embarrass the<lb/>Government, but to know if the volun<lb break="no"/>teers were to be called out ; that would<lb/>satisfy those persons who reside in their<lb/>homesteads, while we are looking after<lb/>the interests of the country. The hon.<lb/>gentlemen who had just spoken was in<lb/>the same position as the Attorney Gener<lb break="no"/>al ; they could put their families on their<lb/>backs and walk off when the Province was<lb/>invaded ; but for those who had families<lb/>it was an important matter. He would<lb/>be sorry to ask any question to embarrass<lb/>the Government, but the people have a <lb/>right to know the number of troops that<lb/>are to be called out, in order that the<lb/>alarm in the country may be allayed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Col. Boyd</persName> said, if there were any<lb/>gentlemen here who ought to be alarmed<lb/>it was his hon. colleague and himself, as<lb/>his hon. colleague lived within a stone's<lb/>throw of the place upon which the enemy<lb/>would make their first attack, while he<lb/>himself only lived three miles away, and<lb/>they were not alarmed ; although they got<lb/>those " bogus telegraphs" they were sa<lb break="no"/>tisfied no body of men would enter this<lb/>country.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:CORA1">Mr. Coram</persName> remarked that it was not<lb/>proper for members of the House to come<lb/>forward every day and call upon the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment to know the state of defence,<lb/>stating that the women at home could not<lb/>sleep nights. It was their duty to keep<lb/>their preparations for defence secret from<lb/>their enemies, and have confidence in the<lb/>Governor, who rules the Province and his<lb/>Executive Council. If there is any dan<lb break="no"/>ger they will give us timely notice, and he<lb/>would depend upon the loyalty of people<lb/>of the Province to fill up any call for<lb/>troops when required. He resided in<lb/>Carleton, and there was not one hundred<lb/>stand of arms in that part of the City,<lb/>while there was every facility for the land<lb break="no"/>
        

            <cb/>
        
ing of an enemy ; but he had no letters<lb/>from any individual saying they were<lb/>alarmed.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
        <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. FISHER</persName> brought in a Bill to au<lb break="no"/>thorize the County of York to assess for<lb/>agricultural purposes.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   The House then proceeded with the<lb/>adjourned debate.<lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     AMENDMENT TO THE FOURTH PARAGRAPH 
     <lb/>                              OF THE ADDRESS. <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. Costigan</persName> - I consider it my <lb/>duty to give my views upon this question,<lb/>and my reasons why I shall vote against<lb/>this Amendment. I do not rise to tell<lb/>this House what side I am on, for that is<lb/>well known by the course I have always<lb/>pursued in this House, and before my<lb/>constituents. When a question comes<lb/>fairly before the House I do not think it<lb/>is to the credit of any representative<lb/>of a consitituency to remain in a posi<lb break="no"/>tion which allows the public to specu<lb break="no"/>late on the course he will take. I <lb/>was rather surprised at a remark made by<lb/>the hon. member from Kent that he con<lb break="no"/>sidered that no anti-Confederates could<lb/>consistently vote for this Government<lb/>unless he was their mere tool.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:DESB2">MR. L. P. W. DESBRISAY</persName> - I rise to<lb/>order. If any man on the floors of this<lb/>House speaks plainly and means what he<lb/>says, I am one, and I ask him not to<lb/>misrepresent or misconstrue what I did<lb/>say, and which I am ready to stand or fall<lb/>by.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. Costigan</persName> - I will not be posi<lb break="no"/>tive as to the exact words. I can only<lb/>assure the hon. member that there is no<lb/>intention to misrepresent him. I wish to<lb/>keep as near as possible to what he did<lb/>say. What he said was : Those who<lb/>supported the Government on this ques<lb break="no"/>tion were prepared to swallow everything<lb/>at their hand.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:DESB1">Mr. DesBrisay</persName> - I did not say so.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. Costigan</persName> - I will tell you what<lb/>I took down in writing : " The hon. gen<lb break="no"/>tleman said no one would support the<lb/>Government but those prepared to swal<lb break="no"/>low everything at their hand."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:DESB1">Mr. DesBrisay</persName> - That hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man had better take down all, and not<lb/>take a fractional part ; he should preserve<lb/>the connection, and not take one part and<lb/>leave another.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. Costigan</persName> - All I can say is -<lb/>that I understood the hon. gentleman to<lb/>make an allusion, at that time, to the sup<lb break="no"/>porters of the Government, which I con<lb break="no"/>sidered uncalled for, and I should be<lb/>pleased to think I was mistaken. In re<lb break="no"/>gard to " sides" on this question, it ap<lb break="no"/>pears to me that queer arguments must<lb/>have been used by the Opposition to con<lb break="no"/>vince those gentlemen who are anti-Con<lb break="no"/>federates, and intend to vote for the<lb/>Amendment, that they are anti-Confeder<lb break="no"/>ates still. To show you an instance of<lb/>what arguments can be brought forward,<lb/>I will relate an anecdote. There were two<lb/>young men standing on the bnk of a<lb/>river engaged in fishing. One of the<lb/>young men proposed that they should<lb/>cross over to the other side of the river; <lb/>the other said they were on the other side<lb/>now. How do you make that appear ?<lb/>Because you are on the other side. It is <lb/>no such thing. But I tell you that you<lb/>are on the other side, and I will stand a<lb/>bet upon it. The bet was taken at once.<lb/>Now, says the young man who proposed<lb/>this bet, how many sides are there to this<lb/>river ? Two, of course. Well, is not <lb/>that one side over there, and is not this<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
         
the other side. (Laughter.)  I suppose<lb/>the same kind of arguments were used to <lb/>convince the anti-Confederates in the op<lb break="no"/>position that they are anti-Confederates<lb/>still. Let us look around and see who<lb/>are anti-Confederates, supposing the<lb/>question of Confederation should come<lb/>up. I hold that the great paramount anti-<lb break="yes"/>Confederate is the hon. member for the<lb/>Count of York (Mr. Fisher) ; constitu<lb break="no"/>tionally speaking, he is pledged beyond<lb/>all other anti-Confederates. I, as an anti-<lb break="yes"/>Confederate, pledged myself to my con<lb break="no"/>stituents to oppose this Quebec Scheme,<lb/>and that pledge extends as long, and no<lb/>longer, than I occupy my seat in the pre<lb break="no"/>sent House of Assembly. Should they<lb/>be dissolved, my pledge will be redeemed.<lb/>The hon. member from York stands<lb/>pledged to oppose the Quebec Scheme or<lb/>any <hi rendition="simple:italic">other</hi> Scheme, as long as this House<lb/>lasts. We are in the same position. He <lb/>could not pledge himself beyond the term<lb/>of his service as a representative for the<lb/>County of York ; therefore, to look at the<lb/>matter fairly and honestly, he stands<lb/>pledged as an anti-Confederate in this<lb/>House more so than any other member.<lb/>It has been said that the return of that<lb/>hon. member was a proof that a change<lb/>of opinion was going on in the<lb/>country in regard to the Quebec<lb/>Scheme. I believe the hon. gentleman<lb/>was true to the Scheme then, and I be<lb break="no"/>lieve he is true to it today. I believe<lb/>those pledges were given to secure the<lb/>votes of the anti-Confederates of York.<lb/>He saw that if he came out to fight the<lb/>battle on the question of Confederation,<lb/>he would not have been returned. There<lb/>was no reason why anti-Confederates<lb/>should not vote for him when he had<lb/>pledged himself to oppose the Quebec<lb/>Scheme. This fact should prevent him<lb/>from boasting of being returned as an anti-<lb break="yes"/>Confederate, and claiming that return as<lb/>a victory over anti-Confederates. It was<lb/>unfair to claim that as a victory, and send<lb/>it abroad through the newspapers that the<lb/>people had changed their minds in re<lb break="no"/>gard to the Scheme. When the Scheme<lb/>was first brought before the people, the<lb/>press advocated it, and there were agents<lb/>travelling through the country - men<lb/>brought from Canada and paid by politi<lb break="no"/>cians in this country, to go among the<lb/>French. (Hear, hear.) They went from <lb/>house to house, asking, how much cedar<lb/>can you furnish to make Railway sleep<lb break="no"/>ers ? What facilities have you for getting<lb/>limestone ? What is the rate of wages ?<lb/>Ignorant people began to look around and<lb/>enquire what all this meant. They told<lb/>them that Confederation was going to be<lb/>carried, and the Canadian Government<lb/>had sent them down to get the material to<lb/>build your Railways at once. Was not<lb/>that a strong influence brought against us?<lb/>I wonder they were not carried away by<lb/>these influences and inducements that<lb/>were held out to them. How is it today ?<lb/>We find the same thing going on, and we<lb/>are not in a position to go through the<lb/>country and counteract its effects. They<lb/>boast of a change of feeling in the country.<lb/>It may be true that there are changes.<lb/>People change from one side to the other.<lb/>Some change in favor of the scheme and<lb/>some against it. I believe if the question<lb/>of the Quebec Scheme was to be put be<lb break="no"/>fore the people of this country today,<lb/>and they were required to vote for or<lb/>against it, they would find as many votes<lb/>in favor of it as there was at the last<lb/>election. ( <persName ref="pers:ANON1">A member</persName>, - They had bet<lb break="no"/>ter try it.") I have no more reason to be<lb/>
          

            <pb n="26" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_026.jpg"/>
     

     <fw type="num">26</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  


     alarmed at a dissolution than any other               
     <lb/>member of the House. It might be an<lb break="no"/>noying, for there were very few willing to <lb/>have an election without some good<lb/>cause ; but I can assure you I do not feel<lb/>at all in fear of a dissolution in giving my<lb/>vote. I believe that as an anti-Confeder<lb break="no"/>ate it is my duty to sustain the present<lb/>Government, not under any circumstances,<lb/>but under <hi rendition="simple:italic">present</hi> circumstances. Before<lb/>the election in York, there were several<lb/>dispatches published in some of the pa<lb break="no"/>pers about " Fenian raids, " and the ex<lb break="no"/>citement in the country. This had its<lb/>effect on the election. After the election<lb/>was over, one of these papers, after giv<lb break="no"/>ing the result of the election, puts in a <lb/>paragraph as a postscript : " Fenian ru<lb break="no"/>mors all contradicted. " It turns round <lb/>and laughs at the people of York after it<lb/>had gained its own ends. I believe that<lb/>if a majority of this House vote against<lb/>the present Government and defeat them,<lb/>it would be the greatest step towards<lb/>carrying the Quebec Scheme which could<lb/>be given. A great deal has been said<lb/>with regard to the delay of the meeting<lb/>of the House. Why do not the hon.<lb/>gentlemen give us some information<lb/>about the delay in calling the Canadian<lb/>Parliament together ; possibly they could<lb/>throw a good deal of light upon that.<lb/>There have been questions which have<lb/>from time to time come before the coun<lb break="no"/>try, upon which Governments have been<lb/>defeated and Governments formed. But<lb/>there has never been a question before<lb/>the country involving the same amount<lb/>of interest as this. It is not only a <lb/>question that affects our rights for to-day<lb/>but it affects our rights for all time to<lb/>come, and the rights of those who come<lb/>after us. If that scheme is adopted, the<lb/>time will come when it will be looked<lb/>upon with horror, and then they will<lb/>think of those who tried to ward off the<lb/>blow. No Government introducing a<lb/>scheme for the union of the Colonies un<lb break="no"/>der the system of representation by popu<lb break="no"/>lation would advance the interests of this<lb/>country. There could be improvements<lb/>made in that scheme, if a scheme was ab<lb break="no"/>solutely necessary, but I do not say it is<lb/>necessary. I will throw out these sugges<lb break="no"/>tions, which will have the effect of show<lb break="no"/>ing how inconsistent that scheme is<lb/>regarding representation by population.<lb/>I contend that upon entering into union<lb/>with another country we should secure<lb/>equal rights and privileges, and have<lb/>equal power to maintain them. We can<lb break="no"/>not go into an Assembly with fifteen votes<lb/>against one hundred and forty-seven<lb/>which Canada has, and obtain equal rights <lb/>there. Suppose a union of these Colonies<lb/>was decided upon, and the details of that<lb/>union had to be considered, the first<lb/>steps which should be taken, in order to<lb/>give fair play, would be to blot out all<lb/>lines of distinction between these Colo<lb break="no"/>nies, and bring them together as one<lb/>Province. Then we might be in a posi<lb break="no"/>tion to say to Canada, we will go into<lb/>union, but give us equal representation.<lb/>They contend they have done this in giv<lb break="no"/>ing the Maritime Provinces a fair propor<lb break="no"/>tion in the Legislative Council. But<lb/>have they not left the division lines, and<lb/>taken us as three or four small Colonies,<lb/>each with our representation in the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Council. If we could have equal<lb/>representation in the Legislature at Otta<lb break="no"/>wa, we might be in a position to advocate<lb/>our interests ; but with fifteen members<lb/>it is perfectly absurd. It has been stated<lb/>by several members of the House, and in<lb/>
     
     
            <cb/>
         

     the press of this country, that the people 
     <lb/>have so changed their minds and feelings<lb/>that this Government had not the confi<lb break="no"/>dence of the people of the Province, nor<lb/>of any one County of it. If a dissolution<lb/>took place to-morrow, and the question<lb/>  of Confederation had to be tried over<lb/>again, I am not prepared to say whether<lb/>I should be here. But I do state<lb/>boldly that the County I represent would send<lb/>representatives pledged to sustain the<lb/>present Government.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">MR. NEEDHAM</persName> rose for the purpose<lb/>of explaining the remark made by the<lb/>hon. member for Kent, referred to by the<lb/>last speaker. The hon. member in refer<lb break="no"/>ring to the injustice that had been done<lb/>to the County of Kent, said, that although<lb/>an Anti-Confederate, he felt he would not<lb/>be acting as a man of spirit, if he did not<lb/>pursue the course he was pursuing at<lb/>present.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">AFTERNOON SESSION<lb/>
            </head>

            <p>   <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName> laid before the<lb/>House a message from His Excellency<lb/>the Lieut. Governor, desiring to call the<lb/>attention of the House of Assembly to<lb/>the expediency of furnishing means to<lb/>enable him to provide more effectually<lb/>for the protection of the frontier of the<lb/>Province from possible insult.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>  Also, a memorandum stating that the<lb/>amount required for the ordinary militia<lb/>service, and the sums paid in connection<lb/>with the prevention of deserters from Her<lb/>Majecty's forces, might be estimated at<lb/>about $40,000.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>  <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. FISHER</persName>. The Government would<lb/>find them united as one man on this occa<lb break="no"/>sion. He was disposed to provide the<lb/>Government with all the means they<lb/>wanted, and would hold them responsible<lb/>for the way it was disposed of.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:THOM1">DR. THOMPSON</persName> said, the Attorney<lb/>General should prepare a resolution so it<lb/>could pass the Legislature to-day.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> remarked, they should<lb/>be prompt in this matter, so as to show<lb/>to the people of this country that the<lb/>Legislature was determined to strengthen<lb/>the hands of the Government in providing<lb/>means of defence, as far as they possibly<lb/>could, by an act or vote of this House.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">AMENTMENT TO THE ADDRESS RESUMED.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MCMI1">MR. McMILLAN</persName>. I feel, that in de<lb break="no"/>claring I have no confidence in the gen<lb break="no"/>eral conduct of the Government, that I<lb/>am giving expression to the feelings of<lb/>the country. Before I attempt to meet<lb/>the points in the speech of the Attorney<lb/>General, which is composed chiefly of de<lb break="no"/>clamation and special pleading, let me<lb/>say I disapprove of the course pursued<lb/>by that gentleman in making attacks<lb/>upon members of the House, and persons<lb/>out of the House, who cannot reply to<lb/>them. The most eloquent part of his<lb/>speech was made up of attacks upon the<lb/>hon. mover of the Amendment. He says,<lb/>" Was he influenced by patriotic motives ?<lb/>Look at his motives—is he not looking<lb/>at his own interest ?" and going on in the<lb/>same strain, " I know that gentlemen<lb/>well ; he and I know each other well—I<lb/>would say nothing to hurt his feelings. "<lb/>Do you suppose if he had anything to in<lb break="no"/>jure him politically he would withhold it ?<lb/>This course is beneath the dignity of a<lb/>gentleman assuming the position of the<lb/>leader of the Government. I raise my<lb/>
     

            <cb/>
         

voice to condemn such a course. Then<lb/>he brings another charge against another<lb/>gentleman who is not on the floors of this<lb/>House. He states the late Provincial<lb/>Secretary has been going through the<lb/>country, from schoolhouse to school<lb break="no"/>house, poisoning the minds of the people<lb/>of the country. Is it not a mean thing<lb/>for him to bring those charges against<lb/>a gentleman who is not in a position to<lb/>answer him. He made a charge against<lb/>the hon. mover of the Amendment that<lb/>he had assailed the Government when he<lb/>was not present to meet him, but he<lb/>thinks it is a perfectly fair thing when he<lb/>is guilty of it himself. He said that<lb/>when he had an interview with the Colo<lb break="no"/>nial Secretary, he never forgot the fact<lb/>that he was a man. I ask him now, if it<lb/>was a manly act to attack a man who was<lb/>not in a position to answer him ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName>. If he makes it his<lb/>business to go through the country and<lb/>attack the individuals who compose the<lb/>Government, I am not precluded from<lb/>answering any attacks made upon us.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCMI1">MR. McMILLAN</persName>. Would it not have<lb/>been more manly for him, when he attacks<lb/>this great Quebec Scheme, to have met<lb/>Mr. Tilley when he challenged him to<lb/>meet him and discuss that scheme ? A<lb/>man having the right side of a question,<lb/>even if no great debater, is superior to a<lb/>first class debater who has not the right<lb/>side. If he felt that scheme was going<lb/>to be the ruin and destruction of the<lb/>country, why did he not accept the chal<lb break="no"/>enge ? I put this question to him last<lb/>year, and he denied that he was chal<lb break="no"/>lenged, but I have heard him admit it<lb/>since. It would have been more manly<lb/>to have done so than have attacked a man<lb/>occupying the high position Mr. Tilley<lb/>does in the hearts of the people of this<lb/>country. Haman like, he will never be<lb/>satisfied until he will get Mordecai Tilley<lb/>strung up ; but I hope the fate of old Ha<lb break="no"/>man will be the fate of Haman Smith.<lb/>The first charge made against the Tilley<lb/>Government is, that they were guilty of<lb/>an act of tyranny upon the people of this<lb/>country. Was it an act of tyranny for<lb/>the leading men of British North America<lb/>to meet in conference and consider, week<lb/>after week, a scheme to consolidate the<lb/>British North American Provinces ? Was<lb/>it an act of tyranny for the Government<lb/>of New Brunswick, after considering that<lb/>scheme and feeling it would be a benefit<lb/>to the country to adopt it, to appeal to<lb/>the people of the country, and say to the<lb/>independent electors of New Brunswick,<lb/>here is a scheme, we think, is for your<lb/>advantage, politically, commercially, and<lb/>financially. Instead of forcing it through<lb/>the Legislature, we ask you to judge for<lb/>yourselves, whether you will adopt or re<lb break="no"/>fuse it. I ask you again, is that an act<lb/>of tyranny, to appeal to the people them<lb break="no"/>selves and let them judge, whether to<lb/>adopt it or not ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>If I am any judge of what is foresha<lb break="no"/>dowed in the Speech, I believe the present<lb/>Government is prepared to force upon<lb/>the people of this country a Union Scheme<lb/>without leaving it to the people of the<lb/>country to judge whether they will adopt<lb/>it or not. The Attorney General laughs<lb/>at this. He has condemned the Quebec<lb/>Scheme, the most important principle of<lb/>which is representation by population. I<lb/>had a great difficulty in making up my<lb/>mind upon that point. I felt the point<lb/>was this. Suppose we departed from the<lb/>basis of representation by population,<lb/>where were we going to land at ? I ask<lb/>
      

            <pb n="27" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_027.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw> <fw type="num">27</fw>
  

     you now, whether you will, in this House, 
     <lb/>by delegation, by resolution, by a com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the House, or any any other<lb/>means, agree to force upon the country a<lb/>scheme which holds the principle of re<lb break="no"/>presentation by population without sub<lb break="no"/>mitting the details of their scheme to the<lb/>representatives of the people in this<lb/>House, or to the people themselves ?<lb/>The hon. Attorney General refuses to<lb/>answer this. I will then take it for granted<lb/>it is the intention to do so. The Speeches<lb/>from the Throne, no matter in what way<lb/>they come - by the command of Her<lb/>Majesty, or any other way - are the policy<lb/>of the Government, if I understand the<lb/>principles of Responsible Government.<lb/>The hon. member for Kent asked him<lb/>what side he was on. I ask him not<lb/>whether he is Anti or Confederate, but I<lb/>will give my opinion by a peculiar oper<lb break="no"/>ation : he is just a cross between the two,<lb/>and after a few more crosses I expect to<lb/>see the Attorney General come out the<lb/>pure breed, and a splendid specimen of a<lb/>Confederate. The Government opposed<lb/>the scheme for a union of the Provinces,<lb/>to save the country, and now they have<lb/>got into power, they have adopted a prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of union, not, probably, to save the<lb/>country, but to hold their offices. The<lb/>Attorney General said he would not take<lb/>office unless the emergencies of the coun<lb break="no"/>try required it. I am not aware of any<lb/>emergency having arisen, and I believe<lb/>any other legal gentleman in the House<lb/>would have filled the office as well and<lb/>as satisfactorily as the Hon. Mr. Smith.<lb/>He said they should not be condemned<lb/>without being heard. Give us an oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity to submit our reports ; give us an<lb/>opportunity to defend ourselves ; before<lb/>condemning us, let us be heard. I main<lb break="no"/>tain they have been heard, and they have<lb/>had an opportunity to show what their<lb/>capacities were, both in an executive and<lb/>administrative point of view, and the<lb/>country, I believe, condemns them after a<lb/>trial of twelve months. In 1854 he did<lb/>not think there was anything wrong in<lb/>him condemning the Government without<lb/>being heard ? Had the Government of<lb/>that day any opportunity of showing what<lb/>they had done ? Was it right for them<lb/>to condemn the Government without be<lb break="no"/>ing heard ? Why, then, is it wrong<lb/>now ? It is right to move this amend<lb break="no"/>ment, and it is the proper time, for the<lb/>acts of the Government are foreshadowed<lb/>in the Speech, and by that we are sup<lb break="no"/>posed to know what the acts are to be.<lb/>The next point is that cry got up about<lb/>Fenianism. He tries to make it appear<lb/>that hon. member from Carleton is<lb/>trying to make difficulties in the House<lb/>on religious grounds. No person would<lb/>regret it more than my hon. friend from<lb/>Carleton. I would feel as indignant as<lb/>any hon. member in this House at an at<lb break="no"/>tack being made upon them on religious<lb/>grounds, for the Head Centre, Stephens,<lb/>is a Presbyterian. I have always had a<lb/>sympathy with the Irish people. They<lb/>have grievances to complain of, and if an<lb/>Irishman, I would take every constitu<lb break="no"/>tional means in my power to relieve those<lb/>grievances. But it is not right to get up<lb/>religious feelings in this House, for which<lb/>I will put the responsibility upon the At<lb break="no"/>torney General. He stated that he en<lb break="no"/>dorsed every sentiment in that Minute of<lb/>Council, which states that they do not<lb/>desire any closer relationship between the<lb/>Colonies than now exists, and he is now<lb/>prepared to go for a scheme of union on<lb/>such terms as he considers for the good<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
           
of the country. I maintain that if there<lb/>is anything the Government of the coun<lb break="no"/>try should take the responsibility of, it<lb/>is a matter affecting our Constitution.<lb/>The Government decline the responsibility<lb/>for the sake of their offices. They decline<lb/>the responsibility of maturing a scheme<lb/>but will bring forward the papers,<lb/>and let the representatives of the people<lb/>do as they like with them. Responsible<lb/>Government, which the people of this<lb/>country so long fought for, is a complete<lb/>farce in the hands of such men. They<lb/>will submit to anything as long as you<lb/>allow them to hold their offices. If the<lb/>Government act recreant to the duty of<lb/>the people who put them in that position,<lb/>it is sufficient to condemn them. I main<lb break="no"/>tain that whatever the decision of the<lb/>House may be, if an appeal is made to the<lb/>people, the people will decide against<lb/>them. The very Antis will reject them.<lb/>Let them appeal to the people, and they<lb/>will find themselves in as great a minority<lb/>as we found ourselves last election.<lb/>There is no great danger of the present<lb/>Government taking any responsibility as<lb/>long as they can hold office. Look at the<lb/>position which they occupy in regard to<lb/>Western Extension. One member of the<lb/>Government denouncing it as a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment work ; another member in St. John,<lb/>having committed himself at the hustings,<lb/>having declared there that he would op<lb break="no"/>pose any Government that would not<lb/>advocate Western Extension as a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment work. If there is anything the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment are responsible for, it is any<lb break="no"/>thing affecting the finances of the coun<lb break="no"/>try or the Constitution, and they throw<lb/>both these questions upon the representa<lb break="no"/>tives of the people. He has declined to<lb/>answer my question concerning Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. I believe the course will be to<lb/>submit the papers, and appoint a Com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the House to report upon them,<lb/>pass an Address affirming the principles<lb/>of union, and then send a delegation<lb/>home to confer with the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, while they are passing through the<lb/>Imperial Parliament, refusing to leave<lb/>the details to the people of this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. They have denounced the Confed<lb break="no"/>eration scheme, and our act, in leaving it<lb/>to the people, as an act of tyranny. How,<lb/>then, will they justify themselves ? How<lb/>will they meet this country and this House<lb/>again, and those Antis that are around<lb/>these boards ? The Hon. Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, in a speech delivered on the hustings<lb/>in Westmoreland, informed the electors of<lb/>the feelings of emotion which almost<lb/>ovecame him when he was signing the<lb/>contract for building the Railway to con<lb break="no"/>nect New Brunswick and Nova Scotia.<lb/>He was overcome in signing that contract.<lb/>I suppose concience was nipping him,<lb/>for if he had succeeded in 1864 in his op<lb break="no"/>position to the Bill in aid of building<lb/>Railways, he would not be in a position<lb/>to enter upon that contract. I hope these<lb/>feelings arose from the pricking of con<lb break="no"/>science, for " While the lamp holds out<lb/>to burn, the vilest sinner may return."<lb/>He states that when he explained this<lb/>great scheme to the people of England,<lb/>they were astonished that men of ordinary<lb/>intelligence could agree to such a scheme.<lb/>Only two had ever read it. He charges<lb/>the British Government and the Colonial<lb/>Secretary with ignorance.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Hon. Mr. Smith. - I do not think 
     <lb/>any hon. member has a right to make a<lb/>statement, and say I made a statement I<lb/>did not make. I did not charge the Colo<lb break="no"/>nial Secretary with ignorance. I said,<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
         

     outside of the British Government only two 
     <lb/>persons had read the scheme at all.<lb/>
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. McMILLAN. - Notwithstanding  
     <lb/>the British Government had given the<lb/>scheme all the consideration that they<lb/>always do to these questions, and pronounc<lb break="no"/>ed it good, and paid the highest compliment<lb/>to the delegates that met in Quebec, the<lb/>people were astonished. It was from the<lb/>manner in which he explained it that<lb/>caused the people of England to express<lb/>astonishment. He said, in the formation<lb/>of the Government was the County of<lb/>York neglected ? No, it was not neglect<lb break="no"/>ed, but other Counties were. Only one<lb/>man, who had no political experience<lb/>whatever - the very first day he took a<lb/>seat in this House, he was taken into the<lb/>Executive Council. This man was to<lb/>represent the four Northern Counties in<lb/>the Province. But he throws out a bait<lb/>now. He says, upon the basis upon<lb/>which the Government was formed, they <lb/>could not take a member in but one of<lb/>their own Anti principles. They really<lb/>desired to take a member from the North<lb/>into the Government. Look at the posi<lb break="no"/>tion the Northern members occupy, and<lb/>ask him if he is sincere in that statement.<lb/>There were two members from Kent and<lb/>two from Gloucester who supported the<lb/>Government on Anti principles, so there<lb/>was no necessity for doing injustice to<lb/>the North in having only one member for<lb/>four Counties. Upon that ground alone,<lb/>if I had no other grievance, I would con<lb break="no"/>demn them.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    There is another bait thrown out in the <lb/>Solicitor Generalship, and I ask my friend<lb/>on my left if he was not induced to be<lb break="no"/>lieve he would get the office. ( <persName ref="pers:FRAS1">Mr. Fra<lb break="no"/>ser</persName>, - No.) Then I have been misinform<lb break="no"/>ed. The next point is the Crown Lands.<lb/>There may be difference of opinion as to<lb/>whether the Minute of Council should be<lb/>recinded, which says no lands shall be<lb/>sold except for actual settlement. If their<lb/>course was such as to prevent the Inter-<lb break="yes"/>Colonial Railroad being built, they were<lb/>right in repealing it, for the object of it<lb/>was to prevent speculation pending the<lb/>negotiations for that Railway. But it<lb/>was their duty to have informed the pub<lb break="no"/>lic of the rescinding of that Minute of<lb/>Council the moment it was done. I<lb/>maintain they were wrong in thinking<lb/>this Railroad would not be built, for I<lb/>have no doubt it will be built by one route<lb/>or the other. I ask the Hon. Surveyor<lb/>General if he is not aware that his depu<lb break="no"/>ties did not give right information. Per<lb break="no"/>sons who applied for this land were told<lb/>they could not get it, the Deputies not<lb/>being aware that this Minute of Council<lb/>was cancelled. If that be so, what a<lb/>spectacle the Crown Land Office present<lb break="no"/>ed ; the Department guided and regulated<lb/>by one regulation, and their Deputies by<lb/>another. See the confusion to which it<lb/>led. The very moment that Minute of<lb/>Council was cancelled, it should have<lb/>been published in the Royal Gazette. I<lb/>do not say anything against Mr. Gibson,<lb/>for I consider he is a credit to the coun<lb break="no"/>try. His enterprise has no doubt been<lb/>an advantage to the section of the country<lb/>where he resides, and it was in his name<lb/>the Attorney General says, these lands<lb/>were published, and any person could op<lb break="no"/>pose him. I deny that. The first appli<lb break="no"/>cation was not published in Mr. Gibson's<lb/>name, but was published in the names of<lb/>A, B and C, and no person would know<lb/>Mr. Gibson was connected with it. This<lb/>was carrying out the principle which has<lb/>been so much denounced throughout the<lb/>
      

            <pb n="28" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_028.jpg"/>
     
<fw type="num">28</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</fw> 

     country.   When these charges were made 
     <lb/>
     against my predecessor, Mr. Brown, he 
     <lb/>
    was ignorant of the fact that fictitious 
     <lb/>names were used, but there was no igno<lb break="no"/>rance about these. The survey was made 
     <lb/>for Mr. Gibson, but the application was 
     <lb/>made in the names of other parties, so 
     <lb/>they cannot screen themselves in any 
     <lb/>way . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FRAS1">Mr. FRASER</persName>—Did you not make an 
     <lb/>order for the survey of 10,000 acres for 
     <lb/>Mr. Gibson. What did you intend by 
     <lb/>that order.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr.  McMILLAN</persName> — I can explain that, 
     <lb/>
     I did make an  order for the survey. upon 
     <lb/>
     the application of Mr.Gibson, but I do 
     <lb/>
     not recollect the number of acres. I sub<lb break="no"/>mitted it to the Council, a majority of 
     <lb/>
    whom were not prepared to rescind the 
     <lb/>Minute of Council, but ordered the sur<lb break="no"/>vey to take place. It was the intention 
     <lb/>of the Council, if the Government remain<lb break="no"/>ed in pow r—and there was no prospect 
     <lb/>of the Inter-Colonial Railroad being 
     <lb/>built—to rescind that Minute of Council. 
     <lb/>In regard to the appointment of Judges. 
     <lb/>I do not feel in a position to touch upon 
     <lb/>that point at all.  I believe that a great 
     <lb/>injustice, by an unjustifiable act, has been 
     <lb/>done to Judge Wilmot. With reference 
     <lb/>to the other vacancy which took place I 
     <lb/>do not pretend to be a judge whether it 
     <lb/>is properly filled or not. When a vacancy 
     <lb/>takes place upon the Bench it is natural 
     <lb/>to suppose that the Government would 
     <lb/>take a view of the leading man of the Bar, 
     <lb/> and from them make selection of a man 
     <lb/>to fill that high position, which is one of 
     <lb/>the highest in the Province. Have they 
     <lb/>done so? I said I was not a judge, but 
     <lb/>those that are judges think they have not 
     <lb/>done so. I doubt the propriety of having 
     <lb/>to go to "Insurance offices" to select a 
     <lb/>man to fill one of the highest positions in 
     <lb/>the Province. They should have full 
     <lb/>confidence that the person so appointed 
     <lb/>will be looked up to.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Attorney General's excuse for al<lb break="no"/>lowing the Export Duty to expire was, 
     <lb/>that no government ever had such diffi<lb break="no"/>culties to contend with as the present Go<lb break="no"/>vernment. What were the difficulties ? 
     <lb/>Were they not returned to the House by 
     <lb/>an immense majority. In the history of 
     <lb/>New Brunswick there never was a time 
     <lb/>when the Opposition was so small. What 
     <lb/>Acts had they to bring in, and what op<lb break="no"/>position was given them to take their at<lb break="no"/>tention from seeing what laws were about 
     <lb/>to expire? Even the members of the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment who went back to the country 
     <lb/>for re-election were not opposed in a 
     <lb/>single instance, and they were supported 
     <lb/>by a two-thirds vote in the House of As<lb break="no"/>sembly. Why then do they try to excuse 
     <lb/>themselves in that way ? There is no 
     <lb/>foundation for this excuse whatever, for 
     <lb/>they had no difficulties to draw their at<lb break="no"/>tention from looking into these matters. 
     <lb/>The arguments advanced by the Attorney 
     <lb/>General are peculiar ;  he would say the At<lb break="no"/>torney General was responsible when he 
     <lb/>was not here. It was not partof the Provin<lb break="no"/>cial Secretary's duty, but he says it was his 
     <lb/>predecessor's duty to know it, and he 
     <lb/>should have come  to the Provincial  Sec<lb break="no"/>retary's office and told the Provincial Sec<lb break="no"/>retary that this law was about to expire. 
     <lb/>The principle is, that the previous Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Secretary ought to have come to 
     <lb/>the present one and told him what his 
     <lb/>duties were; thus admiting at once 
     <lb/>their own incapacity to administer the af<lb break="no"/>fairs of the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName> — I stated distinctly<lb/>that the whole Government were respon<lb break="no"/>
         

            <cb/>
        
sible. It was the duty of the Attorney
<lb/>General, as he had undertaken to see
<lb/>what laws were about to expire. I
<lb/>said the Provincial Secretary was a
<lb/>young man and inexperienced in the duties
<lb/>of his office, and if his predecessor knew
<lb/>of the fact of this law being about to ex<lb break="no"/>pire, he should have communicated it to
<lb/>his successor.<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName>—When he wanted 
     <lb/>to get the Bill through the House he said 
     <lb/>the whole Government were responsible, 
     <lb/>but as soon as he got that through he 
     <lb/>tried to throw the responsibility upon the 
     <lb/>previous Attorney General. and the for<lb break="no"/>mer Provincial Secretary's name was 
     <lb/>lugged in. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>—I will leave it to 
     <lb/>the House. I said we were all responsi<lb break="no"/>ble. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName> — If he wishes to 
     <lb/>
     withdraw the statement that the Provin<lb break="no"/>cial Secretary was not responsible. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. Mr. SMITH</persName> — I did not say so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>—He charges the late 
     <lb/>
     Government with being guilty of an act of 
     <lb/>
     tyranny and despotism, because they ap<lb break="no"/>pealed to the people at an inclement sea<lb break="no"/>son of the year ; but he now says. if the 
     <lb/>
     Government are defeated he will appeal 
     <lb/>
     to the people. He will be guilty of the 
     <lb/>
     same thing he condemned in his prede<lb break="no"/>cessor, in order that he may hold office 
     <lb/>
     a little longer. No man in this country 
     <lb/>
     pretended to be so careless about offices 
     <lb/>
     as that hon. gentleman, but we find he 
     <lb/>
     holds on to them most tenaciously. In 
     <lb/>
     viewing the political  career of the leading 
     <lb/>
     men of British North America, I am not 
     <lb/>
     aware of one individual who has made 
     <lb/>
     more political summersaults than that 
     <lb/>
     hon. gentlemen. Look at his position in 
     <lb/>
     reference to railroads, and in reference to 
     <lb/>
     military matters. He left the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment because they would undertake a 
     <lb/>
     greater responsibility than twenty thou<lb break="no"/>sand pound per year for the Inter-colonial 
     <lb/>
     Railway, and in the Opposition he advo<lb break="no"/>cated the Western Extension as a Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment work, which would involve an 
     <lb/>
     annual liability of over sixty thousand 
     <lb/>
    pounds per year. When a Bill was 
     <lb/>brought before the House to appropriate 
     <lb/>$10,000 for this purpose he moved an 
     <lb/>amendment that the money be appropri<lb break="no"/>ated for Bye-Roads. Next year he brings 
     <lb/>down a Bill to appropriate $30,000 to the 
     <lb/>Militia service. If in one case he was 
     <lb/>sincere, in the other he must have been 
     <lb/>insincere. If he is in the Government he 
     <lb/>is for certain measures, if not he is in op<lb break="no"/>position. When in opposition he was not 
     <lb/>only against the Quebec Scheme, but 
     <lb/>against a Union of any kind. Now he 
     <lb/>has foreshadowed in the speech a Union 
     <lb/>of British North America. I asked him 
     <lb/>if he was not going to support something 
     <lb/>in the shape of appointing a Committee, 
     <lb/>a delegation,  or something of that kind, 
     <lb/>for the purpose of carrying a scheme of 
     <lb/>Union of some kind, and he would not 
     <lb/>answer me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. Mr. SMITH</persName>. I stated to Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Brown that we were prepnred to consider 
     <lb/>
     the question of Union, but not the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     Scheme. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>. If that is so, how 
     <lb/>
     does he endorse every word of that Minute 
     <lb/>
     of Council which says, "they desire no 
     <lb/>
     closer union." If he is sincere in one 
     <lb/>
     case. he must be insincere in the other. 
     <lb/>
     It has been stated by the Canadian and      
     <lb/>
    New Brunswick Press, and stated by Mr. 
     <lb/>Wilmot in Canada, that they were pre<lb break="no"/>pared to meet the members of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of New Brunswick — and <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> par<lb break="no"/>
           

            <cb/>
            
ticularly Mr. Smith — to discuss a Scheme
<lb/>of Union.<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—Mr. Brown had 
     <lb/>
    no authority to make such a statement. 
     <lb/>He distinctly declined a conference al<lb break="no"/>together.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>.—Did he not write 
     <lb/>
     and make a proposition ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—Mr. Brown dis<lb break="no"/>tinctly declined another conference when 
     <lb/>
     he was here. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>.—We have Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Brown's and Mr. Wilmot's statements for 
     <lb/>
     it. The Government formerly denounced 
     <lb/>
     a union of any kind, and now, having 
     <lb/>
     gone half over to a union policy, they 
     <lb/>
     occupy the position they do under false 
     <lb/>
     pretences. I ask him again, if he 
     <lb/>
     is prepared, either by a resolution, com<lb break="no"/>mittee, address or delegation, to support 
     <lb/>
     any scheme of union that has representa<lb break="no"/>tion by population in it. I repeat, I take 
     <lb/>it for granted he is.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—Don't take it for 
     <lb/>
     granted.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>.— You have answer<lb break="no"/>ed every other question. I will take it 
     <lb/>
    for granted . 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. Mr. SMITH</persName>—He seems deter<lb break="no"/>mined that I shall answer all the ques<lb break="no"/>tions he has a mind to put. l stated 
     <lb/>
     distinctly my views in regard to the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of representation by population, as 
     <lb/>
     contained in the Quebec Scheme. I 
     <lb/>
     would never consent to it, unless there 
     <lb/>
     are other protections to counterbalance 
     <lb/>
     it, I attempted to explain the effects of 
     <lb/>
     representation by population, as contain<lb break="no"/>ed in the Scheme, but I do not know how 
     <lb/>
     to provide checks, and if checks cannot be 
     <lb/>
     provided, I never will give my consent to 
     <lb/>
     representation by population. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>.—I think the coun<lb break="no"/>try and the House will give me credit for 
     <lb/>
     getting half am answer from the Attorney 
     <lb/>
     General, and I believe, from the answer, 
     <lb/>
     he is prepared to support a scheme (hear 
     <lb/>
     hear) that contains the principle which he 
     <lb/>
     has denounced throughout the country, 
     <lb/>
     viz: representation by population, coun<lb break="no"/>teracted by something else. The most 
     <lb/>
     important part of the whole scheme he 
     <lb/>
     is prepared to go for; having a large re<lb break="no"/>presentation in the upper branch is not so 
     <lb/>
     much protection. The most important 
     <lb/>
     body is the people's representatives who 
     <lb/>
     have control of the people's money. ln 
     <lb/>
     order to hold his office, he is prepared to 
     <lb/>
     swallow all this. He has swallowed the 
     <lb/>
     half' pill now, and he will swallow the 
     <lb/>
     whole pill to hold on to office. I hope 
     <lb/>
     the expression drawn from him   will open 
     <lb/>
     the eyes of the Anti members. The mem<lb break="no"/>bers of this Government have  proved 
     <lb/>
     recreant to their professions. They pro<lb break="no"/>fessed to be "Antis," and then  when it 
     <lb/>
     is drawn out of their leader, he is going 
     <lb/>
     to support a scheme of union on the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of presentation by population. 
     <lb/>
     When the Quebec Scheme was introduced 
     <lb/>
     the cry throughout the country was, we 
     <lb/>
     are going to be swamped; only fifteen 
     <lb/>
     men in the Canadian Parliament. Is he 
     <lb/>
     not prepared to go for a similar scheme 
     <lb/>
     with only fifteen members ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>—I never have been, 
     <lb/>
     and never will be. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>. —Does he withdraw  
     <lb/>
     that too? No, he will not withdraw it, 
     <lb/>
     for I believe he is committed to it. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve he has not told his supporters that 
     <lb/>he is prepared to submit such a scheme.<lb/>This is tyranny. He was elected to op<lb break="no"/>pose a scheme, and he will come forward<lb/>and support it without any appeal to the<lb/>people. If that is the <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> gov<lb break="no"/>

            <pb n="29" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-16_Page_029.jpg"/>
           
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  <fw type="num">29</fw>

     ernment are going to adopt, then good           
     <lb/>
     bye to Responsible Government. And her             
     <lb/>
     cry got up by the Attorney General was            
     <lb/>
     that the press was against them. The                
     <lb/>
     press was exposing their incapacity, and          
     <lb/>
     they do not desire to hear these things.               
     <lb/>
    It is the duty of the press to deal with           
     <lb/>Governments. It really appears an in<lb break="no"/>jury to the country to denounce a press        
     <lb/>because it speaks out boldly and manly,         
     <lb/>and condemns the acts of a Government.         
     <lb/> He says no injustice has been done to           
     <lb/>York. I think an injustice has been done       
     <lb/>to York, and to other sections of the            
     <lb/>country too. Did not they attempt to do<lb/>injustice to the principles of Responsible<lb/>and Departmental Government, by doing<lb/>away with one of the most important<lb/>offices,  that of Postmaster General ?<lb/>Notwithstanding the additional labour to <lb/>be performed ; the labour is done more<lb/>economically now than it was before the<lb/>office became responsible.  He did<lb/>not think it right for the hon  member for<lb/>York to state at the hustings that this was<lb/>the first step towards the removal of the <lb/>seat of Government. I stated that last <lb/>year. I believed it <hi rendition="simple:italic">then</hi> and I believe it <lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">now</hi>, that it is not the only first step towards<lb/>the removal of the seat of Government, <lb/>but to do away with departmental govern<lb break="no"/>ment altogether. The present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would then rule the country with <lb/>tyranny and despotism, holding their po<lb break="no"/>sition without any responsibility at all.<lb/>Look at their whole career- at their mea<lb break="no"/>sures of last year- the measures fore<lb break="no"/>shadowed in the speech- their course in<lb/>reference to Union principles- their ne<lb break="no"/>glect in allowing the law to expire for<lb/>collecting export duty, and ask yourselves<lb/>are you prepared to sustain this Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. I believe the day will come when <lb/>the country will not sustain those men<lb/>who support them.  Then in reference to<lb/> Fenianism, I do not think there is much <lb/>danger. The leaders keep the excitement<lb/>up for the purpose of getting money.<lb/>True, I am in the Northern part of the <lb/>Province, where there is no great dan<lb break="no"/>ger.  But I ask the Attorney General if<lb/>he was sincere when he appealed to the<lb/>house in a tremulous voice, and said<lb/>this was no time to discuss a motion of <lb/>Want of Confidence, when the country<lb/>was in danger of a conspiracy on our<lb/>borders.  If he was, has he been sin<lb break="no"/>cere lately in ridiculing the whole move<lb break="no"/>ment? If he was sincere in the one<lb/>case he must have been insincere in the <lb/>other. Viewing the whole policy of the <lb/>Gvoernment I have no hesitation in say<lb break="no"/>ing, they have not my confidence, nor<lb/>the confidence of the people.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    The debate was then adjourned until <lb/>to-morrow at 11 o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName> presented the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing resolution :- <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"Resolved unanimously, that an <lb/>humble address be presented to His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency the Lieutenant Governor, re<lb break="no"/>spectfully assuring His Excellency that<lb/>this House, representing the whole peo<lb break="no"/>ple of the Province, will provide for all<lb/>precautionary measures, that the Exe<lb break="no"/>cutive Governmern may deem necessary<lb/>in the present emergency for the de<lb break="no"/>fence of the country."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. FISHER</persName> hoped the House would<lb/>be unanimous, as it would meet a un<lb break="no"/>animous response from the whole peo<lb break="no"/>ple. They must trust the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to use economy ; but money is no<lb/>object when the country was in danger, <lb/>
          

            <cb/>
          
and as far as their means went they<lb/>must give effect to that resolution.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:WILM1">Mr. WILMOT</persName> also expressed him<lb break="no"/>self in favor of the resolution, which was<lb/>carried unanimously.<lb/>  The House then adjourned until 10<lb/>A. M., to-morrow.</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">T. P. D. <lb/>
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2018-05-03, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p>                    SATURDAY, March 17. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>House went into Committee of the <lb/>Whole, on a Bill to alter the place of <lb/>holding elections in the Parish of Hamp<lb break="no"/>ton, in the County of Kings, passed<lb/>without discussion or amendment. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. CUDLIP introduced a Bill to<lb/>incorporate the Inter-Colonial Railway<lb/>Company.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On the motion of Mr. NEEDHAM-\-se-<lb break="maybe"/>conded by Mr. Sutton-\-the debate on<lb/>the Amendment to the Address was<lb/>adjourned over until Monday at twelve.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DESB1">Mr. DesBRISAY</persName> rose and made an<lb/>explanation, regarding a statement<lb/>made in the Globe newspaper, in its<lb/>report of his speech on Thursday, where<lb/>he was made to say, that he had been<lb/>snubbed by petty Railway officials. He<lb/>had never made such remark. When<lb/>travelling on the Railway he had always<lb/>received every civility from the Railway<lb/>officials, and he did not wish such a <lb/>statement to go abroad uncontraindicated.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FRAS1">Mr. FRASER</persName> asked the Provincial<lb/>Secretary if he had been furnished by<lb/>the Canadian Government with copies<lb/>of Mr. Fleming's Report on the Inter-<lb break="yes"/>Colonial Railway routes.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>PROVINCIAL SECRETARY had not<lb/>received any copies of that Report.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of Mr. FRASER, the House<lb/>went into Committee of the Whole (Mr.<lb/>Beveridge in the Chair) to incorporate<lb/>the Provincial Oil Company.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FRAS1">Mr. Fraser</persName> explained, that the object<lb/>of the Bill was to enable a company to<lb/>carry on the manufacture of Oil in the<lb/>Province ; there was no particular loca<lb break="no"/>lity mentioned.  The Bill was almost a<lb/>verbatim copy of the Bill incorporating<lb/>the Caledonia Oil Company ; it went a <lb/>little further and authorised the com<lb break="no"/>pany to deal in monies.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Mr. McCLELAN</persName> did not see why <lb/>the company should not form under the <lb/>general act.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FRAS1">Mr. FRASER</persName>. The gentleman who<lb/>proposed forming the company preferred <lb/>to have a special act<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> could not see why a <lb/>special act should take place merely<lb/>because some gentlemen preferred it.<lb/>All they would have to do to form under<lb/>the general act would be to go into the<lb/>Provincial Secretary's office, fyle cer<lb break="no"/>tain papers, and pay the fees. By allow<lb break="no"/>ing them to take out a special act they<lb/>would escape paying the fees<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Mr. McCLELAN</persName> said, that the fee<lb/>was $40 for coming under the general<lb/>act ; but, of course, it could not be the<lb/>object of the company, that preferred<lb/>doing business on the scale they did, to<lb/>escape the fees. He would move that <lb/>progress be reported, an the Bill re<lb break="no"/>ferred to a Committee.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>ATTORNEY GENERAL did not see<lb/>that any harm could be ????????<lb/>the company a special ????? was<lb/>inclined to support the Bill. He was<lb/>disposed to give every ??????<lb/>???? in to ??????  <lb/>the Province, but he would suggest that<lb/>the Bill be referred to a Committee.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FRAS1">Mr. FRASER</persName> said, that the gentlemen<lb/>proposing to form the company, were<lb/>wealthy business men of Boston ; it was<lb/>not a bogus company, and they intentded<lb/>to bring in a great deal of money into<lb/>the Province.  He thought the bringing<lb/>in of foreign capital ought to be encou<lb break="no"/>raged. These gentlemen did not ask a <lb/>special act, because they would escape<lb/>paying some small fess.  But if they<lb/>came in under the general act, they<lb/>would not purchase lands or hold mines.<lb/>Finally, progress was reported, and the<lb/>Bill was referred to a Committee.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>In the afternoon, Mr. FISHER moved<lb/>that the Address of the House, in accord<lb break="no"/>ance with the resolution passed on Fri<lb break="no"/>day :<lb break="no"/>
            </p>
            <p>"That an Humble Address be pre<lb break="no"/>sented to His Excellency the Lieutenant<lb/>Governor, respectfully assuring His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency that the House, representing <lb/>the whole people of the Province, will<lb/>provide for all precautionary measures<lb/>that the Executive Council may deem to <lb/>be necessary in the present emergency<lb/>for the defence of the Province, be pre<lb break="no"/>sented by the Speaker and the whole<lb/>House."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The members in the House accord<lb break="no"/>ingly proceeded to Government house ;<lb/>and, having returned, the Speaker read<lb/>the Reply of His Excellency :-<lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>
            <p>GENTLEMEN:-\-<lb break="maybe"/>"I thank the House of Assembly for<lb/>the fresh proof they have afforded that<lb/>the ancient spirit of loyalty which ani<lb break="no"/>mated the first founders of the Province<lb/>has neither diminished nor decayed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"I deeply regret that machinations<lb/>of evil-disposed men should render ne<lb break="no"/>cessary a considerable expenditure for<lb/>defensive purposes ; but your liberality<lb/>will have been wisely bestowed, should<lb/>it show to the plotters who dream of a <lb/>descent upon our borders, how little<lb/>they can hope for success in such an <lb/>enterprise.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"The most rigid economy shall be<lb/>exercised in the expenditure of the re<lb break="no"/>sources you have places at my disposal.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"Confiding in the protection of Al<lb break="no"/>mighty God, and assured of the support<lb/>of a gallant and united people, I await<lb/>the future without anxious care."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName> moved the adjourn<lb break="no"/>ment of the House, in honor of St.<lb/>Patrick's Day, which, being carried, the<lb/>day at 10 o'clock.<lb/>                                          A. A, <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>                  MONDAY, March 10. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>After a number of Petitions and Bills<lb/>had been brought in, Mr. FISHER<lb/>moved the House into Committee on a <lb/>Bill to incorporate the Fredericton<lb/>Railway Company, which was agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>DEBATE ON THE AMENDMENT TO THE<lb/>FOURTH PARAGRAPH OF THE ADDRESS<lb/> RESUMED. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. BOTSFORD requested the<lb/>??? of the House, in ????<lb/>ing out the  ???????<lb/>that he should reply to Mr. Mc??<lb/>?? consequence of indisposition ??? could<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

    

    

    

    
-->
    

    

    
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>