<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1867-05-31"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1867-05-31">31 May 1867</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="111"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="122" to="122"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_107.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_108.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_109.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_110.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_111.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_122.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-05-01">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-05-01">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_107">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_107.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_108">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_108.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_109">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_109.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_110">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_110.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_111">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_111.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_122">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_122.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="107" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_107.jpg"/>
   
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> <fw type="num">107</fw>


<!-- GL, 2018-05-01, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
            <!--<p>If we pass this Bill I think it will be dis<lb break="no"/>allowed, for the spirit of the Imperial<lb/>Act is that you cannot recast your judi<lb break="no"/>cial institutions. I say many provisions <lb/>of this law are in force now. I would<lb/>like to ask whether the fiscal laws can be<lb/>changed ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. TILLEY.—Yes, they can.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.— I think you had better<lb/>change them if you have the power. I<lb/>think we have not the power, but the<lb/>Secretary seems to speak ex cathedra in<lb/>regard to the law, while the Attorney<lb/>General does not. I should rather have<lb/>the opinion of the Attorney General upon<lb/>the subject.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>.—I think we have<lb/>the power to change them.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—They did not pass any<lb/>law in Nova Scotia upon the subject, and<lb/>I do not believe we have the power to do<lb/>so, because I believe a port on the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Act is in force. When the Secre<lb break="no"/>tary speaks of men being willing to lose<lb/>sums of £20 rather than bring an action<lb/>in the Supreme Court, does he not know<lb/>they can bring an action in the summary<lb/>process in the Spreme Court at a less<lb/>cost than would have to be paid under<lb/>this Bill ? I believe it would be more<lb/>economical, and the wants of the coun<lb break="no"/>try would be much better satisfied, if we<lb/>adopted my suggestion and increased the<lb/>summary practice to £50 and combined<lb/>the civil and criminal jurisdiction to<lb break="no"/>gether.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Progress was then reported upon the<lb/>Bill and leave asked to sit again.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. TILLEY, by command of<lb/>His Excellency the Administrator of the<lb/>Government, laid before the House de-<lb break="maybe"/>spatches relating to Church patronage.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> brought in a Bill<lb/>relating to paving streets and sidewalks<lb/>in the Town of St. Stephen.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion the House adjourned until<lb/>to-morrow at 9 o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>T.P.D.<lb/>
            </p>-->



            <head rendition="simple:right">FRIDAY, MAY 31.<lb/>
            </head>

            <head rendition="simple:centre">SECOND READINGS.<lb/>
            </head>


            <p>The following Bills were read a second<lb/>time :<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to provide for the more effectu<lb break="no"/>al repairing of the Streets, Sidewalks<lb/>and Bridges of Saint Stephen.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Certain amendments made by the Leg<lb break="no"/>islative Council to the Bill to Incorpo<lb break="no"/>rate the Albert Bank.<lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">THIRD READINGS.<lb/>
            </head>


            <p>The following Bills were read a third<lb/>time :<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill relating to Paved Sidewalks in<lb/>the City of Saint John.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to authorize an assessment in<lb/>
            

            <cb/>
         

the City of Saint John for the purposes<lb/>of an Agricultural exhibition therein.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to amend the Act to provide for<lb/>the erection of a City Hall in the City of<lb/>Saint John.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">REPORT AND BILL.<lb/>
            </head>


            <p><persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName>, from the Road Com<lb break="no"/>mittee, reported that they had prepared<lb/>a Bill relating to Highways, which they<lb/>now begged to introduce.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was received and read a first<lb/>and second time.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">RESOLUTION FOR ADDRESS.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName>, according to a notice<lb/>which he gave on Monday, moved an<lb/>Address to His Excellency the Adminis<lb break="no"/>trator of the Government, praying that<lb/>all papers connected with the claim of<lb/>Thomas King, a Railway Contractor,<lb/>against the Government, might be laid<lb/>before the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Messrs. Wetmore, Quinton and Des<lb break="no"/>Brisay, were appointed a Committee to<lb/>wait upon His Excellency with the Ad<lb break="no"/>dress.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">BILL.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MCAD1">Hon. Mr. McADAM</persName> moved for leave<lb/>to bring in a Bill to authorize the erec<lb break="no"/>tion of a Sorting Boom on Eel River in<lb/>the Counties of York and Carleton.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Leave was granted and the Bill read a<lb/>first and second time.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">COUNTRY MARKET, ST. JOHN.<lb/>
            </head>


            <p><persName ref="pers:QUIN1">Mr. QUINTON</persName> moved the House into<lb/>Committee on a Bill to authorize the<lb/>City Corporation of Saint John to pur<lb break="no"/>chase lands to the northward of the<lb/>County Market in the said City of Saint<lb/>John.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LEWI1">Mr. LEWIS</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was agreed to without de<lb break="no"/>bate.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">COUNTY COURTS.<lb/>
            </head>


            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> moved the House<lb/>into Committee on the further considera<lb break="no"/>tion of a Bill to establish County Courts.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. BOTSFORD</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCQU1">Mr. McQUEEN</persName>.—Whilst I have been<lb/>listening to the debate the question has<lb/>occurred to me whether we have really<lb/>the power to legislate on this matter.<lb/>The Provincial Secretary and Attorney<lb/>General distinctly state that we have ;<lb/>the delegate member for Northumberland<lb/>says we have the legal power, but not<lb/>the moral power ; that it would be a<lb/>breach of faith with Canada to create<lb/>these Courts, as it was not contemplated<lb/>in the Act of Union. When these learn<lb break="no"/>ed men differ it is hard to know what to<lb/>think. There are some things in the Bill<lb/>that commend themselves to my mind.<lb/>It is said that the establishment of these<lb/>Courts will have the effect of giving us<lb/>cheap law and speedy justice, and if this<lb/>is the case it would be a great benefit ;<lb/>
       

            <cb/>
           
but it has been said by my colleague<lb/>Mr. Smith) that the process of law will<lb/>not be any cheaper under this Bill than<lb/>it is now, in the Court of Common Pleas,<lb/>and if the argument he used in support<lb/>of his position is correct, I do not see any<lb/>benefit that can be derived from the pass<lb break="no"/>ing of this Bill. If the Court of Common<lb/>Pleas was presided over by man of legal<lb/>attainments, I think the standard of the<lb/>Court would be raised, and a great many<lb/>more cases be tried by it than at present.<lb/>I think, too, that if the jurisdiction of<lb/>these Courts was increased so as to bring<lb/>in cases up to $200, it would be found a<lb/>great benefit, and if to this were added a<lb/>clause to bind real estate, then we should<lb/>have what is required. In our County<lb/>we have now four Courts every year,<lb/>two sittings of the Supreme Court and<lb/>two of Common Pleas ; the number of<lb/>Jurymen employed to try cases in these<lb/>Courts in all is eighty-four, forty-two of<lb/>each, and if we now go to work and es<lb break="no"/>tablish a County Court besides, forty<lb/>more will be added, thus increasing the<lb/>number to one hundred and twenty-four ;<lb/>and for these additional Jurymen, taking<lb/>the mileage and Jury charges into con<lb break="no"/>sideration, we should have to pay $2,000<lb/>more than we pay now, which would be<lb/>a great increase of the expense. I do not<lb/>think the establishment of these Courts,<lb/>under the circumstances, will commend<lb/>itself to the mind of the country. It is<lb/>true, as has been stated, that these Courts<lb/>have been found to work well in Canada,<lb/>and that is greatly in its favor, but it<lb/>seems strange to me that if we have the<lb/>power to legislate in the matter now, the<lb/>people of Nova Scotia did not adopt it at<lb/>the last meeting of the Legislature. The<lb/>Bill does not commend itself as favorably<lb/>to my mind as it does to some others<lb/>and I shall vote against it, although I<lb/>suppose it will pass.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.—This is a question of very<lb/>considerable importance, and one that<lb/>has occupied my attention a good deal,<lb/>and I supposed this Bill would be supple<lb break="no"/>mented by another, which would do<lb/>away with the Magistrates' Courts all<lb/>over the country. Having this impres<lb break="no"/>sion, when I heard that County Courts<lb/>were to be established here, the matter<lb/>commended itself to my mind at once.<lb/>The idea that because they have them<lb/>in Canada, and that for the sake of uni<lb break="no"/>formity we should have them here, and<lb/>that their introduction at this time will<lb/>give us a chance to share in the expendi<lb break="no"/>tures which will be made for this pur<lb break="no"/>pose, to my mind bears very little weight.<lb/>The question is, are they needed ? And<lb/>if so, how can they best be established<lb/>to accomplish the object desired ? We all<lb/>know that at present the great number<lb/>of Magistrates' Courts held all over the<lb/>country is a great source of litigation,<lb/>and that a man who has a claim against<lb/>another of a very trifling amount, can<lb/>send here and there to bring his witnesses,<lb/>
         

            <pb n="108" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_108.jpg"/>
          
<fw type="num">108</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw>



causing much delay and expense, over a<lb/>matter that is not worth talking about.<lb/>By the introduction of these Courts, es<lb break="no"/>pecially if the Government had deter<lb break="no"/>mined to go on with the second Bill, the<lb/>difficulties and anxieties caused by these<lb/>petty trials, as well as the delay and ex<lb break="no"/>pense, would be very much curtailed,<lb/>and prove a great means of reducing<lb/>litigation. It has been objected that<lb/>County Courts will be attended with a<lb/>great deal of expense, but if we give<lb/>£500 to each of the five Judges, and al<lb break="no"/>low them £50 or so extra for travelling <lb/>expenses, it would only amount to some<lb/>£2800 ; and although the hon. member<lb/>for Westmorland thinks that the Jury<lb/>fees would be very much increased, I<lb/>believe he will find that the great expense<lb/>now incurred by delay would be more<lb/>than counterbalanced by the speedy man<lb break="no"/>ner in which justice could be obtained.<lb/>The reduction in costs on cases between<lb/>£20 and £50 would save to the people of<lb/>this country more than the whole ex<lb break="no"/>pense of holding the Courts. When it<lb/>was proposed to have five Judges I<lb/>thought the Government contemplated<lb/>introducing the District Courts Bill as<lb/>well, but since this is not to be the case,<lb/>I don't see how five Judges are going to<lb/>be occupied the whole time, as they will<lb/>not hold more than four Courts in the<lb/>year, and it cannot be expected that each<lb/>Court will sit more than two or three<lb/>weeks. I think that now we shall have<lb/>either to reduce the number or increase<lb/>their jurisdiction, for there will not be<lb/>enough business for them to do, and the<lb/>litigation of the country is lessening<lb/>every year. In Upper Canada they have<lb/>eleven Judges of County Courts, with a<lb/>very large population ; in Lower Canada,<lb/>with a different style of Judicature, they<lb/>have only twenty Judges altogether ; in<lb/>Nova Scotia they have six, and we have<lb/>five Judges of Superior Courts. If we<lb/>now add five other Judges of County<lb/>Courts, at a large salary, our expenses<lb/>will exceed in proportion those of Upper<lb/>Canada ; and although I think there is<lb/>great necessity for a change, yet I do not<lb/>see how we shall be able to manage,<lb/>unless we reduce the number or extend<lb/>their power. The salaries proposed<lb/>will be too large for the amount of la<lb break="no"/>bor they will be required to perform,<lb/>and I think we should reduce them to<lb/>three, so as not to encumber the funds<lb/>of the country with a larger amount<lb/>than they will bear. If the whole mat<lb break="no"/>ter had been covered with regard to the<lb/>Magistrates Courts, I should have given<lb/>this Bill my full and hearty support,<lb/>believing, as I do, that it would prove<lb/>a great benefit to the country, but as it<lb/>is I do not think this Bill will affect the<lb/>greatest evil which exists, and I have<lb/>great doubts about establishing all these<lb/>Courts without just knowing what the<lb/>requirements of the country are. In<lb break="no"/>deed the General Government may dis<lb break="no"/>
         

            <cb/>
          
allow the appointments after we make<lb/>them, and we should, therefore, be very<lb/>careful how we proceed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CAIE1">Mr. CAIE</persName>.—I am not a lawyer, and<lb/>as I observe that some of our most<lb/>eminent lawyers, statesmen and dele<lb break="no"/>gates differ upon this matter, I shall not<lb/>offer any opinion as to whether we have<lb/>power or not to legislate under the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Act ; but I must say that I entire<lb break="no"/>ly coincide with the remark of the hon.<lb/>member for Northumberland, (Mr.<lb/>Johnson) himself one of the delegates,<lb/>that if we have a doubt on the matter<lb/>we should pause before we act. But<lb/>that hon. member goes on and says that<lb/>undoubtedly power is left with the<lb/>House to legislate upon this subject,<lb/>but that we have not the right to do so.<lb/>I confess, Mr. Chairman, that I do not<lb/>see the difference which the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber tries to make. I think that the <hi rendition="simple:italic">right</hi><lb/>gives the <hi rendition="simple:italic">power</hi>. It is true that the<lb/>House has the power to say to a peti<lb break="no"/>tioner who had a most righteous claim<lb/>against the Government or House, " We<lb/>will not pay you," and the man has no<lb/>redress ; he must be quiet, for he can't<lb/>sue and recover as in any other case.<lb/>But because the House has that power,<lb/>is it right they should therefore cheat a<lb/>man of his just due ? Certainly not ;<lb/>the power confers no right, it is the<lb/>right which gives the power. I think<lb/>that a change is very much needed in<lb/>respect to our Magistrates' Courts, but<lb/>I think it should be brought about, if<lb/>possible, without increasing the costs of<lb/>litigation. I think that if three persons<lb/>in each Parish were appointed to hold<lb/>a Court, once a week, or once a fort<lb break="no"/>night, or once a month, as might be<lb/>found most requisite, with power to ad<lb break="no"/>judicate on amounts up to £50, it would<lb/>do away with many of the cases which<lb/>now come before the Court of Sessions,<lb/>and very much lessen the amount of<lb/>litigation. I think that the measure<lb/>now before the House will prove very<lb/>cumbersome, and be a great expense<lb/>to the country, which might be saved<lb/>by adopting a plan such as I have men<lb break="no"/>tioned, and I shall, therefore, not give<lb/>it my support.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BABB1">Mr. BABBITT</persName>.—Whatever may be the<lb/>differences of opinion existing between<lb/>lawyers and statesmen on this question<lb/>we have, after all, individually to make<lb/>up our minds and decide for ourselves.<lb/>I think we have the right to legislate<lb/>upon any subject which comes under our<lb/>consideration. To me this is a mere<lb/>matter of propriety. The question is<lb/>whether, now and after we go into<lb/>Union, the requirements of the country<lb/>demands the establishment of these<lb/>Country Courts or not. I am satisfied<lb/>that a change is needed, but what should<lb/>it be ? And how can it be, effected ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>The time now occupied in collecting a<lb/>claim through the Supreme Court is too<lb/>long, and justly causes much complaint,<lb/>and if, by the establishment of these<lb/>Courts, we can get justice brought<lb/>nearer home, and obtain it as a cheaper<lb/>rate, it will be just what is required. I<lb/>feel satisfied that this effect will be pro<lb break="no"/>duced, and therefore I shall support the<lb/>Bill. So much for the principle ; the<lb/>details laid down in the Bill I may not<lb/>so readily agree with, but they can be<lb/>argued and arranged as the debates goes<lb/>on. I think the measure will meet with<lb/>the appreciation of the country, if the<lb/>Government don't foist too many Judges<lb/>upon us, and make the machinery too<lb/>heavy and cumbersome. I differ with<lb/>a good many hon. members as to the<lb/>Magistrates, for although some of them<lb/>may not be possessed of very high legal<lb/>attainments, yet many of them are men<lb/>of good abilities, and from their know<lb break="no"/>ledge of facts, with regard to cases<lb/>which come before them, are able to<lb/>administer justice speedily and cheaply.<lb/>Instead of taking away any of the juris<lb break="no"/>diction which they now have I would<lb/>give them more.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOHN1">Mr. JOHNSON</persName>.—You would have<lb/>to give them more brains first.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BABB1">Mr. BABBIT</persName>.—I think that so far as<lb/>small debts are concerned it is a most<lb/>simple method of gaining cheap jus<lb break="no"/>tice. As to complaints of delay in cer<lb break="no"/>tain cases, the same will apply to the<lb/>Supreme Court in a much larger degree,<lb/>and I think that if the powers of Magis<lb break="no"/>trates were increased it would prove a<lb/>great benefit to the country. Most of<lb/>them have now a-days a Jury of three<lb/>to try the causes which come before<lb/>them, and the people find that it is a<lb/>good way, enabling them to obtain jus<lb break="no"/>tice at their own homes, and at a cheap<lb/>rate. As to the present Bill I am in<lb/>favor of the principle, although I think<lb/>that a satisfactory change may be made<lb/>in the details as we go along.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Committee then divided on the<lb/>question of reading the Bill section by<lb/>section, when there appeared —<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:centre">YEAS :</p><p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. Fisher</persName>,<lb/>Hon. Mr. Williston,<lb/>Hon. Mr. Tilley,<lb/>Hon. Mr. Connell,<lb/>Hon. Mr. McMillan,<lb/>Hon. Mr. Wilmot,<lb/>Hon. Mr. McAdam,<lb/>His Honor the Speaker,<lb/>Mr. Lewis,<lb/>Mr. Kerr,<lb/>Mr. Stevens,<lb/>Mr. Sutton,<lb/>Mr. Beveridge,<lb/>Mr. Skinner,<lb/>Mr. Hebert,<lb/>Mr. Chandler,<lb/>Mr. DesBrisay,<lb/>Mr. Quinton,<lb/>
          


            <pb n="109" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_109.jpg"/>
          

<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> <fw type="num">109</fw>
        

Mr. Wetmore,<lb/>Mr. Dow,<lb/>Mr. Ryan,<lb/>Mr. Beckwith,<lb/>Mr. Ferris,<lb/>Mr. Babbit,<lb/>Mr. J. Flewwelling,<lb/>Mr. W. P. Flewelling,<lb/>Mr. Perley,<lb/>Mr. Lindsay—28.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:centre">NAYS :</p><p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. Smith</persName>,<lb/>Mr. Johnson,<lb/>Mr. Young,<lb/>Mr. Caie,<lb/>Mr. Meehan,<lb/>Mr. McInerney,<lb/>Mr. McQueen—8.<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>The question being carried in the<lb/>affirmative, the Chairman proceeded to<lb/>read the Bill section by section.<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>1. There shall be established in each<lb/>of the Counties in this Province a Court<lb/>of Law and of Record, to be styled the<lb/>County Court of [<hi rendition="simple:italic">name of the County</hi>]<lb/>and the Sittings of the said Court shall<lb/>be held at the County Court House.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
            <p>Passed.<lb/>
            </p>
            
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>2. The Governor in Council shall ap<lb break="no"/>point one Judge for the Counties of Char<lb break="no"/>lotte, Carleton and Victoria; one Judge<lb/>for the Counties of York, Sunbury and<lb/>Queen's ; one Judge for the Counties of<lb/>Albert, Westmorland and Kent, one<lb/>Judge for the Counties of Northumber<lb break="no"/>land, Gloucester and Restigouche, and<lb/>one Judge for the Counties of King's and<lb/>Saint John ; provided that the said Court<lb/>for the County of Saint John shall not<lb/>have or exercise any jurisdiction in any<lb/>Cause in which the City Court in and for<lb/>the City of Saint John, or the Police<lb/>Court in the Parish of Portland, in the<lb/>County of Saint John, have jurisdiction.<lb/>The said Judges shall be Barristers of<lb/>not less than seven years standing, and shall<lb/>hold office during good behaviour ; and<lb/>a Clerk for each Court shall be appointed,<lb/>who shall be an Attorney, and shall hold<lb/>his office during pleasure.<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p><persName ref="pers:JOHN1">Mr. JOHNSON</persName>.—We are now going<lb/>to establish County Courts, the principle<lb/>of the Bill is established, the main ques<lb break="no"/>tion is settled, and now having cast my<lb/>vote unavailingly against it, I am pre<lb break="no"/>pared to do what I can to make its pro<lb break="no"/>visions as effective and satisfactory to the<lb/>people as possible. We are, it seems,<lb/>going to appoint five Judges, each Judge<lb/>to hold a Court, having jurisdiction over<lb/>three Counties, and then to appoint a<lb/>separate Clerk for each Court; is that the<lb/>intention ? and that man an Attorney, a<lb/>practising Attorney, who is able to go<lb/>into the Court, and conduct cases whilst<lb/>still holding his position ! Well, I know<lb/>that lawyers are generally pretty good<lb/>men, but I think this House should not<lb/>hold out inducements such as this. I <lb/>really cannot think this is intended.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>.—I sincerely hope<lb/>the same spirit which has been expressed<lb/>by the hon. member for Northumberland<lb/>
     

            <cb/>
          
will influence all the hon. members pre<lb break="no"/>sent, and I thank him for the remarks he<lb/>has made. Two propositions are laid<lb/>down with regard to the Clerk. First, it<lb/>is intended to appoint one for each Court,<lb/>for it is believed that he will be needed.<lb/>All the business could not be attended to<lb/>by one Clerk for all the Courts, and from<lb/>the fact that three Courts will be held by<lb/>each Judge in the year, it will be seen<lb/>that a distinct Clerk of the Court will be<lb/>required, and prove advantageous. Se<lb break="no"/>cond, it is intended that he shall prac<lb break="no"/>tice ; if the House think that he should<lb/>not, we can put that in, but it was thought<lb/>that there would not be sufficient busi<lb break="no"/>ness of the Court to enable him to get<lb/>along if he was excluded from practising.<lb/>If it is thought desirable to make a change<lb/>let a clause be inserted that he shall not<lb/>practice in the County of which he is<lb/>Clerk ; this will cover the ground. The<lb/>Clerk of the Court of Common Pleas is<lb/>now allowed to practice in the same Court,<lb/>and I see no very great evil that would<lb/>arise from it in this case. However,<lb/>wherein the Bill is defective we shall be<lb/>thankful to hear suggestions of improve<lb break="no"/>ment, so that it may be remedied.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOHN1">Mr. JOHNSON</persName>.—I would ask why<lb/>the Clerks of the Peace now appointed<lb/>cannot be appointed to be Clerks of the<lb/>County Courts ; thus saving the expense<lb/>and not leaving the appointments in the<lb/>hands of the Government ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—It is evident there is an<lb/>ovewhelming majority for this Bill, but<lb/>there are certain portions of it which are<lb/>most objectionable, and upon which I<lb/>may say a few words. In Canada they<lb/>have these County Courts, and they are<lb/>said to have worked well ; but it is very<lb/>different there to the system about to be<lb/>established here. There they have a<lb/>Judge for every County, and in some<lb/>Counties they have two. The Judge<lb/>resides in the Shire town, he is always<lb/>there to do his business ; but how will<lb/>it be here ? By this section we are to<lb/>have an ambulatory Judge, going about<lb/>over three Counties, holding his Courts<lb/>here and there, and I should like to ask<lb/>how are we to get at him if he is wanted?<lb/>How can we get access to him ? How<lb/>can we move for a new trial if he is mov<lb break="no"/>ing about in this way, here to-day and<lb/>gone to-morrow ? I just point out this<lb/>inconvenience, and ask the Attorney<lb/>General how we can get out a summons,<lb/>make an application for a new trial, or do<lb/>any other business that may be required<lb/>when the Judge is constantly moving<lb/>about ? How can we set aside a judg<lb break="no"/>ment by default ? Here is a case in which<lb/>we must be prompt, there is only a cer<lb break="no"/>tain time to act, and how or where shall<lb/>we find the Judge ? If we had one for<lb/>each County, as they have in Canada, he<lb/>would be accessible by the people at all<lb/>


            <cb/>
           
times, and the same thing might be done<lb/>here. Make the salaries less and appoint<lb/>more Judges ; divide the salary now pro<lb break="no"/>posed to be given into three parts and<lb/>give us more Judges, and it will prove<lb/>more advantageous. I suppose the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment won't receive my suggestion,<lb/>but I am sure it can't work with only one<lb/>Judge for three Counties. This is, I<lb/>think, a matter worthy of consideration,<lb/>and must commend itself to the minds of<lb/>hon. members who are engaged in the<lb/>law.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>.—This very ques<lb break="no"/>tion has just been decided by a great<lb/>vote, it involves the principle of the Bill,<lb/>and that has been established. How is<lb/>it now in the Supreme Court ? The<lb/>Judges are scattered round over the cir<lb break="no"/>cuits, and the same objection would apply<lb/>equally in their case. Then if the salaries<lb/>were reduced so as to permit of the ap<lb break="no"/>pointment of three times the number of<lb/>Judges they would have to carry on their<lb/>practice as Barristers. But I do not be<lb break="no"/>lieve a Judge should be a practising law<lb break="no"/>yer ; he should be removed from every<lb/>influence which may hinder him from<lb/>forming a fair and impartial opinion. My<lb/>hon. friend says that in Canada the Judges<lb/>are always to be found at one place ; but<lb/>it is not so, they are always moving about,<lb/>although of course where they have one<lb/>Judge to every County they have not so<lb/>large a circuit to travel over. We can<lb break="no"/>not appoint more, for our means will not<lb/>admit, unless we allow the Judges to<lb/>practice, which I consider very undesir<lb break="no"/>able they should do. The Judges who<lb/>are appointed will be required to reside<lb/>in the District over which they preside,<lb/>and this is all that is required.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName>.—I think the idea of<lb/>the hon. member for Westmorland a very<lb/>good one if it could be carried out, but<lb/>in that case it would be impossible to ob<lb break="no"/>tain the consent of any Barrister of good<lb/>standing to accept the office of Judge, as<lb/>the salary would not be sufficient to sup<lb break="no"/>port him in his position, unless he were<lb/>allowed to practice in the Supreme Court,<lb/>and if he were allowed to do that, I con<lb break="no"/>ceive it would be striking at the very<lb/>fountain of justice, and mix up with the<lb/>toils, anxieties and prejudices of private<lb/>business, that calmness of mind and im<lb break="no"/>partial administration of affairs which<lb/>should characterize the Judge. For this<lb/>reason I am entirely opposed to the re<lb break="no"/>duction of the salaries in the manner sug<lb break="no"/>gested.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CHAN1">Mr. CHANDLER</persName>.—The ideas pro<lb break="no"/>pounded by the hon. member for West<lb break="no"/>morland can, I think, be easily overturn<lb break="no"/>ed. He complains that the Judges will<lb/>be moving about, and thinks that a diffi<lb break="no"/>culty will be experienced in certain cases<lb/>from this fact. But the Judges of the<lb/>Supreme Court are always doing the same<lb/>
          

            <pb n="110" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_110.jpg"/>
           
<fw type="num">110</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw>
          

thing, holding three Courts in the year,<lb/>as in the present case, and over a far<lb/>larger circuit than is contemplated by this<lb/>Bill that the County Court Judges shall<lb/>do ; but I apprehend that in vacation they<lb/>will always be found easily enough, and<lb/>this is all that is required for all practical<lb/>purposes.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—The hon. member does<lb/>not seem quite to understand me. He<lb/>says the Judges of the Supreme Court<lb/>are always moving about ; but there is<lb/>always a resident Judge either in Freder<lb break="no"/>icton or Saint John, and we can send to<lb/>our agent in these places and get what<lb/>we want at any time. But with these<lb/>Judges it will not be so, they will be hold<lb break="no"/>ing a Court here to-day and somewhere<lb/>else to-morrow, and so may not be come-<lb break="yes"/>at-able just when they are wanted. As<lb/>to being able to get at them in vacation,<lb/>the hon. member knows that that would<lb/>be the last occasion on which they would<lb/>be required ; it is in times when prompt<lb/>and swift measures have to be taken that<lb/>the difficulty would be experienced.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOHN1">Mr. JOHNSON</persName>.—It strikes me that<lb/>the greatest difficulty is with regard to<lb/>the appointment of clerks, and believing,<lb/>as I do, that the Clerks of the Peace<lb/>will be able to attend to the duties, with<lb/>a sincere desire to improve the Bill, I<lb/>shall move the following amendment :—<lb/>" Strike out all the words after ' good<lb/>behaviour, ' and insert the following :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" And the Clerks for each Court shall<lb/>be the Clerks of the Peace for the re<lb break="no"/>spective Counties ; and shall not be al<lb break="no"/>lowed to practice in the Court of which<lb/>he is such Clerk."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>.—I sincerely hope<lb/>the hon. member will not press that<lb/>amendment, for if the Clerks of the<lb/>Peace are found to be the best parties to<lb/>fill the office of Clerks to the County<lb/>Courts, the Government may appoint<lb/>them. There may or may not be cases<lb/>where it may be found it would not be<lb/>best to do so, but leave it with the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to do this or not as may be found<lb/>requisite. In some cases the Clerk of<lb/>the Peace may not want it, and then he<lb/>would be compelled to give up his present<lb/>office. I hope the hon. member will<lb/>withdraw his amendment, for even if the<lb/>principle may be the very best that can<lb/>be proposed, by leaving it open the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment are at liberty to adopt it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName>.—I do not think this<lb/>is the right place for this amendment to<lb/>come in ; it would, I think, be better to<lb/>let it follow section five.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName>.—I think there is rea<lb break="no"/>son in the amendment, for the Courts of<lb/>Common Pleas being abolished, the<lb/>Clerks will have all the papers for refer<lb break="no"/>ence in case they are wanted, and in the<lb/>place of the duties and emoluments taken<lb/>
          
            <cb/>
          
from them, we give them others of a more<lb/>extended character.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.—I think this will<lb/>involve an increased expenditure for<lb/>salaries, for if you deprive the Clerk of<lb/>the privilege of practising in these Courts,<lb/>although he may still do so in the Su<lb break="no"/>preme Court, he will require additional<lb/>pay. If you say the Clerk of the Peace<lb/>shall be appointed, he will have to give<lb/>up his practice in the Courts which he is<lb/>now allowed, and if he refuses to do<lb/>that, then he must give up the office of<lb/>Clerk of the Peace, and thus the most<lb/>valuable men, those most qualified to fill<lb/>the office, would not get the appointment,<lb/>from the fact that there will not be suffi<lb break="no"/>cient Court business to pay them for the<lb/>services they will be required to perform<lb/>if they are confined to that alone. I think<lb/>it should be left in the hands of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I think everything goes<lb/>to show that the two offices should be<lb/>combined. The Clerk of the Peace has<lb/>usually a safe for the deposit of his pa<lb break="no"/>pers, and this is another consideration<lb/>why he should be appointed. Now the<lb/>Clerks of the Peace are also the Clerks<lb/>of the Court of Common Pleas in every<lb/>County all over the Province, and if they<lb/>are made Clerks of the County Courts,<lb/>and the business is any way large, they<lb/>will gladly take this office combined with<lb/>the other, but of course a good and effi<lb break="no"/>cient Attorney would not accept it, if he<lb/>is prevented from practice and confined<lb/>to this alone.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOHN1">Mr. JOHNSON</persName>.—I think that instead<lb/>of increasing the expense we shall by this<lb/>arrangement lessen it. We shall get a<lb/>better man if he knows that both offices<lb/>are combined than as though they were<lb/>separate. If the Clerk of these Courts<lb/>is allowed to practice, it gives him a<lb/>most dangerous power, for having all<lb/>the papers in his possession in the various<lb/>causes that come before the Court, he<lb/>would be enabled to use them for the<lb/>furtherance of his own cause. Just think<lb/>of a practising Attorney being allowed to<lb/>scrutinize the records of judgment and<lb/>other papers affecting a case in which he<lb/>was interested. Why, if he were at all<lb/>unscrupulous he would pick out little<lb/>troubles and difficulties and use his<lb/>knowledge for his own purposes, and thus<lb/>litigation would be infinitely increased.<lb/>Besides when it became known that such<lb/>a power lay in the hands of this man,<lb/>people would shun the Court, afraid to<lb/>place their cases in the hands of men who<lb/>were in a position to take advantage of<lb/>them.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName>.—I beg to suggest to<lb/>the Attorney General whether at the pre<lb break="no"/>sent stage it would not be well to report<lb/>progress, with leave to sit again. I have<lb/>a case that stood the order of the day<lb/>
       

            <cb/>
         
for yesterday afternoon, but I gave way<lb/>to allow this Bill to be committed, and I<lb/>should now like to take it up and get it<lb/>out of the way.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>.—As it is now only<lb/>a question of detail, and the principle of<lb/>the Bill is established, I am quite willing<lb/>to report progress if I can get it made<lb/>the order of the day for to-morrow a 11<lb/>o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Speaker having resumed the Chair,<lb/>progress was reported, and the Bill made<lb/>the order of the day for to-morrow morn<lb break="no"/>ing at 11 o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">P.E.I. STEAM CO'S CLAIM.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> moved the House into<lb/>Committee on the Report of the Special<lb/>Committee to whom was referred the<lb/>claim of the Prince Edward Island Steam<lb/>Navigation Company's claim, for services<lb/>of the steamer " Princess of Wales" on<lb/>the North Shore route, in the year<lb/>1865.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LEWI1">Mr. LEWIS</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Report which appeared in the pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings of Monday last was read.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName>.—In order, Mr. Chair<lb break="no"/>man, to bring this matter before the<lb/>Committee in some tangible shape, I beg<lb/>to move the following Resolution :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" <hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, As the opinion of this<lb/>Committee, that the sum of — should<lb/>be paid to the Prince Edward Island<lb/>Steam Navigation Company in full for<lb/>their claim in the matter referred in the<lb/>Report now under consideration. "<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>In order to obtain a thorough under<lb break="no"/>standing of the position of affairs in this<lb/>case, it will be necessary to go into a<lb/>great number of papers and evidence,<lb/>which have already been before the Spe<lb break="no"/>cial Committee. We find that in the<lb/>year 1865 the Government required a<lb/>steamer to run on the North Shore route ;<lb/>that having made their wants known<lb/>they received offers, and among them<lb/>one from the Prince Edward Island Steam<lb/>Navigation Company, which offer men<lb break="no"/>tioned the amount that was to be paid,<lb/>the trips to be made, and the notice<lb/>which would be required in case of dis<lb break="no"/>continuance. Here is their proposal :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" Steamboat Company of Prince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island propose to the Government<lb/>of New Brunswick to run the boat "Prin<lb break="no"/>cess of Wales" one trip a week from<lb/>Shediac to Newcastle, touching at Chat<lb break="no"/>ham and Richibucto, going and coming,<lb/>(weather permitting) for the sum of $3,<lb break="no"/>000 for the season.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>This sum to be in addition to the<lb/>$1,500 a year heretofore paid for carrying<lb/>the mails.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The boat to leave Shediac on Tuesday<lb/>morning for Richibucto and Newcastle,<lb/>and to leave Newcastle on Wednesday<lb/>morning for Shediac.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Should this proposition be accepted,<lb/>the Government of New Brunswick to be<lb/>at liberty to terminate the contract on<lb/>
      
            <pb n="111" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_111.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> <fw type="num">111</fw> 
  
giving two weeks notice of their desire<lb/>to do so.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>In event of the contract being cancelled,<lb/>contractors to be paid for services at the<lb/>rate of $3,000 for the season of six months.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">W. H. POPE, for<lb/>P. E. Island S B. Comy."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>15th May, 1865.<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>You will see by this offer that the<lb/>Company require two weeks notice to<lb/>terminate the contract ; and the first<lb/>point which I shall place before the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee, will be this, Was this proposal<lb/>the basis of negotiation ? The Special<lb/>Committee in their Report have entirely<lb/>ignored this proposition on the part of<lb/>the Company, without giving any reason<lb/>for so doing. They do, indeed, seem to<lb/>admit that the offer had been made,but<lb/>they do not conclude that it was acted<lb/>on. It will be shown here, as it was be<lb break="no"/>fore the Committee to whom the matter<lb/>was referred, that this proposal was<lb/>handed in to the Government, and filed<lb/>in the office of the Provincial Secreatry,<lb/>as shown by an endorsement on the back.<lb/>Then what reasons are there to make this<lb/>Committee think it was acted on or re<lb break="no"/>jected ? Now, if we can find that a new<lb/>contract was made, and yet no new basis<lb/>established, then we must conclude that<lb/>the first proposition was the basis of the<lb/>whole transaction and agreement. The<lb/>agreement we find was made, the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee say the boat was employed, but<lb/>they also say that Mr. Hatheway, as<lb/>agent for the Government, made an ar<lb break="no"/>rangement with another Company ; that<lb/>another boat was to be put upon that<lb/>route, and they therefore infer that no ar<lb break="no"/>rangement had been entered into with<lb/>this Company. They had to go to de<lb break="no"/>tached papers and letters in order to<lb/>bring in a Report unfavorable to this<lb/>claim, and they also had statement of<lb/>Mr. Hatheway against the papers and<lb/>affidavit of Mr. Pope. Mr. Pope was<lb/>acting not in his own behalf, but for<lb/>other persons, some of whom reside in<lb/>Prince Edward Island, and some in this<lb/>Province, (they are scattered about in<lb/>various places) and so was the representa<lb break="no"/>tive of the Company. As such the paper<lb/>he produced to the Company on his re<lb break="no"/>turn would show just what contract he<lb/>had made. And how strange, under such<lb/>circumstances, it would seem to the Com<lb break="no"/>pany, in a few weeks after, that on ac<lb break="no"/>count of some vague telegram, or conver<lb break="no"/>sation, the whole contract was over<lb break="no"/>thrown. The Company relied on the<lb/>contract which had been made ; yet the<lb/>Committee came here, after investigating<lb/>the matter, and tell us that the terms of<lb/>the arrangement had been complied with ;<lb/>and the only testimony they bring in<lb/>support of this statement is that Mr.<lb/>Hatheway told a Mr. Pope something.<lb/>But this was no notice under the contract.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>That distinctly states that two weeks<lb/>notice must be given, and if Mr. Hathe<lb break="no"/>way could, by a mere conversation with<lb/>a brother of Mr. Pope, the agent, destroy<lb/>the contract, in what position would it<lb/>leave the Stockholders ? Unless this<lb/>offer of the Agent to the Government<lb/>can be set aside ; unless it can be shown<lb/>that a new arrangement altogether was<lb/>entered into, then this proposition must<lb/>stand as the basis of the agreement.<lb/>The next piece of testimony which comes<lb/>before us is the evidence of Mr. DesBri<lb break="no"/>say. It is in the form of an affidavit,<lb/>and is as follows :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>PROVINCE OF NEW BRUNSWICK.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Lestock Peach Wilson DesBrisay, of<lb/>Richibucto, in the Province of New<lb/>Brunswick, Esquire, maketh oath and<lb/>saith : That on or about the eighteenth<lb/>day of May, in the year of our Lord<lb/>one thousand eight hundred and sixty-<lb break="yes"/>five, this deponent then being a member<lb/>of the House of Assembly of the said<lb/>Province, was present in the City of<lb/>Fredericton, and that on or about the<lb/>time mentioned William Henry Pope,<lb/>of Prince Edward Island, exhibited to<lb/>deponent a copy of a written proposi<lb break="no"/>tion made by the said William Henry<lb/>Pope on behalf of Prince Edward<lb/>Island Steam Navigation Company to<lb/>run the steamer "Princess of Wales"<lb/>from Shediac to Richibucto and Mira<lb break="no"/>michi, which said proposition was as<lb/>follows :<lb/>
            </p></quote>
            <p>(Here is set out the proposition of the<lb/>Company as given above._<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>And deponent further saith : That the<lb/>said proposition was submitted to the<lb/>Honorable George L. Hatheway, then<lb/>Chief Commissioner of Public Works<lb/>for the said Province, and that this<lb/>deponent had several conversations with<lb/>the said George L. Hatheway and also<lb/>with the Honorable Richard Hutchison<lb/>relative thereto.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>And deponent further saith : That in<lb/>the presence and hearing of deponent,<lb/>the said George L. Hatheway accepted<lb/>the said proposal made by the said<lb/>William Henry Pope, as herein before<lb/>mentioned, and contracted with the said<lb/>Steam Navigation Company in the<lb/>terms thereof.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>And deponent further saith : That at<lb/>the time of making such contract, the<lb/>said George L. Hatheway emphatically<lb/>urged upon the attention of the said<lb/>William Henry Pope that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment reserved to themselves the right<lb/>to terminate such contract by giving a<lb/>fortnight's notice of their desire to do<lb/>so.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>And deponent further saith : That on<lb/>the 19th day of May, 1865, this depo<lb break="no"/>nent received from the said William<lb/>Henry Pope a telegram, dated in the<lb/>City of Saint John on that day, in which<lb/>telegram the said William Henry Pope<lb/>informed deponent to the effect that he<lb/>had reason to believe that the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment proposed to pay the Steam<lb/>Navigation Company $100 a trip for<lb/>the service which the said Company<lb/>had contracted to perform after the rate<lb/>of $3,000 for the season, and also ex<lb break="no"/>pressed his dissatisfaction at the pro<lb break="no"/>
        

            <cb/>
      
posed departure from the terms of the<lb/>contract made with the Commissioner<lb/>of Public Works, as herein before men<lb break="no"/>tioned.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>And deponent lastly saith : That on<lb/>receipt of the telegram so received<lb/>from the said W. H. Pope, he, this de<lb break="no"/>ponent, conferred with the said Richard<lb/>Hutchison relative thereto, who stated<lb/>to deponent his intention to telegraph<lb/>to the said W. H. Pope that the con<lb break="no"/>tract made by him with the said George<lb/>L. Hatheway would be carried out in<lb/>the terms thereof.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">L. P. W. DesBRISAY.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Sworn at Richibucto, in the Province<lb/>of New Brunswick, this 17th day<lb/>of May, 1867, before me,</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">G. PHINNY, J. P.<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>You will find that this affidavit of<lb/>Mr. DesBrisay has been entirely ignor<lb break="no"/>ed by the Committee in their Report.<lb/>Here we have the statement of a man<lb/>who knew all about, and was, as a North<lb/>Shore member of the House interested<lb/>in, the matter. He together with Mr.<lb/>Hutchison and Mr. Hatheway evidently<lb/>decide upon the plan proposed by Mr.<lb/>Pope ; but after Mr. Pope has gone away,<lb/>Mr. Hatheway telegraphs to him to make<lb/>a new arrangement, and Mr. Pope, not<lb/>willing to depart from the proposal he has<lb/>made and which has been accepted, con<lb break="no"/>fers with Mr. Hutchison, the only North<lb/>Shore member of the Government, who<lb/>replies in effect "I'll set all right, and<lb/>telegraph Hatheway all about it." This<lb/>evidence, so strongly confirmatory of the<lb/>acceptance of the proposition made by<lb/>Mr. Pope on behalf of the Company, has<lb/>been, as I have said, entirely passed over<lb/>by the Committee, who have taken the<lb/>statement of Mr. Hatheway, who—rely<lb break="no"/>ing on his memory (and he has had, I<lb/>believe, two severe attacks of illness<lb/>since that time) two years after the cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances have occurred and without<lb/>any papers to which he can refer,—denies<lb/>the statement made by Mr. Pope and<lb/>others.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The next paper is the Affidavit of Mr.<lb/>W. H. Pope, the Agent of the Company,<lb/>and the gentleman who submitted the<lb/>proposition to Mr. Hatheway as Agent<lb/>for the Government. It is as follows :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>PROVINCE OF NEW BRUNSWICK.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">In the matter of the Memorial of the<lb/>President and Directors of the Prince<lb/>Edward Island Steam Navigation<lb/>Company to the House of Assembly.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>William Henry Pope, of Charlottetown,<lb/>in Prince Edward Island, Esquire, maketh<lb/>oath and saith : That he has read two let<lb break="no"/>ters purporting to have been written by the<lb/>Honorable George L. Hatheway to the<lb/>Honorable Abner R. McClelan, Chief<lb/>Commissioner of Public Works, in the<lb/>month of July last past, which said let<lb break="no"/>ters are now, as deponent believes, in the<lb/>possession of the Committee of the House<lb/>of Assembly to which was referred the<lb/>Memorial of the said President and Di [...]</p></quote>
         

            <pb n="122" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-31_Page_122.jpg"/>
        
<fw type="num">122</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> 


            <p>
       <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> remarked that this 
     <lb/>
     question concerning replevin  was well 
     <lb/>
     worthy of their consideration ; there<lb break="no"/>fore he would move that progress be 
     <lb/>
     reported and leave asked to sit again.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      Progress was  then reported and leave 
     <lb/>granted.<lb/>
     
     
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">AMENDMENTS.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p>
     His Hon.  <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">the SPEAKER</persName> called the 
     <lb/>
     attention of the House to the fact that 
     <lb/>
     there was a rule distinctly laid down 
     <lb/>
     in regard to amendments,  which had 
     <lb/>
     been violated in the two last amend<lb break="no"/>ments moved to the second section of 
     <lb/>
     the County Court Bill. An amendment 
     <lb/>
     was moved to the latter clause in the 
     <lb/>
     section which provided that a clerk 
     <lb/>
     should be appointed who should hold 
     <lb/>
     his office during pleasure. A division 
     <lb/>
     took place upon this amendment and it 
     <lb/>
     was lost. After this, another amend<lb break="no"/>ment was moved by the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     from Northumberland (Mr. Kerr) on a 
     <lb/>
     previous part of that section. This was 
     <lb/>
     not according to parliamentary prac<lb break="no"/>tice. He then read an extract from 
     <lb/>
      May's Parliamenhary Practice to prove 
     <lb/>
     that when amendment was made to a 
     <lb/>
     clause in a section, and a division taken 
     <lb/>
     upon it, they could not go back and 
     <lb/>
     move an amendment to a previous 
     <lb/>
     clause in the section.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:JOHN1">Mr. JOHNSON</persName> said if they were to be 
     <lb/>
      governed by the rules in the House of 
     <lb/>
     Commons they would have to take the 
     <lb/>
      question upon the principle of the Bill 
     <lb/>
     before it was committed at all. We had 
     <lb/>
     a rule in our own Province which we 
     <lb/>
     should be  governed by, and that rule was 
     <lb/>
     our own customs. It had been cus<lb break="no"/>tomary to take up amendments one after 
     <lb/>
     another in any section of Bill that mem<lb break="no"/>bers chose to move them. The  rule in 
     <lb/>
     the House of Commons and in Canada  
     <lb/>
     and Nova Scotia was always to take the 
     <lb/>
     question whether they would sustain the  
     <lb/>
     Bill or not upon the second reading, but 
     <lb/>
     in New Brunswick we read the Bill a 
     <lb/>
     second   time and then  go into Committee 
     <lb/>
     and read it section by section. We have 
     <lb/>
     always been governed by our own rules, 
     <lb/>
     and it has always been a rule in this 
     <lb/>
     House for members to move any number 
     <lb/>
     of  amendments to any section or any  
     <lb/>
     clause of a section they thought proper. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">POLLING PLACE.<lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Hon. Mr. CONNELL</persName> moved the House 
     <lb/>
     into  Committee to take into consideration 
     <lb/>
     a Bill to establish an additional Polling  
     <lb/>
     Place in the County of Carleton. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:DOW1">Dr. DOW</persName> in the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:JOHN1">Mr. JOHNSON</persName>  asked what the effect 
     <lb/>
     of this Bill would be upon the elections to 
     <lb/>
     be held for  Ottawa ? The elections are 
     <lb/>
     to be held under the law as it now stands, 
     <lb/>
     and the law   fixes certain Polling Places.  
     <lb/>
     

            <cb/>
          

     If they  established a new  Polling Place, 
     <lb/>
     and votes were  given there, would it not 
     <lb/>
      affect the seat of the member who was 
     <lb/>
     returned for that County ?   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Hon. Mr. CONNELL</persName>.—This  Bill is 
     <lb/>
     very  necessary to the inhabitants of the 
     <lb/>
     district, and to avoid the difficulty men<lb break="no"/>tioned by my  hon. friend I shall add to it 
     <lb/>
     a provision that the Bill shall not take 
     <lb/>
     effect until after the first of January. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Bill was then agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Hon. Mr. CONNELL</persName>  brought in a Bill 
     <lb/>
     to amend an Act  to incorporate the 
     <lb/>
     Woodstock Railway Company. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On motion of <persName ref="pers:MCAD1">Hon.  Mr. McADAM</persName>,  
     <lb/>
     the House in Committee agreed  to a Bill 
     <lb/>
     to authorize the erection of a Sorting 
     <lb/>
     Boom on Eel River, in the Counties of 
     <lb/>
    York and Carleton. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SUTT1">Mr. SUTTON</persName> brought in a Bill to in<lb break="no"/>corporate the Grand Loyal Ribbon So<lb break="no"/>ciety in New Brunswick. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr.  YOUNG</persName> asked the Chief Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner of the Board of Works whether it 
     <lb/>
     was the intention of the Government to 
     <lb/>
     pay the claim of John Lagere, late Super<lb break="no"/>visor, for expenditure on the Roads. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> said there was 
     <lb/>
     a Petition before the Board of Works,  
     <lb/>
      asking that the claim be paid, but part of 
     <lb/>
     the expenditure for  which this claim was 
     <lb/>
     made was not authorized by the Board of 
     <lb/>
     Works, and was unjustifiable in equity. 
     <lb/>
     He had not had time to consider the 
     <lb/>
     matter, and nothing had been decided 
     <lb/>
     upon in regard to it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName> asked the Commissioner 
     <lb/>
     whether he would submit the papers upon 
     <lb/>
     the subject without an address ? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> replied that the 
     <lb/>
     papers would be furnished. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr.  SMITH</persName> said he saw in the news<lb break="no"/>papers that an  official list of Senators had 
     <lb/>
     been published in Canada, and he would 
     <lb/>
    ask the Government whether they still 
     <lb/>persisted in  concealing and keeping back 
     <lb/> from the people the names of the Senators 
     <lb/>appointed, or the names of the Senators 
     <lb/> they recommended to be appointed.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr.  FISHER</persName> said it was not in 
     <lb/>
     his power to give any more information 
     <lb/>
     than he did before. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On motion of <persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName>, the 
     <lb/>
     House went into Committee an a Bill to 
     <lb/>
     provide for the more effectual repair of 
     <lb/>
    Streets,  Bridges and Sidewalks in the 
     <lb/>Lower  Highway District, in the Parish of 
     <lb/>St. Stephen. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     The Bill was  agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Messrs. Smith, Kerr, W. P. Flewelling,   
     <lb/>
     Wetmore and  Fisher were appointed a 
     <lb/>
     Committee to confer with a Committee of  
     <lb/>the Legislative Council, in regard to the<lb/>
    proposed address to   Her  Majesty the 
     <lb/>Queen on the subject of Trade between  
     <lb/>this Province  and the United States of 
     <lb/>America. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The House then adjourned until Mon<lb break="no"/>day morning, at 10 o' clock.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">T. P. D.<lb/>
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2018-05-01, Commented out below as it follows Debate Day --> 


           <!-- <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>MONDAY, June 3rd, 1867.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>SECOND READINGS.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The following Bills were read a second<lb/>time :<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to incorporate the Eastern<lb/>Bank of New Brunswick, in the Coun<lb break="no"/>ty of Westmorland.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill in amendment of the Act to<lb/>incorporte the Woodstock Railway<lb/>Company.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to incorporate the Grand Loyal<lb/>Ribbon Society of New Brunswick.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>THIRD READINGS.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The following Bills were read a third<lb/>time :<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to incorporate the Saint John<lb/>Mercantile Marine Assurance Com<lb break="no"/>pany.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to authorize the erection of a<lb/>Sorting Boom on Eel River, in the<lb/>Counties of York and Carleton.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to provide for the more effec<lb break="no"/>tually repairing of the streets, roads<lb/>and bridges of the lower highway dis<lb break="no"/>trict in the Parish of Saint Stephen.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to establish an additional Poll<lb break="no"/>ing Place in the County of Carleton.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>FIRE LOAN BONDS.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—l see by the returns 
     <lb/>
     which have been laid before the House 
     <lb/>
     on the Fire Loan Bonds, that the Solici<lb break="no"/>tor Generel has  compromised with 
     <lb/>
     some of the parties, and that in some 
     <lb/>
     cases  a great reduction has been made. 
     <lb/>
     Now I should like to know by whose 
     <lb/>
     authority this  was done, for I think that 
     <lb/>
     they have   been settled up at a much 
     <lb/>
     greater sacrifice than was required to 
     <lb/>
     be made. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. WILLISTON.—I may say 
     <lb/>
     that each case was submitted to Coun<lb break="no"/>cil, and an order of Council was made 
     <lb/>
     out on each one. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr.  SMITH</persName>.— I should certainly like 
     <lb/>to see them.<lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. WILLISTON.—I will bring 
     <lb/>them down to-morrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr.  SMITH</persName>.— I now give notice that 
     <lb/>
     I shall, at as early a day as the rules 
     <lb/>
     will permit, move the House into Com<lb break="no"/>mittee upon these Papers and Returns. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>BILL TO PREVENT DUAL REPRESENTATION.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. WILLISTON moved the 
     <lb/>House into Committee on a Bill relat<lb break="no"/>ing to Members of the House of Assem<lb break="no"/>bly.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName> in the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. WILLISTON.—This Bill 
     <lb/>
      provides two principles ; first,  that no 
     <lb/>
     person who is returned as a member 
     <lb/>
     for the House of Commons of Canada 
     <lb/>
     can sit or vote in this House ; and se<lb break="no"/>condly, that any person who may now 
     <lb/>
     occupy a seat in the  Legislative Coun- 
     <lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>-->
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>