<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-06-21"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-06-21">21 June 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="5" to="7"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-21_Page_005.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-21_Page_006.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-21_Page_007.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-21_Page_005">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-21_Page_005.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-21_Page_006">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-21_Page_006.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-21_Page_007">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-21_Page_007.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="5" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-21_Page_005.jpg"/>

<fw type="num">5</fw>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY.</head>


            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     FREDERICTON, JUNE 21st, 1866. 
     <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>
     This being the day appointed by Pro<lb break="no"/>clamation for the meeting of the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture, at 9 A. M. the clerk called the House<lb/>together and announced that His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency having dissolved the late House,<lb/>and warrants having been issued for a<lb/>new election, the following members had<lb/>been returned as representatives of the<lb/>people in the House of Assembly, viz :—</p>

<p>For ALBERT COUNTY—Messrs. A. R.<lb/>McClelan and J. Lewis.<lb/>CARLETON COUNTY—Messrs. C. Connell,<lb/>and W. LINDSAY.<lb/>CHARLOTTE COUNTY — Messrs. J. Mc<lb break="no"/>Adam, J. G. Stevens, J. Chandler, and<lb/>F. Hibbard.<lb/>GLOUCESTER COUNTY—Messrs. R. Young,<lb/>and J. Meehan.<lb/>KING'S COUNTY—Messrs. W. P. Flew<lb break="no"/>elling, John Flewwelling, and G.<lb/>Ryan.<lb/>KENT COUNTY—Messrs. W. S. Caie, and<lb/>Owen McInerney.<lb/>NORTHUMBERLAND COUNTY—Messrs. J.<lb/>M. Johnson, Edward Williston, George<lb/>Kerr, and R. Sutton.<lb/>QUEEN'S COUNTY—Messrs. J. Ferris,<lb/>and R. T. Babbit.<lb/>RESTIGOUCHE COUNTY—Messrs. J. Mc<lb break="no"/>Millan, and A. C. DesBrisay.<lb/>SAINT JOHN COUNTY—Messrs. C. Skin<lb break="no"/>ner, J. H. Gray, J. Quinton, and R.<lb/>D. Wilmot.<lb/>SAINT JOHN CITY—Messrs. S. L. Tilley,<lb/>and A. R. Wetmore.<lb/>SUNBURY COUNTY—Messrs. W. E. Per<lb break="no"/>ley, and J. Glazier.<lb/>WESTMORLAND COUNTY—Messrs. A. J.<lb/>Smith, R.. Botsford, A. McQueen, and<lb/>A. Landry<lb/>VICTORIA COUNTY—Messrs. B. Beveridge,<lb/>and Vital Herbert,<lb/>YORK COUNTY—Messrs. H. Dow, C.<lb/>Fisher, J. A. Beckwith, and A. Thomp<lb break="no"/>son.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Under a Commission appointed by His 
     <lb/>Excellency the Lieut. Governor, the<lb/>oaths were administered to those members<lb/>present by His Honor Mr. Justice Wil<lb break="no"/>mot.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     At 10 o'clock His Excellency having 
     <lb/>come down to the Legislative Council<lb/>Chamber commanded the attendance of<lb/>the House of Assembly, when he stated<lb/>that he was not pleased to tell them why<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
       

     they had been called together until they 
     <lb/>had elected a Speaker. Having done<lb/>this he would meet them again at 4<lb/>o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The House then returned to the Lower 
     <lb/>Chamber, when on motion of the Hon. S.<lb/>L. Tilley they separated till 12 o'clock,<lb/>then to meet and appoint a speaker.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     At 12 o'clock the House again met and 
     <lb/>on nomination of the Hon. J. M. John<lb break="no"/>son seconded by Mr. Ferris, the Hon. J.<lb/>H. Gray was chosen to fill the Speaker's<lb/>chair by acclamation.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     At 4 o'clock P. M. His Excellency being 
     <lb/>seated on the throne in the Legislative<lb/>Council Chamber, and having commanded<lb/>the attendance of the House of Assembly,<lb/>opened the Session with the following<lb/>
            </p>
   

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:centre">
     SPEECH : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">" Hon. Gentlemen of the Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cil,</hi><lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">" Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the<lb/>House of Assembly,</hi><lb/>
            </p>

            <p>" The Address of the Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cil to Her Majesty the Queen, on the<lb/>subject of the Union of the British North<lb/>American Provinces, agreed to during<lb/>the late Session, was duly transmitted by<lb/>me to England to be laid at the Foot of<lb/>the Throne, and I am commanded to in<lb break="no"/>form you that Her Majesty has been<lb/>pleased to receive the same very gra<lb break="no"/>ciously.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

    

            <p>
     " The adoption and the reception by 
     <lb/>me for transmission to Her Majesty of<lb/>this Address, led to events which render<lb break="no"/>ed it in my opinion expedient to dissolve<lb/>the then existing General Assembly. I<lb/>have now much satisfaction in resorting<lb/>to your assistance and co-operation at<lb/>the earliest possible moment ; although I<lb/>regret that it should be necessary to call<lb/>you together at a period of the year<lb/>which must, I fear, render your assem<lb break="no"/>bling a matter of much personal incon<lb break="no"/>venience to some of you.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" Her Majesty's Government have al<lb break="no"/>ready expressed their strong and deliber<lb break="no"/>ate opinion, that the union of the British<lb/>North American Provinces under one<lb/>Government is an object much to be de<lb break="no"/>sired. The Legislatures of Canada and of<lb/>Nova Scotia have formed the same judg<lb break="no"/>ment ; and you will now shortly be invit<lb break="no"/>ed to express your concurrence with or<lb/>dissent from the view taken of this great<lb/>question by those provinces.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" You will have learnt with satisfaction<lb/>that the mad attempt of a band of Fe<lb break="no"/>nian conspirators to invade the neighbor<lb break="no"/>ing Province of Canada has met with sig<lb break="no"/>nal and merited failure. You will have<lb/>rejoiced to perceive that the people of the<lb/>British American Provinces are in every<lb/>quarter alike firmly resolved to resist and<lb/>to repel any attack on Her Majesty's au<lb break="no"/>thority and dominion ; and you will, I am<lb/>confident, deeply lament the loss of those<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
        

     brave men who have fallen in the dis<lb break="no"/>charge of that sacred duty.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" Information having reached me,<lb/>which left no room for doubt, that an in<lb break="no"/>vasion of this Province by a considerable<lb/>band of armed and well-organized ma<lb break="no"/>rauders was seriously contemplated, I lost<lb/>no timein taking such measures, in conjunc<lb break="no"/>tion with Vice-Admiral Sir James Hope and<lb/>Major General Doyle, as appeared to me<lb/>necessary to meet the emergency. These<lb/>measures, I rejoice to say, were perfectly<lb/>successful, and the contemplated attack,<lb/>which was at one time imminent, was<lb/>abandoned as an hopeless enterprise.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" You will, I doubt not, concur with me<lb/>in the expression of gratitude for the<lb/>promptitude with which the aid of Her<lb/>Majesty's Naval and Military Force was<lb/>rendered on that occasion, and the mag<lb break="no"/>nitude of the scale on which it was afford<lb break="no"/>ed. Whilst, however, all immediate dan<lb break="no"/>ger of an attack on the Frontier of New<lb/>Brunswick appears to have terminated,<lb/>it is requisite that a strict vigilance<lb/>should still be exercised with regard to<lb/>those who may endeavour to revive such<lb/>projects, or seek to excite dissatisfaction<lb/>within the Province. It will be for yon<lb/>to consider whether, under such circum<lb break="no"/>stances, precautions similar to those<lb/>which have been adopted by the Imperial<lb/>Parliament and by that of Canada should<lb/>for a limited period receive your sanc<lb break="no"/>tion.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     " It appeared to me expedient, while 
     <lb/>the Frontier was menaced with invasion,<lb/>to call into active service a considerable<lb/>force of the Provincial Militia. I have<lb/>to express my entire satisfaction with<lb/>their conduct whilst under arms, and I<lb/>rejoice to be enabled to believe that the<lb/>efforts which, for the last five years, I<lb/>have unremittingly made to effect im<lb break="no"/>provements in the condition and effi<lb break="no"/>ciency of that Force have not proved<lb/>wholy useless.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     " It will be for you to consider whether 
     <lb/>the termination of the provisions of the<lb/>Reciprocity Treaty with the United States<lb/>of America, will render necessary any<lb/>considerable alteration or modification of<lb/>the Revenue Laws of this Province.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     " I trust that an arrangement may ere 
     <lb/>long be again concluded which will se<lb break="no"/>cure, both to the United States and the<lb/>British Provinces, the mutual benefits<lb/>which are likely to ensue from free com<lb break="no"/>mercial intercourse between the two<lb/>countries on a just and satisfactory basis.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">" Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the 
     <lb/>House of Assembly,</hi><lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" The employment for a considerable<lb/>period of an armed force upon the fron<lb break="no"/>tier has rendered necessary an unusual<lb/>expenditure for military service ; but I<lb/>am happy to be able to inform you, that<lb/>there is every prospect that the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture of the year will, notwithstanding<lb/>this unlooked for outlay, be covered by<lb/>the Revenue received.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     " The Accounts of the past and Esti<lb break="no"/>mates of the Expenditure for the current<lb/>year will immediately be laid before you .<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-21_Page_006.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="num">6</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  
 

            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">" Honorable Gentlemen of the Legislative 
     <lb/>Council,</hi><lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">" Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the, 
     <lb/>House of Assembly,</hi><lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     " The question which you are now 
     <lb/>
     called together specially to consider is one 
     <lb/>
    of the most momentous ever submitted to 
     <lb/>a Colonial Legislature.  Your delibera<lb break="no"/>tions will, I doubt not, be undertaken 
     <lb/>with a due sense of the importance of the 
     <lb/>interests they involve, and the solemn <choice><sic>re<lb break="no"/>sponsibilies</sic><corr>responsibilities</corr></choice> which by your decision you 
     <lb/>incur, and will, I trust, be conducted with 
     <lb/>a sole view to the interests of the commu<lb break="no"/>nity at large. That the determination at 
     <lb/>which you arrive may be one calculated 
     <lb/>to promote the welfare and happiness, 
     <lb/>not of this Province only, but one all Her 
     <lb/>Majesty's subjects throughout the whole 
     <lb/>extent of the wide spread dominions of 
     <lb/>the Queen on this Continent, is my ear<lb break="no"/>nest hope and prayer." 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
    

            <p>
     The members of the House of Assem<lb break="no"/>bly having returned to the Lower House. 
     <lb/>
     His Honor the Speaker read the opening 
     <lb/>
     Speech. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Leave was granted to bring in certain 
     <lb/>
     Bills. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>. then moved the following 
     <lb/>
     Address in Reply to His Excellcency's 
     <lb/>
     Speech, which was seconded by Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Beveridge.  </p>

<div type="section"> 
   

<head rendition="simple:centre">PROPOSED ADDRESS IN ANSWER TO HIS<lb/>EXCELLENCY'S SPEECH</head>
     
   
   
            <p>
     To <hi rendition="simple:italic">His Excellency The Hon.</hi> Arthur 
     <lb/>
     Hamilton Gordon, C. M. G.. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut. 
     <lb/>
       Governor and Commander in Chief of 
     <lb/>
     the Province of New Brunswick. &amp;c, &amp;c.</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     THE HUMBLE ADDRESS OF THE HOUSE OF 
     <lb/>
     ASSEMBLY.  
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">May it please Your Excellency,</hi> 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     1. We, Her Majesty's faithful subjects. 
     <lb/>
     the Commons of New Brunswick, thank 
     <lb/>
     Your  for your Speech at the 
     <lb/>
     opening of the present Session.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     2.  We learn with pleasure that Her 
     <lb/>
     Majesty the Queen graciously received 
     <lb/>
     the Address of the Legislative Council. 
     <lb/>
     on the subject of the Union of the British 
     <lb/>
     North American Provinces. transmitted to 
     <lb/>
    England by Your Excellency. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     3. We agree with Your Excellency that 
     <lb/>
     the adoption and reception by Your Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency, for transmission to Her Majesty 
     <lb/>
     of this Address on the subject of the 
     <lb/>
    Union. led to events which rendered it 
     <lb/>expedient to dissolve the late General 
     <lb/>Assembly, and we believe that the Consti<lb break="no"/>tuencies of the Province have justified the 
     <lb/>course adopted by Your Excellency. 
     <lb/>.Although it is an inconvenient season of the 
     <lb/>year for the discharge of Legislative 
     <lb/>duties, we  will cheerfully co-operate with 
     <lb/>Your Excellency in the transaction of such 
     <lb/>  business and the perfecting of such mea<lb break="no"/>sures as the public interest demands. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     4. We know that Her Majesty's Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment have expressed a strong and 
     <lb/>
     deliberate opinion that the union of the 
     <lb/>
     British North American Provinces is an 
     <lb/>
     object  much to be desired, and that the 
     <lb/>
     Legislature of Canada and of Nova Scotia 
     <lb/>
     concur in this view, and Your Excellency 
     <lb/>
     may rely with confidence on our cordial 
     <lb/>
     co-operation in any measure which may 
     <lb/>
     be proposed to secure that object. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     5.  We learn with much satisfaction that 
     <lb/>
    the Fenian conspirators have met with 
     <lb/>signal and merited failure in their wicked 
     <lb/>and mad attempt to invade the neighbor<lb break="no"/>
           

            <cb/>
          
ing Province of Canada. We feel assured 
     <lb/>
     that the people of British North America 
     <lb/>
     are everywhere resolved to resist every 
     <lb/>
     attempt upon Her Majesty's authority and 
     <lb/>
     dominion, and they equally lament with 
     <lb/>
     you the loss of those brave men of Cana<lb break="no"/>da who have fallen in the discharge of 
     <lb/>
     their sacred duty.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     6. We thank Your Excellency for 
     <lb/>
     taking  in conjunction with Vice-Admiral 
     <lb/>
     Sir James  Hopee, and Major General 
     <lb/>
     Doyle, the necessary measures to secure 
     <lb/>
     the people of the Province from the effect 
     <lb/>
     of the invasion of an armed body of ma<lb break="no"/>rauders ; and we are gratified to learn that 
     <lb/>
     the measures adopted were perfectly suc<lb break="no"/>cessful, and that the contemplated attack, 
     <lb/>
     which was at one time imminent, was 
     <lb/>
     abandoned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
       7. We unite with Your Excellency in 
     <lb/>
     the expression of gratitude for the 
     <lb/>
     promptness with which the aid of Her 
     <lb/>
    Majesty's Naval and Military Forces was 
     <lb/>then rendered, and the magnitude of the 
     <lb/>scale on which it was afforded. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
    

            <p>
     8. We agree with Your Excellency in 
     <lb/>
     the conviction that, although all imme<lb break="no"/>diate danger of  an attack has passed 
     <lb/>
     away, necessary precautionary measures 
     <lb/>
     shouldbe adopted and strict vigilance ob<lb break="no"/>served with regard to those who may en<lb break="no"/>deavour to revive projects of invasion or 
     <lb/>
     excite disaffection in the Province, and we 
     <lb/>
     will consider whether the precautionary 
     <lb/>
     measures adopted by the Imperial and 
     <lb/>
     Canadian Parliaments, are not required in 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick in the present emergency. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     9. We were fully prepared to learn that. 
     <lb/>
     the conduct of the Militia Force called 
     <lb/>
     out by Your Excellencv whilst the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince was menaced with invasion, met 
     <lb/>with Your Excellency's approbation, and 
     <lb/>we rejoice that the efforts which have 
     <lb/>been made to improve that branch of the 
     <lb/>public service were attended with advan<lb break="no"/>tage.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     10. We will consider whether the ter<lb break="no"/>mination of the Reciprocity Treaty with 
     <lb/>
     the United States of America. will render 
     <lb/>
     necessary any considerable alteration or 
     <lb/>
     modification of the "Revenue Laws of the 
     <lb/>
     Province; and we unite with Your Excel<lb break="no"/>lency in expressing the hope that ere long  
     <lb/>
     some arrangement may be 'again conclud- l 
     <lb/>
     ed which will secure to both the United 
     <lb/>
     States and the British Provinces, the 
     <lb/>
     mutual benefits which would result from 
     <lb/>
     the establishment of a reciprocal trade on 
     <lb/>
     equitable terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     11 . We rejoice to be informed that the 
     <lb/>
     expenditure of this year will be covered 
     <lb/>
     by the Receipts, notwithstanding the un<lb break="no"/>looked for outlay, occasioned by the em<lb break="no"/>ployment for a considerable period, of an 
     <lb/>
     armed force upon the Frontier. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     12. We thank Your Excellency for 
     <lb/>
     having directed the Accounts of the Re<lb break="no"/>ceipts and Expenditure of the current 
     <lb/>
     year, to be laid before us. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     13. We agree with Your Excellency in 
     <lb/>
     the opinion that the question of the Union 
     <lb/>
     of the British North American Provinces, 
     <lb/>
     upon which the people of New Brunswick 
     <lb/>
     have recently expressed so strong an 
     <lb/>
     opinion, and which Your Excellency has 
     <lb/>
     called us together to consider, is the most 
     <lb/>
     momentous ever submitted to a Colonial 
     <lb/>
     Legislature. We shall approach the con<lb break="no"/>sideration .of the question with a due 
     <lb/>
     sense of the importance of the issues in<lb break="no"/>volved and the solemn responsibility de<lb break="no"/>volving upon us as Representatives of a 
     <lb/>
     free people. Our deliberations shall be 
     <lb/>
     conducted with a single view to the pro<lb break="no"/>motion of their interests; and we fervent<lb break="no"/>ly pray that our determination may be 
     <lb/>
        

            <cb/>
          

     calculated to promote the welfare and 
     <lb/>
     happiness of all Her Majesty's subjects in 
     <lb/>
     the wide-spread dominion of the Queen 
     <lb/>
     on this Continent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     His Honor, the Speaker informed the 
     <lb/>
     House of the death of the Hon. William 
     <lb/>
     Black, late President of the Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Council, and that his funeral would take 
     <lb/>
     place to-morrow (Friday) at 4 o'clock P.M.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On motion of <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. Fisher</persName> it was 
     <lb/>
    resolved that the House show their re<lb break="no"/>spect for the memory of the Hon. Wm  
     <lb/>Black, late President of the Legislative 
     <lb/>Council, by attending the funeral in a 
     <lb/>body and by wearing a badge of mourn<lb break="no"/>ing during the Session, and that at the 
     <lb/>close of the present day's business the 
     <lb/>House adjourn over till Saturday morn<lb break="no"/>ing at 10 o'clock. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Resolutions were passed relating to the  
     <lb/>
    Rules of the House and appointment of 
     <lb/>Committees. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CHAN1">Mr. CHANDLER</persName> moved that the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing petition be received and lie on the 
     <lb/>
     table. 
     <lb/>
            </p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">

            <p>
     " To His Excellency the Honorable 
     <lb/>
     ARTHUR HAMILTON GORDON, C. M. G.. 
     <lb/>
     Lieutenant Governor of the Province of 
     <lb/>
     New Brunswick, &amp;c. &amp;c. &amp;c. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     And to the Honorable the Legislature in 
     <lb/>
     Session assembled— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The humble Petition and Protect of 
     <lb/>
     John W. Cudlip of the City of Saint John, 
     <lb/>
     Esquire.  
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>RESPECTFULLY SHEWETH -<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>That the Honorable John H. Gray now 
     <lb/>
     nominally elected Speaker of the House 
     <lb/>
     of Assembly of New Brunswick is a mem<lb break="no"/>ber against whose return is a Protest for 
     <lb/>
     Bribery and Corruption, and against 
     <lb/>
     whose return a Petition will be presented 
     <lb/>
     to the House of Assembly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Petitioner hereby Protests against 
     <lb/>
     the nomination. election, presentation in 
     <lb/>
     the Upper Branch of the Legislature to 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency or otherwise, of the said 
     <lb/>
     John H. Gray as Speaker or properly and 
     <lb/>
     duly qualified elected Speaker of the 
     <lb/>
     House of Assembly of New Brunswick. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Your Petitoner prays that this Peti<lb break="no"/>tion may be considered according to 
     <lb/>
     Law.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p rendition="simple:right">
     John W. CUDLIP, 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     By his Attorney John  W. Fraser, 
     <lb/>
     Dated 2lst June 1866. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> opposed the recep<lb break="no"/>tion of the petition, as it was an insult to 
     <lb/>
     the intelligence of the House to protest 
     <lb/>
     against an appointmen tjust made by the 
     <lb/>
     unanimous action of the members. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon Mr. JOHNSON did not agree with 
     <lb/>
     his hon. friend, and thought it the right of 
     <lb/>
     every man to be heard when his petition 
     <lb/>
     came in regular form and was couched in 
     <lb/>
     respectful language. Although he was 
     <lb/>
     opposed to any action being taken in the 
     <lb/>
     matter, as he presumed the whole House 
     <lb/>
     was, yet he should support the motion to 
     <lb/>
     receive the petition and lay it on the ta<lb break="no"/>ble. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:STEV1">MR. STEVENS</persName> thought it was an in<lb break="no"/>sult to the House  to state that the gen<lb break="no"/>tleman, whom they had only just elected 
     <lb/>
     to fill the Speaker Chair, was but " nom<lb break="no"/>inally" elected. Was the appointment 
     <lb/>
         

            <pb n="7" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-21_Page_007.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">7</fw> 
 

     merely " nominal," or was it substan<lb break="no"/>tial ? He should oppose its reception. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">HON. MR. WILMOT</persName> would ask the 
     <lb/>hon. member for Charlotte, who had read<lb/>
     the petition (Mr. Chandler), if Mr. Cud<lb break="no"/>lip was in Fredericton, that he so soon 
     <lb/>
     knew of the appointment which had been 
     <lb/>
     made. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:JOHN1">MR. JOHNSON</persName> replied that he was 
     <lb/>
     not, but was represented by his attorney, 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Fraser. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">HON. MR. FISHER</persName> said although he 
     <lb/>was opposed to receiving any petition,<lb/>yet this was informal, inasmuch as it<lb/>was addressed not to the House of<lb/>Assembly, against whose action the pro<lb break="no"/>test was entered, but to His Excellency<lb/>the Lieutenant Governor and the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature. He did not see how, under these<lb/>circumstances, the House could take cog<lb break="no"/>nizance of the matter.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">MR. STEVENS</persName> explained that the peti<lb break="no"/>tion was not against the return of Mr. Gray<lb/>as a member of the House, but against his<lb/>appointment as Speaker, a matter with<lb/>which the petitioner had nothing to do,<lb/>and for which there is not law at all appli<lb break="no"/>cable.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:JOHN1">MR. JOHNSON</persName> said if the petition 
     <lb/>
     was refused it would not appear on the 
     <lb/>
     journals, and its folly might not be known, 
     <lb/>
     whilst the reference to it which must ne<lb break="no"/>cessarily be made might lead some to im<lb break="no"/>agine that there was something in it the 
     <lb/>
     member of the House did not wish to 
     <lb/>
     come to light. Having laid it on the ta<lb break="no"/>ble, they could let it lay there, or throw 
     <lb/>
     it under, as they saw proper, but the 
     <lb/>
     right of petition was sacred and should 
     <lb/>
     not be refused. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The petition was then received and 
     <lb/>
     laid on the table. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On motion of <persName ref="pers:KERR1">MR. KERR</persName> it was re<lb break="no"/>solved to go into consideration of the 
     <lb/>
     Address in Reply to the Speech on Sat<lb break="no"/>urday morning, immediately after the 
     <lb/>
     reading of the Journals. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On motion of <persName ref="pers:KERR1">MR. KERR</persName> it was or<lb break="no"/>dered that 200 copies each of the Ad<lb break="no"/>dress and Reply be printed for the use of 
     <lb/>
     the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. MR. TILLEY</persName> informed the House 
     <lb/>
     that as there was no Committee to report 
     <lb/>
     on the Debates, he was prepared to state 
     <lb/>
     that Messrs. John March and T. P. Dix<lb break="no"/>on were present, and prepared to report 
     <lb/>the proceedings of the House for the<lb/>sum of $150 each for a session of 20<lb/>
    days, and <hi rendition="simple:italic">pro rata</hi> afterwards ; and that 
     <lb/>Mr. G. W. Day was also prepared to print 
     <lb/>the Debates on the same terms as last Ses<lb break="no"/>sion, and he would therefore move that 
     <lb/>these tenders be accepted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The Resolution was adopted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On motion it was ordered that 7000 
     <lb/>
      copies of the debates be printed for gene<lb break="no"/>ral distribution. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     On motion it was ordered that 2000 co<lb break="no"/>pies of the Journels be printed for gene<lb break="no"/>ral circulation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <cb/>
            <p>
     The House then adjourned till Satur<lb break="no"/>day evening at 10 o'clock. 
            </p>

<p rendition="simple:right">
     J.  M. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<!-- GL, 2018-03-20, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

           <!-- <p>
     SATURDAY, JUNE 23d, 1866. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     After the Journals were read the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the House who were absent on 
     <lb/>
     Thursday, were sworn in by His Honor 
     <lb/>
     Judge Allan, with the exception of Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smith, who was still absent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>CONCERNING LOCAL BILLS.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     MR. KERR moved the following reso<lb break="no"/>lution:—" That all local bills which by 
     <lb/>
     the Journals of last Session appear to have 
     <lb/>
     been introduced into this House be al<lb break="no"/>lowed to be received this Session without 
     <lb/>
     requiring that such bills should be pub<lb break="no"/>lished in the local papers or read before 
     <lb/>the Grand Jury." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Mn. JOHNSON said this appeared to 
     <lb/>
     be a general invitaiion for local bills to 
     <lb/>
     be presented. It would be the best way 
     <lb/>
     to suspend the rule in each individual 
     <lb/>
     case ; for there should be no local legisla<lb break="no"/>tion at all this Session except in extreme 
     <lb/>
     cases.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     MR KERR said that there were seve<lb break="no"/>ral important local bills to come before 
     <lb/>
     the House, particularly from St. John, 
     <lb/>
     and to let them stand over until next year 
     <lb/>
     would cause great inconvenience. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     MR. CHANDLER thought they should 
     <lb/>
     postpone all the business they could until 
     <lb/>
     a future session, and only legislate upon 
     <lb/>
     such bills as were urgently required. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     MR. CAIE remarked that he had 
     <lb/>
    brought in a bill during the last session of 
     <lb/>the Legislature praying for the division of 
     <lb/>a Parish in the County of Kent. This 
     <lb/>bill had been advertised for four weeks, 
     <lb/>but had not been presented. He wished 
     <lb/>to know whether it would have to be 
     <lb/>again advertised. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     His Honor the SPEAKER said the 
     <lb/>
     rule did not specify that a bill should be 
     <lb/>
     advertised during the four weeks imme<lb break="no"/>diately preceding the meeting of the 
     <lb/>
     House. It would be for the House to 
     <lb/>
     say whether the rule had been complied 
     <lb/>
     with or not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The resolution was then adopted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     RESOLUTION CONCERNING THE DEBATES. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     MR. RYAN moved—"That for the 
     <lb/>
     purpose of giving information of the pro<lb break="no"/>ceedings of the House the number of 
     <lb/>copies of the Debates ordered to be pub<lb break="no"/>lished be increased from 7,000 to 10,000." 
     <lb/>He believed this was the most important 
     <lb/>Session ever held in New Brunswick, as 
     <lb/>measures were to come before them in<lb break="no"/>volving a change in their Constitution. 
     <lb/>The question upon which they were to 
     <lb/>legislate was one in which the people take 
     <lb/>a great interest, and which had moved 
     <lb/>the whole country from its centre to its<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>circumference. As the expense of the<lb/>increased number of debates was so small,<lb/>being only $4.50 per thousand, and the<lb/>importance of the measures to be intro<lb break="no"/>duced was so great it was desirable to<lb/>have this increased number.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The question was then taken, and the  
     <lb/>
     resolution adopted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The order of the day was then moved,  
     <lb/>
     viz :—   
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>PROPOSED ADDRESS IN ANSWER TO HIS<lb/>EXCELLENCY'S SPEECH.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     MR. BOTSFORD said he did not op<lb break="no"/>pose going on with the order of the day, 
     <lb/>
     but he thought it a matter of courtesy 
     <lb/>
     due to the leader of the late Government, 
     <lb/>
     who was unavoidably absent, that the 
     <lb/>
     consideration of the answer to His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency's Speech should be postponed until 
     <lb/>
     Monday, He (Mr. Smith) would be here 
     <lb/>
     to-night. Questions may arise during 
     <lb/>
     the discussion which it would be neces<lb break="no"/>sary for him to answer, therefore, they 
     <lb/>
     should as a matter of courtesy adjourn the 
     <lb/>
     debate until Monday, particularly as it 
     <lb/>
     has been the usual course to take up this 
     <lb/>
     subject on that day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. MR. FISHER said he did not 
     <lb/>
     want to take advantage of any one, he did 
     <lb/>
     not see that any discussion would arise 
     <lb/>
     which would affect the leeder of the late 
     <lb/>
     Government. They should press the 
     <lb/>
     business forward as fast as possible. 
     <lb/>
     This was the third day of the Session, 
     <lb/>
     and in short sessions, the address was 
     <lb/>
     generally taken up on the second or third 
     <lb/>
     day. He wished to give notice of a reso<lb break="no"/>lution on the subject of Union, and 
     <lb/>
     also to give notice (in the absence of the 
     <lb/>
     Provincial Secretary) of supply. The 
     <lb/>
     public business of the country requires 
     <lb/>
     His Excellency to go up the River on 
     <lb/>
     military matters next week ; they there<lb break="no"/>fore could not delay the consideration of 
     <lb/>
    this address. He would put it to the 
     <lb/>House, whether the Government would be 
     <lb/>justified in doing so. He could not con<lb break="no"/>sent to this delay, and he hoped they 
     <lb/>would not be considered uncourteous in 
     <lb/>pressing on the business of the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     MR. KERR said that he observed in 
     <lb/>
     the journals of 1857 that the House met 
     <lb/>
     on Wednesday the 24th of June, attended 
     <lb/>
     to the routine of business, elected a 
     <lb/>
     Speaker, and on the 25th of June at 2 
     <lb/>
     o'clock they presented the address in 
     <lb/>
     answer to the Speech. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The motion was then carried, after 
     <lb/>
     which His Honor the SPEAKER read 
     <lb/>
     part of the proposed address, when— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     MR. BOTSFORD remarked that there 
     <lb/>
     had been a slight alteration in the phrase<lb break="no"/>ology. He did not know by what parlia<lb break="no"/>mentary rule an address was altered after 
     <lb/>
     it had been published and laid upon the 
     <lb/>
     table. If any alterations were necessary, 
     <lb/>
            the members of the House should have 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>