<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1865-05-30"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-05-26">26 May 1865</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

          
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1865</title>.
                    


          <date when="1865"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

       
<biblScope unit="page" from="108" to="111"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
             
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_108.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_109.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_110.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_111.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-22">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-22">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-21">Marked-up people</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
     
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_108">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_108.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_109">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_109.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_110">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_110.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_111">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_111.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            

           <pb n="108" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_108.jpg"/>

<fw type="num">108</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>
 <p>      
Williston
in 1858, and my mind is still <lb/>
unchanged. I am thoroughly in
favor of<lb/>
responsible Government as any man in <lb/>
this country, and it is the ruling principle <lb/>
in my mind ; but I do not see that it at all <lb/>
bears on the placing the members of de<lb break="no"/>partments out of the House. It is more<lb/>
dangerous to the liberties of the people to<lb/>
have those salaried officers in the House,<lb/>
because when a man gets one of those<lb/>
offices he will struggle for life and death<lb/>
to hold it ; he will go round soliciting<lb/>
votes here and there, and resort to many<lb/>
things he otherwise would not, in order<lb/>
that he may not lose his salary. When<lb/>
we have three paid members of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment on the floors of the House, we<lb/>
have as many as we should have. The<lb/>
Attorney General, I think, is the best paid<lb/>
man in the country, as in addition to his<lb/>
salary, his office gives him a status in<lb/>
the profession, while it does not interfere <lb/>
with it, as it does not take the whole of his <lb/>
time ; but it is necessary for his salary to <lb/>
be high to secure the most talented man <lb/>
to fill the office. In regard to the office
<lb/>
of Post Master General, I am prepared to <lb/>
vote for removal of the office, even if there<lb/>
is no saving to be effected by it, for the<lb/>
office is merely local in its character, and<lb/>
is not one of much importance, as is the<lb/>
case in England, where they keep a cor<lb break="no"/>respondence with all parts of the world.<lb/>
I do not think it is necessary to have an<lb/>
inspector appointed, for clerks can often<lb/>
be sent out of the office to inspect the<lb/>
different Post Offices without interfering<lb/>
with the duties of the department. There<lb/>
has been a cry raised that this was pre<lb break="no"/>paratory to a removal of the seat of Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to St. John. I do not think re<lb break="no"/>moving a couple of clerks to St. John will<lb/>
have any influence in moving the seat of<lb/>
Government. If the question of removing<lb/>
it to St. John came up, and I voted against<lb/>
it, I do not think there would be five of<lb/>
my constituents would find fault with me.<lb/>
The resolutions which I have placed be<lb break="no"/>fore the House, will be the means of<lb/>
perpetuating the seat of Government here,<lb/>
because the difficulties in getting to<lb/>
Fredericton will not be so great as they<lb/>
have been. This system of railways will<lb/>
prevent the necessity or desirability of<lb/>
removing the seat of Government. If a<lb/>
city is in a position to go vigorously into<lb/>
manufacturing and trading operations, the<lb/>
accumulation of public offices and idlers<lb/>
will weaken and destroy the business<lb/>
habits of young men, and they will not<lb/>
acquire the habit of application necessary<lb/>
to put them forward in the world.<lb/>
            </p>

         
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WILL1">Mr.
WILLISTON</persName>.—It is unnecessary for<lb/>
me at this stage of the proceeding to say<lb/>
much on this subject ; but I feel bound<lb/>
by the position I have taken in reference<lb/>
to this subject, to say a few words before<lb/>
the vote is taken. You must remember<lb/>
in 1858, after the office of Post Master<lb/>
General became political, I felt bound to<lb/>
bring in a Bill to repeal that Act. I have<lb/>
been Post Master for some years past,<lb/>
and am pretty well acquainted with the<lb/>
routine of duties which he has to perform.<lb/>
I felt satisfied that eight or nine heads of<lb/>
departments in a House of forty-one mem<lb break="no"/>bers were more than was required, and I<lb/>
felt it my duty to do all in my power to<lb/>
bring about some reform. Mr. Howe, hav<lb break="no"/>ing been educated at his father's office,<lb/>
who was a Post Master at Halifax, has a<lb/>
through acquaintance with the duties of<lb/>
the office, and could perform them much<lb/>
more satisfactorily than a person who knows<lb/>
nothing of the duties, but is appointed<lb/>
because his party has come into power.<lb/>
I have been here for seven years fighting<lb/>
against political influence. I thought<lb/>
          
            <cb/> 
           
that the Government had too many politi<lb break="no"/>cal heads on the floors of the House, and<lb/>
I for one was determined that I would do<lb/>
all in my power to lessen the number of<lb/>
them. In 1859, I brought in a Bill to<lb/>
repeal the Act making this office a politi<lb break="no"/>cal one. I found my hon. friend from St.<lb/>
John, (Mr. Cudlip) who was a prominent<lb/>
member of the House, voting with me,<lb/>
although we numbered but ten. It is<lb/>
gratifying to me now to find members who<lb/>
opposed me on that occasion, when en<lb break="no"/>deavouring to effect that wholesome re<lb break="no"/>form, have changed their minds, and are<lb/>
now introducing this as a Government<lb/>
measure. It is a proud satisfaction to all<lb/>
of us who voted on that occasion. to find<lb/>
public opinion so changed that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment now comes forward to effect that<lb/>
change which the exigencies of the case<lb/>
require. I was sorry to hear my hon.<lb/>
friend from Carleton (Mr. Connell) deny<lb/>
a case where he ignored the decision of<lb/>
the Council. The case was the loss of a<lb/>
money letter sent by "Elijah Clark," and<lb/>
the Postmaster General himself, without<lb/>
the advice of his Council, paid that claim.<lb/>
(Mr. Connell.—" I deny the accusation.")<lb/>
He did that without the advice of his<lb/>
Council, and against the advice of his pre<lb break="no"/>decessors. (Mr. Connell —" Bring
for<lb break="no"/>ward your proofs.") I can bring forward<lb/>
the proofs. It has been said that if we<lb/>
abolish the office of Postmaster General,<lb/>
we should have to appoint a Post Office<lb/>
Surveyor to inspect the Post Offices.<lb/>
This is unnecessary, as the work could be<lb/>
done by the head Clerks in the St. John<lb/>
office. The Postmaster General receives<lb/>
£600 a year. besides his travelling expen<lb break="no"/>ses, which amounted last year to $548 ;<lb/>
the public has to pay those travelling ex<lb break="no"/>penses, even when incurred on an elec<lb break="no"/>tioneering tour. I am happy to see the<lb/>
day when the President of the Council,<lb/>
after seeing the necessity of the case, has<lb/>
the correctness to come forward and pro<lb break="no"/>pound a measure of this kind, which I, an<lb/>
humble number of this House, advocated<lb/>
some years ago.<lb/>

            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName>.—I
confess my mind is<lb/>
not made up on the same grounds as the<lb/>
hon. member who last addressed you. I <lb/>
do not think became he entertained an <lb/>
opinion that was wrong, and the Presi<lb break="no"/>dent of the Council now
entertains an <lb/>
opinion that was wrong, that he should keep <lb/>
that opinion. If the arguments, which <lb/>
appear to have borne very heavily upon <lb/>
the mind of the hon. member who last ad<lb break="no"/>dressed you, are sound, then no
political <lb/>
office ought to be sustained. If
the
head <lb/>
Clerk in the office can bear the responsi<lb break="no"/>bility, then abolish the whole of them. <lb/>
There is not a question that has come be<lb break="no"/>fore the Legislature at this time that
has <lb/>
occupied so much of my thoughts
and at<lb break="no"/>tention, and to which I have given so <lb/>
much serious consideration as this sub<lb break="no"/>ject. I stand in an anomalous posi<lb break="no"/>tion ; here is a Government
measure<lb/>
brought down by a Government I
was <lb/>
sent here to sustain—in whom I have con<lb break="no"/>fidence both financially and politically,<lb/>
and whose acts in this House I am pre<lb break="no"/>pared to support so far as I can consis<lb break="no"/>tently with my own responsibility to the<lb/>
people that sent me her. They sent me<lb/>
here to support that Government, or a<lb/>
Governement formed on Anti-Confederate<lb/>
principles. Unfortunately for me. I took<lb/>
a different view from the Government in<lb/>
reference to this question. I was here in<lb/>
1854, when a resolution was introduced<lb/>
by some hon. member of the House, in<lb/>
order to make the Surveyor General's<lb/>
office and the Postmaster General's office<lb/>
political. I then opposed making the<lb/>
  
            <cb/>

 Surveyor
General's office a political one, <lb/>
because I believed that the head of that<lb/>
office ought to be a Surveyor himself, and<lb/>
understand his business, so as to know<lb/>
when his subordinates did right or wrong.<lb/>
Unless we got a political man
on the <lb/>
floors of the House who understood all <lb/>
the operations that belonged to an office
<lb/>
of that kind. I did not think
it right to <lb/>
make it a political office. I
opposed it <lb/>
then, and if there was a question of that <lb/>
kind before the House now, I
would still <lb/>
oppose it ; for I believe the office of poli<lb break="no"/>tical Surveyor General to be
useless. <lb/>
With regard to the Post Master General's <lb/>
office, I say this : If the Government can <lb/>
show that by making the office non-poli<lb break="no"/>tical the country is going to save a great <lb/>
deal of money, that they can save
twelve <lb/>
or fifteen thousand dollars, I am
prepared <lb/>
to go for it, however inimical it may
be <lb/>
to
the interests of my constituents ;
but <lb/>
they have not done it. and cannot do it. <lb/>
(Hon. Mr. Smith. We will save $3.000.) <lb/>
Have they shown it? They have not, <lb/>
and cannot show it. They cannot get <lb/>
along without more clerks, and
they will <lb/>
have to increase the salaries of the offi<lb break="no"/>cers they now have on account of the in<lb break="no"/>creased labour and increased responsibi<lb break="no"/>lity. With regard to my own private <lb/>
views about all these officers being on the <lb/>
floors of the House, I think in a House of <lb/>
only forty-one members, the fewer <lb/>
political officers on the floors
of
the <lb/>
House the better for the country ; but that <lb/>
is not the reason why I oppose the Bill. <lb/>
I oppose it because the Government do <lb/>
not show that it is going to
benefit the <lb/>
country by saving any money. Another <lb/>
ground is, because by late
arrangements <lb/>
the Post Office Department has
almost <lb/>
become a banking institution. I saw an <lb/>
account that an increase of $24,605
in <lb/>
money orders over six
corresponding <lb/>
months of last year, had passed
through <lb/>
the Post Office since the money order <lb/>
system had been introduced by the late
<lb/>
Government. Now I ask it this House <lb/>
prepared to put this into the hands of <lb/>
irresponsible men ? If the
Government <lb/>
appoint a man to a situation, and that
<lb/>
man does wrong, I hold them responsible <lb/>
for his acts. If they choose to make an <lb/>
office non-political that is political, and <lb/>
put a man in that office, I hold that, ac<lb break="no"/>cording to true, sound political principles, <lb/>
the Government is answerable for the <lb/>
acts of that man if he has done wrong ;
<lb/>
otherwise, let that man be a political <lb/>
officer, and alone be responsible
for his <lb/>
own acts when on the floors of the House.
<lb/>
It is perfectly absurd to talk about Re<lb break="no"/>sponsible Government, if we say the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment can appoint a man to an
office <lb/>
where such a large amount of money is <lb/>
at stake, and that man becomes
a default<lb break="no"/>er, that the Government is not
responsible. <lb/>
There is no necessity for abolishing this <lb/>
office, for the Government cannot show <lb/>
that there will be any saving in money to <lb/>
this Province to justify them in
throwing <lb/>
to the winds an office that is so much <lb/>
needed at present, when there is
such an <lb/>
amount of money passing through the <lb/>
Province. You allow every man in
this <lb/>
country, Nova Scotia, Canada and Great <lb/>
Britain to issue money orders, and give <lb/>
them the guarantee that they have got
the <lb/>
Government responsible, and where is it <lb/>
when the head of the department is a
<lb/>
non-political officer? If you do what is <lb/>
right now you will abolish your money<lb/>
orders, unless you tell the people that<lb/>
they issue those money
orders under a <lb/>
man who is not responsible. [ <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. Smith</persName>. <lb/>
—There
is no political office of this kind
<lb/>
in Nova
Scotia.]
We have nothing to <lb/>
            

            <pb n="109" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_109.jpg"/>

 <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">109</fw>
     
do with Nova Scotia or Canada ; we will <lb/>
act for ourselves, and in our acts we <lb/>
should show we are willing to keep public <lb/>
faith with those abroad as well
as with <lb/>
those at home. I ask the members
of the <lb/>
House how they can—with the issue of <lb/>
these money orders—sustain abroad the <lb/>
integrity they ought to sustain in regard <lb/>
to them ? They cannot. I have
express<lb break="no"/>ed my views, and I must confess, if they
<lb/>
had established a new dynasty, a
new re<lb break="no"/>gime, propounded a new system of
Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, they might have adopted
a dif<lb break="no"/>ferent system from what they have now ; <lb/>
but when they have a system of Respon<lb break="no"/>sible Government in operation, whether it <lb/>
is for weal or woe, we are bound to carry <lb/>
out that principle of responsibility
in all <lb/>
our actions. It is something extraordinary <lb/>
if thirty-six members are afraid of some <lb/>
three or four Generals. I am not afraid <lb/>
of them, and I doubt whether any
mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the House is. If they bring for<lb break="no"/>ward any measure that the other members <lb/>
of the House feels is inimical to the in<lb break="no"/>terests of the country, they cannot get
it <lb/>
to pass with all their acuteness and
gen<lb break="no"/>eralship, even if they had a majority of <lb/>
one. If we had truth and justice
on our <lb/>
side, I should feel that " he is thrice <lb/>
armed whose quarrel is just."
I do not <lb/>
care how many Generals there are
on the<lb/>
floors of the House ; if the
principles of-<lb break="yes"/>
responsible and departmental Government <lb/>
are true, there are no offices
but what the <lb/>
head officer should be a political one. <lb/>
These are the political views I entertain <lb/>
in regard to responsible and departmental <lb/>
Government. So long as I entertain <lb/>
these views, I cannot vote for a Bill that <lb/>
will place the head of so
important a de<lb break="no"/>partment as the Post Office where he <lb/>
cannot be called to account. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>.—There was a very grave <lb/>
reflection made upon me by two
hon. <lb/>
members of this House.
I expected, from <lb/>
the standing which those hon.
members <lb/>
have in this House that they
would have <lb/>
understood the usage of the House.
and<lb/>
when they made a statement
respect<lb break="no"/>ing the character of a late head of a de<lb break="no"/>partment, they would have been
prepared <lb/>
to have proved it. I challenge them to <lb/>
bring forward their proof of the
statements <lb/>
they have made. I wish to show to the <lb/>
country the position they occupy by the <lb/>
course they took with reference
to my <lb/>
position while head of a department.
If <lb/>
the office had not been here, but had been <lb/>
kept at the City of St. John, I would not <lb/>
have got an important missive from the <lb/>
office, and the just indignation of the <lb/>
House and country would have been <lb/>
poured upon my head. Happily for
me I <lb/>
am in a position to show to the House <lb/>
and country that those statements are not <lb/>
founded in truth, and have no foundation <lb/>
whatever. In reference to Elijah Clark.,<lb/>
it is true there was an investigation into
<lb/>
this loss of a letter. It was investigated
<lb/>
by Mr. Johnson, and I also investigated <lb/>
the matter, and I found the direction of <lb/>
Elijah Clark was to send it by steamer <lb/>
from St. John ; instead of that
it was <lb/>
sent by the way of Calais,
in the United <lb/>
States. The department having sent the <lb/>
letter contrary to the direction. I believed <lb/>
the money ought to be paid, and
I re<lb break="no"/>ported these facts without taking
any <lb/>
action in the matter. I was not present
<lb/>
during the sitting of the last
Legislature<lb/>
when these charges were made
against <lb/>
me. I am surprised that no
member of <lb/>
the Government was found to place me <lb/>
in a proper position. I am now here to <lb/>
answer for myself. While I held
that <lb/>
office I challenge any man to show
where<lb/>
I was derelict in my duty or did not dis<lb break="no"/><cb/>charge the duties of that office
faithfully.<lb/>
What was the state of facts, after I left<lb/>
the office. An order in Council was<lb/>
made, and Post Master General Steadman<lb/>
paid the money. I obtained authority<lb/>
from the President of the Council and<lb/>
went over to the office with this me<lb break="no"/>moranda : To Mr. Hale—"Give Mr. Con<lb break="no"/>nell every information in regard to the<lb/>
payment of the claim of Elijah Clark.—A.<lb/>
J. S., and received this reply :—" I have<lb/>
to inform you that you made no order for<lb/>
payment of Elijah Clark. He was paid<lb/>
by order of Council, by Hon. James<lb/>
Steadman in 1861." J. HALE.</p>
            <p>C. CONNELL.</p>
            <p>Now, those gentlemen having made a<lb/>
statement affecting my reputation, I think<lb/>
some explanation is due from them.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. COSTIGAN</persName>.— When I first heard<lb/>
that this office was to be abolished, I was<lb/>
opposed to it ; but if it is to be a saving<lb/>
to the country I will go for it. I have<lb/>
listened to the arguments for and against<lb/>
it, but I have not see wherein there will<lb/>
be any great amount of saving. This is<lb/>
a great change, and ought not to be made<lb/>
without some reason. The same argu<lb break="no"/>ments used for removing this department<lb/>
can be used
for every department on the <lb/>
floor of the House. It is said that the <lb/>
Post Master General, in running an elec<lb break="no"/>tion in his own County, will
yield to un<lb break="no"/>reasonable demands in regard
to Post <lb/>
Offices and mail rides, for the purpose of
<lb/>
securing his election. This same argu<lb break="no"/>ment might be used against any other <lb/>
department. Suppose the Chief Com<lb break="no"/>missioner of the Board of Works
runs an <lb/>
election in the County of York, it may be <lb/>
urged that his constituents
will call upon <lb/>
him to give them more than
reasonable <lb/>
share of the expenditure on roads
and <lb/>
bridges. I have no doubt but
this bill <lb/>
will be carried, although it may be that <lb/>
before four or five years the office will be <lb/>
again on the floors of the House, because <lb/>
it is too important an office to remove. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.—I did state that a sum of <lb/>
money had been paid to Mr. Clark by or<lb break="no"/>der of the Post Master
General without <lb/>
the concurrence of the Council. I have <lb/>
seen and examined the vouchers
on <lb/>
fyle in this House. and I find that matter <lb/>
commenced in 1856 and continued to <lb/>
stand over from time to time,
and after my <lb/>
hon. friend left the Government.
On the <lb/>
4th of January, 1861, the matter was <lb/>
brought up and a report made that the <lb/>
amount should be paid. I now
acknowledge <lb/>
that I was labouring under a
mistake. I <lb/>
retract the charge and avow
that I made <lb/>
the mistake unintentionally ;
when I made <lb/>
that charge I was under the conviction <lb/>
that the order was made without the sanc<lb break="no"/>tion of the Council. Mr. Williston also <lb/>
apologized, and Mr. Connell said
he was <lb/>
satisfied with the explanation.
The Bill <lb/>
was agreed to. 30 yeas ; 9 nays.
<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion
of <persName ref="pers:CUDL1">Mr. CUDLIP</persName> the House <lb/>
went into a Committee of the whole to <lb/>
take into consideration <lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">

            <head>THE
CORRESPONDENCE CONCERNING THE<lb/>
PROPOSED INTERCOLONIAL UNION<lb/>
            </head>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:CUDL1">Mr. CUDLIP</persName>.—I see by the
last mail <lb/>
fiom England that this question, although <lb/>
decided by the people of this Province le<lb break="no"/>gitimately at the polls, is still being
agi<lb break="no"/>tated in England. It has been boldly sta<lb break="no"/>ted by various parties
there,
that the elec<lb break="no"/>tion In New Brunswick was not
the true <lb/>
exponent of public opinion, and that there <lb/>
had been a reaction since the election had <lb/>
been held, and there Would now be a ma<lb break="no"/>jority in favour of the Scheme, that taking <lb/>
out two constituencies
the present position <lb/>
would have been reversed. The whole Go<lb break="no"/><cb/>vernment has been carried on by one or two <lb/>
constituencies, the late
Government had a <lb/>
majority of four or five, and without
the <lb/>
support of St. John they would not have <lb/>
been in existence ; therefore
they had not <lb/>
the confidence of the country. We can<lb break="no"/>not have one rule to apply to one case and <lb/>
one to another. It is said the question
<lb/>
was tried on false issues: that many voted <lb/>
against the Scheme for the purpose of <lb/>
turning out those in power. The same <lb/>
argument can be used on the other
side. <lb/>
I have known men who voted the anti-
<lb break="yes"/>
Confederate ticket in the County, yet in<lb/>
consideration of a feeling of regard for<lb/>
Mr.Tilley they voted in favour
of the <lb/>
Scheme in the City ; and if ever there was <lb/>
a true exposition of public opinion, it was <lb/>
on that question. The Union between <lb/>
England and Scotland, and also
between <lb/>
England
and Ireland was carried by bri<lb break="no"/>bery. It is said false statements are cir<lb break="no"/>culated In England bv the
Canadian dele<lb break="no"/>gation, to induce them to legislate for us <lb/>
in regard to this Intercolonial Union. If <lb/>
there is anything of that kind in contem<lb break="no"/>plation, they had better pause before they <lb/>
attempt it, for we would resist coercion <lb/>
whether it was brought against
us direct<lb break="no"/>ly or indirectly. I think it would be a <lb/>
prudent
course to send a delegation home <lb/>
to correct those false
representations, and <lb/>
have therefore prepared the
following re<lb break="no"/>solutions, and will now move that
they be <lb/>
adopted :- <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" Whereas, the House in a Committee <lb/>
of the Whole had under consideration <lb/>
the resolutions of the Conference held <lb/>
at Quebec on the 10th day of October
<lb/>
last, on subject of the
proposed <lb/>
Confederation of the British North Ame<lb break="no"/>rican Colonies." <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> " And Whereas,
it is the opinion of this <lb/>House that the consummation of said <lb/>
Scheme would prove politically, commer<lb break="no"/>cially, and financially disastrous
to the <lb/>
best interests and prosperity of this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince;" <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> " And Whereas, the loyalty and attach<lb break="no"/>ment of the people of this Province to the <lb/>
Throne and Government of Great Britain <lb/>
cannot be justly impunged,
and they have<lb/>
always manifested a desire to maintain <lb/>
their connection with the Mother Coun<lb break="no"/>try, and to remain a portion of the British <lb/>
Empire;"<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> " And Whereas,
in the exercise of the <lb/>
right of internal self-Government enjoyed
<lb/>
by this Province, its people are entitled to <lb/>
deliberate and decide upon all
questions <lb/>
affecting their own local interests in such <lb/>
manner as to them may seem best
calcu<lb break="no"/>lated to promote their prosperity and wel<lb break="no"/>fare;"<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> " And Whereas,
the General Assembly<lb/>
of this Province was, in the month of Feb<lb break="no"/>ruary last, dissolved by His
Excellency <lb/>
the Lieutenant Governor avowedly to ob<lb break="no"/>tain the decision of the people upon the <lb/>
resolutions adopted at the Conference
<lb/>
and now before this House;" <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> " And Whereas,
at the elections con<lb break="no"/>sequently holden the people of this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince clearly and unequivocally pronounc<lb break="no"/>ed a judgment adverse to the adoption of <lb/>
the said resolutions;" <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> " And Whereas, this House confiden<lb break="no"/>tially believes that Her Majesty's Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will receive with due attention the <lb/>
expression of opinion of this Province so <lb/>
pronounced;"<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> " And Whereas, this House has reason <lb/>
to fear Her-Majesty's Government are but <lb/>
imperfectly aware of the true state
of the <lb/>
feelings of the people of this Province
on <lb/>
this subject;" <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> " Therefore Resolved, as the opinion of <lb/>
this House, that a delegation should at <lb/>
          
            <pb n="110" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_110.jpg"/>

<fw type="num">110</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>
          
once
proceed to England for the purpose<lb/>
of making known to the Imperial
Govern<lb break="no"/>ment the views and feelings of this House <lb/>
and the people of this Province
on this <lb/>
important subject." <lb/>

            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. MCMILLAN</persName> —A
resolution of so  <lb/>
much importance should be fully explain<lb break="no"/>ed by the members of the Government, as<lb/>
I imagine it was brought in with their<lb/>
cognizance. The first proposition say<lb/>
that is the opinion of this
House that the <lb/>
consummation
of this Union would prove <lb/>
politically, commercially and financially  <lb/>
disastrous. I for one have strong
feel<lb break="no"/>ings in favour of this Union,
and entirely <lb/>
dissent from this proposition. Every one<lb/>
knows that political Union is strength. <lb/>
do not believe that to unite these British<lb/>
North American Colonies under one rule <lb/>
would be a political injury to them. neith<lb break="no"/>er do I believe the people of
the country <lb/>
think so. I do not believe that the
people<lb/>
are prepared to say that it will be com<lb break="no"/>mercially injurious to them to have a free<lb/>
intercourse in all articles and
manufac<lb break="no"/>tures between the Provinces,setting aside <lb/>
the barriers of the Custom House. I <lb/>
should like to hear the hon. mover show <lb/>
us how it is going to be politically,
finan<lb break="no"/>cially and commercially
disastrous, and <lb/>
how the country is going to suffer by it.<lb/>
            </p>
 
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CUDL1">Mr. CUDLIP</persName>.—I
do not intend to shirk <lb/>
the question, for I want it to be thorough <lb/>
ly discussed, and I should like to see some <lb/>
of the leading members of the
House <lb/>
take it up. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr.
SMITH</persName> —I thought the ex- <lb break="yes"/>
Surveyor General would feel it his duty to <lb/>
justify the course he has taken on this <lb/>
Union, and would have been
prepared to <lb/>
show wherein it would have been ad<lb break="no"/>vantageous; having done that, I
think he <lb/>
did find plenty of hon. members on the <lb/>
other side to meet any
arguments which <lb/>
he may advance. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. COSTIGAN</persName>.—I
have heard, and the <lb/>
people of this Province believe, that influ<lb break="no"/>ences are at work to endeavour to force<lb/>
this Union upon us; that representations <lb/>
are made in England that we are a people <lb/>
disloyal, and do not wish to do our share <lb/>
of whatever is necessary to maintain the <lb/>
connection between them and the British <lb/>
Government. It is our duty to
protect <lb/>
that character of loyalty by sending a <lb/>
delegation to correct those false represen<lb break="no"/>tations. The ex-Surveyor General has <lb/>
stated that the first part of the resolution <lb/>
is not correct, in stating that this Union <lb/>
would be injurious to the people of this<lb/>
Province. There are many hon. gentlemen<lb/>
in this House better qualified to show<lb/>
wherein that Union would have been in<lb break="no"/>jurious, and the necessity for this resolu<lb break="no"/>tion; but I wish to say a few words in<lb/>
order to show the disadvantages and ruin<lb/>
it would bring upon this Province. It<lb/>
does not require a masterly mind to see it.<lb/>
It has been said that Union is strength,<lb/>
but it would not be so in this case. The<lb/>
more the people became acquainted with<lb/>
the Scheme, the more they opposed it<lb/>
The opponents of the Scheme had to con<lb break="no"/>tend with many disadvantages. I con<lb break="no"/>tend that when the people defeat a Scheme<lb/>
proposed by the Government in power, it<lb/>
is a sure sign that they have a two-third<lb/>
majority of the people of the country, be<lb break="no"/>cause the Government by their position<lb/>
have an influence upon the country, and<lb/>
there is not a locality but what feels this<lb/>
influence, because there is a sympathy ex<lb break="no"/>isting between the Government and the<lb/>
office holders in the country which leads<lb/>
them to adopt their measures when they<lb/>
otherwise would not ; many of those who<lb/>
advocated the Scheme of Confederation<lb/>
did not know what the conditions of the<lb/>
        
            <cb/> 
     
Scheme were, but because the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment proposed it they were bound to<lb/>
carry it out. I know this to be a fact,<lb/>
that many who took an active part against<lb/>
Confederation could not explain how it<lb/>
was to be carried out. We were three<lb/>
distinct people, but were to be governed<lb/>
by one general Government, and that was<lb/>
to be carried on by a majority vote; that<lb/>
majority was to rule the country and tax<lb/>
the people as they saw fit. According to<lb/>
the construction of Government we would<lb/>
be represented by fifteen representatives,<lb/>
and these would have to fight against 145. <lb/>
Although I might have much respect for<lb/>
the ability of our representatives, yet I<lb/>
would not have much reason to expect<lb/>
that they would have much success in<lb/>
anything they undertook for the benefit of<lb/>
the Province. Then the question of the<lb/>
Intercolonial Railway was brought up,<lb/>
and it was said under Confederation we<lb/>
could have the Railway wherever we<lb/>
wished it ; but my opinion is, that if the<lb/>
people of Canada really desire the rail<lb break="no"/>way, the same facilities for building the<lb/>
road exist without Confederation as with<lb/>
it. There was no guarantee that we would<lb/>
have this railroad under Confederation; it<lb/>
might grow out of the Scheme, and it<lb/>
might not. I was said that the general<lb/>
revenues could not expended in the<lb/>
construction of the Canal system, as that<lb/>
was guarded against by a resolution of<lb/>
the Conference, which said that this work<lb/>
should be prosecuted so soon as the finan<lb break="no"/>ces of the country permitted. Who was<lb/>
to decide when the state of the finances<lb/>
would permit it to be built? The general<lb/>
Government of Canada ; and they would<lb/>
not object to have the work go on imme<lb break="no"/>diately if they had Confederation, because<lb/>
they would have an additional inducement<lb/>
to extend them when they drag in those<lb/>
three Lower Provinces to bear their pro<lb break="no"/>portion of this great work. This was one<lb/>
of the grand reasons which induced the<lb/>
Canadians to advocate Confederation.<lb/>
They were involved in difficulties in re<lb break="no"/>gard to the Union with Lower Canada and<lb/>
in regard to their finances, and they real<lb break="no"/>ly required an additional field—not for<lb/>
public expenditure in improvements—but<lb/>
an additional field for taxation and reve<lb break="no"/>nue ; that was the reason why they were<lb/>
so anxious to secure the Union of these<lb/>
Colonies. The Canadians would have no<lb/>
reason to complain if they were taxed,<lb/>
because it would be expended and circu<lb break="no"/>lated among themselves, and would bear<lb/>
upon the people of this country, because<lb/>
they would have to pay this money which<lb/>
would never be returned again. It was<lb/>
said that the Government to each Pro<lb break="no"/>vince should have a certain sum to ex<lb break="no"/>pend for local purposes ; this was true<lb/>
enough, we had to provide for our own<lb/>
local expenditure, and so had the other<lb/>
Provinces except Canada, who had the<lb/>
additional advantage of having the general<lb/>
revenue expended on her public works,<lb/>
and it, therefore, became local expendi<lb break="no"/>ture, and we would have to pay for that<lb/>
from which we would derive no benefit.<lb/>
Now, in regard to representation by<lb/>
population. There is one Section of the<lb/>
Scheme which provides for the readjust<lb break="no"/>ment of the representation by population<lb/>
every ten years. In such readjustment<lb/>
Lower Canada is always to be assigned<lb/>
sixty-five members, and each of the other<lb/>
Provinces shall have the same number of<lb/>
members to which it will be entitled on<lb/>
the same ratio of representation as Lower<lb/>
Canada will then have. According to<lb/>
that in a few years, taking the increase of<lb/>
population according to the past as the

            <cb/>
           
 nearest criterion to judge by, the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of Upper Canada in seventeen <lb/>
years would out-vote the whole of the <lb/>
other Provinces. It has been argued that <lb/>
if we had Confederation it would make a <lb/>
great change, and we would become a <lb/>
great country for capitalists, and emi<lb break="no"/>grants would be induced to come here. <lb/>
Would it change the course of our rivers <lb/>
and give more facilities to manufacturers
?<lb/>
The only change it would make would be<lb/>
to place at the disposal of the General <lb/>
Government in Canada the whole resour<lb break="no"/>ces of the Colonies, and emigration would <lb/>
tend to that part of the
Confederation, for <lb/>
we would be removed from any
benefit <lb/>
arising from the construction of
public <lb/>
works. I believe that there is reason for <lb/>
making the assertion that influences are <lb/>
brought to bear abroad to place the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of this Province and the Government <lb/>
of the day in a wrong position. It is as<lb break="no"/>serted by those who are very anxious <lb/>
about the Confederation scheme, that the <lb/>
Government of the day is merely
called <lb/>
into its present position by accident. I <lb/>
contend that if those who are favourable <lb/>
to Confederation wish to see the present <lb/>
Government
retire from their present <lb/>
position, they had better say
nothing <lb/>
about Confederation, for so long as the <lb/>
people of the country are reminded of the <lb/>
Scheme, just so long will they rally round <lb/>
those who defeated it. <lb/>
            </p>



            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. MCMILLAN</persName>.—I
should like to hear <lb/>
from the hon. mover of the Bill, as those <lb/>
resolutions for the appointment of Dele<lb break="no"/>gates was not named when it was pro<lb break="no"/>posed that this subject should be the or<lb break="no"/>der of the day; therefore, I
think it <lb/>
would be unfair to decide this question at <lb/>so short a notice. If the Government of <lb/>
the day are desirous to have this delega<lb break="no"/>tion appointed, they should take
the res<lb break="no"/>ponsibility of it, and not throw it upon <lb/>
the House. It will be recollected how <lb/>
some of the hon. members spoke
of the <lb/>
delegations of the late
Government, and <lb/>
now they are going to take the same <lb/>
course without taking the responsibility.
<lb/>
( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. Smith</persName>.—Those delegations <lb/>
were unauthorized.) They had the Im<lb break="no"/>perial despatch of 1862 to authorize them ?<lb/>
Did they do anything to bind the House <lb/>
in consulting upon a great
question and <lb/>
submitting it to the country for their
deci<lb break="no"/>sion ? They never claimed any right to<lb/>
force it upon the people. I do not wish <lb/>
to go into the discussion
to-day, as there <lb/>
has not been sufficient time given. <lb/>
            </p>

 

            <p> <persName ref="pers:CUDL1">Mr. CUDLIP</persName>.—I
do not desire that this <lb/>
resolution should be carried
without a dis<lb break="no"/>cussion, because I wish to put
upon re<lb break="no"/>cord the opinion of the country as expres<lb break="no"/>sed through their
representatives. I am <lb/>
bound to say that while I am opposed to <lb/>
those delegations as involving unneces<lb break="no"/>sary expense, yet I now think it necessary,
<lb/>
because this is a question affecting our <lb/>
whole political existence—affecting
the <lb/>
constitution of our country. It is a ques<lb break="no"/>tion upon which every person in the coun<lb break="no"/>try has a right to express his
opinion, and <lb/>
the people of the country have done so,
<lb/>
and expressed an opinion, and I think
it <lb/>
now becomes the duty of their represen<lb break="no"/>tatives to send a delegation to
England to <lb/>
protect their rights. The delegation
<lb/>
which was appointed to confer
on a Union <lb/>
of the Maritime Provinces took upou them<lb break="no"/>selves other duties which the Legislature
<lb/>
had not assigned to them, and to avoid <lb/>
falling into the same error, we wish this <lb/>
delegation to be appointed by the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of the people. It is not right <lb/>
that after the people of this country have <lb/>
expressed their opinion at the polls against <lb/>
Confederation,
that this agitation should <lb/>
          


            <pb n="111" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-30_Page_111.jpg"/> 

 <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">111</fw>
         
 be kept up directly or indirectly as it
has <lb/>
been done. Statements have been
put <lb/>
forth by the press that we will have to <lb/>
come into this Confederation,
because i <lb/>
will be forced upon us We ought
to ex<lb break="no"/>press an opinion in this House, and en<lb break="no"/>dorse that by a delegation confirming
that <lb/>
opinion that they never need hope to <lb/>
carry Confederation in New Brunswick,
<lb/>
and I think we would save money in the <lb/>
end by so doing. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. MCMILLAN</persName>.—It
is amusing to find <lb/>
the Anti-Confederate patty asking for <lb/>
this expensive delegation in order to <lb/>
set themselves right before the people of <lb/>
England. It shows that they are
not <lb/>
satisfied with the position they
hold in <lb/>
the eyes of the English people
in refer<lb break="no"/>ence to this question. What were the <lb/>
arguments put forth by the member
of <lb/>
the Government, and the leading members <lb/>
of the Anti-Confederate party in reference
<lb/>
to the appropriation of money for the Mili<lb break="no"/>tia ? They said it would be a waste of mo<lb break="no"/>ney so far as defence was concerned, but<lb/>
they stood in an unfavorable position in<lb/>
the opinion of the British public, and to<lb/>
prove their loyalty they voted the peo<lb break="no"/>ple's money for this purpose. They are<lb/>
not satisfied with asserting that two<lb/>
thirds of the people are against Confed<lb break="no"/>eration, but it becomes necessary to ap<lb break="no"/>point another delegation to make known<lb/>
the fact, for they feel they are not in a<lb/>
right position before the British public.<lb/>
The hon. member for Victoria (Mr. Cos<lb break="no"/>tigan) said that the more the people dis<lb break="no"/>cussed this question the more unpopular<lb/>
it would become. My experience is<lb/>
right the reverse of this ; the question<lb/>
came upon them so suddenly, and so<lb/>
few months elapsed before they were re<lb break="no"/>quired to vote at the polls, that they had<lb/>
not time enough to form a correct opin<lb break="no"/>ion upon the subject, and the general<lb/>
tendency of the people, when they do<lb/>
not understand a question, is to vote<lb/>
against any change until they do under<lb break="no"/>stand it. If that question was submitted<lb/>
to the people to-morrow, and the people<lb/>
were required to deposit their votes in<lb/>
the ballot box, either for or against it,<lb/>
two thirds of the people in the Province<lb/>
of New Brunswick would vote in favor<lb/>
of it.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr.
NEEDHAM</persName>.—The hon ex-Surveyor<lb/>
General wants to know how this scheme<lb/>
would ruin us, politically. What would<lb/>
we have been had Confederation taken<lb/>
place under this scheme ? Would we<lb/>
have been a Province? certainly not.<lb/>
O, it is said we can have a local legisla<lb break="no"/>ture ; so we could, and its powers would<lb/>
be confined to making laws to prevent<lb/>
cows from running on the commons,<lb/>
providing that sheep shall wear bells,<lb/>
and to issue tavern licences. Hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers may talk about their loyalty and dis<lb break="no"/>loyalty. I would like to ask some of the<lb/>
members of the late Government whether<lb/>
their idea was not this—that they would<lb/>
not have gone for Confederation if they<lb/>
had not believed that it was the first step<lb/>
towards the independence of New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick. ( <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMillan</persName> —it is not true.)<lb/>
I have no hesitation in saying that thous<lb break="no"/>ands of men believed in Confederation,<lb/>
honestly and sincerely, but they do not<lb/>
seem willing to give us any credit for<lb/>
sincerity ; they think they have all the<lb/>
argument, all the honesty and all the<lb/>
loyalty. We have now a direct com<lb break="no"/>munication with the Home Government,<lb/>
as they appoint our Governor ; but if we<lb/>
go into Confederation our Governor<lb/>
would be appointed by the Governor<lb/>
General ; that would raise our dignity<lb/>
very much, to have a local Governor<lb/>
        
            <cb/>
         
appointed by the Governor General ;<lb/>
would not that be derogatory to our po<lb break="no"/>litical standing, both at home and<lb/>
abroad. I heard a Judge, in addressing<lb/>
a Grand Jury, in the County of York,<lb/>
strive to impress upon their minds the<lb/>
necessity for this " Great British Nation<lb break="no"/>ality as he termed it. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Great British <lb/>
Humbug!</hi> I should like to know
where <lb/>
there is any nationality in this Confed<lb break="no"/>eration scheme that we have not got <lb/>
now. We are "<hi rendition="simple:italic">par excellence</hi>"
Blue<lb break="no"/>noses ; those born in Ireland are
Irish<lb break="no"/>men, in Bath Englishmen, in Wales <lb/>
Welshmen, but we are all British
sub<lb break="no"/>jects. Are not we British subjects
as <lb/>
much as if we were born "
Cockneys." <lb/>
We have the real British nationality, and <lb/>
because we did not want any
other we <lb/>
rejected the great <hi rendition="simple:italic">Botheration</hi> or Confed<lb break="no"/>eration scheme, for it all amounts to
the <lb/>
same thing ; thus it is that so
far as poli<lb break="no"/>tics are concerned we are not going to <lb/>
gain anything. I will now allow you that <lb/>
it will be financially disastrous. We will <lb/>
have to give
up all our revenues to Cana<lb break="no"/>da, and they will only refund $201,000;.<lb/>
(Mr. McMillan, will not they assume  <lb/>
our
debts.) We. are prepared to assume <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> our own debts.
Canada has to borrow <lb/>
money
to pay the interest on her own <lb/>
debts, and then wants to assume
ours. <lb/>
It is
like a bankrupt wanting to assume <lb/>
the debts of a rich man. The General <lb/>
Government will give us
$201,000 a year <lb/>
for all time to come. That is, financi<lb break="no"/>ally, the position we are in. No mat<lb break="no"/>ter
how much
the population may in<lb break="no"/>crease in
twenty years, or how many <lb/>
new  roads,
bridges or schools may be <lb/>
required in that time, we can
receive no <lb/>
more
than
that sum. If a man had a <lb/>
million dollars
a year, and he owed the <lb/>
sum
of five millions, and had plenty of <lb/>
friends
to back him, do you suppose he <lb/>
would want to make arrangements
with <lb/>
another
man to take his debt and give <lb/>
him just enough to live on until he died. <lb/>
If he would do that he would he
a fit <lb/>
subject for the Lunatic Asylum.
It was <lb/>
enough to condemn the scheme, that
<lb/>
this
delegation assented to tho proposi<lb break="no"/>tion that whatever arrangements
made <lb/>
between
Canada and the Home Govern<lb break="no"/>ment from that time
to the time Confed<lb break="no"/>eration
went into
operation should form <lb/>
part and parcel of the obligations to be <lb/>
assumed
by the General
Government. <lb/>
At
that very time England had said
to <lb/>
Canada—what are you prepared to do <lb/>
in
reference to your own defence ? Did <lb/>
she say that to New Brunswick, Nova <lb/>
Scotia or Prince Edward island ? No ! <lb/>
Why ?
Because she knew from
the his<lb break="no"/>tory of
the past that these colonies would <lb/>
when
the time arrived;
they would be <lb/>
ready at a moment's notice to
gather <lb/>
round the British flag; but there was a <lb/>
time
in the history
of Canada when it <lb/>
was otherwise,
and there was a neces<lb break="no"/>sity
for asking the question of Canada. <lb/>
At
that very time Canada sent home a <lb/>
delegation charged with a power to <lb/>
agree with the British
Government. to <lb/>
expend a million of money for
their de<lb break="no"/>fence, to be borne not only by  Canada, <lb/>
but
by all
that Confederation. There <lb/>
would
be a direct tax upon every man. <lb/>
woman and child
in this Province, to <lb/>
pay their proportion of that money. <lb/>
When I
saw that
agreement I felt as <lb/>
every
son of New Brunswick ought to
<lb/>
feel,
that if it cost me my life, my
all. <lb/>
Confederation
should
never be carried <lb/>
if I could
help it. It has not come. I <lb/>
do not say I stopped it, but if I was but <lb/>
one little entering wedge I am satisfied
<lb/>
for
the remainder of my life ; so far as <lb/>
           
            <cb/> 

that is concerned I have done my duty, <lb/>
      
and am sincere in my opposition, and it <lb/>
is a matter of moonshine whether they <lb/>
acknowledge it or not. Canada has
<lb/>
sent home a delegation to influence the <lb/>
British people in favor of this Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. I do not say that this scheme is <lb/>
going to be forced upon us,
but they<lb/>
may pass a provisional Confederation<lb/>
Bill, but we do to not want that
or any <lb/>
thing to look like it. Forty-eight
thou<lb break="no"/>sand men in this Province have said we <lb/>
don't want Confederation, and
that <lb/>
should be an end of it. They have said<lb/>
this, notwithstanding
all the influences <lb/>
that have been brought to bear by the <lb/>
Government, telling them the
Inter- <lb break="yes"/>
colonial railway was going past every <lb/>
man's door, whether he lived at Freder<lb break="no"/>icton. Sussex, or the North Shore. <lb/>
Statesmen in framing a scheme of this <lb/>
kind should look forward to future
<lb/>
ages. In this scheme of Confederation, <lb/>
fifty years hence, Upper Canada
would <lb/>
have a majority of thirty-five over
all the <lb/>
other Provinces. This is the position
<lb/>
We would be in, and we are called to <lb/>
pay homage to the statesmen who framed
<lb/>
this scheme, as though they possessed
<lb/>
all the wisdom in the world.<lb/>
            </p>



            <p> House
adjourned until 9 A. M., to<lb break="no"/>morrow.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> T. P. D. <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2016-11-22, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p>  WEDNESDAY, May 31. </p>
            <p>
Mr. BOYD.—I though this subject had <lb/>
been so well ventilated that we should <lb/>
never hear any more about it, but since <lb/>
the matter has been brought in I suppose<lb/>
it has been considered necessary. The <lb/>
first thing I heard of this Union
question <lb/>
was the appointment of delegates
to con<lb break="no"/>fer at Prince Edward Island, on a Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Union of the Maritime Provinces. <lb/>
It seems they went there and commenced <lb/>
their deliberations, but some gentlemen <lb/>
from Canada came down.
pooh-poohed at <lb/>
the idea of such a Scheme, proposed a <lb/>
larger Union, to embrace all the Provin<lb break="no"/>ces, and that was the last of
their mission. <lb/>
Next we find them going off to
Canada <lb/>
without any power from this Legislature, <lb/>
or any other. They met, but it was
impos<lb break="no"/>sible to find out what they were doing ; <lb/>
after a time they returned, yet nothing <lb/>
was known as to their proceedings. This <lb/>
attempt at secrecy roused the
public feel<lb break="no"/>ing, and the press clamoured for informa<lb break="no"/>tion. At last it all came out by
a paper <lb/>
in Prince Edward Island publishing the <lb/>
whole Scheme. When I read it first I <lb/>
was somewhat favourably impressed
by it, <lb/>
but as I read on and came to the Section <lb/>
which provided that the Governor General <lb/>
should have the appointment of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernors of the Lower Provinces, I said at <lb/>
once, then the last link that binds us to <lb/>
England will be broken. I went on fur<lb break="no"/>ther and found that New Brunswick
was <lb/>
to be represented in the General Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment by only fifteen members and I then <lb/>
felt that we should be swamped by Upper <lb/>
Canada. The fact was Canada found her<lb break="no"/>self overwhelmed with debt and wanted to <lb/>
get the support of these Provinces to re<lb break="no"/>lieve her, and so we were to be bought <lb/>
and sold for eighty cents a head. Our <lb/>
people had been content with their posi<lb break="no"/>tion, and if they ever desired a change, it <lb/>was that we might enter into a Union of <lb/>
the Lower Provinces. Then came
the <lb/>
disolution of the House a a time when <lb/>
the people were little prepared for it, and <lb/>
for the first time in the history
of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince we find men who had occupied the <lb/>
highest position in the Government <lb/>
stumping the country to carry their <lb/>
Scheme. But they could not make the  <lb/>
            </p>
-->
</div>

         </div>
 
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>