<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-04-06"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-04-06">6 April 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="101"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_096.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_097.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_098.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_099.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_100.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_101.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-14">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_096">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_096.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_097">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_097.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_098">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_098.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_099">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_099.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_100">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_100.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_0101">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_0101.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="96" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_096.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="num">96</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866</fw> 
    

   <!-- GL, 2018-03-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->   
    <!-- so much desire to give the office to Judge 
     <lb/>
     Ritchie, they would not have taken such 
     <lb/>
     pains to press it upon Judge Parker. 
     <lb/>
     After having offered it three times to 
     <lb/>
     Jukge Parker. and he refused to accept 
     <lb/>
     it, they might have said—You refuse to 
     <lb/>
     accept the office ; we will appoint the 
     <lb/>
     man we think, and you think, best to 
     <lb/>
     fill it.  
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>The House was then adjourned until 
     <lb/>10 A. M., the debate to be resumed by 
     <lb/>Mr. Anglin at 11 to-morrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>T. P. D. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->



            <head rendition="simple:right"> FRIDAY, April 6. 
     <lb/>
            </head>

            <head rendition="simple:centre">MORNING SESSION. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The House went into committee of the 
     <lb/>
     whole on a Bill to facilitate the construc<lb break="no"/>tion of a deep sea wharf in the town of 
     <lb/>St. Andrews ; Mr. Lewis in the Chair. 
     <lb/>Agreed to.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     'The House went into committee of the 
     <lb/>
    whole on a Bill in amendment of the Act 
     <lb/> to incorporate the Digdeguash Lakes and 
     <lb/>Stream Driving Company. Mr. Bever<lb break="no"/>idge in the Chair. Agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     The House went into committee of the 
     <lb/>
     whole on a Bill to incorporate the Peo<lb break="no"/>ple's Street Railway Company in the City 
     <lb/>
     of Saint John. Mr. Lindsay in the 
     <lb/>
    Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CORA1">MR. CORAM</persName> was opposed to the Bill 
     <lb/>
     when it had been presented on a former 
     <lb/>
      occasion, because he believed the rights 
     <lb/>
     of the public were not properly guarded. 
     <lb/>
     Since that time, however, the present Bill 
     <lb/>
     had been thoroughly investigated by a 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Common Council, and 
     <lb/>
     he believed that the clause permitting the 
     <lb/>
     carrying freight on the line had been 
     <lb/>
     struck out of the present Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CUDL1">MR. CUDLIP</persName> should oppose the Bill 
     <lb/>
     if the clause permitting the Company to 
     <lb/>
     carry freight were struck out. He saw no 
     <lb/>
     reason why they should be debarred this 
     <lb/>
     privilege, if they had proper depots for 
     <lb/>
     the purpose of receiving and discharg<lb break="no"/>ing . 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     HON MR. HATHEWAY had not read 
     <lb/>
     the Bill, but as one of the great benefits 
     <lb/>
     his people would receive by the passing 
     <lb/>
     of this Bill, would be that, whereas they 
     <lb/>
     now lose about ten or fifteen barrels by 
     <lb/>
     smashing from drays and jolting over 
     <lb/>
     rough roads, out of every one hundred 
     <lb/>
     sent from St. John, he should oppose the 
     <lb/>
     Bill if there was not a clause permitting 
     <lb/>
     the carriage of freight. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> was opposed to the dis<lb break="no"/>charge of freight upon the streets, as it 
     <lb/>
     would completely block the way, and stop 
     <lb/>
     all traffic. The previous Bill would have 
     <lb/>
     given to one man larger powers than had 
     <lb/>
     ever before been asked of this House. If 
     <lb/>
     proper depots were provided for the re<lb break="no"/>ception and discharge of freight, he could 
     <lb/>
     see no objection to the granting the right 
     <lb/>
     of carriage. There was no trouble about 
     <lb/>
     the means to carry on the work, for mo<lb break="no"/>ney would be forthcoming, as it would be 
     <lb/>
     a very paying business. It would be one 
     <lb/>
     of the greatest monopolies, and he was 
     <lb/>
     desirous to see the proper guards inserted 
     <lb/>
     to secure the rights of the people at 
     <lb/>
     large.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">MR. CONNELL</persName> thought the Bill 
     <lb/>
     should be sent to a select committee to 
     <lb/>
     report upon, so that every interest should 
     <lb/>
     be provided for. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GILB1">MR. GILBERT</persName> could not see why the 
     <lb/>
     traffic should be confined to passengers, 
     <lb/>
     to the exclusion of freight. He thought 
     <lb/>
     

            <cb/>
         

     this point would prove a great benefit to 
     <lb/>
     the public at large. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> had no doubt that 
     <lb/>
     the gentlemen applying for this Act 
     <lb/>
     would be very glad to be permitted to 
     <lb/>
     carry freight, but this was the first move<lb break="no"/>ment, and as the Common Council of St. 
     <lb/>
     John were opposed to the carrying of 
     <lb/>
     freight over the line, and although this 
     <lb/>
     was a step is the right direction, he 
     <lb/>
     should like to see the further power 
     <lb/>
     granted. The objections came from the 
     <lb/>
     members of the Common Council, who 
     <lb/>
     were probably influenced by the weight 
     <lb/>
     of the large number of persons who, as 
     <lb/>
     drivers of drays, now control the freight<lb break="no"/>ing of the city ; but as the Bill in its 
     <lb/>
     present form had been accepted by them, 
     <lb/>
     he thought it a should be passed by this 
     <lb/>
     House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> thought that the regula<lb break="no"/>tion of rates should be under the control 
     <lb/>
     of the Common Council, and with regard 
     <lb/>
     to the carrying of freight, the parties ap<lb break="no"/>plying would not only accept the permis<lb break="no"/>sion, but be very glad to have it granted, 
     <lb/>
     and he thought for all parties it would 
     <lb/>
     only be fair and equitable. And although 
     <lb/>
     it maybe said to interfere with the pri<lb break="no"/>vileges of the large and very respectable<lb/>body of truckmen in the city, yet there<lb/>were higher principles affecting the ques-<lb break="yes"/>of trade and commerce.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR HILL thought that the company<lb/>should not be limited to the payment of<lb/>a certain per centage, or be compelled to<lb/>fix a maximum rate of fare, and although<lb/>the hon. member from St. John (Mr.<lb/>Anglin) regarded this as a great mon<lb break="no"/>opoly, yet they had to enter into compe<lb break="no"/>tition with the natural means of transit,<lb/>and also with the omnibusses and cabs of<lb/>the city. With regard to carrying freight<lb/>in other cities, the horse railways do not<lb/>carry passengers and freight together, but<lb/>he could see not reason why they should<lb/>not carry freight after the passenger<lb/>traffic is over for the day.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CORA1">MR. CORAM</persName> said the Committee for<lb/>the Common Council would be here on<lb/>Monday next, and he would move that<lb/>progress be reported.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">MR. MCCLELLAN</persName> also thought that<lb/>it would be wrong to fix a maximum rate<lb/>of profit.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HATH1">HON. MR. HATHEWAY</persName> could see no<lb/>reason why the company should be pre—<lb/>vented from running their line down upon<lb/>the South or North Market Wharves,<lb/>and giving an opportunity to the up<lb/>river people to load on their five or six<lb/>hundred barrels of flour, and run them<lb/>over for shipment ; and should oppose the<lb/>Bill if there were no clause giving the<lb/>company this permission.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName> differed from the<lb/>preceding member with regard to this<lb/>point, for none of the street railways he<lb/>had heard of carried freight, as it would<lb/>be a constant source of annoyance, from<lb/>their stopping every few minutes to dis<lb break="no"/>charge or take it in from the various<lb/>stores on the line.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> thought perhaps it<lb/>would be best that progress should be re<lb break="no"/>ported, and then submitted to a select<lb/>Committee. Progress reported.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Speaker in the chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> moved that this Bill<lb/>be submitted to a select Committee to re<lb break="no"/>port.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOTS1">HON. MR. BOTSFORD</persName> thought as this<lb/>Bill was of a public character, some mem<lb break="no"/>bers outside of the City of St. John,<lb/>should be upon the Committee, so that<lb/>
       

            <cb/>
    

     the interests of parties outside may be 
     <lb/>
     represented.    
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>This idea was supported by other mem<lb break="no"/>bers, when Messrs. Wetmore, Glazier, 
     <lb/>Hill and Connell were appointed to take 
     <lb/>the matter into consideration.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House went into Committee of the 
     <lb/> Whole on a Bill relating to the Justices 
     <lb/>of the City and County St. John ; Mr. 
     <lb/>Young in the chair.     
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CUDL1">HON. MR. CUDLIP</persName> said this was a Bill 
     <lb/>emenating from the Justices of St. John 
     <lb/>themselves, and was intended to compel 
     <lb/>the attendance or those who would not 
     <lb/>attend the Sessions.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said the reason why 
     <lb/>they would not attend was because some 
     <lb/>four or five justices talked so incessantly, 
     <lb/>that they talked some others out of doors. 
     <lb/>It was true, that although there were 
     <lb/>some eighty or ninety Justices, yet the 
     <lb/>ordinary attendance was about five or 
     <lb/>six ; and with regard to the attendance of 
     <lb/>Jurors, hh thought that their non-atten<lb break="no"/>dance was also largely attributable to the 
     <lb/>babbling spirit which seems to be so pre<lb break="no"/>valent with certain parties at the present 
     <lb/>time. He did not see that this House 
     <lb/>should interfere in the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HATH1">HON. MR. HATHEWAY</persName> thought that 
     <lb/>
     if this Bill passed the next would be 
     <lb/>
     one to allow them to increase the size of 
     <lb/>
     the Court House, as, instead of some 
     <lb/>
     eighty or ninety, he believed there were 
     <lb/>
     some one hundred and forty Justices of 
     <lb/>
     the Peace. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName> agreed with the last 
     <lb/>
     speaker, and thought that there was no 
     <lb/>
     reason why the House should interfere 
     <lb/>
     in the matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CORA1">MR. CORAM</persName> explained that the Mag<lb break="no"/>istrates should be got together at least 
     <lb/>
     once a year, and perhaps it would be 
     <lb/>
     better to amend the Bill authorizing the 
     <lb/>
     calling together of all Magistrates un<lb break="no"/>der the age of fifty years to form a gen<lb break="no"/>eral Sessions. 
     <lb/>HON. MR. CUDLIP thought the idea 
     <lb/>a good one, and would therefore move 
     <lb/>that progress be reported to admit of 
     <lb/>time to take the matter into considera<lb break="no"/>tion. Progress reported. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     The House went into Committee of 
     <lb/>
     the Whole on a Bill to amend an Act 
     <lb/>
     relating to the granting of licenses to 
     <lb/>
    foreigners to transact business. Mr. 
     <lb/>Scovil in the Chair.    
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:YOUN1">MR. YOUNG</persName> explained, that at present 
     <lb/>foreigners could bring in their wares<lb/>
     and transact their business  without con<lb break="no"/>tributing tot he local taxes. He thought 
     <lb/>
     that they should be placed on, at least, 
     <lb/>
     the same footing as our own people. 
     <lb/>
     This Bill gives power to the Sessions 
     <lb/>
     and Municipalities to impose licenses 
     <lb/>
     and penalties upon foreigners doing 
     <lb/>
    business. Agreed to.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    <div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
      AFTERNOON  SESSION. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </head>


            <p><persName ref="pers:DESB2">MR. L. P. W. DESBRISAY</persName> seeing the 
     <lb/>Chief Commissioner of  the Board of 
     <lb/>Works in his place would ask if any, 
     <lb/>and what arrangement had been made 
     <lb/>by the Government with regard to put<lb break="no"/>ting a steamer upon the North Shore. 
     <lb/>The Spring was opening out now, and 
     <lb/>if anything was to be done it should be 
     <lb/>done at once.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HATH1">HON. MR. HATHEWAY</persName> replied that 
     <lb/>no arrangement had yet been made. 
     <lb/>Mr Finlay, the agent, was here a few 
     <lb/>days ago, and they had given him ten 
     <lb/>days to go to Canada and see what ar<lb break="no"/>
         

            <pb n="97" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_097.jpg"/>
          

<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">97</fw> 


     rangement could be entered into. He 
     <lb/>
    had heard that the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would grant a subsidy, but Mr. 
     <lb/>Galt had telegraphed that they would 
     <lb/>not do so, but were willing to enter in<lb break="no"/>to an arrangement for the transmission 
     <lb/>of mails. It was now some fourteen 
     <lb/>days since Mr. Finley left, and if he 
     <lb/>were not heard from by Monday next 
     <lb/>they would enter into negotiations with 
     <lb/>other parties at once. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    </div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     WANT OF CONFIDENCE DEBATE. 
     <lb/>
     
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> resumed. When the 
     <lb/>Debate was adjourned yesterday, he was<lb/>speaking as to the appointment of the<lb/>
     Judges. He had explained how the offer 
     <lb/>
     of the Chief Judgeship had been made 
     <lb/>
     to Mr. Justice Parker, and how the pre<lb break="no"/>sent Chief Justice had been appointed. 
     <lb/>
     With regard to the late appointments, he 
     <lb/>
     was not in the Government at the time, 
     <lb/>
     and therefore was  not responsible, but 
     <lb/>
     still he was ready to endorse the action of 
     <lb/>
     the Government in the matter. It had 
     <lb/>
     been said that great injustice had been 
     <lb/>
     done to Mr. Justice Wilmot, and thr ugh 
     <lb/>
     him to the whole Methodist body of the 
     <lb/>
     Province, by passing him by ; but he 
     <lb/>
     could not look upon it in any such light. 
     <lb/>
     If  Judge Wilmot were entitled to the po<lb break="no"/>sition on account of his religious princi<lb break="no"/>ples, and had been appointed on such 
     <lb/>
     grounds, then would injustice have been 
     <lb/>
     done, not to the Methodists alone, but to 
     <lb/>
    every other religious body. His first ap<lb break="no"/>pointment had been denounced by his 
     <lb/>own party. The hon. member for York 
     <lb/>(Mr. Fisher) not only resigned his con<lb break="no"/>nection with the Government on that oc<lb break="no"/>casion, but four years after he is reported 
     <lb/>to have said that in that appoinment the 
     <lb/>rights of the people had been trampled 
     <lb/>on. But look on the matter on the pro<lb break="no"/>per grounds upon which Judge Wilmot 
     <lb/>was passed over. He had seen fit to take 
     <lb/>such action as was never before taken by 
     <lb/>any member of the Beneh. He had pub<lb break="no"/>licly denounced the religious body to 
     <lb/>which he (Mr. A.) belonged, and as an 
     <lb/>Irishman end Irish Catholic, he felt called 
     <lb/>on to oppose the promotion of such a man. 
     <lb/>After this we had seen him acting the 
     <lb/>part of a violent political partizan. It 
     <lb/>was said that at Sunbury County Court 
     <lb/>House, and also in his official position 
     <lb/>in this House he had taken most active 
     <lb/>part in political discussions of the day. 
     <lb/>Again, we find that at a subsequent  elec<lb break="no"/>tion, when the question of Confedera 
     <lb/>tion did not enter into the contest at all, 
     <lb/>he took an active part and loudly an<lb break="no"/>nounced his views on this matter to in<lb break="no"/>fluence the votes of others. Now, what<lb break="no"/>ever his qualities may be as a lawyer, 
     <lb/>this was sufficient to dabar his promo<lb break="no"/>tion to a higher position. It had been 
     <lb/>said by the hon. member for York (Mr. 
     <lb/>Fisher), and also by his hon. colleague 
     <lb/>from the City of St. John (Mr Wet<lb break="no"/>more), that Mr. Chief  Justice Ritchie 
     <lb/>had caballed with the present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> remarked that he 
     <lb/>did not say this, but that he had referred 
     <lb/>to a report of certain actions, which Mr. 
     <lb/>Anglin could ask Mr. Cudlip to explain 
     <lb/>when he came into the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> could not reply for any 
     <lb/>one else, nor should he be called on to 
     <lb/>prove that certain statements made with 
     <lb/>reference to other parties was not true, 
     <lb/>as it was frequently a hard matter to     
     <lb/>prove a negative, but he could speak on<lb/>his own behalf, and that he would say that<lb/>


            <cb/>
        

     he never said that Chief Justice Ritchie<lb/>took the slightest part in that election. 
     <lb/>
    He was at almost all the meetings that 
     <lb/>were held, but never saw Mr. Ritchie at 
     <lb/>any of them, and  only on one occasion 
     <lb/>had he spoken to him on the subject. 
     <lb/>That was one day immediately after  the 
     <lb/>inauguration of the Quebec  Scheme. 
     <lb/>He met him on the steps of his own 
     <lb/>building and jocularly said, after the<lb/>usual courtesies, " I congratulate you<lb/>on the prospect of an increased salary,"<lb/>In the most serious voice, and in the<lb/>most noble and manly tone he replied, 
     <lb/>" Not even at that price, Sir, will con<lb break="no"/>sent to sell my country." Until he 
     <lb/>heard the remark the other day from an 
     <lb/>honorable member he never knew that 
     <lb/>the Judge had said  that he " would 
     <lb/>sooner vote  for a hedgehog than for a 
     <lb/>Confederate." But even if he had done 
     <lb/>as another had, in showiug his parti<lb break="no"/>zanship, yet it was the duty of the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment to appoint Judge  Ritchie to 
     <lb/>the office of Chief Justice, even on the 
     <lb/>worst ground that had been alleged, 
     <lb/>that of favoritism ; it was their duty to 
     <lb/>appoint him as their friend, and it would 
     <lb/>have been an insult to the whole Pro<lb break="no"/>vince if they had otherwise appointed. 
     <lb/>But he contended that this was not the 
     <lb/>reason why Mr. Ritchie received the 
     <lb/>offer. To the Government it was a 
     <lb/>question, not of friendship, but of quali<lb break="no"/>fication. They regarded him as the 
     <lb/>best man for the office, the possessor of<lb/>sterling qualities, admirably fitting him<lb/>for the discharge of his high duties. It<lb/>the business ?<lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Mr. Anglin</persName>  then referred to a paper 
     <lb/>
    being taken round by an honorable  
     <lb/>member with regard to the appointment 
     <lb/>of Judge Wilmot.    
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> enquired if that pa<lb break="no"/>per was not sent in to Government be<lb break="no"/>fore the appointment of Chief Justice 
     <lb/>Parker on September 8th. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName> replied that he 
     <lb/>
     could not recollect. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said the office was of<lb break="no"/>fered to Judge Parker on the day Chief 
     <lb/>
     Justice Carter retired, and before Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Smith's  return from   England. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> wanted to know if 
     <lb/>
     there was a division in the Council on the 
     <lb/>
     appointment, or whether the Lieutenant 
     <lb/>
     Governor came down and pressed the ap<lb break="no"/>pointment of Judge Ritchie upon them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> replied the matter was 
     <lb/>
     never mooted in what  he might call the 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Council, that is in the 
     <lb/>
     absence of the Lieutenant Governor, and 
     <lb/>
     they knew nothing about it till he came 
     <lb/>
     down and laid the resignation of Chief 
     <lb/>
     Justice Carter before them. Then at 
     <lb/>
     once, and without any division or expres<lb break="no"/>sion of conflicting opinions, it was unani<lb break="no"/>mously decided to proffer the position to 
     <lb/>
     Judge Parker. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> asked what about 
     <lb/>
     the question of salary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said the question of the 
     <lb/>
     salary was not discussed till afterwards. 
     <lb/>
     After the appointment was tendered, 
     <lb/>
     Judge Parker stated his  acceptance of of<lb break="no"/>fice must be dependant on the salary he 
     <lb/>
     was receiving as a Puiane Judge being 
     <lb/>
     retained. His hon. colleague from the 
     <lb/>
     City of St. John (Mr. Wetmore) had 
     <lb/>
     stated that. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> remarked that he had 
     <lb/>
    not <hi rendition="simple:italic">stated</hi> any thing, but that certain 
     <lb/>things were currently reported.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said yes, these ideas, re<lb break="no"/>
         

            <cb/>
         
ports and rumors were the substance of 
     <lb/>the speeches made by those preferring<lb/>these charges against the Government,<lb/>
     
    and this it was that made it so difficult 
     <lb/>to reply to them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     MR WETMORE would explain that 
     <lb/>
     with regard to this  question what  he knew 
     <lb/>
     was this, that he was at Newcastle at the 
     <lb/>
    time the  appointment was made, and call<lb break="no"/>ed on Judge Parker to offer his congra<lb break="no"/>tulations, when in the course of the conver— 
     <lb/>sation the Judge told him that his salary<lb/>was to be retained as it was before.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said, yes it was now ex<lb break="no"/>plained as it really was. He would not<lb/>now say how and when the question was<lb/>discussed, but Judge Parker's demand<lb/>was that the Government should bring in<lb/>a Bill to this House, fixing his salary at<lb/>the same as that of a Puiane Judge. This<lb/>was straightforward, open and manly. He<lb/>did not wish the amount paid him without<lb/>the authority of the representatives of the<lb/>people, and although it had been charged<lb/>that this action of the Government was<lb/>the cause of loss to the country, it had in<lb/>reality been the means of saving a small<lb/>sum of some fifty pounds.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> asked, then if it was<lb/>such a saving, why not bring forward the<lb/>papers and let the people see it.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said this was the cry— 
     <lb/>
    " Why not produce the papers?" He 
     <lb/>might with greater reason ask—Why not 
     <lb/>go on with the business of      the country ? 
     <lb/>Why act as the Opposition had done ?<lb/>Why throw obstacles in the path of the<lb/>Government, and then hold them up to<lb/>the country as unwilling to go on with<lb/> <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName> said he had received<lb/>authority to speak on this matter. He<lb/>knew what opposition was raised in the<lb/>Council, and from what source it came.<lb/>At the time the resignation of Chief Jus<lb break="no"/>tice Carter was received, he moved the<lb/>appointment should be offered to Judge<lb/>Parker at the salary he then held. He<lb/>was of opinion that the salary should not<lb/>be reduced.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said the hon. member  
     <lb/>was mistaken as to the time the discussion<lb/>of the salary took place. On the day the<lb/>resignation was received and the new<lb/>appointment made, there was not one<lb/>word as to the salary. It was subse<lb break="no"/>quently, when the Governor brought the<lb/>matter before them that the ques<lb break="no"/>tion was discussed. He had the most<lb/>distinct recollection of what took place,<lb/>and he was confident that on the<lb/>first occasion, the hon. member moved<lb/>that the appointment be offered to Judge<lb/>Parker, and without any discussion what<lb break="no"/>ever, and without any previous delibera<lb break="no"/>tion, it was decided to offer the situation<lb/>to him. He was rather surprised that<lb/>the movement was approved at first, till<lb/>after the discussion was raised in the<lb/>House, and then he saw and understood<lb/>the whole thing. He was averse to<lb/>dragging our Judges thus before the pub<lb break="no"/>lic, for he was satisfied that their characters<lb/>could not be discussed in the papers, or<lb/>on the floors of the House, without low<lb break="no"/>ering the just dignity they should hold.<lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Mr. Anglin</persName> again referred to the paper 
     <lb/>
     which had been handed round, which he 
     <lb/>
     would call a " round robin," and to the 
     <lb/>
     statement of the hon. member for Char<lb break="no"/>lotte, that when offered to him for signa<lb break="no"/>ture, the hon. member for the City had 
     <lb/>remarked that Judge Wilmot was an in<lb break="no"/>ferior lawyer. He went on to condemn 
     <lb/>the conduct of the hon. member in this 
     <lb/>matter, but cries from all parts of the 
     <lb/>
    

            <pb n="98" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_098.jpg"/>
           
<fw type="num">98</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>
         


     House and galleries rendered it impossi<lb break="no"/>ble for the reporters to catch the con<lb break="no"/>cluding remarks of the speaker.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     After calling the attention of his Honor        
     <lb/>the Speaker to the interruption, he went<lb/>on to remark that even Mr. Cardwell—<lb/>the man who was thought by some to <lb/>speak by inspiration the words of divine<lb/>wisdom—even he had assented to the<lb/>appointment made by the Government.<lb/>In passing from this point, if he had said<lb/>anything to hurt the feelings of any<lb/>member of the Bench, he was extremely<lb/>sorry, as they were, individually, men he<lb/>ever desired to hold in the highest<lb/>esteem.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The chief point of the speech of the   
     <lb/>hon. member for the city (Mr. Welmore)<lb/>
     had been the cry of " office, office, office," 
     <lb/>and he was proud when he appealed to<lb/>the hon. member from Charlotte (Mr.<lb/>Boyd) to know if he had not been offered<lb/>an office, that gentleman replied, " That,<lb/>Sir, was a private affair, and is no busi<lb break="no"/>ness of yours." It is charged that offi<lb break="no"/>ces were promised, but never filled. Now<lb/>what was the condition of things when <lb/>these promises were made? Did we not<lb/>all expect that the mother country would<lb/>respect the decisions of these Colonies?<lb/>Did we not all imagine that the fight was<lb/>fought and the victory won ? That we<lb/>would settle down to manage our own af<lb break="no"/>fairs and carry on the legitimate business<lb/>of the country? But how was it? We<lb/>find that when the first shock of defeat<lb/>was over, the enemies within our borders,<lb/>with renewed force, and, he might say,<lb/>with increased malignity, set to work to<lb/>overthrow the independence of this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. They had not accomplished their<lb/>purpose yet, and he trusted the friends of <lb/>freedom would still hold together, and<lb/>agree to do what lay in their power to<lb/>save our country from the mean and<lb/>sordid grasp of those who, in its over<lb break="no"/>throw, only sees their own aggrandize<lb break="no"/>ment. Was ever a Government so be<lb break="no"/>set? Surrounded by difficulties—the<lb/>influence of Canada on the one hand, and<lb/>the furious attacks of the unscrupulous,<lb/>lying, slanderous and bireling press of<lb/>their opponents, on the other. The Min<lb break="no"/>ister of the Queen evem succumbing and<lb/>descending to be the tool of Canada to<lb/>bring about this Union. Again he would<lb/>ask, was ever a Government so beset?<lb/>Unde circumstances like these, any pro<lb break="no"/>mise made could only be conditional. His<lb/>hon. colleague (Mr. Wilmot) has admit<lb break="no"/>ted that he did not want the Audit Of<lb break="no"/>fice.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName>.—" Yes."   
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName>.—Yes, he remembered 
     <lb/>the hon. member's taking him into a<lb/>back room at a Stubbs Hotel and having<lb/>quite a talk on the subject.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
   
    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName> said, then his hon.  
     <lb/>friend's memory must be greatly at<lb/>fault, for he had never spoken to him<lb/>about it except in open council.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said, he believed his     
     <lb/>hon. friend was to have had that office,<lb/>and it was kept open for him, but the<lb/>objection seemed to be that the salary<lb/>was too small.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName>  would now ask       
     <lb/>whether one of the points considered at<lb/>the time of the construction of the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment was not the carrying on of<lb/>Western Extension?<lb/>
            </p>
       
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName>.—" Yes."       
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName>  then wanted to know          
     <lb/>if they had not had troubles and difficul<lb break="no"/>ties with regard to this question, and if<lb/>he had not distinctly said that if action<lb/>
    
    
            <cb/>
            

     with regard to this was not embodied         
     <lb/>in the Speech, he would resign. Was<lb/>there not also difficulties in regard to the<lb/>Railway management?<lb/>
     
     
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName> rose to order. The      
     <lb/>hon. member had made his speech, and<lb/>had been listened to attentively by the <lb/>House, and unless there was some point<lb/>upon which he needed an explanation,<lb/>or a question he wished to ask, he had<lb/>no right to interrupt the hon. member<lb/>who was speaking by cutting in and<lb/>making another speech.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName>   said he had rights as             
     <lb/>well as other hon. members, and when<lb/>he spoke he was constantly interrupted<lb/>by three hon. members of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and on every occasion he gave <lb/>way and did not object to their ques<lb break="no"/>tions and remarks. His hon. colleague<lb/>had made statements yesterday of what<lb/>had occured, and had striven to show<lb/>that all had gone on harmoniously and<lb/>smoothly in the Council, and now he<lb/>wanted to show that difficulties did ex<lb break="no"/>ist, and that all did not go as smoothly<lb/>as a marriage bell.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">MR. FISHER</persName>  rose to the point of or<lb break="no"/>der, whilst he was speaking he was sub<lb break="no"/>jected to a runnimg fire from all quar<lb break="no"/>ters. He thought it was now too late<lb/>to say members should ask only one<lb/>question ; what was sauce for the goose<lb/>was sauce for the gander.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEED1">MR. NEEDHAM</persName>  thought that was       
     <lb/>all very well, but before applying the<lb/>same it was best to get it. He did not<lb/>hear any running fire kept upon his<lb/>hon. colleague. True, a few questions<lb/>had been asked, but they naturally arose<lb/>out of the statements made. And even<lb/>though interruptions had occured be<lb break="no"/>fore, which were wrong, that fact did<lb/>not make it right now.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName>  was sorry his hon. col<lb break="no"/>league misunderstood him. They never<lb/>had any angry words in the Government,<lb/>and hoped they would not, now they<lb/>were both out. He had told him yester<lb break="no"/>day that the Government had differences<lb/>among themselves, and serious differen<lb break="no"/>ces too, but they were men, and upheld by<lb/>arguments the opinions they entertained.<lb/>He was the first to leave the Government<lb/>on the grounds of Western Extensions,<lb/>and although his hon. friend had threat<lb break="no"/>ened to resign, if action were not taken, he<lb/>did not do so. He did not say yesterday<lb/>that all deliberations in the Council were<lb/>smooth and harmonious; he thought he<lb/>spoke plain, but the hon. member had <lb/>evidently misunderstood him. It was not<lb/>to be supposed that nine men coming to<lb break="no"/>gether would harmonise in their opinions<lb/>on all the subjects that came before them,<lb/>for honest men would speak out what they<lb/>thought. He did not wish to impute mo<lb break="no"/>tives to anyones, but wanted to work in <lb/>harmony with his colleagues. But he was<lb/>trying to answer the charges brought<lb/>against the Government by the member<lb/>for the City, that the Audit Office had not<lb/>been given to Mr. Wilmot. He thought<lb/>members of this House should not be ap<lb break="no"/>pointed to such offices—this House, which<lb/>is the bulwark and fortress of the liber<lb break="no"/>ties of the people. With regard to the<lb/>minor appointments, it was charged that <lb/>the Government did not fill them because<lb/>they were restrained by political coward<lb break="no"/>ice. But no, they were influenced by no<lb/>such feelings. He was now out of the<lb/>Government, but he was assured that they<lb/>refrained from filling these offices from <lb/>higher motives. He had differed on many<lb/>points with the hon. Attorney General,<lb/>
        
            <cb/>
         

     but that hon. member had never showed 
     <lb/>any such spirit as has been evinced by <lb/>some others from whom he differed. But<lb/>supposing these offices had been filled,<lb/>would the Government have been justi<lb break="no"/>fied, in the position of affairs, to have<lb/>made the appointments and thus sacrifice<lb/>their principles. Were they who were<lb/>elected by the people, and the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment who were the elect of the people's<lb/>representatives, to act in such a way as<lb/>to throw the country into the expense <lb/>and confusion of another election, when<lb/>strangers were ready to come in with their<lb/>gold and scatter the elements of dis<lb break="no"/>cord and ruin amongst us. Under<lb/>such circumstances, he would say that<lb/>any honesy, candid man, who had more<lb/>principle than to be accused by mere<lb/>feelings of friendship alone would<lb/>have acted exactly as the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had done. He did not wish<lb/>to disturb any man in his right to<lb/>holding any political opinions, to prevent<lb/>his expressing those opinions and voting<lb/>for them at the polls, but he would now<lb/>distinctly state that if he had his own<lb/>way in the matter he would turn out<lb/>many of the political partisians who fill<lb/>some of our public offices. He would<lb/>again repear that in this matter any hon<lb break="no"/>est, conscientious man would have acted<lb/>just as the Government did, and more, he<lb/>believed his hon. friend who brought these<lb/>charges would have acted just as he did,<lb/>had he been a member of the Government.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Another charge was that there were 
     <lb/>not more representatives from the North<lb/>Shore in the Council. To this he would<lb/>say, that it was the universal under<lb break="no"/>standing that when Confederation was<lb/>put out of view the North Shore was to<lb/>be more fully represented. If the North<lb/>feel that they have reason to complain<lb/>it was not the Government upon whom<lb/>the blame should rest, but upon those<lb/>whose machinations, as so ably describ<lb break="no"/>ed by the Provincial Secretary in his<lb/>most able speech the other day, have so<lb/>surrounded the Province and its Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment woth difficulties. These were<lb/>they upon whom the blame should rest.<lb/>It was well known the Government<lb/>were thus beset. and as long as the<lb/>North sent men to represent them, who<lb/>work with and for those who are thus <lb/>employed, the Government could not<lb/>take them into their Councils.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:KERR1">MR. KERR</persName>  asked if it was the mean<lb break="no"/>ing of the hon. member that he, as a<lb/>North Shore member, was sent here by <lb/>constituents who were working with <lb/>those who were seeking to ruin the<lb/>country. He wished the hon. member<lb/>to know that he represented a constitu<lb break="no"/>ency who were as respectable and loyal<lb/>a people as that which he (Mr. A.) re<lb break="no"/>presented.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> meant nothing of the  
     <lb/>kind; but when he spoke upon this<lb/>scheme, he must speak warmly— a<lb/>scheme to ruin and break up the coun<lb break="no"/>try, and although the hon. member<lb/>might entertain other opinions upon it,<lb/>yet he thought and the majority of the<lb/>people thought, and had unmistakeably<lb/>spoken out, that they thought different<lb break="no"/>ly.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">MR. LINDSAY</persName>.—" Try it again." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName>.—" Try it again!" yes, 
     <lb/>and whom the time comes to demand it<lb/>they would try it again, and as they re<lb break="no"/>turned to their constituents they would<lb/>say, " We as, not because we desire<lb/>it, but because of the clamoring of our<lb/>opponents, that you will speak again<lb/>
         

            <pb n="99" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_099.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">99</fw> 
   

     on this question, and that you will   
     <lb/>speak in more thundering tones and<lb/>by still more startling majorities than<lb/>before, that in this we have been the<lb/>true exponents of the public feeling."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DESB2">MR. L. P. W. DESBRISAY</persName> wished<lb/>to be allowed to ask why it was the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment pledged themselves to make<lb/>these appointments, and did not fulfil<lb/>them ? Was the promise given but to<lb/>deceive, or to place the followers of the<lb/>Government in a humiliating position ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> replied. It was from<lb/>no such motive, but because the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment had to care for the interests<lb/>of the whole people ; because they had<lb/>to act with caution in the face of their<lb/>opponents, like a small body of armed<lb/>men in the presence of a superior foe.<lb/>Hon. members complain becaue the<lb/>Audit Office was not filled, and seek for<lb/>all sorts of reasons why it was not filled.<lb/>They act as they did at the time Confed<lb break="no"/>eration was being discussed, imagine all<lb/>sorts of things, and search for something<lb/>and anything to show if possible that<lb/>the interests of the country have been<lb/>neglected, when the fact is that by not<lb/>filling this office some £300 have been<lb/>saved, and the accounts are presented<lb/>to the House in a better form than ever<lb/>they were before.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Last year they brought in a Bill to<lb/>abolish the office of Postmaster General,<lb/>and it was said that this was the first<lb/>step to the removal of the General Post<lb/>Office to St. John. They forgot that<lb/>the General Post Office had always been<lb/>in St. John up to within a few years,<lb/>and now he would say that he had heard<lb/>it hinted in this House, that somehow or<lb/>other that traitor and scoundrel Anglin<lb/>was going to make something out of it.<lb/>Mr. Howe was to be Postmaster Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, but that vagabond was somehow<lb/>or other going to put money in his<lb/>pocket by it. The hon. member from<lb/>Carleton (Mr. Lindsay) had hinted that<lb/>by some plan, though the Postmaster<lb/>Generalship might be done away, yet<lb/>there would be a need of an inspector, and<lb/>he (Mr. Anglin) was to get this ap<lb break="no"/>pointment. Now the hon. member<lb/>must know very little about the position<lb/>of members in the House, if he supposed<lb/>anything of the kind, for were this the<lb/>case he would have to resign his seat,<lb/>and at the same time neglect his duties<lb/>as editor and proprietor of a newspaper.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">MR. LINDSAY</persName> said he had not men<lb break="no"/>tioned the hon. member's name at all.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said it was not always<lb/>necessary to mention names, they un<lb break="no"/>derstood all about that, but his hon.<lb/>friend seemed to be of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">pachedermous</hi><lb/>kind, the more he was pounded the<lb/>harder his skin became. His hon. col<lb break="no"/>league from the City (Mr. Wetmore) had<lb/>said he seemed to be the dictator, and<lb/>had charge of the Government.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> remarked that it<lb/>seemed so still.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">MR. LINDSAY</persName> would ask the hon.<lb/>member (Mr. Anglin) to reconcile the<lb/>position he assumed on the hustings,<lb/>when he stated he would not belong to,<lb/>nor remain in, a Government which<lb/>would not build Western Extension.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said that wasa bomb<lb break="no"/>shell ! But he was coming to that bye<lb/>and bye. He was now speaking of the <lb/>Postmaster Generalship. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment believed that they could save the<lb/>salary of that officer, £600 a year, and<lb/>that the business would be better per<lb break="no"/>formed by a regular paid head. He was<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
        
pleased, however, to say, that since the<lb/>gentleman who now fills the office had<lb/>been appointed, the affairs of the De<lb break="no"/>partment had been performed as well<lb/>as by any previous head, and any one<lb/>who had reason to consult with him in<lb/>the affairs of his office could not but be<lb/>impressed by the business skill and tact<lb/>evinced by him.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Another charge was, that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had not filled the office of Solici<lb break="no"/>tor General. His hon friend on his left<lb/>(Mr. Wetmore) was marked out for<lb/>that, but it was found that gentleman<lb/>could not run his election, and so the<lb/>office was left to be filled by some mem<lb break="no"/>ber from the North Shore. He did not<lb/>know that the country had suffered<lb/>much by the non-appointment. If the<lb/>office had been filled, it is probable the<lb/>other charge with regard to the expiry<lb/>of the Act on the Export Duty would<lb/>not have come up, as between the At<lb break="no"/>torney General and the Solicitor Gener<lb break="no"/>al it could hardly have been overlooked,<lb/>and this brought him down to the<lb/>charge with regard to the Export Duty.<lb/>Here the Government was to blame, and<lb/>here only. During the last session of<lb/>the House, the Government worked<lb/>hard morning, noon and night. They<lb/>were overwhelmed with work. To be<lb break="no"/>gin with, they had no money. It had<lb/>been said that there was some $95,000<lb/>left in the treasury by the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, but the account with the Com<lb break="no"/>mercial Bank shows that this was not<lb/>the case. For out of all the large re<lb break="no"/>venue received from all sources, they<lb/>found, on taking office, only some<lb/>$8.000 or $9.000, and, as a set off, an<lb/>account of the Post Office considerably<lb/>over that. They had to look into these<lb/>matters, and to see what was the ar<lb break="no"/>rangement with the Messrs. Baring, our<lb/>agents in London. They asked the<lb/>Treasurer ; he did not know. They<lb/>asked the clerks in the office of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Secretary, but neither they nor<lb/>anybody else could tell them anything<lb/>about it, and the Government had to go<lb/>over the large fyle of letters to find out<lb/>what arrangement the late Government<lb/>had made with them. Then in the<lb/>Surveyor General's Office there was<lb/>another mess. The people there were clam<lb break="no"/>ering for the issue of grants of land. It<lb/>seems that pending the negotiations<lb/>with regard to the Inter-Colonial Rail<lb break="no"/>road, no grants could be issued on the<lb/>line of railway, and as everybody was<lb/>made to believe that the road was going<lb/>by their door, no grants were issued at<lb/>all, till the matter of route should be<lb/>decided. Then there was the providing<lb/>for the business of the session, the pre<lb break="no"/>paration of the speech, and that was no<lb/>easy matter. So there was work, and<lb/>hard work, for the Government all the<lb/>time.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     This matter of expiring Acts was pecu<lb break="no"/>liarly the duty of the Attorney General to<lb/>look after ; but hard-worked as he was,<lb/>sometimes till two o'clock in the morn<lb break="no"/>ing, he would say, under the circum<lb break="no"/>stances, he relieved him of all blame,<lb/>and took a share of it himself. The Act<lb/>expired not from want of industry ; they<lb/>might, if they choose, call it incapacity,<lb/>but not lack of industry or vigilance, and<lb/>they now throw themselves for this dere<lb break="no"/>liction of duty on the hands of the coun<lb break="no"/>try, and that was this House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Then there was the great bugbear of<lb/>the sale of Crown Lands, yet after all the<lb/>slanders circulated by a hireling press,<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
       
the Opposition had failed to take up this<lb/>charge in earnest and push the matter<lb/>home, some having fone so far as to say<lb/>that they wished there were more Mr. Gib<lb break="no"/>son's. The House knew that theprinciple in<lb/>every office should be that the heads<lb/>should not stand upon fine points. The<lb/>Government did put up 5000 acres for<lb/>sale ; but then the trouble was the rescind<lb break="no"/>ing of that celebrated order. Now this<lb/>order was made about the time Mr. Til<lb break="no"/>ley went to Canada on the Inter-Colonial<lb/>Railroad, and this regulation was made<lb/>pending those negotiations. It is said<lb/>that these are still pending. Pending ?<lb/>Between whom ? Is it the Governent<lb/>or the small minority who are in the Op<lb break="no"/>position who to day are in the country ?<lb/>These sayings can only be put forth to<lb/>mislead those who have been called by an<lb/>hon. member " the free and enlightened<lb/>electors." With regard to those apply<lb break="no"/>ing for lands, the Surveyor General de<lb break="no"/>cided that all the parties should come and<lb/>make their own applications. These<lb/>thousands of acres of land the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment are charged with selling have<lb/>gradually lessened till now they have<lb/>dwindled to twenty-seven acres, and this<lb/>was all that was left of the thousands.<lb/>But it turns out that these twenty-seven<lb/>acres was land granted to Z. Chipman in<lb/>1860, and so pure are the present Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment that the Opposition have to go<lb/>back and charge upon them the derelic<lb break="no"/>tion of their predecessors six years ago ;<lb/>and more than this, he learned that the<lb/>charge was to be reiterated, and these<lb/>lands were now to be announced as the<lb/>key to very valuable tracts of lands, but<lb/>he was in a position to say that the posi<lb break="no"/>tion of these twenty-seven acres, far<lb/>from being what was now alleged, was<lb/>situated at about four miles above where<lb/>log-cutting had taken place, and here it<lb/>was intended to construct a dam for the<lb/>purpose of bringing down the logs.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Government were also charged<lb/>with disloyalty, and why? Because he<lb/>and six others dared to speak out in the<lb/>language of freemen on a question affect<lb break="no"/>ing the rights and liberties of the people.<lb/>Feeling the position they occupied, and<lb/>the dangers that threatened out country,<lb/>they spoke in the interests of the people<lb/>what they had given them the right to<lb/>say, and he was proud that his name was<lb/>on that expression of the people's opinion.<lb/>It had been said that that dispatch was<lb/>drawn up by him and signed by the other<lb/>six after dinner at Government House :<lb/>in plain words, when they were drunk.<lb/>When he heard these charges made, he<lb/>looked upon his colleague, (Mr. Wilmot)<lb/>who claimed to be the personification of<lb/>knightly courtesy, the man who could<lb/>read Bishop Butler's opinion on what<lb/>true courtesy consists, and remember<lb break="no"/>ed that if the term, " low, despicable fel<lb break="no"/>low," which had been applied by an hon.<lb/>member, was applicable at all, then he, as<lb/>well as himself, was one of those charac<lb break="no"/>ters, for his name stands first on the list.<lb/>But what a charge is this. Is it to be be<lb break="no"/>lieved that men like the Hon. Mr. Odell,<lb/>the Provincial Secreatary, and the Survey<lb break="no"/>or General, at the Government House<lb/>table, while drunk, were worked upon by<lb/>that wily trai or Anglin, to sign that<lb/>memorandum ? No. It was worked on<lb/>paragraph by paragraph, sentence by sen<lb break="no"/>tence, and line by line. And how the<lb/>whole thing is brought down to the point<lb/>that the " low fellow" dared to doubt the<lb/>meaning of certain words used by Mr.<lb/>Cardwell, and to refer to the " Times '<lb/>
        

            <pb n="100" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_100.jpg"/>
      

     <fw type="num">100</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 
    

     newspaper. He would like his hon. 
     <lb/>
     friend to shew the book where it is laid 
     <lb/>
     down that, if a man is in doubt, it is un<lb break="no"/>gentlemanly to say he doubts ; and if no 
     <lb/>
     other charge than that could be brought 
     <lb/>
     against him, then he should go through 
     <lb/>
     life without being thought by very many 
     <lb/>
     as a " low fellow." It was said  that the 
     <lb/>
     reference to the newspaper paragraph was 
     <lb/>
     extraordinary, but then the circumstances 
     <lb/>
     were extraordinary. The hon. member 
     <lb/>
     on his left had said that at one time he 
     <lb/>
     did not believe the question of Union 
     <lb/>
     came from the Queen, and had since 
     <lb/>
     found out that it did. He thought it 
     <lb/>
     was rather hard to find out what had 
     <lb/>
     never occurred, and on this question he 
     <lb/>
     wished to say a few words. It was pro<lb break="no"/>bable that Her Majesty had never seen 
     <lb/>
     the dispatch which was sent from 
     <lb/>
     this Government to Mr.Cardwell, nor that 
     <lb/>
     from him to us. But however that might 
     <lb/>
     be, it was certain that the question of 
     <lb/>
     Union did not at first come from the 
     <lb/>
    British Government, or that the so-called  
     <lb/>delegates had any " just authority" to 
     <lb/>confer on the question of Confederation. 
     <lb/>In the report of the correspondence be<lb break="no"/>tween Nova Scotia and Mr. Cardwell, on 
     <lb/>the Union of the Maritime Provinces, in 
     <lb/>a letter under date September 29th, 1864, 
     <lb/> Sir Richard Graves Macdonnell says : 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " My Ministry are very anxious for the 
     <lb/>
     appointment of delegates from this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince to confer at Quebec with delegates 
     <lb/>
     from the other Maritime Provinces and 
     <lb/>Canada. The subject of the Conference 
     <lb/>is intended to be the feasibility of a Union, 
     <lb/>whether Federal or Legislative, of all 
     <lb/>British North America. Even Newfound<lb break="no"/>land is sending a representation ; and as 
     <lb/>the Conference is intended to commence 
     <lb/>on the 10th October, it would be impos<lb break="no"/>sible for the representatives of Nova Sco<lb break="no"/>tia to reach Quebec at that date, if I 
     <lb/>await your sanction to their appointment 
     <lb/>by the mail due at Halifax on the 12th 
     <lb/>October."  
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     There is no authority from the British 
     <lb/>
     Government for the Convention here. He 
     <lb/>
     goes on to say :   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " I find, however, on further enquiry,<lb/>that no official invitation such as I could<lb/>recognize has been yet received from<lb/>Lord Monck, adequate to justify my<lb/>nominating representatives of this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince to a Conference, <hi rendition="simple:italic">where, strictly<lb/>speaking, they should not proceed at all,<lb/>without your previous sanction</hi>."<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     There is no authority yet. And again,  
     <lb/>
     on the 1st October, Mr. Cardwell re<lb break="no"/>plied :   
     <lb/>
            </p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
   
            <p>
     " I have to thank you for the interest<lb break="no"/>ing intelligence you have conveyed to 
     <lb/>me, and to state, with reference to your<lb/>request for authority to permit certain<lb/>members of your Executive Council to<lb/>repair to Quebec, there to resume the dis<lb break="no"/>cussion of this subject, that I have receiv<lb break="no"/>ed an intimation from Lord Monck that<lb/>he intends communicating with me upon<lb/>it."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     So that up to the 1st October, only a 
     <lb/>few days befoe the meeting of the dele<lb break="no"/>gates, no dispatch had been received by<lb/>Mr. Cardwell from Lord Monck on the<lb/>subject, and the British Government had<lb/>given no authority for such a Confer<lb break="no"/>ence.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     They had all, at one time or another, 
     <lb/>
    

            <cb/>
          

     been in favor of a Union of some kind, 
     <lb/>
     but this scheme of Confederation was 
     <lb/>
     the grafting of old principles upon a 
     <lb/>
    new stock, and, consequently,  could 
     <lb/>bring forth nothing but fungi and rot<lb break="no"/>tenness.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Mr. Anglin</persName> then read from a paper, 
     <lb/>
     the organ of Mr. J. A. S. MacDonald, 
     <lb/>
     to show  that that gentleman had said 
     <lb/>that Canada was virtually without a Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, and it was to fill that want<lb/>that this plan of Confederation was<lb/>
    brought up. Here the secret sessions 
     <lb/>were first originated, and why ? Be<lb break="no"/>cause their deliberations could not bear 
     <lb/>the light. No, they loved the darkness,<lb/>and it seems very much adapted to the<lb/>politicians of Canada. And so, by in<lb break="no"/>volving these Lower Provinces in ruin,<lb/>a plan was laid by which a Government<lb/>could be provided for Canada. The<lb/>scheme was matured and presented to<lb/>the people of this Province. Mr. Mac<lb break="no"/>Donald says it was to be put through<lb/>the three Legislatures at once and he<lb/>(Mr. Anglin) though that the bold stand<lb/>taken by the Chief Commissioner of the<lb/>Board of Works was the means of sav<lb break="no"/>ing to us the liberties of this people.<lb/>The people here solemnly announced<lb/>their decision ; they had been told that<lb/>it must be passed without any change,<lb/>either the dotting of an i or the crossing<lb/>of a t, and then after all this, and the<lb/>matter, so far as we were concerned,<lb/>was concluded, they had the audacity<lb/>and insolence to speak for the people of<lb/>this Province, and appeal to Great Bri<lb break="no"/>tain to pass a law enforcing Union upon<lb/>us. Under such circumstances had the<lb/>Government not the right to clothe the<lb/>expression of their loyalty in such words<lb/>as would show to the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment that they rightly estimated the<lb/>liberties of the people as well as the<lb/>privileges of the Throne.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Mr. Anglin</persName> then read from page 204 
     <lb/>of the Journals of Assembly for last Ses<lb break="no"/>sion an extract from the despatches laid<lb/>before the House by the Government to<lb/>shew the Lieut. Governor had received<lb/>a copy of the Resolutions from Lord<lb/>Monck, and that, when submitted to the<lb/>Canadian Parliament, the 24th section<lb/>had been altered. These Resolutions,<lb/>which we were told could not be de<lb break="no"/>parted from one iota, where coolly altered<lb/>to suit the wishes of Canada without<lb/>consulting with the various parties in<lb break="no"/>terested. That section, as passed by the<lb/>Conference, was as follows :<lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " The local Legislature of each Pro<lb break="no"/>vince may, from time to time, alter the 
     <lb/>electoral districts for the purpose of re<lb break="no"/>presentation in the House of Commons,<lb/>and distribute the representatives to<lb/>which the Province is entitled in any<lb/>manner such Legislature may think<lb/>fit."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     But, instead of the words " in the 
     <lb/>House of Commons," as they called the<lb/>General Assembly, they substituted the<lb/>words " in such local Legislature."<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Now if Canada could serve us in such<lb/>a manner when treating with us on the<lb/>preliminaries—if they would thus alter<lb/>the great charter of our rights, is it to<lb/>be expected that they would treat us<lb/>otherwise afterwards? It appears that<lb/>after they had gone over the whole mat<lb break="no"/>ter and decised upon it—after even a<lb/>clear draft was made of the resolutions,<lb/>they found that a mistake had been<lb/>made. But did the Canadians thus alter<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
         

     the scheme without the assent of, or 
     <lb/>consultation with, our delegates. The<lb/>Hon. Mr. Steves, in reply to a circular<lb/>addressed to the delegates by the Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Secretary, at the request of the<lb/>Lieutenant Governor, says :<lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " I beg to state for the information of 
     <lb/>His Excellency the Lieutenant Gover<lb break="no"/>nor, that my consent has not been re<lb break="no"/>quested to any change in the wording<lb/>of the resolutions agreed to by the Con<lb break="no"/>ference held at Quebec in October last,<lb/>subsequently to their signature."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>J. M. Johnson, Esq., says the same,<lb/>although his letter is not given. Hon.<lb/>Mr. Chandler says :<lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " I have to say that no such consent 
     <lb/>was requested, nor was I made aware<lb/>of any change being made in the word<lb break="no"/>ing of any of the resolutions, after the<lb/>same were agreed to at the Confer<lb break="no"/>ence."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>The Hon. P. Mitchell says the same.<lb/>The Hon. J. H. Gray says the same,<lb/>only, unfortunately, he says too much.<lb/>He says :<lb/>
            </p>
   

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " No such consent was asked of me, 
     <lb/>nor have I directly or indirectly re<lb break="no"/>ceived any communication upon such a<lb/>subject."<lb/>
     
            </p></quote>

            <p>This would have been sufficient, but,<lb/>unfortunately for the result, he goes on<lb/>to add :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" And if I may be permitted to add<lb/>the expression of my personal belief, I<lb/>do not believe that in the wording of<lb/>the original resolutions, as signed by<lb/>myself and others of the delegates, any<lb/>alteration whatever has been made."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Mr. Tilley</persName> was the only one of the<lb/>delegates who was consulted, and he<lb/>remarks that he did not give his con<lb break="no"/>sent to a change in the decision of the<lb/>Conference. He also says that in a<lb/>letter he had received from Mr. Galt,<lb/>that gentlemen had asked, " if there<lb/>was not a mistake in the wording of the<lb/>24th resolution in the record signed by<lb/>the members of the Conference at Mon<lb break="no"/>treal, leaving to the local Legislatures<lb/>the power of determining the electoral<lb/>limits of the Confederate Legislature.<lb/>I find this letter on file, but I cannot<lb/>no remember whether or not I an<lb break="no"/>swered it ; if I did I have not kept a<lb/>copy."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>We had all heard of the very wonder<lb break="no"/>ful manner in which the business in the<lb/>office of the Provincial Secretary was<lb/>carried on, but he would not say any<lb break="no"/>thing against that gentleman, as he<lb/>had made it a point, both in his public<lb/>and private life, not to remark upon the<lb/>proceedings of those who were not in a<lb/>position to reply, and he was sure that<lb/>gentleman would bear him out in the<lb/>remark, that he had on all occasions re<lb break="no"/>frained from any personal expressions<lb/>calculated to wound his feelings.<lb/>Again, another delegate says in his re<lb break="no"/>ply to the circular :<lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " My assent was never requested to 
     <lb/>any change in the resolutions agreed to<lb/>by the Conference held at Quebec in<lb/>October last."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>He goes on to say :<lb/>
            </p>


            <pb n="101" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-06_Page_0101.jpg"/>
   

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">101</fw> 
  

   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " I cannot now remember what took 
     <lb/>place in the Conference when that reso<lb break="no"/>lution passed, nor do my minutes show,<lb/>as it was of very secondary importance<lb/>when compared with many of the ques<lb break="no"/>tions which were discussed."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     It is a question whether this was of 
     <lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">very secondary importance</hi>. But he goes<lb/>on : " I was not present when the re<lb break="no"/>vised copy, engrossed on parchment,<lb/>was signed by the delegation ; but I<lb/>signed alone some time afterwards upon<lb/>the assurance of Colonel Barnard, the<lb/>Secretary, that it was a true copy of<lb/>what had been agreed upon." He<lb/>signed on the sole authority of Mr. Bar<lb break="no"/>nard ! on so large and important a mea<lb break="no"/>sure without investigation ! This letter<lb/>is signed by Charles Fisher.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Here then it is distinctly proved that 
     <lb/>the Canadian delegates, without con<lb break="no"/>sulting any others who were equally<lb/>interesting in the Union proposed, alter<lb break="no"/>ed this document, which was to be at<lb/>once the bulwark and fortress of free<lb break="no"/>dom.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>It had been charged that the despatch<lb/>received from the British Government<lb/>was held back so as to send our delega<lb break="no"/>tion home, but he believed that had that<lb/>despatch been laid before the House by<lb/>the Government, it would have in<lb break="no"/>fluenced a larger number to vote for<lb/>that delegation. The Hon. Attorney<lb/>General had explained this matter, but<lb/>he (Mr. A.) was under the impression<lb/>that it was not received till a day or two<lb/>before the rising the House, and after<lb/>the delegation had been resolved on.<lb/>Upon this he could not now be confi<lb break="no"/>dent, but he was very strongly im<lb break="no"/>pressed that such was the case.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName> said that the des<lb break="no"/>patch bore no date of its receipt, but he<lb/>was sure it was but a few days before<lb/>the rising of the House that it was laid<lb/>before them.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> continued—The dis<lb break="no"/>patch of the 12th July had been condemn<lb break="no"/>ed in unmeasured terms, but what do the<lb/>Government there put forth to call down<lb/>the charge of disloyalty ? They say :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" A large majority of the people of this<lb/>Province are opposed to any closer politi<lb break="no"/>cal connection with Canada than that af<lb break="no"/>forded by the tie of a common allegiance to<lb/>the British Crown, and consider that such<lb/>union would have a decided tendency to<lb/>weaken that dependence on the British<lb/>Empire which they so highly prize,<lb/>and would lead to the neglect and injury of<lb/>their local interests."<lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>And, he would ask, were we not better<lb/>qualified to judge on these points than<lb/>Mr. Cardwell? No man will venture to<lb/>dispute that it was our right and duty to<lb/>consult our own interests in the matter,<lb/>and when Mr. Cardwell speaks of "just<lb/>authority," though it may not be coercion,<lb/>yet it was so near it that it became the<lb/>duty of the Government to speak out and<lb/>say, you may speak of ' just authority,'<lb/>but we have rights upon which you can<lb break="no"/>not infringe without weakening that au<lb break="no"/>thority."<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     Again, the Government in their dis<lb break="no"/>patch had said :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" When a wish is expressed by Her<lb/>Majesty's Government, it will be received<lb/>with that deference which is due to sug<lb break="no"/>gestions emanating from so high a<lb/>source."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
     

            <cb/>
            <p>And again :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" They feel assured that Her Majesty's<lb/>Government will expect and desire that<lb/>the Government of this Province should<lb/>act according to their own convictions of<lb/>right, and in conformity with the senti<lb break="no"/>ments of the people they represent."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>When the resolutions were first sent<lb/>home, Mr. Cardwell had complained of<lb/>some of the provisions, and yet now he<lb/>was anxious to thrust it upon us, and<lb/>well had he expressed his own and Mr.<lb/>Bright's views, which were, that we should<lb/>be thrown off on our own resources and<lb/>made to provide our own means of de<lb break="no"/>fence. The disposition of this people is<lb/>to hold on to the land they love, but he<lb/>looked upon the carrying out of this<lb/>scheme as the first stepping stone to an<lb break="no"/>nexation. When he heard in the Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive halls of Canada the statement of one<lb/>of their members, that he had done much<lb/>for that Province, and at length had<lb/>" brought these Colonies to the threshold<lb/>of independence," he knew that the whole<lb/>scheme pointed to this result. On their<lb/>late trip to Canada, they were at the<lb/>small town of Tecona, and learning that<lb/>Mr. Cartier was also there, he (Mr. A.)<lb/>called on him to pay his respects. In<lb/>the course of the conversation, Mr. Car<lb break="no"/>tier asked: " What do you say to the<lb/>dispatches down in the Lower Provinces?"<lb/>He replied that we were now almost dis<lb break="no"/>patch proof. Mr. Cartier said : "Oh, but<lb/>you must come in." He answered that<lb/>we should not come in if we found it was<lb/>not to our advantage. Mr. C. replied :<lb/>" Oh, but wait a few weeks till after<lb/>Smith gets back, and see what dispatches<lb/>you will get." Mr. Anglin said he did<lb/>not know, to which he replied, " <hi rendition="simple:italic">But I<lb/>know</hi>." Here, then, was the source from<lb/>whence the dispatches came—these dis<lb break="no"/>patches which were put forth as the<lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">ipsissima verba</hi>, the sacred word of Her<lb/>Majesty, when it was more than<lb/>probable that Her Majesty had never even<lb/>seen the despatch. It is well understood<lb/>that the Queen can do no wrong, and<lb/>herein consists the disloyalty and the<lb/>treason, for instead of making the Mini<lb break="no"/>ister of the Colonial Office responsible<lb/>for these acts they desire to turn the<lb/>point back upon the throne itself ; and<lb/>what, he woutd ask, is the good of con<lb break="no"/>stitutional liberties if such action is to<lb/>be tolerated. When the Government<lb/>received that despatch from Mr. Card-<lb break="yes"/>well, preceded as it had been by all that <lb/>previously had been said and done, they<lb/>felt themselves to be in a perilous posi<lb break="no"/>tion. Was it any wonder that they sat<lb/>down and carefully, calmly and serious<lb break="no"/>ly took the matter in hand, and in<lb/>speaking to Mr. Cardwell to speak in<lb/>unmistakeable language to the people<lb/>of Canada. Not in the midst of drunken<lb/>revelry, but as to slow, solemn and<lb/>earnest work, they sat themselves down<lb/>to the task. And now he would ask, was<lb/>there in that Memorandum of Council<lb/>one word derogatory to the Queen ; if<lb/>there was, he was willing to go on his<lb/>knees and recall it ; but there was not<lb/>one, and in all his public and private life<lb/>since his coming to the country, he chal<lb break="no"/>lenged any one to say that he had com<lb break="no"/>mitted an act that was derogatory to his<lb/>character or damaging to the best inter<lb break="no"/>ests of this Province, and once more he<lb/>would express the pride and satisfaction<lb/>he felt that his name was appended to<lb/>that document.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>The House and Debate were then ad<lb break="no"/>journed.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     As I have been called to take the posi<lb break="no"/>tion of Official Reporter, suddenly vaca<lb break="no"/>ted by Mr. Archer, and as I am conscious<lb/>of having done far less than justice to<lb/>this portion of Mr. Anglin's speech, I may<lb/>say that not having followed the debate<lb/>through its windings, and coming in on<lb/>the middle of a speech abounding with al<lb break="no"/>lusions to what had preceded it, it was al<lb break="no"/>most impossible that I should be in a<lb/>position to report with that correctness<lb/>and precision that an accurate acquaint<lb break="no"/>ance with the other speeches would have<lb/>given.</p>

<p rendition="simple:right"> J. MARCH,<lb/>
          <hi rendition="simple:italic">Official Reporter</hi>.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     [ERRATA—On 90th page, 20th line 
     <lb/>from top of 2nd column, read MR. HILL<lb/>said—By the amendment, &amp;c.<lb/>T. P. D.]<lb/>
            </p>
   <!-- GL, 2018-03-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

           <!-- <p>
     SATURDAY, APRIL 7. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On motion of MR. COSTIGAN, the 
     <lb/>House went into Committee on " A Bill<lb/>to encourage the exploration of vacant<lb/>Crown Lands and the discovery of Tim<lb break="no"/>ber Berths thereon." After some discus<lb break="no"/>sion, the progress was reported, and the Bill<lb/>referred to a Select Committee.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Further progress was made on " A Bill<lb/>to authorise the Woodstock Railway<lb/>Company to issue debentures."<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     ADJOURNED DEBATE ON MR. FISHER'S 
     <lb/>AMENDMENT.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName>.—Before I begin, I will 
     <lb/>express my regret at having occupied the<lb/>attention of the House so long. I felt,<lb/>and still feel, that the debate has hung<lb/>on so long that it is scarcely warrantable<lb/>to protract it, but some of the hon.<lb/>members wanted explanations of various<lb/>kinds, which so interrupted me as ren<lb break="no"/>dered it impossible for me to get<lb/>through yesterday. I do not want to<lb/>complain of it, but I bring it forward<lb/>as an excuse for taking up the time to<lb break="no"/>day. I concluded last evening with<lb/>drawing your attention to a despatch<lb/>from Mr. Cardwell, and was endeavour<lb break="no"/>ing to show what there was to justify<lb/>us in entertaining some doubts as to the<lb/>exact meaning of the despatch. There<lb/>was nothing ungenglemanly or uncour<lb break="no"/>teous in our conduct in expressing such<lb/>doubts. I would like to have you point<lb/>out to me what paragraph—what sen-<lb break="maybe"/>tence—what line, or what word there is<lb/>in that Memorandum in which there is<lb/>any thing disloyal or any thing that<lb/>evinces disrespect. True, we alluded to<lb/>the Times newspaper, but we knew that<lb/>those Canadian delegates were in Eng<lb break="no"/>land plotting against the liberties of<lb/>this country, and we knew they had<lb/>with them extraordinary resources to<lb/>enable them to do so. We found in<lb/>that paper false statements which had<lb/>originated in this Province, but had been<lb/>copied in that leading paper of the<lb/>world, and made the foundation of<lb/>newspaper articles; we believed these<lb/>articles were inspired by these Canadian<lb/>delegates and Mr. Cardwell and the<lb/>members of the Imperial Parliament<lb/>
            </p>-->
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>