<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1865-05-22"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-05-22">22 May 1865</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

    
          
            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1865</title>.
                    


     <date when="1865"/>.  



          <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="80" to="84"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0080.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0081.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0082.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0083.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0084.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-02-27">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-02-27">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0080">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0080.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0081">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0081.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0082">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0082.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0083">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0083.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0084">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0084.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="80" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0080.jpg"/>
      
     <fw type="num">80</fw>   <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> 


     <!-- GL, 2018-02-27, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->        
   
           <!-- <p>
     in too many cases they frequent. and keep 
     <lb/>
     them twenty-eight days under a rtrict 
     <lb/>
     discipline and subordination, that will re<lb break="no"/>sult in real good. If the question of the 
     <lb/>
     draft is the only difficulty in the way, hon. 
     <lb/>
     members need have no fear, for let the 
     <lb/>
     camp be stationed here at Fredericton, 
     <lb/>
     and give us the $30,000, and we'll keep it 
     <lb/>
     well supplied for years to come. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. —I am convinced that the 
     <lb/>draft is the most obnoxious thing that 
     <lb/>was ever introduced into a nation, and it 
     <lb/>is never adopted in any form in England, 
     <lb/>except under the most pressing difficul<lb break="no"/>ties.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>. — Under the old law 
     <lb/>
     all the men of the Province between the 
     <lb/>
     ages of 18 and 45 were called out for 
     <lb/>
     three days drill, whilst now we only ask 
     <lb/>
     for a certain number to form a camp of 
     <lb/>
     instruction, at a great saving of the time 
     <lb/>
     and producing labor of the country. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Hon. Mr. ALLEN</persName>. — The drafting of men 
     <lb/>for the Militia is not now introduced for 
     <lb/>the first time; it was established in the<lb/>Bill which passed in 1862. The 16th Sec<lb break="no"/>tion of that Bill contains the same princi<lb break="no"/>ple as this. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SUTT1">Mr. SUTTON</persName>. —If' I thought the draft 
     <lb/>
     would ever be enforced, and it would be 
     <lb/>
     compulsory for' men to leave their homes 
     <lb/>
     to go to camp, I would vote against it, but 
     <lb/>
     as I believe there will be plenty of volun<lb break="no"/>teers I am willing to support this Section. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. BOTSFORD. —Although the 
     <lb/>
    principle of drafting was established in 
     <lb/>1862 yet it was never enforced, as people 
     <lb/>came forward voluntarily. My hon. col<lb break="no"/>league, (Mr. Gilbert) although opposed to 
     <lb/>the draft here, joins the hon. members for 
     <lb/>Carleton, who were willing enough to take 
     <lb/>our men and send then off to Canada to 
     <lb/>fight her battles there under Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. He says, things have changed; he 
     <lb/>too has changed, when he joins those who 
     <lb/>were desirous to force Confederation upon 
     <lb/>us. The hon. member for Carleton, (Mr. 
     <lb/>Connell) when asked, What shall we do?<lb/>says, Do as Canada does. Canada, who<lb/>has brought down the estimate England<lb/>held of these Colonies by refusing to es<lb break="no"/>tablish a system for defence. I think,<lb/>however, when it is known in England<lb/>what we are doing here, she will not con<lb break="no"/>sider us so disloyal nor so fond of annex<lb break="no"/>ation as they would make us out to be.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. McMILLAN. — The Hon. President<lb/>of the council says there are secret influ<lb break="no"/>ences at work against us in Canada and in<lb/>Nova Scotia. I would ask, Is it right for<lb/>a gentleman holding the high position he<lb/>does in this Province, to say that his fel<lb break="no"/>low colonists are animated by such un<lb break="no"/>worthy feelings, without producing some<lb/>proof. The Hon. Surveyor General seems<lb/>to be willing to shut us up entirely<lb/>to ourselves. Build a wall round<lb/>New Brunswick, like that around<lb/>China; don't break the eggshell that<lb/>separates us from the great world;<lb/>isolate us, cut us off rather from our fel<lb break="no"/>low men. and if an enemy enters Canada<lb/>at Niagara, don't go the resistance of our<lb/>fellow colonists, but leave them to do as<lb/>best they can. I believe that without<lb/>Confederation we cannot have the defen<lb break="no"/>ces of Militia in a proper conditions. They<lb/>will be of no actual service till we have<lb/>them all united under the general direc<lb break="no"/>tion of one head.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName> replied to some personal<lb/>remarks made by Hon. Mr. Botsford, and<lb/>then Progress was reported.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The SPEAKER having resumed his seat<lb/>the House adjourned to meet on Monday<lb/>morning at 9 o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>J.M.<lb/>
            </p>

    
            <milestone type="unknown"/>-->
        
<head rendition="simple:right">MONDAY, May 22.</head>
     

            <p>On motion of Mr. CONNELL, the House 
     <lb/>went into Committee for the further con<lb break="no"/>sideration of "A Bill to authorize the 
     <lb/>the municipality of the County of Carleton to 
     <lb/>issue debentures for a Railway purpo<lb break="no"/>ses."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILL1">Mr. WILLISTON</persName> — Are the members of<lb/>the County of Carleton unanimous in their<lb/>desire that the lands of the whole County<lb/>should be taxed to support the views of<lb/>the municipality of Carleton? The Bill<lb/>which passed this House for the purpose 
     <lb/>of aiding the construction of the St. Ste 
     <lb/>phen Branch Railway authorizes the tax<lb break="no"/>ing of all property in a certain district 
     <lb/>which was to be benefitted by the road; 
     <lb/>but here the Whole County will have to 
     <lb/>be taxed, a large proportion of which will 
     <lb/>receive no benefit from the Railroad at 
     <lb/>all.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName>. — According to the first 
     <lb/>
     secton of this Bill, the municipality frame 
     <lb/>
     a Bill, which they send down to the 
     <lb/>
     Government to sanction, and all the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment has to do is see that it is in 
     <lb/>
     accordance with the laws of the Province, 
     <lb/>
     thus you give the municipality of Carleton 
     <lb/>
     the right to legislate for that County. 
     <lb/>
     The Corporation of St. John, with its 
     <lb/>
     executive powers and credit, have no such 
     <lb/>
     power vested in them; when they want 
     <lb/>
     to borrow money the whole thing must be 
     <lb/>
     set out in a law, and by that law they 
     <lb/>
     must borrow it ; but here you authorize 
     <lb/>
     the municipality to do the whole legis<lb break="no"/>lation, which is to affect the rights of 
     <lb/>thousands of people; and the Governor in 
     <lb/>Council must sanction their acts if they 
     <lb/>are not contrary to this law, or any other 
     <lb/>law in the Province. This Bill should 
     <lb/>cover the whole thing. It should show 
     <lb/>the form of debentures and what security  
     <lb/>should be given. It involves a large 
     <lb/>amount of money, and we are going 
     <lb/>through it with Railroad speed, none of 
     <lb/>us understanding its importance. This 
     <lb/>piecemeal legislation is the worst kind we 
     <lb/>can have. We are giving up our rights<lb/>as a legislative body and putting it in the<lb/>hands of a municipality, investing them<lb/>with a power they ought not to hvae, and<lb/>which we have not right to give them.<lb/>They should have inserted in their Bill<lb/>all that we required to render it of value<lb/>so that it would have protected the rights<lb/>of all parties, for if we do not secure those<lb/>rights to the people we depart from the<lb/>true principles of legislation.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. — I would be willing to<lb/>amend it if the President of the Council<lb/>thinks it necessary, for the people of Car<lb break="no"/>leton are anxious to develope the resour<lb break="no"/>ces of the country, but are not now ask<lb break="no"/>ing for anything, but the privilege of<lb/>assessing themselves for the purpose of<lb/>carrying on a public work, and I do not<lb/>
               <lb/>think any public rights are invaded by<lb/>doing so; if we were going to tax the<lb/>whole country there might be some rea<lb break="no"/>son in the arguments of the hon. member<lb/>for York, and if he would bring in a simi<lb break="no"/>lar measure for his County, I would en<lb break="no"/>courage it, for I believe we should encour<lb break="no"/>age those who are willing to help them<lb break="no"/>selves.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>. — If the hon. members<lb/>for the County of Carleton will take the<lb/>responsibility of this measure, I will sup<lb break="no"/>port the Bill; but I object to giving the<lb/>people the power to legislate on this ques<lb break="no"/>tion, because it is inconsistent with our<lb/>constitution; reference has been made to<lb/>the Seho[....] Law, but that is not a parallel<lb/>case with this; that merely gives permis<lb break="no"/>sive power to the people to accept the<lb/>provision of a law already made, I want<lb/>to record my opinion against this measure<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
    

     which entirely ignores the principle of 
     <lb/>
     representative Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>. — It appears to be the im<lb break="no"/>pression of the hon. member from Carle<lb break="no"/>ton that. this is a local matter, and no other 
     <lb/>
     part of the Province is interested in it. 
     <lb/>
     If the hon. member will raise the money 
     <lb/>
     in the County of Carleton; if the people of 
     <lb/>
     Carleton will agree to tax themselves, and 
     <lb/>
     raise the money among themselves, it 
     <lb/>
     would be well enough: but under this 
     <lb/>
    Biil there is no mention made of where 
     <lb/>thesé bonds are to be sold. They may be 
     <lb/>sold in the English market at fifty per 
     <lb/>cent discount, and by that means still 
     <lb/>further depress our Provincial securities, 
     <lb/>which are now selling at eight per cent 
     <lb/>discount; therefore, every. man in this 
     <lb/>Province is interested in this matter. I 
     <lb/>feel satisfied we are entering upon. what I 
     <lb/>consider to be a dangerous principle; that 
     <lb/>a law can be made by this Legislature 
     <lb/>and then rendered nugatory by an assem<lb break="no"/>bly of the people. It is not so in the 
     <lb/>School law to which reference has been 
     <lb/>made. That law still remains the law of 
     <lb/>the land; people do not have to pass a vote 
     <lb/>upon it to say whether it shall be the law 
     <lb/>of the land or not, but have simply to say 
     <lb/>in each locality whether they will accept 
     <lb/>its provisions or not. By adopting the 
     <lb/>principle contained in this Bill, we are 
     <lb/>entering upon a course which if followed 
     <lb/>up, will be utterly disastrous. We are in 
     <lb/>a different position in regard to building 
     <lb/>railroads from Canada; we have to import 
     <lb/>from abroad nearlyn all we require to build 
     <lb/>them, and by that means are involved in 
     <lb/>an amount of expenditure which has redu<lb break="no"/>ced our revenue very materially; whereas 
     <lb/>In Canada they have the most of the ma<lb break="no"/>terial in their own Province. It is, there<lb break="no"/>fore, absurd to say this Bill will not affect 
     <lb/>the welfare of the people of the whole 
     <lb/>Province, for every pound our debentures 
     <lb/>are sold below par is a loss to the whole 
     <lb/>country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HATH1">Hon. Mr. HATHEWAY</persName>. — if we had never   
     <lb/>constructed a line of Railway in this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince our revenues would have been in a<lb/>better position than they are at present;<lb/>but having commenced their construction,<lb/>they will not yield a revenue until ex<lb break="no"/>tended.By grants and legislation we<lb/>have a line of Railway to within eleven<lb/>miles of the village of Woodstock, which<lb/>will be extended upwards, and if there<lb/>will be any line likely to pay it will be the<lb/>connection between Woodstock and the<lb/>St. Andrews Railway. The people of<lb/>Carleton have just as good right to put<lb/>their debentures in the market as the<lb/>people of St. Stephen; but there is a prin<lb break="no"/>ciple involved in this Bill, and I shall vote<lb/>against it without the members of the<lb/>County of Carleton take the responsibility,<lb/>for they are here as the exponents of pub<lb break="no"/>lic opinion in that County. If they will<lb/>strike out that section f the Bill which<lb/>refers it back to the people, I will vote <lb/>for it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HILL1">Mr. HILL</persName> — One objection taken by the<lb/>hon. member for Northumberland if, that<lb/>those debentures proposed to be issued by<lb/>the municipality of Carleton, if floated in<lb/>the English market, will depress our<lb/>Provincial debentures. I think this ap<lb break="no"/>prehension is most unfounded. If the<lb/>debentures of Carleton sell at a discount<lb/>it is not reason why the Provincial deben<lb break="no"/>tures should any more than the de<lb break="no"/>bentures of a city in Massachusetts would<lb/>affect the bonds of the State. Capitalists<lb/>in buying those bonds look at the se<lb break="no"/>curity, and if the municipality of Carleton<lb/>cannot give good security they cannot<lb/>sell those debentures, and in consequence<lb/>cannot build this road. Reference has<lb/>
     

            <pb n="81" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0081.jpg"/>
        
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">81</fw>

  

     been made to the town of St. Stephen         
     <lb/>putting their debentures in the English<lb/>market. I do not think they will go be<lb break="no"/>yond the river St. Croix, there being only<lb/>$150,000 required. Suppose the city of<lb/>St. John had, by its Common Council,<lb/>asked this Legislature to authorize them<lb/>to take stock in Western Extension to an<lb/>amount not exceeding $400,000, and an<lb/>"Act" for that purpose had passed with<lb break="no"/>out a clause submitting it to the people,<lb/>would there be anything to prevent its<lb/>being submitted to the people ? They<lb/>could say the law authorizes us to issue<lb/>bonds to that extent. Now, shall we<lb/>take stock to the extent of ten, fifty, or a<lb/>hundred thousand dollars. It would be<lb/>perfectly legal to do so, and the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture could not interfere with them. In<lb/>like manner, if we pass this Bill without<lb/>that section, it will be perfectly legal to<lb/>refer it to the people.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HATH1">Hon. Mr. Hatheway</persName>. - Suppose they       
     <lb/>do not accept it ?<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:HILL1">Mr. Hill</persName>. - Then the law would become         
     <lb/>inoperative. We passed a law authoriz<lb break="no"/>ing the Magistrates of St. Stephen to<lb/>make an assessment, but they need not<lb/>order that assessment unless they choose<lb/>to do so. It has been said that " all power<lb/>emanates from the people," but now it is<lb/>stated that it is not constitutional, or in<lb/>the power of the Legislature, to give back<lb/>into the hands of the people any of that<lb/>power. This is going back to the old<lb/>doctrine of the " divine right of Kings;"<lb/>that doctrine was held sacred and it was<lb/>contended that Kings had no power to<lb/>divest themselves of this right, or delegate<lb/>it to others. In this Legislature the doc<lb break="no"/>trine is advanced that its powers are so<lb/>sacred that we cannot delegate any part<lb/>of those powers back to the people of<lb/>Carleton, by accepting a Bill which allows<lb/>them to decide whether they will tax<lb/>themselves or not. It has been said that<lb/>the members of the County of Carleton<lb/>should represent the opinions of that<lb/>County, they may represent their political<lb/>views on Confederation, but may not re<lb break="no"/>present the views of a majority of the<lb/>County on finance ; therefore, I should<lb/>like to see this question submitted direct<lb break="no"/>ly to the people in order to guard their<lb/>interests, for I believe it is an important<lb/>measure. This road will be a great bene<lb break="no"/>fit to the town of Woodstock and the sur<lb break="no"/>rounding country, by bringing them nearer<lb/>to a market, and consequently enhance<lb/>the value of Agricultural produce. As<lb/>soon as Western Extension is built, it<lb/>will bring them into direct communica<lb break="no"/>tion with St. John, and this branch will be<lb/>a feeder to that road. I believe the only<lb/>way in which private enterprise can build<lb/>railroads in this country, is by the assist<lb break="no"/>ance of counties and towns in the shape<lb/>of guarantees.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:ALLA1">Hon. Mr. Allan</persName>. - As this discussion         
     <lb/>is likely to occupy a great deal of time,<lb/>and as the introduction of this dangerous<lb/>principle is not fully understood, I intend<lb/>to move that the Bill be referred to a Se<lb break="no"/>lect Committee ; if this is not done, I<lb/>shall vote against the Bill. If we adopt<lb/>the principle contained in the Bill, we<lb/>could refer every measure involving a tax<lb/>to the people - even to the building of any<lb/>public building, court house, or gaol - and<lb/>divest ourselves of all responsibility.<lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. Lindsay</persName>. - The building of a Court <lb/>House or Jail is a necessity, and if we<lb/>passed a Bill to provide for the erection<lb/>of those buildings, we could issue a man<lb break="no"/>damus and compel the people to erect<lb/>them.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. Connell</persName>. - The whole population <lb/>are interested in this road, except a few<lb/>

            <cb/>
          

     
     
     in one Parish, and leaving this Bill to the      
     <lb/>people will remove their objections. In<lb/>reference to the motion of the Attorney<lb/>General, I would rather see the Bill post<lb break="no"/>poned for three months than to have it<lb/>referred to a Committee, for that would<lb/>be evading the question and prevent us<lb/>from getting a railroad at all.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. Smith</persName>. - I think we had bet-      
     <lb/>ter test the question whether this House<lb/>will affirm the principle of referring these<lb/>questions to the people, or not.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. McMillan. - I do not see why, in <lb/>a mere local matter, the people of Carle<lb break="no"/>ton should not be the best judges of whe<lb break="no"/>ther they will adopt that Bill or not, as<lb/>they have to pay the tax ; we have estab<lb break="no"/>lished the principle in our School law,<lb/>and in the construction of public works<lb/>the Government often state that if the<lb/>people will do certain things the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will aid them ; as for instance, the<lb/>Facility Bill granted $10,000 a mile for<lb/>railroads, upon condition that Companies<lb/>would build them. We have established<lb/>the principle in the St. Stephen Branch<lb/>Railroad, and why should we deal in a<lb/>different manner with the people of Carle<lb break="no"/>ton? It is a charge made against their<lb/>intelligence and common sense to say<lb/>they should not have the liberty to tax<lb/>themselves to carry on a certain work,<lb/>and this argument put forth by some of<lb/>the members of the Government, is a doc<lb break="no"/>trine from which I entirely dissent.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Hon. Mr. Gillmor. - We are charging  
     <lb/>the people of Carleton with a great amount<lb/>of ignorance when we charge them with<lb/>having elected men who do not understand<lb/>their wants. I do not see why they should<lb/>not take the responsibility of this mea<lb break="no"/>sure. I would make it imperative upon<lb/>members representing localities to take<lb/>the responsibility of their local Bills. In<lb/>regard to the School law, that is not a<lb/>parallel case ; according to that law any<lb/>particular locality can avail themselves of<lb/>its provisions, but cannot disannul it ; but<lb/>I think we established the principle in<lb/>the case of the St. Stephen's line, and it<lb/>is a dangerous principle, and should not<lb/>be carried out to any great extent, and<lb/>only under peculiar circumstances. In<lb/>this case a large majority of the people<lb/>must be benefited, and if they are willing<lb/>to tax themselves, I will, under these cir<lb break="no"/>cumstnces, vote for the Bill, for I do not<lb/>believe a few individuals should retard any<lb/>great work.<lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. - Connell moved the following as  
     <lb/>the 6th Section of the Bill, " Before any<lb/>by-law passed under the authority of this<lb/>Act shall be transmitted to the Provincial<lb/>Secretary for the apaproval of the Governor<lb/>in Council, it shall be published in a news<lb break="no"/>paper published in the County, and a copy<lb/>sent to the Town Clerk in every town and<lb/>parish, who shall call a meeting of the<lb/>rate-payers on property for the purpose of<lb/>considering the by-law at the time and<lb/>place to be prescribed by the County<lb/>Council, by posting up notices in three or<lb/>more of the most public places in the<lb/>Parish, at least twenty days before the<lb/>day appointed for the meeting. The meet<lb break="no"/>ing shall be organized and the votes taken<lb/>for and against the by-law, and certified<lb/>by the Chairman of the meeting to the<lb/>Secretary Treasurer of the municipality,<lb/>in the same manner as in the case of the<lb/>election of County Councillors, or Town<lb/>and Parish officers. If it is made to ap<lb break="no"/>pear that a majority of the rate-payers on<lb/>property at such meeting vote for such<lb/>by-law, the Governor in Council is autho<lb break="no"/>to approve thereof, otherwise the<lb/>said by-law shall be made inoperative."<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. Wetmore read an extract from a     
     <lb/>
          

            <cb/>
      
law passed in 1862 establishing municipal<lb/>authorities, and proceeded to show that<lb/>the people could take the benefit of that<lb/>law if they thought proper, and he could<lb/>not see the distinction between the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of that and the measure now before<lb/>them, authorizing certain parties to take<lb/>advantage of the Facility Bill and tax<lb/>themselves to construct this portion of<lb/>Railroad.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Needham. - The hon. member who <lb/>has last addressed you has mistaken the<lb/>point ; that law regarding municipal cor<lb break="no"/>porations is not disannulled ; if the people<lb/>adopt it in one County they can in another.<lb/>The section introduced by the hon. mov<lb break="no"/>er of the Bill renders the whole law in<lb break="no"/>operative, provided the people reject it,<lb/>and is an introduction of republican in<lb break="no"/>stitutions.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     
     
         Mr. Connell. - The vote on this sec<lb break="no"/>tion will either prevent the road being<lb/>built, or aid and assist it.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     
     
         Mr. Needham. - That is an unfair way        
     <lb/>to state it. I do not vote against the<lb/>people of Carleton having the benefit of<lb/>the Facility Bill, but I vote against the<lb/>principle which it establishes.<lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
         Mr. Cudlip. - The case is one of emer-        
     <lb/>gency ; it is one of vital interest to the<lb/>people, and not an every day matter ; if<lb/>it was an ordinary matter I should vote<lb/>against it. The members of the County<lb/>have made themselves responsible for the<lb/>measure by advocating the principle that<lb/>this Railroad is necessary, and are willing<lb/>the people should be taxed for it. I<lb/>shall take no vote as a precedent, and<lb/>shall not be bound three years hence by<lb/>my vote now, for I may change my<lb/>opinions. I hold that a man has a perfect<lb/>right to change his opinions when he sees<lb/>they are wrong.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     
     
          Mr. Beveridge. - The hon. members  
     <lb/>for Carleton will be disappointed if the<lb/>Bill does not pass, for two-thirds of the<lb/>people of that County are in favor of it,<lb/>and they have a right to be heard.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    The House was now divided on this <lb/>section, when there appeared 13 yeas and<lb/>14 nays.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Connell. - I move that the Bill <lb/>be postponed for three months. If we<lb/>force this Bill upon the people it will<lb/>create a great deal of dissatisfaction. In<lb/>Nova Scotia a Bill was passed to tax the<lb/>people for the purpose of constructing a<lb/>road from Halifax to Windsor, without<lb/>the people being heard on the question.<lb/>The consequence was that the people re<lb break="no"/>sisted the measure, and the difficulty was<lb/>so great that it had to be abandoned.<lb/>When the Liquor Law was first intro<lb break="no"/>duced, I understood it contained a clause<lb/>to refer it to the people, and I was in fa<lb break="no"/>vor or it. I believe if that clause had<lb/>been in the Bill, a majority of the people<lb/>would have sanctioned it, and probably<lb/>now it would have been the law of the<lb/>land. People have told my colleague and<lb/>myself that we were going to force this<lb/>measure upon them. I said I never would<lb/>give my consent to have a Bill of that<lb/>kind pass without being referred to the<lb/>people. There is hardly a place in Cana<lb break="no"/>da where the principle is not adopted.<lb/>If the hon. members wished to prevent<lb/>us from building this Railway, they have<lb/>accomplished their object.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Hon. Mr. Smith. - It is not our duty <lb/>to deviate from a principle in order to<lb/>make our legislation harmonize with the<lb/>promises made at the hustings by the<lb/>hon. member from Carleton. If the people<lb/>of Carleton want this Bill, which is of so<lb/>much importance, and a majority of the<lb/>people of the County are in favor of it,<lb/>the hon. member is recicant to his duty<lb/>
     
            <pb n="82" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0082.jpg"/>
          
<fw type="num">82</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>
     
      in not taking the responsibility of it. I 
     <lb/>think my hon. friend had better take the<lb/>Bill as it stands.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. Needham</persName>. - The Bill is not im<lb break="no"/>perative, - as it stands they need not act <lb/>upon it. I am not going to vote to post<lb break="no"/>pone it, when eighteen out of twenty in<lb/>the municipality said they wanted it.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. Lindsay. - We want the matter to       
     <lb/>go before the country fairly, that we are<lb/>not willing to have this Bill forced upon<lb/>them. If we pass this Bill it will go into<lb/>operation under the present Council, and<lb/>it is not known whether they represent<lb/>the wishes of the County on this question.<lb/>
     
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. Smith</persName>. - Was not the Bill     
     <lb/>sent down here by the municipality<lb/>
     
            without the amendment? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
                <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. Lindsay</persName>.- The Municipality party  
     <lb/>may have been satisfied with the Bill as it<lb/>stands, but some of the people deny<lb/>that they represent their wishes on this<lb/>subject, and they have no more right to<lb/>carry out the provisions of the Bill than<lb/>the late House would have had to have<lb/>decided on the question of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, without leaving it to the people.<lb/>The promises I made at the hustings I<lb/>shall always endeavor to carry out.<lb/>
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
             <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName>. - I cannot discover any 
     <lb/>new system of legislation in leaving a<lb/>measure of this kind to the people. I<lb/>do not see why two thirds of the inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants of a County, if they choose to im<lb break="no"/>pose a tax upon themselves, should be<lb/>prevented from doing so, if it was not in<lb break="no"/>jurious to the country generally. It is<lb/>a local matter, and these hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>men do take the responsibility in asking<lb/>the House to pass a law in this way.<lb/>    Upon the question being taken the <lb/>Bill was agreed to as amended.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Hon. Mr. Allen</persName> moved the House       
     <lb/>into a Committee of the Whole for the<lb/>further consideration of a BILL RELATING<lb/>TO THE MILITIA.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>

            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. Young</persName> in the Chair.     
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:CUDL1">Mr. Cudlip</persName>, in continuing the discus<lb break="no"/>sion on the 24th Section said, - I do not<lb/>think there will be the least difficulty<lb/>in finding men to form this camp, with<lb break="no"/>out drafting them. The draft works<lb/>unfairly, and will tend to make the Bill<lb/>unpopular, for it favors the rich to the<lb/>detriment of the poor man, because if a<lb/>rich man is drafted he can afford to hire<lb/>a substitute, but a poor man has not the<lb/>means to do so, but is compelled to<lb/>leave his home and attend this camp,<lb/>however unwilling he may be. I think<lb/>that even in actual invasion the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment should find material to carry on<lb/>the war out of the property of the coun<lb break="no"/>try without resorting to a draft. I shall<lb/>move this amendment to the section ;<lb/>instead of the words Commander-in-<lb break="yes"/>Chief, substitute " His Excellency the<lb/>Lieutenant Governor, or the Comman<lb break="no"/>der-in-Chief for the time being, by and<lb/>with the consent of Her Majesty's Exe<lb break="no"/>cutive Council."<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. Needham</persName>. - I do not know what 
     <lb/>the advice of the Executive has to do with<lb/>the Commander-in-Chief in the regula<lb break="no"/>lation of the militia and the appointment<lb/>of officers ; it would be inconsistent with<lb/>this law, and would make it a mass of <lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">heterogenious conglomorate nonsense</hi>. The<lb/>Government should have nothing to do<lb/>with these militia promotions, calling<lb/>out men and drafting them, except it is<lb/>a question of finance.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Col. Boyd</persName>. - We had better let the<lb/>section stand as it is.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Hon Mr. Allen</persName>. - The civil branch 
     <lb/>of the Government has nothing to do<lb/>with advising the Commander-in-Chief<lb/>about military movements. The hon.<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
   

     member for Resigouche speaks of hav<lb break="no"/>ing one head for the forces under Con<lb break="no"/>federation ; that would be in Canada ;<lb/>surely it would be better to have that<lb/>head in this Province. The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Carleton said there was no such<lb/>thing as drafting men in England. If<lb/>the hon. member will take the trouble<lb/>to look in the militia law of England he<lb/>will find that there is a compulsory law<lb/>there to compel men to attend military<lb/>drill. The volunteers are a separate<lb/>branch of the service, and can attend or<lb/>not as they see fit.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. Lindsay</persName>. - Do you say they draft  
     <lb/>the militia in England?<lb/>
     
     
            </p>

            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Hon. Mr. Allen</persName>. - I do ; the Queen       
     <lb/>is the head of the army and the militia,<lb/>and she has power to raise companies<lb/>by a draft. It is the same in this coun<lb break="no"/>try, the Commander-in-Chief is head of<lb/>the militia, irrespective of the advice of<lb/>the Executive Council. This has been<lb/>the case formerly, and when we passed<lb/>a militia law in 1862, there as no such<lb/>objection taken to it as there is now.<lb/>I do not say the hon. gentleman has not<lb/>a right to change his mind if anything<lb/>has occurred in those years to make it<lb/>necessary to repeal the law passed then,<lb/>but unless they can show some reason<lb/>why this power should not be vested in<lb/>the Commander-in-Chief, it is wrong to<lb/>insert those words. If the principle is<lb/>right that the Commander-in-Chief has<lb/>power to call out the militia for five days,<lb/>the same principle will apply to twenty<lb/>days. I do not think the members of<lb/>the Council desire the patronage of ap<lb break="no"/>pointing the officers, for they have plenty<lb/>to do, and plenty of responsibility with<lb break="no"/>out it. Those appointments have been<lb/>generally made in accordance with the<lb/>recommendation of the Colonel of the<lb/>Battalion, and I do not think it is desir<lb break="no"/>able to make any change.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
             <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. Gilbert</persName>. - I think my hon. friend, 
     <lb/>the Attorney General, does not like to<lb/>assume the responsibility which this<lb/>amendment would impose upon the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment. The Queen cannot draft the<lb/>militia, or exercise her prerogative on<lb/>any question of importance, without the<lb/>consent of her Privy Council. When<lb/>the militia bill of 1862 was before the<lb/>House I took exception to it then as I<lb/>do now.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. Connell</persName>. - I think the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment should advise in those matters<lb/>where the people are interested. We<lb/>have been a Government of progress,<lb/>but I fear as matters are going now we<lb/>can call it by that name no longer, for<lb/>we are going back to the dark ages. It<lb/>has been stated that such a thing never<lb/>existed as the Commander-in-Chief be<lb break="no"/>ing advised by his Council, but if you<lb/>look back to the year 1838, you will find<lb/>that such a law did exist in this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. At that time the whole resources<lb/>of the Province were voted by the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature in order to put down the rebellion<lb/>
               <lb/>in Canada ; and the third section of a law<lb/>passed at that time says, "The Com<lb break="no"/>mander-in-Chief, by the advice of his<lb/>Executive Council." That Bill was<lb/>passed for the purpose of defending our<lb/>institutions and aiding our fellow colon<lb break="no"/>ists in putting down what was called the<lb/>rebellion. If the Government choose to<lb/>force this Bill through the House they<lb/>should take the responsibility of advis<lb break="no"/>ing the Commander-in-Chief. At pre<lb break="no"/>sent they have nothing to do with the<lb/>Bill after it passes the House, and the<lb/>whole thing will be carried out by some<lb/>militia colonels who will get a sword<lb/>by their side and a feather in their cap,<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
   

     and lord it over the rest, being respon<lb break="no"/>sible to no one.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Gillmor. - In reading the<lb/>first section of this Act, passed in 1838, you<lb/>will find that the " Commander-in-Chief<lb/>of this Province, for the time being, by<lb/>and with the consent of Her Majesty's<lb/>Council, be and are hereby authorised<lb/>to <hi rendition="simple:italic">enroll</hi> and <hi rendition="simple:italic">organize</hi>, &amp;c.," but you look<lb/>at the sixth section you will find that the<lb/>power to call out is entirely with the<lb/>Commander-in-Chief. Thus it will be<lb/>seen that this law does not strengthen<lb/>my hon. friend's amendment.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Hon. Mr. Allen</persName>. - The hon. member      
     <lb/>for Carleton has been in the House for a<lb/>number of years, but he has never raised<lb/>an objection of this kind before. He does<lb/>not take the same view of it as he did<lb/>when he was in the Government. Has<lb/>any practical evil resulted from the pow<lb break="no"/>er being vested in the Commander-in-<lb break="yes"/>Chief? because some persons in Carleton<lb/>choose to wear cocked hats, the hon.<lb/>member thinks it is all nonsense. Is it<lb/>not a principle that all militia power<lb/>should be vested in one head, who should<lb/>direct their movement and disband them<lb/>when necessary? When money is to be<lb/>expended it is done by the advice of the<lb/>Council, and it is a check upon the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor. He may call out men, but unless<lb/>the Executive appropriate money they<lb/>would not stay long. The ruiling power<lb/>by this means remains with the Exec<lb break="no"/>tive, because they have the control of the<lb/>finances, without which these organiza<lb break="no"/>tions could not take place at all. I think<lb/>if this amendment is to be carried, it will<lb/>affect the whole principle of the Bill, and<lb/>our entire militia organization be sub<lb break="no"/>verted.<lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. Gilbert</persName>. - Let me call your atten<lb break="no"/>tion to the 29th section: " The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Com<lb break="no"/>mander-in-Chief</hi> may makearrangements<lb/>for the transport of such companies to the<lb/>place of assembly and for their return<lb/>thence, and in case of companies coming<lb/>more than -- miles may pay their rea<lb break="no"/>sonable expenses of transport."<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:ALLA1">Hon. Mr. Allan</persName>. - You will see in the    
     <lb/>2nd clause of the 28th section that the<lb/>pay is to be reegulated by the Governor<lb/>in Council, and I thought I had regulated<lb/>the 29th in the same way. The right to<lb/>control the money is invested in the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor in Council.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. Gilbert</persName>. - Where is the difference<lb/>between loss of time and money? Is not<lb/>the loss of time a loss to the country in<lb/>the shape of loss of labor?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:ALLA1">Hon. Mr. Allan</persName>. - I cannot say it is 
     <lb/>not a loss of time and money, but some<lb break="no"/>thing of this kind is necessary in every<lb/>country. To pass this amendment would<lb/>interfere with the whole arrangements of<lb/>the law. It might be necessary to do<lb/>something with the militia when it would<lb/>be impossible to call the Council together.<lb/>It is a principle that there should be one<lb/>head to the army and navy, and why<lb/>should it not be so with the militia?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
       <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. Lindsay</persName>. - That case applies only  
     <lb/>to actual invasion. The Executive know<lb/>when it is necessary to call out the militia,<lb/>therefore it should be left to them, for<lb/>they are responsible to the country, and<lb/>know its wants and wishes. But after the<lb/>men are called out let the Commander-in-<lb break="yes"/>Chief take the responsibility of their ma<lb break="no"/>nouvering.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. Needham</persName>. - The Government are 
     <lb/>responsible for everything connected to the<lb/>political interestes of the country, but the<lb/>militia is a separate organization, and is<lb/>not connected with the political Govern<lb break="no"/>ment at all.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:ALLA1">Mr. Allan</persName>. - The law passed in<lb/>
          

            <pb n="83" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0083.jpg"/>
      
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">83</fw>

     
     1862 declares the Governor shall be Com<lb break="no"/>mander-in-Chief in the absence of the<lb/>Governor General. The same provision<lb/>applies to Nova Scotia, although it may<lb/>not be in precisely the same words. It<lb/>applies also to Canada, for our militia<lb/>law of 1862 was copied from the Cana<lb break="no"/>dians, and is nearly identical in terms. If<lb/>we pass this amendment it will repeal<lb/>that law, and there will be no uniformity<lb/>in the militia law of the three Provinces.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
        <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. Smith</persName>. - In Canada the prin<lb break="no"/>ciples of Responsible Government exist<lb/>in all their purity, and if it was desirable<lb/>to have this alteration, it would have<lb/>been claimed in that Province. The<lb/>Governor of Canada is <hi rendition="simple:italic">ex-officio</hi> Governor<lb/>of the other North American Colonies,<lb/>and it is desirable that there should be<lb/>uniformity in our legislation, so that we<lb/>should not have a different law from the<lb/>other Provinces.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. Gilbert</persName>. - Could the Commander-      
     <lb break="yes"/>in-Chief in Canada call out the militia<lb/>without the consent of the Executive ?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
        <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. Smith</persName>. - He could, though<lb/>any prudent Commander-in-Chief should<lb/>consult with his Council, yet there<lb/>is no such thing as the Governor's being<lb/>obliged to do so. If hon. members think<lb/>it is desirable that the Government should<lb/>be consulted in regard to the appoint<lb break="no"/>ments made in the militia, it should be<lb/>discussed independent of this Bill, and I<lb/>am not prepared to say which side I will<lb/>take on the question.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   On the question being taken on the<lb/>amendment the House divided - yeas 9, <lb/>nays 14.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. Gilbert</persName> moved that all the words       
     <lb/>in the 26th section after "Officer of the<lb/>Battalion" be struck out. Motion lost.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:CUDL1">Mr. Cudlip</persName> moved that the following<lb/>clause be inserted in the 28th section :<lb/>" The pay of any officer shall not exceed<lb/>that of a Captain in Her Majesty's infan<lb break="no"/>try regiments, to be determined by the<lb/>Governor in Council." in lieu of part of<lb/>the first section which says - "The officers<lb/>shall receive during the time of service<lb/>the same pay as offiers of corresponding<lb/>rank in Her Majesty's infantry regi<lb break="no"/>ments."<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
        <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Col. Boyd</persName>. - The Colonel will select<lb/>the best officers he has to go to this camp,<lb/>and if they are not well paid they will not<lb/>be willing to go, and that will be the end<lb/>of this camp instruction. There is a re<lb break="no"/>sponsibility attached to those officers, be<lb break="no"/>sides a great deal of expenses, such as<lb/>keeping horses, thus making it necessary<lb/>for them to have full pay.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName>. - I am at a loss to know<lb/>why these officers should be put to extra<lb/>expense. They attend this camp because<lb/>they have a very proper zeal to look after<lb/>the interests of the force and render it<lb/>efficient. They ought not to expend more<lb/>than the men, if they have their rations.<lb/>(Mr. Allan : They do not.) They should<lb/>receive rations the same as the privates,<lb/>otherwise the colonels might be disposed<lb/>to lord it over them. They might keep<lb/>horses and an orderly or two, and though<lb/>I might admire this sort of thing, yet I<lb/>do not think it would conduce to the ad<lb break="no"/>vantage of the military service.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. Lindsay</persName>. - The gallant colonel has<lb/>disclosed the secret. The officers are<lb/>going to have horses, &amp;c., the same as if<lb/>they were going to meet an enemy, while<lb/>the privates have to lose their time by<lb/>coming to this camp to support their dig<lb break="no"/>nity. In this camp instruction there<lb/>should be no distinction made between<lb/>the pay of the private and the officer, for<lb/>the private may be the better man of the<lb/>two.<lb/>
            </p>

    
            <cb/>
            <p>
     
        <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. Connell</persName>. - In Canada they have a      
     <lb/>military school, in which the officers are<lb/>divided into two classes, the first class<lb/>get $100 and the second class $50, and<lb/>they drill until they understand the thing<lb/>perfectly. It would be better for us if we<lb/>were guided more by Canada, not only in<lb/>this, but in the Confederation scheme.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:HATH1">Hon. Mr. Hatheway</persName>. - It would re<lb break="no"/>quire a great stretch of the imagination<lb/>to think that the Government could form<lb/>any scheme that the hon. member from<lb/>Carleton would agree to. I was told that<lb/>he said he would resist the draft if his son<lb/>was drawn - my boys are only too anxious<lb/>to go without the draft. He said it was<lb/>going to be a useless Bill, and he would<lb/>fight it through section by section. If it<lb/>is such a useless Bill, he had better allow<lb/>it to be made as ridiculous as possible, <lb/>and then the odium and ridicule thrown<lb/>upon it will defeat it. The question now<lb/>is, whether or not we shall give the $30,<lb break="no"/>000 under a Bill as nearly in accordance<lb/>with the acts of Canada and Nova Scotia<lb/>as it is possible to make it? The Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General has spent a great deal of time<lb/>preparing this Bill, and I hope it may be<lb/>allowed to pass, although some of the<lb/>members of the Government have doubts<lb/>whether any great amount of good will<lb/>result from it.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:ALLA1">Hon. Mr. Allan</persName>. - I think the scale<lb/>mentioned in this additional section is<lb/>high enough.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:LEWI1">Mr. Lewis</persName>. - I am in favor of this<lb/>amendment, because you should allow<lb/>what is fair and right to the officers, for<lb/>they have to spend money for accoutre<lb break="no"/>ments.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   On division of the House this amend<lb break="no"/>ment was carried.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Col. Boyd</persName> moved that the following be<lb/>the 84th section of the Bill : That no<lb/>Militia man employed in the deep sea<lb/>fisheries shall be liable to be called on to<lb/>do duty as such in any camp instruction<lb/>during the fishing season between the<lb/>months of April and November.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     
     
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:ALLA1">Hon. Mr. Allan</persName>. - Any person drawn<lb/>can procure a substitute, and if you make<lb/>one class of people you will have to make<lb/>another.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Col. Boyd</persName>. - It is well known that we          
     <lb/>have in the County of Charlotte a number<lb/>of vessels that go to Labrador and the<lb/>Gulf of St. Lawrence. These vessels have<lb/>to depart by the middle of April, and if<lb/>they are drafted the voyage must be<lb/>broken up.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
        <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. Lindsay</persName>. - If you draft a man that     
     <lb/>is working a new farm, you break up his<lb/>business just as much as you break up<lb/>the fisherman's, and " justice when it<lb/>ceases to be even handed, ceases to be<lb/>justice. "<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:HILL1">Mr. Hill</persName>. - If the farmer is drafted, he       
     <lb/>simply loses a month ; but the fisherman<lb/>loses the whole season. The Attorney<lb/>General did not take into consideration<lb/>the fact that this country requires a navy<lb/>as well as an army, and these fishermen<lb/>are training for a navy, and should not be<lb/>called upon to serve on land.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. Gilbert</persName>. - This draft will be doing     
     <lb/>the fisheries a great injustice by taking<lb/>them away from their business ; these<lb/>sailors may be required when a draft for<lb/>a navy is enforced.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. Smith</persName>. - The Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eral should have excepted this class of<lb/>people. This draft is taking their em<lb break="no"/>ployment from them, for they sometimes<lb/>have a share in the vessel, and it is abso<lb break="no"/>lutely necessary they should go on their<lb/>voyage in the Spring.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. Gilbert</persName>. - I am prepared to sus<lb break="no"/>tain the amendment, and believe there<lb/>
       

            <cb/>
    


     should be no draft at all, because there<lb/>will be hundreds of volunteers from all<lb/>parts of the Province. The same argu<lb break="no"/>ments that apply to the fishermen will<lb/>apply with equal force to the farmer,<lb/>manufacturer and lumberman. The farm<lb break="no"/>er may be prevented from putting in his<lb/>crop. The manufacturers of lumber may,<lb/>during the sawing season - that is in the<lb/>spring of the year during the freshet - <lb/>have the men drawn out of the mills, and<lb/>thus causing them a great deal of trouble<lb/>and inconvenience. The exception should<lb/>also be extended to the Grammar Schools<lb/>and Universities throughout the country,<lb/>for there is no greater injury you can fix<lb/>upon the young men of the Province than<lb/>hastily calling them from their homes to<lb/>attend this drill exercise for twenty-eight<lb/>days. They will never become good citi<lb break="no"/>zens afterwards, for they will have a de<lb break="no"/>sire to be engaged in this sort of calling.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. Smith</persName>. - I thought we had      
     <lb/>determined that question about the draft,<lb/>but my hon. colleague has made an attack<lb/>upon his constituents that I feel called<lb/>upon to answer. He says the men at<lb break="no"/>tending this camp will be useless here<lb break="no"/>after. It is a slander upon the young<lb/>men of the country, for there are plenty<lb/>of young men who can stay twenty-eight<lb/>days in this camp without spoiling their<lb/>morals, or unfitting them for becoming<lb/>useful citizens.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Col. Boyd</persName>. - The care of fishermen is 
     <lb/>not parallel with that of the lumberman<lb/>or farmer. The lumberman can work in<lb/>the woods all winter, and the farmer can<lb/>work on his farm all summer, but the fish<lb break="no"/>erman loses his whole year's work, there<lb break="no"/>fore he should be exempt.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>   <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName>. - This is a very reason<lb break="no"/>able proposition, and should be extended<lb/>to all fishermen instead of those only who<lb/>are engaged in the deep sea fisheries, for<lb/>I do not see any reason why they should<lb/>be exempt more than the others.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   This amendment was lost - yeas 11,<lb/>nays, 14.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
        <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName> called attention to the<lb/>97th section, which says : " If any person<lb/>shall wilfully interrupt or hinder any<lb/>Militia man at drill or on duty, or at tar<lb break="no"/>get practice, or shall trespass upon any<lb/>lands or range marked out or set apart for<lb/>that purpose, every such person shall be<lb/>liable to a penalty not exceeding - <lb/> dollars for each offence, and may also be<lb/>taken into custody by verbal order of the<lb/>Commanding Officer, and detained until <lb/>such drill duty or practice is performed;"<lb/>and remarked that these powers were too<lb/>extensive, for the Commanding Officer<lb/>might have a spite against some person,<lb/>and would walk him off into limbo, keep<lb break="no"/>ing him there for the remainder of the<lb/>twenty-eight days, simply because he<lb/>might happen by chance to walk on the<lb/>grounds set apart for drill exercise.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
        <persName ref="pers:ALLA1">Hon. Mr. Allan</persName>. - Some persons may      
     <lb/>interrupt the practice, by running through<lb/>the men or standing by the target, and<lb/>there should be some power to arrest him<lb/>at once, instead of having to go to the<lb/>Magistrate and get out a summons for<lb/>him to appear next day, the men thereby<lb/>losing a whole day's practice, and this<lb/>man probably not worth a farthing.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. Needham</persName>. - I think it better be      
     <lb/>amended in this way, " Any person wil<lb break="no"/>fully interfering, or shall willfully trespass<lb/>on any lands set apart for such purpose,<lb/>may be taken into custody by the verbal<lb/>order of the Commanding Officer until<lb/>such practice is over, and for every suc<lb break="no"/>ceeding offence he may be fined."<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     
     
     
        <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. Gilbert</persName>. - Who is to decide whe<lb break="no"/>ther it is a willful trespass or not ? It should<lb/>
          

            <pb n="84" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-22_Page_0084.jpg"/>
         
<fw type="num">84</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1863.</fw> 


     be, " if he is ordered off, and refuses to            
     <lb/>go, he should be taken into custody. It<lb/>is very hard for a man to be deprived of<lb/>his liberty ; some men are very sensitive<lb/>and would remember it all the days of<lb/>their life.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Hon. Mr. Allan. - My hon. friend says <lb/>who is to decide whether it is a willful<lb/>trespass or not ; the distinction is well<lb/>known ; if a man goes upon the ground<lb/>after he has been forbidden, he is willfully<lb/>interfering with the practice, and should<lb/>be taken into custody for that day by the<lb/>verbal order of the commanding officer.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Hon. Mr. Smith suggested that the  
     <lb/>words " and refuse to leave after being<lb/>requested to do so," be inserted after the<lb/>word ' purpose' in the Section. This sug<lb break="no"/>gestion was adopted.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
          Mr. Wetmore moved that the follow<lb break="no"/>ing be the 102 Section of the Bill :- <lb/> "That no Militia man employed in the salt<lb/>water fisheries shall be liable to be called<lb/>on to do duty as such, in any camp of in<lb break="no"/>struction during the fishing season be<lb break="no"/>tween the months of March and Novem<lb break="no"/>ber in each year."<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         This Section was lost.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    On motion of <persName ref="pers:HILL1">Mr. Hill</persName> the following<lb/>additional clause was inserted in the 83rd<lb/>Section, " Members of Fire Companies,<lb/>and Hook and Ladder Companies in any<lb/>city or town, shall be exempt from duty<lb/>beyond the limits of the same respect<lb break="no"/>ively."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    The Bill was then reported as agreed<lb/>to, with certain amendments.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    The House then adjourned until nine <lb/>o'clock tomorrow.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">    T.P.D.<lb/>
            </p>




<!-- GL, 2018-02-27, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p>    TUESDAY, MAY 22.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
         Mr. Young moved a ryder to the Militia<lb/>Bill. He had been looking over the Can<lb break="no"/>adian Act, and he found among the ex<lb break="no"/>empts " sea-faring men, branch pilots,<lb/>and pilots actually engaged in their call<lb break="no"/>ing." He thought this would cover the<lb/>deep sea fishery men who certainly should<lb/>not be liable to the draft.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Keen said he thought that seamen, <lb/>branch pilots, and those engaged in deep<lb/>sea fisheries should be exempt. The<lb/>pilots were as much required to attend to<lb/>vessels entering our ports, as ferrymen to<lb/>cross our streams. In Canada all fisher<lb break="no"/>men and pilots engaged on the Lakes<lb/>were exempt.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Hon. Mr. Hatheway said this ryder <lb/>would cover all the people of the County<lb/>of Gloucester as it was well-known that<lb/>every man there kept his fishing boat and<lb/>went out in the morning to return at<lb/>night.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
         Mr. Young explained that there were        
     <lb/>over a thousand militia men, besides those<lb/>whom it was contemplated to, exempt.<lb/>His object was to exempt those men who<lb/>go to the Labrador coast and elsewhere,<lb/>and are absent during four months in the<lb/>year.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Hon. Mr. Allan said he thought it <lb/>would be best to let the Bill run for a<lb/>year, and in that time it would be seen<lb/>upon whom it bore hardly, and could be<lb/>remedied.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     
     
         Mr. Williston said those who were       
     <lb/>engaged in the deep sea fisheries had but<lb/>a short time to obtain their livelihood,<lb/>and during that time they should be ex<lb break="no"/>empt.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     
     
     
         Mr. Needham wanted to know the         
     <lb/>meaning of deep sea fisheries. The sea is<lb/>defined as below low water mark. The<lb/>difficulty would be to define the meaning<lb/>of the term. He had looked over the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Dictionary and found sea, seaman,<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     
     and sea devils, but nothing of sea-faring  
     <lb/>men.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. McClellan said if any class of<lb/>men should be exempt it was the farmers<lb/>of the country. We were giving a great<lb/>power into the hands of an irresponsible<lb/>officer withouth having received any com-<lb break="yes"/>complaint or petition from the people, and he<lb/>thought the whole thing was uncalled for.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Boyd moved the following to be <lb/>added to the list of exempts, as an amend<lb break="no"/>ment : " That no militia man employed<lb/>in the deep sea fisheries in the Gulf of St.<lb/>Lawrence, Bay de Chaleur and Bay of<lb/>Fundy, be called on to do duty as such in<lb/>any camp of instructions during the fishing<lb/>season between the months of April and<lb/>October in each year ; and also branch<lb/>pilots and apprentices, and pilots employ<lb break="no"/>ed in their calling during the season of<lb/>navigation.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     
     
     
         Mr. Coran thought that any man who       
     <lb/>was engaged in harbour fisheries, which<lb/>were of great importance to the country,<lb/>should be placed amongst the exempts.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Hon. Mr. Allen felt confident that if <lb/>this class of men were made exempt that<lb/>dissatisfaction would be felt among many<lb/>other callings. It would be very difficult<lb/>to define who came within the meaning of<lb/>the law, and he thought that it would be<lb/>best to let the Bill remain as it is for this<lb/>year. The hon. member for Albert (Mr.<lb/>McClellan) seemed to pursue a somewhat<lb/>inconsistent part, as he now opposes a<lb/>Bill which contains the same provisions<lb/>as that he supported under the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
         Mr. McMillan said there was one class 
     <lb/>of men who should be exempt, and he was<lb/>sure the Hon. Commissioner of the Board<lb/>of Works would support him in this ; he<lb/>referred to the lumbermen of the Province.<lb/>At certain seasons it would be a gret loss<lb/>to have these men taken from their em<lb break="no"/>ployment. Suppose a gang of men were<lb/>employed on a raft of logs coming down<lb/>the Nashwaak and they were to be called<lb/>off to attend drill, the Hon. Commissioner<lb/>would be subjected to great loss ; he<lb/>thought these should be added to the list<lb/>of exempts.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. Wetmore said he had moved in  
     <lb/>this matter yesterday when the Bill was<lb/>before the Committee, and he could not<lb/>support either the ryder, or amendment,<lb/>unless it included all who were engaged<lb/>in salt water fisheries. He hoped the<lb/>hon. member for Charlotte would allow<lb/>them to be included in the amendment.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>    Mr. Thompson did not believe the <lb/>draft would be enforced at all, as there<lb/>would be plenty of volunteers to fill the<lb/>camp. He thought it was all nonsense<lb/>to bring in these exemptions, and that the<lb/>Bill should remain as it is.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     
         Mr. Otty informed the Hon. Attorney        
     <lb/>General that what is implied by deep sea<lb/>fisheries could easily be known by refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the Fishery Act, 14th Victoria,<lb/>Chap. 31, Section 4, where the coast fish<lb break="no"/>eries are defined to be " situated on the<lb/>sea coast of the Province, or around any<lb/>island laying off the said sea coast, be<lb break="no"/>tween low water mark and three marine<lb/>miles of each coast or island." The deep<lb/>sea fishery would be outside of this line.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
         Mr. Needham thought that lawyers   
     <lb/>should be added to the list of exempts, as<lb/>it would be very hard to take them from<lb/>their duties during the settings of the<lb/>Courts.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
         Mr. McClellan would explain to the  
     <lb/>hon. Attorney General that at the time of<lb/>the passing of the last Bill he did not<lb/>vote for it. He believed the Bill was not<lb/>debated at all. There was, however, a dif<lb break="no"/>ferent construction placed upon : certain<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     words now from what was then contem<lb break="no"/>plated. The consent of the Queen<lb/>was understood to mean the Queen and<lb/>Her Council ; the command of His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency the Lieutenant Governor was<lb/>considered the Governor and his advisers.<lb/>Now these terms are confined to the per<lb break="no"/>sons named without reference to their<lb/>Council or advisers. If it were not for<lb/>this construction he would not have spok-<lb break="maybe"/>on the subject.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. Lindsay said it would be very hard      
     <lb/>for the farmers to be called out ; the<lb/>season was short, and if they lost a<lb/>month's labor, it might affect their sub<lb break="no"/>sistence for the year. He thought the<lb/>best plan would be to move a ryder that<lb/>nobody should be called out. If the law<lb/>passes, every man should take his turn,<lb/>and if any one was to be exempted, the<lb/>farmers certainly should be ; they are the<lb/>bone and sinew of the country. The peo<lb break="no"/>ple can do without fish, for they can get<lb/>beef and farm produce, but if these fail<lb/>the country would suffer.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     
     
         Mr. Fraser hoped that another class      
     <lb/>would be included in the list ; he referred<lb/>to the back settlers, who were a very va<lb break="no"/>luable class of people.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Williston would suggest to the <lb/>hon. mover of the amendment the desira<lb break="no"/>bility of including the Straits of North<lb break="no"/>umberland. He wished the House to un<lb break="no"/>derstand that tho grounds used for fish<lb break="no"/>ing purposes by the people on the coast<lb/>are the same as those used by the Ameri<lb break="no"/>cans, the only difference being that our<lb/>people go out in their whale boats for the<lb/>day and return at night, and they lie off<lb/>in their vessels. There would be no dif<lb break="no"/>ficulty in determining what is meant by<lb/>deep sea fishing, as it is understood by<lb/>the Americans as outside of three miles<lb/>from the coast line.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     
     
     
     
     
         Mr. Lewis said there was so much dif-   
     <lb/>ficulty in knowing what was really meant<lb/>that he thought the Bill should remain as<lb/>it is.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Bailey said there was another class <lb/>of men he should like to see added, and<lb/>that was all men engaged in the coasting<lb/>trade, and the fresh water sailors running<lb/>in our rivers and inland lakes.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. Landry said a great many of his   
     <lb/>people hired out for a month, and if they<lb/>lost this time they would be subject to a<lb/>great inconvenience, and all should be<lb/>treated alike. The best plan would be to<lb/>kill the Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Cudlip said if anything justified <lb/>him in the action he took yesterday as to<lb/>the compulsory draft, it was the feeling<lb/>which was manifested this morning. He<lb/>was strongly opposed to men being taken<lb/>from their calling in a time of peace. The<lb/>hon. members were speaking as the<lb/>people, and the feeling was general that<lb/>every calling should be exempt from the<lb/>draft. But he thought if there was one<lb/>class more than another upon which it<lb/>would fall heavily, it was those engaged<lb/>in the shore fisheries. These men are at<lb/>home, and come within the law, whilst<lb/>those who are absent engaged in the deep<lb/>sea fisheries could not be reached. He<lb/>hoped the ryder would be made to cover<lb/>both parties.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     
     
     
     
         On the amendment being put the House       
     <lb/>divided, yeas 10, nays 10. They were<lb/>therefore both lost.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         The Militia Bill being read a third time  
     <lb/>was then passed as amended by the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
         Hon. Mr. Gillmor moved the House   
     <lb/>into Committee of the Whole on a Bill to<lb/>provide for repairing and improving Great<lb/>Roads and Bridges and other public works<lb/>and services.<lb/>
            </p>-->

    

    
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>