<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-07-04"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-07-04">4 July 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="74" to="77"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_074.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_075.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_076.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_077.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-27">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-27">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_074">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_074.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_075">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_075.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_076">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_076.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_077">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_077.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="74" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_074.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">74</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>
   
            <head rendition="simple:right">WEDNESDAY, JULY 4.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p>Certain Bills received a second and<lb/>third reading after which Mr. WET<lb break="no"/>MORE read and laid before the House<lb/>the petition and protest of George Mc<lb break="no"/>Leod and others, voters in the County of<lb/>Kent, against the return of William S.<lb/>Caie and Own McInerney, as members<lb/>of the General Assembly, on the ground<lb/>that the election was illegal, inasmuch as<lb/>the Sheriff had notified the people that<lb/>the election would take place at a certain<lb/>time, and had afterward changed the<lb/>date; and also on the gournd of bribery<lb/>and corruption.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> it was<lb/>order that on Saturday next the 7th<lb/>instant, at the hour of 10 A. M., the<lb/>House do go into consideration of the<lb/>charges contained in the petition of Geo.<lb/>McLeod and others against the return of<lb/>Messers. Caie and McInerney.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> moved for leave to<lb/>bring in a Bill to place the road from<lb/>North Richmond to South Richmond, in<lb/>the County of Carleton, on the Great<lb/>Road list. Leave granted, and the Bill<lb/>was read a first and second time, and re<lb break="no"/>ferred to the Chief Commissioner of the<lb/>Board of Works.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName> moved for leave to<lb/>bring in a Bill to place the road from the<lb/>North of Keswick, in the County of<lb/>York, to the River St. John, opposite<lb/>Woodstock, on the Great Road list.<lb/>Leave was granted, and the Bill was read<lb/>a first and second time, and referred to<lb/>the Chief Commissioner of the Board of<lb/>Works.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName> moved for leave to 
     <lb/>bring in a Bill to place the road from<lb/>Thompson's Mills, in the Parish of<lb/>Douglas, passing through Stanley to<lb/>Bonestown, on the Great Road list.<lb/>Leave was granted and the Bill was read<lb/>a first and second time, and referred to<lb/>the Chief Commissioner of the Board<lb/>of Works.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The order of the day was then taken up. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     RESOLUTIONS ON THE UNION DELEGATION. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> said he thought it was 
     <lb/>not right that delegates should be bound<lb/>down in their action by any restrictions<lb/>laid upon them by this House<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> rose to close the debate<lb/>and said:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I had some anticipation that some<lb/>amendment would be offered by the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment to the resolution I laid before<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
        
this House, but I had no thought that<lb/>they would have moved such an amend<lb break="no"/>ment as they did. I always thought we<lb/>were a deliberative Assembly, sent here<lb/>by the people to exercise our judgments<lb/>and intellects on all matters pertaining to<lb/>the well-being of the people of this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. But it appears the Government<lb/>do not entertain such an opinion. They<lb/>talk as though all the blessings which<lb/>they predicted Confederation was to<lb/>bring, had already been experienced.<lb/>Rather than the course they have pur<lb break="no"/>sued, I think they should have come be<lb break="no"/>fore this House, and said "the country<lb/>have determined to try the experiment of<lb/>Union" and explained the course they<lb/>intended to follow, so that hon. members<lb/>might bring their powers of mind to bear<lb/>upon the subject, and suggest such modi<lb break="no"/>fications and alterations as to them was<lb/>deemed necessary. Instead of this they<lb/>are shrouding their conduct in mystery<lb/>and concealment. When I asked the<lb/>Attorney General if it was the intention<lb/>of the Government to confederate New<lb/>Brunswick and Canada if Nova Scotia<lb/>decided not to come in, the required in<lb break="no"/>formation was concealed. They bring<lb/>forward a resolution intimating that the<lb/>Union is to include all the Provinces,<lb/>yet refuse to say if they will agree to a<lb/>Union of only two. The people of New<lb/>Brunswick may be wiling to go into a<lb/>Union with all the Provinces, while they<lb/>would not agree that this Province should<lb/>unite with Canada alone. I do not be<lb break="no"/>lieve the Government are justified in<lb/>pursuing such a mysterious course, nor<lb/>that hon. members will do justice to their<lb/>constituents if they vote for the amend<lb break="no"/>ment.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> then referred to a misun<lb break="no"/>derstanding which had arisen with regard<lb/>to the working of Hon. Mr. Fisher's<lb/>Amendment, and then proceeded: - <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>In the Amendment made by the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment they make the declaration that<lb/>hon. members of this House are not here<lb/>to deliberate on the terms of Union, but<lb/>simply to clothe with unlimited power the<lb/>delegates who may be sent on this mis<lb break="no"/>sion; that they will not admit of opinions<lb/>being expressed by those whom the peo<lb break="no"/>ple have sent to speak for them. I ask<lb/>the House if they are willing to ignore<lb/>their functions, to shirk all the responsi<lb break="no"/>bility and place it on the shoulders of<lb/>the Government? I repudiate any such<lb/>doctrine that in a case like this, when the<lb/>changing of the Constitution is contem<lb break="no"/>plated, that the people's representatives<lb/>should take no responsibility. All the<lb/>responsibility of the acts of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment will rest upon them and the peo<lb break="no"/>ple. I think hon. members had better<lb/>pause, for notwithstanding the doctrine<lb/>here laid down by the Government, the<lb/>result, if disastrous, will rest with them,<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
        

     and the people will call them to account 
     <lb/>for it. It does not seem to me that it is not<lb/>possible there can be a majority of the<lb/>members of this House willing to stultify <lb/>themselves and ignore their functions,<lb/>and do nothing more on this great ques<lb break="no"/>tion than to appoint delegates with power<lb/>to change the Constitution of this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince without their having a voice in the<lb/>matter. The hon. member for Northum<lb break="no"/>berland ( Mr. Johnson) told us that Mr.<lb/>Galt contemplated reducing the taxes in<lb/>Canada. Does he? I'd show that he<lb/>contemplates greatly increasing them<lb/>Mr. Galt himself admitted in his speech<lb/>in the Canadian Parliament that they are<lb/>in such financial difficulty that he should<lb/>call upon them to give the Government<lb/>power to issue five million dollars of Trea<lb break="no"/>sury notes. The duties they now pay in<lb/>Canada are much higher than with us,<lb/>and although Mr. galt says that that<lb/>would probably be their last Session, yet<lb/>before Confederation is accomplished, he<lb/>is compelled to raise the duties on vari<lb break="no"/>ous articles to meet their present emer<lb break="no"/>gencies. I hold in my hand a report of<lb/>Mr. Galt's speech when presenting his fi<lb break="no"/>nancial statement, and I will read what<lb/>he says, as also the remarks of Mr. Geo.<lb/>Brown on the course pursued by the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment. The Provincial Secretary<lb/>(Mr. Tillney) had told us that in Canada<lb/>they had an excise duty of theiry cents a<lb/>gallon on whiskey. Does he knwo that<lb/>it is now intended to raise that to sixty<lb/>cents, and under Confederation we will<lb/>have to pay that amount. The people of<lb/>Canada want more money than they have,<lb/>and even now they are paying eight per<lb/>cent. for it. Their finances are in a very<lb/>bad state.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Galt says ( I shall merely read a<lb/>few extracts from his speech): - <lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"This year the financial statement in<lb break="no"/>cluded the expense of the election of Le<lb break="no"/>gislative Councillors last fall, but it was<lb/>not likely that this Parliament would ever<lb/>have to provide means for another Gene<lb break="no"/>ral Election."<lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>For Militia he would not ask for $50,<lb break="no"/>000 as usual, but "he wished to be em<lb break="no"/>powered to spend a sum no less than $1,<lb break="no"/>500,000." And then he goes on to spe<lb break="no"/>cify the articles upon which a higher duty<lb/>must be paid. "It would be his duty to<lb/>increase the excise duty on spirits from<lb/>thirty to sixty cents." "On Indian corn,<lb/>coarse grains, &amp;c., imported from the<lb/>United States, there would be a duty of<lb/>ten cents a bushel. On flour the duty<lb/>would be fifty cents a barrel." "On tea<lb/>the Government proposed adding to the<lb/>specific duty three cents a pound, making<lb/>the duty on tea as nearly as possible<lb/>twelve or twelve and a half cents a pound,<lb/>instead of nine cents as heretofore." There<lb/>is also to be a change in the duy on mo<lb break="no"/>lasses. It is put down at $1 per gallon,<lb/>
       

            <pb n="75" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_075.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>   <fw type="num">75</fw>  
 

     but that I presume must be a mistake. I 
     <lb/>take it, it is meant to put a duty of $1<lb/>for every 100 pounds. So then we are to<lb/>have a duty on flour, a charge which I<lb/>have always resisted. This is intended<lb/>to prevent our importing from the States<lb/>and compel us to use the grain and flour<lb/>of Canada. Free ports are to be abolish<lb break="no"/>ed, and then twelve and a half cents is a<lb/>pretty heavy duty to pay on a pound of<lb/>tea. I ask if these changes are made<lb/>when the Parliament of Canada are not<lb/>expected to meet again, shall we pay less<lb/>when we are united with her?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">HON. Mr. TILLEY</persName> - Yes.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - He says yes, but it is<lb/>know that the expenses of the General<lb/>Government will be very great, and that<lb/>on this account the taxes must largely in<lb break="no"/>crease. The popel here us more tea<lb/>in proportion they they do in Canada,<lb/>and this item is but a forerunner of what<lb/>must follow. Even with their present<lb/>duty on molasses we should have to pay<lb/>$10,000 more for the quantity we use<lb/>than we do now, and even this is to be<lb/>increased. And then at last he goes<lb/>on to say the Government will issue<lb/>$3,000,000 of legal tender notes to meet<lb/>the immediate requirements of the coun<lb break="no"/>try. And yet we are told that they ahve<lb/>a surplus of funds. It is evident they<lb/>are driven to the last extremity to met<lb/>their liabilities. The power and influence<lb/>of Canada is felt in this country even<lb/>now. I felt it in the late Government. It<lb/>seems incredible, yt it is a fact that they<lb/>attempted to influence the time of the<lb/>meeting of our Legislature, and I believe<lb/>that the Secretary is under the influence<lb/>which the Canadians wield.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Now hear what Mr. George Brown<lb/>says:</p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>Hon. Mr. BROWN regretted that<lb/>the honl gentleman had made such a<lb/>speech as he had done at the present<lb/>juncture. This was certainly a very bad<lb/>time to make such propositions as he had<lb/>laid down in the Budget. He ventured<lb/>t say that when that Scheme (that is the<lb/>financial statement of Mr. Galt) went<lb/>before the country it would produce the<lb/>wildest commotion. He was greatly sur<lb break="no"/>prised at the magnitude of the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture. The hon. Finance Minister had<lb/>stated that he would not have submitted<lb/>the Scheme now had he thought it would<lb/>throw and obstacles in the way of Con<lb break="no"/>federation. He (Mr. Brown) certainly<lb/>considered it most unfortunate that such<lb/>a thing had been done on the eve of<lb/>the consummation of the Union of the<lb/>Provinces. The Scheme in many im<lb break="no"/>portant particulars was bad. He consi<lb break="no"/>dered that taking off a tax and putting<lb/>on another was a way of robbing Peter<lb/>to pay Paul. So far from mending mat<lb break="no"/>ters they had been made worse. He (Mr.<lb/>B.) intended to meet the proposition at<lb/>length at another time. He held that<lb/>the Scheme of the hon. Finance Minister<lb/>would throw the country into political<lb/>commotion which the Government had<lb/>been formed to set at rest, and that put<lb break="no"/>ting forward such propositions at this<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
        

     time was little short of madness. By 
     <lb/>this, too, no one would say that the House<lb/>would rise for months to come."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Now these are the remarks of George 
     <lb/>Brown, one of the Quebec Schemers.<lb/>You see he says that there is no know<lb break="no"/>ing that the House will rise for months<lb/>to come. At the opening of the present<lb/>session the members of the Government<lb/>were terribly anxious to bring on the<lb/>business, and get the delegates appointed.<lb/>I believe they intended to have sailed by<lb/>the steamer that sails from Halifax to<lb break="no"/>morrow. But now there seems to be<lb/>some hitch, they don't seem to mind how<lb/>long the session lasts.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>. - Our lives are not 
     <lb/>a burden to us at any rate.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - Then they ought to be. 
     <lb/>I put it to him if he was not in collusion<lb/>with the Governor, and assisted the back<lb break="no"/>stairs Government in undermining the<lb/>late administration. Mr. Speaker, at<lb/>that time we were like a man surrounded<lb/>by enemies, who did not know which<lb/>way to move lest he should be endanger<lb break="no"/>ing his life. We were surrounded by an<lb/>unscrupulous Opposition, and by secret<lb/>influences which were at work to over<lb break="no"/>throw us, and at that time I did feel<lb/>that life was a burden. But I would ask<lb/>the Provincial Secretary if he approves of<lb/>the actions of the Governor? Last winter<lb/>was spent by him in looking after politics;<lb/>day after day he was in this House watch<lb break="no"/>ing the proceedings, and he seemed to<lb/>have little else to do. I say if he thinks<lb/>the course pursued, the wily influences<lb/>used by this backstair's Government, this<lb/>Talleyrandism, right, then his life ought<lb/>to be a burden to him.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>His Honor <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">the SPEAKER</persName> asked Mr.<lb/>Smith to confine his remarks to the sub<lb break="no"/>ject before the House as much as possible.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - It seems, Mr. Speaker,<lb/>that hon. members of the Government<lb/>may be allowed to go out of their way to<lb/>make attacks on us, but I am to be<lb/>strictly confined to the bare subject in<lb/>hand.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>His Honor <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">the SPEAKER</persName> hoped the<lb/>hon. member would not think that he<lb/>would not act as justly and impartially<lb/>with him as with any other member of<lb/>the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - I should be sorry to<lb/>think, Mr. Speaker, that any such course<lb/>would be adopted, but the hon. Attorney<lb/>General was permitted to wander away<lb/>into the action of the late Government,<lb/>yet I am not to be allowed to reply to the<lb/>charges he put forth.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName>. - I rise to a point of 
     <lb/>order. The hon. member for Westmor<lb break="no"/>land has stated that the Opposition in<lb/>the last House was unscrupulous. Now<lb/>I was in the Opposition last session. I<lb/>beg to say that my opposition to them<lb/>was neither factious nor unscrupulous,<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
         
but the fact was the Opposition had an<lb/>unscrupulous Government to deal with.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - There it is. The hon.<lb/>member for St. John takes great um<lb break="no"/>brage at my speaking of the late Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion as unscrupulous, but does not hesi<lb break="no"/>tate to speak of the late Government in<lb/>the same terms.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName>. - You first made use<lb/>of the expression, and I certainly had a<lb/>right to return the compliment.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - I havae challenged the<lb/>Secretary, and I do so again, to show<lb/>that the late Government were unconsti<lb break="no"/>tutional in any of their acts, or that they<lb/>were guilty of mal-practice or mal-ad<lb break="no"/>ministration. To return, I was reading<lb/>the financial statement of Mr. Galt, to<lb/>show that the fiscal condition of Canada<lb/>is very bad. Now I will refer to the<lb/>constitutional part of the question. The<lb/>hon. member for Northumberland (Mr.<lb/>Johnson) in his speech yesterday sai,<lb/>and he read largely from a book, to show<lb/>that the people of the United States were<lb/>not appealed to in the preparing of their<lb/>Constitution. But let us look into the<lb/>matter, and first see the care taken in the<lb/>organization of a State. I shall quote<lb/>from the same work as he did,<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"When a new State is proposed to be<lb/>organized, the people elect delegates to<lb/>a Convention, for the purpose of framing<lb/>a Constitution. After that instrument<lb/>has been adopted in Convention, it is<lb/>submitted to the vote of the people, and,<lb/>on ballot, they declare 'for the Consti<lb break="no"/>tution,' or 'against the Constitution.'<lb/>If the affirmative receive a majority of<lb/>votes, it is adopted; if the majority vote<lb/>for the negative, the Constitution is re<lb break="no"/>jected. Whenever the people desire it,<lb/>another Convention is called. In the old<lb/>States it is difficult to effect a revision of<lb/>that instrument."<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>It is usual for the Legislature to pass<lb/>a law to take the vote of the people<lb/>whether or not a Convention shall be<lb/>authorized to meet for the purpose of re<lb break="no"/>vising the Constitution. The people bal<lb break="no"/>lot directly upon the question - "For a<lb/>Convention," "against a Convention."<lb/>If carried in the affirmative, the next<lb/>Session of the Legislature passes a law<lb/>authorizing a Convention to be convened,<lb/>and its members to be elected. The de<lb break="no"/>legates are then elected and the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion assembles according to law, and pro<lb break="no"/>ceed to revise the Constitution. This<lb/>body sometimes continues in session<lb/>several weeks. When the revised instru<lb break="no"/>ment has been completed the Conven<lb break="no"/>tion orders its submission to the vote of<lb/>the pople, and then adjourns. The<lb/>people cast their ballots either "for the<lb/>Constitution" or "against the Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion." If adopted, a new Government is<lb/>organised, but if rejected and the effort<lb/>to change the Government has failed, the<lb/>old Constitution is continued in force.<lb/>
            </p>
            <pb n="76" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_076.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="num">76</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 
 

            <p>These proceedings, namely, the passsing of<lb/>the Bill by the Legislature, and the tak<lb break="no"/>ing of the vote of the people whether or<lb/>not a Convention shall be convened; the<lb/>passing of the Bill for the election of the<lb/>delegates and the other formalities allud<lb break="no"/>ed to, occupy some four or five years."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"The sovereign power of a State is de<lb break="no"/>rived from the people." But here they<lb/>take the ground that the General Govern<lb break="no"/>ment is the fountain of all power, and<lb/>sends out her little streams to the local<lb/>Legislature, thus reverting the idea of<lb/>the United States. Now let me show you<lb/>that they did appeal to the people to rati<lb break="no"/>fy what they had done in Convention.<lb/>"The Convention continued in session<lb/>four months, and on the 17th day of Sep<lb break="no"/>tember, 1787, the following organic in<lb break="no"/>strument was adopted." Then follows<lb/>the Constitution signed by George Wash<lb break="no"/>ington - "This Constitution was reported<lb/>to the Congress; and from that body was<lb/>sent to the respective States for ratifica<lb break="no"/>tion, in accordance with proceedings of<lb/>the Convention." The Resolution of<lb/>Congress passed on the 28th September,<lb/>1787, was as follows:<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved unanimously</hi>- That the Re<lb break="no"/>port of the Convention be transmitted to<lb/>the several Legislatures, in order to be<lb/>submitted to a Convention of delegates<lb/>chosen in each State by the people thereof,<lb/>in conformity to the resolves of the Con<lb break="no"/>vention made and provided in that case."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Here the Convention showed proper 
     <lb/>respect for the rights of the people. I<lb/>have gone into the subject more than I<lb/>intended at first. The House will pro<lb break="no"/>bably vote for the Amendment, taking<lb/>from us the right of expressing our opin<lb break="no"/>ions on the subject of Union. The Re<lb break="no"/>solutions I submitted are surely reasona<lb break="no"/>ble. There is one point on which I think<lb/>none can take exception to, and that is<lb/>that these Lower Provinces shall have<lb/>at least one member each in the Execu<lb break="no"/>tive Council of the General Parliament,<lb/>to secure the rights and interests of their<lb/>own people for all time to come. This I<lb/>hold should be put in the Scheme, for in<lb/>a written Constitution it is necessary that<lb/>every point should be well defined as the<lb/>management of affairs will necessarily be<lb/>in strict accordance with the letter of the<lb/>Constitution. Canada will form the all-<lb break="yes"/>powerful part of the Confederation, and<lb/>we ask for the appointment of one of our<lb/>members to the Executive; and let it be<lb/>as a right, as part of the great Magna<lb/>Charter, and not be humiliated to ask it<lb/>as a favour from Upper Canada. I think,<lb/>too, that the Inter-colonial railway<lb/>should be <hi rendition="simple:italic">bona fide</hi> commenced before<lb/>the General Government should have the<lb/>right to tax us for its construction. No<lb/>arrangement, I fear, will be made by<lb/>which they will be able to proceed except<lb/>by taxing us, unless their hand it stayed.<lb/>I believe the first Session of the General<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
   

     Parliament we shall have the Stamp du<lb break="no"/>ties fixed upon us. We shall also have a<lb/>tax put upon newspapers. 12 1/2 cents a<lb/>pound on tea, a tax on flour, and a heavy<lb/>export duty on our lumber. Then the<lb/>only means to take to secure the build<lb break="no"/>ing of the Inter-colonial railroad is by<lb/>preventing these burdens being placed<lb/>upon us till the work is underway. The<lb/>putting in of this provision will not affect<lb/>Confederation at all, it will only secure<lb/>us if it is put in. Mr. Galt expresses the<lb/>opinion that soon we shall be entirely<lb/>sepeerated from England. He expects to<lb/>see us a great nationality on this Conti<lb break="no"/>nent, friendly to England, but yielding<lb/>her no allegiance. This is I am opposed to<lb/>I want to see no seperation from the Mo<lb break="no"/>ther Country. I think the Resolutions I<lb/>have offered deserve the support of this<lb/>House. If hon. members are willing to<lb/>yield up their right of opinion they will<lb/>of course vote for the Amendment, but if<lb/>not they must support the Resolutions.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House then divided on the Amend<lb break="no"/>ment. <hi rendition="simple:italic">Ayes</hi>- Hon. Mr. Tilley, Hon. Mr.<lb/>Fischer, Hon. Mr. Williston, Hon. Mr.<lb/>McClellan, Hon. Mr. McMillan, Hon.<lb/>Mr. Wilmot, Hon. Mr. Connell, Mr.<lb/>Lindsay, Mr. Perley, Mr. McAdam,<lb/>Mr. Ryan, Mr. Babbit, Mr. Ferris, Mr.<lb/>J. Flewwelling, Mr. Glazier, Mr. Wet<lb break="no"/>more, Mr. Quinton, Mr. DesBrisay, Mr.<lb/>Thompson, Mr. Beckwith, Mr. Chandler,<lb/>Mr. Beveridge, Mr. Sutton, Mr. Kerr,<lb/>Mr. DAvis, Mr. Stevens, Mr, Hibbard,<lb/>Mr. Skinner, Mr. Johnson, and Dr.<lb/>Dow - 30.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Nays</hi>- MR. Smith, Mr. Young, Mr.<lb/>CAie, Mr. Botsford, Mr McQueen, Mr.<lb/>Meehan, Mr. McInerny, and Mr. Land<lb break="no"/>ry - 8.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Messrs. W.P. Flewelling and Herbert<lb/>were absent.<lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     AFTERNOON SESSION. 
     <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> moved the House into 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole on a Bill to in— 
     <lb/>
     corporate the Shipwrights' Union. of the 
     <lb/>
     City of Saint John. Mr. DesBrisay In 
     <lb/>
     the Chair.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
       <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> said this was a similar 
     <lb/>
    Bill to that passed the other day to in<lb break="no"/>corporate the Caulkers' Association. It 
     <lb/>was merely a Mutual Benefit Society. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The Bill was agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> moved 
     <lb/>
     the House into Committee of the Whole 
     <lb/>
     on a Bill further to amend the Law re<lb break="no"/>lating to Parish Schools. . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon Attorney General</persName> explained that 
     <lb/>
     this Bill was before the last Session. It 
     <lb/>
     merely provides that where a County 
     <lb/>
     adopts the assessment principle they shall 
     <lb/>
     receive the amount. of ten per cent above 
     <lb/>
     what is granted to other Parish Schools, 
     <lb/>
     which by the old law is confined to Par<lb break="no"/>ishes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Hon. Mr. CONNELL</persName> was in favor of 
     <lb/>the principle of assessment for Schools,<lb/>but should prefer to have the Bill left<lb/>over till the next Session of the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - was surprised at the At<lb break="no"/>torney General bringing in this Bill as it<lb/>was imperfect. It did not provide the<lb/>regular machinery for carrying out its pro<lb break="no"/>visions. No power was given in the<lb/>School Act to the Sessions to assess for<lb/>School purposes, and consequently it<lb/>could not be carried out.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> said<lb/>the provision requiring the peole of a<lb/>Parish to meet together was applicable<lb/>under this Bill to a County.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> thought it would be<lb/>better for the Attorney General to look<lb/>into the matter of Education and hiring in<lb/>a Bill that would remedy the evils exist<lb break="no"/>ing under the present School Law, which<lb/>has been found to be very inoperative. The<lb/>money now paid was frittered away in sup<lb break="no"/>porting ten Schools where two are suf<lb break="no"/>ficient for the wants of the people. In<lb/>1863, he brought in a Bill to remedy the<lb/>matter, and it was the duty of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to take hold of the question and see<lb/>that the law is carried out. He would<lb/>ask if the Board of Education had done<lb/>their duty in limiting the number<lb/>of Schools to the requirements of a Parish or<lb/>district? He did not speak against the<lb/>present Bill, but to draw the attention of<lb/>the Attorney General to the preparation<lb/>of a new Bill that will remedy the evils<lb/>that now exist, for we grant more money<lb/>for the purposes of Education than any<lb/>other country in proportion to our popu<lb break="no"/>lation, but we do not get results commen<lb break="no"/>surate with the amount we pay out. His<lb/>idea was that there should be fewer<lb/>Schools and they more effective.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr. HIBBARD</persName> thought it would be<lb/>better to have a general revision of the<lb/>School Law than to fill up the Statue<lb/>Book with amendments to the existing<lb/>law. He thought the present system of<lb/>inspecting schools very unsatisfactory,<lb/>inasmuch as they have so much ground<lb/>to go over that they canoot give<lb/>more than an hour or two to a school<lb/>when the work should not be got through<lb/>within half a day. The law also provides<lb/>that rate-payers shall be called together<lb/>in cases of assessment, but who were<lb/>they? The law does not define it suffici<lb break="no"/>ently. It should say rate-payers on real<lb/>and personal property. If the law needs<lb/>amending it would be best to thoroughly<lb/>revise the existing law.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LEWI1">Mr. LEWIS</persName> said the present system of 
     <lb/>inspection was very unsatisfactory. He<lb/>knew that in his part of the country the<lb/>Inspector (Mr. Duval) would go to a<lb/>school and go from it without producing<lb/>any benefit. The people were crying out<lb/>all over the country, and he should op<lb break="no"/>
       

            <pb n="77" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-07-04_Page_077.jpg"/>
          
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">77</fw> 


     pose any Bill till there was a revision of   
     <lb/>the whole law.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BABB1">Mr. BABBITT</persName> agreed with the re<lb break="no"/>marks made. There was much dissatis<lb break="no"/>faction existing with regard to the pre<lb break="no"/>sent law. The average attendance princi<lb break="no"/>ple he thought had worked badly in the<lb/>back settlements. The system of in<lb/>spection he thought was worthless, and<lb/>denominational grants he did not believe<lb/>in. He thought the best plan was to give<lb/>the amount to a general seat of learning<lb/>and improve the status of the Parish<lb/>Schools.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> also called the atten<lb break="no"/>tion of the Attorney General to the sub<lb break="no"/>ject and while he could not oppose the<lb/>passage of the present Bill, he thought it<lb/>necessary that the whole School Law<lb/>should be revised.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> the fur<lb break="no"/>ther consideration of the Bill was post<lb break="no"/>poned till the next session of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> moved the House<lb/>into Committee of the Whole on a Bill to<lb/>provide for defraying of expenses of the<lb/>civil Government. <persName ref="pers:LEWI1">Mr. LEWIS</persName> in the<lb/>chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName> moved the House<lb/>into Committee of the Whole on a a Bill<lb/>relating to the City of Fredericton. <persName ref="pers:CHAN1">Mr.<lb/>CHANDLER</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was agreed to with certain<lb/>amendments.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:QUIN1">Mr. QUINTON</persName> moved the House<lb/>into Committee of the Whole on a Bill to<lb/>enable the Corporation of St. John to<lb/>effect certain improvements in the streets<lb/>of said City on the Eastern side of the<lb/>Harbor. <persName ref="pers:DOW1">Dr. DOW</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> moved<lb/>the House into Committee of the Whole<lb/>on a Bill to provide for the repairs and<lb/>improvement of the Roads and Bridges,<lb/>and other public works and services<lb/> <persName ref="pers:FLEW1">Mr. J. FLEWWELLING</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

            <p>
     The Bill was agreed to.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> submitted the follow<lb break="no"/>ing Report :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>The Committee to whom was referred<lb/>the Bill to incorporate the <choice><sic>Internationa-</sic><corr>International</corr></choice><lb/>Telegraph Company submit the follow<lb break="no"/>ing Report :<lb/>
            </p>


            <p>The Committee have taken the matter<lb/>into consideration, and whilst they are<lb/>in favor of the Bill with some amend<lb break="no"/>ments, they find that certain persons and<lb/>interests are opposed to the passage of<lb/>the Bill, and desire to be heard in oppo<lb break="no"/>sition thereto, and there being not suffi<lb break="no"/>cient time to hear them during the pre<lb break="no"/>sent session of the Legislature, the<lb/>Committee recommend the further con<lb break="no"/>sideration of the Bill remain over until<lb/>next Session, and the Committee ask<lb/>that in the meantime their organization<lb/>may remain with power to them to make<lb/>a further report at the next session of<lb/>the Legislature.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">C. N. SKINNER,<lb/>CHARLES CONNELL,<lb/>J. M. JOHNSON.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Sept. 4 1866<lb/>
            </p></quote>

    
            <cb/>
            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> moved for leave to     
     <lb/>bring in a Bill to permit the annexation<lb/>to British America upon certain condi<lb break="no"/>tions, by and with the consent of the<lb/>Imperial Parliament, of the States of<lb/>Maine, Vermont, Massachusetts and Con<lb break="no"/>necticut, with provisions for the organiza<lb break="no"/>tion of Territorial Government for Penn<lb break="no"/>sylvania, Nantucket Island and New<lb/>York.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> stated that this was<lb/>intended as a set off to the Bill intro<lb break="no"/>duced into the Congress of the United<lb/>States to annex these Provinces to them.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill caused much laughter, but<lb/>was not received.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> moved the House into<lb/>Committee of the Whole on a Bill rela<lb break="no"/>ting to Marriage. Dr. Dow in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> explained that this Bill 
     <lb/>contemplates the reduction of the time<lb/>for publishing banns, and the reduction of<lb/>the license fees, and the remission of the<lb/>fee demanded from the clergy for regis<lb break="no"/>tration by the Clerk of the Peace. It<lb/>would be better to take the fee for re<lb break="no"/>gistration at the time of issuing of the<lb/>license.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> was opposed to the short 
     <lb/>ening of the time of publication of<lb/>banns ; he thought three weeks was<lb/>quite little enough time. He should<lb/>therefore oppose that section, although<lb/>he was in favor of the other two.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCQU1">Mr. McQUEEN</persName> thought the two pro<lb break="no"/>visions would clash ; he was of opinion<lb/>that it would be better to make the time<lb/>of publication three months.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BABB1">Mr. BABBITT</persName> was in favor of the Bill,<lb/>especially of the section relieving the<lb/>minister officiating from paying to the<lb/>Clerk of the Peace a fee of three and<lb/>nine pence for registration.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> thought that great<lb/>inconvenience would arise if the party<lb/>were compelled to produce to the clergy<lb break="no"/>man a certificate from the Clerk of the<lb/>Peace that the fee of fifty cents had<lb/>been paid for registration. Many mar<lb break="no"/>riages that take place in the back set<lb break="no"/>tlements are by the publication of banns.,<lb/>and then the party would have to go<lb/>the county town to get the certificate. He<lb/>was afraid that this Section would not<lb/>work.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> was opposed to the<lb/>shortening of the time of publication of<lb/>banns, and thought it best to lay the Bill<lb/>over till next Session.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName>, <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>, and<lb/>others, also spoke on the Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Mr. TILLEY</persName> moved that the further<lb/>considerations be postponed three months<lb/>House divided on postponement—Yeas<lb/>13, Nays 18.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A further discussion then ensued with<lb/>regard to the propriety of making the al<lb/>terations proposed by the Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Progress was reported, without leave<lb/>to sit again.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>House adjourned till tomorrow morn<lb break="no"/>ing at 9 o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     J. M. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<!-- GL, 2018-03-27, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
           <!-- <p>
     —     
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     THURSDAY, JULY 5     
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>After the usual routine of business had<lb/>been disposed of, the House in Com<lb break="no"/>mittee passed the following Bills :<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill to incorporate the People's<lb/>Street Railway Company in the City and<lb/>County of St. John."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill to encourage the formation of<lb/>Oyster Beds."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill relating to certain Parish Offi<lb break="no"/>cers."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill to amend a law relating to the<lb/>Export Duty on Lumber."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill to provide for the expense of<lb/>the Legislature."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. McCLELEN presented sev<lb break="no"/>eral petitions from the inhabitants of the<lb/>County of Westmorland, praying that a<lb/>more central line of railway may be<lb/>constructed through that County than<lb/>the one now proposed to be built by the<lb/>International Railway Company<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of Mr. YOUNG, the House<lb/>passed a Resolution authorizing the<lb/>Government to expend the sum of $2.000,<lb/>(being a grant made for that purpose in<lb/>1863.) In the improvement of Bethurst<lb/>Harbor, provided the expenditure of<lb/>that sum would produce a correspond<lb break="no"/>ing benefit.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of Mr. CAIE, the House<lb/>went into Committee on a Bill to pro<lb break="no"/>vide for the more effectual repairing of<lb/>Roads and bridges in the Parish of<lb/>Carleton, County of kent.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. CAIE said the Bill was similar to<lb/>one passed for the Parish of Richibucto<lb/>some years ago, and which had been<lb/>found to work well, for a great deal<lb/>more work had been done since it went<lb/>into operation than was done formerly.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> said the princi<lb break="no"/>ple of the Bill was very good, but it was<lb/>not fair to make a distinction between<lb/>different sections of the country ; under<lb/>this Bill persons would have to pay<lb/>twenty-five cents in lieu of a day's work,<lb/>but under the general law they would<lb/>have to pay fifty cents. He thought that<lb/>if they exacted a money tax, instead of<lb/>having the present absurd law, more<lb/>work would be done than at present.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said they should<lb/>not select one or two Parishes, and<lb/>make them an exception to the general<lb/>law. If they found that more work was<lb/>done, when a tax of twenty-five cents<lb/>was exacted they had better make it ap<lb break="no"/>plicable to the whole Province.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. YOUNG said there were laws 
     <lb/>similar to this in operation in some dis<lb break="no"/>tricts in Northumberland, and they had<lb/>been found to work well. When it was<lb/>made compulsory that persons should<lb/>pay twenty-five cents in lieu of a day's<lb/>work, more work was done than under<lb/>the present system.<lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>