<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1867-05-29"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1867-05-29">29 May 1867</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="96" to="97"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-29_Page_096.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-29_Page_097.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-04-24">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-04-24">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-29_Page_096">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-29_Page_096.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-29_Page_097">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-29_Page_097.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="96" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-29_Page_096.jpg"/>
           

     <fw type="num">96</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> 

            <p>[...] question should be well looked into. If<lb/>we are to give up our Stock to Canada, it<lb/>would, of course, be better to give a<lb/>bonus of $3,500 more to the Railway.<lb/>I think, however, it will be found that my<lb/>construction of the Act in this particular<lb/>is correct, that its application is to<lb/>property we had at the time Act was<lb/>passed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.—If the construc<lb break="no"/>tion put upon the Act by the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Westmorland is correct, it would<lb/>enable New Brunswick and Nova Scotia<lb/>to take stock in anything, and make the<lb/>General Government responsible for it ;<lb/>thus, though it might amount to $14.000,<lb break="no"/>000, and the value be in reality only<lb/>$7,000,000 yet they would have to pay<lb/>the full amount. If his constriction is<lb/>right, it would of course be the easiest<lb/>way to do it, but I am afraid that is neither<lb/>the intention nor the construction of the<lb/>law. I know in Conference we told<lb/>them that we had Railways which should<lb/>go in ; Canada said they had no Rail<lb break="no"/>ways, but they had $16,000,000 stock in<lb/>the Grand Trunk and it was not expected<lb/>that that should come in with their debts.<lb/>So with regard to the stock which we<lb/>hold in the Saint Andrews and Quebec<lb/>Railway ; that becomes the property of<lb/>the Government, because that was taken<lb/>before the Act, but I do not think we<lb/>could now take more stock and expect<lb/>them to become responsible for it. This<lb/>power, I think is not conferred upon us<lb/>by the Act.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I should like to know, 
     <lb/>then, how we can legislate on the County<lb/>Courts? There is a Bill now before the<lb/>House which contemplates the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture of large salaries for Judges, which<lb/>is not provided for in the Act of Union.<lb/>Sections 96. 97 and 100 say :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" 96. The Governor General shall ap<lb break="no"/>point the Judges of the Superior, District<lb/>and County Courts, in each Province,<lb/>except those of the Courts of Probate in<lb/>Nova Scotia and New Brunswick."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"97. Until the Laws relative to Pro<lb break="no"/>perty and Civil Rights in Ontario, Nova Scotia<lb/>and New Brunswick, and the pro<lb break="no"/>cedure of the Courts in those Provinces<lb/>are made uniform, the Judges of the<lb/>Courts of those Provinces appointed by<lb/>the Governor General shall be selected<lb/>from the respective Bars of those Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"100. The Salaries, Allowances and<lb/>Pensions of the Judges of the Superior,<lb/>District and County Courts, (except the<lb/>Courts of Probate and Nova Scotia and New<lb/>Brunswick), and of the Admiralty<lb/>Courts, in cases where the Judges thereof<lb/>are for the time being paid by salary,<lb/>shall be fixed and provided by the Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     I would ask why the exception is made 
     <lb/>of the Courts of Probate, if it is not to<lb/>show that we have power over these and<lb/>no others? I would also ask if it is<lb/>competent to make a Judge of Probate<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
           

     a Judge of a County Court? I think not  
     <lb/>—I do not believe we have the power to<lb/>do anything of the kind. I am aware that<lb/>section 92, clause. 14, gives to the Local<lb/>Legislature—<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"The administration of Justice in the<lb/>Province, including the constitution,<lb/>maintenance and organization of Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Courts, both of Civil and Criminal<lb/>Jurisdiction, and including procedure in<lb/>Civil matters in those Courts."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     But, still, we cannot pass an Act here        
     <lb/>to appoint Judges to the County Courts<lb/>because the Act of Union gives that<lb/>power into the hands of the General<lb/>Government, both of Courts and Judges.<lb/>And if we can create County Courts,<lb/>why, I would ask, cannot we go on<lb/>and create District Courts, too? That<lb/>power, it seems to be conceded, is<lb/>denied to us.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.—The exception 
     <lb/>was made of Courts of Probate because<lb/>it was distinctly understood, and it is<lb/>embodied in the Act, that no person<lb/>appointed to those Courts could be paid<lb/>out of the central funds. But suppose<lb/>we chose to increase the number of<lb/>Supreme Judges to seven, they would<lb/>all have to be paid out of the general<lb/>fund ; and, whether these Courts are<lb/>established here now or not, the Act<lb/>concedes to us the power to create the<lb/>new Courts. There is no trouble at all<lb/>about the spirit and sentiment of what<lb/>was intended, nor I think about the law<lb/>itself.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILM1">Hon. Mr. WILMOT</persName>.—I do not think<lb/>the salaries we may fix will be binding<lb/>upon the General Government, but so<lb/>far as the creating of these Courts and<lb/>the appointing of Judges is concerned, I<lb/>think there is no doubt but that we have<lb/>the power. I have long felt the necessi<lb break="no"/>ty of such Courts here, as have long been<lb/>established in England and in Western<lb/>Canada, and I know it was distinctly<lb/>talked about and settled by the Confer<lb break="no"/>ence. I think also that we have a perfect<lb/>power to take additional stock in Rail<lb break="no"/>ways or to give a bonus right out, as we<lb/>see fit, but I think that to do it after the<lb/>passage of that Act, and thus increase<lb/>our liability, would be to practice a fraud<lb/>upon the General Government.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—Then there is prosecu<lb break="no"/>tion for crime, that pertains, I see, to the<lb/>New Dominion, as I understand it ; and<lb/>I would ask the Attorney General if the<lb/>criminal jurisprudence of the country be<lb break="no"/>longs to the General or Local Govern<lb break="no"/>ment?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>.—I shall not take<lb/>up the time in answering these matters<lb/>to-day, but when the County Courts<lb/>Bill comes up, I will go into the whole<lb/>question.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:BABB1">Mr. BABBIT</persName>.—I would ask who we   
     <lb/>are to get information from if not from<lb/>
           

            <cb/>
    

         

     the Government? If the Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eral is the proper authority to give infor<lb break="no"/>mation on these questions, I think he<lb/>certainly ought to do it. If it is not his<lb/>duty, then we ought to look to some one<lb/>else who can enlighten us on these im<lb break="no"/>portant matters, for at present we seem<lb/>to be legislating in the dark.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.—This discussion has been<lb/>very profitable, enbracing as it does the<lb/>very business for which we came here,<lb/>and I think we ought to have another<lb/>sitting.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I should certainly very<lb/>much like to have some of my questions<lb/>answered, I have tried almost everything<lb/>to gain information, but as yet I have<lb/>been unsuccessful.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName>.—I can sympathize<lb/>with my hon. friend, for I well remember<lb/>how I was kept in the dark on very im<lb break="no"/>portant matters on one occasion, although<lb/>I asked questions for a period of forty<lb/>days.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName>.—I move, Mr. Chairman,<lb/>that you have the Chair, report progress,<lb/>and ask leave to sit again.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName> called the attention of 
     <lb/>the Committee to the fact that during the<lb/>whole debate, which had taken a wide<lb/>range, there had been nothing before the<lb/>Chair, in the shape of motion, or resolu<lb break="no"/>tion, and that according to the rules laid<lb/>down they could not report progress<lb/>without having something to make pro<lb break="no"/>gress in. He hoped in future that some<lb/>resolution would be placed distinctly be<lb break="no"/>fore the Committee, so that the rules of<lb/>debate might not be infringed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> having resumed his<lb/>seat, Mr. Stevens reported that the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee of the Whole House having had<lb/>under their consideration the Report of<lb/>the Auditory General, begged to report<lb/>that they had made progress therein, and<lb/>asked for leave to sit again.<lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">PETITIONS, BILLS, ETC.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> presented the Peti<lb break="no"/>tion of Thomas King, of the City of St.<lb/>ohn, Railway Contractor, praying for an<lb/>investigation of his claim against the<lb/>Government.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Petition was received and laid on<lb/>the table.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> moved for leave to 
     <lb/>bring in a Bill in further amendment of<lb/>the Act relating to the management of<lb/>the General Public Hospital in the City<lb/>of Saint John.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Leave was granted and the Bill read a 
     <lb/>first time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> asked the Chief Commis<lb break="no"/>sioner of the Board of Works to lay be<lb break="no"/>fore teh House the Petition of William<lb/>O'Brien relating to a Bridge.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> said he would<lb/>do so to-morrow morning.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> moved for leave to 
     <lb/>
        

            <pb n="97" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-29_Page_097.jpg"/>
     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw>  <fw type="num">97</fw>


     bring in a Bill to provide for the inspec<lb break="no"/>tion of Petroleum and Coal Oils and<lb/>Burning Fluids.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Leave was granted and the Bill read 
     <lb/>a first time.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FERR2">Mr. FERRIS</persName> presented the Petition 
     <lb/>of J.C. Bergee, jr., and 85 others, in<lb break="no"/>habitants of Queen's County, praying<lb/>that parts of the Counties of the Queen's,<lb/>Subury, Kent, and Northumberland<lb/>might be formed into a separate County.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Petition was received and laid   
     <lb/>on the table.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> laid before the 
     <lb/>House certain papers relating to Fire<lb/>Loan Bonds and Delegation Expenses.<lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SENATORS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.- I will take this oppor<lb break="no"/>tunity to ask if the Government still<lb/>continue to withhold the information<lb/>about the appointment of Senators?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.- We have receiv<lb break="no"/>ed no further information since my last<lb/>reply.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FERR2">Mr. FERRIS</persName> presented the Petition 
     <lb/>of Charles Clarke and 100 others, in<lb break="no"/>habitants of Queen's County, praying<lb/>that the line of certain Great Roads<lb/>might be changed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Petition was received and laid<lb/>on the table.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">N. E. ANTIMONY COMPANY.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> moved the House into<lb/>Committee on a Bill to ratify and con<lb break="no"/>firm the incorporation of the New<lb/>Brunswick Antimony Company.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> said the Bill was<lb/>accompanied by a Petition, and all the<lb/>requirements of the Act had been com<lb break="no"/>plied with but making oath before a<lb/>Justice of the Peace, which as some<lb/>of the parties resided in the United<lb/>States was found very inconvenient, and<lb/>they prayed to be released from the por<lb break="no"/>tion of the law.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr. HIBBARD</persName> said it would require<lb/>more than the bare statement of the Pe<lb break="no"/>tition that the 15 per cent, of the capital<lb/>stock had been paid up. He did not<lb/>believe it had been, but if it had, it<lb/>was very easy for them to show proof ;<lb/>the Secretary's office was quite near, and<lb/>the information could very soon be ob<lb break="no"/>tained.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> said he heid the<lb/>Secretary's certificate that the amount<lb/>had been paid up.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr. HIBBARD</persName> said he believed the<lb/>matter had been before the Government<lb/>and they, not having proof of the propor<lb break="no"/>tion of stock having been paid up, refused<lb/>to grant the certificate.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILL1">Hon. Mr. WILLISTON</persName> confirmed the<lb/>statement of Mr. Hibbard as to the<lb/>withholding of the certificate.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
    

    

    

    

    

            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> said that was very<lb/>strange, as she held the certificate in his<lb/>hand, signed by the Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILL1">Hon. Mr. WILLISTON</persName> said there<lb/>must be some mistake about it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> moved that progress be<lb/>reported, which, the Speaker having re<lb break="no"/>sumed the Chair, was done.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> then moved that the<lb/>Bill be referred to a Special Committee<lb/>to report upon, and Mesers, Stevens,<lb/>Smith, and Ilibbard were so appointed.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">ST. STEPHEN FIREMEN.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCAD1">Hon. Mr. McADAM</persName> moved the House<lb/>into Committee on a Bill relating to Fire<lb break="no"/>men in the Parish of St. Stephen.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was agreed to without any<lb/>debate.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House then adjourned till to<lb break="no"/>morrow morning, at 10 o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>


<p rendition="simple:right">J.M.</p>

<!-- GL, 2018-04-24, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
           <!-- <p>THURSDAY, May 30.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The following Bills were read a third<lb/>time, passed the House, and were sent to<lb/>the Legislative Council for their concur<lb break="no"/>rence therein :<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill to incorporate the Richibucto<lb/>Boom Company. "<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill further to amend the Law<lb/>relating to the Poor House in the City<lb/>and County of St. John, in respect to<lb/>Vagrants and Beggars. "<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill in addition to the Act to pro<lb break="no"/>vide for the Relief of the Sufferers by the<lb/>late calamitous Fire at Indiantown, in the<lb/>Parish of Portland. "<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill relating to Firemen in Mill-<lb break="yes"/>town, in the Country of Charlotte. "<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill to enable the Corporation of<lb/>the City of St. John to make certain im<lb break="no"/>provements on the Streets of St. John,<lb/>on the Western Side of the Harbor. '<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName>, in compliance<lb/>with the request of the hon. member for<lb/>Northumberland (Mr. Kerr), laid before<lb/>the House the Petition of William<lb/>O'Brien, praying that he may receive<lb/>compensation for losses sustained in the<lb/>erection of a Bridge in Northumberland.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. QUINTON moved the House into<lb/>Committee (Mr. McQUEEN in the<lb/>Chair) on a Bill relating to Paved Side<lb break="no"/>walks in the City of St. John.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> asked informa<lb break="no"/>tion of the Chairman of the Committee to<lb/>whom was referred matters relating to the<lb/>amending of the Labor Act, whether<lb/>any progress had been made therein, and<lb/>whether their Report would be made<lb/>shortly ?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. BECKWITH replied that the<lb/>Committee had made progress, but they<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     had been delayed by his being called to 
     <lb/>the Agricultural Board ; however, they<lb/>would have their Report in to-morrow.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> moved the House<lb/>into Committee (Mr. DESBRISAY in<lb/>the Chair) on a Bill to attend an Act en<lb break="no"/>titled an Act to provide for the erection<lb/>of a City Hall in the City of St. John.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of Mr. QUINTON, the<lb/>House in Committee (Mr. W. P. FLEW-<lb break="maybe"/>ELLING in the Chair) agreed to a Bill<lb/>authorizing the assessment of the City<lb/>and County of St. John, for the purpose<lb/>of an Agricultural Exhibition therein.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. QUINTON presented a Petition<lb/>from the Justices of the Peace in the City<lb/>of St. John, praying that a Bill presented<lb/>by the Common Council of the City of<lb/>St. John, for widening the Country<lb/>Market, may not be passed by this<lb/>Legislature.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> moved that a Select Com<lb break="no"/>mittee be appointed to take into conside<lb break="no"/>ration the Petition of William O'Brien,<lb/>praying for compensation for losses sus<lb break="no"/>tained in the erection of a Bridge in the<lb/>County of Northumberland.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Committee : Messre, Chandler, Babbit,<lb/>DesBrisay:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> reported that the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee to whom had been referred the Bill<lb/>to incorporate the St. John Marine In<lb break="no"/>surance Company had amended the same,<lb/>and recommended the Bill as amended.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>COUNTY COURTS.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> moved the House<lb/>into Committee upon a Bill to establish<lb/>County Courts.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. BOTSFORD in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr FISHER.- This Bill will recom<lb break="no"/>mend itself, and it is not necessary for me<lb/>to make any lengthy remarks upon it. It<lb/>has long been the desire of the country<lb/>that there should be some more expendi-<lb break="maybe"/>tious way of collecting small debts, and a<lb/>less expensive way of administering jus<lb break="no"/>tice ; therefore, to meet this want, this<lb/>Bill has been prepared to establish<lb/>County Courts, so that causes may be<lb/>brought to a more speedy issue, diminish<lb/>the amount of business in the Supreme<lb/>Court and get rid of the Court of Com<lb break="no"/>mon Pleas. They will try a large pro<lb break="no"/>portion of the Criminal business, which is<lb/>now a great expense to the country from<lb/>persons being detained in jail for a length<lb/>of time, in consequence of the infre<lb break="no"/>quency of the sittings of the Supreme<lb/>Court in some Counties. If we feel that<lb/>there County Courts are necessary, we<lb/>will all feel anxious that its provisions<lb/>should be made as perfect as possible, and<lb/>we invite the assistance of hon. members<lb/>to attain that object. A question has<lb/>been asked as to whether this House has<lb/>the right to legislate upon this subject.<lb/> <lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>