<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1865-05-23"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-05-23">23 May 1865</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1865</title>.
                    


     <date when="1865"/>.  



          <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="84" to="86"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-23_Page_0084.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-23_Page_0085.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-23_Page_0086.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-02-27">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-02-27">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-23_Page_0084">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-23_Page_0084.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-23_Page_0085">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-23_Page_0085.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-23_Page_0086">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-23_Page_0086.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="84" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-23_Page_0084.jpg"/>
          
<fw type="num">64</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1863.</fw> 
           

   <!-- GL, 2018-02-27, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day -->      
<!--<p>
     be, " if he is ordered off, and refuses to            
     <lb/>go, he should be taken into custody. It<lb/>is very hard for a man to be deprived of<lb/>his liberty ; some men are very sensitive<lb/>and would remember it all the days of<lb/>their life.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Hon. Mr. Allan. - My hon. friend says <lb/>who is to decide whether it is a willful<lb/>trespass or not ; the distinction is well<lb/>known ; if a man goes upon the ground<lb/>after he has been forbidden, he is willfully<lb/>interfering with the practice, and should<lb/>be taken into custody for that day by the<lb/>verbal order of the commanding officer.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Hon. Mr. Smith suggested that the  
     <lb/>words " and refuse to leave after being<lb/>requested to do so," be inserted after the<lb/>word ' purpose' in the Section. This sug<lb break="no"/>gestion was adopted.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
          Mr. Wetmore moved that the follow-_ 
     <lb/>ing be the 102 Section of the Bill :<lb break="no"/>" That no Militia man employed in the salt<lb/>water fisheries shall be liable to be called<lb/>on to do duty as such, in any camp of in<lb break="no"/>struction during the fishing season be<lb break="no"/>tween the months of March and Novem<lb break="no"/>ber in each year."<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         This Section was lost.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    On motion of Mr. Hill the following<lb/>additional clause was inserted in the 83rd<lb/>Section, " Members of Fire Companies,<lb/>and Hook and Ladder Companies in any<lb/>city or town, shall be exempt from duty<lb/>beyond the limits of the same respect<lb break="no"/>ively."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    The Bill was then reported as agreed<lb/>to, with certain amendments.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    The House then adjourned until nine <lb/>o'clock tomorrow.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    T.P.D.<lb/>
            </p>-->


            <head rendition="simple:right">    TUESDAY, MAY <choice><sic>22</sic><corr>23</corr></choice>.<lb/>
            </head>
   
    

            <p>
         Mr. Young moved a ryder to the Militia<lb/>Bill. He had been looking over the Can<lb break="no"/>adian Act, and he found among the ex<lb break="no"/>empts " sea-faring men, branch pilots,<lb/>and pilots actually engaged in their call<lb break="no"/>ing." He thought this would cover the<lb/>deep sea fishery men who certainly should<lb/>not be liable to the draft.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Keen said he thought that seamen, <lb/>branch pilots, and those engaged in deep<lb/>sea fisheries should be exempt. The<lb/>pilots were as much required to attend to<lb/>vessels entering our ports, as ferrymen to<lb/>cross our streams. In Canada all fisher<lb break="no"/>men and pilots engaged on the Lakes<lb/>were exempt.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Hon. Mr. Hatheway said this ryder <lb/>would cover all the people of the County<lb/>of Gloucester as it was well-known that<lb/>every man there kept his fishing boat and<lb/>went out in the morning to return at<lb/>night.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
         Mr. Young explained that there were        
     <lb/>over a thousand militia men, besides those<lb/>whom it was contemplated to, exempt.<lb/>His object was to exempt those men who<lb/>go to the Labrador coast and elsewhere,<lb/>and are absent during four months in the<lb/>year.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Hon. Mr. Allan said he thought it <lb/>would be best to let the Bill run for a<lb/>year, and in that time it would be seen<lb/>upon whom it bore hardly, and could be<lb/>remedied.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     
     
         Mr. Williston said those who were       
     <lb/>engaged in the deep sea fisheries had but<lb/>a short time to obtain their livelihood,<lb/>and during that time they should be ex<lb break="no"/>empt.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     
     
     
         Mr. Needham wanted to know the         
     <lb/>meaning of deep sea fisheries. The sea is<lb/>defined as below low water mark. The<lb/>difficulty would be to define the meaning<lb/>of the term. He had looked over the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Dictionary and found sea, seaman,<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
 

     
     and sea devils, but nothing of sea-faring  
     <lb/>men.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. McClellan said if any class of<lb/>men should be exempt it was the farmers<lb/>of the country. We were giving a great<lb/>power into the hands of an irresponsible<lb/>officer withouth having received any com-<lb break="yes"/>complaint or petition from the people, and he<lb/>thought the whole thing was uncalled for.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Boyd moved the following to be <lb/>added to the list of exempts, as an amend<lb break="no"/>ment : " That no militia man employed<lb/>in the deep sea fisheries in the Gulf of St.<lb/>Lawrence, Bay de Chaleur and Bay of<lb/>Fundy, be called on to do duty as such in<lb/>any camp of instructions during the fishing<lb/>season between the months of April and<lb/>October in each year ; and also branch<lb/>pilots and apprentices, and pilots employ<lb break="no"/>ed in their calling during the season of<lb/>navigation.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     
     
     
         Mr. Coran thought that any man who       
     <lb/>was engaged in harbour fisheries, which<lb/>were of great importance to the country,<lb/>should be placed amongst the exempts.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Hon. Mr. Allen felt confident that if <lb/>this class of men were made exempt that<lb/>dissatisfaction would be felt among many<lb/>other callings. It would be very difficult<lb/>to define who came within the meaning of<lb/>the law, and he thought that it would be<lb/>best to let the Bill remain as it is for this<lb/>year. The hon. member for Albert (Mr.<lb/>McClellan) seemed to pursue a somewhat<lb/>inconsistent part, as he now opposes a<lb/>Bill which contains the same provisions<lb/>as that he supported under the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
         Mr. McMillan said there was one class 
     <lb/>of men who should be exempt, and he was<lb/>sure the Hon. Commissioner of the Board<lb/>of Works would support him in this ; he<lb/>referred to the lumbermen of the Province.<lb/>At certain seasons it would be a gret loss<lb/>to have these men taken from their em<lb break="no"/>ployment. Suppose a gang of men were<lb/>employed on a raft of logs coming down<lb/>the Nashwaak and they were to be called<lb/>off to attend drill, the Hon. Commissioner<lb/>would be subjected to great loss ; he<lb/>thought these should be added to the list<lb/>of exempts.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. Wetmore said he had moved in  
     <lb/>this matter yesterday when the Bill was<lb/>before the Committee, and he could not<lb/>support either the ryder, or amendment,<lb/>unless it included all who were engaged<lb/>in salt water fisheries. He hoped the<lb/>hon. member for Charlotte would allow<lb/>them to be included in the amendment.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>    Mr. Thompson did not believe the <lb/>draft would be enforced at all, as there<lb/>would be plenty of volunteers to fill the<lb/>camp. He thought it was all nonsense<lb/>to bring in these exemptions, and that the<lb/>Bill should remain as it is.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
     
         Mr. Otty informed the Hon. Attorney        
     <lb/>General that what is implied by deep sea<lb/>fisheries could easily be known by refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the Fishery Act, 14th Victoria,<lb/>Chap. 31, Section 4, where the coast fish<lb break="no"/>eries are defined to be " situated on the<lb/>sea coast of the Province, or around any<lb/>island laying off the said sea coast, be<lb break="no"/>tween low water mark and three marine<lb/>miles of each coast or island." The deep<lb/>sea fishery would be outside of this line.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
         Mr. Needham thought that lawyers   
     <lb/>should be added to the list of exempts, as<lb/>it would be very hard to take them from<lb/>their duties during the settings of the<lb/>Courts.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
         Mr. McClellan would explain to the  
     <lb/>hon. Attorney General that at the time of<lb/>the passing of the last Bill he did not<lb/>vote for it. He believed the Bill was not<lb/>debated at all. There was, however, a dif<lb break="no"/>ferent construction placed upon : certain<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
         

     words now from what was then contem<lb break="no"/>plated. The consent of the Queen<lb/>was understood to mean the Queen and<lb/>Her Council ; the command of His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency the Lieutenant Governor was<lb/>considered the Governor and his advisers.<lb/>Now these terms are confined to the per<lb break="no"/>sons named without reference to their<lb/>Council or advisers. If it were not for<lb/>this construction he would not have spok<lb break="no"/>on the subject.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. Lindsay said it would be very hard      
     <lb/>for the farmers to be called out ; the<lb/>season was short, and if they lost a<lb/>month's labor, it might affect their sub<lb break="no"/>sistence for the year. He thought the<lb/>best plan would be to move a ryder that<lb/>nobody should be called out. If the law<lb/>passes, every man should take his turn,<lb/>and if any one was to be exempted, the<lb/>farmers certainly should be ; they are the<lb/>bone and sinew of the country. The peo<lb break="no"/>ple can do without fish, for they can get<lb/>beef and farm produce, but if these fail<lb/>the country would suffer.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     
     
         Mr. Fraser hoped that another class      
     <lb/>would be included in the list ; he referred<lb/>to the back settlers, who were a very va<lb break="no"/>luable class of people.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Williston would suggest to the <lb/>hon. mover of the amendment the desira<lb break="no"/>bility of including the Straits of North<lb break="no"/>umberland. He wished the House to un<lb break="no"/>derstand that tho grounds used for fish<lb break="no"/>ing purposes by the people on the coast<lb/>are the same as those used by the Ameri<lb break="no"/>cans, the only difference being that our<lb/>people go out in their whale boats for the<lb/>day and return at night, and they lie off<lb/>in their vessels. There would be no dif<lb break="no"/>ficulty in determining what is meant by<lb/>deep sea fishing, as it is understood by<lb/>the Americans as outside of three miles<lb/>from the coast line.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     
     
     
     
     
         Mr. Lewis said there was so much dif<lb break="no"/>ficulty in knowing what was really meant<lb/>that he thought the Bill should remain as<lb/>it is.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Bailey said there was another class <lb/>of men he should like to see added, and<lb/>that was all men engaged in the coasting<lb/>trade, and the fresh water sailors running<lb/>in our rivers and inland lakes.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         Mr. Landry said a great many of his   
     <lb/>people hired out for a month, and if they<lb/>lost this time they would be subject to a<lb/>great inconvenience, and all should be<lb/>treated alike. The best plan would be to<lb/>kill the Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Cudlip said if anything justified <lb/>him in the action he took yesterday as to<lb/>the compulsory draft, it was the feeling<lb/>which was manifested this morning. He<lb/>was strongly opposed to men being taken<lb/>from their calling in a time of peace. The<lb/>hon. members were speaking as the<lb/>people, and the feeling was general that<lb/>every calling should be exempt from the<lb/>draft. But he thought if there was one<lb/>class more than another upon which it<lb/>would fall heavily, it was those engaged<lb/>in the shore fisheries. These men are at<lb/>home, and come within the law, whilst<lb/>those who are absent engaged in the deep<lb/>sea fisheries could not be reached. He<lb/>hoped the ryder would be made to cover<lb/>both parties.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     
     
     
     
         On the amendment being put the House       
     <lb/>divided, yeas 10, nays 10. They were<lb/>therefore both lost.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
         The Militia Bill being read a third time  
     <lb/>was then passed as amended by the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
         Hon. Mr. Gillmor moved the House   
     <lb/>into Committee of the Whole on a Bill to<lb/>provide for repairing and improving Great<lb/>Roads and Bridges and other public works<lb/>and services.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    
            <pb n="85" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-23_Page_0085.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>  <fw type="num">85</fw> 
   

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CUDL1">Mr. CUDLIP</persName> in the chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Bill was agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GILL1">Hon. Mr. GILLMOR</persName> moved the House 
     <lb/>
     into Committee of the whole on   Bill to 
     <lb/>
     provide for the defraying of the expenses 
     <lb/>
    of the civil government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CUDL1">Mr. CUDLIP</persName> in the chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Hon. Mr. BOTSFORD</persName> moved the House 
     <lb/>
    into Committee of the whole on a Bill re<lb break="no"/>lating to Sewers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. BEVERIDGE in the chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLIN</persName> moved the House 
     <lb/>
     into Committee on a Bill to promote and 
     <lb/>
     regulate a Reformatory School for juvenile 
     <lb/>
     offenders. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> in the chair. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLIN</persName> said it had been 
     <lb/>considered by a great many persons in St. 
     <lb/>John that such schools were necessary. 
     <lb/>Various schemes had from time to time 
     <lb/>been proposed, but none of them had suc<lb break="no"/>ceeded, chiefly from the want of means to 
     <lb/>carry them into effect. His Honor Judge 
     <lb/>Parker had taken a great interest in the 
     <lb/>subject, and obtained information as to 
     <lb/>the working of such institutions in Eng<lb break="no"/>land, and had laid it before the Quarter 
     <lb/>Sessions. The plans he has suggested 
     <lb/>have not been considered possible, and 
     <lb/>nothing has been done. The Bill now 
     <lb/>before the Committee was founded on a 
     <lb/>different principle to any that had been<lb/>suggested here. It was almost a tran<lb break="no"/>script of the Reformatory Bill passeded by 
     <lb/>the Imperial Parliament, and he consider<lb break="no"/>ed this in itself a great recommendation. 
     <lb/>Instead of being carried on as a public 
     <lb/>institution, it provides that it shall be 
     <lb/>supported by private interests. Hon. Mr. 
     <lb/>Anglin then proceeded to explain the 
     <lb/>provisions of the Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> asked if the juvenile crimi<lb break="no"/>nals were to be associated with the poor, 
     <lb/>
    ignorant children picked up from the 
     <lb/>streets. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLIN</persName> explained that it was   
     <lb/>
     only intended for juvenile criminals who     
     <lb/>
    were subjected to 14 days in the Peniten<lb break="no"/>tiary.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName> asked if there was any 
     <lb/>
     petition before the House in support of 
     <lb/>
     the Bill. It seemed that the Government 
     <lb/>
     were to support it by a grant of money, 
     <lb/>
     and he should like some further informa<lb break="no"/>tion on the subject. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLIN</persName> explained that the 
     <lb/>
     subject was one that had been urgred for 
     <lb/>
     a long time—some seven or eight years,— 
     <lb/>
     and as to the grant, it was not compul<lb break="no"/>sory, but permissive. The School would 
     <lb/>
     be under the inspection of the Governor 
     <lb/>
     and Council, and any person appointed for 
     <lb/>
     the purpose of inspection, and if the 
     <lb/>
     School wes not carried on in such a man<lb break="no"/>ner as would prove beneficial the grant 
     <lb/>
     could he withheld. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName> had a great objection to 
     <lb/>
     appropriating the public funds for such a 
     <lb/>
    purpose. He had watched the operations       
     <lb/>of hon. members for St. John when the 
     <lb/>Hospital Bill was up, and he noticed after 
     <lb/>the whole was got through they wanted 
     <lb/>an appropriation of £2,000. He did not 
     <lb/>know but this might be something of the 
     <lb/>same kind; at any rate, the Bill was too im<lb break="no"/>portant to be rushed through, and he hoped<lb/>progress would be reported to give mem<lb break="no"/>bers an opportunity of looking it over.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLIN</persName> said there was not, 
     <lb/>nor had there been, any desire to push<lb/>the Bill through. It had been on fyle<lb/>since the first week of the Session, and<lb/>hon. members could have investigated it.<lb/>He had been careful to point out the pro<lb break="no"/>visions of the Bill, so that nothing should<lb/>be passed without coming under the di<lb break="no"/>
          

            <cb/>
        
rect notice of the Committee. With re<lb break="no"/>gard to the sectarian character of the 
     <lb/>
     instruction to be imparted in the School, 
     <lb/>
     the gentlemen who had framed the Bill 
     <lb/>
     did not believe in any religion which was 
     <lb/>
     not sectarian. They regarded it as hav<lb break="no"/>ing no existence -- as a nonentity. No 
     <lb/>
     injustice was done to any denomination, 
     <lb/>
     for all could under this Bill get up just 
     <lb/>
     such an institution. If hon. members 
     <lb/>
     thought best, he was willing to submit it 
     <lb/>
     to a select Committee to alter and amend 
     <lb/>
     it, if they thought necessary, and report 
     <lb/>
     to the House upon it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">Hon. Mr. WILMOT</persName> said from his know<lb break="no"/>ledge of the City of St. John, he believed 
     <lb/>
     it necessary that some such institution as 
     <lb/>
     this should be established. Judges Parker 
     <lb/>
     and Ritchie had both taken this matter up 
     <lb/>
     at different times, and brought it before 
     <lb/>
     the notice of the Sessions, and impressed 
     <lb/>
     upon them the necessity of making some 
     <lb/>
     provision for juvenile offenders. He should 
     <lb/>
     
    like to have seen a measure that would 
     <lb/>heve included all denominations; but as 
     <lb/>there appeared to be little prospect of 
     <lb/>this at present, and as the ccae was a 
     <lb/>pressing one, he was in favour of being 
     <lb/>referred to a Select Committee to report 
     <lb/>upon it.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> thought the Bill was entirely 
     <lb/>
    of a local character. In no other country 
     <lb/>than St. John would sufficient juvenile 
     <lb/>offenders be found to warrant the estab<lb break="no"/>lishment of such an institution. And even 
     <lb/>if it were not so, no country could at any 
     <lb/>rate afford more than one, and that ac<lb break="no"/>cording to this Bill, must be under the 
     <lb/>religious instruction of one denomination. 
     <lb/>And then to take an offender who had 
     <lb/>been sentenced to 14 days imprisonment 
     <lb/>and put him in a Reformatorn  for five 
     <lb/>years, looked very much like placing a tax 
     <lb/>   upon the country for its support. He saw 
     <lb/>that the Bill was very important, and that 
     <lb/>all the Province would be effected by it. 
     <lb/>He admitted the general principles of the 
     <lb/>Bill, but it should be very carefully guard<lb break="no"/>ed. He would like to know if the Bill 
     <lb/>had been laid before the Sessions.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLIN</persName> said it had not; but 
     <lb/>
     so much had been said and done, that 
     <lb/>
     certain parties ln St. John thought it 
     <lb/>
     ought to be brought before the House. 
     <lb/>
     Manny of the difficulties had been removed, 
     <lb/>
     and they were ready to work at 
     <lb/>
     once and put up a building; but without 
     <lb/>
     the passage of the Bill they would have 
     <lb/>
     no power to retain the children. As to 
     <lb/>
     the support of the Government, it was 
     <lb/>
    entirely free to be given or withheld, and 
     <lb/>if that was considered an objection, rather 
     <lb/>than have nothing done, he was willing to 
     <lb/>allow that section to be struck out. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName> asked if the subject of 
     <lb/>
     establishing a Reformatory had not been 
     <lb/>
     before the Sessions, and if this buîlding 
     <lb/>
     were put up to what denomination would 
     <lb/>
     it belong.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLIN</persName> said the Sessions had 
     <lb/>
    not been able to agree upon any plan by 
     <lb/>which it could be carried on. It was well 
     <lb/>to have everything plain and above board, 
     <lb/>and he would say that this Bill emanates 
     <lb/>from from the Catholic body of St. John. The 
     <lb/>hon. member for Carleton seemed to be<lb/>afraid that a building which had been <lb/>erected in St. John was to be used for<lb/>this purpose. He could assure thim that<lb/>no such thing was contemplated. There<lb/>was one provision in the Bill which he<lb/>had forgotten to mention, and that was,<lb/>the parents of those children placed in the<lb/>School would be liable for a certain por<lb break="no"/>tion of their support, and could be sued<lb/>if they refused to pay. The bill in its<lb/>character was not local, but provincial;<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
     

     but it was denominational, as without a<lb/>course of religious instruction, it was be<lb break="no"/>lieved no improvement could be looked<lb/>for. The difficulty with the Sesions had<lb/>been chiefly that they thought the country<lb/>ought not to provide the funds, and were 
     <lb/>
     afraid the Province would not. He was 
     <lb/>
     quite willing to allow progress to be re<lb break="no"/>ported, so that members could read the 
     <lb/>
     Bill and consider its provisions. He did<lb/>not wish to smuggle it through the house<lb/> 
               <lb/>
    for it was an object of the greatest im<lb break="no"/>portance that these poor unfortunate chil<lb break="no"/>dren should be saved from a life of crime, 
     <lb/>and that the community should be re<lb break="no"/>lieved of them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CORA1">Mr. CORAM</persName> said it was time something 
     <lb/>was done in this matter. The police re<lb break="no"/>ports of Saint John show that the number 
     <lb/>of juvenile offenders is continually in<lb break="no"/>creasing, and he t thought it was a great 
     <lb/>wrong that children of tender age, who 
     <lb/>had been brought up in vice and crime, 
     <lb/>should for some small offence be put in 
     <lb/>the Penitentiary to become hardened by 
     <lb/>contact with old offenders. He saw no 
     <lb/>objection to children being trained and 
     <lb/>instructed in the religion of their fore<lb break="no"/>fathers, and nothing in the Bill that should 
     <lb/>prevent its going through. He was in 
     <lb/>favor of progress being reported that 
     <lb/>members might look into the Bill and be 
     <lb/>in a position to carry it through the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> endorsed the idea of 
     <lb/>the hon. member for Saint John ; but the 
     <lb/>hon. member for Carleton (Mr. Connell) 
     <lb/>seemed to think that because there was no 
     <lb/>petition it was therefore hardly worth 
     <lb/>while to go into the matter. The hon. 
     <lb/>member had not probably seen the police 
     <lb/>court of Saint John. There, frequently, 
     <lb/>boys of from eight to twelve years of age 
     <lb/>were arraigned for trifling offences,, (but 
     <lb/>which the law regarded as larceny, and, 
     <lb/>therefore, the Magistrate could not over<lb break="no"/>look) and were sentenced for different 
     <lb/>periods to the Provincial Penitentiary. 
     <lb/>If the Magistrate made the penalty light 
     <lb/>on account of the circumstances in which 
     <lb/>they were reared, and the influences by 
     <lb/>which they were surrounded they were sure 
     <lb/>to be brought up again and again. The 
     <lb/>Penitentiary was a very bad school to 
     <lb/>teach boys to reform, for there they were 
     <lb/>thrown in contact with men of the worst 
     <lb/>character, who had committed the vilest 
     <lb/>crimes. The hon. member was afraid 
     <lb/>there was something sectarian in the 
     <lb/>School proposed to be established; he 
     <lb/>would ask the hon. member if he was 
     <lb/>ready to proscribe the Roman Catholics? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>. -- No, but let it be known 
     <lb/>
     by what denominetion the School is to be 
     <lb/>
     carried on . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> would put it to the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member if he was willing to prevent the 
     <lb/>
     Protestants moving in the matter? He 
     <lb/>
     thought the step a very laudable one, and 
     <lb/>
     one that reflects credit on the Catholics. 
     <lb/>
    of Saint John for taking the initiative in a 
     <lb/>matter of so much importance. he was 
     <lb/>sorry the Protestants had not moved be<lb break="no"/>fore. but he hoped they would do so now. 
     <lb/>The hon. member for Northumberland 
     <lb/>(Mr. Kerr) appeared to be alarmed lest<lb/>the country should crumble to pieces on<lb/> 
               <lb/>the mention of money grants, but he was<lb/>sure that money could not be better em<lb break="no"/>ployed than in such an undertaking. All<lb/>that other denominations would have to<lb/>do, was to subscribe funds and put up a<lb/>building, to have a Reformatory too. He<lb/>had frequently heard both Mr. Justice<lb/>Parker and Mr. Justice Ritchie speak in<lb/>the strongest terms of the necessity for<lb/>such a reform school, and he was glad that<lb/>steps were taken to do something for these<lb/>poor untrained boys.<lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="86" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-23_Page_0086.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="num">86</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>



            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Mr. McCLELLAN</persName> said no hon. member 
     <lb/>
    could object to the position taken by the 
     <lb/>hon. member for the city of Saint Joh.. 
     <lb/>There could be no doubt but that a Re<lb break="no"/>formatory was very much needed there. 
     <lb/>The only objection he raised was that it<lb/>was sectional and sectarian, and therefore<lb/>should not be supported by the funds of 
     <lb/>the Province. He thought the Catholics 
     <lb/>were entitled to much praise for the steps 
     <lb/>they were taking, but this School being 
     <lb/>entirely for the benefit of Saint John, and 
     <lb/>under the care of the Catholic body, should 
     <lb/>not be upheld by public grants. He did 
     <lb/>not think such Institutions were needed in 
     <lb/>  any other part of the country; but, apart 
     <lb/>but apart from the grant, was willing to assist in 
     <lb/>carrying out the views of those who had 
     <lb/>framed the Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName> said the objections to 
     <lb/>
    the Bill semed to be narrowing down to 
     <lb/>the details. Judgess Parker and Ritchie, 
     <lb/>whose only motives could be to bring 
     <lb/>juvenile offenders from the paths of vice 
     <lb/>and iniquity into those of virtue, had ta<lb break="no"/>ken great interest in this matter, and he 
     <lb/>thought the House should take hold with 
     <lb/>them and do something to assist in carry<lb break="no"/>ing out so laudable an object.   The train<lb break="no"/>ing in this school would sectarian and 
     <lb/>he thought it should be; he did not see 
     <lb/>how such an Institution could be carried 
     <lb/>on if it were not sectarian. As to the 
     <lb/>grant the Governor and Council were not 
     <lb/>compelled to take action, and give towards 
     <lb/>its support. All denominations could or<lb break="no"/>ganize under this law, and amounts could 
     <lb/>be granted to each as required. It was, 
     <lb/>however, entirely voluntary on the part of 
     <lb/>the Governor and Council and also on 
     <lb/>the part of the Sessions, to grant any<lb break="no"/>thing towards its support. If there were 
     <lb/>any objection. to this Section, he had no 
     <lb/>doubt the hon. mover would consent to 
     <lb/>have it struck out And as there was so 
     <lb/>little objection. he thought it would be 
     <lb/>best to go on and pass the Bill at once. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     AFTERNOON SESSION -- 3 P.M. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> said Section 7 gave authority 
     <lb/>
     to the Sessions to assess the whole in<lb break="no"/>habitants to any amount needed for an 
     <lb/>
     object that was entirely sectarian, and as 
     <lb/>
     there was no petition from them asking 
     <lb/>
     that such a power might be granted he 
     <lb/>
     thought the Committee should pause be<lb break="no"/>fore passing the Bill. Section 10 says 
     <lb/>
     that this Reformatory could only be made  
     <lb/>
     available for one denomination, and he 
     <lb/>
     did not think that all other sects should 
     <lb/>
     be assessed to support it. He hoped pro<lb break="no"/>cess would be reported. to give time for 
     <lb/>
     the Bill to be printed and circulated about 
     <lb/>
     the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName> could see no objection 
     <lb/>
     to it. If gentlemen chose to get up a school 
     <lb/>
     of this kind and to support it, every en<lb break="no"/>couragement should be given them. There 
     <lb/>
     was no danger that the Sessions would 
     <lb/>
     assess the whole population for one deno<lb break="no"/>minational school, and if the hon. mover 
     <lb/>
     would strike out the Section with refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the Governor and Council, he 
     <lb/>
     could see nothing objectionable in the 
     <lb/>
     Bill, or that required that progress should 
     <lb/>
    be reported. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName> said his only objection 
     <lb/>
     was that a grant should be taken from the 
     <lb/>
     Provincial funds. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLIN</persName> thought the striking 
     <lb/>
     out at that clause would seriously detract 
     <lb/>
     from the usefulness of the Institution. 
     <lb/>
     He should test the feeling of the House 
     <lb/>
     upon it, but he would" rather consent to 
     <lb/>
     have it struck out than have no Bill at all. 
     <lb/>He thought the Committee now thorough<lb break="no"/>ly understood the Bill, and did not call<lb/>for reporting progress. So far as the in<lb break="no"/>
          

            <cb/>
         
struction was concerned-this school would 
     <lb/>
     be denominational ; but it was neither 
     <lb/>
     sectarian nor sectional that we should have 
     <lb/>
     one murderer, or one thief, or one felon 
     <lb/>
     the less, and the community one good 
     <lb/>
     citizen more. He was opposed to even 
     <lb/>
     the smallest denomination having any<lb break="no"/>thing but fair play and he asked no more 
     <lb/>
    for the denomination to which he belong<lb break="no"/>ed that he would willingly grant Protes<lb break="no"/>tant Episcopalians, or Presbyterians, or 
     <lb/>Baptists.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HILL1">Mr. HILL</persName> considered the move a good 
     <lb/>one; taking up the youth who had been<lb/>
     
    surrounded by evil influences all their  
     <lb/>lives and placing them where better habits 
     <lb/>would be inculcated. The objectionable 
     <lb/>point was that the Governor and Council 
     <lb/>may give pecuniary assistance. The 
     <lb/>" may" might just as well be "shall," for 
     <lb/>that was the effect of the clause. The 
     <lb/>carrying on of a Reformatory was hedged 
     <lb/>with difficulties. If it should be carried 
     <lb/>on without any religious instruction, in 
     <lb/>five years the inmates would be more like 
     <lb/>heathens than christians. Then it would<lb/>certainly be a wrong to compel them to<lb/>receive a certain denominational educa<lb break="no"/>tion contrary to the wishes of their 
     <lb/>parents. And then there was the plan 
     <lb/>now introduced ; but this is denomina<lb break="no"/>tional, and he did not wish to see the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment suffering any greater denomina<lb break="no"/>tional pressure than now, and he thought 
     <lb/>the Government grant should be struck 
     <lb/>out. But with regard to the Sessions he 
     <lb/>was willing to go further than the Bill 
     <lb/>provided, and make it compulsory on them 
     <lb/>to assess the people to support such a 
     <lb/>school. If a youth were sent there, it was 
     <lb/>not for the benefit of the denomination to 
     <lb/>which his father belonged. but for the 
     <lb/>good of the community. He did not ap 
     <lb/>prove of any more denominational grants, 
     <lb/>for he believed that now some schools re<lb break="no"/>ceived assistance more on account of the 
     <lb/>denomination than from any merits they 
     <lb/>possessed in themselves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HATH1">Hon. Mr. HATHEWAY</persName> thought the ques<lb break="no"/>tion should not be taken up on denomi<lb break="no"/>national grounds. He regretted that re<lb break="no"/>ligion was brought up in connection with 
     <lb/>grants to schools. It had long been com<lb break="no"/>plained that the Provincial Penitentiary 
     <lb/>had been used for these young miscreants,<lb/>while the people all over the Province 
     <lb/>had to pay for their support. The Gaol<lb/>accommodation of Saint John was not 
     <lb/>sufficient, and so they had to be sent 
     <lb/>there; and now when it is proposed to 
     <lb/>take them off the hands of the Province, 
     <lb/>complaints are made that it is the work 
     <lb/>of a certain denomination. In his official 
     <lb/>capacity, as one of the Commissioners of 
     <lb/>Public Institutions, he had seen children 
     <lb/>working at the same bench with the vilest 
     <lb/>criminals. This should not be. He was 
     <lb/>in favor of the Bill, and should go for 
     <lb/>anything that would tend to benefit these 
     <lb/>juvenile offenders. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> referred to the position 
     <lb/>
    of boys in the Penitentiary that they were 
     <lb/>liable to the same penalties, as the men; 
     <lb/>that from the influences by which they 
     <lb/>had been surroundedsil all their lives they 
     <lb/>were not so much to blame; that their 
     <lb/>being sent to the Penitentiary was but 
     <lb/>the means of hardening and totally des<lb break="no"/>troying them; and he thought they should 
     <lb/>not be sent there at all, but at once put 
     <lb/>into Reformatory, and that there every<lb break="no"/>thing should be done to save them from a 
     <lb/>life of degradation and crime. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName> had never known but one 
     <lb/>
     case of good resulting from punishment 
     <lb/>during the ten years of his magistracy,<lb/>and that was a boy who was sentenced to<lb/>the Penitentiary with two others. He<lb/>
  

            <cb/>
       

     came back and has since lived honestly 
     <lb/>and worked industriously. He believed<lb/>that children should not be sent there are<lb/>all, but that Magistrates should have<lb/>power to commit them directly to the Re<lb break="no"/>formatory. The obejct of conviction was<lb/>not punishment, but reformation. He<lb/>felt that punishment should never be in<lb break="no"/>flicted by man except for murder, and he<lb/>fully believed that if during the last cen<lb break="no"/>tury men had done as much to reform<lb/>abuses as they have to punish offences<lb/>there would not be so much crime and<lb/>degradation as there are now.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:THOM1">Mr. THOMPSON</persName> was anxious to see some<lb/>such Institution established, as he be<lb break="no"/>lieved it would be the means of saving a<lb/>a large amount of money in the expenditure<lb/>for the Provincial Penitentiary.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName> said it was evident that<lb/>juvenile delinquency was on the increase;<lb/>this was shown by the report of the Chief<lb/>of Police in Saint John. It therefore, 
     <lb/>now becomes necessary for the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture to deal with the matter. and, decide 
     <lb/>whether these young criminals should con<lb break="no"/>tinue to be educated in crime, or stop the 
     <lb/>present system and train them in a Re<lb break="no"/>formatory, where their habits would be 
     <lb/>changed. This was not a local affair; it 
     <lb/>was not confined to Saint John, but one in 
     <lb/>which all the country felt an interest. 
     <lb/>After the friends of the Institution had 
     <lb/>done all their means would permit, the 
     <lb/>Government should step in and assist in 
     <lb/>the work. The system now proposed is 
     <lb/>carried out in England and upheld by 
     <lb/>English law. If it is wished to reform 
     <lb/>these youths it is not only necessary to 
     <lb/>give them a moral training but also a reli<lb break="no"/>gious, a spiritual training. the only mode 
     <lb/>by which they could permanently be bene<lb break="no"/>fitted is by giving them a Christian train<lb break="no"/>ing in that which is right and good. He 
     <lb/>thought the hon. member for Saint John 
     <lb/>(Mr. Anglin) deserved much credit for 
     <lb/>introducing the Bill.   
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. MCMILLAN</persName> did not view this ques<lb break="no"/>tion in the light of a denominational in<lb break="no"/>stitution but as a sectional, a local one. 
     <lb/>It had been admitted that even Frederic<lb break="no"/>ton was not in a position to support one 
     <lb/>of these Reform Schools, and it was evi<lb break="no"/>dent that only Saint John could be bene 
     <lb/>fitted. He therefore should oppose the 
     <lb/>granting of the Provincial funds for a 
     <lb/>purely local object.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> regretted that an institution 
     <lb/>could not be obtained that would embrace 
     <lb/>the whole juvenile offenders of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, but as it appeared this could not 
     <lb/>be done, he thought this one had a strong 
     <lb/>a claim on the revenues of the country. 
     <lb/>Still he was opposed to giving the power 
     <lb/>to grant  into the hands of the Governor 
     <lb/>and Council.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On the question whether power should 
     <lb/>be given to the Governor and Council to 
     <lb/>grant assistance to the Institution the 
     <lb/>House divided—Yeas 10. Nays 11. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Progress was then reported  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName> moved the House into 
     <lb/>Committee of the whole on a Bill relating 
     <lb/>to Marriage. Mr. LEWIS in the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>This Bill, the object of which is to 
     <lb/>shorten the time in the publication of 
     <lb/>banns, and to reduce licence fees, was 
     <lb/>supported by Petitions from almost every 
     <lb/>part of the Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>After some remarks by various mem<lb break="no"/>bers progress was reported.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILL1">Hon. Mr. GILLMOR</persName> moved for leave to 
     <lb/>bring in a Bill relating to Light Houses. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> moved for leave to bring in 
     <lb/>a Bill relating to Saint John's Church, 
     <lb/>Chatham.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>House adjourned to meet on Thursday<lb/>morning at 9 o'clock.  J.M.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
       
     <lb/>
            </p>
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>