<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1867-05-21"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1867-05-21">21 May 1867</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="54" to="61"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_054.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_055.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_056.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_057.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_058.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_059.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_060.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_061.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-04-18">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-04-18">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_054">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_054.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_055">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_055.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_056">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_056.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_057">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_057.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_058">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_058.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_059">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_059.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_060">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_060.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_061">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_061.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="54" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_054.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="num">54</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES IN THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw>
  

<!-- GL, 2018-04-18, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

           <!-- </p>
   
            <p>increase the wants of the country in<lb break="no"/>crease in proportion.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House adjourned until to-morrow<lb/>at 9 o'clock.<lb/>T.P.D.<lb/>
            </p>-->


            <head rendition="simple:right">TUESDAY, MAY 21.<lb/>
            </head>

            <head rendition="simple:centre">SECOND READINGS.<lb/>
            </head>
   
    

    

    

    

            <p>The following Bills were read a second<lb/>time:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to repeal an Act relating to<lb/>burial grounds in the town of Saint An<lb break="no"/>drews.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to authorize the Corporation of<lb/>the City of Saint John to assess in<lb break="no"/>habitants for the purpose of an Agricul<lb break="no"/>tural Exhibition.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill relating to the Paving of the<lb/>Side-walks in the City of Saint John.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill relating to the purchase of lands<lb/>in the County of Westmoreland, for the<lb/>purpose of a Market place.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to amend the Act relating to the<lb/>levying, assessing and collecting of rates<lb/>in the City of Saint John.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill in amendment to the Act relative<lb/>to Municipalities.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill relating to the election of mem<lb break="no"/>bers to serve in the General Assembly.<lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">THIRD READINGS.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p>The following Bills were read a third<lb/>time:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to authorize the erection of a<lb/>Marine Hospital at the Port of Caraquet.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to provide for the erection of an<lb/>Alms House and Work House in the<lb/>County of Northumberland, with power<lb/>to make rules, order and regulations for<lb/>the management of the same.<lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">RULE OF PUBLICATION.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName> asked Mr. Quinton if<lb/>he had brought in any Bill contrary to<lb/>the rule of the House, with respect to<lb/>the publication of notice. He saw it<lb/>stated in one of the papers that a Bill<lb/>had been brought in affecting the asses<lb break="no"/>sing of Saint John, for $20,000. He<lb/>thought there was some mistake as he<lb/>had no recollection of anything of the<lb/>kind.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:QUIN1">Mr. QUINTON</persName> said the statement was<lb/>incorrect. He had brought in a Bill to<lb/>assess $12,000, for the Streets of Carle<lb break="no"/>ton, and the rule was suspended in that<lb/>case as, although the Bill had been pub<lb break="no"/>lished, he was not supplied with the cer<lb break="no"/>tificate; but it would be handed in if it<lb/>was not already done. The statement<lb/>in the paper was evidently a mistake, the<lb/>two affairs being mixed up by some<lb/>means.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> moved for leave to<lb/>bring in a Bill to Incorporate the Saint<lb/>John Trades' Co-operative Association.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Leave granted and the Bill being<lb/>brought in was read a first time.<lb/>
            </p>

    
            <cb/>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">GREAT ROADS.</head>


            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> moved the<lb/>House into Committee on a Bill realting<lb/>to the Great Roads of the Province.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName> said that last year he<lb/>brought in a Bill to have a very impor<lb break="no"/>tant road, in the County of Gloucester,<lb/>placed on the Great Road list; and he<lb/>wished to ask the Chief Commissioner<lb/>why that road was not included in this<lb/>Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> said that every<lb/>year there were a large number of Bills<lb/>introduced to place certain roads upon<lb/>the Great Road list. Last year there<lb/>were seventeen, and it was evidently im<lb break="no"/>possible to comply with all. The object<lb/>of this Bill was not so much to increase<lb/>the number of miles as to place on the<lb/>list short roads leading to the Railways<lb/>and other very public places. It will be<lb/>found that he had not specially favored<lb/>his own County in this Bill, when, per<lb break="no"/>haps it might have been supposed he<lb/>would have done so. One road did run<lb/>into the County of Albert, but it was<lb/>more than counterbalanced by the repeal<lb/>of the road which leads from Salmon<lb/>River to Point Wolf. The County of<lb/>King's might appear to have been favor<lb break="no"/>ed, but on examination it would be<lb/>found that the number of miles taken off<lb/>was more than equivalent to those now<lb/>put on the list. The short roads leading to<lb/>the Railways had been found necessary<lb/>to be placed on, while others of less im<lb break="no"/>portance had been taken off. In West<lb break="no"/>morland County there was about half a<lb/>mile of road leading from Moncton to the<lb/>Petitcodiac Bridge, which al lwould<lb/>agree was very necessary to be placed<lb/>on the last, and another short road at the<lb/>Petitcodiac Station. There was one<lb/>road in the County of Carleton, about six<lb/>miles long, which was one of the largest<lb/>additions, and a short piece leading from<lb/>Woodstock Corner to the landing. In<lb/>Saint John County he had added the road<lb/>from the Suspension Bridge to the Port<lb break="no"/>land Road, the road from the City to In<lb break="no"/>diantown, and about a mile and a half of<lb/>the road from the Marsh Bridge to the<lb/>Penitentiary. It would be conceeded on<lb/>all hands that these were quite necessary,<lb/>and he thought that partiality had not<lb/>been known to any particular section of<lb/>the country.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> said that the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Gloucester need not complain<lb/>that one road had not been put on the<lb/>Great Road list, for he had applied a<lb/>great many times to have several placed<lb/>on, but as yet ineffectually.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said there were several<lb/>roads in Westmorland which he would<lb/>like to have seen on the list, but he sup<lb break="no"/>posed it was not possible to put on all the<lb/>[missing] roads, and he thought the country<lb/>now was pretty well provided for, al<lb break="no"/>though of course he did not think they<lb/>had received full Justice. (Laughter)<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
    

            <p><persName ref="pers:CAIE1">Mr. CAIE</persName> thought he had great cause<lb/>of complaint, for the County of Kent was<lb/>about the only one in which additions<lb/>had not been made. He held a petition<lb/>from about five hundred of the inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants of the County, praying that the<lb/>road known as the McLaughlin Road<lb/>should be placed on the Great Road list.<lb/>The matter was a very important one,<lb/>for if this road were put in order the in<lb break="no"/>habitants of Welsford would be brought<lb/>very much nearer to the Railway than<lb/>they now are. By this road they would<lb/>be able to get their produce to the Rail<lb break="no"/>way by driving a distance of about thirty<lb/>miles, whereas now they ahve to go<lb/>eighty, and consequently thousands of<lb/>bushels of grain which would have pass<lb break="no"/>ed over the Railway last yaer, if the road<lb/>had been passable, were disposed of in<lb/>other ways, at a loss to the people. When<lb/>the Chief Commissioner was over that<lb/>way the weather was very unpleasant,<lb/>and he was not able to go over the road,<lb/>but he (Mr. C.) hoped the next time to<lb/>have the pleasure of driving him out<lb/>there. The road was cut through a dis<lb break="no"/>tance of twenty miles; but for want of<lb/>bridges over the streams which flow into<lb/>the Richibueto and the head waters of<lb/>the Buctouche and Shediac Rivers, it<lb/>could not be used for the purposes re<lb break="no"/>quired. He hoped that at least next<lb/>Session the road would be put in good<lb/>order.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Bill was agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> moved for teh<lb/>suspension fo the Rule to allow him to<lb/>bring in a Bill for the more effectual re<lb break="no"/>pairing of the Roads and BRidges of the<lb/>Parish of Hopewell, in the County of Al<lb break="no"/>bert.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The rule was suspended and leave be<lb break="no"/>ing granted the Bill was brought in and<lb/>read a first time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BEVE1">Mr. BEVERIDGE</persName> presented a Petition<lb/>from William Johnson, and forty others,<lb/>inhabitants of the Parish of Gordon, in<lb/>the County of Victoria, praying that a<lb/>road leading to the Tobique River might<lb/>be placed on the Great Road list.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Petition received and referred to the<lb/>Chief Commissioner of the Board of<lb/>Works.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILL1">Hon. Mr. WILLISTON</persName> moved for<lb/>leave to bring in a Bill relating to the<lb/>election of members to serve in the House<lb/>and Legislative Assembly.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">NOTICE OF ADDRESS.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> gave notice that he<lb/>should move the following Address:<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">Resolved</hi>, That an humble Address be<lb/>presented to His Excellency the Lieu<lb break="no"/>tenant Governor, praying that his Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency will be pleased to cause to be<lb/>laid before this House all Contracts and<lb/>papers relating to the empllyment of the<lb/>Steamer Princess of Wales to run on the<lb/>route from Shediac to Newcastle, in the<lb/>year 1865."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> said he had a memorial<lb/>from the Prince Edward Island Steam<lb/>
          

            <pb n="55" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_055.jpg"/>


     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> <fw type="num">55</fw>  
  

     Navigation Company, praying that the 
     <lb/>papers relating to a contract entered in<lb break="no"/>to by the Government with them to run<lb/>the Steamer "Princess of Wales" on the<lb/>North Shore in 1865 may be submitted<lb/>to a Committee of the HOuse to be inves<lb break="no"/>tigated and reported on.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said the matter had 
     <lb/>been before the Government, but as it<lb/>was a delicate matter, it was thought<lb/>best to let it got to a Committee, and in<lb/>accordance with the notice of motion the<lb/>papers would be submitted without the<lb/>formality of an Address.<lb/>
       
     <lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">BILLS, ETC.<lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Hon Mr. McCLELAN moved for leave 
     <lb/>to bring in a Bill to amend the Act In<lb break="no"/>corporating the Albert Bank.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Leave granted and the Bill begin<lb/>brought in was read a first time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> presented a Peti<lb break="no"/>tion from the Mayor, Aldermen and<lb/>Commonalty of the City of Fredericton,<lb/>praying that the Corporation may be<lb/>empowered to contract a loan in aid of<lb/>the Fredericton Railway, and as action<lb/>had only lately been taken on the sub<lb break="no"/>ject he prayed that the rule might be<lb/>suspended, which being done, leave was<lb/>granted, and the Bill read a first time.<lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PROCLAMATION - FISHERIES. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> asked the Provincial Sec<lb break="no"/>retary, whether, in accordance with the<lb/>statement put forth the other day, that<lb/>the proclamation of Union would issue<lb/>on the 20th instant. the Government had<lb/>received any intimation of the fact from<lb/>England.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> said the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had not received any communica<lb break="no"/>tion from England on the subject yet.<lb/>He had promised to reply to the hon.<lb/>member for Kent (Mr. Cale) with regard<lb/>to the Fisheries on the North Shore, and<lb/>would not say, that there were a num<lb break="no"/>ber of vessels on our coasts — one of<lb/>which had lately gone from Saint John<lb/>to Grand Manan — under the direction of<lb/>the Admiral, which were authorized to<lb/>see that our Fisheries were protected.<lb/>He was not informed as to theirnumber,<lb/>but His Excellency the Administrator of<lb/>the Government was now in communica<lb break="no"/>tion with the Admiral of the Station on<lb/>the subject, and he had no doubt that<lb/>they would attend to their duty<lb/>thoroughly.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> enquired if the same ar<lb break="no"/>rangement wtih regard to the licences<lb/>to American fishermen would be enter<lb break="no"/>ed into this year as last?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> thought that pro<lb break="no"/>bably the same principle would be con<lb break="no"/>tinued, but that it was contemplated to<lb/>advance the rate till measures were<lb/>taken by the General Parliament.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAIE1">Mr. CAIE</persName> asked what privileges the 
     <lb/>licences conferred upon American fish<lb break="no"/>
          

            <cb/>
           

     ermen, and if they were allowed to cast 
     <lb/>their bait close in short.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> believed that the 
     <lb/>taking out of licences put them on the<lb/>same footing as our own fishermen, but<lb/>he was not quite sure of the exact pri<lb break="no"/>vileges conferred.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said he understood that 
     <lb/>the licence gave them exactly the same<lb/>privileges as they enjoyed under the<lb/>Reciprocity Treaty, and he thought that<lb/>on examination this would be found to<lb/>be correct.<lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PETITIONS, BILLS, ETC. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Hon. Mr. CONNELL</persName> presented a 
     <lb/>Petition from James McIntosh and C.<lb/>D. Everett of the City of Saint John,<lb/>praying that the Act relating to the<lb/>formation of Oyster Beds might be<lb/>amended.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Petition was received and refer<lb break="no"/>red to the Committee appointed to take<lb/>into consideration all matters connected<lb/>with the Fisheries of the Province.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAIE1">Mr. CAIE</persName> presented a petition from 
     <lb/>over four hundred persons, inhabitatnts<lb/>of the County of Kent, praying that the<lb/>road known as the McLaughlin Road<lb/>might be placed upon the Great Road<lb/>List.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Petition was received and refer<lb break="no"/>red to the Chief Commissioner of the<lb/>Board of Works.<lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SPECIAL DAY FOR ELECTIONS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName> moved the House into 
     <lb/>Committee on a Bill relating to the<lb/>election of members to serve in the<lb/>General Assembly, so far as relates to<lb/>the County of Gloucester.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:QUIN1">Mr. QUINTON</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName> explained that this Bill<lb/>had been before a Special Committee,<lb/>who had reported favorable upon it. It<lb/>was simply to make it binding on the<lb/>Sheriff to cause elections to take place<lb/>on Monday, instead of leaving it to his<lb/>discretion. Great inconvenience was<lb/>felt from the course usually pursued<lb/>and Monday being the day which would<lb/>interfere less than any other with the<lb/>duties of the fishermen, it was con<lb break="no"/>sidered important the change should<lb/>be made. The Bill provided that elec<lb break="no"/>tions should take place on the Monday<lb/>following the day of nomination, but<lb/>three whole days must intervene be<lb break="no"/>tween that day and the day for pol<lb break="no"/>ling.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> thought that this<lb/>was interfering with the privilege of the<lb/>Sheriff. It had been found very satis<lb break="no"/>factory to leave the appointment of the<lb/>day entirely in the Sheriff's hands, and<lb/>to deprive him of power which was con<lb break="no"/>ferred upon those of every other County<lb/>might lead to difficulties. Moreover, the<lb/>Sheriff might appoint Saturday as the<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
     

     day for nomination and then three days 
     <lb/>notice could not be given, and this would<lb/>be contrary to the General Election Law.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said this difficulty could 
     <lb/>not occur, for the Bill specially provided<lb/>that three whole days must elapse, con<lb break="no"/>sequently the Sheriff could not appoint<lb/>Saturday for nomination, but must make<lb/>it Friday. The people of Gloucester<lb/>were largely fishermen, and it was in their<lb/>interest the Bill was brought in. They<lb/>return from their duties on Saturday to<lb/>go to Church Sunday, and are at home<lb/>ready for an election on Monday, but if<lb/>appointed for any other day they ahve to<lb/>leave their occupation and return speci<lb break="no"/>ally for the purpose of voting. So far as<lb/>the principle was concerned, he thought<lb/>it quite fair, but he would again ask the<lb/>Attorney General, as he had asked two<lb/>or three times before, how far the provi<lb break="no"/>sions of the Imperial Act of Union was in<lb/>force, and if we had the power to legis<lb break="no"/>late upon such questions as these?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> had told the hon. 
     <lb/>member for Gloucester (Mr. Young) when<lb/>the Bill was submitted that if it only con<lb break="no"/>templated the fixing of a certain day, and<lb/>did not interfere with the other provisions<lb/>of the Election Law, he would support it.<lb/>With regard to the question of the hon.<lb/>member for Westmorland (Mr. Smith) as<lb/>to how far the Imperial Act of Union was<lb/>in force, he could, of course, express his<lb/>private opinion, and he would say that<lb/>he thought this Bill did not in any way<lb/>interfere or conflict with th eprovisions of<lb/>that Act. He had now expressed hi<lb/>private opinion on the matter, but the<lb/>hon. member must know that he ought<lb/>not to ask any such question. It was<lb/>evidently done only to bother and annoy<lb/>him.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> was quite sincere in ask<lb break="no"/>ing the question, and he was surprised at<lb/>the remark of the Attorney General. He<lb/>(Mr. Fisher) had given his private opini<lb break="no"/>on, but it was certainly his duty to give a<lb/>public and official opinion upon this<lb/>question. If the Attorney General had<lb/>not looked into the matter, he should<lb/>have done so, and been in a position to<lb/>tell the House when they met just how<lb/>far that Act extended to our legislation at<lb/>the present Session. The Attorney<lb/>General had said that the House could<lb/>make the change in the law asked for in<lb/>the Bill, but he (Mr. S) had grave doubts<lb/>on the matter, for the Imperial Act was<lb/>based upon our laws as they were at the<lb/>passage of that Act, and was therefore<lb/>binding upon up, so far as making an al<lb break="no"/>teration in our laws was concerned. He<lb/>should not, however, oppose the passing<lb/>of the Bill, for he believed the change<lb/>would prove beneficial to the pople of<lb/>Gloucester.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> said that if the Bill 
     <lb/>merely required the Sheriff to appoint a<lb/>
     

            <pb n="56" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_056.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="num">56</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY 1867.</fw>
     
particular day for the elections, it could<lb/>certainly pass, without being affected by<lb/>the Imperial Act. He was not going into<lb/>a discussion upon the action of the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Act, but he would again say the<lb/>hon. member ought not to put the ques<lb break="no"/>tion to him. It was his duty as Attorney<lb/>General, after the Act had passed, to sit<lb/>down and bring to bear upon it all the<lb/>past and present knowledge he possessed,<lb/>and see if according to the Act of Union<lb/>we at this time have the power to legis<lb break="no"/>late upon it. It was not his duty to ex<lb break="no"/>press an opinion before the passage of the<lb/>Bill, but afterwords.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said this was a most ex<lb break="no"/>traordinary proposition. It was certainly 
     <lb/>
     the duty of the Crown Oflicers to advise 
     <lb/>
     the House of their opinions upon all legal 
     <lb/>
     matters that came before them of an im<lb break="no"/>portant public charactcr, and not to wait 
     <lb/>
     till Bills had passed before expressing 
     <lb/>
     that opinion.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Bill was then agreed to without 
     <lb/>
     further discussion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">EXPORT DUTY ON LUMBER<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> moved the House<lb/>into Committee on a Bill relating to the<lb/>Export Duty on Lumber.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. BOTSFORD</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>.— This is a Bill<lb/>which is intended to apply after the con<lb break="no"/>summation of Union. It provides that<lb/>the Export Duty on Lumber, which we<lb/>retain as a source of special revenue,<lb/>shall be collected by the officers of Cana<lb break="no"/>da, the Government paying them com<lb break="no"/>mission on the amounts they collect. If<lb/>this can be arranged, it will prevent the<lb/>necessity of appointing local officers for<lb/>the purpose ; but should difficulties arise<lb/>by their requiring too large a sum for the<lb/>collection of the duties, then the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment may appoint other officers for the<lb/>purpose.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr. HIBBARD</persName>.— Do I understand<lb/>that the amount of Export Duty collected<lb/>is to be paid into the general revenues of<lb/>Canada?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>.— Oh, no ; but that<lb/>the Deputy Treasures of Canada be em<lb break="no"/>ployed to collect the amounts at the<lb/>various ports<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr. HIBBARD</persName>.— I am afraid that the<lb/>employment of these men, all over the<lb/>country, will consume almost all the duty<lb/>that is collected. I think that the work<lb/>should be done with as little expense as<lb/>possible, and for this purpose one man<lb/>would be quite able to attend to the<lb/>whole work.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>,— One man could<lb/>not go all over the country to collect<lb/>the duties. The deputy Treasurers, when<lb/>the vessels are cleared, can very well col<lb break="no"/>lect the amounts from the parties.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr. HIBBARD</persName>.— If that is the inten<lb break="no"/>tion I shall not oppose the Bill, but I do<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
    


     think that now we should try every means<lb/>of cutting down our expenses, instead of<lb/>adding to them, and I hope the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will see that the work is done at as<lb/>small a cost as possible.<lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.— I am very happy to say,<lb/>Mr. Chairman, that I can support the<lb/>Government on this Bill. I have looked<lb/>through it, though not very carefully, but<lb/>sufficiently to see that it will be best to<lb/>pay a commission to the officers of Cana<lb break="no"/>da to collect the duties on Lumber, and<lb/>pay them over to the proper local officer.<lb/>That is, we say to the revenue officers<lb/>appointed by Canada, You now get so<lb/>much for your duties, which do not occu<lb break="no"/>py the whole of your time ; we will give<lb/>you so much upon the duties you collect,<lb/>if you will devote say one eighth of your<lb/>time to our service. And if this ar<lb break="no"/>rangement cannot be entered into at a<lb/>satisfactory rate, then the Government<lb/>have power to proceed any appoint other<lb/>officers for the purpose. There is one<lb/>point, however, to which I wish to call<lb/>the attention of the Attorney General,<lb/>and that is, that I think the Bill should<lb/>show upon its face the title of the Act by<lb/>which the duties are at present collected.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>,— I have no objec<lb break="no"/>tion to the insertion of the title of the<lb/>Act, although I do not think it is at all<lb/>material.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was then agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">PETITIONS AND BILLS<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MCAD1">Hon. Mr. McADAM</persName> presented a Peti<lb break="no"/>tion from Thomas Cotter and others, in<lb break="no"/>habitants of the Parish of Saint David's,<lb/>in the Country of Charlotte, praying that<lb/>they be authorized to assess a sum of<lb/>three hundred dollars, for the erection of<lb/>a Town Hall in said Parish.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Petition received and laid on the table.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCAD1">Hon. Mr. McADAM</persName> moved for the         
     <lb/>suspension of the rule to allow him to<lb/>bring in a Bill to provide for the erection<lb/>of a Town Hall in the Parish of Saint<lb/>David's, in the County of Charlotte, in<lb/>accordance with resolutions passed at a<lb/>town meeting in that parish, and submit<lb break="no"/>ted in a petition now before the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The rule was suspended, and leave<lb/>being granted, the Bill was brought in<lb/>and read for a first time.<lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">EXPENSES OF DELEGATES.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:CAIE1">Mr. CAIE</persName>.— It is with reluctance I<lb/>occupy the time of the House in speaking,<lb/>as I know the anxiety all experience to<lb/>get through the business and return<lb/>home, and I am sorry that so much valu<lb break="no"/>able time has been occupied with useless<lb/>talk already. Still, I consider it a duty I<lb/>owe myself and my constituents to see, as<lb/>far as I am able, that the revenues of the<lb/>Provinces are expended judiciously and<lb/>economically. Large amounts have been<lb/>expended since our last Session in dele<lb break="no"/>
           

            <cb/>
        
gations, and I now wish to ask the Hon. 
     <lb/>Provincial Secretary if it is the intention<lb/>of the Government to submit the papers,<lb/>showing the amounts paid for this pur<lb break="no"/>pose, without the time and formality of an<lb/>Address<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—The papers have already 
     <lb/>been asked for by my colleague, Mr.<lb/>McQueen<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAIE1">Mr. CAIE</persName>.—If that is the case, of       
     <lb/>course I have nothing more to say.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCQU1">Mr. McQUEEN</persName>.—I gave notice the 
     <lb/>other day that I should move an Address<lb/>for a detailed statement of the expendi<lb break="no"/>ture for these delegations. I will not ask<lb/>if it will be given without my pressing<lb/>the Address?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.—Yes, I have seen 
     <lb/>the notice on the Order Book, and the<lb/>papers will be laid before the House.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I wish we could get the 
     <lb/>items ; some of them would be quite<lb/>amusing.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.— Yes, not doubt of<lb/>it ; and I suppose the hon. member speaks<lb/>from his experience of delegations.—<lb/>(Laughter.)<lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">WOODSTOCK BRANCH RAILWAY.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Hon. Mr. CONNELL</persName> moved the<lb/>House into Committee on a Bill to pre<lb break="no"/>vent the Municipal Councillors of the<lb/>Country of Carleton, who are stockhol<lb break="no"/>ders, voting on the subsidy to the<lb/>Woodstock Branch Railway.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On the reading of the Bill Messrs.<lb/>Smith, Kerr, and others thought it in<lb break="no"/>volved a principle contrary to the spirit<lb/>of the Railway Bill, and on Mr. Lindsay<lb/>expressing his conviction that it did not<lb/>express the idea which was intended,<lb/>namely, to prevent Councillors who<lb/>hold stock donating the County funds<lb/>to their own use, Mr. Smith moved<lb/>that its further consideration be post<lb break="no"/>poned three months, which was car<lb break="no"/>ried.<lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">RECEIVER GENERAL.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> moved the House<lb/>into Committee on a Bill relating to the<lb/>Office of Receiver General.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. BOTSFORD</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>.—The Bill ex<lb break="no"/>plains itself, but it may be necessary<lb/>for me to say a few words. After the<lb/>Union is begun, it will be necessary<lb/>that we should have some person ap<lb break="no"/>pointed to receive the Revenues which<lb/>will be paid to the Province by the<lb/>General Government of Canada, as well<lb/>as those collected here, and to pay<lb/>them out for the purposes required.<lb/>He will also require an office and a<lb/>clerk. But as yet it is hard to say ex<lb break="no"/>actly what his duties will be, and what<lb/>emolument he should receive. In six<lb/>or eight months the House will meet.<lb/>
          

            <pb n="57" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_057.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> <fw type="num">57</fw> 


     again ; by that time it will be known 
     <lb/>
     exactly what is required. and for this 
     <lb/>
     purpose the Bill is only intended to be 
     <lb/>
     of a temporary character. It may be 
     <lb/>
     found necessary to make the office po<lb break="no"/>litical, but that could be better deter<lb break="no"/>mined after a short experience. Some 
     <lb/>
     have suggested that the name of Trea<lb break="no"/>surer, which we already have would 
     <lb/>
     be just as good as this, but as the other 
     <lb/>
     Provinces have adopted the title of Re<lb break="no"/>ceiver General for this officer, we have 
     <lb/>
     thought it best to adopt it also. lt was 
     <lb/>
     thought best not to make the salary too 
     <lb/>
     high at first, and we have therefore put 
     <lb/>
     it down not to exceed two thousand dol<lb break="no"/>lars a year. It in this respect we may 
     <lb/>
     be found to have erred, it can easily 
     <lb/>
     be remedied at the end of six months 
     <lb/>
     or so. We have put down the Clerk's 
     <lb/>
     salary at (not to exceed) one thousand 
     <lb/>
     or twelve hundred dollars. As I said 
     <lb/>
     before, this Bill is only intended to be 
     <lb/>
     temporary. and to make provision for 
     <lb/>
     the carrying out of the necessary mea<lb break="no"/>sures at the commencement of the 
     <lb/>
     Union, and at the next meeting of the 
     <lb/>
     House.  When the wants of the country 
     <lb/>
     are known in this respect, and what the 
     <lb/>
     officer should be, any change can be 
     <lb/>
     made. All we now ask is that the 
     <lb/>
     House put confidence in the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment for that time with regard to this 
     <lb/>
     matter. As to the manner in which the 
     <lb/>
     accounts shall be kept, i find that in 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia, where they have estab<lb break="no"/>lished a similar office. they require that 
     <lb/>
    there should be one cash book kept, 
     <lb/>which is open for the inspection of the 
     <lb/>members of the Government and Legis<lb break="no"/>lature, and that I think is a good ar<lb break="no"/>rangement. The Government is not 
     <lb/>wedded to the plan which they have 
     <lb/>here laid down, but are willing to hear 
     <lb/>any suggestions which hon. members 
     <lb/>may please to suggest on the subject. 
     <lb/>The office is here made non-political, 
     <lb/>and is to be held during the pleasure 
     <lb/>of the Government. This, I think, is 
     <lb/>all that is necessary for me to say on the 
     <lb/>Bill. We only want to have a law so 
     <lb/>operative that none of the monîes 
     <lb/>coming to us may be lost, and this Bill 
     <lb/>is so drawn as to run with the Bill of 
     <lb/>Union.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCQU1">Mr. McQUEEN</persName>.—At first I thought 
     <lb/>
     this office was intended to be political, 
     <lb/>
     but l now find that it is only permis<lb break="no"/>sive. If the first intention had been 
     <lb/>
     carried out, I should most certainly 
     <lb/>
     have opposed it, for we have so many 
     <lb/>
     " Generals" now, that the funds coming 
     <lb/>
     to us out of the Union will not be suffi<lb break="no"/>cient to satisfy them all. As it is not 
     <lb/>
     intended to make the office of Receiver 
     <lb/>
     General political, however, i shall offer 
     <lb/>
     it no opposition, as it is evident that 
     <lb/>such an office will be required under the<lb/>Union.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.— I am glad to see the 
     <lb/>
     Bill which is in your hand, Mr. Chair<lb break="no"/>man.  At first it was intended that the 
     <lb/>
     office should be political, and I think it 
     <lb/>
     would be very wrong to place all our 
     <lb/>
     funds in the hands of a man who at any 
     <lb/>
     day is liable to go out of office. For 
     <lb/>
     many years our finances have in 
     <lb/>
     the hands of a man, who has had the 
     <lb/>
     confidence of the whole country, and 
     <lb/>
     now that wo' are in a transition state, 
     <lb/>
     they should be as far removed from po<lb break="no"/>litical trials and influences as possible. 
     <lb/>
     The officer to be appointed by this Bill 
     <lb/>
     will have to receive the funds remitted 
     <lb/>
     from Canadn twice a year, the revenues 
     <lb/>
     from our Crown Lands and Export 
     <lb/>
     Duty on Lumber, and to pay them out 
     <lb/>
     for Bye Road and other appropriations. 
     <lb/>
     His duties will be less onerous than 
     <lb/>
     those of our present Treasurer, which 
     <lb/>
     have been wall attendcd to, and ac<lb break="no"/>companied by heavy responsibilities. 
     <lb/>
     That officer has never received more 
     <lb/>
     than £500 a year, and with the heavy 
     <lb/>
     sureties he has had to provide this sum 
     <lb/>
     was not too much. But now I think it 
     <lb/>
     might be reduced somewhat. In this 
     <lb/>
     connexion, too, I may say that as the 
     <lb/>
     number of members in the House will 
     <lb/>
     be considerably lessened, we shall he 
     <lb/>
     able to get rid of some of the heads of 
     <lb/>
     Departments. In Nova Scotia I find 
     <lb/>
     they have combincd the offices of the 
     <lb/>
     Provincial and Financial Secretaries, 
     <lb/>
     and gice a salary of £600. The office 
     <lb/>
     of Solicitor General is abolished, and 
     <lb/>
     the same thing can be donc here, for 
     <lb/>
     there will be no necessity for two 
     <lb/>
     Crown officers. The salary of the At<lb break="no"/>torney-General can also be reduced. 
     <lb/>
     His duties will be much lighter than 
     <lb/>
     they have been—the only cases which 
     <lb/>
     will occupy his attention are trespasscs 
     <lb/>
     on the public domain, attending to 
     <lb/>
     crimes and criminals. and the recovery 
     <lb/>
     of debts due the Crown. His salary, 
     <lb/>
     therefore, can be greatly reduced. In 
     <lb/>
     Nova Scotia they have put it down to 
     <lb/>
     £400. I merely mention this in con 
     <lb/>
     nexion with other matters, and shall be 
     <lb/>
     glad to see a Bill with this object 
     <lb/>
     brought in. There is one thing, how<lb break="no"/>ever, I think should be inserted in this 
     <lb/>
     Bill, and that is. that the Receiver 
     <lb/>
     General be required to submit to the 
     <lb/>
     House a yearly statement of the funds 
     <lb/>
     passing through his hands. If the Bill 
     <lb/>
     had been intended to make this oflice 
     <lb/>
     political, it would have been a new fea<lb break="no"/>ture to require him, as head of a depart<lb break="no"/>ment, to give security for the faithful 
     <lb/>
     performance of his duty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>.—I have a little sus<lb break="no"/>picion of creating these new offices. It 
     <lb/>
     seems that the duties are to be decreased, 
     <lb/>
     but the officers increased, so that the less 
     <lb/>
     work there is to do, the more there will 
     <lb/>be to do it, and be paid for doing it.<lb/>This<lb/>
     

            <cb/>
      

     morning we passed a Bill to appoint offi<lb break="no"/>cers to collect our export duties, who are 
     <lb/>
     to get a commission for it, and then hand 
     <lb/>
     the amounts over to the Receiver, who 
     <lb/>
     is to be paid for receiving them. I think 
     <lb/>that a good many of these offices are<lb/>more for ornament then use, for I have<lb/>found that, as a general rule, the clerks<lb/>do all the work, and the heads of the de<lb break="no"/>partment get the pay. I don't think there<lb/>is any good in having so many men with<lb/>" General" after their names. The Trea<lb break="no"/>surer in Saint John now receives the<lb/>funds which are collected all over the<lb/>Province, and why can't he still do it in<lb/>this case. Why not have all these money<lb/>matters come into one man's hands? We<lb/>have a Bill now before the House to re<lb break="no"/>duce the representation all over the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, but that will be useless if so many<lb/>Generals are to remain on the floors of<lb/>the House. We don't know anything<lb/>about the New Dominion yet, and I think<lb/>it will be just as well to let the matter<lb/>stand over, at least till the Imperial Act<lb/>is placed before us. There is now no<lb/>need of a Surveyor General, for the<lb/>clerks in the office can do all the work,<lb/>and give whatever information is requir<lb break="no"/>ed. We have a Postmaster General, but<lb/>it is said that the next in command below<lb/>him is now all astray with his accounts,<lb/>and he says that it is the fault of the<lb/>clerks. I don't see why, when we have<lb/>so many Generals, things should go so<lb/>much astray if they were properly looked<lb/>after. We shall now want a very large<lb/>sum of money to put our Roads and<lb/>Bridges in good order, and the money<lb/>taken out for the purpose of keeping up<lb/>the office of Receiver General would ma<lb break="no"/>terially assist for that purpose. We want<lb/>to open up new roads and prepare the<lb/>way for an increased immigration, but<lb/>we shall not be able to do so unless the<lb/>expenses are cut off in other directions.<lb/>I was talking to a Canadian a short time<lb/>ago, who was down here to buy up wil<lb break="no"/>derness lands ; he said that in Canada<lb/>they could not be obtained under a cost<lb/>of seven dollars an acre, and I advised<lb/>him to go to the Crown Land Office and<lb/>see if he could not buy what he wanted<lb/>here. The trouble with us is that all our<lb/>wilderness lands lie on the Eastern side<lb/>of the river, and cannot be got at except<lb/>by crossing in a canoe or ferry of some<lb/>sory<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">A MEMBER</persName>.—I suppose you want to         
     <lb/>get that bridge put across at Woodstock.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>.—Yes, and it cannot         
     <lb/>be done without money, which, if we go<lb/>on increasing the public offices, will not<lb/>be able to be obtained. I therefore think<lb/>this Bill should be laid over, at least till<lb/>we have the Imperial Act of Union<lb/>laid before us.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName>. —I think, Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Chairman, this is a most sensible Bill; 
     <lb/>
         

            <pb n="58" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_058.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="num">63</fw>   <fw type="running">DEBATES IN THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> 
  

     that this is a move in the right direction 
     <lb/>Perhaps it might have been well for us<lb/>to have know a little more about the<lb/>Ottawa matter, but as that is not the<lb/>question now before us, we will waive all<lb/>that. Some think that it is an uncalled<lb/>for expense to create this office and have<lb/>one man to receive all the provincial<lb/>funds. But I have found that it is a bad<lb/>thing to have too many pockets, for in<lb/>the transferring the money from one to the<lb/>other there is a great probability of its<lb/>lessening every time, and hard to find<lb/>some of it when it is wanted. And os if<lb/>our revenues were left to be collected<lb/>all over the Province by a number of<lb/>officers, we should not be able to tell ex<lb break="no"/>actly how things were going on. But<lb/>with this office everything come into one<lb/>pocket, and can be got at whenever it is<lb/>wanted. The office of the Receiver Gen<lb break="no"/>eral should be in the neighborhood of the<lb/>Crown Land Department, where it would<lb/>be convenient to receive the sums paid in<lb/>for our public domain. I really do think<lb/>this is an absolutely necessary office. I<lb/>am glad that it is not to be political, for then<lb/>the officer would have to be engaged in<lb/>attending to the general business of the<lb/>country, while his clerks would be left to<lb/>do the work of the office. With regard<lb/>to the salary, I am not one that thinks it<lb/>profitable to cut down the salaries of pub<lb break="no"/>lic officers to the lowest point, for when<lb/>work is poorly paid for it is frequently<lb/>poorly done, but I think if the Receiver<lb/>General receives about sixteen hundred<lb/>dollars, and his clerk six hundred dollars,<lb/>it would be about the right thing.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr. HIBBARD</persName>. — I have sat here for 
     <lb/>some days and heard the murmurings<lb/>about the Government not doing any<lb break="no"/>thing, but I am glad they are now going<lb/>to work in earnest. I think this Bill is<lb/>very necessary, and am very happy to<lb/>give it my support. It is of great import<lb break="no"/>ance that there whould be one officer to<lb/>receive all the funds that are coming to<lb/>[missing]. I do not know whether it is intend<lb break="no"/>ded that the Receiver General should be<lb/>a member of the Executive Council or<lb/>not.<lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>. — No.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HIBB1">Mr. HIBBARD</persName>. — I am glad of that,<lb/>for the officer would then be political, and<lb/>he should be a member of this House, and<lb/>I think it best that he should stand<lb/>aside. I think, however, that the office<lb/>might be combined with that of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Secretary, for that officer will now<lb/>have far less duties to perform than here<lb break="no"/>tofore, and if this could be done it would<lb/> save a good deal of the £400 required for<lb/>a separate officer. In the State of<lb/>Maine I think the whole thing is done at<lb/>a less sum than two thousand dollars, and<lb/> we have many very efficient men who<lb/>would be glad to do it for £400, if it is<lb/>
       

            <cb/>
         
found impractical to merge it in the Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Secretary's office. I think the<lb/>Government are now working right, and<lb/>that the Bill is good, and if we can get<lb/>the work as faithfully performed for £400<lb/>it would be a saving of £200 towards<lb/>some other object. I do not think the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment are careless of the position in<lb/>which they leave us, and I fully believe<lb/>that if we husband our resources under<lb/>the New Dominion, that there is not a<lb/>Province of the British Empire that will<lb/>have more money for local purposes than<lb/>New Brunswick. But if we go to work<lb/>and create a lot of offices at large salaries,<lb/>we shall embarrass ourselves completely<lb/>for it must be borne in mind that we<lb/>have nothing to fall back upon, but what<lb/>we get from Canada and our public do<lb break="no"/>main, and I am sure that, with proper<lb/>management, our Crown Lands would<lb/>pay into the general revenues at least<lb/>three times what they do now, and then<lb/>be not oppressive to the people of this<lb/>country. It is evident to my mind that<lb/>it will be impossible for us to get along<lb/>without this office, but at the same time<lb/>let it be as inexpensive as possible, con<lb break="no"/>sistent with efficiency. I hope the De<lb break="no"/>puty Treasurer at the various ports will<lb/>be willing to collect our Export Duties<lb/>at a very small commission, for if we<lb/>have to appoint other officers all over the<lb/>Province to attend to that duty, we shall<lb/>find that it will use up all the receipts<lb/>from that source. I hope also that the<lb/>Government will put the salary of this<lb/>new office down to £400, for there are<lb/>many good and reliable men who will be<lb/>willing to faithfully perform the duties of<lb/>that office for that sum. A clerk can<lb/>plainly be found for £200, and only one<lb/>will be required. Under these circum<lb break="no"/>stances I hope the Government will con<lb break="no"/>sider the matter and do the very best<lb/>they can.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. — That this officer is re<lb break="no"/>quired, Mr. Chairman, there can be no<lb/>kind of doubt; but I hope it will satisfy<lb/>the people of the fact the idea which<lb/>has continually been put forth that the<lb/>number of public officers would be re<lb break="no"/>duced , is all a delusion, but that it will<lb/>rather be increased. If all the Bills<lb/>about to be introduced, according to the<lb/>intimations of the Attorney General, are<lb/>carried, we shall have a great many new<lb/>officers. We are told that we shall have<lb/>District Court Judges, Chancellors, and<lb/>all that, so that, even though many of<lb/>the officersa t present existing may be<lb/>abolished, we shall have just as many as<lb/>before. The Postmaster General is to be<lb/>displaced, but thisnew office is to be<lb/>established, so that as fast as they are re<lb break="no"/>duced in one direction they spring up in<lb/>another. I perfectly agree with the hon.<lb/>member for Charlotte (Mr. Hibbard) that<lb/>it will be a pity if it cannot be united<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
          

     with some other office, and if it is non- 
     <lb break="yes"/>policial I think it might very well be<lb/>added to the Provincial Secretary's du<lb break="no"/>ties, for the work will be comparatively<lb/>light. All he will have to do will be to<lb/>receive the sixty thousand dollars or so<lb/>for our export Duty, the amounts<lb/>accruing from our Casual and Territorial<lb/>Revenue, which will not be large, and<lb/>the sum we are to receive from Canada<lb/>under the Act, which I think will be very<lb/>small indeed. For all the debts con<lb break="no"/>tracted and the three million pounds<lb/>sterling, is a first charge, taking prece<lb break="no"/>dence of all others, and mus be liqui<lb break="no"/>dated before we can get what is pro<lb break="no"/>mised under the Act; and if there is<lb/>nothing left we can of course get noth<lb break="no"/>ing, for the amounts to come to us are<lb/>only secondary charges upon the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Government. I agree with my hon.<lb/>friend from Charlotte too in the opinion<lb/>that £400 is amply abundant to pay<lb/>the Receiver General. The idea at first was<lb/>to make the office political, and the head<lb/>of a department, but I find that a great<lb/>organic change has been effected since it<lb/>was introduced. I don't know that it is<lb/>quite right to take the Bill off the files of<lb/>the House and later it to suit the changes<lb/>in the feelings of the Government. That<lb/>Bill, Mr. Chairman, has never been in<lb break="no"/>troduced to the Speaker, in reality, but I<lb/>am not going to oppose it on that ac<lb break="no"/>count. I do not believe the Receiver<lb/>General will require a clerk at all. I<lb/>know taht when I am attending to my<lb/>own business I work a great deal harder<lb/>than I ever did in a Government. Here<lb/>the Provincial Secretary has been away<lb/>from his office for many months, but it<lb/>was found that Mr. Fulton could run<lb/>the machine just as well when he was<lb/>away as when at home, and although it is<lb/>generally thought the Secretary is a<lb/>dreadfully hard-working man, yet I be0<lb/>lieve he has frequently to run down to<lb/>Saint John just to make people think he<lb/>has plenty to do. It is the same with<lb/>the other departments; the chief trouble<lb/>is for the heads to find something to do.<lb/>In this case I think £400 quite enough,<lb/>especially as it is not political, for we<lb/>only pay £600 to the heads of depart<lb break="no"/>ments, who have to go back to their con0<lb/>stituents for election, and it coses that<lb/>sum to do it — if not in money, at least in<lb/>trouble and anxiety — and so £400 is in<lb break="no"/>finitely better than £600 as the head of a<lb/>department. I do not see the necessity<lb/>of a clerk at all, for the amount we do re<lb break="no"/>ceive from Canada will come in bulk and<lb/>the other duties will be very light. I<lb/>have often heard it said that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment have too much infuence on the<lb/>floors of the HOuse, and as this Bill is<lb/>opposed to that principle, and the office<lb/>will be required, I shall give it my sup<lb break="no"/>port, but I hope the Government will not<lb/>
         

            <pb n="59" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_059.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> <fw type="num">59</fw> 
   

     attempt to fill the blank with a larger<lb/>sum than sixteen hundred dollars.<lb/>
     
     
      </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BABB1">Mr. BABBIT</persName>.—I quite agree with all 
     <lb/>that has been said with regard to the 
     <lb/>office of Receiver General not being po<lb break="no"/>litical, and when I heard that it was in<lb break="no"/>tended to be so, I tried to get the Bill, 
     <lb/>but it could not be found. It seems how<lb break="no"/>ever, that it was taken away to make this 
     <lb/>most beneficial change. I hope it will be 
     <lb/>so arranged that this officer will receive 
     <lb/>not only the amounts coming from 
     <lb/>Canada. but our own Export Duty. On 
     <lb/>referring to the Auditor's Report, I see 
     <lb/>that large amounts are lying back in the 
     <lb/>hands of the Deputy Treasurers year 
     <lb/>after year. That is something I don't 
     <lb/>believe in, and I hope this officer will see 
     <lb/>that the amounts received by them shall 
     <lb/>be promptly and fully paid up. I am sa<lb break="no"/>tisfied that £400 will be an ample salary<lb/>to pay a man for the duties required of<lb/>him, and that plenty of good men can be<lb/>found who would gladly take it at that<lb/>sum, and ask for no clerk. It is much<lb/>better to put the sum as small as pos<lb break="no"/>sible, for it is very easy to increase it if<lb/>found insufficient ; but if it is made large<lb/>at first, it will be found very difficult to<lb/>cut it down afterwards. It seems to me<lb/>that in all these things we are inclined to<lb/>commence too big. There is, however,<lb/>one department that I consider is not suf<lb break="no"/>ficiently paid, and that is, the Postmas<lb break="no"/>ters at some of the larger offices, who,<lb/>though their duties are much heavier than<lb/>this officer's will be, don't get anywhere<lb/>near £400, and I therefore think the Re<lb break="no"/>ceiver General should not get over that<lb/>sum.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <lb/>Mr. CHANDLER.—It is admitted on<lb/>every side that an office of this kind is<lb/>necessary, and while the hon. members<lb/>have been speaking. I have been turn<lb break="no"/>ing in my mind what salary such an officer<lb/>should receive. Does the duty require<lb/>much thought or mental ability? No,<lb/>sir, it is not an office like that of At<lb break="no"/>torney General, where large attainments<lb/>are requisite, but merely one in which<lb/>transactions of an ordinary kind are car<lb break="no"/>ried on, and under these circumstances<lb/>I think that £400 will be amply sufficient.<lb/>The country abounds with men who will<lb/>gladly do the duty for that sum.<lb/>
            </p>
       
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>.- There is one<lb/>element in the Bill that I wish to explain<lb/>The Government do not. want to make a<lb/>big salary, but the Bill is only of a tem<lb break="no"/>porary character, and that question will
<lb/>best be settled at the next Session, when 
<lb/>it is known exactly what is required of
<lb/>this officer. After seven months or so
<lb/>the House can decide as to the perma<lb break="no"/>nency of the salary at the sum named.
<lb/>If the office were made political it would
<lb/>be worth double the amount than if non<lb break="no"/>political. But hon. members are astray
<lb/>somewhat with regard to the salaries of<lb/>
  
<cb/>

     United States officials. Why, a short 
     <lb/>
     time ago, General Banks was made 
     <lb/>
     President of a Railroad, owned by I 
     <lb/>
     private Company, with a salary of ten 
     <lb/>
     thousand dollars ; and a man who had 
     <lb/>
     been engaged in I a public office all his 
     <lb/>
     life, died a short time ago worth seventy 
     <lb/>
     thousand dollars. A friend of mine 
     <lb/>
     asked a gentleman there how he had 
     <lb/>
     managed to save so much. "Oh," he 
     <lb/>
     replied, "he was very economical." It 
     <lb/>
     is apparent that if the salary they get is 
     <lb/>
     small, they are yet able to live well and 
     <lb/>
     become wealthy. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">Hon. Mr. WILMOT</persName>.—I am one that 
     <lb/>
     believes the greatest economy should be 
     <lb/>
     practiced, with due regard to efficiency. 
     <lb/>
     The hon. member for Queen's (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Babbit has said that plenty of men can 
     <lb/>
            be got for £400 a year, and no clerk al<lb break="no"/>lowed. Now, even if the Province be 
     <lb/>
               reduced to a municipality, I do not think 
     <lb/>
               the Receiver General should be paid less 
     <lb/>than the Chamberlain of the City of Saint<lb/>John. The Common Council pay Mr.<lb/>Ruel £400, and he has an office and a<lb/>clerk allowed him besides. I very much<lb/>doubt if it would be desirable to have no<lb/>clerk, for there are many times when<lb/>persons would want to go to the office<lb/>when the Receiver General could not be<lb/>there. When it was proposed to<lb/>decrease the salaries of the De<lb break="no"/>puty Treasurers, I opposed it, but<lb/>it was carried, and what has been the<lb/>result ? Why since that time there have<lb/>been very heavy defalcations, which was<lb/>not the case before. The Receiver Gen<lb break="no"/>eral will be required to give very heavy<lb/>bonds, and ought to be a good man, and<lb/>when clerks in private business can get<lb/>£300, I think this officer should not get<lb/>less than £500. Hon. members have<lb/>spoken about officials in the United States.<lb/>Why, it is well know that the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment is the most expensive in the world.<lb/>There they go in for the spoils, every<lb/>man trying to get as much as he can<lb/>while in office ; the officials of the City<lb/>of New York, it is well know, are paid<lb/>the most extravagant amounts, and it is<lb/>useless to draw a comparison between<lb/>their system and ours.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.- I think if £400 is found<lb/>to be too low, it can very easily be raised<lb/>The giving of large salaries does not al<lb break="no"/>ways have the effect of making men do<lb/>their work more thoroughly ; nor is it<lb/>among those that receive good, fair, re<lb break="no"/>munerative salaries that defalcations so<lb/>frequently occur as with those whose<lb/>salaries are very large. There was the <lb/>Postmaster of the United States, who<lb/>received a very large salary, went off<lb/>with some millions of dollars of the<lb/>public funds, and the Collector of the<lb/>City of New York, which is considered<lb/>one of their best offices, did the same<lb/>thing. Because the City of Saint John<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
      

     
     choose to pay their Chamberlain £400 is 
     <lb/>
     no reason why we should give our Re<lb break="no"/>ceiver General £500. We know that the 
     <lb/>
     duties of the Presidents of Banks are 
     <lb/>
     much more onerous than the Receiver 
     <lb/>
     Generalship will be, and yet they only 
     <lb/>
     received, till lately £400 a year. I think 
     <lb/>
     that sum quite sufficient to pay for the 
     <lb/>
     duties to be performed, but he should be 
     <lb/>
     provided with a clerk. lt is not neces<lb break="no"/>sary that his salary should be large, but 
     <lb/>
     one will he required. I do not think the 
     <lb/>
     office should be united with that of the 
     <lb/>
     Provincial Secretary, for he as Provincial 
     <lb/>
     and Financial Secretary will have quite 
     <lb/>
     enough to do ; but now that the Post 
     <lb/>
     Office is removed the Auditor will have 
     <lb/>
     much less to do—only the school an?? 
     <lb/>
     and bye road accounts to look after—and 
     <lb/>
     it might possibly be added to that. The 
     <lb/>
     bye road accounts, I think, should be 
     <lb/>
     audited in the various localities where 
     <lb/>
     the money is expended, as it can there 
     <lb/>
     be done much more efficiently than at a 
     <lb/>
     remote distance. On this matter, how<lb break="no"/>ever, I think that £400 is quite adequate 
     <lb/>
     for an accomplished and efficient officer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>—I move the 
     <lb/>
     blank be filled with $2,000. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      <persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName>.—I move, in amend<lb break="no"/>ment, that it be filled with $1,600. If 
     <lb/>
     we become wealthy, as the Provincial 
     <lb/>
     Secretary has predicted, it will be very 
     <lb/>
     easy to add another £100 to it. The 
     <lb/>
     duties require to be performed promptly 
     <lb/>
     and efficiently, but $1, 600 us quite suffi<lb break="no"/>cient and as much as we can now afford 
     <lb/>
     to pay. One clerk at about $600 salary 
     <lb/>
     will be plenty, and many will be glad to 
     <lb/>
     get the situation who are thoroughly 
     <lb/>
     capable of performing the duty. I do not 
     <lb/>
     think this office should be united with any 
     <lb/>
     other. The Auditor's duties will be much 
     <lb/>
     lighter in the future, as they should be, 
     <lb/>
     for that officer has been very much over 
     <lb/>
     worked. I think the idea of' the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member for Northumberland (Mr. Kerr) 
     <lb/>
    is good, respecting the auditing of the 
     <lb/>bye road accounts in the localities where 
     <lb/>the moneys are expended, for during the 
     <lb/>past year in the office frauds were known 
     <lb/>to have been practised, but it was so far 
     <lb/>off that they could not be well looked 
     <lb/>into. I think the Financial Secretary 
     <lb/>and Auditor might very well be now 
     <lb/>united in one individual, with one clerk 
     <lb/>to assist him. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCAD1">Hon. Mr. McADAM</persName>—I want to ask 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member from Northumberland 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Kerr) it he will accept the office of 
     <lb/>
     Receiver General, with a salary of £400? 
     <lb/>
     If he will, I am sure I will vote for him, 
     <lb/>
     for no one could he obtained who would 
     <lb/>
     perform the duties better, or give more 
     <lb/>
     satisfaction to the country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>—I am not in a position to 
     <lb/>
     talk about the salary I should require 
     <lb/>until I get the offer of the situation—<lb/>
    (Laughter.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="60" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_060.jpg"/>
       

     <fw type="num">60</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> 
    

   
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. — That is a new way to<lb/>get support for the Government — (laugh<lb break="no"/>ter). I think they could get all the re<lb break="no"/>quier if they put such questions to other<lb/>hon. members. The hon. member of the<lb/>Government from Saint John (Mr. Wil<lb break="no"/>mot) is very much opposed to small sala<lb break="no"/>ries. He wanted the salary of the Auditor<lb/>General to be kept up, whereas now it is<lb/>shown that the duties can be performed<lb/>for two or three hundred dollars a year.<lb/>I have no doubt that the hon. member is<lb/>a Senator by this time, and I am very<lb/>anxious to see whether, when the Pro<lb break="no"/>clamation comes, — if it does not break<lb/>the other cable, for it is said the enws<lb/>was so weighty that it broke down the<lb/>cable of 1866, — if he will resign his seat<lb/>in this House. He is the most extrava<lb break="no"/>gant man I ever knew, and thinks officers<lb/>can't get too large salaaries till they be<lb break="no"/>come rogueish. I shall second the mo<lb break="no"/>tion for £400, but I do not think a clerk<lb/>will be needed.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">Hon. Mr. WILMOT</persName>. — I am sure I have 
     <lb/>nothing to gain by desiring the salary to<lb/>be £500. I have brought in motions to<lb/>have salaries reduced, but I say that after<lb/>the salaries of the Deputy Treasurers<lb/>were reduced there were large defalca<lb break="no"/>tions, and there were none before. I am<lb/>sure I do not know in what I am extrava<lb break="no"/>gant, unless it be that I would rather<lb/>have a good man in the office, and pay<lb/>him well, than have a poor one at a low<lb/>rate. With regard to the Senatorship<lb/>and my seat in this House, the hoh.<lb/>member may rest assured that I shall not<lb/>resign until I know more about tht mat<lb break="no"/>ter than he does now.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. — The hon. member says 
     <lb/>there were no defalcations under the high<lb/>salary arrangement, but I remember the<lb/>case of a man named BAiley, who was<lb/>Surveyor General, and got a salary of I<lb/>don't know how much — £1200, I believe,<lb/>— who embezzled the public money to<lb/>the extent of thousands of punds, and<lb/>who was after all granted a pension of<lb/>£500 a year; so that there is nothing in<lb/>the principle he lays down, at all.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>. — This arrange<lb break="no"/>ment, as I have said, is only for a few<lb/>months, and then it must be revised to<lb/>suit the requirements of the Province<lb/>under Union, and the difference for that<lb/>time will be very small. I am in favor of<lb/>the larger sum, but am not particular, as<lb/>it will not be binding to those who come<lb/>after us.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. — There was a man 
     <lb/>who held the position of Surveyor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral, who said that the salary was so<lb/>large he did not know how to spend it,<lb/>and wanted £100 taken off, but it could<lb/>not be done. (Laughter). The Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General was, I think, in the govern<lb break="no"/>ment at the time. I would like to ask<lb/>the hon. member of the Government (Mr.<lb/>Wilmot) what his idea of the salary of<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
         

     the Auditor General is now? There was 
     <lb/>Surveyor General Bailey, who got so<lb/>great a salary that he had to keep horses<lb/>and carriages, and men to look after<lb/>them, to spend it; and when any one want<lb break="no"/>ed to see him he was always just going<lb/>for a drive, and they had to wait for him.<lb/>The clerks have to do all the work in<lb/>that office now, and I think the head of<lb/>the department won't be wanted any<lb/>more. As to the work of the Receiver<lb/>General, it will be very light, and he<lb/>won't need a clerk. He will only have<lb/>
     to be in his office from 9 o'clock till 3, or 
     <lb/>so, and he certainly won't want to go<lb/>out much during that time. I think the<lb/>bonds he is required to give ($10,000) are<lb/>too large, but it does not make much dif<lb break="no"/>ference as they will never be collected.<lb/>It is well known that directly a man has<lb/>embezzled money and gone off, a sym<lb break="no"/>pathy is got up for the bondsmen, and<lb/>after a time the bonds are cancelled.<lb/>That has always been the case, and it<lb/>will be so. Plenty of good men can be<lb/>found to take the office at £400, but it<lb/>seems that directly "General" is put on<lb/>to a name, some hon. members think the<lb/>salary should be raised.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Amendment being put was car<lb break="no"/>ried in the affirmative, and the blank was<lb/>filled with "sixteen hundred dollars."<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The section referring to the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of a Clerk was then read.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. — I move that the section 
     <lb/>you have just read, Mr. Chairmaan, re<lb break="no"/>lating to the Clerk be struck out. The<lb/>Attorney General says the Bill is only<lb/>intended to be temporary, and will run<lb/>but a few months, so that the duties of<lb/>the office can be carried on. If so, then<lb/>it will be best to leave to our successors<lb/>the details of the matter, and they can<lb/>supply a Clerk, if one is found to be<lb/>needed.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>. — I think on the 
     <lb/>salary of the Receiver General it made<lb/>very little difference whether the sum<lb/>were put at £400 or £500, but with the<lb/>heavy bonds which he will be required<lb/>to give, it may not be so easy to find a<lb/>man to fill the place. It has been said<lb/>that the duties will be very light, but<lb/>with regard to the Crown Lands alone,<lb/>he will have to be in his office every hour<lb/>in the day to receive the amounts as they<lb/>are paid in, and pay out what may be<lb/>required. Under these circumstances<lb/>he will require a clerk, the salary need<lb/>not be large, as in the case of illness or other<lb/>absence from the office, there must still<lb/>be some one there to attend to the pub<lb break="no"/>lic business. Although the Receiver<lb/>General may not be constantly engaged<lb/>yet he will have to be constantly there, and<lb/>a clerk will consequently be necessary<lb/>to fill his place during forced absence.<lb/>And one of probity and intelligence<lb/>should be appointed as well as one able<lb/>to obtain the necessary securities for the<lb/>faithful performance of his duty.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. — That is a sharp idea to<lb/>
           

            <cb/>
    

put forth, that because a man may be<lb/>taken sick, therefore he should have a<lb/>clerk. In the same way the Registrars,<lb/>the Deputy Treasurers and everybody<lb/>else would want a clerk, but i such a<lb/>case it is very easy to appoint a Deputy<lb/>for the time being. I think all the duties<lb/>can very well be performed by one man,<lb/>but if it is found necessary a clerk can be<lb/>appointed afterwards, say at the next<lb/>Session. If the Government now put in<lb/>a man as clerk, even though he may not<lb/>be required, it is not probable that those<lb/>who are left here at the next Session<lb/>would displace him. It is exactly the<lb/>same as if the salary had been placed at<lb/>a high figure, for it would have been<lb/>found very difficult to cut it down. It is<lb/>for this reason that I move the section<lb/>be struck out.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On putting the motion a division was<lb/>called, when there appeared —<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>YEAS — Messrs. Kerr, Sutton, Hibbard,<lb/>Landry, McInerney, Caie, McQueen,<lb/>Smith, Young, Thompson, DesBrisay,<lb/>Ryan, Lindsay, J. Flewwelling and Bab<lb break="no"/>Bit.  15 <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>NAYS — Messrs. Mcchan, McClelan,<lb/>Beveridge, Dow, Beckwith, Queinton,<lb/>Tillery, Connell, Wilmot, Williston,<lb/>Fisher, McAdam, and W.P. Flewel<lb break="no"/>ling. 13 <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>It was therefore carried in the affirma<lb break="no"/>tive.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The other sections passed without dis<lb break="no"/>cussion.<lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     PETITIONS, BILLS, ETC. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> presented the Peti<lb break="no"/>tion of the Municipal Councillors of the<lb/>County of York, praying that they may<lb/>be authorized to grant aid to the Freder<lb break="no"/>icton Railway Company.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Petition received and laid on the<lb/>table.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> mvoed for the sus<lb break="no"/>pension of the rule to enable him to<lb/>bring in a Bill to enable the Municpal<lb/>Council of the County of York to grant<lb/>aid to the Fredericton Railway Company<lb/>in constructing a Railway from thecity<lb/>of Fredericton to Hartt's Mills, in the<lb/>said County, being a branch of Western<lb/>Extension.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The rule was suspended, leave granted<lb/>and the Bill being brought in was read<lb/>a first time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> presented a Petition<lb/>from D. Munroe, and fourteen others, in<lb break="no"/>habitants of the Parish of Woodstock,<lb/>praying for the continuance of certain<lb/>Acts relating to the Upper Woodstock<lb/>Road district.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Petition received and laid on the<lb/>table.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> moved for leave to<lb/>bring in a Bill to revive and continue<lb/>certain Acts relating to the repair of<lb/>Roads in the Upper Woodstock Road<lb/>district, in the County of Carleton.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Leave granted, and the Bill being<lb/>brought in was read a first time.<lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="61" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-21_Page_061.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw>  <fw type="num">61</fw>
    

   
            <p>
     House adjourned till to-morrow morn<lb break="no"/>ing at 10 o'clock.  </p>

<p rendition="simple:right">J.M.
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2018-04-18, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

   
           <!-- <p>
     WEDNESDAY, May 22nd. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House having met, the Journals<lb/>were read, and several Bills received a<lb/>second reading.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     A Bill relating to the Election of Mem<lb break="no"/>bers to serve in the General Assembly,<lb/>so far as relates to the County of Clou-<lb break="maybe"/>cester.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The following Bills were read a third 
     <lb/>time and passed the House:<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     A Bill relating to the Export Duty on 
     <lb/>Lumber.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill relating to the officer of Receiver<lb/>General.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>BURYING GROUND AT ST. ANDREWS.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of Mr. CHANDLER the<lb/>House went into Committee (Mr. Lewis<lb/>in the Chair) to take into considereation<lb/>a Bill to repeal Section 4, Chapter 27,<lb/>Act 14 Victoria, entitled "An Act relat<lb break="no"/>ing the Public Burying Gounds in the<lb/>Town of St. Andrews."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. CHANDLER said that an Act of<lb/>Assembly had been passed by which it<lb/>was declared that certain Public Bury<lb break="no"/>ing Grounds in St. Andrews should not<lb/>be used for the interment of the bodies<lb/>of diseased persons. The fourth section<lb/>of said Act contained a clause that the<lb/>Act should not come into operation until<lb/>certain things had been done. Those<lb/>things have been done, and they were<lb/>now in a position to have that section re<lb break="no"/>pealed. He then read a Petition praying<lb/>for the repeal of the section which he ob<lb break="no"/>served brought the matter clearly and<lb/>distinctly before the House. He said the<lb/>Petition was signed by all the clergymen<lb/>and almost all the inhabitants of St. An<lb break="no"/>drews. He would not make any more<lb/>observations further than to say that<lb/>burial grounds in the neighborhood of a<lb/>Town affected the health of its inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants. These burial grounds were at<lb/>the head of the town, which was situa<lb break="no"/>ted on a slightly inclined plain, and they<lb/>water running through those grounds<lb/>got into wells, and this had a highly<lb/>injurious effect upon the health of the<lb/>people of the place. He hoped there<lb/>would be no opposition to the Bill, but<lb/>that it would be allowed to pass.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was then agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> presented a Petition from<lb/>the REv. C. S. Ogg, Francis Elliot,<lb/>George McNell and others, the ministers,<lb/>Elders and Trustees of St. Andrews<lb/>Church, praying that a Bill may be pass<lb break="no"/>ed authorizing the sale of the old church,<lb/>and to add the proceeds towards defray<lb break="no"/>ing the expense incurred in the erection<lb/>of the new Church belonging to the said<lb/>Petitioners and congregation.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> brought in a Bill to autho-<lb break="maybe"/>rise the Trustees of the St. Andrews<lb/>Church, Chatham, to sell or otherwise<lb/>16<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>dispose of the old St. Andrews Church in<lb/>the Town of Chatham.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> said a Bill had 
     <lb/>passed a Committee of the House yes<lb break="no"/>terday relating to the Great Roads, but<lb/>they had since, on a closer examination,<lb/>discovered a word or two which re<lb break="no"/>quired alteration. He wished to know<lb/>whether it could be altered, or whether<lb/>it was necessary to recommit the Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said that if it involved   
     <lb/>any principle it could not be altered<lb/>without being recommitted, but if it<lb/>was a mere verbal alteration to rectify<lb/>an error it was not necessary to recom<lb break="no"/>mit it.<lb/>
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Mr. McCLELAN said itw as but to<lb/>change a name, which would extend<lb/>the road about one mile and a half fur<lb break="no"/>ther.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>His hon., the SPeAKER put the ques<lb break="no"/>tion the HOuse, to whether the alteration<lb/>should be made without recommitting<lb/>the Bill. Question carried in the affir<lb break="no"/>mative.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> presented a Petition from<lb/>a number of the inhabitants of the<lb/>County of Westmorland, prayinig that<lb/>an Act may pass to provie for the con<lb break="no"/>struction of a Canal to connect the wa<lb break="no"/>ters of the Bay of Fundy with the Gulf<lb/>of St. Lawrence.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of Hon. Mr. FISHER the<lb/>House went into a committee of the<lb/>Whole (Mr. Botsford in the Chair) on<lb/>"A Bill to authorize the City Council<lb/>of Fredericton to raise money, by way<lb/>of a loan, for the erection of a Country<lb/>Market and City Hall in the said City."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The BIll was agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> presented a Peti<lb break="no"/>tion praying that an Act may pass to<lb/>Incorporate the St. John Trades' Co<lb break="no"/>operative Association.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>QUESTION CONCERNING UNION.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> asked whether the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment had received any information<lb/>either direct from england, from or<lb/>through Canada, or from or though<lb/>Nova Scotia, or from any other source<lb/>in reference to the proclamation of<lb/>Union.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> replied that he had<lb/>not received any information in refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the proclamation from any<lb/>source.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> hoped the Secretary had<lb/>not given instruction to keep the infor<lb break="no"/>mation back.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> replied that he<lb/>had not.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. CHANDLER presented a Peti<lb break="no"/>tion praying that Section 2, Chap. 47 of<lb/>Section 26 Victoria, relating to certain<lb/>exemptions from duty at the Port of<lb/>St. stephen, be repealed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of Hon. Mr. CONNELL<lb/>the House went into Committee (Mr.<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Botsford in the Chair) on "A Bill to 
     <lb/>amend Chap. 45 of the Revised statutes<lb/>of Municipalities."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> gave notice that he would<lb/>move a resolution for an Address to<lb/>His Excellency the Administrator of the<lb/>Government for a return showing any<lb/>increase that may have taken place,<lb/>since the first day of June last, in the<lb/>salaries and emoluments of the officers<lb/>and employees connected with the Euro<lb break="no"/>pean and North American Railway.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill relating to Great Roads was<lb/>read a third time and passed the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> submitted papers<lb/>relating to the claims of the PRince Ed<lb break="no"/>ward Island Steamship Company.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. sTEVENS</persName> moved that the in<lb break="no"/>vestigation of these matters be referred<lb/>to a Select Committee.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Committee — Messrs. Stevens, Ryan<lb/>and Beveridge.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>REPRESENTATION OF COUNTIES<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> moved the House into<lb/>a Committee of the Whole on "A Bill<lb/>to repeal certain sections of a law re<lb break="no"/>lating to the election of Representatives<lb/>to serve in the General Assembly, and<lb/>to make other provisions in lieu there<lb break="no"/>of.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:YOUN1">Mr. YOUNG</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. — A few days ago,<lb/>when I was advocating an incrrease of<lb/>representation for the County of Carle<lb break="no"/>ton, several members thought it would<lb/>be better to introduce a Bill to reduce<lb/>the representation on the floors of the<lb/>House instead of increasing it. That<lb/>coincided with my views, for I thought<lb/>in view of our altered circumstances<lb/>we should reduce our expenses as much<lb/>as possible. The basis upon which the<lb/>representation of the Counties now<lb/>stand is very unfair. In the County of<lb/>Carleton, which I have the honor to re<lb break="no"/>present, the have one representative<lb/>to 9400 inhabitants; County of Albert<lb/>one to 4722; Charlotte one to 5907;<lb/>Gloucester one to 7519; Kent one to<lb/>7927; King's one to 7761; Northumber<lb break="no"/>land one to 4700; Queen's one to 6600;<lb/>Restigouehe one to 2437; St. John one<lb/>to 3085; Westmorland one to 6311;<lb/>York one to 5810. This representation<lb/>is very unfair, and when I had a Bill<lb/>before the House to increase the repre<lb break="no"/>sentation of Carleton it was generally<lb/>conceded that if a Bill was prepared<lb/>which would do justice to all sections<lb/>of the country it would receive the sup<lb break="no"/>port of the hon. members of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature. Accordingly I introduced a Bill<lb/>which is now befoer the Committee,<lb/>which provides that there shall be one<lb/>member for every 7500 inhabitants. My<lb/>first idea was to make it for every 8000,<lb/>
            </p>-->
      </div>   </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>