<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-04-11"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-04-11">11 April 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="107"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-11_Page_106.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-04-11_Page_107.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-14">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-14">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-11_Page_106">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-11_Page_106.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-04-11_Page_107">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-11_Page_107.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="106" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-11_Page_106.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="num">106</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>   
   
<!-- GL, 2018-03-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

           <!-- <p>would be impossible for the members of<lb/>the Government to be in their seats, and<lb/>in their absence they did not know what<lb/>might be brought before the House. The<lb/>request he had made on behalf of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment was reasonable, and the usual<lb/>one adopted, and he thought it might be<lb/>complied with.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. CONNELL acquiesced in the re<lb break="no"/>quest of the Attorney General, for although<lb/>the local business of the country might be<lb/>gone on with, yet it was customary to<lb/>adjourn if the Government were not in a<lb/>position to carry on the general business.<lb/>He thought the time asked should be<lb/>granted.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. MCCLELAN did not wish to throw<lb/>any obstacles in the way of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, but he was of the opinion that<lb/>matters not connected with the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment might be carried on by the House,<lb/>and this was the only object he had in<lb/>view in offering his remarks.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. GILBERT had important Bills<lb/>to bring in, yet if circumstances were such<lb/>that the Government were compelled to<lb/>ask for an adjournment, common courtesy<lb/>required that it should be granted<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> had not spoken with<lb/>a view to oppose the Government, but,<lb/>knowing that a large number of local<lb/>Bills had to be passed, he though that<lb/>these, as the Government were not con<lb break="no"/>nected with, nor affected by them, might<lb/>be taken up in committee and got<lb/>through with.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On motion of MR. NEEDHAM, the<lb/>House then adjourned till to-morrow at<lb/>3 o'clock P. M.<lb/>J. MARCH.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>TUESDAY, APRIL 10.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>After the Journals were read, the House<lb/>adjourned until half-past two to-morrow,<lb/>at the request of Hon. Mr. Smith, who<lb/>stated that the Government had tendered<lb/>their resignations to His Excellency, but<lb/>the acceptance had not been received or<lb/>the correspondence closed.<lb/>T. P. D.<lb/>
            </p>-->


            <head rendition="simple:right">WEDNESDAY, APRIL 11.<lb/>
            </head>


            <p>The House met pursuant to the adjourn<lb break="no"/>ment at half-past two P. M.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">MR. KERR</persName> moved the House into<lb/>Committee of the Whole on a Bill to in<lb break="no"/>corporate the Northern Bank.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON MR. SMITH</persName> then rose and said,<lb/>that he had hoped to have been ready to<lb/>give the reasons why the Government had<lb/>tendered their resignations, but regretted<lb/>he was not yet in a position to do so.<lb/>He had just received a note from the<lb/>Governor saying that he could not give a<lb/>reply to them till four or five o'clock, and<lb/>as under these circumstances it was usual<lb/>to adjourn from day to day, he was com<lb break="no"/>pelled again to ask the indulgence of the<lb/>Houser.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">MR. KERR</persName> thought that local matters<lb/>could be gone on with without affecting<lb/>the position of the Government. If he<lb/>imagined that anything could arise to<lb/>affect them, he would [illegible] made [illegible]<lb/>motion. It would probably be three or<lb/>four days before that would be [illegible]<lb/>take up any business of general interest,<lb/>but in the meantime he should like the<lb/>local business to be transacted.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">MR. FISHER</persName> said they should remem<lb break="no"/>
         

            <cb/>
      
ber that the request for adjournment came<lb/>from the Government, and though he felt<lb/>the necessity of proceeding with the local<lb/>business yet he could not feel it his duty<lb/>to proceed against their motion. He did<lb/>not look for the effect the going on might<lb/>have on the past or present, but on the<lb/>future, and as it was usual to adjourn, he<lb/>was in favor of allowing the Government<lb/>time to conclude their correspondence.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOYD1">MR. BOYD</persName> said, as the House had<lb/>heard from the Attorney General that the<lb/>Governor had not yet returned an answer<lb/>to their resignation, it was their duty to<lb/>adjourn in compliance with the request of<lb/>the Government.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SUTT1">MR. SUTTON</persName> could see no reasona<lb break="no"/>ble objection to the House proceeding<lb/>with local business whilst the correspon<lb/>dence between the Government and the<lb/>Governor was pending.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName> reiterated that it<lb/>was usual to adjourn the House from day<lb/>to day under such circumstances as the<lb/>Government were now placed, but it was<lb/>in the hands of the House to adjourn or<lb/>go on, as they saw fit.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILB1">MR. GILBERT</persName> said this Province was<lb/>not a Crown Colony, but was ruled by a<lb/>Government responsible to the people,<lb/>and exigencies having arisen to cause the<lb/>Government to tender their resignation,<lb/>and a reply to the same not having been<lb/>yet received, he though the House must<lb/>adjourn in compliance with the request of<lb/>the Attorney General. The difficulty<lb/>would be to distinguish between general<lb/>and local business, or where the line<lb/>should be drawn. Under responsible and<lb/>departmental Government all business<lb/>transacted by this House must be con<lb break="no"/>sidered as affecting the general interests<lb/>of the Province, and although business<lb/>might be retarded for a few days by the<lb/>adjournment, yet a precedent must be es<lb break="no"/>tablished that the Government must be in<lb/>a working condition for the business to<lb/>be constitutional, and he should, there<lb break="no"/>fore, support the motion for adjournment.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:THOM1">MR. THOMPSON</persName> said they knew what<lb/>the rules of the British Government were<lb/>on this point, and though time was lost,<lb/>yet it enabled the members to know ex<lb break="no"/>actly how matters stood. He wanted to<lb/>go on constitutionally, manly and fairly,<lb/>and to see the principles established car<lb break="no"/>ried out. A change was made in our<lb/>Constitution about fifteen years ago, by<lb/>those who he believed were seeking office,<lb/>yet having now a responsible Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, or having had it up to within the<lb/>past few days, he thought the House<lb/>should adjourn, or they would be like a<lb/>balloon with the cords cut, and go up<lb/>God knows where. To proceed consti<lb break="no"/>tutionally required time, and as the At<lb break="no"/>torney General had asked for an adjourn<lb break="no"/>ment they should do so and save the<lb/>trouble and bother that would otherwise<lb/>arise. The hon. member for York (Mr.<lb/>Fisher) was one of the framers of the plan<lb/>of departmental Government, and he did<lb/>not want to see him like a child with a<lb/>card house, up foot and knock down all<lb/>his work. He was little of a politician,<lb/>and had taken up very little of the time<lb/> <lb/>given to talking, but rather to listening,<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
        

     and had only spoken now to jog the mem<lb break="no"/>ory of the hon, member for York, as they<lb/>all knew the least drop was sometimes<lb/>sufficient to stimulate.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said it was always the<lb/>case under circumstances like the present<lb/>to adjourn from day to day. He did not<lb/>like this lounging about, not at work, yet<lb/>he believed that a number of hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers had been hard at work during the<lb/>past few days, and they looked as though<lb/>they had heavy care upon their minds.<lb/>The Government might be considered in<lb/>a moribund condition, and as the hon.<lb/>member, the late head of the Opposition,<lb/>but who now, he supposed, he must ad<lb break="no"/>dress as the hon. member for York, would<lb/>naturally be very busy, he thought time<lb/>should be given those forming a new admin<lb break="no"/>istration to mature their plans, and as<lb/>under the circumstances it could not be<lb/>expected that the members of the mori<lb break="no"/>bund Government, as well as the leading<lb/>members of the Opposition, would be able<lb/>to be in their seats, there would be very<lb/>few to discuss the questions that came<lb/>before them, if they should decide to go<lb/>on with Bills of a local character. Under<lb/>such circumstances, matters might be<lb/>brought before the House of great im<lb break="no"/>portance, and carried without the know<lb break="no"/>ledge of many of the members. The hon.<lb/>member for Charlotte (Mr. Thompson)<lb/>had spoken of Responsible Government<lb/>as a balloon with its cords cut, and gone<lb/>off, no one knows where, but he rather<lb/>regarded it as gone up and collapsed.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HATH1">HON. MR. HATHEWAY</persName> said the 
     <lb/>Provincial Secretary was away attending<lb/>the supposed death-bed of his father, and<lb/>as soon as the memorandum had been<lb/>sent to and received from him, the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment had laid their resignations be<lb break="no"/>fore the Governor. Time must be given<lb/>to prepare the reply, and the Government<lb/>was not to blame for any delay. His<lb/>hon. friend from Northumberland (Mr.<lb/>Kerr) had never been a member of a Go<lb break="no"/>vernment. If he had, he would not find<lb/>it so very comfortable.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName> said the delay was first<lb/>charged to the Opposition, and then to<lb/>the Government. He had been in many<lb/>Governments, and had resigned three<lb/>times. The last time it took from Janu<lb break="no"/>ary till April to get a reply accepting it,<lb/>and now the question was, how long would<lb/>it take by the rate of proportion to get a <lb/>reply to the resignation of eight men ?<lb/>He did not understand his hon colleague's<lb/>(Mr. Anglin) reference to the time re<lb break="no"/>quired by what he had termed the " late<lb/>Opposition," but he could assure his hon.<lb/>friend and the House that, so far as he<lb/>was concerned, he was ready to go on<lb/>with the business.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:DESB2">MR. L. P. W. DESBRISAY</persName> would en<lb break="no"/>dorse the sentiments of the hon. member<lb/>for St. John, (Mr. Wilmot), and further<lb/>state that there was no question of "cour<lb break="no"/>tesy" to the Opposition. They do not<lb/>ask for the " courtesy" of time to be<lb/>granted to mature plans, and did not<lb/>want it. He came here an independent<lb/>member, and when it was remembered<lb/>that he came to support the Government,<lb/>said that Government had <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> to intro<lb break="no"/>duce measures for the good of the coun<lb break="no"/>try. He was not to be surprised <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
would leave their ranks. And now <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
they found they cannot go <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> with the<lb/>
business, they wanted to <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName> said the country 
 

            <pb n="107" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-04-11_Page_107.jpg"/>
    

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>             <fw type="num">107</fw>      
   

     would have to thank the hon. member  
     <lb/>for Kent for defining his position, and at<lb/>the same time for his gratoitous attack<lb/>upon the Government. It would be ima<lb break="no"/>gined that when it was known that the<lb/>Government were in the throes of disso<lb break="no"/>lusion, any man possessing a heart with<lb/>the least sentiment of feeling would have<lb/>refrained from any expression of reproof<lb/>of condemnation. But such an attack,<lb/>be held, was ungenerous and unfeeling in<lb/>the extreme. They did not ask for a<lb/>suspension of business on their own ac-<lb break="yes"/>account, but only that the business of the <lb/>country might be carried on according to<lb/>the principles which had been laid down<lb/>and accepted.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr,. FISHER said that everything was         
     <lb/>passing along smoothly and pleasantly,<lb/>but the hon. member for St. John (Mr.<lb/>Anglin) had thrown a firebrand into the<lb/>discussion, and called forth the remarks of<lb/>the hon. member for Kent.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Mr. ANGLIN</persName> was not aware that he   
     <lb/>had thrown any firebrand, and if the hon.<lb/>member for Kent did not know anything<lb/>about the time required to get together<lb/>and form a new Government, he should<lb/>have refrained from making the remarks<lb/>he had. He said that it was only courtesy<lb/>to the retiring Government and to the<lb/>Opposition, to adjourn, that they might<lb/>have time, on the one hand, to obtain<lb/>their reply, and on  the other to mature <lb/>new plans.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HILL1">Mr. HILL</persName> said he should like to see       
     <lb/>the business go on, but it was patent to<lb/>all, that all might be done would<lb/>amount to nothing. The House would<lb/>probably be adjourned, prorogued or dis<lb break="no"/>solved this week, and there would be<lb/>no time to Bills which might pass the<lb/>House, to be got through the Legislative<lb/>Council.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:FRAS1">Mr. FRASER</persName> said this was not only  
     <lb/>the case, but the business would not be<lb/>constitutional. The Governor was at the<lb/>present time without advisers, and con<lb break="no"/>sequently the House could not go on<lb/>with the business of the country.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName> said he had no doubt 
     <lb/>of the unconstitutionality of the House<lb/>proceeding with business, and should<lb/>move that the House adjourn til to-mor<lb break="no"/>row at half-past two P.M.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     
     
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> said he did not wish to go 
     <lb/>on if any reasonable objection could be<lb/>shown. There was a precedent in the<lb/>matter, for on the 28th of October, 1865, the<lb/>House passed the address and on the <lb/>30th went in a body to  Government <lb/>House. On the 31st met and proceeded<lb/>with business without adjournment till<lb/>Mr. Ritchie came down and announced<lb/>that a new Government was formed, and<lb/>writes issued for a new election.  The <lb/>House was then prorogued. If this was<lb/>the case, then why could not business go<lb/>on now. This, he believed, was the only<lb/>precedent, and business was carried on<lb/>from day to day. He did not wish, how<lb break="no"/>ever, to act discourteously to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, but as the Bill he had introduced <lb/>was entirely local, he could not see how<lb/>it could in any way embarrass or affect<lb/>them.<lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HATH1">HON. Mr.  HATHEWAY</persName>  said the posi      
     <lb/>tion of affairs was different now from that<lb/>referred to. On that  occasion  Mr. <lb/>Ritchie came to the House and announced<lb/>the resignation of the Government, and <lb/>that the Governor had called upon others<lb/>to carry on the business. No such com<lb break="no"/>munication had been made now.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">Mr. WILMOT</persName> said he was a member        
     <lb/>
         

            <cb/>
     

     of the Government, and he thought it       
     <lb/>was a case in point.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. FISHER</persName>, said he went to Govern<lb break="no"/>ment House on that one aion, and they<lb/>were two days ferating the new adminis<lb break="no"/>tration, and when Mr. Ritchie came to<lb/>the house the new members had been<lb/>sworn in. He hoped the hon. member<lb/>for Northumberland would withdraw <lb/>his motion and allow the House to adjourn.<lb/> Mr. KERR complied, and the House<lb/>then adjourned til to-morrow, at half-<lb break="yes"/>past two P.M.</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">J. March.<lb/>
            </p>
   

<!-- GL, 2018-03-14, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

          <!--  <p>
     THURSDAY, APRIL 12.               
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     
     
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. Mr. SMITH</persName> stated that the cor<lb break="no"/>respondence had not yet closed concern<lb break="no"/>ing the resignation of the Governemnt,<lb/>as they had not received a reply which<lb/>his Excellency had promised them; un<lb break="no"/>der these circumstances, he thought they<lb/>should proceed with the business of the<lb/>country.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The House in Committee agreed to "A 
     <lb/>Bill to establish an additional polling <lb/>place in the County of Your."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Also "A Bill to amend the law relating <lb/>to the widening of Cross Street in Saint<lb/>John."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>" A Bill to incorporate the President, <lb/>Directors and Company of the Northern<lb/>Bank."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"A Bill to authorize the Corporation<lb/>of St. John to become Shareholders in<lb/>the European and North American Rail<lb break="no"/>way Company for its extension from St.<lb/>John Westward."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CORA1">Mr. CORAM</persName> said the bill was to au<lb break="no"/>thorize the Corporation of St. John to<lb/>take stock in that Railway to the extent<lb/>of $60,000 and to issue debentures for<lb/>that purpose.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Mr. ANGLIN</persName> said if the road was<lb/>likely to be built by the Company he<lb/>would be willing to pledge the credit of<lb/>St. John for a much larger amount, but<lb/>he saw no prospect of this, for it had<lb/>been five months since the Company had<lb/>commenced operations, and he believed<lb/>that not one dollar of the Company's<lb/>stock had been paid up by the stockhold<lb break="no"/>ers. The day he came up to Fredericton<lb/>he saw but 17 men employed on the road,<lb/>and he thought it was a bogus transaction<lb/>from beginning to end. He did not know<lb/>whether to oppose the bill or not, particu<lb break="no"/>larly as it was only a Permissive Bill.<lb/>Mr. CORAM said the Common Count-<lb break="maybe"/>cil would not sell these debentures with<lb break="no"/>out they were certain that the Company<lb/>would carry out their arrangement, and<lb/>build the road.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. HILL said he was authorized by   
     <lb/>Mr. Burpee to state that there were sev-<lb break="maybe"/>enty-five men working on the road. He<lb/>(Mr. Burpee ) said that he had no doubt<lb/>but what they were in a position to go on<lb/>and complete the work. He (Mr. H.)<lb/>thought it was the duty of the House to<lb/>render all the assistance they could to the<lb/>Company, as that was the only means of<lb/>preventing its being built as a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment work.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     Mr. LINDSAY thought the City of  
     <lb/>St. John should give a bonus to the Com<lb break="no"/>pany of that amount, as the building of<lb/>this Railroad would prove a great benefit<lb/>to that city, as was the building of the<lb/>Grand Trunk Railroad to Portland, which<lb/>increased that value of property there four<lb break="no"/>fold.  He was surprised that his hon. <lb/>friend from St. John (Mr. Anglin) oppos-<lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     ed everything that came up regarding   
     <lb/>Western Extension. He (Mr. Anglin)<lb/>was afraid he was going to be a false pro-<lb break="maybe"/>phel fo he had stated that a foot of<lb/>Railway never would be built under the<lb/>Subsidy Act.  He (Mr. L) thought St.<lb/>John would be a gamer if they gave four<lb/>times that amount as this road would<lb/>bring the trade from the interior to the<lb/>sea-board. He would do all he could for<lb/>the company, but he was opposed to Rail<lb break="no"/>ways being built as Government works.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     
     
     Mr. GILBERT said his hon. friend      
     <lb/>from St. John, (Mr. Anglin), who should<lb/>be well informed in regard to the ability<lb/>of this Company to build the road, be<lb break="no"/>ing lately a member of the Government,<lb/>called this a bogus Railway Company.<lb/>We should, therefore, hesitate before<lb/>passing a bill authorizing the Corpora<lb break="no"/>tion of St. John to tax the citizens to<lb/>aid this company. He wished to encour<lb break="no"/>age the building of Railroads, as it open<lb break="no"/>ed up the country and leads to emigra<lb break="no"/>tion and the settlement of the country.<lb/>but he considered that a company that<lb/>undertook the work of building Western<lb/>Extension should have a very large capi<lb break="no"/>tal to carry on the work successfully.<lb/> <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     Nr. ANGLIN said his hon. friend    
     <lb/>(Mr. Gilbert) could judge for himself.<lb/>The road would cost $2,500.000, and<lb/>there had not been one dollar paid up or<lb/>called for.  The Company had already<lb/>a subsidized stock of $140,000, and they<lb/>want this $60,000 in addition. If it was<lb/>not permissive Bill, he would give it<lb/>his most strenuous opposition.<lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     
     
     Mr. FISHER said the only objection  
     <lb/>he had to the Bill was that the amount of<lb/>stock to be taken in St. John was not<lb/>one-tenth of what it should be. The<lb/>town of Woodstock, with only two thou<lb break="no"/>sand inhabitants, had given $40,000 in<lb/>aid of their branch line, and surely St. <lb/>John, with its wealth and population,<lb/>should give $500,000. He would vote for<lb/>the Bill.<lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     
     
     
     
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> said that Common  
     <lb/>Council had sent this Bill up to the House<lb/>and they had no right to reject it without<lb/>sufficient cause. The Corporation would<lb/>not take stock in it if they thought it was<lb/>likely to prove a bogus company.<lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     The Bill was then agreed to, after which       
     <lb/>some Bills were introduced, and the<lb/>House adjourned to meet at 10 A.M. to<lb break="no"/>morrow.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     T.P.D. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

            <p>
     
     
     
     
     FRIDAY, APRIL 13.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     The House met pursuant to adjourn<lb break="no"/>ment at 10 A.M.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>After the readying of a number of Bills<lb/>for the third time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. GILBERT said the ballot system<lb/>had now been in operation for two years,<lb/>but it was notorious that the voter was<lb/>not sufficiently protected in his approach<lb/>to the ballot box.  A canvasser could<lb/>take hold of a man and take him to the the<lb/>ballot box, and compel him to vote as he<lb/>wished, even though he had his ballot in<lb/>his pocket to deposit for another candi<lb/>date. No man should be allowed to co<lb/> trol the action of an elector. Some hon<lb/>members might think the Bill did not<lb/>
            </p>-->

    
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>