<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-03-28"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-03-28">28 March 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="67" to="71"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_067.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_068.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_069.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_070.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_071.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-07">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_067">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_067.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_068">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_068.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_069">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_069.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_070">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_070.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_071">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_071.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="67" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_067.jpg"/>
        
     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  <fw type="num">67</fw> 
    


<!-- GL, 2018-03-07, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
            
   
          <!--  <p>
     it be necessary to pass Such a law in 
     <lb/>
     this instance, how much more important 
     <lb/>
     is it that a Judge should keep aloof 
     <lb/>
     from all political contests. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The hon. member from Restigouche 
     <lb/>
     has called us " mongrels," and has con<lb break="no"/>demned us because we have alluded to 
     <lb/>
     the despatches from the Home Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in the speech. My hon. colleague 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Gilbert) also does so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There is an unerring law of nature 
     <lb/>
     applicable to the animal kingdom, that 
     <lb/>
     when certain species amalgamate they 
     <lb/>
     produce hybrids. These Counties have 
     <lb/>
     returned what I call hybrid politicians, 
     <lb/>
     and the sooner their constituents dis 
     <lb/>
     pose of them, the better their interests 
     <lb/>
     will be subserved . 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Thu Surveyor General thanked the 
     <lb/>
     House for its indulgence, and left the 
     <lb/>
     question in its hands, feeling satisfied 
     <lb/>
     that after calmly considering the evi<lb break="no"/>dence, it will triumphantly acquit the 
     <lb/>
     Government, which will be responded 
     <lb/>
     to by a large majority ot the people of 
     <lb/>
    this Province. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->


            <head rendition="simple:right">WEDNESDAY, MARCH 28. 
   
            </head>
        

   
            <p>
     On motion of <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName>, the 
     <lb/>
     House went into a Committee of 'the 
     <lb/>
     Whole on a Bill to revive. and continue 
     <lb/>
     an Act entitled an Act for the relief of 
     <lb/>
     insolvent debtors. This. Bill caused a 
     <lb/>
     long discussion. and was finally referred 
     <lb/>
     to a select Committee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The House then proceeded to the order 
     <lb/>
     of the day:  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     THE ADJOURNED DEBATE ON MR. FISHER'S 
     <lb/>
     AMENDMENT. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">MR. McCLELLAN</persName> said that before the 
     <lb/>
     Hon. Surveyor General resumed his 
     <lb/>
     speech, he would claim the indulgence of 
     <lb/>
     the House to reply to some observations 
     <lb/>
     which that gentleman made yesterday 
     <lb/>
     when he (Mr. McC.) was not in his seat. 
     <lb/>
     He was informed that the Hon. Surveyor 
     <lb/>
     General had complained of his having 
     <lb/>
     made an unfair statement concerning the 
     <lb/>
     granting of twenty-seven acres to Mr. 
     <lb/>
    Gibson without public sale. What he 
     <lb/>( Mr. McClellan) stated was as follows: 
     <lb/>That on enquiry at the Land Office he 
     <lb/>had ascertained that amongst other lands 
     <lb/>granted to Mr. Gibson, were two small 
     <lb/>lots detached from the main body, one of 
     <lb/>fifty acres at the Nashwaak Falls, and 
     <lb/>another of twenty- seven acres at the head 
     <lb/>of the river, and commanding the waters 
     <lb/>of St. Mary's Lake, that the latter, 
     <lb/>though advertised in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi>, along 
     <lb/>with the other lands applied for at the 
     <lb/>time, was not sold publicly but granted 
     <lb/>to Mr. Gibson without being offered to 
     <lb/>public competition at all, but that the 
     <lb/>clerk had told him in justification of the 
     <lb/>proceeding, that this lot was so granted 
     <lb/>to Mr. gibson to compensate him for a 
     <lb/>deficiency in another lot which he (Mr. 
     <lb/>Gibson) held. The Hon. Surveyor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral could not have noticed the whole re<lb break="no"/>ference,, or he would not have imputed 
     <lb/>any unfairness in the statement. Several 
     <lb/>other hon. members could assert that he 
     <lb/>had so stated the case, every word of 
     <lb/>which he (Mr. McClellan) could substan<lb break="no"/>tiate. He did not censure this Govern<lb break="no"/>ment particularly in this matter, but the 
     <lb/>system was open to suspicion. and if this 
     <lb/>was the proper time to discuss the ques<lb break="no"/>tion of the crown lands, he was quite 
     <lb/>prepared to show that however much the<lb/>
      
            <cb/>
        

     Government might <hi rendition="simple:italic">veneer</hi> or <hi rendition="simple:italic">whitewash</hi> 
     <lb/>
     their system of management, a close in<lb break="no"/>spection would reveal the fact, that the 
     <lb/>
     interests of the people were neglected 
     <lb/>
     and a great public wrong inflicted by the 
     <lb/>
     present administration in connection with 
     <lb/>
     this matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. MR. SMITH</persName> rose to order, and 
     <lb/>
     said this was not the proper time to argue 
     <lb/>
     the question further, when the Hon. Sur<lb break="no"/>veyor General was entitled to the floor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">MR. ANGLIN</persName> said the Hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for Albert (Mr. McClelan) had stated the 
     <lb/>
     case most unfairly and unjustly yesterday, 
     <lb/>
     and he was now putting it in exactly the 
     <lb/>
     same light again. His impression, from 
     <lb/>
     what his hon. friend had stated, was that 
     <lb/>
     these twenty-seven acres were part and 
     <lb/>
     parcel of the 10,000 acres sold to Mr. Gib<lb break="no"/>son, and these twenty-seven acres were sold 
     <lb/>
     to him by the present Surveyor General 
     <lb/>
     without competition, because they com<lb break="no"/>manded tha head waters of the St. Mary's 
     <lb/>
     Lake. This was the impression convey<lb break="no"/>ed to every member of the House, with 
     <lb/>
     the exception of the late surveyor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral. The sale of this land took place in 
     <lb/>
     1860, by order of the Government, and it 
     <lb/>
     passed through sereral hands before Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Gibson bought it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">MR. McCLELAN</persName>, in reply, said that 
     <lb/>
     the hon. member from St. John would do 
     <lb/>
     well to keep cool, for if it became a ques<lb break="no"/>tion of veracity between that hon. gentle<lb break="no"/>man and himself, he (Mr. McClelan) had 
     <lb/>
     no fear that his assertion would have. as 
     <lb/>
     much weight with the people of New 
     <lb/>
     Brunswick as that of the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     from St. John. He had stated only facts, 
     <lb/>
     which he was prepared to prove, and he 
     <lb/>
     had done so, too, frankly and openly, and 
     <lb/>
     without any prevarication or distortion 
     <lb/>
     and concealment.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hon MR. SMITH again rose to order, 
     <lb/>
     and. amidst considerable confusion, the 
     <lb/>
     standing order of the House was insisted 
     <lb/>
     on by Mr. Needham, and the discussion 
     <lb/>
     was continued with closed doors. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     
     AFTERNOON SESSION 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     Hon MR. BOTSFORD.—Before the 
     <lb/>
     recess my hon. friend from the County 
     <lb/>
     of Albert (Mr. McC.) was making some 
     <lb/>
     explanation with reference to what I 
     <lb/>
     considered a charge made by him 
     <lb/>
     against. the Government. I charged 
     <lb/>
     him with imparting to the people erone<lb break="no"/>ous information in regard to the twenty- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     seven acres of land which Mr. Gibson 
     <lb/>
     purchased from Mr. Chipman at the rate 
     <lb/>
     of $3 per acre. In his explanation he 
     <lb/>
     still conveys the same eroneous impres<lb break="no"/>sion, that this land was purchased from 
     <lb/>
     the Government without competition. 
     <lb/>
     It has been stated here that I maintain<lb break="no"/>ed the doctrine that all information re<lb break="no"/>garding Crown Lands should be sought 
     <lb/>
     for at the head office of the department, 
     <lb/>
     l never made any such assertion. I 
     <lb/>
     never said information should not be 
     <lb/>
     imparted at the deputies' office. I said 
     <lb/>
     that when they wanted information on 
     <lb/>
     which to ground a charge against the 
     <lb/>
     head of the department, it, was a fair, 
     <lb/>
     open, manly way to come to the head 
     <lb/>
     office for information.   
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In reference to the charge that notice 
     <lb/>
     was not given in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Royal Gazette</hi> of 
     <lb/>
     the rescinding of this Order of Council, 
     <lb/>
     it will be borne in mind tha from 1862t 
     <lb/>
     until June, 1865, all notices in the Royal 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi> for the sale of land, under auc<lb break="no"/>tion, was subject to a condition of ac<lb break="no"/>
          

            <cb/>
       
tual settlement, but from the time that<lb/>order was rescinded in 1865, that notice<lb/>requiring actual settlement was left out. 
     <lb/>
     The very moment that condition was 
     <lb/>
     not annexed to the advertisements, the 
     <lb/>
     land would be sold at auction to the 
     <lb/>
     highest bidder. therefore this gave it. 
     <lb/>
     every possible publicity. (Mr. Lind<lb break="no"/>say— The <hi rendition="simple:italic">Royal Gazette</hi> says the condi<lb break="no"/>tions will be explained at the time of 
     <lb/>
     sale, and the deputy said he had no in<lb break="no"/>structions only those which he had re<lb break="no"/>ceived some years ago, and he was led 
     <lb/>
     to suppose the same regulations still 
     <lb/>
     continued.) If any person will take the 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi> and look at the advertisements 
     <lb/>
     for the sale of land by auction, from last 
     <lb/>
     June, he will find that there are no con<lb break="no"/>ditions of actual settlement attached to 
     <lb/>
     those sales after the rescinding of the 
     <lb/>
     Order of Council, thereby conclusive<lb break="no"/>ly showing to every deputy—through 
     <lb/>
     this <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi>, which is his rule and 
     <lb/>
     guide—that no condition of actual set<lb break="no"/>tlement was required. Notwithstand<lb break="no"/>ing that notice did take place, itdid not 
     <lb/>
     increase the sales of land, neither did 
     <lb/>
     the publication of the rescinding of the 
     <lb/>
     Order of Council, and the comments 
     <lb/>
     thereon in the St. John paers, in Sep<lb break="no"/>tember. In the month of July there 
     <lb/>
     were two thousand one hundred acres 
     <lb/>
     sold, in August three thousand one hun<lb break="no"/>dred, September three thousand, Octo<lb break="no"/>ber three thousand two hundred. Nov<lb break="no"/>ember two thousand seven hundred, 
     <lb/>
     December three thousand. This shows 
     <lb/>
     very conclusively that the sales of land 
     <lb/>
     did not increase after the rescinding of 
     <lb/>
     the Order of Council was published 
     <lb/>
     throughout the length and breadth of 
     <lb/>
     the land. The next charge was made 
     <lb/>
     in reference to the non-appointment of 
     <lb/>
     an Auditor General. (Mr. Botsford 
     <lb/>
     then read the law regarding the office.) 
     <lb/>
     We have gone according to law and the 
     <lb/>
     accounts in that office have been made 
     <lb/>
     up, so that they could see at a glance 
     <lb/>
     the state of the finances of the country. 
     <lb/>
     The hon. member for Westmorland 
     <lb/>
     (Mr. Gilbert) has alluded to a vote of 
     <lb/>
     want of confidence, which he says has 
     <lb/>
     taken place in the other branch of the 
     <lb/>
     Legislature. I do not know as it is 
     <lb/>
     parliamentary to speak  of the proceed<lb break="no"/>ings of that body, but I think that I have 
     <lb/>
     a right to do so, as the subject has been 
     <lb/>
     introduced. It has been represented 
     <lb/>
     that that vote of want of confidence is 
     <lb/>
     no more or less than that they are favor<lb break="no"/>able to a union in any way whatever. 
     <lb/>
     This means nothing more or less than 
     <lb/>
     that they are favorable to the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     Scheme. It has been stated by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     mover of the amendment, that it is per<lb break="no"/>fectly futile for any member of the 
     <lb/>
     House of Assembly to object to this 
     <lb/>
     question of representation by popula<lb break="no"/>tion, as it was a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi> with Upper 
     <lb/>
     Canada. Therefore, the Legislative 
     <lb/>
     Council, knowing they could get no 
     <lb/>
     other scheme, have by their vote of 
     <lb/>
     want of confidence declared themselves 
     <lb/>
     in favor of the Quebec Scheme. (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     Wilmot—The leader of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, so far as I understood him, ad<lb break="no"/>mitted that he would consent to repre<lb break="no"/>sentation by population, provided there 
     <lb/>
     were checks in the Legislative Council. 
     <lb/>
     I put the question to him and he ad<lb break="no"/>mitted it clearly and distinctly.) 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. MR. SMITH</persName>—I made no such 
     <lb/>
     statement. I said I never would 
     <lb/>
     go for representation, pure and simple. 
     <lb/>
     I would not go for it without checks and 
     <lb/>
    guards could be placed upon it to neutralize 
     <lb/>
   

            <pb n="68" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_068.jpg"/>
           

     <fw type="num">68</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 


     its effects. The principle, to my mind,<lb/>is entirely wrong, but if that principle is 
     <lb/>
     adopted the number of representatives 
     <lb/>
     must be restricted.  
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p>HON MR. BOTSFORD. - The hon. 
     <lb/>mover of the amendment has said that 
     <lb/>Upper Canada would not accede to any 
     <lb/>proposition for union unless it contained 
     <lb/>the principle of representation by popula<lb break="no"/>tion; and , therefore without this any 
     <lb/>union was impracticable. That is we 
     <lb/>have to submit, because Upper Canada 
     <lb/>chooses to put forward a proposition, a 
     <lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi>. New Brunswick, contain<lb break="no"/>ing 250,000 inhabitants, must swallow the 
     <lb/>scheme because Upper Canada says so. 
     <lb/>It is a proposition no free man who knows 
     <lb/>his rights will ever submit to. The mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Legislative Council know 
     <lb/>these facts: therefore, when they passed 
     <lb/>the amendment to the Address, they 
     <lb/>promulgated the idea that the Quebec 
     <lb/>Scheme would be a benefit to the country. 
     <lb/>In the public prints we find the division 
     <lb/>in that body, on this question, was nine 
     <lb/>for the amendment and four against it. 
     <lb/>I will suppose a case. Suppose the num<lb break="no"/>ber of members in this House was reduced 
     <lb/>to thirteen. which was the number pre<lb break="no"/>sent when that amendment passed, and 
     <lb/>we should rush this amendment through 
     <lb/>when the mover and seconder were ab<lb break="no"/>sent, what would the country say to such 
     <lb/>deliberations? I think my hon. friend 
     <lb/>(Mr.Fisher) would be the first man to con<lb break="no"/>demn it, for I think he is far above tak<lb break="no"/>ing that course. Of those nine who voted 
     <lb/>in the majority, three were delegates who 
     <lb/>helped to concoct the scheme, and the 
     <lb/>other six were not opposed to it. This 
     <lb/>being the case, how can it be said that 
     <lb/>there was a change of public opinion upon 
     <lb/>this subject. My hon. friend (Mr. F.) 
     <lb/>has said that when the principle of one 
     <lb/>of those resolutions came up which pro<lb break="no"/>vided that a certain number of gentlemen 
     <lb/>should be selected from the Legislative 
     <lb/>Council, that he and his colleagues did 
     <lb/>not agree about it. The people or this 
     <lb/>Province. were led to believe that this 
     <lb/>resolution was the unanimous decision of 
     <lb/>those thirty delegates. (Mr. Fisher. - I 
     <lb/>told him more than three-fourths of the 
     <lb/>delegates were in favor of the mode 
     <lb/>adopted in the scheme for the constitution 
     <lb/>of the Legislative Council. I only gave 
     <lb/>my own opinion as being opposed to<lb/>them.) My hon. friend was opposed to<lb/>the principle of forming the Federal<lb/>Council by selecting members from the<lb/>Legislative Councils of the different Pro 
     <lb/>vinces. Do you suppose that Mr. George 
     <lb/>Brown, who was the concocter of the 
     <lb/>scheme, would not have put the screws on 
     <lb/>and confined us to numbers, when he 
     <lb/>found there was a disagreement among 
     <lb/>our delegates in one of the most import<lb break="no"/>ant points. This I consider one of the 
     <lb/>most objectionable features in the scheme. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Another objection made was in refer<lb break="no"/>ence to the reinstatement of Mr. Inches 
     <lb/>
     into the Crown Land Office. In 1863, a 
     <lb/>
     petition to His Excellency recommending 
     <lb/>
     the reinstatement of Mr. Inches into that 
     <lb/>
     office was signed by Messrs. Stevens, 
     <lb/>
     Glazier, Vail, Allen, Gillmor, Monroe, 
     <lb/>
    Lindsay, Ferris, Beveridge, McClelan, 
     <lb/>Stiles, Scovil, Boyd, Williston, McPhe<lb break="no"/>lim, Young, Landry, Dow, Costigan, Des<lb break="no"/>Brisay, Ryan, Crocker, Gray, Skinner, 
     <lb/>Grimmer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GILB1">MR. GILBERT</persName>.—I do not object to the 
     <lb/>
     reinstatement of Mr. Inches, because I 
     <lb/>
     never thought he was culpable. I never 
     <lb/>thought that either he, or the hon. mover<lb/>
      

            <cb/>


     of the amendment were blameable for<lb/>the course they took at the time.<lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOTS1">HON. MR. BOTSFORD</persName>.—I merely 
     <lb/>brought this forward to show that a large 
     <lb/>majority of the members of the House of 
     <lb/>Assembly, in 1863, were in favor of rein<lb break="no"/>stating Mr. Inches. In 1865 a similar 
     <lb/>petition was got up and signed by twenty-<lb break="yes"/>five of the members of the present As<lb break="no"/>sembly. (Mr. Wetmore—We signed it 
     <lb/>because we thought the Surveyor General 
     <lb/>did not understand the business of the 
     <lb/>office, and it was very important that 
     <lb/>some one should be there that did.) My 
     <lb/>hon. friend likes a passage at arms; he 
     <lb/>does not give the true reason, but says it 
     <lb/>was for my especial benefit. We have 
     <lb/>then a majority of the House of Assem<lb break="no"/>bly, just from the people, signing a peti<lb break="no"/>tion for the reinstatement of Mr. Inches, 
     <lb/>therefore that could be no charge against 
     <lb/>the Government. Another charge made 
     <lb/>against the Government by the hon. 
     <lb/>mover of the amendment, was in regard 
     <lb/>to my temporary absence on a visit to 
     <lb/>my family. ( <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. Fisher</persName>—I did not refer 
     <lb/>to him in particular. I referred to the 
     <lb/>fact that the members of the Government 
     <lb/>were floating over the country, the At<lb break="no"/>torney General being absent for four or 
     <lb/>gve months, to which I attributed the dif<lb break="no"/>ficulties in which the Government were 
     <lb/>involved.) I think the inference is drawn 
     <lb/>that my duties are not attended to. Why<lb/>does he not make a charge in a fair way, 
     <lb/>so it can be understood, and not deal in 
     <lb/>inuendoes? Why does he allude  in 
     <lb/>general terms to the duties of my office 
     <lb/>being neglected because I occasionally 
     <lb/>visit my family? The first question put 
     <lb/>to me when I was offered the office was, 
     <lb/>would I remove my permanent residence 
     <lb/>to Fredericton? I replied that I would 
     <lb/>accept of no political office upon those 
     <lb/>terms. I said I would accept of no office 
     <lb/>if I could not attend to its duties and 
     <lb/>have time to visit my family. this ques<lb break="no"/>tion of residing in Fredericton involves 
     <lb/>an importannt principle to every gentle 
     <lb/>man on the floors of this House. If ac<lb break="no"/>cepting a political office outside the 
     <lb/>County of York involves a permanent 
     <lb/>residence in Fredericton, it is a virtual 
     <lb/>denial of any political office to any person 
     <lb/>living beyond the County of Sunbury, and 
     <lb/>is an injustice to other parts of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. I ask the hon. mover of the 
     <lb/>amendment to point out what has been 
     <lb/>neglected in my office during my tempor<lb break="no"/>ary absence. While other gentlemen 
     <lb/>enter their offices at ten o'clock in the 
     <lb/>morning, and retire at three, having an 
     <lb/>hour's intermission at noon. I am not 
     <lb/>confined to hours. I am there from half- 
     <lb break="yes"/>past eight in the morning until six at 
     <lb/>night. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
    

            <p>
     The hon. mover of the amendment 
     <lb/>
     charges the members of this Government 
     <lb/>
     with being vascillaiing in their conduct - <lb/>with being low and mean, more pigmies. 
     <lb/>
     This comes with a bad grace from one who 
     <lb/>
     boasts of being of such political gigantic 
     <lb/>
     stature. We know what he thinks of 
     <lb/>
     himself by his card, which he issued to 
     <lb/>
     the electors of York . He says, "I have 
     <lb/>
     left the impress of my mind upon the in<lb break="no"/>stituions of this country. " This was not 
     <lb/>
     spoken during the heat of debate. but 
     <lb/>
     was written when he had time for calm 
     <lb/>
     reflection. Hee calls us low and mean be<lb break="no"/>cause we signed a Minute of Council, 
     <lb/>
     which he said was insulting to the Queen's 
     <lb/>
     minister. When a question was pro<lb break="no"/>pounded to us, we gave our views in a 
     <lb/>
     calm, loyal and dignified manner, as Brit<lb break="no"/>ish subjects in New Brunswick. We had 
     <lb/>


            <cb/>
         

     considered whether this scheme of union 
     <lb/>
    was beneficial or not, and these were our 
     <lb/>views, and they were the views of a large<lb/>majority of the people of this country, 
     <lb/>who endorse every word of that dispatch. 
     <lb/>We did not wish to adopt a scheme of 
     <lb/>union which would subvert the Constitu<lb break="no"/>tion, and bring upon us "lamentation 
     <lb/>and woe." He (Mr. F.) will leave the 
     <lb/>impress of his mind upon the institutions 
     <lb/>of this country; and he might have added<lb/>his actions in this country will stare him 
     <lb/>in the face. He was tried before a com<lb break="no"/>mittee of this House and condemned. 
     <lb/>( <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. Fisher</persName>.—I was not.) He was thrust 
     <lb/>out as unworthy to serve the Government 
     <lb/>by the force of public opinion, and now he 
     <lb/>calls us low and mean, ( <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. Fisher</persName>,—I 
     <lb/>did not.) and said we had no capacity. 
     <lb/>After being thrust out of the Government, 
     <lb/>he was like the spaniel who, after being 
     <lb/>castigated by his master, would turn 
     <lb/>round and lick his hand. He was obse<lb break="no"/>quious to the concocters of the Quebec 
     <lb/>Scheme; he agreed to all but one prin<lb break="no"/>ciple. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     There is another charge made against 
     <lb/>
     the Government, which I shall touch very 
     <lb/>
     briefly upon. We are charged with ma<lb break="no"/>king our promotions on the Bench on 
     <lb/>
     political grounds. I deny it. We say 
     <lb/>
     that Chief Justice Ritchie is a man com<lb break="no"/>petent and able to fill that situation. As 
     <lb/>
     a jurist, Judge and Barrister, he is 
     <lb/>
     pre-eminently qualified for that situation. 
     <lb/>
     Hon. gentlemen may assert that the 
     <lb/>
     promotion was an insult to Judge Wil<lb break="no"/>mot, but that does not detract from his 
     <lb/>
     talents or position; it. is a charge based 
     <lb/>
     upon a baseless foundation. If Judge 
     <lb/>
     Ritchie was incompetent to fill the office, 
     <lb/>
     then the Government would allow the 
     <lb/>
     charge was valid . Who made it a po<lb break="no"/>lital matter? My hon. friend, the 
     <lb/>
     mover of the Amendment, has made it 
     <lb/>
     so, because he justifies Judge Wilmot 
     <lb/>
     for exerting his influence in addressing 
     <lb/>
     Juries from the Bench on the question
     <lb/>
     of Confederation. Then again, after 
     <lb/>
     Confederation had been dead and buried, 
     <lb/>
     after all had become calm, and party 
     <lb/>
     spirit had died away, there occurred a 
     <lb/>
     vacancy in the County of York, and 
     <lb/>
     everybody knew that my hon. friend en<lb break="no"/>tered the contest to fill that vacancy, with 
     <lb/>
     the avowed denial that Confederation had 
     <lb/>
     anything to do with it. It was a purely 
     <lb/>
     party question between Mr. Fisher and 
     <lb/>
     the Government. He put it upon the 
     <lb/>
     grounds of hostility to the present Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, and hostility to Tim Anglin, 
     <lb/>
     he would not even say Mr. Anglin. It 
     <lb/>
     was merely a party question whether 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Pickard should be returned or not. 
     <lb/>
     When Judge Wilmot descended and en<lb break="no"/>tered the political contest without any 
     <lb/>
     excitement concerning Confederation, 
     <lb/>
     for Mr. Fisher himself ignored the 
     <lb/>
     ground that Confederation had anything 
     <lb/>
     to do with the election; he prostituted 
     <lb/>
     the Bench and made it a political arena. 
     <lb/>
     He openly went to the polls and gave 
     <lb/>
     his vote, saying at the same time: 
     <lb/>
     "there is a vote for Charles Fisher." 
     <lb/>
     If that is not dragging the ermine into 
     <lb/>
     politics I do not know what it is. We 
     <lb/>
     were discussing in the House, not long 
     <lb/>
     since a question whether a Judge had a 
     <lb/>
     right to sit in judgment on a case where 
     <lb/>
     he is interested to the extent of one- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     seventh part of a cent: but here you have 
     <lb/>
     a Judge descending from the Bench and 
     <lb/>
     identifying himself with party politics, 
     <lb/>
     by voting for Mr. Fisher, against the 
     <lb/>
     Government. ( <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName>.—Where 
     <lb/>
     did you get your information?) He 
     <lb/>
    

            <pb n="69" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_069.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  <fw type="num">69</fw> 
    

     said, "here is a vote for Charles 
     <lb/>Fisher." ( <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName> - How do you<lb/>know?) I hard so. I am prepared to<lb/>show that Judge Ritchie never voted<lb/>nor took any part in a political contest,<lb/>and when Confederation came up he<lb/>had nothing to do with it. there is no<lb/>instance on record where a judge ever<lb/>mixed himself up with party political<lb/>questions. Suppose a row took place be<lb break="no"/>tween the party he was voting for and<lb/>the other side and a murder was com<lb break="no"/>mitted, and he was called upon to try<lb/>those parties, could he divest himself of<lb/>political feeling, and bring his mind<lb/>into that calm state, that he could give<lb/>a dispassionate judgement.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The ex-Surveyor General chooses to 
     <lb/>style us traitors. I shall not reply to him<lb/>in the same way, for I know he gets ex<lb break="no"/>cited, and we must make allowances for 
     <lb/>
     him. He called the Attorney General 
     <lb/>
     a mongrel, and he thought he would 
     <lb/>
     soon get to the pure breed. ( <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. 
     <lb/>
     McMillan</persName> - I called him a cross between 
     <lb/>
     a Confederate and an anti-Confederate, 
     <lb/>
     and I was perfectly justified in saying so, 
     <lb/>
     for he has declared in that Minute of 
     <lb/>Council that he was against all union,<lb/>and then by the Speech from the Throne<lb/>he had foreshadowed a scheme of union.)<lb/>My hon. friend accuses us of being a<lb/>cross between a Confederate and an<lb/>anti, because we have respectfully, by<lb/>the command of His Excellency, put<lb/>into the Speech that he has received cer<lb break="no"/>tain commands with reference to a<lb/>Union of the colonies, and we answer<lb/>to that and say, that when that corres<lb break="no"/>pondence is laid before us it will recieve<lb/>due consideration from this House. He<lb/>condemns us because we only respect<lb break="no"/>fully allude to it, and my hon. colleague <lb/>(Mr. Gilbert) takes the other extreme,<lb/>and condemns us because we put it in<lb/>at all. these are two antagonistic prin<lb break="no"/>ciples, and it is an unerring law of na<lb break="no"/>ture, that different species of vegetables<lb/>or animals produce hybrids, therefore,<lb/>when he calls us a cross breed, I will<lb/>call my hon. friend from Westmorland,<lb/>and the ex-Surveyor General, hybrid<lb/>politicians, and I think their constitu<lb break="no"/>ency would be benefited by destroying<lb/>this hybrid breed. I will now thank<lb/>this House for the attention which they<lb/>have paid me while addressing them. I<lb/>do not appeal to their sympathy, but I<lb/>say that, in my opinion, the charges<lb/>made against the department over which<lb/>I have supervision are perfectly ground<lb break="no"/>less; other charges brought against the<lb/>Leader of the Government have been<lb/>already explained. I ask the House to<lb/>give the charges a calm investiation,<lb/>and not pre-judge us, for I feel satisfied,<lb/>whatever the decision my be, they can<lb break="no"/>not put their hand on one title of evi<lb break="no"/>dence to justify any of the charges made<lb/>against this Government, for I am satis<lb break="no"/>fied that they have discharged their duty,<lb/>and I am satisfied the vote of this As<lb break="no"/>sembly will acquit them of any such<lb/>charges made on so baseless a founda<lb break="no"/>tion.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">MR. CONNELL</persName>. - I will make a few 
     <lb/>observations in reference to the subject<lb/>of debate, which has arisen out of the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing resolution:<lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "And your Excellency may rely with 
     <lb/>confidence upon our cordial co-operation<lb/>and support in the adoption of such mea<lb break="no"/>sures as may be deemed necessary for the<lb/>protection of the country; but we re<lb break="no"/>spectfully state to your Excellency that<lb/>
     

            <cb/>
         

     your constitutional advisers, by their 
     <lb/>general conduct, are not entitled to our<lb/>confidence."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     I am one of those who believe that the 
     <lb/>course pursued by the Government has<lb/>not given satisfaction to the country, and<lb/>I will give my reasons for this belief.<lb/>During the last sitting of the Legislature,<lb/>a resolution was brough into the House<lb/>and supported by the Government, that a<lb/>delegation should go to England. Where<lb/>was the necessity for that delegation and<lb/>what good has resulted from it? That<lb/>delegation was sent avowedly by the<lb/>authority of this House, for the purpose<lb/>of conveying to the British Government<lb/>an idea of the state of things that existed<lb/>in this Province, and I ask the Attorney<lb/>General if he believed it necessary to go<lb/>to England to convey this information to<lb/>them? Did he think they had the con<lb break="no"/>stitutional right to interfere in our local<lb/>matters? They had previously sent a<lb/>despatch giving the result of the elections<lb/>in this Province, to show that the people<lb/>had rejected the Quebec Scheme, as they<lb/>had only returned nine Confederates in<lb/>the whole Province, although there were<lb/>four who had not declared themselves for<lb/>or against the Scheme. It is about time<lb/>they should write another despatch, for<lb/>we are all for union now. His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency's speech is for union and some of<lb/>the hon. members are for union one way<lb/>and some another. The Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eral will go for union, provided there are<lb/>some checks made to counter-balance re<lb break="no"/>presentation by population. Was it ne<lb break="no"/>cessary or desirable to put the Province<lb/>to the great expense of that delegation?<lb/>It is true the Government may shelter<lb/>themselves by saying this delegation<lb/>was authorized to go to England by a<lb/>resolution of the House which says:<lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "<hi rendition="simple:italic">Whereas</hi>, in the exercise of the right 
     <lb/>of internal self-government enjoyed by<lb/>this Province, its people are entitled to<lb/>deliberate and decide upon all questions <lb/>affecting their own local interests in such<lb/>manner as to them may seem best calcu<lb break="no"/>lated to promote their prosperity and wel<lb break="no"/>fare; 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     "<hi rendition="simple:italic">Therefore Resolved</hi>, As the opinion of 
     <lb/>this House, that a delegation should at<lb/>once proceed to England for the purpose<lb/>of making known to the Imperial Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment the views and feelings of this<lb/>House, and the people of this Province<lb/>on this important subject."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     I was opposed to this resolution, and I 
     <lb/>was in the minority; but small as that<lb/>minority was at that time, it is now the<lb/>feeling of a vast majority of the people of<lb/>this Province. The course pursued by<lb/>the Government in initiating that delega<lb break="no"/>tion cost a large sum of money; while it<lb/>was unnecessary, uncalled for, and, in its<lb/>results, was of no benefit to the Province.<lb/>This delegation preformed things which<lb/>the resolution did not authorize them t<lb/>do. What authority did they have to en<lb break="no"/>ter into any arrangements, or contracts,<lb/>for building this line of railway between<lb/>Moncton and Amherst? They had no<lb/>authority whatever except what was given<lb/>them under the Facility Act, which gives<lb/>the Government no authority to make any<lb/>contracts. They may have had some<lb/>secret arrangements which were never<lb/>made public, but they were not authorized<lb/>by this House or by law to make any con<lb break="no"/>tracts whatever. The delegates who <lb/>went from Nova Scotia were authorized<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
         

     by their colleagues - as appears from 
     <lb/>minutes of Council to make arrangements<lb/>concerning the fisheries, reciprocity and<lb/>railways, but our delegates had no<lb/>
     authority to enter into a contract with 
     <lb/>parties in England to build the railway<lb/>from Moncton to Amherst. The only<lb/>thing I can see in the law in reference to<lb/>the matter is this  The facility act in<lb/>reference to this Railway is restrained,<lb/>unless Nova Scotia makes a contract for<lb/>their portion of the line. Then it is al<lb break="no"/>lowed to operate, but it gives no authori<lb break="no"/>ty to the Government to enter into con<lb break="no"/>tracts for building it. I should like to<lb/>know why if is that this line of railway<lb/>connecting with the Nova Scotia line<lb/>should have more of the immediate atten<lb break="no"/>tion of the Government than any of the <lb/>other lines contemplated under the<lb/>Subsidy Act. It seems arragenments<lb/>are made, contracts entered into, and the<lb/>surveys paid for this railroad. By what<lb/>authority has the Government entered into<lb/>a contract to pay them all the cost of a<lb/>right of way, where it exceeds $200 a mile<lb/>which will be a considerable sum as the<lb/>road runs through valuable mash land?<lb/>why do they give them this preference, <lb/>while is is very difficult for parties en<lb break="no"/>gaged in other railways, to even get their<lb/>road acknowledged? ( <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Mr. Anglin</persName>, - In<lb/>what case?) In Woodstock the road has<lb/>not been acknowledge, nor the survey<lb/>paid, although the work is going on.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GILB1">MR. GILBERT</persName>. - The survey has been 
     <lb/>paid. My hon. friend undertook to<lb/>make another survey, which has not been<lb/>paid.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. MR. SMITH</persName>. - The impression 
     <lb/>you wish to convey is that we are not do<lb break="no"/>ing what ought to be done, in regard to<lb/>the Woodstock Railway. Mr. Hartley<lb/>and Mr. Hay came down here to talk the<lb/>matter over. I told them the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would give them every asistance,<lb/>for we felt disposed to encourage them<lb/>in every way.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">MR. CONNELL</persName>. - It is very important 
     <lb/>that these matters should be entered in<lb break="no"/>to at once. They have not yet been ac<lb break="no"/>knowledged even up to the present time. 
     <lb/>it is true, the Attorney General promised<lb/>to have the matter closed in ten days<lb/>after Mr. Hartley and Mr Hay were here.<lb/>but the reason now given is that the<lb/>contract had some slight informality<lb/>about it. If that is the case, why not in<lb break="no"/>form the company of the fact, that they<lb/>may remedy the evil and the road be<lb/>acknowledged by the Government? All<lb/>I want is fair play. They have not ex<lb break="no"/>tended the same justice to the Wood<lb break="no"/>stock Railway as they have to the other<lb/>for they have paid for the survey of that,<lb/>and, in addition to this, they have paid<lb/>for a second survey which has been made<lb/>on the Dorcaester line, to suit the conve<lb break="no"/>nience of somebody. That being sthe<lb/>case, why do they not pay for the survey<lb/>of the road at Woodstock? But I sup<lb break="no"/>pose while the present Government re<lb break="no"/>main in power, we need not expect any<lb/>justice of that kind. The Woodstock<lb/>company have furnished their bonds and<lb/>have done all the law requires, while no<lb/>such requirements have been made of the<lb/>St. Stephen branch, Western Extension, <lb/>or the Dorcaester line, and no paper ex<lb break="no"/>ist in the office showing that fact. If<lb/>there is any fair play in this, I do not<lb/>understand it.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     There has been a great deal said in re<lb break="no"/>ference to the Government offices not be<lb break="no"/>ing filled up, and in consequence many<lb/>evils have arisen throughout the Prov<lb break="no"/>
        

            <pb n="70" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_070.jpg"/>
         
<fw type="num">70</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 

vince. Take, for instance, the office of<lb/>Solicitor General. The expense incur<lb break="no"/>red in sending law officers to the Cir<lb break="no"/>cuits, although convenient for the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment to aid their friends, has been<lb/>charged upon the public revenue, al<lb break="no"/>though the hon. mover of the amendment<lb/>discharges the duties of the Carleton Cir<lb break="no"/>cuit, yet there are other cases where the <lb/>presence of a law officer was required. <lb/>One of which was connected with a mat<lb break="no"/>ter of sufficient importance to lead to a <lb/>correspondence between the British Min<lb break="no"/>ister at Washington and the Government<lb/>of this Province. The origin of the mat<lb break="no"/>ter was trivial, but the results were im<lb break="no"/>portant, for it has led to a great deal of <lb/>bad feeling along the border of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, besides inflicting a great injustice<lb/>upon one individual, who, by means of it,<lb/>has lost part of his form. One of the <lb/>principal law officers on this occasion, <lb/>who seemed to lead the whole matter,<lb/>was the aid-de-camp of the Lieutenant<lb/>Governor. The Governor rules, and his<lb/>advisers obey, and this is a sample of it.<lb/>The result of this matter was in conse<lb break="no"/>quence of neglect on the part of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Secretary. In consequence of<lb/>informality in the first proceedings taken<lb/>by the Provincial Secretary, and subse<lb break="no"/>quently, the prosecution was abandoned.<lb/>This was an important matter. Connect<lb break="no"/>ed, as it is, with a foreign country, it <lb/>ougt not to have been left in the way<lb/>and manner it was. This shows the want<lb/>of proper law officers of the Crown, and<lb/>a sufficient reason why a Solicitor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral should have been appointed. It<lb/>would save the Government from dis<lb break="no"/>grace, and revent the loss of the public<lb/>revenue. I am glad that the whole mat<lb break="no"/>ter is closed, and I hope that in future the<lb/>like will not occur again.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The elections for York and Westmor<lb break="no"/>land have been brought before the<lb/>House, but they have nothing to do<lb/>with the subject of debate, for the ques<lb break="no"/>tion is, whether the members of the <lb/>Government have discharged their duty. <lb/>I will read a note which I received from<lb/>a farmer in the Country of Carleton :<lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     CARLETON COUNTY, March 9th, 1866. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. C. CONNEL :<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Dear Sir, - I hope you will send me<lb/>the sayings and doings of the House of <lb/>Assembly, this Session. I hope you<lb/>will have a good time while there, and <lb/>that if possible, you will turn out the<lb/>present Government, and put one in<lb/>that will save New Brunswick. You<lb/>have been a good worker in breaking<lb/>up the old nest, and I hope you will<lb/>now put your shoulder to the wheel and<lb/>help turn them out, for we are in jeo<lb break="no"/>pardy.<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <p>I believe that is the opinion of a very<lb/>large majority of the inhabitants of this<lb/>Province, and I know it is of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of Carleton whom I represent. The<lb/>hon. member for Kent (Mr. Caie) told<lb/>us, the other day, that the people in<lb/>Kent were all dissatisfied with the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment. I can tell the Attorney Gen<lb break="no"/>eral that there is one universal feeling<lb/>of dissatisfaction against the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment throughout the Province. Since<lb/>the commencement of this debate the<lb/>eyes of the people of this Province have<lb/>been opened to see the vacillating eon-<lb break="yes"/>duct of the Government They were <lb/>elected to oppose Confederation, and<lb/>
          
            <cb/>
         
they have come down here to propound<lb/>to this House and country that they are<lb/>in favor of Union. This shows their in<lb break="no"/>consistency, and their friends and sup<lb break="no"/>porters in this House, as well as the<lb/>people, can have no confidence in them.<lb/>It is the custom for all Governments in<lb/>other colonies to propound some policy<lb/>at the opening of the Session, in order<lb/>that the House and people may under<lb break="no"/>stand their position, but there was<lb/>nothing of that kind done here last Ses<lb break="no"/>sion. They said there was no time,<lb/>in consequence of the House being<lb/>called together late in the season,<lb/>and a delegation had to be appoint<lb break="no"/>ed to go to England : but I exxpexted at<lb/>the meeting of this House the policy of<lb/>the Government would have been enun<lb break="no"/>ciated, and the result of their mission to<lb/>England made known in this debate,<lb/>neither of which have we been favored<lb/>with. It is my opinion, that if we can<lb break="no"/>not get a better scheme we should take<lb/>the Quebec Scheme. I am not pledged<lb/>for or against my scheme. If a better<lb/>can be got I shall be pleased to have it<lb/>for we want a union and must have it.<lb/>We have heard something about being<lb/>reduced to our original elements by a <lb/>dissolution of the House, but these<lb/>ythings I think will have no influence. <lb/>The Attorney General said he would go<lb/>for a scheme of union containing the<lb/>principle of representation by popula<lb break="no"/>tion, provided there were checks to<lb/>counter balance it. If the Government<lb/>have abandoned the principes upon<lb/>which they were elected they are de<lb break="no"/>ceiving their friends and supporters in<lb/>this House, and throughout the country,<lb/>by not bringing before the House their<lb/>policy on this great question, in com<lb break="no"/>parison with which all other questions<lb/>should sink into insignificance.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Surveyor General gives his at<lb break="no"/>tention to his office, and when any mat<lb break="no"/>ter is brought under his notice, so-far<lb/>as I am aware, he gives proper atten<lb break="no"/>tion to it ; but as to the evils existing<lb/>in the office, it appears he has not the <lb/>conception of mind to eradicate and re<lb break="no"/>form them. The office requires an <lb/>over-hauling and re-organizing, for its<lb/>entire arrangements are a disgrace to<lb/>the country, but the capacity of the pre<lb break="no"/>sent Surveyor General seems unequal<lb/>to his position. It is not my intention<lb/>to go into the question in reference to<lb/>the sale of lands to Mr. Gibson, for he<lb/>has got those lands, and is entitled to<lb/>them by law, if their was a fair compe<lb break="no"/>tition in their purchase, but if I had<lb/>been in the Government I would not<lb/>have done as they did. I would not<lb/>have come down and found fault with<lb/>the Tilley Government. I would have<lb/>come down in a manly, straight-for<lb break="no"/>ward way, and said, we found the sur<lb break="no"/>vey was made and we sold the land<lb/>(Mr. Smith - It was a charge made<lb/>against us.) We said the House and<lb/>country understood that the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment ordered the survey. There<lb/>has been a great deal of talk in regard<lb/>to giving up those lands. I think the <lb/>Government are chargeable in not<lb/>standing by their friends (Mr. Smith<lb/>- it is pretty hard to tell who they are.)<lb/>Mr. Gibson is one of them at all events, <lb/>and the Government should have re<lb break="no"/>quired Mr. Gibson to give up his three<lb/>years license or withheld the sale, and <lb/>they had the power to do so ; as it was,<lb/>it was not a fair competition. The<lb/>Crown Land Office requires over-haul<lb break="no"/>
           

            <cb/>
       

     ing. I have received a great many 
     <lb/>communications, particularly during the <lb/>last year, requesting me to communi<lb break="no"/>cate with the office, for the interest of<lb/>the back settlers through the country,<lb/>in order to bring under the notice of<lb/>the Surveyor General the grievances<lb/>that exist. If the Surveyor General <lb/>had investigated the matter, all these<lb/>communications might have been saved,<lb/>and the people have been satisfied. I will<lb/>mention a case that has occurred in the <lb/>settlements of Knowlsville, Johnswille<lb/>and Glasgow, in the County of Carleton.<lb/>A vast number of people place in my<lb/>hand the certificate from the commis<lb break="no"/>sioner, that the work and settlement had<lb/>been done, and all the requirements of<lb/>the law complied with. I brought the<lb/>the case of some twenty of these under<lb/>the notice of the Government, and the<lb/>reply to my application was, that in<lb/>most of the cases $3 still remained due,<lb/>and required to be paid. I communi<lb break="no"/>cated with the commissioner to know the<lb/>authority under which he acted, and re<lb break="no"/>ceived the following reply :<lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "In answer to yours of the 4th of     
     <lb/>January, 1866, I beg to state that all the<lb/>parties in the list have done work to<lb/>the amount of $57, and paid $3 com<lb break="no"/>mission. I have the authority of the<lb/>Deputy for so doing."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     In answer to an enquiry made of 
     <lb/>Mr. Gowan, dated July, 1864, he made<lb/>the following statement : "The com<lb break="no"/>mission is included in the $60, viz. $57<lb/>in work and $3 in cash ;" and I have<lb/>forwarded the said letter to him, the<lb/>only satisfaction I could get from the<lb/>department was, a reference to the<lb/>rules and regulations of the office. <lb/>With reference to the rules of 1861, es<lb break="no"/>tablishing the mode of settlement and<lb/>terms of payment applicable to settlers<lb/>under the Labor Act, here in the face of<lb/>these regulations we have the authority<lb/>of the department to violate them. It<lb/>is true since this debate has commenced,<lb/>the Surveyor General has informed me,<lb/>that all cases up to November, 1865, oc<lb break="no"/>curring where $57 have been paid and<lb/>$3 commission, the grants will issue. <lb/>There is a direct violation of their own<lb/>rules and regulations, which shows to the <lb/>country the outrageous manner in which<lb/>the proceedings of that office is conduct<lb break="no"/>ed, and the incompetency of its head. In<lb/>a blustering way he endeavored to fix<lb/>some charge upon me with reference to<lb/>my knowledge of the annulment of the<lb/>order, that no lands should be sold unless<lb/>for actual settlement. I can state that,<lb/>for this hour, no communication of the an<lb break="no"/>nulment of that order has been made to<lb/>the deputies throughout this Province,<lb/>and the only information they have is<lb/>through the public Press, which showed<lb/>its disapprobation of the conduct of the<lb/>head of the department. But the Sur<lb break="no"/>veyor General, in excuse, exhibits to this<lb/>House a petition signed by myself and <lb/>some others, in October last, in order to<lb/>show that I knew of the annulment of the<lb/>order, and that I should have made it<lb/>known, particularly to Mr. Harley, who<lb/>was the deputy. To my certain know<lb break="no"/>ledge Mr. Hartley stated to me, after the <lb/>exposure in the public Press in Decem<lb break="no"/>ber, that it was the first intimation that <lb/>he had of the repeal of the order. I hap<lb break="no"/>pened to go into the Crown Land Office<lb/>previous to my making the application <lb/>and it was intimated to me, by Mr.<lb/>
          

            <pb n="71" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-28_Page_071.jpg"/>
           

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  <fw type="num">71</fw> 


     Inches, that the order had been re<lb break="no"/>pealed, the grants would issue 
     <lb/>
     to all previous sales under the order. 
     <lb/>
     This was the way the business of the of<lb break="no"/>fice was managed. They sold land under 
     <lb/>
     certain conditions. and then violated 
     <lb/>
     them. Why did they not extend some 
     <lb/>
     of these privileges to the Hartley sales? 
     <lb/>
     They forgot who were required to per<lb break="no"/>form the conditions of the law to the let<lb break="no"/>ter, and received no grants. The inat<lb break="no"/>tention of the Commissioner, or the want 
     <lb/>
     of knowledge in reference to the matter, 
     <lb/>
     has caused persons a great inconvenience. 
     <lb/>
     I know it from the many calls I have to 
     <lb/>
     attend to in these matters and my com<lb break="no"/>munications to the Crown Land Office 
     <lb/>
     will show a further evidence in regard to 
     <lb/>
     it. I will mention a case where a grant 
     <lb/>
     was issued to a man who actually does 
     <lb/>
     not own the land and, four or five others 
     <lb/>
     have been kept out of their grants where 
     <lb/>
     the labor had been performed, within my 
     <lb/>
     personal knowledge, for the last three or 
     <lb/>
     four years. This matter was brought 
     <lb/>
     under the notice of the Surveyor General 
     <lb/>
     during the last Session. I had to take 
     <lb/>
     the matter in hand myself, and get a sur<lb break="no"/>vey, and have now the returns in my 
     <lb/>
     hand for the purpose of being handed in 
     <lb/>
     to the Crown Land Office, which being 
     <lb/>
    done I am informed the grants will be 
     <lb/>issued. If this is the way one of the 
     <lb/>most important departments, affecting 
     <lb/>every settler throughout the Province, is 
     <lb/>to be managed—it the head of the depart<lb break="no"/>ment is incompetent - it is a charge 
     <lb/>against the Government, and I hope by a 
     <lb/>vote of this House a change will take 
     <lb/>place, and a thorough reformation be es<lb break="no"/>tablished that office. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The Surveyor General attacked me in a 
     <lb/>
     rather defiant manner, in reference to a 
     <lb/>
     case —, that I did not inform some<lb break="no"/>body that I knew this Order of Council<lb/>
    was rescinded. ( <persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. Botsford</persName>—I did not, 
     <lb/>I made no charge against him. It was in 
     <lb/>reply to a charge made against me in re<lb break="no"/>ference to a petition, he said it was not 
     <lb/>known, and I said he knew it.) I made 
     <lb/>no charge. I said there appeared to be 
     <lb/>some mis-apprehension in reference to 
     <lb/>something in connection with Mr. Hart<lb break="no"/>ley. ( <persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. Botsford</persName> - I made no charge 
     <lb/>against Mr. Hartley. I asked his hon. 
     <lb/>colleague (Mr. Lindsay) who the deputy 
     <lb/>was that stated the land could not be 
     <lb/>sold, and he replied, Mr. Hartley. I was 
     <lb/>replying when he ( <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. Connell</persName> rose up 
     <lb/>and stated it was not known. I replied 
     <lb/>that he knew of it, and others knew of<lb/>it.) I stood up for the purpose of remov<lb break="no"/>ing an erroneous impression so far as Mr. 
     <lb/>Hartley was concerned. Mr. Hartley knew 
     <lb/>nothing in reference to this order being 
     <lb/>rescinded until it was remarked upon by 
     <lb/>the papers in St. John He said he had 
     <lb/>seen in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Telegraph</hi>, that there was a 
     <lb/>great difficulty about the Government 
     <lb/>selling land, and that the order of Coun<lb break="no"/>cil had been rescinded. I replied I had 
     <lb/>known that some time ago. He said 
     <lb/>that this was the first he had heard of it. 
     <lb/>The Surveyor General knows that was 
     <lb/>Mr. Hartley's position, and that was the 
     <lb/>reason I made these observations  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The debate was then adjourned until 
     <lb/>
     to-morrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     T. P. D. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2018-03-07, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


            <!--<milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     THURSDAY, MARCH 27. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The House went into Committee of the<lb/>Whole (Mr. Scovil in the chair) in fur<lb break="no"/>ther consideration of a Bill to abolish the<lb/>property qualification of members to serve<lb/>in the General Assembly of the Province.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>MR. COSTIGAN explained that the<lb/>object of the Bill was to do away with<lb/>the law that now existed. That demand<lb break="no"/>ed that candidates offering to serve in<lb/>the General Assembly of the Province<lb/>should possess real estate to the value of<lb/>£300. the true principle, which it was<lb/>the object of the Bill to establish, was, that<lb/>the choice of representatives should be<lb/>left to the constituents. The abolish<lb break="no"/>ment of the property qualification would<lb/>give them a freer choice, and this would<lb/>be better for the interests of the country.  
     <lb/>As the law now stood, a man might offer 
     <lb/>to serve in whom all the electors of a 
     <lb/>County, save one were perfectly willing 
     <lb/>to confide, and this one man might object 
     <lb/>to his election, and say he had no pro<lb break="no"/>perty qualification. Mr. Contigan then 
     <lb/>quoted from a despatch to Mr. Dundas, 
     <lb/>Governor of Prince Edward's Island, from 
     <lb/>the late Secretary of the Colonies, on the 
     <lb/>subject of election of the Legislative 
     <lb/>Council, in which the Duke of New<lb break="no"/>castle said, that the property qualifica<lb break="no"/>tion ought to be possessed not by the can<lb break="no"/>didate, but by the voter. In Great Britain 
     <lb/>no property  qualification was now re<lb break="no"/>quired of candidates to the Imperial Par<lb break="no"/>liament. With regard to the law in the 
     <lb/>Province, he did not see why it should be 
     <lb/>allowed to stand on the Statute Book, for 
     <lb/>it was not carried out. It gave to the 
     <lb/>man having no property qualifications, but 
     <lb/>who did not respect the law, and advan<lb break="no"/>tage over the honest unqualified man who<lb/>did.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL said<lb/>he had always opposed this Bill. Though<lb/>he could not deny that the property quali<lb break="no"/>fication had been abolished in England.<lb/>He did not see that was a conclusive ar<lb break="no"/>gument for abolishing it in the PRovince.<lb/>the principle of safety and conservatism<lb/>required that the men who sent represen<lb break="no"/>tatives to the Legislature should be pos<lb break="no"/>sessed of property. If the electors sent<lb/>a representative who had no property,<lb/>would he be a safe man to whom to sub<lb break="no"/>mit the protection of their property? He<lb/>did not think that it was too much to de<lb break="no"/>mand that all men who proposed to serve<lb/>as representatives in the House of Assem<lb break="no"/>bly should be possessed of real estate to <lb/>the amount of £300.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>MR. NEEDHAM said that the were<lb/>some great principles connected with the<lb/>principle of the Bill that ought to be un<lb break="no"/>derstood. He would take the present op<lb break="no"/>portunity to announce his political faith.<lb/>
               <lb/>He wished the people to understand that<lb/>he had not been born a politician -\- the<lb/>principles he maintained had not grown<lb/>up with him from his boyhood, but<lb/>had their commencement about the year<lb/>1847 and 48. Ever since th etime he had<lb/>been politically regenerated, he could say<lb/>that he had never fallen away from poli<lb break="no"/>tical grace. He entertained the same<lb/>principles now as those he had learnt in<lb/>the years 1847 and '8. In making use of<lb/>bold expressions of opinion, men were<lb/>often misunderstood, but the opinion he<lb/>was about to utter he had before express<lb break="no"/>ed on the floors of the House and outside<lb/>its walls. He did believe in the princi<lb break="no"/>ple of universal suffrage, and he would<lb/>tell the House why he believed in ti. In<lb/>this deliberative Assembly where they le-<lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>

    
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     gislated on the lives, property and liber<lb break="no"/>ties of the people -\- he wished to say that<lb/>
     that principle was consonant with the 
     <lb/>spirit of the British Constitution, and he<lb/>wished that opinion put on record. When<lb/>he spoke of universal suffrage -\- he meant<lb/>that every man in teh community who<lb/>paid taxes had a right to vote, and to have<lb/>a say in the legislation of the country.<lb/>They were there to legislate on the lives,<lb/>liberties, and properties of teh people <lb break="no"/>and the most abject man, he meant abject,<lb/>not in spirit, but in purse, who paid<lb/>the least amount of taxes had as much right<lb/>to have a voice in the choice of a repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives as the richest. Liberty was<lb/>dear to every man -\- the live of man was<lb/>not to be measured by the reiches he pos<lb break="no"/>sessed, it was as precious to the man who<lb/>had scarcely a rag to cover him -\- as to<lb/>him who was clothed in purple and fine<lb/>linen; was not life to Lazarus the beggar<lb/>as dear as life was to the rich man Dives?<lb/>He said that the most abject man in con<lb break="no"/>dition had the right to an equal voice in<lb/>the legislature of his country with the<lb/>most powerful.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     He would call the attention of his breth<lb break="no"/>ren of the law to a statement made by<lb/>Sir William Blackstone in his commen<lb break="no"/>taries -\- a man whose dicta was never dis<lb break="no"/>sented from. It was perfectly consonant<lb/>he said, with the spirit of the British Con<lb break="no"/>stitution, that every man who paid taxes<lb/>should have a vote, and the time would<lb/>come when that principle would be carried<lb/>out -\- might ws not always right. The<lb/>Parliament of England when it established<lb/>property qualification for members, gave as<lb/>a reason why a certain class of men ought<lb/>to be excluded from the right of voting, that<lb/>they were men of so mean a situation in<lb/>life that they had no will or mind of their<lb/>own. If Sir William Blackstone had lived<lb/>..... day, he would know that it was not<lb/>always the poor man who wa influenced<lb/>by the will of others, or who was most<lb/>corrupt. He had seen a poor man in<lb/>one of the back settlements of York<lb/>County, whose barns and house had been<lb/>swept away by fire, who had solicited and<lb/>received donations to help him to repair his<lb/>loss; he had seen that man at the polls<lb/>offered $10 to vote against a candidate<lb/>whose principles he believed in; but,<lb/>though homeless, barnless and shelter-<lb break="yes"/>less, he turned away from the proffered<lb/>bribe and voted as his judgement and his <lb/>conscience dictated. And that was a <lb/>specimen of a York elector. He had as<lb break="no"/>signed the reason why the property quali<lb break="no"/>fication was at first demanded, but when<lb/>Blackstone said that it was consonant<lb/>with the spirit of the British Constitution<lb/>that every man who was taxed should<lb/>have the right to vote, then, he said,<lb/>policy ought to give way to absolute right.<lb/>It was the Legislature that gave the peo<lb break="no"/>ple the right to vote. But he held that<lb/>it was the inalienable right of every man<lb/>born into the world to enjoy life and lib-<lb break="maybe"/>tery. Go back to the most ancient times,<lb/>and they would find that every man had<lb/>the same right as he came from the<lb/>hand of God. Then the weakest and<lb/>most abject man was equal in these re<lb break="no"/>spects with the richest and strongest.<lb/>That was the original stae, and the same<lb/>rights that existed then existed now.<lb/>That inalienable right to life and liberty,<lb/>and to have a voice in the Government,<lb/>had never been given up by the people.<lb/>The, if the right to vote had never been <lb/>given up, there was no reason why they<lb/>should be asked to give the people the<lb/>right; and the people had the abso-<lb break="maybe"/>
            </p>-->
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>