<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-06-30"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-06-30">30 June 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="51" to="57"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_051.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_052.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_053.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_054.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_055.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_056.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_057.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_051">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_051.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_052">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_052.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_053">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_053.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_054">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_054.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_055">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_055.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_056">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_056.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_057">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_057.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="51" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_051.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">51</fw> 
  

   
            <head rendition="simple:right">
     SATURDAY, June 30. 
     <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>Progress was reported on a Bill intro<lb break="no"/>duced by <persName ref="pers:WILM1">Hon. Mr. WILMOT</persName> entitled<lb/>"A Bill to authorise the extension of<lb/>St. John Street."<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> asked if the<lb/>Contingent Committee had made any ar<lb break="no"/>rangements for directing the Debates<lb/>Last year they had given at the rate of<lb/>four dollars for each member; as this was<lb/>to be a short Session, he did not think<lb/>the House was willing to give so much.<lb/>He had not yet given any order in regard<lb/>to it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SUTT1">Mr. SUTTON</persName> said the Chairman of<lb/>the Committee was absent or they might<lb/>take the matter into consideration. No<lb break="no"/>thing had been done yet.<lb/>
            </p>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">ADJOURNED DEBATE ON MR. FISCHER'S<lb/>RESOLUTION REGARDING THE APPOINT<lb break="no"/>MENT OF DELEGATES.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> resumed - I complained<lb/>yesterday of the way the Provincial Sec<lb break="no"/>retary met this question. I think his<lb/>Speech was not of that character which<lb/>we had a right to expect from the posi<lb break="no"/>tion he occupies. His object appeared to<lb/>be to create prejudice against my stand<lb break="no"/>ing and position. He charged me with<lb/>having brow-beat members. I then sta<lb break="no"/>ted distinctly that it was not true. I re<lb break="no"/>peat that it is a charge unfounded in fact.<lb/>But if it were so, what has it to do with<lb/>the question? Is not such language un<lb break="no"/>dignified when men's judgements are be<lb/>ing appealed to, and not their prejudices.<lb/>I consider that it was unfair, for I made<lb/>not attack on him or any other member of<lb/>the House. I felt impressed with the im<lb break="no"/>portance of the occasion, and having cer<lb break="no"/>tain objections to the Scheme, I thought<lb/>it right to lay them before the House. If<lb/>they were entitled to any consideration,<lb/>the Government should accord that con<lb break="no"/>sideration to them. The Provincial Sec<lb break="no"/>retary has enlarged upon the beauties of<lb/>the Scheme, and I repeat: are we prepa<lb break="no"/>red to accept the Quebec Scheme? Sev<lb break="no"/>eral members of the House have stated<lb/>they are not prepared to do so, because<lb/>they have objections to it. Only two or<lb/>three gentlemen have stated they were in<lb/>favor of it. When Mr. Ryan stated he<lb/>was in favor of the Quebec Scheme - <lb/>( <persName ref="pers:RYAN1">Mr. Ryan</persName>: - I said I was in favor of a<lb/>better Scheme, if we could get it; but if<lb/>not, I am in favor of the Quebec Scheme,)<lb/>if he has a good bargain now, why does<lb/>he want any more. It is of the most vi<lb break="no"/>tal importance, in view of futrue time,<lb/>that in adopting a measure of Union, it<lb/>should be so prepared that it would work<lb/>harmoniously, and do justice to every<lb/>portion of the Confederacy, or the<lb/>most disastrous consequences must re<lb break="no"/>sult. We are told that we are to get an<lb/>advantage over Upper Canada, because<lb/>her population increases more rapidly<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
        

     than ours, and she only gets eighty cents 
     <lb/>
     per head on the population of 1861. 
     <lb/>
     That subject would be brought up in the 
     <lb/>
     General Parliament, and it would be said 
     <lb/>
     by the Canadians that New Brunswick 
     <lb/>getting eighty cents per head was un<lb break="no"/>just to their population, and they would<lb/>make a great for their proportion out of<lb/>the public chest. The Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary said I made no objections to the fi<lb break="no"/>nancial affairs in the Scheme. I stated<lb/>that the principle of Union had been de<lb break="no"/>cided by the people, and the object of all<lb/>should be to get as good a Scheme as we<lb/>can. I stated that it would be unjust to<lb/>the people of New Brunswick to have to<lb/>pay their proportion of the expense of<lb/>constructing the Canals to open up the<lb/>Great West. That is part of the finan<lb break="no"/>cial question. Every objection which I<lb/>made the Provincial Secretary seemed to<lb/>think no objection. If the speeches<lb/>made here are read by the politicians of<lb/>Canada, they will sai: how can you ask<lb/>for these alterations? Your Lower<lb/>House approved of the Scheme because<lb/>they have sent you, who thought no al<lb break="no"/>terations were necessary, here to agree<lb/>to the Scheme. The Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary said it was unwise to state the po<lb break="no"/>licy of the Government. When this in<lb break="no"/>formation goes to Canada, will it not<lb/>excite distrust and suspicion there? Is<lb/>it not an extraordinary position for the<lb/>Government to take to say secresy was<lb/>the policy of the Government, lest the<lb/>members of the Legislature in Canada<lb/>would find out what we wanted and de<lb break="no"/>feat their object. The objection to re<lb break="no"/>presentation by population the Provin<lb break="no"/>cial Secretary has failed to answer. He<lb/>was asked why it was that this was in<lb break="no"/>serted:<lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "The number of Members may at 
     <lb/>any time be increased by the General<lb/>Parliament - regard being had to the<lb/>proportionate rights then existing."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     giving the Government the power of in<lb break="no"/>creasing the representation indepent<lb break="no"/>ly of the decimal representation; and he<lb/>passed it over with really no comment at<lb/>all . When we are now to have 194<lb/>members, and an increase every decimal<lb/>period: why should there be a provision<lb/>made to increase the number of members<lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">ad libitum</hi>. This is a most dangerous<lb/>principle, and would be most disasterous<lb/>to us. I put it forward as a proposition<lb/>that you cannot point to any portion of<lb/>the British Empire where the representa<lb break="no"/>tion is by population. When the Bills<lb/>have been before the House to incrase<lb/>the representation of Counties, the Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Secretary has said himself that<lb/>representation by population was not<lb/>right. He has repeatedly stated that it<lb/>was not a correct principle. I oppose it<lb/>as a principle. It is not right as applied<lb/>to a federation or Federal Government,<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
          
under the English system fo Goverment<lb/>where the whole Executive power is<lb/>under the control of the people's repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives. In a Confederation under<lb/>that principle the larger powers often<lb/>over-ride and swallow the less powerful.<lb/>Under the principle of representation by<lb/>population London would be entitled to<lb/>send sixty-five members to the British<lb/>Parliament, about one-tenth of the whole,<lb/>whereas now she only sends sixteen.<lb/>The principle is applied in the United<lb/>States, but they have a salutary and suffi<lb break="no"/>cient check in their Senate. The Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Secretary has advanced no argu<lb break="no"/>ments against the objection I made, that<lb/>we ought to have equal representation in<lb/>the Upper Branch. If he says we have<lb/>more than fair play, the Maratime Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces have one third of the represen<lb break="no"/>tatives; how then can he go to England<lb/>and urge upon the Delegates to modify the<lb/>Scheme in that respect? I believe a<lb/>majority of the members of the House are<lb/>opposed to the reasoning of the Provin<lb break="no"/>cial Secretary on that question. States<lb break="no"/>men should not only look to the passsing<lb/>hour, but they should look to the past,<lb/>and judge of the future as to how any<lb/>measure would practically work. I trust<lb/>the Government will reconsider my ob<lb break="no"/>jections. The Provincial Secretary<lb/>seemed to take the position of an advo<lb break="no"/>cate, and his policy seemed to be to vin<lb break="no"/>dicate himself and show that the Scheme<lb/>contained no defects. He arraigned and<lb/>impugned the report of the Controller of<lb/>Customs. ( <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. Tilley</persName> I said his<lb/>figures were right, but the conclusions<lb/>arrived at by persons outside were not<lb/>reliable.) If he says the report is all<lb/>right I will read a portion of the report.<lb/>( <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. Tilley</persName> then explained that<lb/>some of the calculations were made by<lb/>estimating what revenue certain articles<lb/>would yield if a certain tariff was applied<lb/>to them, and Mr. Smith read a portion of<lb/>the report to prove that our taxation<lb/>would be higher under Confederation<lb/>than at the present, and continue.) The<lb/>Provincial Secretary says that notwith<lb break="no"/>standing Canada has not surplus, Nova<lb/>Scotia no surplus, New Brunswick no<lb/>surplus, we are to have the Inter-colonial<lb/>Railway built. Millions of money are to<lb/>be expended on the Canals. The Hud<lb break="no"/>son Bay Territory is to be purchased and<lb/>our taxes reduced. ( <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. Tilley</persName>, I<lb/>said they would not be increased.) I<lb/>think the Provincial Secretary is mis<lb break="no"/>taken in that, but admitting he is not,<lb/>how is it possible to incur all these ex<lb break="no"/>penses, without increasing our taxes.<lb/>Will he pretend to say that stamp duties,<lb/>on every description of taxation that<lb/>exists in Canada will not be applied to<lb/>us. I believe that the taxes will not only<lb/>be as high as they are now in Canada, but<lb/>they will be much higher if she incurs<lb/>
         

            <pb n="52" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_052.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="num">52</fw>   <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  
  

     these expenses. The Government of   
     <lb/>Canada is driven to the last extremity to<lb/>get money she borrowed last year $2,000,<lb break="no"/>000 and paid seven per cent. for it. We<lb/>have never paid over six per cent. except<lb/>the discount upon our debentures. The<lb/>Secretary has failed to show that our<lb/>finances would be improved by a Union<lb/>with Canada, his financial statement in re<lb break="no"/>gard to this is utterly fallacious. He gives<lb/>Canada the credit of providing for the<lb/>deficiency in the Post Office Depart<lb break="no"/>ment. According to Mr. Odell's report<lb/>the office would be self-sustaining by<lb/>the addition of a small tax upon news<lb break="no"/>papers, and this will be put upon them<lb/>after we go into Union. He says we<lb/>gain by not having to pay so large a<lb/>proportion for the construction of the<lb/>Inter-Colonial Railway, as we would<lb/>have to do by a former agreement. I<lb/>opposed that law, which has not ex<lb break="no"/>pired, giving 3 1/2 twelfths of the money<lb/>required for the construction of the<lb/>Inter-Colonial Railway, because I con<lb break="no"/>sidered that Nova Scotia in that adjust<lb break="no"/>ment had the advantage of us, for she<lb/>is a richer country, has a larger popu<lb break="no"/>lation, and there would be the terminus<lb/>of the road. I am not opposed to Rail<lb break="no"/>roads, but I am opposed to recklessly<lb/>running a country in debt. The Pro<lb break="no"/>vincial Secretary is not prudent and<lb/>cautious enough, he was willing to do<lb/>it without any hesitation at all. I said<lb/>the benefits to be derived from the con<lb break="no"/>struction of that road would not be<lb/>equivalent to the expenditure, and I<lb/>resigned my seat as Attorney General<lb/>in consequence. When the Provincial<lb/>Secretary accuses me of not bringing<lb/>forward great measures, I want him to<lb/>point out what great measure he has<lb/>brought forward that has not ended<lb/>in smoke, like the Inter-Colonial Railway<lb/>and the Prohibitory Liquor Law. He<lb/>says my talents are for destruction and<lb/>not for construction. Is this to be ap<lb break="no"/>plied to me because I pointed out the<lb/>objections to this scheme that suggested<lb/>themselves to my mind and opposed the<lb/>Inter-Colonial Railway? I think it is<lb/>wring to make these charges. He says<lb/>that when they prepared that scheme<lb/>he saw it would be such an advntage<lb/>to New Brunswick, that he thought the<lb/>people would embrace it at once. This<lb/>proves that his judgement is not reliable.<lb/>he told us after his return from Canada<lb/>that the scheme would not be submitted<lb/>to the people until it had been first<lb/>debated on the floors of the House. He<lb/>told the people of Carleton that the<lb/>matter would be submitted to the<lb/>House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> - I stated there, as<lb/>I did at the Institute in St. John, that the<lb/>measure would not be submitted to the<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
         

     Legislature until and election hd taken 
     <lb/>place.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - Will you deny the state<lb break="no"/>ment which appeared in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Morning<lb/>News</hi> that you had stated to the people of<lb/>Carleton that before a dissolution took<lb/>place the matter would be submitted to<lb/>the House of Assembly and discussed?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> - The report was 
     <lb/>not a correct one. My statement was in<lb/>answer to a question asked by Mr.<lb/>Macshane.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - That proves how diffi<lb break="no"/>cult it is to understand his statements.<lb/>I think he wanted to evade Mr. Mac<lb break="no"/>shane. Will the Secretary undertake to<lb/>state distinctly that the Government did<lb/>not come to a decision not to have a<lb/>dissolution?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> - I stated so. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - Why then did the elec<lb break="no"/>tion take place in Northumberland?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> - I stated that in 
     <lb/>the first place we thought we would meet<lb/>the House, and at that time we issued<lb/>the writ for that election, but subsequent<lb break="no"/>ly we changed our policy.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - That shows their incon<lb break="no"/>sistency; they determined first to meet<lb/>the House, and then immediately after<lb break="no"/>wards to dissolve it. It was an act of<lb/>tyranny for them to dissolve the House<lb/>in mid-winter upon a question of such<lb/>importance to the country. If the day<lb/>appointed for holding the elections had<lb/>been stormy, men who had to travel thirty<lb/>or forty miles would not have been able<lb/>to have got to the polls. Vast numbers<lb/>of the electors were engaged in lumber<lb break="no"/>ing operations at that season fo the<lb/>year, and could not vote at all. The<lb/>people should have had time to give a<lb/>calm consideration to such a great ques<lb break="no"/>tion. The Government dissolved the<lb/>House because they expected to carry<lb/>the elections, but they were disappoint<lb break="no"/>ed. Short as the time was for the<lb/>people to consider the scheme, they<lb/>would not submit it to them, because<lb/>official etiquette forbade its being pub<lb break="no"/>lished until it was submitted to the eye<lb/>of the Queen, and we first received it<lb/>from Prince Edward Island. It has<lb/>been said that the Queen and British<lb/>Government were in favor of this<lb/>scheme, and this was given as a reason<lb/>why we should adopt it. They have<lb/>rung changes upon it, that Her Majesty<lb/>the Queen wanted the consummation of<lb/>this scheme of Union. This was pros<lb break="no"/>trating the Queen's name. We know<lb/>that in the House of Commons no man<lb/>dare make use of the Queen's name,<lb/>for it is a breach of Parliamentary rule.<lb/>The Queen can do no wrong, and her<lb/>name can be identified with no party,<lb/>She is ready to award the palm to those<lb/>who win the victory. The Queen re<lb break="no"/>commends the "Reform Bill" but in<lb/>
     

            <cb/>
          

     the discussion upon that bill it was not 
     <lb/>used as an argument that the Queen<lb/>wanted it passed. Although she spoke<lb/>of it she only spoke of the will of her min<lb break="no"/>istry. Suppose the Queen did not want<lb/>Confederation; with all her virtues she<lb/>is but a woman, and what value would<lb/>her judgment be regarding a country<lb/>she never saw. What do the British<lb/>Ministry know about this country? If<lb/>they had the same means of knowledge<lb/>that we have concerning it I would value<lb/>their judgement. There is not a man in<lb/>the British Ministry that has ever been<lb/>in this country, and the people of Eng<lb break="no"/>land know little about it. They look<lb/>upon it as a political matter for they see<lb/>the necessities of Canada, and they know<lb/>that some scheme must be devised or<lb/>that country would be in the throes of re<lb break="no"/>bellion. When we are asked to ignore our<lb/>own judgment because the Ministry of<lb/>England, who are men of great intellect,<lb/>learning and erudition, are in favor of it<lb/>I say their judgment in this matter is<lb/>no better than ours. The people of<lb/>England, we are told, want it too. We<lb/>asked Mr. Cardwell if it was not be0<lb/>cause they assumed that the taxation<lb/>upon them would cease for this portion<lb/>of the Empire. Mr. Cardwell said this<lb/>was true, but he was not prepared to<lb/>admit that this was the only reason why<lb/>they wanted it, but he acknowledged it<lb/>to be one of the leading reasons, and he<lb/>acknowledged the force of many of the<lb/>objections. The people all seemed to<lb/>think that it was to be a Legislative<lb/>Union, and when it was explained to<lb/>them that there wre to be six seperate<lb/>Parliaments they seemed to be aston<lb break="no"/>ished, and said it was objectionable and<lb/>wrong. The scheme has been prepared<lb/>with reference to the difficulties of Ca<lb break="no"/>nada which have existed for the last fif<lb break="no"/>teen years in regard to representation<lb/>by population. In 1841 and Act of Union<lb/>was passed to unite the two Canadas<lb/>under one Government, each to have an<lb/>equal number of representatives. Lower<lb/>Canada had then three or four hundred<lb/>thousand population more than Upper<lb/>Canada. If the principle of represen<lb break="no"/>tation by population is right now it was<lb/>right then. Mr. George Brown is the<lb/>person who has been advocating this<lb/>principle, and it has been the apple of<lb/>discord between the two Canadas. Up<lb break="no"/>per Canada has increased largely in<lb/>population and wishes an incrased<lb/>number of representatives, and this dif<lb break="no"/>ficulty has been increasing until the<lb/>while machinery of Government has<lb/>come to a dead lock. The scheme is<lb/>deficient in not providing some triunal<lb/>to appeal to in the event of a conflict be<lb break="no"/>tween the General Government and the<lb/>Local Legislature. The Prov. Sec.<lb/>seems to think that the General Govern<lb break="no"/>
      

            <pb n="53" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_053.jpg"/>
           
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY 1866.</fw>    <fw type="num">53</fw> 


     ment should determine what out rights 
     <lb/>are. Although they might be disposed<lb/>to do justice, it would be the decision of<lb/>a political tribunal, and their decision,<lb/>though right, would not be satisfactory.<lb/>I have no desire to prolong this debate<lb/>I feel that Confederation isa fixed fact<lb/>so far as the people have the power, but<lb/>I consider it my duty to state my objec<lb break="no"/>tions to the scheme, and his is made the<lb/>subject of a telegram published in large<lb/>letters in yesterday's <hi rendition="simple:italic">Telegraph</hi>: "Smith<lb/>speaking against tie. He objects to<lb/>everything and offers and amendment.<lb/>Tilley meets him and crushes him."<lb/>I do not think I am annihilated yet,<lb/>neither am I chargeable with speaking<lb/>against time, and no hon. member can<lb/>sustain such a charge.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> - My hon. friend spoke 
     <lb/>on an important point, that was in regard<lb/>to the respective Colonies having no right<lb/>of appeal. I should liek to know his<lb/>views, I thought the Governor General<lb/>presided over all, and the appeal was to<lb/>him.<lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - I should prefer having<lb/>judicial tribunal composed of Judges, and<lb/>they might make it a Court of Appeal, for<lb/>all the local Legislatures. I would not<lb/>appeal to the Governor at all or his Coun<lb break="no"/>cil, because it is a matter that requires to<lb/>be interpreted the same as other contracts.<lb/>we ought to have the best judicial minds<lb/>in the country to determine such dis<lb break="no"/>putes. I suggest this in all fairness. I<lb/>suppose Canada would be willing to con<lb break="no"/>cede this unless she feels that she has the<lb/>power and means to exercise it arbitrari<lb break="no"/>ly, and si going to hold the Local Gov<lb break="no"/>ernments in the palm of her hand. I<lb/>shall call attention to some of the facts<lb/>connected with the resignation of the late<lb/>Government. The Prov. Sec. takes the<lb/>opportunity, feeling he is addressing a<lb/>sympathetic audience, to make an<lb/>attack upon me and the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. I shall feel it my duty to vin<lb break="no"/>dicate myself so far as I can. I chal<lb/>lenge him to point to any act of our<lb/>administration that will not bear the light<lb/>of day - to point to a single act of mis<lb break="no"/>appropriation or embezzelment of the<lb/>public funds, or an wilful act of wrong<lb/>done. I challenge him to a strict en<lb break="no"/>quiry. It is well enough to say the con<lb break="no"/>duct of the late Government was such as<lb/>to destroy confidence. I deny it. There<lb/>were charges brought against us, but the<lb/>House felt that we had been guilty of no<lb/>wrong, and had committed no act of <hi rendition="simple:italic">mis<lb break="no"/>feasance</hi> or <hi rendition="simple:italic">mal-feasance</hi>. We pled<lb/>guilty to an act of omission in allowing<lb/>the export duty law to expire. We came<lb/>o the House the first day of April, and<lb/>the law expired the first of May. The<lb/>Provincial Secretary was more to blame<lb/>than any member of the Government, for<lb/>it was his duty to have know that it<lb/>

            <cb/>
        

     was about to expire, and communicated 
     <lb/>the fact to his successor. If he knew of<lb/>it he was very culpable indeed, for it<lb/>would not injure the Government, but<lb/>would injure the country. The coun<lb break="no"/>try placed him in a position of power and<lb/>honor, and it was his duty in justice to<lb/>the people to make it known. We did<lb/>not when leaving the Government appoint<lb/>a Magistrate or appropriate a dollar out<lb/>of the public chest. We had a most<lb/>determined and reckless opposition aided<lb/>by the Provincial Secretary, who was they<lb/>forty-second member, and knew every<lb break="no"/>thing that was going on. The Governor<lb/>consulted with the opposition, which it<lb/>was wrong for him to do, for every Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment is entitled to have the confidence<lb/>of the Governor, and he should know no<lb/>other man so far as the constitution is<lb/>concerned. This is a right that belongs<lb/>to the people, and the popoel were insulted<lb/>by the Governor when he took the advice<lb/>of the opposition. The people delegate<lb/>to the Government certain powers, and<lb/>we were entitled to all the privileges inci<lb break="no"/>dent to our position, which were guaran<lb break="no"/>teed to us by the constitution. When<lb/>the Governor consulted with the opposi<lb break="no"/>tion he violated the constitution and the<lb/>people have sustained him, but I believe<lb/>the time will come when they will see<lb/>their error. The time that the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor Manners-Sutton dissolved the<lb/>House the people ignored the constitu<lb break="no"/>tional question, but in less than twelve<lb/>months they asserted their constitutional<lb/>rights and maintained them. The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor sent for Mr. Mitchell to come to<lb/>Government house before the House met<lb/>and never communicated that fact to the<lb/>Government, and I think it was resolved<lb/>then to have a dissolution. The PRovincial<lb/>Secretary entered the political campaign,<lb/>and I think told the people that the House<lb/>would never meet.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> - We intended to 
     <lb/>petition the Governor and get a dissolu<lb break="no"/>tion.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - Why did you not do it?<lb/>I can prove he said the House would ne<lb break="no"/>ver meet. Is the Provincial Secretary<lb/>prepared to endorse such conduct as that?<lb/>Is not that back stairs influence. We<lb/>know that every agency was employed to<lb/>win from us our supporters. Offers of<lb/>office were made, and we were misrepre<lb break="no"/>sented in every way in order to overturn<lb/>the Government. It was told that I had<lb/>pledged myself and signed the Quebec<lb/>Scheme, a statement willfully false; but<lb/>the Provincial Secretary now repeats the<lb/>statement, and says I was committed to<lb/>the Quebec Scheme.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> - I put it in this<lb/>way: If the hon. member learned from<lb/>Mr. galt and Mr. Howland, when he was<lb/>at Washington, that no change could be<lb/>made in the Scheme, and then came back<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
         
and negotiated with His Excellency con<lb break="no"/>cerning Union, he would be said to be in<lb/>favor of the Quebec Scheme.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - This is one of his eva<lb break="no"/>sions.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> - I rise to order.<lb/>There is no evasion about it. It is par<lb break="no"/>liamentary that when a a member, rising in<lb/>his place, makes a statement, it is to be<lb/>taken. If he says it is an evasion, he is<lb/>out of order.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - I say it was an evasion<lb/>of the great point in the question, and is<lb/>unfounded in fact. He must have seen<lb/>in the correspondence between the late<lb/>Government and the Governor that I did<lb/>not commit myself to Union or the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Scheme.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILM1">Mr. WILMOT</persName> - I do not know the<lb/>meaning of the Speech then.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - The Speech says: "I<lb/>have received Her Majesty's commands<lb/>to communicate to your a correspondence<lb/>on the affairs of British North America,<lb/>which has taken place between Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's principle Secretary of State for the<lb/>Colonies and the Governor General of<lb/>Canada; and I am further directed to<lb/>express to you the strong and deliberate<lb/>opinion of Her Majesty's Government,<lb/>that it is an object much to be desired<lb/>that all the British North American Col<lb break="no"/>onies should agree to unite in one Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment." There is not one singel word<lb/>in that Speech which attaches the slight<lb break="no"/>est responsibility to the Governor's Min<lb break="no"/>istry. The Governor himself admitted<lb/>that point; he wished us to put some<lb break="no"/>thing in favor of Union in the Speech,<lb/>and we rejected it. The Provincial Sec<lb break="no"/>retary says we took all the responsibility.<lb/>Before the election he did not speak so<lb/>boldly, and say he was willing to assume<lb/>all the responsibility of the acts of the<lb/>Governor, but he is very bold after the<lb/>battle is fought and the victory won.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> - I did at the hus<lb break="no"/>tings.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - They said it was a mat<lb break="no"/>ter between the Governor and his late<lb/>advisers, and they had nothing to do<lb/>with it. I believe His Excellency's Ad<lb break="no"/>visers wanted to shirk the responsibility,<lb/>but they do assume it. The Governor<lb/>wrote a memorandum, making an attack<lb/>upon his late advisers -- making a charge<lb/>of felony against the for taking a paper<lb/>off the file in the Council Chamber.<lb/>Does the Council assume responsibil<lb break="no"/>ity of that and endorse it? He mae be<lb/>the scoin of the House of Gordon - <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>His Hon, <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">the SPEAKER</persName> - You should<lb/>make no charge against the Governor.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - The House will make<lb/>some indulgence for men who stand here<lb/>defending themselves against a charge<lb/>false and unfounded. This charge was<lb/>made against me when the elections were<lb/>pending, and published in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Royal</hi><lb/>
       

            <pb n="54" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_054.jpg"/>
         

   <fw type="num">54</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 
  

     
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Gazette</hi>, and sent over the country to have<lb/>an effect upon the elections.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Paragraph in the Speech attaches 
     <lb/>
     no constitutional responsibility upon the 
     <lb/>late Government. The answer to the Le<lb break="no"/>gislative Council was the subject of much<lb/>debate. His Excellency wished to put<lb/>something in ti in reference to Union, but<lb/>we said No, and he gave way. They say<lb/>we were committed to Union. I say I<lb/>stated in my place in the late House that<lb/>I was for Union provided we cuold get a<lb/>Union advantageous for this Province,<lb/>for it was my country and I would con<lb break="no"/>sent to no Scheme of Union that did not<lb/>give protection to the rights and interests<lb/>of the people of this Province. This is<lb/>also stated in the correspondence, and in<lb/>all my intercourse with the governor. I<lb/>always maintained the same principle.<lb/>When the Provincial Secretary said that<lb/>I had pledged myself to Union and con<lb break="no"/>sulted my friends upon the subject he did<lb/>not do us justice. I asked him if he knows<lb/>that Mr. Mitchell was sent for a few days<lb/>before the House met. ( <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Mr. Tilley</persName>. I<lb/>do.) The first time he was sent for I was<lb/>in the United States, and not a single<lb/>member of the Government knew that he<lb/>was sent for. The second time he was sent<lb/>for the Provincial Secretary knew of it.<lb/>Does that look as if the Governor was<lb/>acting <hi rendition="simple:italic">bona fide</hi> with us, when he con<lb break="no"/>cealed from us the fact that he had sent<lb/>for a member of the Opposition? Was<lb/>such conduct justifiable? I protested<lb/>from time to time against the Governor's<lb/>acting with the members of the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion. The Provincial Secretary knew<lb/>every thing that was to take place and<lb/>every thing that did take place. When<lb/>the Governor sent for me about twenty<lb/>minutes before three, he had his answer<lb/>prepared for the Legislative Council. I<lb/>told him that he had violated his agree<lb break="no"/>ment. He said he did not know that the<lb/>Legislative Council were going to present<lb/>this address. No said I, but we are not<lb/>responsible for the Legislative Council, he<lb/>did not pretend to deny that he violated<lb/>the arrangement, but tried to justify it.<lb/>He then told me he would give me half-<lb break="yes"/>an-hour to consult my colleagues. I<lb/>told him no, the debate on the want of<lb/>confidence motion was going on, and they<lb/>would have to be in the House; he said<lb/>"he would send the coaches down for<lb/>them to come up." I said they could not<lb/>leave the House. He replied, "I sup<lb break="no"/>pose not;" he then left me but before he<lb/>did so, he said very cooly, if you do not<lb/>like the answer you can relieve your<lb break="no"/>selves of the responsibility. I asked him<lb/>if this was fair. He said had we not bet<lb break="no"/>ter resign, and get out of the way. I<lb/>am informed that the Clerk of the Exe<lb break="no"/>cutive Council was there reay to swear<lb/>in a new Government. It was a propo<lb break="no"/>sition made by this man who boats of his<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
          

     good name, that we should resign the 
     <lb/>seals of office and let our enemies come<lb/>in and take the Government of the coun<lb break="no"/>try, or in other words that we should<lb/>prove recreant to our trust, and to every<lb/>principle of honor which bound us faith<lb break="no"/>fully to fulfil that trust. The PRovincial<lb/>Secretary says I was to consult my<lb/>friends about Union, he knows that is<lb/>not correct. He knows that I was to<lb/>consult my friends about the appointment<lb/>of a committee to take the subject of<lb/>Union into consideration. I said I could<lb/>not pledge myself as to what the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee were to do. They might autho<lb break="no"/>rize another Conference or authorize a<lb/>Conference of the Lower Colonies. I<lb/>ask the Attorney General whether it is<lb/>the intention of the Government to unite<lb/>New Brunswick with Nova Scotia and<lb/>Canada or whether they intend to make<lb/>it a <hi rendition="simple:italic">sine qua non</hi> that all British North <lb/>America shall be united. I made certain ob<lb break="no"/>jections to the Quebec Scheme, viz.:<lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     1. Representation by Population.  
     <lb/>2. That each Province should have an<lb/>equal number of Legislative Councillors.<lb/>3. That the Lower Provinces should be<lb/>exempt from taxation for the Canals of<lb/>Upper Canada, and for the purchase mo<lb break="no"/>ney and other expenditures connected<lb/>with the North West Territory.<lb/>4. That the Revenues collected in the <lb/>Provinces should be for the benefit<lb/>of each Province when collected, ex<lb break="no"/>cept a certain amount to be given for<lb/>the support of the General Government.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     The Governor acknowledged that the 
     <lb/>objections were reasonable, but now he is<lb/>willing to go for the Quebec Scheme. I<lb/>told him that if I went into political ob<lb break="no"/>livion for ever, I would never consent to<lb/>representation by population, unless it<lb/>was neutralized by some checks. This I<lb/>stated to the House several times during<lb/>the last session. I told the Governor<lb/>that I never would go into Union<lb/>blindfold, and trust to luck as to what<lb/>kind of Union we were to get, but I must<lb/>know the terms of the Union proposed<lb/>before I would agree to it. I will be here<lb/>at all times to raise my voice in vindica<lb break="no"/>tion of the people's rights and interests,<lb/>and I plead for them that the Scheme<lb/>may be altered, because I think the coun<lb break="no"/>try is opposed to it. I think it is the in<lb break="no"/>tention of the Government to appoint<lb/>men to proceed to England who were de<lb break="no"/>legates at the Quebec Conference, and as<lb/>the Provincial Secretary has undertaken<lb/>to dissipate every objection made to the<lb/>Scheme, when this is known to the Cana<lb break="no"/>dian delegates they will not consent to<lb/>have it modified. Therefore I ask them<lb/>to send some men who were not at the<lb/>Conference at Quebec. I do not think it<lb/>would be right to take men from the Op<lb break="no"/>position, but they should take men who<lb/>were not committed to the Scheme so<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
          

     that we may get a Scheme under which 
     <lb/>justice would be done to every member<lb/>of the Confederacy.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> - A large portion 
     <lb/>of the speech of my hon. friend is more<lb/>adapted to another time and another oc<lb break="no"/>casion. We are not here to discuss the<lb/>question of the position of the late<lb/>Government in all its bearings.<lb/>He complains that the subject was<lb/>dragged in my the Provincial Secre<lb break="no"/>tary. I think he himself was the first<lb/>aggressor. He objects to the mode of<lb/>carrying this Union measure, and says it<lb/>was aided by the treacherous conduct of<lb/>the Governor. I do not intend to follow<lb/>him in but very few of his objections. He<lb/>referred to our position when the House<lb/>was dissolved by the late Governor<lb/>Manners-Sutton, and compared it with<lb/>the action of His Excellency, but there is<lb/>a great difference between the two. He<lb/>and I were in the Goverment at that<lb/>time, and one ground of our complaint<lb/>was that the Governor had allowed the<lb/>members to return to their ordinary busi<lb break="no"/>ness before the question was raised re<lb break="no"/>garding the Prohibitory Law; had he<lb/>raised an objection to it during the Ses<lb break="no"/>sion of the Legislature, the dissolution<lb/>might have been avoided. His great pa<lb break="no"/>ramount object was to oust his Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and the Prohibitory Liquor Law<lb/>was made the stalking horse to accom<lb break="no"/>plish that object. I am not going to fol<lb break="no"/>low him through the mazes of his corres<lb break="no"/>pondence, but will only say that after<lb/>reading it and reading the speech, I<lb/>came to the conclusion that my hon.<lb/>friend's Government had agreed with the<lb/>Governor upon some question of Union.<lb/>I have not had much to do with the back<lb/>stairs influence to which he has referred.<lb/>From the time the Governor came to the<lb/>Province until I entered this Government,<lb/>I have never had five minutes conversa<lb break="no"/>tion with him upon any political question.<lb/>When I entered the late House my mind<lb/>was made up that no power on earth<lb/>would induce me to assist that Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to carry that Union. I came to the<lb/>House pledged to oppose them. I be<lb break="no"/>lieved they acquired power unfairly, and<lb/>their opposition was an opposition<lb/>to the Government more than an<lb/>opposition to Union. It was not dis<lb break="no"/>cussed fairly before the country. Ev<lb break="no"/>ery man was told that his horses, cows,<lb/>hens, dogs, and every thing he had, would<lb/>be taxed if he went for this Union. Men<lb/>went from hustings to hustings proclaim<lb break="no"/>ing everywhere that we would be taxed to<lb/>death.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - I said taxation would be 
     <lb/>increased. I said nothing about taxing<lb/>dogs and hens.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> - Writings putting 
     <lb/>forth propositions of that kind were cir<lb break="no"/>culated over the Province, and that int<lb break="no"/>
          

            <pb n="55" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_055.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">55</fw> 
 
end men to vote against Union. The el<lb break="no"/>ection in the County of York was the<lb/>commencement of the " silent rumbling"<lb/>that hurled the Government from power,<lb/>and it should that the minds of the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of the country were against them.<lb/>My hon. friend speaks of patriotism and<lb/>party. I say that it was party that deci<lb break="no"/>ded the question of Union, when it was<lb/>first brought before the people ; the peo<lb break="no"/>ple were humbugged and they felt it. I<lb/>believe the Government in November<lb/>last desired to recast this measure of<lb/>Union, but I believed the people had been<lb/>cheated, and I said I would go to the<lb/>House of Assembly to prevent the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment from carrying any Scheme of<lb/>Union through that House. I said the<lb/>question should be again left to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple, and the men who inaugurated the<lb/>principle were the proper men to carry<lb/>it out. The only pledge I ever made to<lb/>my constituents in my life was that I<lb/>would agree to no Union unless there<lb/>was an appeal to the people. I differ<lb/>with my hon. friend in regard to the<lb/>constitutional part of the question. I<lb/>hold when he put the question of Union<lb/>in the Speech he committed the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to Union. He was not obliged to<lb/>put it in ; he could have said to the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor that there was no necessity for put<lb break="no"/>ting that paragraph into the Speech, be<lb break="no"/>cause those despatches could be laid be<lb break="no"/>fore the House, but if put in the Speech<lb/>they would have to endorse them. My<lb/>hon. friend said his life had been a burden<lb/>to him. He felt the difficulties that sur<lb break="no"/>rounded him ; he recommended appoint<lb break="no"/>ments to office, and the Governor would<lb/>not make them ; he held office without<lb/>responsibility and without power. He<lb/>told us the country was in great peril.<lb/>Who were they in peril of ? He had<lb/>succeeded in cajoling the people only<lb/>fifteen months before, but during that<lb/>time the people had time to consider and<lb/>they went against him by an overwhelm<lb break="no"/>ing majority. I do not think there is a<lb/>man on the floors of this House, or a<lb/>man in the country, that would not say,<lb/>after reading the address in answer to the<lb/>Speech, that the Government had agreed<lb/>to some kind of Union. This paragraph<lb/>in the address says :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>" The correspondence which has taken<lb/>place between Her Majesty's Principal<lb/>Secretary of State for the Colonies and<lb/>the Governor General of Canada, on the<lb/>affairs of British North America, when<lb/>laid before us, will receive due attention,<lb/>and the opinion expressed by Her Ma<lb break="no"/>jesty's Government will command that<lb/>respect and attention which is due to sug<lb break="no"/>gestions emanating from so high a<lb/>source."<lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>That is a full avowal of their pol<lb break="no"/>icy of Union, but in order that the world<lb/>might know that Mr. Anglin had them in<lb/>the hollow of his hand, they add the rest<lb/>of the paragraph.<lb/>
            </p>

            <cb/>
           
 <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>— When the hon. member<lb/>speaks of Mr. Anglin having the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment in the hollow of his hand, he<lb/>states what is not true.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>— The Government<lb/>could not live with him, and they could<lb/>not live without him and were turned<lb/>out.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>— It is not true.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>— It is easy to say<lb/>it is not true, but that does not alter the<lb/>case, for the fact is indisputable. He<lb/>helped to prepare that celebrated " Mi<lb break="no"/>nute of Council," and that was one of<lb/>the things that helped to kill them at the<lb/>election. The paragraph continues,—<lb/>" but in any Scheme for a Union of the<lb/>British North American Colonies which<lb/>may be proposed." I ask the House<lb/>what that means " any Scheme of Union<lb/>which may be proposed." Proposed by<lb/>whom ? By the Government. Did they<lb/>intend to bring forward any measure ?<lb/>If the Government had been sustained<lb/>last year on the " want of confidence<lb/>motion" we would have defeated them<lb/>on this paragraph, for there were consti<lb break="no"/>tutional men enough in the House to have<lb/>done so. I think that any man with a<lb/>knowledge of the English language would<lb/>say after reading that paragaraph that<lb/>some Scheme of Union was in contem<lb break="no"/>plation ; and that Scheme would be a<lb/>measure and that measure would be a<lb/>measure of the Government. For what<lb/>purpose ? For the purpose of uniting<lb/>these Provinces, and providing sufficient<lb/>safeguards for their protection. There<lb/>cannot be any doubt that this was the<lb/>meaning of that paragraph. The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment complained of the address of the<lb/>Legislative Council, and tried to induce<lb/>the people to believe that they were a<lb/>body who represented nobody, and were<lb/>not a co-ordinate branch of the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture. They have taken the first action<lb/>on this question as also have the Legis<lb break="no"/>lative Councils of Nova Scotia and Cana<lb break="no"/>da. My hon. friend complains that the<lb/>Governor in answering the address of<lb/>the Legislative Council, did not give him<lb/>time to consult his colleagues upon the<lb/>question. He says " a vote of want of<lb/>confidence was going on." That was a<lb/>mighty matter. He had not time to come<lb/>down and discuss the matter for Mr.<lb/>Anglin was speaking and had the lobbies<lb/>filled to order.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>— The Governor proposed<lb/>that I should take half-an-hour to come<lb/>down and consult my colleagues.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>— I would have<lb/>taken the half-hour and sent for my col<lb break="no"/>leagues to Government House and dis<lb break="no"/>cuss the matter. I do not think they<lb/>would have been confined to half-an-hour<lb/>for if they had come he could not have<lb/>turned them out. It was Saturday after<lb break="no"/>noon and the House would have been<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
         

     glad to have adjourned until Monday 
     <lb/>morning. All he had to do was to tell<lb/>the House that the Government had im<lb break="no"/>portant business to transact with the<lb/>Governor, and Mr. Anglin would have<lb/>been willing to postpone his remarks, and<lb/>that would have obviated the difficulty.<lb/>The Government at that time were hold<lb break="no"/>ing power against the will of the people.<lb/>The Government wished to make certain<lb/>appointments and the Governor would<lb/>noy make them.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>— The hon. member has 
     <lb/>
     made a statement that I have explained 
     <lb/>half a-dozen times. The Governor did<lb/>not refuse to make these appointments.<lb/>The Governor did not think it desirable<lb/>to make any displacements before he<lb/>went to England, in view of its effect at<lb/>the Colonial office, and this met with the<lb/>concurrence of his Council.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>— It was stated dif<lb break="no"/>ferently by Mr. Hatheway.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>— I have stated it often,<lb/>and there is no occasion to refer to Mr.<lb/>Hatheway for he is not here to answer<lb/>for himself.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>— I was informed<lb/>that the Government wanted to make<lb/>these appointments, and it was more<lb/>than insinuated that his refusal was one<lb/>cause of Mr. Anglin's resignation. Mr.<lb/>Anglin in order to sustain the <choice><sic>humilat<lb break="no"/>ing</sic><corr>humiliating</corr></choice> position the Government was in,<lb/>said, the country was in great peril,<lb/>and this corrobates that idea. The<lb/>Government were afraid to dissolve the<lb/>House because they knew the feelings<lb/>of the country were against them.<lb/>They had an evidence of this in the<lb/>York election, but they resolved to hold<lb/>on to power as long as possible. This<lb/>Union question should rise above all<lb/>party questions ; it is a questions of pat<lb break="no"/>riotism and its object is to promote the<lb/>welfare of our common country. My<lb/>hon. friend says the policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment is a policy of concealment. I<lb/>should not think he would mention it,<lb/>after the exhibition the Government<lb/>made last session. After they came<lb/>down to the House, they were silent<lb/>beyond measure on this important ques<lb break="no"/>tion.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>— My hon. friend is en<lb break="no"/>tirely mistaken. We told the House we<lb/>had no measure to submit.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>— I am not entirely 
     <lb/>mistaken. One great object of my motion<lb/>was to draw them out upon the subject of<lb/>Confederation. I tried to get some ex<lb break="no"/>pression of opinion on the subject from<lb/>the ex Surveyor General, but he trerated<lb/>it in the most child-like way. His reply<lb/>to my question was : Are you for the<lb/>Quebec Scheme ? The present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment have never concealed their action<lb/>in this matter. They say that any Union<lb/>proposed must be based upon the Que<lb break="no"/>
    

            <pb n="56" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_056.jpg"/>
         
<fw type="num">56</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES IN THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 
   

     bec Scheme, and they are determine to 
     <lb/>secure the best terms they can for New<lb/>Brunswick. Though the thirty-three de<lb break="no"/>legates agreed to the Quebec Schsme, it<lb/>was but a compromise, for it is a lot to be<lb/>supposed that any one member was<lb/>perfectly satisfied with all its parts. No<lb/>Scheme could be made where there are<lb/>different interests without a compromise.<lb/>My hon. friend says there was a vast<lb/>amount of haste used in preparing this<lb/>Scheme, and there was no parallel case<lb/>of a constitution being prepared in so<lb/>short a time. I differ with him. You<lb/>may search the history of the Colonial<lb/>Empire, and you will not find a consti<lb break="no"/>tution, the formation of which has taken<lb/>more time than this. The constitutions<lb/>of Upper and Lower Canada were likely<lb/>drawn by some second hand lawyer. The<lb/>constitution of United Canada aws<lb/>drawn by the British Government, and<lb/>all the knowledge they had of what was<lb/>required was from Lord Durham, and<lb/>one element was not introduced into that<lb/>constitution until Lord Durham com<lb break="no"/>plained of its omission. United Canada<lb/>is now a flourishing country, but before<lb/>the Union there was a dullness and lassi<lb break="no"/>tude in the country which contrasted un<lb break="no"/>favorable with the United States, where<lb/>all was life and action. It is in Canada<lb/>now that you see the great elements of<lb/>advancement. Is it not this Union that<lb/>has made Montreal the populous city she<lb/>is? They have built Railroads and Ca<lb break="no"/>nals, and their population has increased<lb/>very rapidly. This has been the result of<lb/>their Union, and it will probably be the<lb/>result of this. How long did my hon.<lb/>friend want the constitution to be kept<lb/>in the political crucible before it could be<lb/>formed? It was formed by thirty-three gen<lb break="no"/>tlemen, and most of them were men of good<lb/>education and constitutional know<lb break="no"/>ledge, and had been occupied in public<lb/>business during the greater part of their<lb/>lives. The realisation of this Union is<lb/>one of the day-dreams of my live, and I<lb/>consider it will prove a great advantage<lb/>to the country. We have the example<lb/>of the United States. There were some<lb/>thirteen States who saw that it would be<lb/>for their mutual benefit to unite, and<lb/>they have since risen in wealth and<lb/>prosperity until they have attained their<lb/>present position. The model of our<lb/>Constitution has been the Brit<lb break="no"/>ish Parliament. The head of our Go<lb break="no"/>vernment is to be the Queen's represen<lb break="no"/>tative. We only apply the principle of<lb/>the American Constitution as far as<lb/>they work out some of the principles<lb/>we have adopted as incident to our po<lb break="no"/>sition. My hon. friend (Mr. Smith)<lb/>says he cannot agree with the principle<lb/>of representation by population. I<lb/>understood him to assent to that princi<lb break="no"/>ple last winter, and only wanted certain<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
       

     checks. We never can be united with<lb break="no"/>out representation by population, be<lb break="no"/>cause Upper Canada will not consent to<lb/>any other basis. Lower Canada will<lb/>not consent to Legislative Union. I<lb/>will ask my hon. friend if he perfers<lb/>a Legislative to a Federal Union?<lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - I will answer that at 
     <lb/>some future time, for it requires a<lb/>lengthy reply.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> - I take it my hon. 
     <lb/>friend would prefer a Legislative Union<lb/>with representation by population, to a<lb/>Federative Union, because he says that<lb/>the principle of representation by popu<lb break="no"/>lation is inapplicable to a Federative<lb/>Union, but then he says he is willing to<lb/>go into a Federative Union provided he<lb/>could get the necessary checks. I think<lb/>the Constitution provides checks in the<lb/>Upper Branch. This Branch is entirely<lb/>distinct from the American Senate.<lb/>The Senate together with the people<lb/>can make treaties , and they require no<lb/>further action from the Legislative<lb/>body, but a treaty made by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Great Britain is a powerless in<lb break="no"/>strument unless enacted by the <choice><sic>Parlia<lb break="no"/>liament</sic><corr>Parliament</corr></choice>. He says in the United States<lb/>Senate each State has an equal repre<lb break="no"/>sentation, and objects to the Scheme<lb/>because it does not make this provision.<lb/>He is in favor of united the Maratime<lb/>Provinces with a view of uniting the<lb/>whole. After they are united he<lb/>will have exactly what he wants,<lb/>for then each Province will have<lb/>twenty-four members in the Upper<lb/>House and four more from Newfound<lb break="no"/>land. In the United states all power is<lb/>in the peeple, and they confer a certain<lb/>portion of that power upon the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the different States, another<lb/>portion to the Federal Government, and<lb/>another portion they keep themselves.<lb/>There is no analogy between their Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and ours; they require a Court<lb/>of Appeal as necessary to their condi<lb break="no"/>tion. Our Parliament is all powerful,<lb/>all the power that is not conferred upon<lb/>the Local Legislature is given to the<lb/>General Government. The tendency<lb/>of this arrangement is to a Legislative<lb/>Union. It will arise out of this in the<lb/>future, and be the final result. There is<lb/>a provision made for assimilating all<lb/>the Laws in every part of the Confeder<lb break="no"/>acy except Lower Canada. The pro<lb break="no"/>visions made for selecting Judges from<lb/>any part of the Confederacy is I think a<lb/>good arrangement, and will be an ad<lb break="no"/>vantage to the public interest. I was<lb/>concerned in a case where there was<lb/>only one Judge in the Province that<lb/>could try it on account of having an in<lb break="no"/>terest in it.</p>

<p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> - I will ask my hon.<lb/>friend if he has any objections at all to<lb/>the Quebec Scheme, and if he has I<lb/>wish him to state what they are.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> - My idea is if we 
     <lb/>can get any improvements I will go<lb/>for them. I said before that I did not<lb/>believe that there was one gentleman<lb/>out of the thirty-three but what objec<lb break="no"/>ted to some of its provisions, and it is<lb/>but a compromise, each one giving up<lb/>certain objections in order that all<lb/>might agree. You cannot devise a<lb/>Scheme that all will agree to each<lb/>provision in it. We may acquire<lb/>some advantage for New Brunswick<lb/>and Nova Scotia in this controversy, for<lb/>we know that a few thousand pounds<lb/>would be an advantage to us, but it<lb/>would be very little advantage spread<lb/>over the whole Confederacy. The hon.<lb/>member for Gloucester (Mr. Young)<lb/>says the great question with this coun<lb break="no"/>try is regarding the eighty cents a head,<lb/>to aid us in supporting our local im<lb break="no"/>provements. In CAnada they do not<lb/>get a single dollar from the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment towards local improvements.<lb/>They have municipal corporations to<lb/>attend to those matters, and through<lb/>their agency they make theri public<lb/>improvements. In the United States<lb/>every improvement is made by direct<lb/>taxation, and they receive no money<lb/>from the public treasury. In the con<lb/>ference we took the position that our<lb/>people had been accustomed to receive<lb/>from the public treasury certain sums<lb/>of money to enable them from time to<lb/>time to carry on their schools, roads,<lb/>and local improvements. The enquiry<lb/>was then made of waht would meet our<lb/>resources in future, and the conclusion<lb/>arrived at was, that eighty cents per<lb/>head, with our casual and territorial<lb/>revenue, our underdeveloped minerals and<lb/>unproductive forests, would make all<lb/>the improvements we required, to as<lb/>great an extend as in the past. There<lb/>was a remark made by my hon. friend<lb/>from St. John (Mr. Skinner) about<lb/>giving the delegates some instructions.<lb/>I think they will be pretty well instruct<lb break="no"/>ed, after hearing the discussion in this<lb/>House. If you send delegates with in<lb break="no"/>structions, and the delegates from the<lb/>other Provinces receive pacific instruc<lb break="no"/>tions, and they all stand by their in<lb break="no"/>structions, they can never come to an<lb/>agreement; there must be a mutual<lb/>concession and compromise amongst<lb/>them all.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName>. - I did not say I 
     <lb/>would give the delegates pacific instruc<lb break="no"/>tions. I said we should discuss and<lb/>mature this matter, and have a plan,<lb/>and instruct the delegates, but allow<lb/>them a margin to go upon to better en<lb break="no"/>able them to get what they want.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>. - I thought from 
     <lb/>the tenor of his speech that he wished<lb/> to give the delegates positive instructions.<lb/>I do not think he is acting consistent;<lb/>
     
   

            <pb n="57" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-30_Page_057.jpg"/>
       

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">57</fw> 
    

     he ran his first election upon the Quebec 
     <lb/>Scheme, and his second election upon the<lb/>proposition made by the Government.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> - The first election, 
     <lb/>was said to be run upon the Quebec<lb/>Scheme as it stood. At a meeting held<lb/>at the Institute previous to the election,<lb/>Mr. Tilley stated to the people that if<lb/>they did not like the Quebec Scheme in<lb/>its entirety not to reject it, but to sustain<lb/>Union although they might not believe in<lb/>every letter and sentence of the Scheme.<lb/>So I claim to have run the election and<lb/>yet have my own judgment about the<lb/>Scheme. The Confederate paty when<lb/>they come here have still the right to<lb/>exercise their judgement as to whether<lb/>they would suggest any amendments.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName> - I supposed the 
     <lb/>elections were generally run on the pro<lb break="no"/>position made by the Government. I<lb/>
     think the whole representation of our    
     <lb/>country will go for the Quebec Scheme if<lb/>they cannot get a better. They talk about<lb/>Nova Scotia not coming in to this Union.<lb/>Would it not be a good think for us if<lb/>she did not come in for a year or two.<lb/>Look at the advantage we will derive<lb/>from the construction of this Inter-colo<lb break="no"/>nial Railroad, two-thirds of the money<lb/>expended to build it will be circulated in<lb/>our Province, and all our young men in<lb/>every station in life will be employed. It<lb/>will open up our country and develop our<lb/>resources. I believe if a vote was taken<lb/>to-morrow to build the road under the<lb/>arrangement of 1862 the pople would<lb/>decide to have it built. Under that ar<lb break="no"/>rangement we were to build 3 1/2-twelfths<lb/>but now we have to contribute but one-<lb break="yes"/>thirteenth. They say we will have to<lb/>pay for the canals in Canada. I say if I<lb/>went to Ottawa I would vote for the<lb/>canals at once, for I beliee they would be<lb/>beneficial to us. I was astonished when<lb/>I was there, at the progress of that coun<lb break="no"/>try, and if those canals give us the trade<lb/>of that vast west - if the teeming welath<lb/>of the soil come down to this country,<lb/>and St. John is made the vast emporium,<lb/>who can conceive the greatness and<lb/>power of that city. The Erie Canal has<lb/>made New York the Empire City, and like<lb/>means produces like effect. If the Union<lb/>alone was subject to all the objections<lb/>made by my hon. friends, I believe this<lb/>Inter-colonial Railway would be an answer<lb/>to the whole of them, for it will cause<lb/>towns and villages to be built along its<lb/>course, and continuous benefits will be<lb/>
     
            <cb/>
         

     derived therefrom. There has been a de<lb break="no"/>sire for many years to make a railway from<lb/>the Atlantic to the Pacific, and it is only<lb/>through British Territory that favourable<lb/>passes can be found. Explorers were not<lb/>aware that they had passed the rocky<lb/>mountains till they found the decending<lb/>waters on the other side. I want to carry<lb/>this Confederation to the Pacific Ocean.<lb/>There are Iron, Gold and other Minerals<lb/>at the Red River Settlement, and the<lb/>Americans are ready to go in there and<lb/>settle and organize a Government. The<lb/>reason the people of England take such<lb/>an interest in this question is this: they<lb/>see by our constitution that we admire<lb/>the institutions of the mother country, and<lb/>that we are going to form a nation which<lb/>is to be part of themselves; and they<lb/>further say, if we wish to separate from<lb/>them they do not wish to retain us; but<lb/>if we wish to remain, all the power of the<lb/>nation will be put forth to sustain us. A<lb/>member of the British Government in<lb/>speaking of the Fenians said: "the mur<lb break="no"/>derers have attacked these Provinces.<lb/>What harm have these Provinces done<lb/>them that they should be attacked. I<lb/>have no doubt but that the Provinces will<lb/>be able to defend themselves, but come<lb/>what will the whole power of the Empire<lb/>will be put forth to defend them." We<lb/>find the old feeling is there yet, let us<lb/>then form one great country and depend<lb/>upon it they will respect us. Let us<lb/>unite, and we will become a powerful<lb/>nation, our resources will be developed,<lb/>our condition improved, our railroads<lb/>built, and our prosperity increased be<lb break="no"/>yond any thing we at present anticipate.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The question was then taken whether<lb/>the amendment should be added to the<lb/>Resolution, when there appeared. -<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Yeas - Messrs. Botsford, Smith, Mee<lb break="no"/>han, Landry, McQueen, Caie, McInerney,<lb/>Young, - 8.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Nays - Messrs. Fisher, Tilley, McMil<lb break="no"/>lan, McClellan, Williston, Wilmot, Con<lb break="no"/>nell, Kerr, Stevens, Sutton, Johnson,<lb/>Baveridge, Lewis, Hibbard, Chandler,<lb/>Dow, Beckwith, Thompson, Quinton,<lb/>DesBrisay, John Flewwelling, Babbit,<lb/>Ferris, Wetmore, Lindsay, McAdam,<lb/>Ryan, Perley, Skinner, Herbert, - 30.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The original resolution was then put,<lb/>when the same division took place, the<lb/>yeas, voting nay, and the nays, yeas.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:STEV1">Mr. STEVENS</persName> brought in "A Bill to<lb/>provide for the regulation of connecting<lb/>lines of Railway in this Province."<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>
            <p>The House in Committee agreed to a<lb/>Bill introduced by <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName> enti<lb break="no"/>tled "A Bill to authorize the munici<lb break="no"/>pality of the County of Carleton, to issue<lb/>Debentures to a certain amount to aid in<lb/>paying for the enlarging and repairing<lb/>the County Court House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Also, a Bill introduced by <persName ref="pers:PERL1">Mr. PER<lb break="no"/>LEY</persName>, entitled "A Bill to provide for the<lb/>election of councillors, and the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of Parish offices in the municipality<lb/>of Sunbury."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Also a Bill brought in by <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr.<lb/>McCLELAN</persName> entitled "A Bill to incor<lb break="no"/>porate the Albert Bank."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House then adjourned until Mon<lb break="no"/>day morning at 9 a.m.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">T.P.D.<lb/>
            </p>


<!-- GL, 2018-03-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p>MONDAY,, July 2d<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>NORTH SHORE STEAMER.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. McCLELAN in reply to a<lb/>question put by the hon. member from<lb/>Gloucester (Mr. Young) said that a bar<lb break="no"/>gain had been made with Canada for the<lb/>placing of a steamer on the North Short<lb/>route, to call at various ports. The<lb/>contract was not yet signed but there was<lb/>no doubt the steamer would be put on.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>PETITION AGAINST MR, MEEHAN.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>This being the day appointed for the<lb/>consideration of the charges contained in<lb/>the petition of William H. Gordon,<lb/>against the return of John Meehan as a<lb/>representative in the General Assembly,<lb/>at 10 o'clock the doors being closed the<lb/>Speaker proceeded to ballot for the Com<lb break="no"/>mittee to whom the whole matter should<lb/>be referred. The petitioner was repre<lb break="no"/>sented at the bar of the House by his<lb/>counsel, -\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\-\- Rainsford, Esq., and the<lb/>sitting member by W.H. Needham, Esq.,<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The names of eleven members drawn<lb/>by the clerk were then read, and the<lb/>counsel proceeded to strik off three men<lb/>each. The Committee thus struck was as<lb/>follows: -\- John Flewwelling, F. Hibbard,<lb/>John Lewis, Richard Sutton, and Charles<lb/>Connell. A. J. Smith was appinted<lb/>nominee for Mr. Meehan, and J.G.<lb/>Stevens for the Petitioner. The oath was<lb/>then administered, and they retired to the<lb/>Committee room to investigate the whole<lb/>matter.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>FINANCIAL STATEMENT.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> then laid before<lb/>House the statement of the estimates for<lb/>the present, and the expenditure of the<lb/>past year, which is as follows:<lb/>
            </p>-->
        </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>