<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-03-23"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-03-23">23 March 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1866</title>.
   
         
                    

           <date when="1866"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="47" to="51"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_047.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_048.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_049.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_050.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_051.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-18">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-18">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-21">Marked-up people</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_047">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_047.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_048">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_048.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_049">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_049.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_050">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_050.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_051">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_051.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="47" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_047.jpg"/>

 <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">47</fw>

            <!--<p> DEBATES
OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> 47<lb/>
            </p>-->

<!-- GL, 2016-11-18, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 


            <!--<p> dictation,
when it suited my purpose, and<lb/>
that I am willing none to be dictated to from<lb/>
the same quarter ;—and I know
that I was<lb/>
about as honest in the one case as I<lb/>
am in the other; they both answered<lb/>
my purposes as a politician, and he<lb/>
could truthfully have said what matters<lb/>
is how much social hate and discord I<lb/>
produce, or how much untruthfulness I<lb/>
am guilty of, if I can only succeed in<lb/>
defeating the Government, for I shall<lb/>
then be elevated to their position. Op<lb break="no"/>position means to oppose, right or wrong,<lb/>
at least in my case. Yes! I know these<lb/>
things, but who on earth could doubt my<lb/>
piety, my truthfulness and my loyalty, that<lb/>
heard me at the close of my speech re<lb break="no"/>commend peace and good will. I fixed<lb/>
the whole matter by throwing over all<lb/>
misrepresentations, this hypocritical man<lb break="no"/>tle of deception, and this quotation will<lb/>
give you a good description of his ap<lb break="no"/>pearance at the close:</p>
            <p>"Then richer grown in gilts and grace,<lb/>
With every rite complies,<lb/>
And deeper lengthens down his face,<lb/>
And higher rolls his eyes."</p>
            <p>The debate was then adjourned until<lb/>
eleven to-morrow, Hon. Mr. Gillmor to<lb/>
resume.</p>
            <p>The House was then adjourned until<lb/>
to-morrow at nine.</p>
            <p>A.A.</p>
            <lb/>-->


            <head rendition="simple:right">FRIDAY, March 23.</head>
            <lb/>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. MR. SMITH</persName> called the attention<lb/>
of the House to a communication in the<lb/>
<hi rendition="simple:italic">Morning Telegraph</hi>, which professed to<lb/>
give a statement of what took place be<lb break="no"/>tween Mr. Tilley and himself. This letter<lb/>
was signed by "A Looker on," and he<lb/>
thought he knew the writer, who was one<lb/>
of the most malicious, unprincipled politi<lb break="no"/>cal partisans in the Province, and was a<lb/>
person who had frequently attempted to<lb/>
injure him. He would state that the<lb/>
statements contained in that letter were<lb/>
utterly untrue, which could be proved by<lb/>
twenty witnesses, and he would be much<lb/>
obliged if that paper would publish this<lb/>
denial of their truth.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILB1">MR. GILBERT</persName> called the attention of<lb/>
the Chief Commissioner of the Board of<lb/>
Works to the unsafe condition of the<lb/>
bridge over the Memramcosk River, in<lb/>
the County of Westmorland. He had<lb/>
received a letter stating that the bridge<lb/>
was likely to be carried away by the ice<lb/>
in the spring. If this took place it would<lb/>
cause a great deal of inconvenience.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:HATH1">HON. MR. HATHEWAY</persName> said if his<lb/>
hon. friend would place the letter in his<lb/>
hand, he would refer it to the Supervisors,<lb/>
and if they reported the bridge to be in<lb/>
that state, he would have it repaired.</p>
            <p>The House in Committee then agreed<lb/>
to "A Bill to provide for the settlement<lb/>
and support of the poor in this Province"</p>

<div type="section">
            <head>A BILL TO INCORPORATE THE ABERDEEN<lb/>
IRON COMPANY.</head>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:CONN1">MR. CONNELL</persName> in explaining the ob<lb break="no"/>jects of the Bill, said it was <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> 
               <lb/>
the purpose of getting<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
               <lb/>
abroad, and every one would<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
               <lb/>
desirability of introducing<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> the<lb/>
country, to open up the mines and min<lb break="no"/>erals, which are extensive, the operations<lb/>
upon which are only now beginning;<lb/>
            
            <cb/>
        
under the General Act there was some<lb/>
doubt about holding lands, and it was<lb/>
necessary in operations of this kind that<lb/>
the company should hold a great deal of<lb/>
land.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:KERR1">MR. KERR</persName> said that there was no<lb/>
doubt whatever under the General Act<lb/>
but what they had power to hold lands.<lb/>
There were several companies of this<lb/>
kind got up in other parts of the Province<lb/>
with quite as large a capital as that pro<lb break="no"/>possed in this Bill, and the general law<lb/>
gave each of these corporations all the<lb/>
power they needed for the purchase<lb/>
of lands. Unless some special provisions<lb/>
were required, he did not see the neces<lb break="no"/>sity of this Bill.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName> said the company<lb/>
would have to go abroad to obtain capi<lb break="no"/>tal, and if the parties could show a special<lb/>
Act of incorporation it would, no doubt,<lb/>
facilitate their operations very much.<lb/>
Therefore, if this Bill simply contains the<lb/>
provisions of the General Act, it would<lb/>
be unwise in this Legislature to refuse<lb/>
to pass it.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Mr. ANGLIN</persName> stated that under an<lb/>
Act of this kind, stock could be secured<lb/>
more readily; for at the stock exchange <lb/>
it would be proof that the company had a<lb/>
real existence, although it might be a mere<lb/>
nominal existence, but it was something<lb/>
tangible, and parties could recommend<lb/>
themselves more readily in consequence<lb/>
of it. But he thought it would be ad<lb break="no"/>visable to re-enact the old rule that re<lb break="no"/>quired $30 to be paid on all private Bills<lb/>
that came there, because many other<lb/>
Bills of a like nature would be coming in.</p>
            <p>The Bill was then agreed to. The<lb/>
House then went into Committee on "A<lb/>
Bill to empower the Justices in the sev<lb break="no"/>eral Courts in this Province to act in<lb/>
several cases relating to Parish rates and<lb/>
taxes," which produced a long discussion,<lb/>
after which progress was reported.</p>
            <lb/>
</div>
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">ADJOURNED DEBATE ON MR. FISHER'S<lb/>
AMENDMENT</head>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">HON. MR. GILLMOR</persName> resumed—I re<lb break="no"/>gret I had not finished my remarks last<lb/>
evening, which I would have done had<lb/>
the House remained in session a few<lb/>
minutes longer.</p>
            <p>If any further reasons were necessary</p>
            <p>to justify the personal allusions which I</p>
            <p>have made to my hon. friend from York</p>
            <p>(Mr. Fisher) that the attack which he</p>
            <p>has made upon the Government, I can</p>
            <p>give them. I entered the Temperance</p>
            <p>Hall in Fredericton on declaration day,</p>
            <p>a comparative stranger to most of the</p>
            <p>audience, and my friend, not satisfied with<lb/>
attacking the Government, referred to me</p>
            <p>personally, pointing me out, and said,</p>
            <p>"There is the Provincial Secretary; An-</p>
            <p>glin has him in the hollow of his hand,</p>
            <p>and can rule him as he pleases." I have</p>
            <p>kept quiet upon this point until I could</p>
            <p>meet him face to face in this Assembly.<lb/>
To be attacked in that manner before an<lb/>
audience in the city of Fredericton was<lb/>
quite enough to move the indignation of<lb/>
any man, and I would not be worthy to<lb/>
               <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> of the
constituents of Charlotteto<lb break="no"/>wn <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
               <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
                  <lb/>
            <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
           <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/></p>
           <p>  A charge against the Government,<lb/>
which I did not notice yesterday, in their<lb/>
             
            <cb/>
          
   neglect in not renewing the Export Duty<lb/>
Law." The Chief Commissioner of Pub<lb break="no"/>lic Works has acknowledged that the<lb/>
Government have been guilty of that<lb/>
omission, and none of us will deny that<lb/>
the present Government are responsible<lb/>
for it. It has given me a great deal of<lb/>
anxiety. I am personally responsible, as<lb/>
well as all my colleagues, but notwith<lb break="no"/>standing the omission, the evil has been<lb/>
entirely remedied, and not one cent<lb/>
has been lost to the people of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. ( <persName ref="pers:ANON1">A member</persName>,—You need not
thank<lb/>
the Government for that.) Such is the<lb/>
result. Who should we thank? The<lb/>
Government are responsible for the man<lb break="no"/>agement of public affairs, and cannot<lb/>
shrink from it if they would, but must<lb/>
bear the blame of the omission. It is<lb/>
not an evidence of inability, but is an<lb/>
oversight that might have occurred in any<lb/>
Government, and in extenuation of it, I<lb/>
will not even urge the circumstances un<lb break="no"/>der which the Government was formed,<lb/>
and when the country knows that no<lb/>
harm has resulted from it, I am sure that<lb/>
a generous public will not condemn us<lb/>
on that charge.</p>
            <lb/>
            <p>I was a little surprised at the remarks<lb/>
made by the late Surveyor General. One<lb/>
reason he gave for opposing the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, was that the interests of the North<lb/>
had been neglected in the formation of<lb/>
the Government, and I thought it un<lb break="no"/>generous in him to make such an allu<lb break="no"/>sion as he did to the Hon. Mr. Hutchi<lb break="no"/>son ; from my short acquaintance with<lb/>
him, I believe him quite competent and<lb/>
quite ready to protect the northern in<lb break="no"/>terests, and, although comparisons are<lb/>
odious, I think he will compare favorably<lb/>
with that hon. gentleman, morally, intel<lb break="no"/>lectually, or as a business man, or with<lb/>
any man on the floor of the House. I<lb/>
consider him a man of prudence, ability<lb/>
and sterling integrity. The hon. member<lb/>
(Mr. McMillan) may be opposed to him<lb/>
politically, but that is no reason he should<lb/>
charge him with incapacity. (Mr. McCle<lb break="no"/>lan—In the absence of my friend
(Mr.<lb/>
McMillan) I will say I understood him to<lb/>
refer to his want of political experience,<lb/>
and not his want of ability.) I under<lb break="no"/>stood him to say both, and I do not think<lb/>
it fair to decry a man thus in his absence.<lb/>
If the interests of the North suffer, it<lb/>
will not be for want of capacity in Mr.<lb/>
Hutchison.</p>
            <p>I should be glad indeed, if the North<lb break="no"/>ern interests could be more largely re<lb break="no"/>presented at the Council Board, but the<lb/>
great question decided at the last General<lb/>
Election precluded them from taking in<lb break="no"/>to the Executive Council those who<lb/>
entertained different opinions upon that<lb/>
question, although it would have been<lb/>
very gratifying to my colleagues and my<lb break="no"/>self if it could have been done. ( <persName ref="pers:HATH1">Hon.<lb/>
Mr Hatheway</persName>—My hon. friend on my<lb/>
left says there were two members from<lb/>
the County of Gloucester who were anti-<lb break="yes"/>
Confederates. Does he not know that<lb/>
there was a scrutiny going on, and while<lb/>
that was pending they could not become<lb/>
members of the Government.)</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> —<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> no! a<lb/>

            <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
               <unclear n="">that office <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> me, and I am sure</unclear><lb/>
         my hon. friend thinks me sincere in this;<lb/>
           
            <pb n="48" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_048.jpg"/>
           
<fw type="num">48</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 

     did I not
think so I am sure I would not<lb/>
so speak.</p>
            <p>There are other hon. members who<lb/>
get credit for knowing a great deal about<lb/>
finance, and without wishing to depre<lb break="no"/>ciate them, or recommend myself, I feel<lb/>
quite satisfied there is not one among<lb/>
them who can discharge the duties bet<lb break="no"/>ter than I can.</p>
            <p>As I made allusion, yesterday, to the<lb/>
Inter-colonial Railway, and it has been<lb/>
talked about considerably during this<lb/>
debate, and has been held out as a great<lb/>
inducement for us to go into Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, I will venture, although a little<lb/>
out of connexion, to read an extract<lb/>
from the Toronto <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi>, which speaks<lb/>
Mr. George Brown's sentiments on that<lb/>
question:—</p>
            <lb/>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"Upper Canadians have not suffered<lb/>
enough, it appears, in the estimation of<lb/>
Upper Canadian members of the Cab<lb break="no"/>inet, from being tied to one poor East<lb break="no"/>ern Province, it must have three more<lb/>
added to its already heavy burdens.<lb/>
One Legislature is not a sufficiently<lb/>
cumbrous, unwieldy and expensive<lb/>
body, buyt must add to it the represen<lb break="no"/>tatives of three other communities, each<lb/>
section with varying local interests,<lb/>
and all pulling at the same purse. And<lb/>
to show what we may look for in the<lb/>
future, we are to pay four-twelfths of<lb/>
the cost of a Railway to unite us to these<lb/>
new allies, and to keep the road running<lb/>
besides. Truly a charming scheme to<lb/>
be proposed by a retrenchment Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, whose sole aim was to be the re<lb break="no"/>duction of expenditure, and the correc<lb break="no"/>tion of abuses in administration. New<lb/>
burdens of an enormous amount are to<lb/>
be imposed upon the people of Upper<lb/>
Canada, a Railway job to be undertaken,<lb/>
likely to be as disastrous and disgrace<lb break="no"/>ful as the Grand Trunk, and an already<lb/>
unwieldy political system to be encum<lb break="no"/>bered three fold; all that Messrs. Sicote<lb/>
and Sandfield McDonald may get rid of<lb/>
the difficulties with which their Govern<lb break="no"/>ment is surrounded."</p></quote>
       
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">SECOND EXTRACT.</head>
            <lb/>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"There is a refreshing coolness in the<lb/>
demand that Canada shall pay for the<lb/>
construction of a road, which is pro<lb break="no"/>fessedly designed to draw away trade<lb/>
from its great estuary. We have been<lb/>
building up the St. Lawrence at im<lb break="no"/>mense expense, and have had very hard<lb/>
work to compete with the Hudson and<lb/>
Erie Canals. According to the views<lb/>
of the late Hon. Mr. Merritt, steamship<lb/>
lines were alone needed to secure the<lb/>
object we desire. The ministry pur<lb break="no"/>pose, however, to withdraw the steam<lb break="no"/>ships from the St. Lawrence. If this<lb/>
could be done it would be an act of sui<lb break="no"/>cide in Canada to take part in the<lb/>
scheme. As it cannot be done it is sim<lb break="no"/>ply an absurdity. It may be difficult to<lb/>
escape from pledges given to the repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives of the Lower Provinces, but<lb/>
the members of the Cabinet may rely<lb/>
upon it, that they will have their reward<lb/>
for the abandonment or postponement<lb/>
of the measure in the approbation of<lb/>
their constituents and the Province at<lb/>
large."</p></quote>
           

            <p>Another extract from the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Globe</hi> of<lb/>
Toronto:</p>
            
          <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote"><p>"We have a debt of seventy millions<lb/>
            and a deficiency of three or four mil<lb break="no"/><cb/>lions, created by undertaking works<lb/>
            which have failed to pay any return for<lb/>
            the cost of construction. But no enter-<lb/>
            prise, the burden of which we have as-<lb/>
            sumed, comes anything near the Inter<lb break="no"/>colonial, in the poverty of its promised<lb/>
            results. It will not secure the profita<lb break="no"/>able settlement of an acre of land; it will<lb/>
            now help our trade; it will not pay its<lb/>
           own running expenses; the few barren<lb/>
            acres at the East are to get $50,000 a<lb/>
            year of our money, while half a contin<lb break="no"/>ent is to get a few words addressed to<lb/>
            the Colonial Minister."</p></quote>
            <lb/>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:FISH1">MR. FISHER</persName> —When was that writ<lb break="no"/>ten?</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">MR. GILLMOR</persName> —In 1862.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:FISH1">MR. FISHER</persName> —Mr. Brown has chang<lb break="no"/>ed his mind since that time.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">MR. GILLMOR</persName> —Those men broke<lb/>
faith once in reference to the Inter<lb break="no"/>colonial Railroad, and could do it again.<lb/>
Mr. Brown changed his views on this<lb/>
question because he wanted to get re<lb break="no"/>presentation by population, and when<lb/>
in Confederation, the Inter-colonial Rail<lb break="no"/>road depends upon a majority of the<lb/>
Federal Parliament. It is not a part of<lb/>
the Constitution of the Confederated Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:FISH1">MR. FISHER</persName> —It would be perfectly<lb/>
constitutional if we make that in the<lb/>
agreement.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName> —The British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment agree to guarantee the amount<lb/>
necessary to build the Road.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:NEED1">MR. NEEDHAM</persName> —They guaranteed<lb/>
that before, but I promise you they will<lb/>
not send the money until they get<lb/>
security.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">HON. MR GILLMOR</persName> —I will now<lb/>
read an extract from a speech made in<lb/>
Canada, to show why Mr. Brown was wil<lb break="no"/>ling to go to such an expenditure for a<lb/>
non-paying railroad. It was in order to<lb/>
get representation by population:</p>
           

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>"After many years of political strife<lb/>
between the two Canadas, the principle of<lb/>
representation equal for each of the Cana<lb break="no"/>das was fully established. The Hon.<lb/>
Mr. Brown has been for a long time try<lb break="no"/>ing to effect a change in that part of the<lb/>
Constitution of the Canadas. Every<lb/>
effort having failed to effect that, he, as a<lb/>
last resort, adopted Confederation as the<lb/>
only means of effecting his darling ob<lb break="no"/>ject. Had he been able to bring that<lb/>
about without asking the aid of the Mari<lb break="no"/>time Provinces, we should never have<lb/>
heard anything of Confederation. Is it<lb/>
wise for the Lower Provinces to go in and<lb/>
help Mr. Brown and his followers break<lb/>
up an arrangement solemnly entered into<lb/>
between the two Canadas? Will it not<lb/>
be the means of forcing a million of<lb/>
Lower Canadians into an arrangement<lb/>
contrary to their wishes, and consequent<lb break="no"/>ly they will not work harmoniously in<lb/>
the new order of things, and the num<lb break="no"/>ber can make some trouble.</p></quote>
            <lb/>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:FISH1">MR. FISHER</persName> —What authority is<lb/>
that?</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:NEED1">MR. NEEDHAM</persName> —I will endorse it.</p>
<cb/>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">MR. GILLMOR</persName> —My hon. friend, Mr.<lb/>
Wilmot, occupies a singular position ; he<lb/>
has heard the charges brought against the<lb/>
Government, and all the charges which<lb/>
have been made were for acts done or<lb/>
omitted while Mr. Wilmot was in the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment; and yet in his speech he ne<lb break="no"/>ver alluded to one of them. I was sur<lb break="no"/>prised, for he was equally with myself<lb/>
and my colleagues responsible for all that<lb/>
had been done up to the date of<lb/>
his resignation, and he was even<lb/>
more responsible, being an old po<lb break="no"/>litician and one of the gentlemen call<lb break="no"/>ed upon by His Excellency to form a<lb/>
Government. He said he was offered<lb/>
the office which I hold. I was anxious<lb/>
he should have taken it, and it was on<lb break="no"/>ly at the last moment that I accepted<lb/>
it. My friend said that he soon discover<lb break="no"/>ed how things were going on, and he was<lb/>
not going to take the office, and act "Jack<lb/>
in the Box." He has no right to charge<lb/>
me with being the mere instrument of<lb/>
any man or body of men. He knows<lb/>
me too well to imagine any such thing,<lb/>
and if he wishes to convey any such<lb/>
impression, he does me great injustice.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName> —I did not charge you<lb/>
with any improper conduct. I differed<lb/>
with the leader of the Government, and<lb/>
my hon. friend agreed with him.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">MR. GILLMOR</persName> —I have differed from<lb/>
the Attorney General, and I have agreed<lb/>
with him as matters appeared to my<lb/>
mind, but are we to come before the<lb/>
country, having been sworn to secresy,<lb/>
and state what we have differed upon.<lb/>
When I went into the Government, al<lb break="no"/>though I knew little about the duties of<lb/>
an Executive Councillor, yet I knew that<lb/>
as long as I remained there I was respon<lb break="no"/>sible for every act, whether I agreed<lb/>
personally to it or not, and I am bound to<lb/>
come before the House and the country<lb/>
and sustain my colleagues and the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment on all their acts. I think the<lb/>
impression has gone abroad in the coun<lb break="no"/>try that we have had a great deal of<lb/>
discord; such is not correct. There has<lb/>
been, I think, a great deal of harmony<lb break="no"/>more than I anticipated on entering the<lb/>
Government. It is only reasonable to<lb/>
conclude that nine men will on many<lb/>
matters entertain different opinions.</p>
            <p>My hon. friend says he had written out<lb/>
his resignation at the close of the Ses<lb break="no"/>sion. I never saw it. I think he did go<lb/>
out of the Council Chamber once, in a<lb/>
pet, and wrote out what he called his<lb/>
resignation, but I was told he tore it up,<lb/>
and was back again in fifteen minutes as<lb/>
pleasant as ever.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName> —Did you know<lb/>
I made an arrangement to leave the<lb/>
Government at the close of the Session?</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">MR. GILLMOR</persName> —Why do you ask me<lb/>
about an arrangement made before I came<lb/>
in? If I had the making of an arrange<lb break="no"/>ment, I would not buy any man to come<lb/>
into the Government by the promise of<lb/>
an office.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName> —Do you charge me<lb/>
with being bought?</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">MR. GILLMOR</persName> —You say you would<lb/>
not go into the Government and take<lb/>
the office of Provincial Secretary, but<lb/>
you did go into the Government on a<lb/>
promise that you was to get the office<lb/>
of Auditor General. No man should<lb/>
stipulate for any reward of that kind on<lb/>
going into a Government. I did not do<lb/>
so. I thought, under the circumstances,<lb/>
it was my duty to help all I could, and<lb/>
do the best I could, to help along the<lb/>
Government of the country.<lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="49" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_049.jpg"/>
       
 <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">49</fw>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName>.—I was anxious not to<lb/>
join. I was not willing to go in without<lb/>
some voice in the formation of it.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">MR. GILLMOR</persName>.—My hon. friend had <lb/>
a voice in the formation of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. There might have been a
differ<lb break="no"/>ence of opinion, for it is difficult to get <lb/>
men who can run their elections and dis<lb break="no"/>charge the duties of the Departments. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> [Here there was quite a lengthy discus<lb break="no"/>sion between Messrs. Wilmot, Smith and <lb/>
Hatheway, about arrangements made at <lb/>
the formation of the Government and the <lb/>
matters upon which differences
of opinion <lb/>
existed.]<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">MR. GiLLMOR</persName>.—One difference in <lb/>
the Government was in reference to the <lb/>
appointment of a Mr. Travis, and as <lb/>
there was no, vacancy there could be no <lb/>
appointment. We were all anxious to <lb/>
assist our friends in every way we could <lb/>
consistent with the public interest. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> My late colleague (Mr. Wilmot) said he <lb/>
would not sustain any Government that <lb/>
would allow a member of the Opposition
<lb/>
to carry a resolution to reduce the salary <lb/>
of a public official. He heard the dis<lb break="no"/>cussion regarding the reduction of the <lb/>
Auditor General's salary, and I did not <lb/>
hear him say much against it, but some <lb/>
of my colleagues said he had found fault; <lb/>
but he remained with the Government <lb/>
from that time until his resignation,
and <lb/>
never made any complaint, but has ta<lb break="no"/>ken part in all the Government has done, <lb/>
and is responsible for all. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName>.—The cause of dissatis<lb break="no"/>faction on my part was on account of the<lb/>
President of the Council saying that the<lb/>
Government wished the House to fix the<lb/>
salary, when, by order of the House, the <lb/>
Government themselves were to fix
it ; <lb/>
and I am now charged with not taking <lb/>
the Audit Office on account of the reduc<lb break="no"/>tion of salary.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> [Here another discussion arose between <lb/>
<persName ref="pers:HATH1">Mr. Hatheway</persName> and <persName ref="pers:WILM1">Mr. Wilmot</persName>.] <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">MR.
GlLLMOR</persName> —My hon. friend and <lb/>
late colleague says he never was
opposed <lb/>
to the abstract question of Union of the <lb/>
Colonies, and that the Government has <lb/>
done him injustice. The abstract ques<lb break="no"/>tion of union has never been submitted to <lb/>
the electors of New Brunswick, and an <lb/>
abstract question of union never will be,<lb/>
except the Confederates can work it in <lb/>
some way to assist them to carry the <lb/>
Quebec Scheme. To submit the abstract <lb/>
question of union to the people would be<lb/>
an abstract absurdity, for the conditions <lb/>
and details of any agreement is
the all- <lb break="yes"/>
important part of it. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:FISH1">MR. FISHER</persName>.—I
would ask my hon. <lb/>
friend what he means, then, by the para<lb break="no"/>graph in the Address in answer
to the <lb/>
Speech, which refers to that subject?
ln <lb/>
answer to a question put by Mr. Wilmot, <lb/>
did you hear me say that I was not op<lb break="no"/>posed to union in the abstract ?
<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">MR.
GlLLMOR</persName>.—I remember to have <lb/>
heard His Excellency say that there were <lb/>
some members in the Executive who were <lb/>
not opposed to union, and he pointed to <lb/>
Mr. Wilmot and Mr. Hutchison; and l <lb/>
have heard Mr. Wilmot say he preferred <lb/>
a Legislative Union to a Federal
Union. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">MR. SMITH</persName> —You
(Mr. Wilmot) <lb/>
never said before the Council that you <lb/>
was not opposed to the abstract
principle <lb/>
of union of British North
America. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName>.—I
did and am author<lb break="no"/>ized
by Judge Allen to say so. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:FISH1">MR. FISHER</persName> —My
hon. friend says <lb/>
          the mere
question
of union in itself<lb/>
          
            <cb/>
    
 amounts to nothing. I would ask him<lb/>
           what he means by the eleventh paragraph<lb/>
           in the Address? <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">Mr.
GlLLMOR</persName>.—The time has not <lb/>
come to explain that. It explains itself. <lb/>
We are now considering a vote of
want of <lb/>
confidence. ( <persName ref="pers:ANON1">A member</persName>,—You as it is <lb/>
a mere dodge.) I say the question of <lb/>
abstract union is a mere dodge to catch <lb/>
somebody—for it means anything, or <lb/>
nothing. It is a phrase manufactured to <lb/>
meet every person's view, and bring them <lb/>
in to work on a majority against the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. Do you suppose, Mr. Speaker, <lb/>
that the Province will ever be called upon <lb/>
to decide the question of union without <lb/>
going into the details and
conditions ? <lb/>
Some are for the Quebec Scheme,
some <lb/>
for union in the abstract, and some oppos<lb break="no"/>ed to both these, but are opposed to the <lb/>
Government, and they hope, by this dodg<lb break="no"/>ing, to carry a majority on this amend<lb break="no"/>ment. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> My hon. friend (Mr. McClelan) states <lb/>
that dame rumor say the
Government <lb/>
have made a great many offers of office to <lb/>
hold a majority on this vote.
Dame ru<lb break="no"/>mor now says the Opposition have pro<lb break="no"/>mised all the offices, should they succeed, <lb/>
and are now offering six hundred pounds <lb/>
for a vote. ( <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Mr. Fisher</persName>,—Did my
hon. <lb/>
friend say I have offered
anybody an <lb/>
office? I challenge him to
produce
the <lb/>
man to whom I have offered
office or <lb/>
money.) Dame rumor says they have
<lb/>
filled, in prospective, all the offices,
and <lb/>
are now offering money. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> There are no persons more liberal <lb/>
than those who have nothing to give. <lb/>
I am quite sure that the Government <lb/>
would not insult any hon. member by <lb/>
holding out any offer as a bribe, and <lb/>
am sure there is no constituency
that <lb/>
has sent any men mean enough to sell<lb/>
himself. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> There are very extraordinary efforts<lb/>
being made to prolong this debate in <lb/>
order that some fortuitous circumstance <lb/>
may turn up to help the
Opposition. lf <lb/>
it is true that such liberal
offers
have <lb/>
been made in the anticipated new Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, the liberality of the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion is much like the man who was ex<lb break="no"/>ceedingly willing to give away milk <lb/>
after his cows went dry. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The Opposition have to get the pre<lb break="no"/>sent Government out, and then get in <lb/>
themselves, before they have anything
<lb/>
to give, and before that is done there is <lb/>
rather a serious operation to go<lb/>
through.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:KERR1">MR.
KERR</persName>. After this very exciting<lb/>
discussion, which has taken us by sur<lb break="no"/>prise. I may say it is a wonder how <lb/>
the Government have so long held
to<lb break="no"/>gether, when we know the difference of <lb/>
opinion they have maintained on almost <lb/>
all questions; it is surprising
how they <lb/>
were enabled to come together and sit <lb/>
at the some Council board. I have been <lb/>
in the House fourteen yours. The Pre<lb break="no"/>sident of the Council came in the same <lb/>
day that I did. He has had the sweets <lb/>
of office, and l have been left out in the <lb/>
cold. I regret the warmth to which the <lb/>
debate has given rise. It is not
desira<lb break="no"/>ble we should have such scenes, more <lb/>
especially between those who have the <lb/>
destinies of this Province in their charge <lb/>
to a large extent. I did hope—after <lb/>
the Hon. Provincial Secretary had <lb/>
stated in the House that he would not <lb/>
say hard things, as he was too well
<lb/>
bred for that—he would
not
have gone <lb/>
to the extreme length to which he has. <lb/>
I think there
was some things he might <lb/>
       
            <cb/>

         have omitted without marring the<lb/>
beauty of his speech. He has thrown<lb/>
a bomb shell among the members of the <lb/>
Government, causing them to reveal the <lb/>
secrets of the Council Chamber of last <lb/>
season, and if these scenes
were fre<lb break="no"/>uent there must have been some
hard <lb/>
feelings. I am not surprised that
there <lb/>was difference of opinion there.
I be<lb break="no"/>lieve this Government was formed upon<lb/>
one single idea. The most discordant<lb/>
elements were brought together, and <lb/>
the members of the Government scarce<lb break="no"/>ly agreed upon any question except anti- <lb break="yes"/>Confederation. I regret the dissolution<lb/>
of the Assembly took place. I believe <lb/>
if the House had met last winter, and <lb/>
the subject of Confederation had been <lb/>
discussed. and the debates had gone <lb/>
abroad in the country, people would <lb/>
have understood the arguments for
and <lb/>
against that great question,
and at the <lb/>
next election we would have had the <lb/>
matter settled one way or the other. <lb/>
Confederation is the main question now, <lb/>
for every speaker has said more or less <lb/>
about it. Before the last election, I, <lb/>
like man others, was undecided <lb/>
whether the Scheme propoundcd in <lb/>
Quebec was one this country should <lb/>
adopt, but I thought that disturbance <lb/>
might take place, as it was expected <lb/>
that at the 0 me of the American war,<lb/>
disbanded soldiers who were without <lb/>
employment might create disturbance
<lb/>
on our borders, and if we did all in our <lb/>
power to assist ourselves by entering
<lb/>
into confederation which was highly <lb/>
approved of in England, the whole <lb/>
power of the nation would be put forth <lb/>
for our assistance. I did not think this <lb/>
union was going to give us such great<lb/>
prosperity as some predicted,
neither did <lb/>
I think it would bring desolation
und <lb/>
ruin on this Province. No great change <lb/>
of this kind is ever made without a <lb/>
great deal of dissatisfaction
being ex<lb break="no"/>pressed by the minority. In Scotland <lb/>
there was no dissolution of the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture when the union with England was <lb/>
effected, and since that union
has been <lb/>
consummated, that country has pros<lb break="no"/>pered as well as any other portion of <lb/>
the world, although the representation <lb/>
of that country in Parliament is very <lb/>
small. In Ireland union was not <lb/>
brought about by an appeal to the peo<lb break="no"/>ple. Union appears to o the order of <lb/>
the day; we have union in commercial
<lb/>
matters, union in Australia and the <lb/>
Cape Coast Colonies. lt has been<lb/>
stated that union is strength. It cer<lb break="no"/>tainly would be strength for a poor <lb/>
country like this to be joined
to a large <lb/>
wealthy country. And it is my opinion <lb/>
that the confederation of these colonies
<lb/>
must ultimately take place. After the <lb/>
election no man was qualified to sit in <lb/>
council, or fit for any office throughout <lb/>
the country, unless he was known as an <lb/>
anti-Confederate. In the North there <lb/>
was only one member chosen to
repre<lb break="no"/>sent the whole of the Northern Coun<lb break="no"/>ties. where we have had three during <lb/>
the last ten or fifteen years,
all men of <lb/>
ability. I do not mean to say the pre<lb break="no"/>sent member is not capable, for I be<lb break="no"/>lieve there are few better
business men <lb/>
in the Province. He is a strong Con<lb break="no"/>servative, and is a man that will think <lb/>
and act for himself; but there
were <lb/>
other men in the North quite as com<lb break="no"/>petent to have taken a seat at the <lb/>
Council Board. We have been left with<lb/>
only one gentleman in tho Council, and <lb/>
that gentleman attending to his
business <lb/>

            <pb n="50" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_050.jpg"/>
           
<fw type="num">50</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 

       in England, so that we have not a sin<lb break="no"/>gle member in the Government at pre<lb break="no"/>sent. ( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. Smith</persName> —No injustice will <lb/>
be done to the North.) I am glad to <lb/>
hear it, but I am very sceptical about it. <lb/>
I have been for many years in opposi<lb break="no"/>tion to the Government, but I have al<lb break="no"/>ways been ready to give them a <lb/>
hearty support in any measure which<lb/>
I believed to be right They have not<lb/>
done right in leaving the important<lb/>
office of Auditor General unfilled. The<lb/>
accounts may have been well audited,<lb/>
the gentleman who occupies the office<lb/>
may have discharged his duty faithfully,<lb/>
but I do not think, as the matter stands,<lb/>
he can make such a report of the ac<lb break="no"/>counts as ought to have the entire con<lb break="no"/>fidence of the country. He is not fur<lb break="no"/>nished with the materials to examine the<lb/>
accounts in such a way as ought to be<lb/>
done. Then again, we have reason to<lb/>
find fault with the Government for in<lb break="no"/>curring the heavy expense of delega<lb break="no"/>tion to England on a useless mission.<lb/>
A despatch was written the 12th of<lb/>
April last, to be laid before this House.<lb/>
That despatch must have been received<lb/>
at the opening of the Legislature, and<lb/>
any person looking at it would say,<lb/>
that anything we could do by delegation<lb/>
could be effected by a despatch of the<lb/>
Government. They certainly have not<lb/>
done anything to change the views of<lb/>
the Bristish Government on confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. In order to carry out that dele<lb break="no"/>gation, the country had to give up the<lb/>
services of the Attorney General for<lb/>
three months, and incur an expense of<lb/>
£700, which is a large sum of money to<lb/>
throw away without receiving an equiv<lb break="no"/>alent. I spoke and voted against that<lb/>
delegation, and I disapprove of it yet<lb/>
There is a matter connected with out<lb/>
debentures, coupons, and other matters<lb/>
lying in various hands. He might have<lb/>
made some arrangements about having<lb/>
them taken up and destroyed, but I fear<lb/>
it was not done. There are £17,000 of<lb/>
our debentures which fall due the 1st<lb/>
April, and we have debentures lying in<lb/>
St. John which are not accessible to the<lb/>
public. A large amount of money will<lb/>
be required which will have to be paid<lb/>
in new debentures, and those new de<lb break="no"/>bentures should be sold in this country<lb/>
so as to save so much interest to the<lb/>
country.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">MR. GILLMOR</persName> —Is my hon. friend<lb/>
not aware that there are £16,000 in de<lb break="no"/>bentures in the treasury at St. John<lb/>
which have been there four weeks.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:KERR1">MR. KERR</persName>.—I am aware of that<lb/>
fact. I took down money to purchase<lb/>
some of those debentures, and was told<lb/>
no person was authorized to sell them.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">MR. GILLMOR</persName>.—Those debentures are<lb/>
kept in the treasury for the purpose of<lb/>
exchanging them for those that fall due<lb/>
in May. We had no occasion to raise<lb/>
money upon them. If our debentures<lb/>
were absorbed in New Brunswick we<lb/>
would not have to draw £5,000 sterling<lb/>
               <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> the
interest on our rail<lb break="no"/>road <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> along
Canada being in<lb/>
debt, are we not £6,000,000 in debt, and<lb/>
only <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> piece
of railroad to show<lb/>
for it. ( <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. Needham</persName>—who built it?)<lb/>
A larger amount of money was ex<lb break="no"/>pended in building it than it was worth<lb/>
and it <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
upon the Province<lb/>
for <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> debt
of £70,000 currency<lb/>
annually, which was what we owe<lb/>
besides, gives us a debt for which we<lb/>
have to pay £88,000 per annum. This<lb/>
is a heavy charge for the few public<lb/>
        
            <cb/>
         
works we have. We are owing that <lb/>
     
          money, and when that money is falling <lb/>
due we should look ahead and see where <lb/>
the means are to come from to pay
it.
<lb/>
There should be no default in paying the <lb/>
interest in England, for if they lose con<lb break="no"/>fidence in us, our debentures will go
<lb/>
down in the British market. I desire <lb/>
to see these debentures placed where <lb/>
the people can get them, if that can be<lb/>
done without any risk of the public<lb/>
funds of the country. We hear a great<lb/>
deal said about the theory of union. I<lb/>
do not know what this theory is. There<lb/>
was a delegation appointed last session<lb/>
to effect a union of the Maritime Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces. I do not know whether it was<lb/>
done to keep up some sort of appear<lb break="no"/>ance, or whether there was any inten<lb break="no"/>tion to effect such a nation. I have never<lb/>
heard of anything being done.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. MR. SMITH</persName> —It was distinctly<lb/>
understood that we were requested to do<lb/>
it by Nova Scotia.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:KERR1">MR. KERR</persName> —That may be the case,<lb/>
but it stands recorded upon the Journals<lb/>
of our House. We have no assurance<lb/>
that they intend to bring down any scheme<lb/>
of union, and as I believe Confederation<lb/>
must ultimately be carried, I intend to<lb/>
give my assistance to any improvement<lb/>
upon the Quebec Scheme; but at the<lb/>
same time I believe the Quebec Scheme<lb/>
as it is, is better for us than to be alone.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CORA1">MR. CORAM</persName> —I am here to-day an<lb/>
independent representative of the City and<lb/>
County of St. John. I have no other ob<lb break="no"/>jects in supporting any Government than<lb/>
the best interests of my country. What<lb/>
is the indictment brought against this<lb/>
Government? A great many arguments<lb/>
have been brought forward by members<lb/>
on both sides, and a great many charges<lb/>
made in a rambling way, without proving<lb/>
one single point. I cannot see why the<lb/>
present Government cannot carry on the<lb/>
business of the country as well as a new<lb/>
Government could. If I have not been<lb/>
misinformed, the mover of the Amend<lb break="no"/>ment has always been finding fault and<lb/>
bringing a vote of want of confidence<lb/>
against every Government of which he is<lb/>
not a member himself. This being the<lb/>
leader that some other gentlemen have.<lb/>
I was elected to oppose the Quebec<lb/>
Scheme, and I am in the confidence of<lb/>
those who sent me here. If I change my<lb/>
views, it is my duty to tender my resig<lb break="no"/>nation; until I do that, I will carry out<lb/>
the views of those who sent me here by<lb/>
supporting the present Government.<lb/>
When we look at the indictment and lift<lb/>
the veil, we see nothing but Confederation<lb/>
under it, and the object is to carry out<lb/>
the Quebec Scheme as it was, is, and<lb/>
shall be. We should not go into Confed<lb break="no"/>eration until the route of the Intercolo<lb break="no"/>nial Railroad is settled and put under<lb/>
seal, so that it cannot be altered. A<lb/>
reason given why we should go into Con<lb break="no"/>federation is that we would be better pro<lb break="no"/>tected; we would have soldiers sent down<lb/>
to guard us by night against Fenians.<lb/>
I do not believe there would be one<lb/>
             <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> down from
Canada to defend<lb/>
               <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> New
Brunswick. Will going<lb/>
into Confederation make us more loyal?<lb/>
No, I am just as loyal as ever <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
               <lb/>
for I am prepared to <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
               <lb/>
defend the <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
               <lb/>
and the liberty <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
               <lb/>
this <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
               <lb/>
results will allow <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
               <lb/>
all men to live in friendship and move, in<lb break="no"/>stead of hatred and strife. It is our duty to<lb/>
        
            <cb/>
         
protect all men when we can, whether <lb/>
they are Protestants or
Catholics, but if <lb/>
they come against the laws of my coun<lb break="no"/>try, I will put them down. A charge
<lb/>
brought against the Government is the <lb/>
great expense of the delegation going to <lb/>
England. At the last sitting of the Le<lb break="no"/>gislature a majority of the
House decid<lb break="no"/>ed to send a delegation to England,
and <lb/>
they went according to the wishes of the <lb/>
House and the people. Why should we <lb/>
condemn the Government, before the <lb/>
correspondence between the Government <lb/>
and the Mother Country is laid before the<lb/>
House? They have not brought any ev<lb break="no"/>idence to prove they have done wrong in <lb/>
this particular. When the documents <lb/>
are produced, if they have not done ac<lb break="no"/>cording to the wishes of the people, I <lb/>
will vote against them. I will
try them <lb/>
before condemning them. I like to see fair <lb/>
play and justice dealt out to
every man. <lb/>
With regards to railroads, that is a ques<lb break="no"/>tion with which I will deal when it comes <lb/>
before the House in proper shape. When<lb/>
they are called upon for the
agreement in <lb/>
regard to Western Extension, then
I
will <lb/>
do my best to sustain them or go against <lb/>
theme as I think proper. Another com<lb break="no"/>plaint was, why was not the
House called <lb/>
together sooner? Where is the damage <lb/>
done? We know the Attorney General <lb/>
was at Washington negotiating regarding <lb/>
the Reciprocity Treaty, and we should <lb/>
not condemn him betore he brings his do<lb break="no"/>cuments before the Home so that we <lb/>
can see whether he has carricd out the <lb/>
trust reposed in him. On these grounds<lb/>
I think the indictments are wrong, there<lb break="no"/>fore I cannot condemn the
Government <lb/>
without a fair trial.<lb/>
            </p>


            <p> <persName ref="pers:SCOV1">MR. SCOVIL</persName> —As we are progressing
<lb/>
so slow
in this debate, I will occupy but <lb/>
little time. I am not in the habitat of ma<lb break="no"/>king long speeches to place myself be<lb break="no"/>fore my constituents. When this
House <lb/>
was first formed, the people were called <lb/>
upon to decide one of the greatest ques<lb break="no"/>tions that ever came before them. They <lb/>
gave their decision, and we were
returned <lb/>
by a two-thirds majority, to oppose this <lb/>
Quebec Scheme, which was a scheme <lb/>
          propounded by the wise men of the dif<lb break="no"/>ferent Provinces, and laid before
the <lb/>
people of this Province for them
to accept. <lb/>
When the House was dissolved, I was <lb/>
determined not to offer as a
candidate on <lb/>
that occasion, but from the pressure
of <lb/>
circumstances, I came to the conclusion <lb/>
that, as this question was
agitating the <lb/>
minds of the people, and they having
<lb/>
elected me three times before, I would<lb/>
come forward and advocate my princi<lb break="no"/>ples, and they returned me. My hon.<lb/>
friend (Mr. Kerr) says if this Government<lb/>
was turned out, the prospects of Confed<lb break="no"/>eration would be almost certain. He has <lb/>
good reason for saying so, and I
look <lb/>
upon him with honor, as carrying out the<lb/>
principles advocated by him on the hust<lb break="no"/>ings. When I came forward to advocate <lb/>
my principles, I declared myself an anti- Confederate, and my reason for going<lb/>
against this amendment is to maintain<lb/>
those persons in <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>, who have taken<lb/>
the charge of the Province. <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
               <lb/>
thing to induce me <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> mind of<lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> this scheme of Confederation <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
should be in favor of the Quebec Scheme<lb/>
I would not enter this House, for I <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> it my duty to resign my <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
               <lb/>
               <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> these boards <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear><lb/>
<unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> their own <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
               <lb/>
but they tell them they are now in power,<lb/>
and they will have Confederation
though<lb/>
            



            <pb n="51" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-23_Page_051.jpg"/>
         
 <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">51</fw>

       elected to oppose
the scheme. Among <lb/>
all their indictments, I cannot see that <lb/>
one has been sustained. I cannot see <lb/>
one reason for turning out the present
<lb/>
Government. It is true, since they came
<lb/>
into power there has been a
continual cry <lb/>
throughout the country that the people <lb/>
had changed their minds about
Confed<lb break="no"/>eration. In the County of King's, if <lb/>
there is any change, it is rather against <lb/>
the scheme. I admit there has been <lb/>
an oversight in not observing that the <lb/>
Export Duty Law was about to
expire. <lb/>
Of that overnight the Government have <lb/>
taken the responsibility and the
difficulty <lb/>
has been remedied without the loss of a <lb/>
single dollar. If they have been guilty <lb/>
of the omission, they might well be ex<lb break="no"/>cused under the circumstances.
There <lb/>
was a continual pressure brought to bear <lb/>
upon them from Canada, England, and <lb/>
the Confederates of this
Province; and <lb/>
the press has been most unscrupulous. <lb/>
The Provincial Secretary has said all I <lb/>
had to say about them, and I agree with <lb/>
every word he said concerning
them. <lb/>
My hon. friend from Carleton (Mr. Lind<lb break="no"/>say) has said the British
Government <lb/>
wished us to enter into Confederation.
<lb/>
I look upon this question as one for the <lb/>
people of New Brunswick to decide. I<lb/>
do not believe we are to be dictated to <lb/>
even by the British Government, and we <lb/>
should not submit to Downing Street <lb/>
dictation. I have heard the hon. mover <lb/>
of the amendment harangue the House in <lb/>
former times, complaining of the
Govern<lb break="no"/>ment being led by Downing Street dic<lb break="no"/>tation. My hon. friend has told us that<lb/>
if we were loyal subjects of Great Britain, <lb/>
we would submit to any thing. ( <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. <lb/>
Lindsay</persName>,—I said loyalty
consisted in <lb/>
obedience.) When I speak of the Queen <lb/>
I speak with respect; but those men in <lb/>
office are no more than we are. They <lb/>
may be there to-day and out to-morrow. <lb/>
What does Mr. Cardwell know
about the <lb/>
benefits arising from Confederation? The <lb/>
people have told Mr. Cardwell that they <lb/>
do not want Confederation. but still the <lb/>
scheme is agitated; and we have the for<lb break="no"/>ty-second member of the House going <lb/>
through the length and breadth of the
<lb/>
land, lecturing the people upon the bene<lb break="no"/>fits of the scheme—a professional poli<lb break="no"/>tician, with nothing to do but to
stir up <lb/>
people's minds about Confederation. He <lb/>
is now on the floors of the House,
or the <lb/>
next thing to it. l heard, my hon. friend <lb/>
(Mr. Wetmore) talk about the stuffing <lb/>
process. I think he is getting
as much <lb/>
stuffing as any other hon. member in <lb/>
this House, and I think my hon. friend <lb/>
from Westmorland is getting stuffed <lb/>
too. </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName>.—My
hon. friend re<lb break="no"/>fers to stuffing. I shall be haupy to hear <lb/>
him go on and tell how the Government </p>
            <p>are stuffing him.<lb/>
            </p>
 
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SCOV1">MR. SCOVlL</persName>.—l will tell him that no <lb/>
Government is stuffing me. I did not <lb/>
come into this House to seek for office.<lb/>
( <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName>—They stuff you, and you <lb/>
don't know it.) I have common sense, <lb/>
and I do not allow the Attorney General <lb/>
or the forty-second member to stuff me. <lb/>
Those individuals who are looking up <lb/>
with their mouths open, getting stuffed, <lb/>
will have to disgorge, to explain them<lb break="no"/>selves to their constituency. <lb/>
            </p>
 
            <p> There has
been a great cry raised about
<lb/>
a Minute of Council, signed by the mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Government and addressed to <lb/>
Mr. Cardwell, whom the hon. mover of <lb/>
the amendment wishes to bow down
to and<lb/>
worship. I saw this dispatch and thought <lb/>
      
            <cb/>
      
it a well-written article. I read that
dis<lb break="no"/>patch over to a person who had
told me<lb/>
it was one of the worst documents he<lb/>
ever saw. But before I got through, he <lb/>
said the country ought to be proud that <lb/>
they had seven men, such men in the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, who would honestly express <lb/>
their opinions.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I was always in favor of union, and <lb/> when the Quebec Scheme came up, I<lb/>
                  tried, if possible, to agree with it. I<lb/> sifted it, and came to the conclusion
                  that <lb/> New Brunswick would be nowhere under <lb/> that scheme; for under it, I
                  do not be<lb break="no"/>lieve the rights and interests of the people <lb/> are
                  protected. ( <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. Lindsay</persName>,—How,<lb/> then,
                  can you eulogize the men who said <lb/> they were opposed to a union of the <lb/>
                  Provinces?) I gave them credit for <lb/> using those strong terms. We do not <lb/>
                  want any closer union with Canada, un<lb break="no"/>less we see the rights of the
                  people pro<lb break="no"/>tected. ( <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr.
                     Wetmore</persName>,—Did you say, <lb/> during the election, that you were in
                  favor <lb/> of union?) We had the Quebec Scheme, <lb/> and we had to allow the
                  whole of it or <lb/> reject it. I told the people that l looked <lb/> upon a union
                  of the colonies as advan<lb break="no"/>tageous, but I did all I could to satisfy
                  <lb/> the people that the Quebec Scheme was <lb/> not the scheme for New
                  Brunswick; and <lb/> I should be recreant to my trust if I <lb/> went against
                  those men who formed this <lb/> Government on those principles, for if <lb/> they
                  were ousted, I have no doubt but it <lb/> would be an advantage to the scheme. I
                  <lb/> believe people are apt to change their mind.<lb/> I have changed my mind in
                  some things. <lb/> I was a young politician when I came <lb/> here, and in the
                  course of my political life <lb/> in this House, I always condemned <lb/> a
                  Government for dismissing good public <lb/> servants to put others in their place,
                  but <lb/> I have got to be almost a smasher on <lb/> that point. I used to think
                  the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment would live down such opposition, <lb/> but I
                  believe now that when a public offi<lb break="no"/>cer goes out to canvass, and
                  uses his <lb/> office for a canvassing shop, he should be <lb/> turned out of his
                  office at once. ( <persName ref="pers:DESB2">Mr. L. <lb/> P. W.
                     DesBrisay</persName>.—I would ask him how <lb/> he supports a Government that
                  is unable <lb/> to turn out even the meanest man holding <lb/> an office in this
                  Province?) <lb/>
               </p>

            <p> There was then some conversation he- <lb break="yes"/>
tween <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. Wetmore</persName> and <persName ref="pers:SCOV1">Mr. Scovil</persName> re<lb break="no"/>garding the appointment in offices, and <lb/>
bribery, after which the debate was then <lb/>
adjurned until 12 o'clock to-morrow. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SCOV1">MR.
SCOVlL</persName>. by leave, brought in a <lb/>
Bill to change the Constitution of the <lb/>
Legislative Council, after which the <lb/>
House was adjourned until 10 A. M. to<lb break="no"/>morrow <lb/></p>


<p rendition="simple:right">T. P. D.</p>
         
<!-- GL, 2016-11-18, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->


           <!-- <p> SATURDAY,
MARCH 24. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> MR. BOYD called
attention to a para<lb break="no"/>graph in the Morning News—which
he <lb/>
read—reflecting upon his popularity as a <lb/>
militia officer, and asserting
that he had <lb/>
been superseded. So far he said from <lb/>
being the most unpopular officer in the <lb/>
militia; he would take it upon himself to <lb/>
say that there was not a more popular <lb/>
office in the service. Instead of
super<lb break="no"/>seding him, the Government had asked
<lb/>
him if he could conveniently
take com<lb break="no"/>mand of his battalion at this time. He <lb/>
(Mr. Boyd)
had told His Excellency that <lb/>
he could not, and His Excellency then <lb/>
said, if he could not go, he would send<lb/>
another office to take command in his<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>

            <p> place. The statements in the News were <lb/>
a parcel of the greatest lies
ever fabrica<lb break="no"/>ted. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> HON MR.
HATHEWAY called the <lb/>
attention of the House to a
statement in <lb/>
an article in the Fredericton Reporter in <lb/>
which he (Hon. Mr. Hatheway) was
made
<lb/>
to say that His Excellentcy had entrusted
<lb/>
him with this formation of the
Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. He gave that statement a flat con<lb break="no"/>tradiction. The editor or reporter of that <lb/>
paper in which it appearered, having
sat <lb/>
through the debate, must have known
it <lb/>
to be un'trua What he had said
was that<lb/>
His Excellency had called upon him to<lb/>
form an administration, but he declined.<lb/>
            </p>



            <p> House went into Committee of the<lb/>
Whole on a Bill to amend the act to in-<lb break="maybe"/>
corperate
the Albert Railway Company. <lb/>
            </p>


            <p> MR. KERR spoke first (but owing to <lb/>
noise in the House we could not catch <lb/>
the exact purport of his observations). <lb/>
He called the attention of the Attorney <lb/>
General to the Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> ATTORNEY GENERAL said the <lb/>
observations of the hon. member of Nor<lb break="no"/>thumberland showed better than any ob<lb break="no"/>servations he could make the effect
of <lb/>
going into Confederation under the <lb/>
Quebec Scheme, with its cardinal prin<lb break="no"/>ciple of representation by population. <lb/>
It was said there was no danger of the <lb/>
Province with its limited representation <lb/>
being swamped. But here at home in the <lb/>
attitude assumed by that hon. member in <lb/>
this Bill, Was an illustration on a small <lb/>
scale of what would happen to
the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince under Confederation. It
had been <lb/>
said that if the Province went into Con<lb break="no"/>federation, that it would not be taxed <lb/>
for the construction of Canals
in
Cana<lb break="no"/>da, for it would have a voice in the mat<lb break="no"/>ter. But how, with an overwhelming <lb/>
Canadian majority, and on questions af<lb break="no"/>fecting Canadian interests, could the re<lb break="no"/>presentatives of the Province protect
it <lb/>
against large expenditures. With re<lb break="no"/>gard to the Bill under consideration, its <lb/>
object was simply to extend the time <lb/>
given to the Company to construct the <lb/>
railway from two to five years. The Sub<lb break="no"/>sidy Act under which the Company was <lb/>
formed was now the lay of the land; <lb/>
there was no limitation to it. It was no <lb/>
act of grace; therefore to give any Com<lb break="no"/>pany the privileges of the Bill; it was a
le<lb break="no"/>gislative right. He thought the
Com<lb break="no"/>pany ought to have the extension
of time; <lb/>
they were expecting aid from England, <lb/>
and the result would, he anticipated, be <lb/>
the construction of the railway. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> MR. CONNELL
had no objection to <lb/>
support the Bill. With reference
to the <lb/>
objections raised by the hon. member of<lb/>
Northumberland (Mr. Kerr), he thought <lb/>
that the people of the North
Shore were <lb/>
much more able to take advantage
of the <lb/>
Subsidy Act, and build a railway in that <lb/>
district, than the people of St. Stephen<lb/>
and Woodstock to construct their bran<lb break="no"/>ches. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> MR. HILL doubted
very much the pol<lb break="no"/>icy of incurring large debts for railways;
<lb/>
he had always thought that railways
<lb/>
should not be built faster than the inter<lb break="no"/>ests of the Province required. Though<lb/>
opposed to the principle, yet
now that <lb/>
the Province had adopted the course of<lb/>
construction of railways under
the  Subsi<lb break="no"/>dy Act,
he thought that fair
play to these <lb/>
sections that had not yet taken
advantage<lb/>
of that Act demanded that they should<lb/>
not now go back. He was <unclear n="">?</unclear>
               <lb/>
            </p>-->
</div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>