<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1865-05-01"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-05-01">1 May 1865</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1865</title>.
                    


     <date when="1865"/>.  



          <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="11" to="17"/>.

        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_011.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_012.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_013.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_014.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_015.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_016.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_017.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2017-11-16">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2017-11-16">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_011">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_011.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_012">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_012.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_013">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_013.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_014">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_014.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_015">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_015.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_016">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_016.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_017">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_017.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="11" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_011.jpg"/>
            <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">11</fw>

<!-- GL, 2017-11-16, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

<!--<p>
     make it pay four, we should go on at 
     <lb/>once. If it does not pay but two per<lb/>cent, the wealth coming into the country<lb/>will make it up by indirect means. It<lb/>will come through the community at large,<lb/>as well as if it came directly. I must<lb/>support the resolution, because I consider<lb/>that it will forward Western Extension,<lb/>which will be a benefit to the whole com-<lb break="yes"/>unity.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Adjourned to 9 a.m. Monday 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     T.P.D.    
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     Monday, May 1. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Mr. BOYD</persName> moved for leave to bring in 
     <lb/>a Bill for the preservation of Deer on the <lb/>Island of Grand Manan, and also present<lb break="no"/>ed a petition from certain parties, that an<lb/>Act may pass providing for the same. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Hon. Mr. ALLEN</persName> moved for leave to 
     <lb/>bring in a Bill to authorize the erection of<lb/>a Sorting Room near the lower bridge on<lb/>the Nashwaak.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName> moved for leave to bring          
     <lb/>in a Bill to provide for Simultaneous Elec<lb break="no"/>tions throughout the Province<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SUTT1">Mr. SUTTON</persName> asked the Speaker if any                  
     <lb/>provision had been made for the services<lb/>of a Law Clerk.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> had no information on the                     
     <lb/>subject.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName> said, he understood that a       
     <lb/>gentleman was now engaged drafting<lb/>Bills for the members of the House, and<lb/>he would like to know whether he was<lb/>engaged by the House, or by private<lb/>members.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Mr. BOYD</persName> was in favor of the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of a Law Clerk. Although he had<lb/>personally been very successful in draw<lb break="no"/>ing up Bills, yet he believed that the ser<lb break="no"/>vices of a competent Clerk would greatly<lb/>facilitate the business of the Session. <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName> never thought a Law               
     <lb/>Clerk necessary, and did not think there<lb/>had been one till the last House had cre<lb break="no"/>ated the office. The honorable members<lb/>composing the present House were pre<lb break="no"/>sumed to be wise and discreet, and he<lb/>thought quite competent to draft their<lb/>own Bills, and as he believed every unne<lb break="no"/>cessary expense should be reduced, he<lb/>would draw up a resolution that ser<lb break="no"/>vices of a Law Clerk be dispensed with.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SUTT1">Mr. SUTTON</persName> thought it hardly neces<lb break="no"/>sary to bring in a motion to dispense with<lb/>the office, for, so far as this House was<lb/>concerned, no such office was in exist<lb break="no"/>ence. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName> said, it was very easy               
     <lb/>to ascertain the opinion of the House on the<lb/>question, and he would, therefore, move<lb/>that it is not desirable that the office of<lb/>Law Clerk, created by the last House, be<lb/>continued. <lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName> said, it would be ab<lb break="no"/>surd to pass such a resolution, as it was<lb/>well understood that the offices created<lb/>by the last House had nothing whatever<lb/>to do with the present.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName> said if the House so un<lb break="no"/>derstood it, he would withdraw his mo<lb break="no"/>tion.<lb/>
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Mr. BOYD</persName> then moved that a Law Clerk 
     <lb/>be employed to prepare Bills for this<lb/>House.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName> said, that in doing away   
     <lb/>with that office, the House would not be<lb/>acting right towards many of the mem<lb break="no"/>bers. Those engaged in agricultural pur<lb break="no"/>suits, and others, were not so able at legal<lb/>forms as the honorable member for West<lb break="no"/>morland. The argumentative talents, and<lb/>legal knowledge of that gentleman were<lb/>not shared by some others, and there<lb/>were members who were young in the<lb/>House who would find it difficult to draft<lb/>a Bill without the aid of a Law Clerk.<lb/>
        

            <cb/>
       

     He should, therefore, vote for the resolu<lb break="no"/>tion.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On division, the motion was negatived.   
     <lb/>The House, on motion of Mr. OTTY,<lb/>took up the order of the day, and the dis<lb break="no"/>cussion on the Address in Reply. <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     
     FIFTH PARAGRAPH, AND MR. KERR'S       
     <lb/>AMENDMENT RESUMED.<lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName>.— I mentioned to the 
     <lb/>House on Saturday, that I thought there<lb/>
was nothing in the existing law on the <lb/>
Statute Book to prevent the Government<lb/>
taking action with regard to Railway Ex<lb break="no"/>tension. On looking over the law, I can<lb break="no"/>not find anything that would directly pre<lb break="no"/>vent them. But then there is no law to<lb/>prevent murder, but simply to punish<lb/>those who commit that crime. Al<lb break="no"/>though there is nothing in the law to pre<lb break="no"/>vent the Government from carrying on<lb/>Railway extension, yet there is such a<lb/>thing as public faith, and if the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment entered into any arrangement<lb/>with parties to engage in the work, the <lb/>credit so pledged ought to be maintained.<lb/>On looking over the Facility Bill - some<lb break="no"/>times called the Lobster Bill - I find in<lb/>the fourth section, a certain bonus is given<lb/>to any company who, by conforming to<lb/>certain requirements, fulfil the terms of<lb/>the act. Under this Bill, passed by the <lb/>last House, a company was formed in St.<lb/>John, who obtained an act of Incorpora<lb break="no"/>tion, under the title of the European and<lb/>North American Railway Western Ex<lb break="no"/>tension Company. The Legislature held<lb/>out certain inducements which should ac<lb break="no"/>crue to parties complying with certain acts. <lb/>The company in St. John was formed, and<lb/>a large amount of stock secured, and be<lb break="no"/>fore Declaration day in St. John, it was<lb/>said that a gentleman - Mr. Parks - had<lb/>gone to England to get such stock taken<lb/>up there as would enable the company to <lb/>carry on the work. There is no doubt,<lb/>but that Mr. Parks has gone for that pur<lb break="no"/>pose, and the talents and energy possessed<lb/>by that gentleman leaves no room to sup<lb break="no"/>pose but that everything will be done to<lb/>accomplish the object of his mission. If<lb/>an individual makes a certain offer to ano<lb break="no"/>ther, and arranges to do certain things, if<lb/>certain acts are complied with, - if that<lb/>individual fails to fulfil the engagements<lb/>entered into, there is a Court of Chancery<lb/>through which the injured party can ob<lb break="no"/>tain redress for his grievances, but when<lb/>engagements are entered into with a<lb/>Government, and they fail to perform,<lb/>there is no redress; there is nothing but <lb/>the good faith of that Government to rely<lb/>on as a guarantee of the fulfillment of the<lb/>promises made. I feel assured that the<lb/>present Government are embarrassed in<lb/>their action by the engagements entered<lb/>into by the late Government, and that<lb/>there are certain rights existing under the<lb/>acts on the Statute Book which prevents<lb/>further legislation. I am glad that the<lb/>Government have, in as strong terms as<lb/>they could, held out to the people of the<lb/>country the promise of Western Exten<lb break="no"/>sion, as soon as circumstances will per<lb break="no"/>mit. If it was not for existing laws, and<lb/>engagements entered into under them, the<lb/>want of means to carry on the work would<lb/>not have been as great a barrier as some<lb/>seem to imagine. My only regret is, that<lb/>the Government could not proceed, but I<lb/>am satisfied they will do so as soon as<lb/>possible, and, therefore, under these cir<lb break="no"/>cumstances, shall vote that the paragraph<lb/>pass.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>.— The subject of Rail<lb break="no"/>ways has been before this country for a<lb/>long time. In 1837 the first move was<lb/>made, and from the time the first grant<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
         

     from the casual revenue was made down   
     <lb/>to the present, not a year has passed but<lb/>the subject has been discussed in this<lb/>House. It is much to be regretted that<lb/>the statement has been put forth here<lb/>that the legislation of the last Session is not<lb/>intended to be amended by the present<lb/>Government. I think the country looks<lb/>for this. I have always been in favor of <lb/>measure which like these tend to open<lb/>up and improve the country. True, at<lb/>the first there were great difficulties about<lb/>the St. John and Shediac Railway; but<lb/>gradually these were overcome, and now<lb/>we have that road. Still, in consequence<lb/>of having no connection at either end, it<lb/>is of little value to the country, as it in<lb break="no"/>volves a large expenditure of money<lb/>without any adequate return. It is satis<lb break="no"/>factory, however, to know that it is one<lb/>of the best constructed roads in British<lb/>North America. But it is not my pur<lb break="no"/>pose to go into the subject of that Rail<lb break="no"/>road. I believe it is necessary for the <lb/>prosperity of this country that the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment take some immediate action with<lb/>regard to the extension Westward. I do<lb/>not think the statement made by them in<lb/>the paragraph under discussion is a very<lb/>correct one. I should like to ask the<lb/>Government if they have made any effort<lb/>to ascertain the nature of the difficulties<lb/>spoken of, and if they cannot be removed.<lb/>I very much doubt if any difficulties <lb/>really exist to prevent further legislation<lb/>in this matter. Will the hon. member<lb/>for St. John tell the House whether it is<lb/>the intention of the people of the County<lb/>of St. John, who have taken up stock, to<lb/>raise obstacles to the carrying out of this<lb/>work? Is not the course laid down meant<lb/>rather to assist the Government to get<lb/>rid of the responsibility resting upon<lb/>them, which, I admit, is great? I believe<lb/>the Treasury is nearly empty - then why<lb/>do they speak of the improved state of<lb/>the finances of the country? I am sur<lb break="no"/>prised that the Government should have <lb/>laid the Speech of His Excellency on the<lb/>table without propounding to the House<lb/>the policy they intend to pursue. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve it is customary for the mover of the<lb/>Address to define the policy of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment and the course they intend to<lb/>pursue. I should have been pleased<lb/>to have heard the President of the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil state the policy and course of the<lb/>Government. He has not seen fit to do<lb/>so; but they come and lay the Speech<lb/>before us, and the only statement they<lb/>make in explanation of their intentions is<lb/>the introduction of a Bill for the aboli<lb break="no"/>tion of the office of the Postmaster General. <lb/>I do not now intend to speak on that sub<lb break="no"/>ject; but when it comes up I shall state<lb/>to the House the opinions I entertain as<lb/>to the importance of that office to the <lb/>commercial and financial interests of the<lb/>country. I would, however, ask if we<lb/>are to go back to the irresponsible mode<lb/>of carrying on the public business which<lb/>once existed here. If this Address pass,<lb/>the office of the Postmaster General goes<lb/>back into the hands of the parties who are<lb/>totally irresponsible to the country; and <lb/>I am prepared with facts and figures to<lb/>show that such a course would be most<lb/>destructive to the postal interests of the<lb/>Province. It is an office second to no<lb/>other. When I had the honor to hold <lb/>that office I performed the duties it in<lb break="no"/>volved, and carried into effect decisions<lb/>of the Council. I did not, however, on <lb/>every little matter consult with them, nor<lb/>should I if I held such an office again, for<lb/>I believe that it detracts from the further<lb break="no"/>ance of the interests of public business.<lb/>This is the only reform - but I call it de<lb break="no"/>
          

            <pb n="12" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_012.jpg"/>
<fw type="num">12</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>
          

struction—I see foreshadowed in reference 
     <lb/>to this matter. If the Government intend<lb/> to refer to the course to be pursued by the<lb/>heads of Departments, I hope they will<lb/>inform the country,— which is looking to<lb/>the House that something may be done— <lb/>that they will assume the country that<lb/>something <hi rendition="simple:italic">will</hi> be done to stop the tide<lb/>of emigration from this Province. Unless<lb/>some steps are taken by the develop<lb break="no"/>ment of resources of the country; un<lb break="no"/>less public works are inaugurated to im<lb break="no"/>prove the state of the country, young men<lb/>will leave as fast as they can: and I should<lb/>like to have seen some assurance given<lb/>that some measures would be introduced<lb/>for the good of this Province in this re<lb break="no"/>spect. It is said: Let them depend on <lb/>their own exertions; but when there is <lb/>little or nothing on which their exertions<lb/>can be effectually expended, they will go<lb/>away to places where they can do better.<lb/>Look at our Exports. The country once<lb/>depended on its lumber, but now almost<lb/>every move in that direction entails a loss.<lb/>I am sorry in looking over the Speech<lb/>to see nothing having reference to the <lb/>mineral resources of the country. The<lb/>time has come when these, if properly<lb/>fostered and encouraged by judicious le<lb break="no"/>gislation, would make a vast improve<lb break="no"/>ment in the labour and industry of this <lb/>Province. Look at the coal mines of Al<lb break="no"/>bert and Queen's Counties; is anything<lb/>being done to encourage the develop<lb break="no"/>ment of their riches? When in the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment I was instrumental in producing<lb/>a grant of $2000 to develop our mine<lb break="no"/>ral resources, and I now consider it to be<lb/>one of the first and most important points<lb/>to be looked after by a Government. Un<lb break="no"/>fortunately many of these mines are in <lb/>the hands of individuals who cannot work<lb/>them to advantage, (Hon. Mr. Smith; <lb/>" Would you take them out of their<lb/>hands?") I would do something to en<lb break="no"/>courage monied men to come to the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince and buy them, even if they had to <lb/>pay and exorbitant price for them, rather<lb/>than they should remain as they are. I <lb/>know gentlemen at the present time who<lb/>are willing to go into the working up of<lb/>the coal districts, but what would be the<lb/>use of spending five, ten or twenty thou<lb break="no"/>sand dollars without seeing a chance for<lb/>a return? I think the Government should<lb/>take hold of this matter.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Again, there is a large quantity of 
     <lb/>
     iron in the district in which I reside in<lb break="no"/>deed there the most valuable iron is found 
     <lb/>
     of any place in the Provinces. Where is 
     <lb/>
     every facility for working it, plenty of 
     <lb/>
     wood for firing, but what is the state of 
     <lb/>
     things, what is the fact? Last year a 
     <lb/>
     gentleman from England said to a gentle<lb break="no"/>man interested in the working of the 
     <lb/>mines and who was desirous of obtaining<lb/>the assistance of capitalists, "Your iron<lb/>is without doubt very valuable, there is <lb/>wood and every other requisite for the<lb/>working, but till we can ascertain by the <lb/>action of the Colonies that they intend to<lb/>provide for the defences of the country it <lb/>would not be safe to invest money in the <lb/>work." If we could have obtained Confe<lb break="no"/>deration there would have been no dif<lb break="no"/>ficulty. I believe that if the majority of <lb/>the people were able to express their opi<lb break="no"/>nion on that question to-day, they would <lb/>decide its favour. The people in the<lb/>section of the country where I reside know<lb/>the value that connection would have<lb/>been. I have often invited the President<lb/>of the Council to go up and visit that <lb/>part, and I now extend the invitation to<lb/>the Hon. Surveyor General. I hope he<lb/>will come and see for himself the value <lb/>of the mineral resources we possess and <lb/>
        

            <cb/>
       

     that the next Speech will have something 
     <lb/>
     to say about it. We have the iron, we 
     <lb/>
     have the wood and coal. and for three 
     <lb/>
     months in the year we have water com<lb break="no"/>munication but for the other nine months 
     <lb/>
     we no outlet for the productions of 
     <lb/>
     the country. Lumber with us is nearly 
     <lb/>
     run out, and it is to be hoped the peo<lb break="no"/>ple will now leave off a business not 
     <lb/>
     good for the country and engage in 
     <lb/>
     some operations that will prove more be<lb break="no"/>neficial. At the first we had a company 
     <lb/>
     at work, but their operations did not 
     <lb/>
     prove successtul. Now the company are 
     <lb/>
     working right. They have one furnace 
     <lb/>
     and another partially completed, but un<lb break="no"/>less they receive some assistance from the 
     <lb/>
     Government by opening up communica<lb break="no"/>tion it is doubtful if they will be long able 
     <lb/>
     to continue on. The expense of carry<lb break="no"/>ing on the works is very large; wood 
     <lb/>
     and coal can only be brought in at prices 
     <lb/>
     that make the labor unremunerative. 
     <lb/>
     This matter is most important. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—What, do you want 
     <lb/>
     a railway? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>.—Yes, we want you to 
     <lb/>
     build it now. The Government have not 
     <lb/>
     shewn to the country that I have done 
     <lb/>
     anything to remove the difficulties said to 
     <lb/>
     exist, which precludes them from carrying 
     <lb/>
     on Western Extension. It appears that 
     <lb/>
     the only way in which they are at all 
     <lb/>
     bound, is by the offer of Mr. Livesey to 
     <lb/>
     build the line to the Nova Scotia bound<lb break="no"/>ary. But what does that amount to? 
     <lb/>
     The offer was accepted on certain condi<lb break="no"/>tions, which have not yet been fulfilled. 
     <lb/>
     It seems that somebody has been at work 
     <lb/>
     in order to obtain the building of the line 
     <lb/>
     from the Bend through the County of 
     <lb/>
     Westmorland, and that that work is to go 
     <lb/>
     on, whatever else is done. This arrange<lb break="no"/>ment however, has nothing to do with 
     <lb/>
     Western Extension. I do not see that it 
     <lb/>
     stands in the way at all. If it does, I 
     <lb/>
     should like to see some paper from the 
     <lb/>
     last Government; shewing that difficulties 
     <lb/>
     really do exist. It is said with regard to 
     <lb/>
     the company formed in St. John, that the 
     <lb/>
     President, now in England, has written 
     <lb/>
     back that nothing can be done there. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HATH1">Hon. Mr. HATHEWAY</persName>.—Do you think 
     <lb/>
     that Mr. Tilley would now sell out his 
     <lb/>Stock?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>.—I believe he would, 
     <lb/>
     since it appears the company will not be 
     <lb/>
     able to go on. The arrangement with 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Livesey seems to be the only difficulty 
     <lb/>
     in the way, if a difficulty really exist. 
     <lb/>
     The railway in operation has been man<lb break="no"/>aged well, but the Government appear to 
     <lb/>
     desire to be relieved from all responsibili<lb break="no"/>ty with regard to extended works. Col. 
     <lb/>
       Boyd is the only member now in the 
     <lb/>
     House—Mr. Wilmot and I came in short<lb break="no"/>ly after—who heard the first speech made 
     <lb/>
     before this House by Sir. J. Harvey. He 
     <lb/>
     said his Government would lead the way, 
     <lb/>
     but it was for the Legislature to act.— 
     <lb/>
     I am glad to see that the President of the 
     <lb/>
     Council has changed his views on the 
     <lb/>
     question of railways. He has a perfect 
     <lb/>
     right to change his mind, and I hope he 
     <lb/>
     will change it on the subject of Confeder<lb break="no"/>ation. Whenever anything is said on 
     <lb/>
     this question, the honorable member 
     <lb/>
     looks over at me. It is said the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was formed on the principle of Con<lb break="no"/>federation. If such be the case, Mr.<lb/>Speaker, I appeal to you, whether a Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment founded on one question alone,<lb/>without a reference to the general inter<lb break="no"/>ests of the country, can have the confi<lb break="no"/>dence of the people. The honorable mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Northumberland has said that he<lb/>could not support the present Government<lb/>because of the conservative element in it.<lb/>
            </p>

            <cb/>
            <p>
       Mr. WILLISTON.—Mr. Speaker, I made 
     <lb/>
     no such observation. I merely said, that 
     <lb/>
     I could not support them in this matter. 
     <lb/>
     I could not vote for this part of the speech. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>.—If the honorable mem<lb break="no"/>ber did not say so, I stand corrected, al<lb break="no"/>though I was of opinion he did say it, but 
     <lb/>no matter. So far as the Government is 
     <lb/>concerned, it makes no difference to me 
     <lb/>now, that I am speaking in reference to 
     <lb/>their action with regard to their railway 
     <lb/>policy, for if they will go to work and 
     <lb/>carry out a good policy, I will support 
     <lb/>them. Ithink that something like the 
     <lb/>following, instead of the paragraph under 
     <lb/>debate, would have been more satisfactory 
     <lb/>to the people : " We will consider whe<lb break="no"/>ther further facilities can be afforded for 
     <lb/>the extension of Railways in this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince. We are pleased to learn that the 
     <lb/>completion and extension of the European 
     <lb/>and North American Railway, from the   
     <lb/>frontier of Nova Scotia to the boundary 
     <lb/>of the United States, will be undertaken 
     <lb/>as soon as the necessary legislation can 
     <lb/>be had thereon." I want the country to 
     <lb/>understand, that this work will go on 
     <lb/>when legislation can be had upon it. 
     <lb/>But I wish to refer to the Speech gener<lb break="no"/>ally. " We share with Your Excellency <lb/>the feelings of satisfaction at the prospect 
     <lb/>of the speedy restoration of peace in the 
     <lb/>neighboring Republic." Everybody must 
     <lb/>rejoice at the speedy close of the war, 
     <lb/>but still must deeply regret what has 
     <lb/>taken place with regard to the death of 
     <lb/>the President. I have been in that sec<lb break="no"/>tion of country, and seen the devastation 
     <lb/>and destruction that have taken place   
     <lb/>there. I have seen the battle fields and 
     <lb/>the hospitals, and know the evils result<lb break="no"/>ing from the civil war; and hon. members 
     <lb/>who have not witnessed them, must all 
     <lb/>regret the strife which has raged there. 
     <lb/>On hearing the news of the death of the 
     <lb/>President, I was very much struck with 
     <lb/>surprise and regret, and was glad to see 
     <lb/>the feelings   of sympathy which was ex<lb break="no"/>pressed. I had the pleasure of a personal 
     <lb/>interview with the President. A kinder- 
     <lb break="yes"/>hearted man did not exist; his counte<lb break="no"/>nance showed it. His death is a loss to 
     <lb/>the nation -a loss that must be felt to be 
     <lb/>great at the present time. I am rejoiced   
     <lb/>at the expressions of sorrow which has 
     <lb/>pervaded the minds of all on this Conti<lb break="no"/>nent on this subject. Every friend to 
     <lb/>humanity must abhor the act of the mur<lb break="no"/>derer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     I next come to the Confederation busi<lb break="no"/>ness. I shall not make any remarks on 
     <lb/>
     this further than to say, that when the re<lb break="no"/>solution comes before the House, I shall 
     <lb/>
     state my views on the subject. They are 
     <lb/>
     known now in the country. I thought I 
     <lb/>
     was correct in the judgment I formed of 
     <lb/>
     the scheme, and I think so yet. We must 
     <lb/>
     either provide for the defence of this 
     <lb/>
     country or let it alone. It is the duty of 
     <lb/>
     Government to see to the proper defence 
     <lb/>
     of the Colony, or the had better let 
     <lb/>
     legislation alone. If Confederation had 
     <lb/>
     taken place, I would have voted for the 
     <lb/>
     appropriating of such a sum as would be 
     <lb/>
     suited for the purpose according to our 
     <lb/>means. But until they adopt this policy<lb/>I shall not vote away a shilling, except<lb/>for such small affairs as are absolutely<lb/>indispensible. Look at the report of Col.<lb/>Jervois. He says that beyond Kingston<lb/>it is futile to provide for the defence of<lb/>Canada. On this account I believe Con<lb break="no"/>federation would have proved a benefit,<lb/>so that we should have had a means for de<lb break="no"/>fence, and further means which we could<lb/>probably have obtained from the British<lb/>Government; but for us to attempt to<lb/>provide for the defence alone is futile. The<lb/>
            </p>

    

    


            <pb n="13" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_013.jpg"/>
            
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">13</fw>


            <p>people of the United States do not want 
     <lb/>nor desire a war with us, but the feeling 
     <lb/>with regard to the Alabama and our 
     <lb/>vessels is very strong. The President of<lb/>the United States, in speaking to the <lb/>Lord Palmerston, remarked, that he was<lb/>a great statesman, but wrong in the course<lb/>he pursued with regard to the Alabama.<lb/>The people do not desire war; but they<lb/>number their population by millions, and<lb/>soon there will e large bodies of men,<lb/>who have acquired a military ardor, out<lb/>work, - these will be found going to<lb/>Mexico and Canada.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. Mr. SMITH</persName> — Do you expect war? 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>. — I express my honest 
     <lb/>
     convictions that these men will leave the 
     <lb/>States and go to Canada, Mexico, Cuba,<lb/>and parts of South America. I am glad<lb/>to see that the Canadians are determined<lb/>to se what the British Government is<lb/>is going to do. Some of the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers think the people here do not want<lb/>connection with Canada, and other that<lb/>the connections was too speedy. I saw<lb/>that throughout the [illegible] the honorable<lb/>President of the Council opposed it only<lb/>on the grounds of the time. (Mr. Smith - "O,<lb/>no.") And we have the word of the<lb/>hon. member for Kent that his first ob<lb break="no"/>ject was to turn out the existing Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and then see what was to be done.<lb/>(Mr. DesBrisay - "I did not say that.")<lb/>The matter with regard to the Militia Bill,<lb/>the Post Office, and the Union of the<lb/>Colonies, will come up hereafter and be<lb/>discussed, I presume. I do not wish<lb/>to take up the time, as this is to be a short<lb/>Session. I see the hon. member is going<lb/>to speak and I hope he will show us<lb/>some plan by which the country can raise<lb/>money without paying interest. I think<lb/>something might be done in this matter.<lb/>The time has come when it is necessary<lb/>to fix on some solid basis for our Banking<lb/>interests. I am sure the people would<lb/>be benefitted if a different state of things<lb/>existed. In New York the people feel<lb/>secure. The way they work in Canada I<lb/>have not looked into if this Railway<lb/>goes on, some plan could be matured by<lb/>which the Province could issue notes<lb/>which would be a legal tender for duties<lb/>and all other things. There are many<lb/>other things I should like to have seen<lb/>in the Speech, but will not now go into<lb/>them. In reference to the Railway, I<lb/>hope the Government will take immedi<lb break="no"/>ate action on it. If it is not carried on<lb/>great evils will fall upon the country; <lb/>young men and old men too, that can get<lb/>away will leave. The people want Rail<lb break="no"/>ways, and it is just as well to have them<lb/>at once. There is no source of wealth so<lb/>good for the Province.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">Hon. MR. WILMOT</persName> — I thought the hon. 
     <lb/>member for Carleton was gong to oppose<lb/>the action of the present Government,<lb/>but find at the close he intends to support<lb/>it, or that at least he will offer no factious <lb/>opposition to their measures. With re<lb break="no"/>gard to the clause of the Address under<lb/>debate, I think it already shows that the<lb/>Government intend to proceed with the <lb/>work as soon as existing legislation ad<lb break="no"/>mits. The hon. member for Northum<lb break="no"/>berland say they are opposed tothe pro<lb break="no"/>secution of Western Extension as a Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment work, but are willing it should <lb/>be carried on by a company. I think the<lb/>Government should not have their hands<lb/>tied up by the passing of these amendments.<lb/>I would ask the hon. member for North<lb break="no"/>umberland if the question was on a road<lb/>from Sherdiac to Chatham if they would<lb/>oppose it as a Government work, I rather<lb/>think they would want it left open to be<lb/>carried on as would be found best. I<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
          

     hope the hon. member will be induced to 
     <lb/>withdraw his amendment, and give the<lb/>Government a chance to go on with<lb/>the public business. The hon. member<lb/>for Carleton wants the work to go on at<lb/>once; but let the Government have time.<lb/>The hon. member, Mr. Boyd, and myself<lb/>are the oldest members of the House.<lb/>When Railways were first mooted I moved<lb/>a resolution which, if noted on, would<lb/>have prevented our being burdened with<lb/>a heavy foreign debt. I thought then<lb/>that Treasury notes should have been<lb/>issued, and I think so still. That was in<lb/>1849, just after the great depression of<lb/>1847. Now we have experiences in con<lb break="no"/>structing roads; we have plenty of labor<lb/>if we had the money to employ it; there<lb/>is lumber to make the sleepers, material<lb/>and skilled mechanics to erect station-<lb break="yes"/>houses and all other works. The only<lb/>articles we really need to import is the iron<lb/>rails to lay the track. My object always<lb/>has been to employ the labor of our own<lb/>country, and I hope the time will soon<lb/>come when we shall be able to make our<lb/>own rails. I have always been in favour<lb/>of progress and free trade; but while the<lb/>made gold the basis for paying the<lb/>debt, it was important that the imports<lb/>should exceed the exports, as otherwise<lb/>it would cause a panic and crisis. We<lb/>have seen what has been done in the<lb/>United States, and the plans they have<lb/>adopted to raise means to carry on their<lb/>great undertakings. The House will<lb/>have to see in what way Railways can<lb/>best be provided for. I heard in St. John<lb/>that there were a million dollars lying in<lb/>the Bank at three per cent interest. If<lb/>we had an issue of Province notes as in<lb/>Prince Edward Island we could raise<lb/>money to carry on our public works as<lb/>the House well knows. The revenue<lb/>last year was $1,080,000. I shall not,<lb/>however, go into figures, but I hope the<lb/>House will give the Government a chance<lb/>to do something. They do not intend to<lb/>be a do nothing government, nor to enter<lb/>upon works which will embarrass and dis<lb break="no"/>tress the Province. All they ask is to be<lb/>allowed time to mature their plans and<lb/>carry out a policy which shall be for the<lb/>welfare of the country.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SUTT1">Mr. SUTTON</persName> — When I was elected to<lb/>a seat in this House, I was not pledged to<lb/>the support of any Government, neither<lb/>was I sent to support Confederation, for<lb/>Confederation was dead before the elec<lb break="no"/>tion took place, but I was returned pledged<lb/>to oppose this measure. Few as the pub<lb break="no"/>lic woks are which this Government have<lb/>introduced, they have introduced one too<lb/>many for me. I have had the pleasure to<lb/>shake hands with the President of the<lb/>United States, although I deplore the com<lb break="no"/>mission of a crime, the result of which<lb/>has filled all hearts with sorrow. But<lb/>with regard to this question. Last year<lb/>the people of the North paid $2,300 to the <lb/>support of the Railway from St. John to<lb/>Shediac. This line is of very little advan<lb break="no"/>tage to them and I think it would be an<lb/>act of injustice to them to make them pay<lb/>a further sum to push the extension to the<lb/>Western frontier. If the people of Saint<lb/>John have confidence that the Railway<lb/>will be of so much benefit to them, - and<lb/>they will get the benefit if any body does<lb/>- let them take stock in the company and<lb/>assist in building it. There are four Coun<lb break="no"/>ties in the North that would receive little<lb/>or no benefit from this extension. Why<lb/>did not the Government foreshadow the<lb/>construction of a line to the North? If<lb/>this had been done, we might have had <lb/>machinery at work and care building in<lb/>Chatham. I remember the promise of an<lb/>

<cb/>

honorable member for York, that we<lb/>should have rail for rail, spade for spade,<lb/>sleeper for sleeper but it does not seem to<lb/>be the intention of Government to pursue<lb/>that plan. We have had experience in<lb/>the building of Railways and the honor<lb break="no"/>able member for Saint John must know<lb/>that the cost of construction would be<lb/>much greater to the Government than it would<lb/>be to a company like that formed. The<lb/>roads and bridges are in a bad state, and<lb/>require heavy expenses to put them in a <lb/>good condition. The roads from Chatham<lb/>to Richibucto is said to be so bad that it<lb/>is almost impossible to get along. I have<lb/>worked for years, side by side, with some<lb/>of the members of the present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment and know their ability, but on this<lb/>point I cannot give them my support, If<lb/>my honorable friend and colleague saw<lb/>the injury that will be done to the people<lb/>of the North by this measure, he would<lb/>not stay in any Government who deter<lb break="no"/>mined to carry on the work.<lb/></p>

<p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">MR. NEEDHAM</persName> — I wish the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Charleton were in his place to hear<lb/>my remarks. With regard to the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Northumberland's remarks, there<lb/>are always two sides to a story. Believing,<lb/>and knowing as I did, that Western Ex<lb break="no"/>tension included a line to Chatham, I did<lb/>make the remark that I would go for their<lb/>having rail for rail. But, as Western Ex<lb break="no"/>tension was the basis of the whole thing,<lb/>as he is opposed to our end of the line, of<lb/>course I am absolved from my remark - <lb/>This is an important measure, but beore<lb/>coming to it, I wish to follow the example<lb/>of other hon. members who have spoken<lb/>on the Speech, and introduced a good<lb/>many things outside of it. No man hav<lb break="no"/>ing any regard for humanity, or the prin<lb break="no"/>ciples of right and wring, can do other<lb break="no"/>wise than endorse the expressions of the<lb/>Speech and Reply, respecting the death<lb/>of the President of the United States. It<lb/>is not often the case in the present day<lb/>that the head of a nation falls by the hand<lb/>of an assassin, and the effect of this blow <lb/>will be felt not only by every manly heart<lb/>on this continent, but by those on the <lb/>other side of the Atlantic. It is well<lb/>known that from the time of the firing<lb/>of the first gun at Sumter to the present, my<lb/>sympathies have been in favour of the<lb/>North. But with regard to Railways, and<lb/>I am glad the hon. member for Carleton<lb/>is now in his seat, I do not quite under<lb break="no"/>stand the position he takes. He is surely<lb/>not willing to take the right of building<lb/>Railways given to companies, by existing<lb/>acts, from them, for this principle if ex<lb break="no"/>tended would deprive the people of<lb/>Queen's from the right to the coal mines,<lb/>and deprive Carleton of their iron. Any<lb/>man who would pursue such a course, and<lb/>take Stock away from any company, ought<lb/>not to be permitted to stand on the floors<lb/>of this House. I am opposed to the<lb/>building of Railways by companies, as I<lb/>think is should be Government work.<lb/>Still rights granted to companies must be<lb/>maintained, but if the conditions are not<lb/>complied with, then I believe the work<lb/>should be carried on by Government and<lb/>with a due regard to the interests of the<lb/>different parts of the Province. The hon.<lb/>member for St. John has fully explained<lb/>the principle of the private rights of indi<lb break="no"/>viduals, and how the law slips to res<lb break="no"/>train any infractions of those rights. I can<lb break="no"/>not go for this amendment. There was a<lb/>time when I was on the floor of the House<lb/>with the hon. members for Carleton and<lb/>the remark of his to-day, brings back to the<lb/>remembrance of old times. It was when<lb/>he said, "Something must be done." I<lb/>have not heard it since the time we were<lb/>
 

  
            <pb n="14" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_014.jpg"/>
       <fw type="num">14</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>

     on the floors together before, and then I 
     <lb/>spoke of his laying sacrilegious hands on<lb/>King's College. When he made the re<lb break="no"/>mark that something must be done, it put<lb/>me in mind of a story (which I related to <lb/>the House) of three boys. They were<lb/>named respectively, Charles, James and<lb/>John. These boys were out in the fields<lb/>together when a heavy rain storm came<lb/>on, and they took refuge under a tree.<lb/>Whilst standing there the tree was struck<lb/>by lightning and overturned, the roots<lb/>tearing up the ground all round, and got<lb/>the boys into a bad scrape. Charles turns<lb/>round to James and asks, "Can you<lb/>pray?" "No." "John can you pray?"<lb/>"No." "Well, by hokey something<lb/>must be done." The honorable member<lb/>says, that the Government was formed on<lb/>the principle of Federation, then why<lb/>does he look for any measures from them. <lb/>But I always thought this Government<lb/>was formed on <hi rendition="simple:italic">Anti</hi>-Confederation prin<lb break="no"/>ciples. If they are not, they can't have <lb/>my support. Confederation was not dead <lb/>when I was elected, but it received its <lb/>death blow at my election. (Laughter.)<lb/>I am glad that reference is made to this<lb/>subject in the Speech, and that the report<lb/>of the delegates is to be laid on the table. <lb/>I hope when it is brought in and laid<lb/>there, no hand will be raised to disturb<lb/>its everlasting repose. Reference has<lb/>been made to the remarks made by hon.<lb/>members in their canvas, and on the<lb/>hustings; I think this unnecessary, as<lb/>as almost any man is the best of a political<lb/>contest, will say something or other that<lb/>he can't sustain afterward. That scheme<lb/>was replete with financial destruction, and<lb/>political ruin to this country. When I<lb/>heard that $2.75 was put forth as the pro<lb break="no"/>bable tax per capita, I said that manner of <lb/>arriving as it was not honest - it was a<lb/>political trick. It was made up on the<lb/>whole population. Now, the 250,000 in<lb break="no"/>habitants of this country don't pay taxes,<lb/>but only, about 71,000, and if the rate<lb/>were made up in this way, it would give <lb/>some $12.90 per head The city of Fred<lb break="no"/>ericton is taxed some $10,000 a year; the <lb/>population is 6,000. Now, I know very<lb/>well that if you divide the ten by six you<lb/>get one and something over, but $1 and<lb/>something over is not the tax the people<lb/>pay. No, that would be on men, women,<lb/>children, and babies, and they don't do<lb/>anything towards the avenue that I know<lb/>of, unless they do in Carleton.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> - "Don't they wear<lb/>clothes?"<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName> - Yes, when they've got 
     <lb/>them. My honorable friend, Mr. Connell<lb/>says that three-fourths of this people are<lb/>in favor of Confederation. I tell him it is<lb/>not the case. It is the opinion that there<lb/>are not three quarters of Carleton, nor a <lb/>half, nor a third, in its favor.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName> - How do you know?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName> - Because I believe<lb/>what the people tell me; I believe if the<lb/>subject were submitted to the County,<lb/>the ballot boxes set up every few miles,<lb/>and the people provided with ballots -<lb/>Confederation - No Confederation - the<lb/>result would be that not one-third of<lb/>this country would be in favor of it. It<lb/>was a scheme connected in Canada to suit<lb/>their own locality. They may have been<lb/>educated, as it was stated, by desires for<lb/>fair dealing with us, but what honesty is<lb/>there in saying, if you give us all your re<lb break="no"/>venue be it what may, we will give you<lb/>$250,000 out of it for yourself as long as<lb/>you live. The good old Judge Marshall<lb/>of Nova Scotia has shown that in fifty<lb/>years this arrangement would have<lb/>swamped the whole of us. What would<lb/>
            <cb/>

   
have become of us if the scheme had been<lb/>carried. Where would we have got the<lb/>fifteen members to go in the general go<lb break="no"/>vernment? Who among us could compete<lb/>with the members up in Canada. In forty<lb/>years our revenue would have been $4,<lb break="no"/>000,000, and we should have got some<lb/>$201,000 for our own use whilst the bal<lb break="no"/>ance would have gone to them. No man<lb/>is worth the name of a statesman who<lb/>legislates merely for to-day. He should <lb/>look into and provide for the future, for if<lb/>he don't live for ever, somebody else will.<lb/>I have said the scheme possessed the<lb/>germs of political destruction, and so it<lb/>does. The only link that now binds us<lb/>to the mother country is the appointment<lb/>of His Excellency as our Governor. Judge<lb/>Halliburton may say in England that the<lb/>people of New Brunswick are disloyal,<lb/>but who believes it? I wish I had Sam<lb/>Slick here. This link that binds us to<lb/>England was to have been broken and our<lb/>Governor was to be appointed, and sent<lb/>down from that place up there is <hi rendition="simple:italic">Shoger<lb break="no"/>moc</hi>. (A member - "Ottawa,") Yes Ot<lb break="no"/>tawa. The cat was then let out of the <lb/>bag, but there was not a white hair on it,<lb/>not even on the tip of her tail. They talk<lb/>about my being noticed in the papers, <lb/>well that's good: for you know that's an<lb/>honor anyway (laughter.) The delegates<lb/>went to Prince Edward Island and met.<lb/>Now I hold that notwithstanding His Ex<lb/>cellency by the advice of the Governor<lb/>General, appointed delegates to meet other<lb/>delegates, yet he had no right to sanction<lb/>their acts. The Canadians were just ar<lb/>ranging for a Union of Upper and<lb/>Lower Canada, and hearing of the pro<lb break="no"/>posed Legislative Union down here, came<lb/>down, broke up our Convention, and got<lb/>themselves all re-appointed to meet again<lb/>in Canada. Now this was right enough<lb/>as long as they only met to deliberate, but<lb/>they had no right to draw up a protocol,<lb/>such as they did. When they got back<lb/>here they found it necessary to go round<lb/>the country and stir up the people. It put<lb/>me in ind of one of Aesop's fables. A<lb/>certain animal, called a monkey went out<lb/>on a little travelling expedition, (I don't<lb/>know whether he went to Quebec or not)<lb/>but one thing is certain, but some means or<lb/>other he got back without a very import<lb break="no"/>ant appendage. Of course the other mon<lb break="no"/>keys came round to see such a strange<lb/>sight, and so to get them all into the same<lb/>fix as himself, he told them that was the<lb/>fashion where he came from, and advised<lb/>them to follow his example. It was just<lb/>so with the delegates. They went to Que<lb break="no"/>bec, lost their tails, and on coming<lb/>back want us all to cut off ours. The<lb/>hon. member for Carleton County says if<lb/>the young men are going away; so they<lb/>are here. Some time ago there were<lb/>some seven or eight who started off to<lb/>join the war because they thought they<lb/>could make more by going than by stay<lb break="no"/>ing here. That's right enough. It is the<lb/>case everywhere, but that is not a good<lb/>place to live in. People take the notion<lb/>of going away from a place. I know a <lb/>whole lot who went off to Salt Lake, to<lb/>the Mormons. Did the country suffer by<lb/>that? No, because it saved us the trou<lb break="no"/>ble of putting them in a lunatic asylum,<lb/>and the expense of supporting them there. <lb/>The honorable member says he knows<lb/>all about the Post Office. There is no<lb/>doubt of it. He says he did things with<lb break="no"/>out consulting with his colleagues in the<lb/>Government, and I believe him. The ho<lb break="no"/>norable member now asks the Hon. Sur<lb break="no"/>veyor General to make a visit up to his<lb/>part of the country. Well if he can't go,<lb/>there is one thing he can do, get himself<lb/>
         
<cb/>

photographed and send his picture Per<lb break="no"/>haps that would do as well? Now I am<lb/>not in the Government, I haven't been<lb/>and I don't intend to be - till the time<lb/>comes. But this principle laid down by<lb/>the honorable member for Carleton of<lb/>doing things without the consent of his<lb/>colleagues is anew one to me. Since<lb/>the creation of the office of Post Master<lb/>General there has been an annual defi<lb/>ciency of about $20,000.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName> - What was it before?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName> - It never amounted to<lb/>that sum before. I believe the Post Of<lb break="no"/>fice department was conducted just as<lb/>well under the old regime as now.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">AFTERNOON SESSION - 2:30 P.M.<lb/>
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:WILL1">Mr. WILLISTON</persName> read a further report<lb/>from the Contingent Committee, recom<lb break="no"/>mending that as the house had made<lb/>provision for the publication of the Debates<lb/>furnished by official reporters, no allow<lb break="no"/>ance of money be granted to members of<lb/>the press representing newspapers; yet, <lb/>being sensible of the benefit of a diffused<lb/>information, they recommend that they<lb/>be provided with such stationary as they<lb/>may need. One coach had been agreed <lb/>to for the use of House, and they<lb/>further recommended the employment of<lb/>another by the Sergeant-at-Arms to ex<lb/>pedite the businesss - Received.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">THE DEBATE ON THE FIFTH PARAGRAPH RESUMED<lb/>
            </head>


            <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">MR. NEEDHAM</persName> - I agreed with the hon.<lb/>member for Carleton in his remarks on <lb/>the President of the United States; but<lb/>when he came down to the question of<lb/>defence, I thought he would have used<lb/>some sound argument on the subject. I<lb/>think some other plan than that pursued<lb/>should have been adopted by the Opposi<lb break="no"/>tion, but with regard to defence, I am of opi<lb break="no"/>nion that if this country were able to spend<lb/>even ten times the amount of the reve<lb break="no"/>nues of this Province and of Canada, it<lb/>would all amount to nothing if we were <lb/>assailed. The repent of Col/ Jervois per<lb break="no"/>fectly shows this. With regard to our<lb/>natural defence - the Militia - when the<lb/>question comes up I shall express my<lb/>opinions upon it. I will now say, that if<lb/>we had a lot of officers well drilled, pro<lb break="no"/>vided with clothing, guns, and ammuni<lb break="no"/>tion, it would be better than turning out<lb/>the whole of the Province, to forget in<lb/>three hours what they have learned in<lb/>three days. If a plan of this kind could<lb/>be arranged, I think that in connection<lb/>with the volunteer movement and the<lb/>regular army, it would prove effective;<lb/>but I believe our best defense is not to<lb/>talk so much about war. As to war<lb/>between Great Britain and the United<lb/>States, we have only to turn to the papers<lb/>to see the ministers in the British Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment declaring that the two Governments<lb/>never stood on a better footing than at<lb/>present, that should differences arise they<lb/>could only be settled by arbitration and <lb/>diplomacy.We may beat them at that,<lb/>but we could not by putting the country<lb/>in a state of defence. I do not want my<lb/>words to be understood as conveying an<lb/>idea that we would quietly sit down and<lb/>submit to invasion. Not at all. I am<lb/>sure if the time came, the country would<lb/>rise and join heart and hand to resist the<lb/>spoiler of our hearths and homes. (A<lb/>MEMBER - "We could lick them.") It is<lb/>all very well to talk about licking, but<lb/>when the lick comes, perhaps it would be<lb/>found best to let licking alone. I agree<lb/>with my honorable friend that the lumber<lb break="no"/>ing interests are becoming useless. I <lb/>have made up my mind to one thing, and<lb/>
   

     
            <pb n="15" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_015.jpg"/>
     <fw type="num">15</fw>

     That is, that this giving to great lumbering  
     <lb/>
     men the right to cut out some 20, 30 or 
     <lb/>
     40 miles of timber land shoul be be abolish<lb break="no"/>ed. The plan I think should be adopt<lb break="no"/>ed of selling by the thousand. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     I agree in what has been said as to our 
     <lb/>
     Mines and Minerals. I believe that either 
     <lb/>
     I or the Government, before the Session 
     <lb/>closes, will show that we have faith in<lb/>these resources by employing a competent<lb/>gentleman to make a thorough geological<lb/>survey of the Province, and see what we<lb/>really have here.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     All I have to say is, that if the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment will carry out Railway Extension<lb/>according to the law, either by themselves<lb/>or by engagements with companies, they<lb/>shall receive my support. The people<lb/>must and will have Western Extension.<lb/>The Government are new men, filling<lb/>new offices, and I am willing to give them<lb/>a chance. I believe they should have at<lb/>least three or four days to feel the honors<lb/>laid upon them. But afterwards, if they<lb/>do not inaugurate a policy of extended<lb/>works, then they must know that there<lb/>are people in this country and House who<lb/>will do so. I say this to show the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment that I am willing to aid them in<lb/>carrying out Western Extension.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Another thing, I am willing to go the    
     <lb/>
     whole hog to show the British Govern<lb break="no"/>ment that we are sincere, and that we do 
     <lb/>not want to sever the connection existing<lb/>between us, or annex ourselves to the<lb/>States, (for I do not believe this feeling<lb/>resides in the breast of one man). I want<lb/>them to know that the reason we rejected<lb/>the Scheme was because we love the con<lb break="no"/>nection with our mother country, and that<lb/>the very men who voted against, are wil<lb break="no"/>ling, if necessary, to shed every drop of<lb/>their blood in defence of her cause and<lb/>institutions.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>. - The member for York 
     <lb/>
     has made a long Speech with very little  
     <lb/>
     touching the matter under discussion. I   
     <lb/>
     am not finding fault with the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment for not carrying on Western Exten<lb break="no"/>sion, for I believe the revenues of the<lb/>country are in too low a state to admit of<lb/>it; and are not only so now, but will be<lb/>for years to come in too feeble a state to<lb/>carry on the work of the main trunk with<lb break="no"/>out taking into consideration the branches.<lb/>The expense of this work alone will en<lb break="no"/>tail a burden of $260,000 a year upon the<lb/>country. But I do find fault because they<lb/>assign reasons for not carrying on the<lb/>work that do not in reality existe. The<lb/>Company with which arrangements were<lb/>made have not fulfilled the conditions of<lb/>that engagement. Before they can claim<lb/>anything from this Province, they have to<lb/>show that they have fulfilled the condi<lb break="no"/>tions; that they have provided sufficient<lb/>funds, and that they really intend to go<lb/>on with the work by commencing to build<lb/>a portion of the line. Before the state<lb break="no"/>ment made with regard to them can be<lb/>sustained, they have to do certain things<lb/>which as yet are undone. But supposing<lb/>that they had done all that was required<lb/>of them, was not this law on the Statute<lb/>Book a year ago? Did not the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for St. John know of this law when he<lb/>made the statement on the hustings that<lb/>the work must be carried on at once as a<lb/>Government measure? Since that time<lb/>no engagements have been entered into<lb/>which would prevent the road from being<lb/>carried on. I belive the position taken<lb/>by the Government sufficient in itself to<lb/>kill the company in Saint John. We find<lb/>by the hon. member fo the government,<lb/>the hon. member for Northumberland,<lb/>that it is not the intention of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to proceed with the work, whilst<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
        

     the President of the Council says it will 
     <lb/>
     be preceeded with. (Hon. Mr. Smith      
     <lb/>
     " No, No.") I would call the attention of   
     <lb/>the hon. member for St. John (Mr. An<lb break="no"/>glin) to an article in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Freeman</hi> under<lb/>the signature of A. I (and for which, who<lb break="no"/>ever writes, he holds himself responsible,)<lb/>in which, after reference to the clause of<lb/>the address under debate, he says that he<lb/>"hopes the existing legislation will not<lb/>prevent the Government from going<lb/>on with the work. " - Now I want to know<lb/>how the intend to carry it on. There is<lb/>another point. As I understand the an<lb break="no"/>swer to the Speech, it is intended to fore<lb break="no"/>shadow the action of the Government not<lb/>in the future, not a year or two hence, but<lb/>ath the present time. The Answer now<lb/>under debate, however, does not seem to<lb/>claim this for its object this Session. I<lb/>believe the financial condition of<lb/>country for years to come will not admit<lb/>of the Government carrying on the work.<lb/>The cost of the main trunk to the coun<lb break="no"/>try, without the branches, will amount to <lb/>$268,000 a year, and if the branches are<lb/>built to the sum of $390,000. I am not <lb/>in a position therefore to vote for the<lb/>Government to carry on this work, and I<lb/>hope the hon. member for Northumber<lb break="no"/>land in the Government will not do his<lb/>constituents the great injustice of laying<lb/>this burden upon them. If they want the<lb/>road to be built, why not assist the com<lb break="no"/>pany by still further facilities without<lb/>undertaking the whole work as a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment measure. I am in favor of the<lb/>Amendment.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> said in his Speech he   
     <lb/>
     had reffered to the Act to build extension   
     <lb/>
     Westward and to the Facility Bill. He  
     <lb/>wished just to call the attention of the<lb/>House to the 13th Section of the Bill<lb/>which provides that companies, to entitle<lb/>them to any claims allowed by the Act,<lb/>must commence to build the road within<lb/>two years. He merely wished to show up<lb/>honorable members that if any company<lb/>complied with conditions within that time<lb/>they would be in a position to make a<lb/>claim for the grant.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLIN</persName>. - I have not spoken  
     <lb/>
     as yet, as I thought I would let honorable 
     <lb/>members have an opportunity to express<lb/>their opinions, so that I might know what<lb/>ground to take. I was surpised at the<lb/>opening attack by the hon. member on my<lb/>left (Mr. Gilbert). Many of the members<lb/>seemed much hurt by his remarks, but I<lb/>considered that he paid the highest tribute<lb/>he could have done to the Government, for<lb/>he saw that the Government ought to have<lb/>done in forty-eight hours from its forma<lb break="no"/>tion what would take and ordinary one<lb/>seven years to work out. He must have<lb/>believed the members of the Government<lb/>to be men of unparalelled ability, if he<lb/>imagined they could have even treated<lb/>upon all the subjects he mentioned. The<lb/>hon. member for Restigouche has given<lb/>the same speech which I have heard be<lb break="no"/>fore - the same cuckoo cry - that he was<lb/>not opposed to the Government, but the<lb/>finances of the country would not admit of<lb/>further Railway Extension. I think the<lb/>words of the speech are definite. It dis<lb break="no"/>tinctly states that the work will be pro<lb break="no"/>ceeded with as soon as practicable, Oh but<lb/>it is said, one member of the Government<lb/>-who was not then a member of any Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment - said on the hustings, that he<lb/>would not belong to a Government that<lb/>would act at once proceed with the work.<lb/>It is not expected that he can drag along<lb/>seven or eight other men with him to pro<lb break="no"/>secute his ideas, without time for them to<lb/>mature their plans. What that member<lb/>said, he repeats, that when the Govern<lb break="no"/>
       

            <cb/>
         
ment fails to carry out plans which he 
     <lb/>thinks are for the benefit of the country,<lb/>he will no longer remain a member of that<lb/>Government. Oh, but the finances are<lb/>low. Yes, but what did a then honorable<lb/>member say on platforms in St. John about<lb/>this Western Extension. He said that<lb/>first there was the $10,000 a mile - an out<lb/>an out gift, the the amount of Stock sub<lb break="no"/>scribed, then the stock taken by the City<lb/>of $400,000, and if sufficient could not be<lb/>raised after this, he was willing to guaran<lb break="no"/>tee to provide the balance of the cost at<lb/>six per cent. This proposition was put<lb/>forth by those who now are so fearful of<lb/>burdening the revenues. We are not<lb/>here to judge the late Government. This<lb/>Government, however, distinctly state<lb/>their policy. They says existing legisla<lb break="no"/>tion precludes us from taking action ona<lb/>anything that would infringe on the rights<lb/>of the people. The opposition say there<lb/>is nothing in the way - this is admitting<lb/>that there was nothing in the legislation<lb/>- that it meant nothing. I have said, and<lb/>I says again, that it was all a sham. It<lb/>was my impression at the time that no<lb/>company would be formed, but Iwas mis<lb break="no"/>taken; a company has been formed; still<lb/>I freely state that I don't believe they will<lb/>ever do anything - that they will ever turn<lb/>the first sod. They have raised funds,<lb/>however, and their President has gone<lb/>home. It is true we could repeal the act,<lb/>but we would not do so whilst there was a<lb/>semblance of infringement of rights gua<lb break="no"/>ranteed to any one by the Act. I am<lb/>responsible for what I said on the hust<lb break="no"/>ings, and prepared to stand by it. The<lb/>state of the finances has nothing to<lb/>do with this question. Railroads in their<lb/>construction do not take money from the<lb/>revenues. Is it raised by loan and if it<lb/>entailed the levying of further taxes, they<lb/>would be cheerfully paid in Saint John.<lb/>But we have a strong belief that it will<lb/>entail no burden on the country at all.<lb/>If the city take the Stock of $400,000 they<lb/>agreed to, taxes there will be increased<lb/>about one third. I should have to pay<lb/>about $12 more than I now pay, and some<lb/>would have to pay $500 more. I say this<lb/>to show the strong faith the people have<lb/>in the feasibility and paying qualities of<lb/>the road. Works of this kindought to<lb/>be carried on by the Government. I find<lb/>the objections raised to this work more<lb/>contradictory than the speech. Some<lb/>want the work to go on, others don't want<lb/>it at all, while member fo the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment want it to go on, and yet not to<lb/>go on. I think the section ought to pass.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName>. - I did not rise to defend   
     <lb/>
     the late Government at all. I rose think<lb break="no"/>ing this Government did not require to  
     <lb/>
     take so long to define their policy. I 
     <lb/>
     was born in this country. I may say this 
     <lb/>great country, with capabilities to main<lb break="no"/>tain a large population, who could put<lb/>out all their energies and yet not exhaust<lb/>its resources. I thought that it was not<lb/>necessary the Government should take<lb/>long to shew the policy they intended to<lb/>follow. I thought the men who composed<lb/>that Government, possessed as they are of<lb/>great minds and large abilities, could go<lb/>on with the great public works, and de<lb break="no"/>fine their position even thought they had<lb/>not been in existence twenty-four hours.<lb/>I rose, not to oppose the Government, but<lb/>as the representatives of a large and influ<lb break="no"/>ential consituency - not to defend the<lb/>late Government, for I was opposed to its<lb/>do-nothing policy. But wishing to warn<lb/>the new Government that "something<lb/>ought to be done," that the sound of the<lb/>pick and the hammer might be heard in<lb/>the land; that great works might be car<lb break="no"/>
        

            <pb n="16" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_016.jpg"/>
    <fw type="num">16</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw>


ried on, and that connection with Nova 
     <lb/>Scotia should be commenced and pushed<lb/>through to completion. Not knowing<lb/>
     what hindrances were in the way, was I to 
     <lb/>
     stop? I thought they had had time enough 
     <lb/>
     to deliberate on what was wanted by a 
     <lb/>
     small country like this, with a population 
     <lb/>
     of less than 300,000. I told them I in<lb break="no"/>tended to support them if they brought in 
     <lb/>
     measures I could approve. I came here 
     <lb/>
     perfectly free and independent, I came here 
     <lb/>
     not as a partizan of any set of men. I 
     <lb/>came here pledged against Confederation,<lb/>no farther am I pledged, and I propounded<lb/>the same ideas to my constituents on the<lb/>hustings as I did here. After the state<lb break="no"/>ment made by the President of the Coun<lb break="no"/>cil, that obstacles stood in the way of car<lb break="no"/>rying on the work of the main line, I<lb/>learned that there had been a distinct<lb/>offer made to carry on the work to com<lb break="no"/>pletion. I do not intend to oppose the<lb/>Government, but am I to be catechized<lb/>because, when the speech was going by<lb/>without discussions, and the mover of the<lb/>address gave no statement of the policy of<lb/>the Government, I rose to express my<lb/>opinions on public works.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName> - I do not quite un<lb break="no"/>derstand the object of the hon. member's 
     <lb/>
     lashing himself into such an immense   
     <lb/>
     fury. The hon. member is not bound so  
     <lb/>
     far as I know, certainly not to me, for I      
     <lb/>was not in the Government at the time of<lb/>the elections. He is only pledged on the<lb/>question of Confederation. I do not com<lb break="no"/>plain of the course pursued by my hon.<lb/>colleague. I only expressed my disap<lb break="no"/>pointment and surprise at the course<lb/>which he saw proper to pursue, a course<lb/>that must surprise our constituents as<lb/>much as it did me. The Government had<lb/>not been in existence twenty-four hours,<lb/>when the hon. member stood up and said<lb/>that the indications were bad, and com<lb break="no"/>plained that we had not brought in any<lb/>great scheme for the colonization of the<lb/>country. As I said, he is not responsible<lb/>to me, but to his constituents. It has<lb/>gone forth to the country that he is in the<lb/>Opposition, still I don't complain of his<lb/>action, but I tell him as I would any<lb/>other hon. member that I was surprised<lb/>and disappointed at the course he saw fit<lb/>to pursue. And now it is said that no<lb/>difficulties really exist to prevent the<lb/>carrying out of this railway work, I put<lb/>it to the late Surveyor General, if Mr.<lb/>Parks did not go to England under pledges<lb/>of the late Government. And under these<lb/>circumstances, we should be recreant to<lb/>every principle of justice, if we proceeded<lb/>with the work. I ask the hon. member, if<lb/>he were a member of a Government, whe<lb break="no"/>ther he would not feel bound by such ac<lb break="no"/>tion. He is please that the Government<lb/>do not intend to carry on the work, yet<lb/>his late leader was willing to guarantee<lb/>the balance of the cost of Western Exten<lb break="no"/>sion. Mr. Tilley is by all acknowledged<lb/>to be a cautious man, and would not make<lb/>such a pledge unless he intended to carry<lb/>it out. The hon. member cannot deny<lb/>this - his mouth is shut on this point. I<lb/>want to put it to this House whether they<lb/>are willing the Government should act in<lb/>violation of the good faith of the late Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, and that the pledges made by<lb/>them should be broken, in order to carry<lb/>this work at once.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
      Mr. McClellan. - Do I understand 
     <lb/>that the Government would go on with<lb/>the work if no legislation stood in the way?<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>. - Yes.   
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>. - In case the company         
     <lb/>surrender their charter has the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment any right to go on with the work?<lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <cb/>
        

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>. - It is not usual to 
     <lb/>ask questions of this kind until the ad<lb break="no"/>dress has passes, and I shall certainly de<lb break="no"/>cline to answer.<lb/>
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>. - But this may have a 
     <lb/>material bearing on the vote of the House.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>. - In reply to the quest<lb break="no"/>tion of the President of the Council I<lb/>would say, that if the late Government<lb/>had not been prepared to meet the legis<lb break="no"/>lature on the question they would not<lb/>have met them, but if the had intended<lb/>to carry on a certain work they would<lb/>have foreshadowed it in the Speech. I<lb/>would direct the attention of Hon. Mr.<lb/>Anglin to the promise of the late Provin<lb break="no"/>cial Secretary which he states was to pro<lb break="no"/>vide for the building of the road West<lb break="no"/>ward if sufficient Stock was not taken up<lb/>to complete the work.<lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLIN</persName>. - What I said was 
     <lb/>that the Facility Bill provided a grant of<lb/>$10,000 a mile &amp; there was a large<lb/>amount of Stock subscribed, the city had<lb/>agreed to take $40,000 worth of Stock<lb/>and then Mr. Tilley promised to provide<lb/>all the rest at six per cent.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>. - What I understood 
     <lb/>by the statement of Mr. Tilley was this,<lb/>that as a member of the Government he<lb/>would take the responsibility of guaran<lb break="no"/>teeing the balance over a million dollars,<lb/>taking security on the whole of the road.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName>. - Being a new member<lb/>and rather green, I may be pardoned if I<lb/>state my opinion on this matter. I ap<lb break="no"/>prehend that if the Government want to<lb/>pass an Act for the prosecution of the<lb/>work, they will apply to the House to do<lb/>so after existing legislation can be sur<lb break="no"/>mounted. I understand Government<lb/>intend to carry on Western Extension<lb/>and therefore I shall support the passage<lb/>of this paragraph. I think there are in<lb break="no"/>dependent men enough in the country to<lb/>look after public works, and carry them<lb/>on with economy, and that they could get<lb/>more out of it than any individual com<lb break="no"/>pany could do. But of course if influences<lb/>are brought to bear upon them, and they<lb/>begin to give two prices to one con<lb break="no"/>tractor, and three to another, the public<lb/>money will be wasted. I do not expect<lb/>anything of this kind from the present<lb/>Government, for from the high standing<lb/>they hold - although there is rather too<lb/>much conservative element in it - I judge<lb/>in their hands the finances are safe.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. - I am disappointed in<lb/>reading the Speech that the Government<lb/>are not going on with the work. The<lb/>President of the Council says he is not<lb/>responsible for the statements that go<lb/>forth, and other members of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment say they are not responsible.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ANGL1">Hon. Mr. ANGLIN</persName>. - I said that I was<lb/>responsible.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. - Yes and the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber said more than that. He said also<lb/>that he was not a member of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment when he made certain statements,<lb/>and consequently is not responsible as<lb/>such. Mr. Tilley said that he would gua<lb break="no"/>rantee, after all the Stock of the Company<lb/>was paid up, and the whole sums re<lb break="no"/>ceived, to build the balance of the road,<lb/>taking the road as security. Now - (A<lb/>member "Don't go into that.") Very<lb/>well, other members have talked aside<lb/>from the question ; however, I wish to<lb/>say a word or two. An honorable mem<lb break="no"/>ber this morning referred to a remark of<lb/>mine which he got second hand. He said<lb/>I had made a remark on Saturday that<lb/>"he would explode". I did not say so<lb/>and I think , after the effort of this morn<lb break="no"/>ning there is no danger of his exploding<lb/>to night. He further referred to remarks<lb/>
      
<cb/>

made to Mr. Goodspeed. I said that the<lb/>statement he put forth that every man,<lb/>woman, and child would be taxed $8 a<lb/>head was not true. It appears to me that<lb/>honorable members have been wandering<lb/>back in their Speeches to other para<lb break="no"/>graphs. The members of the present<lb/>governement used to cry to the late Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, bring down your measures ; now<lb/>they find fault because of the expressions<lb/>used on the absence of - line of policy<lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">they</hi> intend to pursue.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>. - I would not like to<lb/>take the position of the honorable mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Northumberland that his feelings<lb/>were with the conservative element in the<lb/>Government, nor would I like to take an<lb/>opposite one, but I think that gentlemen<lb/>in the Government should be thankful to<lb/>Confederation, that by it they have ar<lb break="no"/>rived at positions they would not other<lb break="no"/>wise have had. Flushed with victory their<lb/>exposition of Confederation is worth little.<lb/>I believe that half the votes in the coun<lb break="no"/>try are in its favour. I am opposed to the<lb/>passage of the paragraphs in the address,<lb/>as it seems to complain of certain things<lb/>which have arisen under existing legisla<lb break="no"/>tion - which they declare to be a sham<lb/>and a delusion. I do not suppose that<lb/>the Government after the surrender of<lb/>any rights any company may have thought<lb/>they held, would proceed to act under<lb/>the Act of 1856, and proceed with the<lb/>trunk and branches as they see fit. It<lb/>may be they have the power and ability<lb/>to use the offices entrusted to them for<lb/>the good of the country. I am willing to<lb/>give them a fair and reasonable time to<lb/>mature their plans. But we are not wil<lb break="no"/>ling to allow them to increase the public<lb/>expenditure without consulting the peo<lb break="no"/>ple. On a question so much discussed<lb/>and talked about, the Government might<lb/>readily be supposed to have arrived at a<lb/>conclusion as to what course to pursue.<lb/>I understood companies were organized<lb/>and were prepared to go on, but I fear<lb/>that the action of the Government will<lb/>lend to upset what has been done. This<lb/>paragraph does not contain a sufficiently<lb/>explicit policy as to the ideas entertained<lb/>by the Government on Railway affairs. I<lb/>think the Amendment gives the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment sufficient power to do all they need<lb/>to do.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>. - I readily accord the view<lb/>of the law as expounded by the hon.<lb/>member for the City of Saint John. I<lb/>
               <lb/>think they are precluded as a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment from interfering with the rights of<lb/>a Company that may have intended to<lb/>enter upon this work. I think it is now<lb/>proceeding as well as we could expect.<lb/>We learn that it is intended to carry on<lb/>the line to fill up the gap to the Nova<lb/>Scotia boundary, and that the later Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment accepted the offer made. As such<lb/>be the case I think it premature to inter<lb break="no"/>fere with the efforts put forth to fill up this<lb/>gap. I have not yet heard that the State<lb/>of Maine have yet taken up the matter<lb/>with that energy this is necessary to as<lb break="no"/>sure us that they will be at the bound<lb break="no"/>ary before we can be there. If they care<lb/>not taking measures it would be prema<lb break="no"/>ture for us to go forward with the por<lb break="no"/>tion of the work, till they are ready to<lb/>meet us.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName>.- I understand they are<lb/>taking measures, and that a deputation<lb/>will probably be here in a few days to lay<lb/>their action before us.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.- Are they from the legisla<lb break="no"/>ture or are they capitalists?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName>. - They represent a<lb/>Company.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.- Railways are usually built<lb/>
     

            <pb n="17" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-01_Page_017.jpg"/>
         <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">17</fw>


     and carried on by private capital. The 
     <lb/>Great Trunk and Great Western lines of<lb/>Canada were constructed by British Ca<lb break="no"/>pitalists who expected them to pay but<lb/>were disappointed. When we look at<lb/>Canada with its great traffic, and see that<lb/>they are not able to pay the interest on<lb/>their stock as preference claims, we ought<lb/>to pause before we undertake further ex<lb break="no"/>tension. We talk as though we had four<lb/>times the population and resources we<lb/>really possess. We look at the state of<lb/>Nova Scotia and find that last year they<lb/>paid $60,000 whilst we paid $90,360. We<lb/>used to be told that we would never be<lb/>known till we got a debt. It strikes me<lb/>we must pretty well known on the<lb/>other side by this time. At the close of<lb/>the year 1863 we had to pay Baring £15,<lb break="no"/>000, to meet the balance of interest<lb/>against us and yet they want to go on<lb/>building the road. The report of the<lb/>Commissioners state that 20,000 rails are<lb/>required to replace those worn out at cer<lb break="no"/>tain parts of the line. These cost about<lb/>one shilling a-piece and it would take<lb/>from £500 to £1000 to replace them on<lb/>the track. The revenue received last year<lb/>only amounted to about $20,000, not<lb/>sufficient to pay one month's interest due<lb/>to Great Britain. When I see all this I<lb/>think it would be premature to undertake<lb/>further works. We have had all Govern<lb break="no"/>ments in power under the Railway<lb/>policy, and the result has been the same.<lb/>If we saved up our revenues till we were<lb/>in a better condition, after having paid<lb/>our debts we could go on with the public<lb/>works. We are not like Nova Scotia with<lb/>her mines and minerals; we have no gold<lb/>fields; we do not go so deep into the<lb/>shore fisheries, and yet they are able to<lb/>keep their debt at a lower figure than we<lb/>can. Take Prince Edward Island; they<lb/>are going on faster than any other of the other<lb/>Provinces. They export a vast amount<lb/>of wealth to the United States, and pay<lb/>
               their debt, or at least they are in a good posi<lb break="no"/>tion to be able to wipe it out at any time.<lb/>It is said we must have railroads to keep<lb/>our population. What is peopleing Aus<lb break="no"/>tralia, New Zealand, and California? Is<lb/>it not emigration from other places?<lb/>Why, even in the State of Maine, a Mr.<lb/>Goodall complains that something must<lb/>be done. Agricultural interests must be<lb/>improved, or the young men will all go out<lb/>West. I saw it stated that lately there<lb/>has been a perfect exodus from Canada.<lb/>There have been many who have left<lb/>Nova Scotia since the war first began.<lb/>Look at Charlotte County in 1854, one of<lb/>the most prosperous years the country<lb/>ever saw; during that year young men<lb/>kept going away. Why was it? The<lb/>country was prosperous. The fact is that<lb/>when they make up their minds to go,<lb/>they will go, and no railways or anything<lb/>else will prevent them. I would like to<lb/>see the young men go back, like their<lb/>fathers did, into the woods, and gain for<lb/>themselves farms and independence. But<lb/>
 young men of this day want to do some-   
     <lb/>thing easier than that. A man, as soon as<lb/>he gets a few hundreds of dollars toge<lb break="no"/>ther, must be a merchant, so that in almost<lb/>every village there are ten retail shops<lb/>where one would do, and the men stand<lb/>round the doors all day long with their<lb/>hands in their pockets. It is said, let us<lb/>have railroads to circulate money. But.<lb/>this circulation does not last long. I<lb/>would ask the hon. member for West<lb break="no"/>morland, what benefit has Moncton re<lb break="no"/>ceived from the Railway? I do not want<lb/>to see the money go out of the country<lb/>in the shape of interest as in the past.<lb/>I think the offer of $10,000 a mile a most<lb/>
       

            <cb/>
 

     liberal one, and that it will be taken up, 
     <lb/>and the work done. If the people of St.<lb/>John are in earnest and want this line so<lb/>much, why don't they put their hands in<lb/>their pockets and do a little more to raise<lb/>the required Stock? In the construction<lb/>of the present line the land damaged<lb/>amounted to £40,000, while in Nova<lb/>Scotia they did not amount to one-third<lb/>that sum. After the disappointment we<lb/>have all felt at the reports of the Cana<lb break="no"/>dian Railways, it is too much to say that<lb/>the Government can remedy the evils that<lb/>exist, and that it is possible to find men,<lb/>honest men, to fill all the offices of the<lb/>country. I think men are about as they<lb/>were, and when money is placed in their<lb/>way they like to get hold of it.<lb/>To go on with our road will add £16,<lb break="no"/>950 more to our interest, whilst the whole<lb/>interest on our debt will amount to<lb/>£158,160, and this to be paid by 250,000<lb/>people. When I look at the state of<lb/>Railway stock in Canada, I find that on<lb/>the Great Western there is a loss of £12<lb/>on every paid up share of £18. Look<lb/>at the state of our stocks. I see they are<lb/>quoted at from 92 to 95, and money worth<lb/>4 and 4 1-2 per cent. During the build<lb break="no"/>ing of the road our debentures were worth<lb/>4 and 5 per cent premium now they are<lb/>down to 92, and I don't think there is<lb/>much prospect for a rise. Who is going<lb/>to invest $190,000 in carrying on our<lb/>railway policy? If any one will, it will<lb/>relieve our finances very much. I see by<lb/>the Act of 1856 that the branches were to<lb/>be carried on.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName> - The provision was 
     <lb/>that they were to go on with the trunk or<lb/>the branches as they could.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>. - If they are going to deal 
     <lb/>fairly, the Government must serve all<lb/>
     portions of the Province alike. Seeing 
     <lb/>
     all this, I cannot withdraw my amend<lb break="no"/>ment, and I am sure members of the 
     <lb/>
     Government, were they in my circum<lb break="no"/>stances, would do the same. I think it 
     <lb/>
     best for the law to take its course, and 
     <lb/>
     leave the work for companies to take up. 
     <lb/>
     It may be that Mr. Parks will come out 
     <lb/>
     and surrender his charter forthwith. 
     <lb/>
     Then the Government are going to take 
     <lb/>
     the matter in hand; but I would like to 
     <lb/>
     know where they are going to get the 
     <lb/>
     money, and if they intend to raise it on 
     <lb/>
     the same terms as in 1857, I think they 
     <lb/>
     will find great difficulty, as our bonds 
     <lb/>
     have settled down and will not likely rise 
     <lb/>
     again for some time to come. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HILL1">Mr. HILL</persName>.- The hon. member for 
     <lb/>
     Northumberland asked if the State of 
     <lb/>
     Maine were doing anything towards 
     <lb/>
     building the road on their side of the 
     <lb/>
     line. The assistance given to the com<lb break="no"/>pany, of which Mr. Poor is the President, 
     <lb/>
     is one million of acres of land, subject to 
     <lb/>
     a claim of Massachusetts of $250,000. 
     <lb/>
     This claim, it is expected, will be given 
     <lb/>up to the company, as the effect of<lb/>building the road will be to pour<lb/>a stream of trade and travel into Boston<lb/>equal to the amount. The feeling in<lb/>Boston is growing very favorable to this<lb/>plan. They also receive a large unsettled<lb/>claim, and $100,000 was expected to be<lb/>appropriated by the last Congress, but<lb/>was not got through. In addition to<lb/>this, the city of Bangor take stock in the<lb/>company to the extent of $500,000, on<lb/>the condition that the line run from Ban<lb break="no"/>gor to Mattawamkeag Point. Their ob<lb break="no"/>ject in pushing the line so far up is to<lb/>carry the trade of Aroostook and the<lb/>upper country to Bangor instead of Saint.<lb/>John. The House will see that the Eu<lb break="no"/>ropean and North American Railway<lb/>Company have a strong team to work<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
     

     with, and it is generally supposed they 
     <lb/>will experience no difficulty in carrying<lb/>on the work. The Government there do<lb/>not build, as they have no revenue de<lb break="no"/>rived for that purpose. If anything were<lb/>given it would have to be raised by direct<lb/>taxation.<lb/>
            </p>

    

   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:KERR1">Mr. KERR</persName>.-I would be just as free to 
     <lb/>give them lands as the State of Maine,<lb/>
     and as to unsettled claims there are an in<lb break="no"/>definite amount of them, that we could 
     <lb/>
     readily bestow upon any company desir<lb break="no"/>ing to build, but it appears the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment really have not given one dollar to<lb break="no"/>ward the prosecution of the work. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>On the division of the House on the amend<lb break="no"/>ment - Yeas 10. Nays 29.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On the division of the House, on the fifth<lb/>paragraph - Yeas 27. Nays 12.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName> moved that the fifth<lb/>paragraph be reconsidered, and the fol<lb break="no"/>lowing substituted in its place: "We are<lb/>pleased to learn that the completion and<lb/>extension of the European and North<lb/>American Railway, from the frontier of<lb/>Nova Scotia to the boundary of the United<lb/>States, will be undertaken. If existing<lb/>laws preclude immediate action, we will<lb/>consider any measure which may be pro<lb break="no"/>posed for their amendment, and which<lb/>will provide for an early commencement of<lb/>the work."<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On division of the House on reconsid<lb break="no"/>eration - Yeas 2, Nays 28.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Paragraphs 6,7 and 8, were read and passed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     On the reading of the 9th, <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName> 
     <lb/>asked the Government if they intended to<lb/>take steps for the reduction of salaries of<lb/>public officers, and make other retrench<lb break="no"/>ments.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.- It is the intention<lb/>of Government to exercise the strictest<lb/>economy they can, without impairing the<lb/>usefulness of public offices.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Paragraphs 10 and 11, were then read<lb/>and passed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:OTTY1">Mr. OTTY</persName> moved that the Address be<lb/>engrossed, signed by the Speaker, and<lb/>presented to the Governor by the whole<lb/>House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:OTTY1">Mr. OTTY</persName> further moved, that a Com<lb break="no"/>mittee be appointed to wait on His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency to be informed when he will be<lb/>pleased to receive them therewith.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILM1">Mr. WILMOT</persName> moved for leave to bring<lb/>in a Bill to prepare an Act for the Incor<lb break="no"/>poration of the Carleton and Saint John<lb/>Ship Building and Trading Company.<lb/>Also, presented a petition from G. Allen<lb/>and others, praying for said Act of Incor<lb break="no"/>poration.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Mr. BOYD</persName> presented a petition from the<lb/>Ministers, Elders and Trustees of the<lb/>Church of Scotland, praying that certain<lb/>Bills before the House may pass.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Mr. BOYD</persName> moved for leave to bring in<lb/>a Bill to provide for the payment of the<lb/>expenses of Grand Jurors.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName> moved for leave to bring<lb/>in a Bill relating to the registry of Bills<lb/>of Sale of personal chattels.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Hon. Mr. ALLEN</persName> moved the House into<lb/>Committee on the Bill to revive and con<lb break="no"/>tinue the Act to regulate the sale of Spirit<lb break="no"/>uous Liquors.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>House in Committee-Mr. McClellan<lb/>in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Mr. ALLEN</persName> said, this was an Act to re<lb break="no"/>vive and continue an Act of 1854. That<lb/>law expires to-day. Adopted.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SPEA1">The SPEAKER</persName> having taken the Chair,<lb/>on motion, the Bill became law.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Adjourned till 9 a.m. to-morrow.</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">J.M.<lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2017-11-17, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

           <!-- <p>Tuesday, May 2<lb/>Mr. Gilbert moved that the House go<lb/>
            </p>
-->
    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>