<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-03-29"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-03-29">29 March 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="71" to="78"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_071.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_072.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_073.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_074.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_075.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_076.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_077.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_078.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-07">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-07">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_071">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_071.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_072">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_072.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_073">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_073.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_074">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_074.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_075">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_075.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_076">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_076.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_077">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_077.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_078">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_078.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="71" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_071.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  <fw type="num">71</fw> 
   
<!-- GL, 2018-03-07, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 

          <!--  <p>
     Inches, that the order had been re<lb break="no"/>pealed, the grants would issue 
     <lb/>
     to all previous sales under the order. 
     <lb/>
     This was the way the business of the of<lb break="no"/>fice was managed. They sold land under 
     <lb/>
     certain conditions. and then violatcd 
     <lb/>
     them. Why did they not extend some 
     <lb/>
     of these privileges to the Hartley sales? 
     <lb/>
     They forgot who were required to per<lb break="no"/>form the conditions of the law to the let<lb break="no"/>ter, and received no grants. The inat<lb break="no"/>tention of the Commissioner, or the want 
     <lb/>
     of knowledge in reference to the matter, 
     <lb/>
     has caused persons a great inconvenience. 
     <lb/>
     I know it from the many calls I have to 
     <lb/>
     attend to in these matters and my com<lb break="no"/>munications to the Crown Land Office 
     <lb/>
     will show a further evidence in regard to 
     <lb/>
     it. I will mention a case where a grant 
     <lb/>
     was issued to a man who actually does 
     <lb/>
     not own the land and, four or five others 
     <lb/>
     have been kept out of their grants where 
     <lb/>
     the labor had been performed, within my 
     <lb/>
     personal knowledge, for the last three or 
     <lb/>
     four years. This matter was brought 
     <lb/>
     under the notice of the Surveyor General 
     <lb/>
     during the last Session. I had to take 
     <lb/>
     the matter in hand myself, and get a sur<lb break="no"/>vey, and have now the returns in my 
     <lb/>
     hand for the purpose of being handed in 
     <lb/>
     to the Crown Land Office, which being 
     <lb/>
    done I am informed the grants will be 
     <lb/>issued. If this is the way one of the 
     <lb/>most important departments, affecting 
     <lb/>every settler throughout the Province, is 
     <lb/>to be managed—it the head of the depart<lb break="no"/>ment is incompetent -\- it is a charge 
     <lb/>against the Government, and I hope by a 
     <lb/>vote of this House a change will take 
     <lb/>place, and a thorough reformation be es<lb break="no"/>tablished that office. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The Surveyor General attacked me in a 
     <lb/>
     rather defiant manner, in reference to a 
     <lb/>
     case -———, that I did not inform some<lb break="no"/>body that I knew this Order of Council<lb/>
    was rescinded. (Mr. Botsford—I did not, 
     <lb/>I made no charge against him. It was in 
     <lb/>reply to a charge made against me in re<lb break="no"/>ference to a petition, he said it was not 
     <lb/>known, and I said he knew it.) I made 
     <lb/>no charge. I said there appeared to be 
     <lb/>some mis-apprehension in reference to 
     <lb/>something in connection with Mr. Hart<lb break="no"/>ley. (Mr. Botsford -\- I made no charge 
     <lb/>against Mr. Hartley. I asked his hon. 
     <lb/>colleague (Mr. Lindsay) who the deputy 
     <lb/>was that stated the land could not be 
     <lb/>sold, and he replied, Mr. Hartley. I was 
     <lb/>replying when he (Mr. Connell rose up 
     <lb/>and stated it was not known. I replied 
     <lb/>that he knew of it, and others knew of<lb/>it.) I stood up for the purpose of remov<lb break="no"/>ing an erroneous impression so far as Mr. 
     <lb/>Hartley was concerned. Mr. Hartley knew 
     <lb/>nothing in reference to this order being 
     <lb/>rescinded until it was remarked upon by 
     <lb/>the papers in St. John He said he had 
     <lb/>seen in the Telegraph, that there was a 
     <lb/>great difficulty about the Government 
     <lb/>selling land, and that the order of Coun<lb break="no"/>cil had been rescinded. I replied I had 
     <lb/>known that some time ago. He said 
     <lb/>that this was the first he had heard of it. 
     <lb/>The Surveyor General knows that was 
     <lb/>Mr. Hartley's position, and that was the 
     <lb/>reason I made these observations  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     The debate was then adjourned until 
     <lb/>
     to-morrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     T. P. D. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>-->
          


  <head rendition="simple:right">
     THURSDAY, MARCH <choice><sic>27</sic><corr>29</corr></choice>. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     The House went into Committee of the<lb/>Whole (Mr. Scovil in the chair) in fur<lb break="no"/>ther consideration of a Bill to abolish the<lb/>property qualification of members to serve<lb/>in the General Assembly of the Province.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:COST1">MR. COSTIGAN</persName> explained that the<lb/>object of the Bill was to do away with<lb/>the law that now existed. That demand<lb break="no"/>ed that candidates offering to serve in<lb/>the General Assembly of the Province<lb/>should possess real estate to the value of<lb/>£300. the true principle, which it was<lb/>the object of the Bill to establish, was, that<lb/>the choice of representatives should be<lb/>left to the constituents. The abolish<lb break="no"/>ment of the property qualification would<lb/>give them a freer choice, and this would<lb/>be better for the interests of the country.  
     <lb/>As the law now stood, a man might offer 
     <lb/>to serve in whom all the electors of a 
     <lb/>County, save one were perfectly willing 
     <lb/>to confide, and this one man might object 
     <lb/>to his election, and say he had no pro<lb break="no"/>perty qualification. Mr. Contigan then 
     <lb/>quoted from a despatch to Mr. Dundas, 
     <lb/>Governor of Prince Edward's Island, from 
     <lb/>the late Secretary of the Colonies, on the 
     <lb/>subject of election of the Legislative 
     <lb/>Council, in which the Duke of New<lb break="no"/>castle said, that the property qualifica<lb break="no"/>tion ought to be possessed not by the can<lb break="no"/>didate, but by the voter. In Great Britain 
     <lb/>no property  qualification was now re<lb break="no"/>quired of candidates to the Imperial Par<lb break="no"/>liament. With regard to the law in the 
     <lb/>Province, he did not see why it should be 
     <lb/>allowed to stand on the Statute Book, for 
     <lb/>it was not carried out. It gave to the 
     <lb/>man having no property qualifications, but 
     <lb/>who did not respect the law, and advan<lb break="no"/>tage over the honest unqualified man who<lb/>did.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> said<lb/>he had always opposed this Bill. Though<lb/>he could not deny that the property quali<lb break="no"/>fication had been abolished in England.<lb/>He did not see that was a conclusive ar<lb break="no"/>gument for abolishing it in the PRovince.<lb/>the principle of safety and conservatism<lb/>required that the men who sent represen<lb break="no"/>tatives to the Legislature should be pos<lb break="no"/>sessed of property. If the electors sent<lb/>a representative who had no property,<lb/>would he be a safe man to whom to sub<lb break="no"/>mit the protection of their property? He<lb/>did not think that it was too much to de<lb break="no"/>mand that all men who proposed to serve<lb/>as representatives in the House of Assem<lb break="no"/>bly should be possessed of real estate to <lb/>the amount of £300.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">MR. NEEDHAM</persName> said that the were<lb/>some great principles connected with the<lb/>principle of the Bill that ought to be un<lb break="no"/>derstood. He would take the present op<lb break="no"/>portunity to announce his political faith.<lb/>
               <lb/>He wished the people to understand that<lb/>he had not been born a politician -- the<lb/>principles he maintained had not grown<lb/>up with him from his boyhood, but<lb/>had their commencement about the year<lb/>1847 and 48. Ever since th etime he had<lb/>been politically regenerated, he could say<lb/>that he had never fallen away from poli<lb break="no"/>tical grace. He entertained the same<lb/>principles now as those he had learnt in<lb/>the years 1847 and '8. In making use of<lb/>bold expressions of opinion, men were<lb/>often misunderstood, but the opinion he<lb/>was about to utter he had before express<lb break="no"/>ed on the floors of the House and outside<lb/>its walls. He did believe in the princi<lb break="no"/>ple of universal suffrage, and he would<lb/>tell the House why he believed in ti. In<lb/>this deliberative Assembly where they le<lb break="no"/>
         
            <cb/>
            

     gislated on the lives, property and liber<lb break="no"/>ties of the people - he wished to say that<lb/>
     that principle was consonant with the 
     <lb/>spirit of the British Constitution, and he<lb/>wished that opinion put on record. When<lb/>he spoke of universal suffrage - he meant<lb/>that every man in teh community who<lb/>paid taxes had a right to vote, and to have<lb/>a say in the legislation of the country.<lb/>They were there to legislate on the lives,<lb/>liberties, and properties of the people - <lb/>and the most abject man, he meant abject,<lb/>not in spirit, but in purse, who paid<lb/>the least amount of taxes had as much right<lb/>to have a voice in the choice of a repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives as the richest. Liberty was<lb/>dear to every man - the live of man was<lb/>not to be measured by the reiches he pos<lb break="no"/>sessed, it was as precious to the man who<lb/>had scarcely a rag to cover him - as to<lb/>him who was clothed in purple and fine<lb/>linen; was not life to Lazarus the beggar<lb/>as dear as life was to the rich man Dives?<lb/>He said that the most abject man in con<lb break="no"/>dition had the right to an equal voice in<lb/>the legislature of his country with the<lb/>most powerful.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     He would call the attention of his breth<lb break="no"/>ren of the law to a statement made by<lb/>Sir William Blackstone in his commen<lb break="no"/>taries - a man whose dicta was never dis<lb break="no"/>sented from. It was perfectly consonant<lb/>he said, with the spirit of the British Con<lb break="no"/>stitution, that every man who paid taxes<lb/>should have a vote, and the time would<lb/>come when that principle would be carried<lb/>out - might was not always right. The<lb/>Parliament of England when it established<lb/>property qualification for members, gave as<lb/>a reason why a certain class of men ought<lb/>to be excluded from the right of voting, that<lb/>they were men of so mean a situation in<lb/>life that they had no will or mind of their<lb/>own. If Sir William Blackstone had lived<lb/> <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>
 day, he would know that it was not<lb/>always the poor man who wa influenced<lb/>by the will of others, or who was most<lb/>corrupt. He had seen a poor man in<lb/>one of the back settlements of York<lb/>County, whose barns and house had been<lb/>swept away by fire, who had solicited and<lb/>received donations to help him to repair his<lb/>loss; he had seen that man at the polls<lb/>offered $10 to vote against a candidate<lb/>whose principles he believed in; but,<lb/>though homeless, barnless and shelter-<lb break="yes"/>less, he turned away from the proffered<lb/>bribe and voted as his judgement and his <lb/>conscience dictated. And that was a <lb/>specimen of a York elector. He had as<lb break="no"/>signed the reason why the property quali<lb break="no"/>fication was at first demanded, but when<lb/>Blackstone said that it was consonant<lb/>with the spirit of the British Constitution<lb/>that every man who was taxed should<lb/>have the right to vote, then, he said,<lb/>policy ought to give way to absolute right.<lb/>It was the Legislature that gave the peo<lb break="no"/>ple the right to vote. But he held that<lb/>it was the inalienable right of every man<lb/>born into the world to enjoy life and lib<lb break="no"/>tery. Go back to the most ancient times,<lb/>and they would find that every man had<lb/>the same right as he came from the<lb/>hand of God. Then the weakest and<lb/>most abject man was equal in these re<lb break="no"/>spects with the richest and strongest.<lb/>That was the original stae, and the same<lb/>rights that existed then existed now.<lb/>That inalienable right to life and liberty,<lb/>and to have a voice in the Government,<lb/>had never been given up by the people.<lb/>The, if the right to vote had never been <lb/>given up, there was no reason why they<lb/>should be asked to give the people the<lb/>right; and the people had the abso<lb break="no"/>
          

            <pb n="72" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_072.jpg"/>
      

     <fw type="num">72</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES IN THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 


    

     lute right, why make laws to restrict them,             
     <lb/>in its exercise?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. Needham</persName> proceeded to say that,<lb/>though he believed the principle of uni<lb break="no"/>versal suffrage perfectly consonant with<lb/>the principles of common justice and of<lb/>the British Constitution, he did not wish<lb/>to be understood as seeking to carry it<lb/>out where property was concerned. Take<lb/>the example of a civic body, who only<lb/>met to manage the affairs of a county<lb/>and City, in reference to their property.<lb/>That was a body created by law, but they<lb/>were placed there to legislate on proper<lb break="no"/>ty; they had a right to impose rates. He<lb/>would go for that. He would make a<lb/>sliding scale to give votes according to<lb/>property, when the question was simply<lb/>that of property, and not the lives and<lb/>liberties of men. He could understand<lb/>the policy of imposing a qualification of<lb/>the electors. When the question came<lb/>to property, let them come down to a<lb/>sliding scale, and let every man have a<lb/>vot according to tis value. They might<lb/>think of those things as they liked, they<lb/>would have to adopt them. He had now<lb/>enunciated his principles with regard to<lb/>universal suffrage. He would say, fur<lb break="no"/>ther, that there was nothing that made<lb/>his blood glow so warmly, nothing that<lb/>stirred his manhood more than when he<lb/>thought of the glorious principles of<lb/>liberty. Let them talk of their parties<lb/>and their policies of Liberal, Conserva<lb break="no"/>tive or Tories; the principles of liberty<lb/>was the vitality and the reality of political<lb/>life. He was prepared to stand or fall by<lb/>this principle. It was a matter of little<lb/>importance what he, individually, thought<lb/>it was - of no importance what because<lb/>of himself - but it was a matter of vital<lb/>importance whether those indefeasible<lb/>principles were held sacred or not.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. Needham</persName> then went on to speak of 
     <lb/>the abolishment of the property qualifica<lb break="no"/>tion of members in England, quoting from<lb/>the Imperial Act, which he said, gave an<lb/>emphatic denial to all who said that a<lb/>property qualification was necessary in a <lb/>member of Parliament.<lb/>
     
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Let them suppose a case, that an elec<lb break="no"/>tion had come round. On the day of nomi<lb break="no"/>nation, the property qualification of a<lb/>candidate had been tested, and that he<lb/>had proved himself qualified and ran his<lb/>election; but before the day of victory<lb/>arrived, by some interposition of Provi<lb break="no"/>dence the property upon which the quali<lb break="no"/>fication was founded was swept away, that<lb/>man would be elected without any pro<lb break="no"/>perty qualification. Was he any the worse<lb/>for it? But if that election held good, was<lb/>the spirit of the law in that case carried<lb/>out? If they make a property qualifica<lb break="no"/>tion, do not let them make any deci<lb/>about the matter. If it was necessary be<lb break="no"/>fore the election, it was necessary after<lb/>it. With regard to the property qualifica<lb break="no"/>tion, they all knew that it was evaded.<lb/>By the first law that was enacted in the<lb/>Province regarding it in 1846, all that a<lb/>man had to do was to make a statement<lb/>that he had real estate; it did not make<lb/>it necessary that he should show it. Un<lb break="no"/>der that law it was impossible for any one<lb/>to prove that a proposing dandidate had<lb/>not a property qualifications, for he had<lb/>to prove a negative, and to do that he<lb/>would have to put every man and woman<lb/>in the Province on the stand to prove<lb/>that he had not the legal property quali<lb break="no"/>fication, and a prosecution under the law<lb/>would have stretched out until the crack<lb/>of doom. In the present law they put in<lb/>a section that made it necessary to state<lb/>
     

            <cb/>
         

     where that property was, but that also  
     <lb/>could be evaded. (Here <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. Needham</persName> <lb/>entertained the House at great length<lb/>with his own case under that law.) Mr.<lb/>Needham then asked what was the good<lb/>of a property qualification? and proceed<lb break="no"/>ed to put a case. He would suppose that<lb/>when the present House was dissolved,<lb/>at the end of four years, and he had no<lb/>property qualification, ut that he found<lb/>some one to give him a deed of property,<lb/>would that deed of property really be his?<lb/>would the possession of it make him more<lb/>capable to act as a legislator? The ac<lb break="no"/>tual possession of property was no evi<lb break="no"/>dence of a man's powers of mind, it was<lb/>an evidence that the man had the power<lb/>of accumulating property, but no evi<lb break="no"/>dence that he had legislative talents; it<lb/>was an evidence of prudence, and fore<lb break="no"/>thought, but no evidence of statesmanlike<lb/>capacity. How could the possession of so<lb/>many acres of land prove that a man was<lb/>fit for a legislator? The question was <lb/>one of great importance, and one that<lb/>would ultimately become the law of the<lb/>land, and he hoped the present House<lb/>would follow the example set them by the<lb/>Parliament of England and pass this Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">MR. LINDSAY</persName> thought the Bill re<lb break="no"/>quired a good deal of consideration. He<lb/>believed in an extension of teh franchise<lb/>to a limited extent, but he had never<lb/>been and never would be in favor of uni<lb break="no"/>versal suffrage. He was opposed to<lb/>giving the right hof voting to the loose,<lb/>floating population of the countyr, who<lb/>had neither interest or concern in its af<lb break="no"/>fairs. He objected to the principle of<lb/>this Bill. He allowed a man to be a repre<lb break="no"/>sentative who had not a right to vote.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:COST1">MR. COSTIGAN</persName> - That was not a 
     <lb/>fair way of putting the objection. The<lb/>Bill did not give a man a right to be a <lb/>representative who had not a right to <lb/>vote, ut it gave the electors the right to<lb/>choose whom they pleased.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">MR. LINDSAY</persName>. - that did not change 
     <lb/>the question. he thought if the hon.<lb/>mover did not expect an election this year,<lb/>he had better consent to its postponement<lb/>for the Bill required a good deal of con<lb break="no"/>sideration. He thought that every man,<lb/>before he was either representative or<lb/>elector, should have a stake in the coun<lb break="no"/>try, and every man in this country might<lb/>have a stake if he choose.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:THOM1">Dr. THOMSON</persName>, (who was inaudible 
     <lb/>in the gallery) was understood to say that<lb/>he agreed with the views of the Hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber of Carleton who had just spoken.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LAND1">MR. LANDRY</persName> was understood to 
     <lb/>speak in favor of the principle of univer<lb break="no"/>sal suffrage, and to say that he supported<lb/>the Bill willingly, as it would enable the<lb/>French population of Westmorland, whose<lb/>rights were neglected by the Government<lb/>to send Frenchmen to good eductation,<lb/>and who could speak English, to attend<lb/>to their interests. He only supported the<lb/>Government on account of Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:OTTY1">MR. OTTY</persName> was glad the hon. member 
     <lb/>
     from Carleton, who had expressed his 
     <lb/>views on this subject, hd seen the error<lb/>of his ways, and given up the doctrine of<lb/>representation by population, for he had<lb/>distinctly declared he was opposed to<lb/>universal suffrage - that property must<lb/>be represented, and not people; that on<lb/>the part of the Quebec Scheme was a re<lb break="no"/>cantation of Mr. George Brown's grand<lb/>principle, representation by population.<lb/>What woudl be the effect of that Bill?<lb/>It would place in the House persons hav<lb break="no"/>ing no stake in the country, and no<lb/>
       
            <cb/>
           

     interest in the prosperity of the country. 
     <lb/>The principle was bad, and to elucidate it<lb/>he would read a letter he had received<lb/>from one of his constituents that morn<lb break="no"/>ing, wherein he complained that at the<lb/>parish election four person were elected<lb/>for parish officers who paid neigher<lb/>rate nor tax in the parish, and one of the<lb/>elected was a black boy under twenty-one<lb/>years of age; and yet the Clerk of the<lb/>peace stated to the Magistrates,<lb/>when called to give his opinion, that<lb/>the election must stand, Although<lb/>the property qualification laws had<lb/>been repealed in England in 1858,<lb/>still the circumstances of the people there<lb/>and here were very different; and what<lb/>might be very applicable there, would not<lb/>suit our floating population, where a per<lb break="no"/>son might be here to-day and gone to<lb break="no"/>morrow, and his property was the only<lb/>chain to bind him to his country. The<lb/>Bill was an important one, and it required<lb/>consideration. It was an alterationin<lb/>the Constitution; and, although the Hon.<lb/>Attorney General had stated it had been<lb/>up for discussion before every House fo<lb/>some years back, he could not go for the<lb/>Bill until he enquired further into the<lb/>matter. If the hon. member who intro<lb break="no"/>duced the Bill would report progress, he<lb/>might be induced to go for his Bill.<lb/>And here he would allude, while they<lb/>were upon the discussion of the qualifi<lb break="no"/>cation of members, to the inconsistency<lb/>and injustice of the appointment of mem<lb break="no"/>bers of the Upper House under the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Scheme, which while it provided that<lb/>the firstmembers of teh Legislative<lb/>Council should be appointed from the<lb/>present members of the different Provin<lb break="no"/>cial Legislative Councils, it made no<lb/>provision or assurance that after<lb break="no"/>wards, or when vacancies occur, the<lb/>members representing New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick, Nova Scotia or Prince Edward's <lb/>Island, should possess property, or reside<lb/>in the respective Provinces for which the<lb/>are appointed. By the 16th Section of<lb/>the Quebec Scheme Lower Canada had<lb/>the privilege of always having Legisla<lb break="no"/>tive Councillors residing and possessing<lb/>property in that district to represent her,<lb/>but after the first Councillors die, or va<lb break="no"/>cancies occur, New Brunswick, Nova<lb/>Scotia and P.E. Island might have to<lb/>submit to be represented by Legislative<lb/>Councillors, who possess no qualification<lb/>in the Privince they are to represent,<lb/>need not even reside there and may not<lb/>even ever have been in the country they<lb/>are appointed by the Canadian Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to represent.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCMI1">MR. McMILLAN</persName> said they were not<lb/>called upon at the present time to dis<lb break="no"/>cuss the great scheme, with regard to the<lb/>Bill before the House; it, in reality, ex<lb break="no"/>tended the rights of the people, gave<lb/>them a larger field to make a selection<lb/>from in their choice of representatives.<lb/>The law, as it now stood, was imperative,<lb/>for property qualification was evaded.<lb/>He should vote for the Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LEWI1">MR. LEWIS</persName> said he would be com<lb break="no"/>pelled to vote against the Bill. He<lb/>thought that there ought to be property<lb/>qualifications demanded of candidates. It<lb/>had been said that the possession of pro<lb break="no"/>perty did not give a man brains. That<lb/>was true; but it would be very danger<lb break="no"/>ous to have men with too much brains<lb/>and no property, as representatives of the<lb/>constituencies of the Province.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOYD1">MR. BOYD</persName> was opposed to the Bill,<lb/>and thought its principle most dangerous.<lb/>If it became law it would open the door<lb/>
         

            <pb n="73" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_073.jpg"/>
        
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>  <fw type="num">73</fw> 

       

     and let in representatives who would 
     <lb/>
     lower the character of the House and 
     <lb/>
     change its complexion entirely. It would 
     <lb/>
     change the character of the representa<lb break="no"/>tives altogether. There were many 
     <lb/>
     young men with winning ways who had 
     <lb/>
     no more brains than his bot, who would 
     <lb/>
     get into the House if thie Bill passed. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:NEED1">MR. NEEDHAM</persName>. - It was an exceed<lb break="no"/>ingly high compliment For the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber of Charlotte (Mr. Boyd) to pay his 
     <lb/>constituents, to say they could be cajoled 
     <lb/>by men without brains. </p>
    

<p><persName ref="pers:HATH1">HON. MR. HATHEWAY</persName> took a very 
     <lb/>different view of the Bill from the hon. 
     <lb/>member for Charlotte. He would put a 
     <lb/>case that might happen under the law as 
     <lb/>it stood. If he was a merchant doing 
     <lb/>business in Fredericton, say to the ex<lb break="no"/>tent of $60,000, yet if he had not £300 
     <lb/>real estate, he could not offer merely be<lb break="no"/>cause he had not the property qualifica<lb break="no"/>tion demanded by law, yet he could go 
     <lb/>into the Crown Land Office and take out 
     <lb/>land to the value of £300, and he would 
     <lb/>be entitled to sit He would put another 
     <lb/>case. In St. Mery'a there was a teacher 
     <lb/>who had been known in the parish l'or 
     <lb/>twenty-one years. who waa an honest, 
     <lb/>honorable man and in whom all the peo<lb break="no"/>ple had confidence; what right had the 
     <lb/>Legislature merely because that teacher 
     <lb/>had not the property qualification, to 
     <lb/>restrict the electors from voting for him, 
     <lb/>and oblige them, were there no other 
     <lb/>qualified candidate in the field, to tote 
     <lb/>for Hatheway, say because he was pos<lb break="no"/>sessed of an estate? The hon. member 
     <lb/>for Charlotte (Mr. Boyd) thought the 
     <lb/>Bill most dangerous, but he was not 
     <lb/>afraid of it, for property would always 
     <lb/>have its influence. He was in favor of 
     <lb/>the principle of the Bill, for it gave great<lb break="no"/>er right to the electors in the choice of<lb/>representatives. He had yet to learn that 
     <lb/>the man who had little property did not 
     <lb/>feel as much interest in the prosperity, 
     <lb/>welfare and good governance of the 
     <lb/>country as the man who held a great 
     <lb/>stake. He would give the people free 
     <lb/>choice. If they had confidence in certain 
     <lb/>men, why should the Legislature restrict 
     <lb/>them in the right to return them as re<lb break="no"/>presentatives?   
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SUTT1">MR. SUTTON</persName> briefly suppported the 
     <lb/>Bill<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">MR. WILMOT</persName> thought it was much 
     <lb/>
     more important to regulate the franchise 
     <lb/>
     than to abolish the property qualification. 
     <lb/>
     He believed the law was evaded now re<lb break="no"/>garding it. There was no Bill that they 
     <lb/>
    could pass in the House through which 
     <lb/>they could not drive a coach and four. 
     <lb/>With regard to universal suffrage, while 
     <lb/>in theory the justness of the principle 
     <lb/>might be difficult to combat, yet the prac<lb break="no"/>tical carrying of it out had, it was well 
     <lb/>known, not worked well, and had been 
     <lb/>most dangerous and destructive.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> said that, so far his 
     <lb/>
     judgement went, he entirely accorded 
     <lb/>
     with the principle of the Bill. It appear<lb break="no"/>ed to him very reasonable. What right, he 
     <lb/>
     asked, where people having property if they 
     <lb/>
     wanted a certain person to represent 
     <lb/>
     their interests in the Legislature, had the 
     <lb/>
     law to demand that that person should be 
     <lb/>
     possessed of a certain property qualifica<lb break="no"/>tion? He could not see why it was ne<lb break="no"/>cessary that he should have property. 
     <lb/>
     The question arose, who had appointed 
     <lb/>
     representatives to the Legielature? Was 
     <lb/>
     it not the people who possessed the pro<lb break="no"/>perty of the country? Representatives<lb/>
    were sent to the Legislature not because 
     <lb/>they possessed property, but to represent 
 

            <cb/>
        

     the people's interests. It was not requi<lb break="no"/>site that the electors should possess pro<lb break="no"/>perty; but all that was required, he 
     <lb/>
     thought, of a man they wished to elect 
     <lb/>
     was that the electors should have confi<lb break="no"/>dence in him, in his integrity, and his 
     <lb/>
     ability to discharge the duties of a repre<lb break="no"/>sentative. As the law stood, however 
     <lb/>
     capable a man might be, whatever the 
     <lb/>
     amount of confidence the electors could 
     <lb/>
     place in him, unless he had a certain 
     <lb/>
     property qualification, his abilities were 
     <lb/>
     scattered to the wind. If the people had 
     <lb/>
     a right to return representatives, he 
     <lb/>
     would give them the right to appoint 
     <lb/>
     whom they pleaeed, whether the persons 
     <lb/>
     had property or not. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> had 
     <lb/>
     alwaya opposed the Bill, though, no 
     <lb/>
     doubt. in point of principle, the thing was 
     <lb/>
     right. It appeared just that electors 
     <lb/>
     who had the right to choose representa<lb break="no"/>tives should appoint whom they pleased. 
     <lb/>
     But the Bill did seem to ignore the pro<lb break="no"/>tective point of the property qualification. 
     <lb/>
     They (the members of the House came 
     <lb/>
     to the Legislature to represent the pro<lb break="no"/>perty of those who sent them there; and 
     <lb/>
     the law, as it stood, demanded that those 
     <lb/>
     who represented the property of the 
     <lb/>
    country should have an interest in what 
     <lb/>they represented. If electors choose to 
     <lb/>elect a representative without property, 
     <lb/>that man represented not only the pro<lb break="no"/>perty of those who sent him there, but 
     <lb/>the property ot the whole country. If 
     <lb/>the principle of the Bill was right, if car<lb break="no"/>ried out, he thought that it would have 
     <lb/>little practical effect as long as they ad<lb break="no"/>hered to the principle that the men who 
     <lb/>voted should possess property; that, 
     <lb/>after all was the true safeguard, the 
     <lb/>centre of safety. Though the principle 
     <lb/>was right, he deemed it undesirable that 
     <lb/>the election portals should be thrown open 
     <lb/>to every man. He admitted that, in re<lb break="no"/>gard to the Bill, his mind was in a cer<lb break="no"/>tain degree changed, but he thought, as 
     <lb/>the subject was of great importance, they 
     <lb/>should take time for further considera<lb break="no"/>tion, and he would recommend that pro<lb break="no"/>gress be now reported . 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Finally, progress was reported. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
     

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     AFTERNOON. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     DEBATE ON THE AMENDMENT TO THE 
     <lb/>
     FOURTH PARAGRAPH OF THE ADDRESS. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">MR. CONNELL</persName> resumed. Mr. Con<lb break="no"/>nell, on commencing. was understood to 
     <lb/>
     remark, that in his last speech he was 
     <lb/>
     going on to refer to the conduct of the 
     <lb/>
     present Government, and to say. that if 
     <lb/>
     the people had an opportunity to pass 
     <lb/>
     judgment on the acts of the present Go<lb break="no"/>vernment, they would not defend it in the 
     <lb/>
     course it had pursued. The question 
     <lb/>
     against the Government had come down 
     <lb/>
     to union. What was their position in re<lb break="no"/>gards it? It appeared that all were 
     <lb/>
     now for union, yet they were not pre<lb break="no"/>pared to bring down any measure, or to 
     <lb/>
     state what they were going to do. He 
     <lb/>
     wanted to put this matter to rest, for the 
     <lb/>
     interests of the country were endangered 
     <lb/>
     in consequence of the unsettled state of 
     <lb/>
     that question. The Government stood 
     <lb/>
     condemned before the country for the 
     <lb/>
     course they had pursued. In York. 
     <lb/>
     where the first opportunity was given to 
     <lb/>
     the people to express their opinion. there 
     <lb/>
     was an utter condemnation of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. The hon. member for York (Mr. 
     <lb/>
     

            <cb/>
      

     Needham) denied that confederation had 
     <lb/>
     anything to do with the election. Well, 
     <lb/>
     suppose it had not, it showed at any rate 
     <lb/>
     that the general conduct of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was opposed by York. The people 
     <lb/>
     of York, by the course they had pursued 
     <lb/>
     had utterly condemned the course of the 
     <lb/>
     Government, and that was the matter be<lb break="no"/>fore the House. On the question of 
     <lb/>
     union the Government had shown an ut<lb break="no"/>ter want of candor. After they put that 
     <lb/>
     paragraph in the speech, they ought to 
     <lb/>
     have come. down and said emphatically, 
     <lb/>
     whether or not they were prepared to 
     <lb/>
     bring in a measure. But it was generally 
     <lb/>
     understood that the Government them<lb break="no"/>selves would not come down with a mea<lb break="no"/>sure. There was however, an arrange<lb break="no"/>ment that if a measure of some descrip<lb break="no"/>tion were brought down by a member 
     <lb/>
     outside, they would support it. There 
     <lb/>
     was, he believed. an understanding to that 
     <lb/>
     effect. The Government. no doubt, were 
     <lb/>
     committed in some way to bring down 
     <lb/>
     a measure during the present sitting of 
     <lb/>
     the House. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>.—He 
     <lb/>
     had told the House on the first day of the 
     <lb/>
     debate that the Government did not in<lb break="no"/>tend to submit a scheme. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">MR. CONNELL</persName>. - Neither submit a 
     <lb/>scheme themselves nor support a measure<lb/>brought in by an outside member? Was<lb/>there no subterfuge about this matter - <lb/>the leader of the Government did not<lb/>deny they would get one of their sup<lb break="no"/>porters to bring in a measure. If a mea<lb break="no"/>sure were brought down in this way<lb/>how would they act? It had been<lb/>rumored that a course of this<lb/>kind was intended. It would be<lb/>too inconsistent, the Government said,<lb/>to bring down a measure themselves, but<lb/>they would get up a side wind and bring<lb/>the matter in that way. They would get<lb/>up an address, moved by one of their sup<lb break="no"/>porters, setting forth that whereas they<lb/>House was in favor of union, and where<lb break="no"/>as it was the desire of Her Majesty that<lb/>the union of the Colonies should take<lb/>place, &amp;c., resolved that an humble ad<lb break="no"/>dress be presented to Her Majesty, &amp;c.<lb/>They would get the House to pass an<lb/>address in favor of union, leaving the de<lb break="no"/>tails to be settled by a delegation to be<lb/>sent home to Great Britain. He had been<lb/>assured that that was the course the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment were going to take. Talk after<lb/>that of a selfish Government, a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment holding on to power. Here<lb/>was a Government that had so late<lb break="no"/>ly talked so loudly about independence,<lb/>and resistance to coercion, willing now to<lb/>permit the interests of the country to be<lb/>encroached upon by the acts of the Im<lb break="no"/>perial Government. Who ever heard of<lb/>such a thing as to leave the whole settle<lb break="no"/>ment of the details fo a scheme having<lb/>such a vast bearing in the interests of the <lb/>country, to the British Government? He<lb/>was surprised to find his hon. friend, the<lb/>member of St. John (Hon. Mr. Cudlip) <lb/>who had always been opposed to union<lb/>in any way or shape, remaining in a Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment that would take such a coursse as<lb/>that he had described. He would be sor<lb break="no"/>ry, for his own part, to let the<lb/>Government send home a delega<lb break="no"/>tion to settle with the British Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment the details of a measure of<lb/>union. He would like so see such a mat<lb break="no"/>ter taken up and brought about by peo<lb break="no"/>ple who were really in earnest. He was<lb/>not committed to any scheme, but if they<lb/>could not get a better one than that<lb/>
    settled upen at the Conference at Quebec, 
     <lb/>
   

            <pb n="74" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_074.jpg"/>
        

     <fw type="num">74</fw>    <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 
 

     they had better take that than none at<lb/>all. He could have no confidence in any 
     <lb/>
     measure of union brought down by the 
     <lb/>
     present Government. How could it be 
     <lb/>
     expected that. any man could, when the 
     <lb/>
     Government had no confidence themselves 
     <lb/>
    in union. At one time they were found 
     <lb/>denouncing the scheme as destructive to 
     <lb/>the best interests of the country, and de<lb break="no"/>claring, both in their speeches and ad<lb break="no"/>dresses that New Brunswick desired no 
     <lb/>closer union with Canada than it had at 
     <lb/>present, and yet they were willing not 
     <lb/>only to adopt union. but to leave the de<lb break="no"/>tails entirely in the hands of the Imperial 
     <lb/>Government lt was desirable, he 
     <lb/>thought that a change in the present 
     <lb/>condition of the people of the Province 
     <lb/>should take place. It was said that Cana<lb break="no"/>da was in debt, and was bankrupt, 
     <lb/>and that it desired union with this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince to help it out of its difficulties. But 
     <lb/>he entertained a very different opinion. 
     <lb/>He had travelled through Canada, and he 
     <lb/>knew the extent of its resources and he 
     <lb/>was of opinion that to be united to such 
     <lb/>a country could do no harm to a Province 
     <lb/>like New Brunswick. Then, again, it 
     <lb/>was said that all the advantagea of union 
     <lb/>would be on the side of Canada. If Ca<lb break="no"/>nada waa to be so vastly mure benefitted 
     <lb/>by union, as some people said, than this 
     <lb/>Province would be, let those who hold 
     <lb/>that opinion go there and live. There 
     <lb/>would be no difficulty about that. He 
     <lb/>would quote some remarks of a gentle<lb break="no"/>man, Mr. Derby. who had drawn up a 
     <lb/>report for the United States Government 
     <lb/>on the Reciprocity Treaty, concerning 
     <lb/>this poverty-struck country, and they 
     <lb/>would show what opinions an intelligent 
     <lb/>writer held of the resources ol Canada ; then 
     <lb/>let them cry out about its being poverty- 
     <lb break="yes"/>pinched: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     "Those persons who are continually 
     <lb/>
     trying to depreciate Canada, and create a 
     <lb/>
     prejudice against any union with that 
     <lb/>
     colony, should read carefully the Report 
     <lb/>
     lately prepared by Mr. Derby at the re<lb break="no"/>quest of the Secretary of the Treasury at 
     <lb/>Washington. He traces the progress 
     <lb/>Çanada aa made in material wealth, and 
     <lb/>in all the elements that constitute ma<lb break="no"/>terial greatness. He says:—"From 185l 
     <lb/>to) 1861 the population of Canada increas<lb break="no"/>ed more rapidly than the population of 
     <lb/>the Union. . . . . In the fifteen<lb/>years from 185l to 1865 the whole ex<lb break="no"/>ports and imports of Canada rose from 
     <lb/>$35,000,000 to $87,000,000. Her reve<lb break="no"/>nue rose also from $3,500,000 to $10,<lb break="no"/>500,000. Betweeen 185l and 1861 her 
     <lb/>improved land increased from 7.307,950 
     <lb/>acres to 10,855,854 or forty-nine per 
     <lb/>cent; the value of the same from $263,<lb break="no"/>516,000 to $466,675,780. The wheat 
     <lb/>crop, which exceeds that of Illinois, and 
     <lb/>of each of our States, rose from 15, 756,<lb break="no"/>493 bushels to 27, 274, 779, or seventy 
     <lb/>eight per cent. The oat crop, larger 
     <lb/>than that of New York. the leading State 
     <lb/>of our Union, rose from 20, 369, 247 bush<lb break="no"/>els to 38,772, 170, or ninety-one per 
     <lb/>cent. During the same period the value 
     <lb/>lumber rose from an average of $7 to 
     <lb/>$10 per M. And in the interval between 
     <lb/>1851 and 1863 her export of lumber rose 
     <lb/>from $5, 085 628, of which but twenty per 
     <lb/>cent. reached the United States to a total 
     <lb/>of $12, 264, 178. . . . . From 1851<lb/>to 1861 she has increased her miles of 
     <lb/>Railway from twelve to nineteen hun<lb break="no"/>dred; she has increased her wheat and 
     <lb/>oat crop, her wool, the value of her for<lb break="no"/>ests and wealth more than we have, al<lb break="no"/>
          

            <cb/>
       
thought she is naturally inferior in climate, 
     <lb/>soil and position."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Here was the clear evidence of a gentle<lb break="no"/>man every way competent to judge as to<lb/>the progress, resources, and the value and<lb/>extent of the trade of Canada. It was<lb/>evidence that could not be disputed. It 
     <lb/>
    was most desireable that such statements 
     <lb/>as that he had read should go forth to the 
     <lb/>people of the Province. It would help 
     <lb/>them to refute those who repeated the 
     <lb/>assertion that Canada was a poverty- 
     <lb break="yes"/>stricken country. He would refer on 
     <lb/>this point not only to the evidence of Mr. 
     <lb/>Derby; he would read the testimony 
     <lb/>of another witness to the value and the 
     <lb/>great resources of that country: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p>
     " Hitherto, in common with most of our 
     <lb/>
     countrymen. as I supose I have thought 
     <lb/>
     Canada, or, to speak more accurately, 
     <lb/>
     British America, a mere strip lying 
     <lb/>
     north of the United States, easily de<lb break="no"/>tachable from the parent state, but inca<lb break="no"/>pable of sustaining itself, and therefore<lb/>ultimately, nay, right soon, to be taken<lb/>on by the Federal Union, without materi<lb break="no"/>ally changing or affecting its own condi<lb break="no"/>tion or development. I have dropped<lb/>the opinion as a national conceit. I see<lb/>in British North America, stretching as<lb/>it does across the Continent, from the<lb/>shores of Labrador and Newfoundland to<lb/>the Pacific, and occupying a considerable<lb/>belt of the temperate zone, traversed<lb/>equally with the United States by the<lb/>lakes, and enjoying the magnificent<lb/>shores of the St. Lawrence, withits<lb/>thousands of islands in the river and the <lb/>gulf, a <hi rendition="simple:italic">region grand enough for the seat<lb/>of a great Empire</hi>.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     "In its wheat fields in the West, its 
     <lb/>broad ranges of the chase at the North,<lb/>its inexhaustible lumber lands - the most<lb/>extensive now remaining on the Globe - <lb/>its invaluable fisheries, and its yet undis<lb break="no"/>turbed mineral deposits, I see the ele<lb break="no"/>ments of wealth. I find its inhabitants<lb/>vigorous, hardy, energetic, perfected by<lb/>the Protestant religion and the British con<lb break="no"/>stitutional liberty. I find them jealous of<lb/>the United States and of Great Britain,<lb/>as they ought to be; and therefore,<lb/>when I look at their extent and resources,<lb/>I know they can <hi rendition="simple:italic">neither be conquered by<lb/>the former</hi> nor permanently held by the<lb/>latter. They will be independent, as<lb/>they are already self-maintaining. Hav<lb break="no"/>ing happily escaped the curse of slavery,<lb/>they will never submit themselves to the<lb/>domination of slave holders, which prevails<lb/>in, and determines the character of, the<lb/>United States. They will be a Russia in<lb/>the United States, which to them will be<lb/>France and England. But they will be a<lb/>Russia Civilized and Protestant, and that<lb/>will be a very different Russia from that<lb/>which fills all Southern Europe with ter<lb break="no"/>ror, and by reason fo that superiority,<lb/>they will be the more terrible to the<lb/>dwellers in the southern latitudes.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     "The policy of the United States is to 
     <lb/>propitiate and secure the alliance of Ca<lb break="no"/>nada while it is yet young and incourious<lb/>of its future. But on the other hand, the<lb/>policy which the United States actually<lb/>pursues is the infatuated on of rejecting<lb/>and spurning vigorous, prerennial, and <lb/>ever-growing Canada, while seeking to<lb/>establish feeble states out of decaying<lb/>Spanish Provinces on the coast and in<lb/>the islands of the Gulf of Mexico.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     "I shall not live to see it, but the man 
     <lb/>is already born who will see th United<lb/>States mourn ever this stupendous folly,<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
         

     which is only preparing the way for ulti<lb break="no"/>mate danger and downfall. All southern<lb/>political stars must set, though many<lb/>times they rise again with dimished<lb/>splendor. <hi rendition="simple:italic">But those which illuminate the<lb/>pole remain forever shining, forever in<lb break="no"/>creasing in splendor</hi>."<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     Here was the opinion of a very eminent 
     <lb/>statesman, Mr. Seward, and it was very<lb/>strong and important evidence thta<lb/>Canada was not the poverty struck place<lb/>the opponents of the scheme endeavored<lb/>to make out. For his part he thought<lb/>it was not the opinion of the Province<lb/>that a closer union with such a country<lb/>was not desirable. he believed the peo<lb break="no"/>ple of the Province did desire a closer<lb/>union, and he was perfectly prepared to test<lb/>that opinion by running another election.<lb/>( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Attorney General</persName>. - The hon. member<lb/>had no means of knowing the mind of the<lb/>Province.) Well, he was perfectly will-<lb break="yes"/>in to run an election and try it that way,<lb/>and he was prepared to find thta a great<lb/>change of feeling had taken place in the<lb/>country, not only on the question of<lb/>union, but with regard to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment. As there was undoubtedly a grow<lb break="no"/>ing feeling on confederation in the coun<lb break="no"/>try, and as the feeling was almost unani<lb break="no"/>mous in the House in favor of union, if<lb/>it was necessary an address, embldying<lb/>that opinion, could be put int the hands<lb/>of the Government, and calling on them<lb/>to dissolve the House and give the peo<lb break="no"/>ple an opportunity to give practical ex<lb break="no"/>pression to their views at the polls. And,<lb/>if necessary, a despatch could be got up<lb/>showing a very great change of feeling<lb/>had taken place since last March, with<lb/>regard to the Government. No act of<lb/>the Attorney General would redound<lb/>more to his credit, and give more satis<lb break="no"/>faction than to let the people have an op<lb break="no"/>portunity to show the change of feeling<lb/>on the question of confederation. He<lb/>would be lauded and extolled through the<lb/>Province as a patriotic man.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     ( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Attorney General</persName>. - At what time did 
     <lb/>he want the election to take place?) The<lb/>sooner the better for the interests of the<lb/>country. It was necessary, in order to<lb/>settle the question that something should<lb/>be done immediately.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     He would now refer to military mat<lb break="no"/>ters, and he must say they were in a <lb/>most unsatisfactory state. He had di<lb break="no"/>rected a letter to His Excellence on the<lb/>subject of defence in the County of<lb/>Carleton, for he felt that it would not<lb/>have been doing himself and his col<lb break="no"/>league justice. They would ont have<lb/>done their duty if they had not reported<lb/>to His Excellency on the defenceless<lb/>state of three important points, Wood<lb break="no"/>stock, Centreville and Richmond. He<lb/>thought it was high time to look to their<lb/>defences when the Governor and the At<lb break="no"/>torney General were travelling night and<lb/>the country. If there was no cause for<lb/>alarm, what occasion was there to take<lb/>such an extraordinary course? He had re<lb break="no"/>ceived from His Excellency a reply to his<lb/>communication, and he say something in<lb/>it which he did not approve of. He did<lb/>not care how high in position the indi<lb/>vidual was who took such a course with<lb/>him, he would not submit to it. He would<lb/>read the letter he had received from His<lb/>Excellency, and he should certainly reply<lb/>to it publicly. His colleague and himself<lb/>had not done any act they were not<lb/>authorized to do, in having communicated<lb/>to His Excellency on the defenceless<lb/>
     

            <pb n="75" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_075.jpg"/>
        
<fw type="running">DEBATES ON THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">75</fw>


     state of Carleton, and giving their rea<lb break="no"/>sons why something should be done, and<lb/>in view of what was doing in St. John,<lb/>St. Stephens and St. Andrews, they were<lb/>justified in thinking that injustice had<lb/>been done to their County. He held the<lb/>Government responsible for everything<lb/>that was in that correspondence. He was<lb/>not going to take the position that this<lb/>was a matter between the Commander-<lb break="yes"/>in-Chief and his colleague and himself,<lb/>but between them and the Government,<lb/>and he wished it to be distinctly under<lb break="no"/>stood that whatever remarks he made<lb/>concerning His Excellency, he applied to<lb/>his Government, and he held the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment responsible for these acts. He<lb/>did not care how high in position the in<lb break="no"/>dividual was, he should not be allowed<lb/>to ride rough-shod over the country<lb/>without his raising his voice against such<lb/>tyranny. He had done nothing which he<lb/>was not authorized to do, and what he<lb/>had said in private to His Excellency, he<lb/>was prepared to affirm in public. It was<lb/>said that the Government of the country<lb/>were powerless in the hands of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernor. It has been said on the floor of<lb/>the House that they could do nothing,<lb/>that there was a power behind them<lb/>greater than themselves, thwarting their<lb/>actions, and that in the hands of that<lb/>power they were completely paralized.<lb/>He would ask if it was a position for the <lb/>Government to take, when they said that<lb/>all militia matters were in the hands of<lb/>the Governor. If the Governor had<lb/>power to make appointments without the<lb/>consent of the Government, and if the<lb/>Governor had power to refuse appoint<lb break="no"/>ments recommended by his Council, he<lb/>held that it was a disgrace to the country.<lb/>He knew that there had been appoint<lb break="no"/>ments recommended that had been refus<lb break="no"/>ed to be made by the Governor. He said<lb/>that was not a position for the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of the country to be placed in. If<lb/>for no other thing, he would condemn<lb/>the Government for the humiliating posi<lb break="no"/>tion they held on the question of militia<lb/>appointments with regard to the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor. He had had the honor of holding a<lb/>position in a Government, and he would<lb/>say that he would not have held that po<lb break="no"/>sition for one hour if any interference had<lb/>been attempted to be made in the ad<lb break="no"/>ministration of the duties of his office<lb/>by the highest individual in the land.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Mr. Connell then proceeded to read <lb/>the following correspondence, on which<lb/>he commented at great length, and said<lb/>he wished it published as part of his<lb/>speech :<lb/>
            </p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">May it please Your Excellency</hi>,—<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    The undersigned Representatives of the <lb/>County of Carleton have learned that<lb/>since they left Woodstock for the purpose<lb/>of attending to their Legislative duties,<lb/>much alarm exists along the Borders<lb/>in the County of Carleton, and that fears<lb/>are entertained that unless some precau<lb break="no"/>tionary measures are taken, unlawful<lb/>acts of aggression may occur.<lb/> <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    It is now reported that Your Excellen- <lb/>cy has ordered the calling out of the Mili<lb break="no"/>tia at St. John ; this information to the<lb/>people of the upper section of the coun<lb break="no"/>try will have the effect of increasing the<lb/>excitement which there exists, as they<lb/>will believe that such action would not<lb/>have been taken unless strong reasons<lb/>exist.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    We respectfully urge upon Your Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency the necessity of calling out and<lb/>
       

            <cb/>
      
organizing a limited number of men,<lb/>which may easily be procured from the<lb/>Volunteers, as we believe that this course<lb/>will have the effect of allaying the existing<lb/>excitement, and be the means of assuring<lb/>the inhabitants of their being protected.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    We beg to suggest that in case Your <lb/>Excellency accedes to the suggestions<lb/>now made, that Woodstock, Centreville<lb/>and Richmond are the points at which<lb/>the services of a guard would be of<lb/>greatest value, as from these places com<lb break="no"/>munication could be more easily had with<lb/>the Volunteers and Civil Authorities of<lb/>the County.</p>      
<p>(Signed)</p>
<p rendition="simple:right">                          Chas. Connell,<lb/>                           William Lindsay.</p>

<p>To His Excellency, the Honorable A.H.<lb/>    Gordon, C.M. G., Lieutenant Gover<lb break="no"/>nor, &amp;c.<lb/>
            </p></quote>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">                 Government House,<lb/>                                Fredericton.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Gentlemen</hi>,—<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    I have the honor to acknowledge the <lb/>receipt of your letter (without date),<lb/>wherein you state that much alarm exists<lb/>along the borders in the County of Carle<lb break="no"/>ton, and that fears are entertained that<lb/>unless some precautionary measures are<lb/>taken unlawful acts of aggression may<lb/>occur. You add that this excitement<lb/>will be increased by the fact that a por<lb break="no"/>tion of the Militia at St. John has been<lb/>called out to aid the small garrison of<lb/>that town, and you request that a body of<lb/>men should be organized and called out<lb/>in the County of Carleton as a means of<lb/>assuring the inhabitants of their being<lb/>protected.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    The House of Assembly, animated by <lb/>a most patriotic spirit, have placed the<lb/>entire resources of the Province at the<lb/>disposal of the Executive for defensive<lb/>purposes, but their liberality imposes upon<lb/>me the obligation of a double vigilance<lb/>as to the unnecessary expenditure of a <lb/>single shilling of the resources thus bes<lb break="no"/>towed.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    The question then to be considered is <lb/>not whether alarm exists among the more<lb/>timid of the inhabitants of any particular<lb/>district, but whether such alarm is rea<lb break="no"/>sonable and well founded, or is undeserv<lb break="no"/>ing of serious attention. It is, perhaps,<lb/>natural that a certain degree of apprehen<lb break="no"/>sion should be felt along the whole frontier,<lb/>but a little reflection will, I think, suffice<lb/>to show that Woodstock is not exposed<lb/>to any serious danger. The condition of<lb/>the roads at this season, and for a month<lb/>or two to come, is usually such as to pre<lb break="no"/>clude all idea of their being traversed by<lb/>large bodies of men, but even under or<lb break="no"/>dinary circumstances, a descent upon New<lb/>Brunswick, through Houlton and Wood<lb break="no"/>stock, by any considerable force, would<lb/>be an enterprise extremely difficult to ex<lb break="no"/>ecute. No great number of men could<lb/>collect at Houlton without public atten<lb break="no"/>tion being attracted to the fact, and even<lb/>supposing the force to be permitted to<lb/>assemble at Bangor unmolested by the<lb/>authorities of that city—a most improba<lb break="no"/>ble supposition—it could not traverse the<lb/>long intervening distance without an<lb/>amount of previous preparation with re<lb break="no"/>spect to transport and supplies, which<lb/>would occupy a considerable time, and<lb/>become universally known long before<lb/>a movement could be possibly made. Those<lb/>who believe the leaders of the Fenian<lb/>conspiracy to possess some military know<lb break="no"/>
          

            <cb/>
         
ledge, can hardly suppose them so grossly 
     <lb/>ignorant as to adopt a plan which would<lb/>be precisely such, as it would be most de<lb break="no"/>sirable that they should follow, which<lb/>would afford ample warning of their in<lb break="no"/>tentions, and which would assure their<lb/>immediate and utter discomfiture. The<lb/>idea of an invasion of New Brunswick,<lb/>in the direction of Woodstock, by a Fe<lb break="no"/>nian Force, may, therefore, I think be<lb/>dismissed as chimerical. I was glad on<lb/>conversing with Mr. Connell on Thurs<lb break="no"/>day last, to find that he expressed his full<lb/>concurrence in these sentiments, and did<lb/>not partake the silly panic which he re<lb break="no"/>presents as prevailing among his consti<lb break="no"/>tuents.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    It is of course possible that a few law- <lb/>less men whose object was plunder, might<lb/>under cover of the name of Fenianism,<lb/>commit some depredations, although it is<lb/>difficult to see how such men would pro<lb break="no"/>pose to escape the general indignation<lb/>sure to be raised against them on both<lb/>sides of the boundary line. Against isola<lb break="no"/>ted acts of burglary or arson, it is evi<lb break="no"/>dently the duty of the local authorities<lb/>to be on the watch and to take such mea<lb break="no"/>sures as may seem necessary, if suspi<lb break="no"/>cious characters are reported to be in the<lb/>vicinity, against any outrage by a gang of<lb/>robbers of a more organized description<lb/>I desired to provide when urging the for<lb break="no"/>mation of Home Guards upon the fron<lb break="no"/>tier. The appeal then made has been<lb/>well responded to in the County of Car<lb break="no"/>leton, though not in the Village of Wood<lb break="no"/>stock itself, and the last returns shew me<lb/>that a force of over five hundred men,<lb/>armed and provided with abundance of<lb/>ammunition, are ready to turn out at the<lb/>shortest notice if required.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Such a force, it appears to me, is more<lb/>than adequate to encounter any emergen<lb break="no"/>cy. I will not say of <hi rendition="simple:italic">probable</hi>, but of <hi rendition="simple:italic">pos<lb break="no"/>sible</hi> occurrence ; and I should not feel<lb/>justified in calling upon the Province to<lb/>incur expenditure which the exigencies<lb/>of the case do not appear to me to re<lb break="no"/>quire. I am fully aware of the grave respon<lb break="no"/>sibility which, in case of error, would rest<lb/>upon me, but whilst I shall not of course<lb/>object to an expenditure which the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature may authorize, I cannot recommend<lb/>its being incurred except at those points<lb/>where danger appears to me to be real<lb/>and pressing. In delining to do other<lb break="no"/>wise, I perform a most disagreeable and<lb/>unpleasant duty, and it may be satisfac<lb break="no"/>tory to you to know that there are locali<lb break="no"/>ties far from the frontier where the inha<lb break="no"/>bitants are as loud in claiming that extra<lb break="no"/>ordinary measures should be taken for<lb/>their protection as the people of Wood<lb break="no"/>stock are represented by you to be.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Should the measure of precaution al- <lb/>ready taken at any time appear inade<lb break="no"/>quate, should the organization already ef<lb break="no"/>fected break down or become illusory, or<lb/>should danger of the character contem<lb break="no"/>plated appear seriously to threaten the<lb/>locality in which you are interested, I<lb/>need not say that steps which, in my opi<lb break="no"/>nion, would at present be injudicious and<lb/>uncalled for, might become not only pro<lb break="no"/>per but necessary. In that event I shall<lb/>not hesitate to assume the responsibility<lb/>of acting as the circumstances may then<lb/>seem to require.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    I am, Gentlemen, <lb/>            Your obedient servant,</p>                         <p rendition="simple:right">ARTHUR GORDON <lb/>                                        Lieut. Governor. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>To Messrs. Connell and Lindsay, &amp;c.<lb/>     You are requested to give publicity to       <lb/>this letter.<lb/>
            </p></quote>


            <pb n="76" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_076.jpg"/>
         
     <fw type="num">76</fw>   <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>
            

<p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. Connell</persName> said he held the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment responsible for the small protec<lb break="no"/>tion they had given to Carleton. He<lb/>considered that in his Excellency's re<lb break="no"/>ply to his colleague's letter there was 
     <lb/>couched an insinuation that they desir<lb break="no"/>ed to get an expenditure of money in 
     <lb/>their section of the country, and that 
     <lb/>that was their reason for urging addi<lb break="no"/>tional defence for Carleton. He said he 
     <lb/>was perfectly sincere, and in earnest, in 
     <lb/>fearing the possible occurrence or acts 
     <lb/>of aggression, and in urging the organ<lb break="no"/>izing of a limited number of men. He 
     <lb/>had told his Excellency, in case any 
     <lb/>emergency arose that the people of 
     <lb/>Carleton would do what had been done 
     <lb/>in Canada, open subscriptions for the 
     <lb/>families of those who were sent to the 
     <lb/>frontier; so far as he was concerned he 
     <lb/>would most willingly subscribe to such 
     <lb/>a fund, and he would do more if any 
     <lb/>danger arose: if any conflict happened 
     <lb/>he would be with those penle on the 
     <lb/>occasion. The letters he had just read 
     <lb/>had been published. But there were 
     <lb/>some documents which had not been 
     <lb/>published to which he desired to draw 
     <lb/>the attention of the Government. The 
     <lb/>first was a communication from his col<lb break="no"/>league and himself to his Excellency, 
     <lb/>inclosing a letter from L. P. Fisher, 
     <lb/>Mayor of Woodstock, and others, inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants of Woodstock and vicinity, re<lb break="no"/>questing them to urge on His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency the necessity of calling out a body 
     <lb/>of the Militia force of the County. This 
     <lb/>letter showed that the declarations made 
     <lb/>by his colleague and himself of the 
     <lb/>alarm in the County were not without 
     <lb/>foundation.
     <lb/>
            </p>
   

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY, 
     <lb/>
     22nd March. 1866. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">May it please Your Excellency</hi>: 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The undersigned have received by mail 
     <lb/>
     last evening the enclosed letters, signed 
     <lb/>
     by L. P. Fisher, who is Mayor, J. R. 
     <lb/>
     Hartley, Warden, and J. C. Winslow. 
     <lb/>
     Clerk of the Peace, and Robert A. Hay, 
     <lb/>
     J. P., with one hundred and twenty-eight 
     <lb/>
     others, inhabitants of Woodstock and 
     <lb/>
     vicinity. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     These letters, we think, will assure 
     <lb/>
     Your Excellency that we have only anti<lb break="no"/>cipated the wishes of the inhabitants in 
     <lb/>
     urging that Your Excetlmcy would au<lb break="no"/>thorize the calling out of a limited portion 
     <lb/>
     of the Militia of Carleton County. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It is important that the existing alarm 
     <lb/>
     along the border should be allayed. 
     <lb/>
     While the inhabitants are ready to do 
     <lb/>
     their part, they feel they are entitled to 
     <lb/>
     the same consideration that some other 
     <lb/>
     parts of the Province are receiving. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In Your Excellency's reply (without 
     <lb/>
     date) to our communication upon the sub<lb break="no"/>ject of Militia, Your Excellency seems to 
     <lb/>
     be under the impression that the inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants of Woodstock have been backward 
     <lb/>
     in tendering their services for the forma<lb break="no"/>tion of the Home Guard. Immediately 
     <lb/>
     on Your Exeellency's wish bein com<lb break="no"/>municated to the residents of Woodstock, 
     <lb/>
     the names of about one hundred volun<lb break="no"/>teers were placed in the hands of the 
     <lb/>Lieutenant Colonel for transmission to 
     <lb/>Your Excellency. We believe that this 
     <lb/>company has not been recognised by 
     <lb/>Your Excellency, nor any arms distribut<lb break="no"/>ed to them. </p>
   
<p>We can only repeat what we have al<lb break="no"/>ready urged, that Your Excellency will 
     <lb/>be pleased to direct that a limited portion<lb/>
           

            <cb/>
          

     of the Militia may be called out to aid    
     <lb/>
    the inhabitants in guarding the fron<lb break="no"/>tier.    
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We have the honor to be,      
     <lb/>

     Your Excellency's     
     <lb/>

     Most obedient servants,    
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p rendition="simple:right">
     (Signed) CHAS CONNELL,    
     <lb/>
   
     WM. LINDSAY.   
     <lb/>
     
            </p>

            <p>To His Excellency the Honorable A.H. 
     <lb/>Gordon, C. M. G., Commander-in- 
     <lb break="yes"/>Chief, &amp;c. 
     <lb/>
            </p></quote>

    
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     WOODSTOCK 
     <lb/>
     20th MARCH, 1866. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Messrs. Connell and Lindsay</hi>.— 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Gents, -  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     We, the undersigned inhabitants of<lb/>Woodstock and vicinity, beg to inform  
     <lb/>
    you that, owing to the organization in the   
     <lb/>United States known as the Fenian Bro-   
     <lb/>therhood, and in the rumors that are  
     <lb/>everyday becoming more startling, and  
     <lb/>as this section of the country is contigu-  
     <lb/>ous to the Unlted States and entirely 
     <lb/>undefended, and open at any time to the 
     <lb/>incursions of predatory bands, the peo<lb break="no"/>ple generally feel themselves to be in a 
     <lb/>state of insecurity. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
    

            <p>
     We therefore, earnestly request that 
     <lb/>
     you will urge upon His Excellency, the 
     <lb/>
     Commander-in-Chief, the importance of 
     <lb/>
    calling out a portion of the Militia force 
     <lb/>of the County. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">L. P. FISHER, 
     <lb/>J. R. HARTLEY, 
     <lb/>R. H HAY,</p> 
     
<p>And one hundred and twenty-eight others.<lb/>
            </p></quote>
   
            <p>
     He would now read the reply of His 
     <lb/>
     Excellency to these communications. a 
     <lb/>
     document, it would seem, that the Go<lb break="no"/>vernment hadnot seen. It seemed to 
     <lb/>
     him that there was a change of basein   
     <lb/>
    this letter, and that it had been taken in   
     <lb/>order to put him in a false position.    
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     
     GOVERNMENT HOUSE  
     <lb/>
     FREDERICTON, 22 March, 1866 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     
     
     
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Gentlemen</hi>,
            </p>

            <p>I am directed by His Excellency the 
     <lb/>Lieutenant Governor to acknowledge<lb/>the receipt of your letter of this day,<lb/>transmitting communications from the<lb/>Mayor of Woodstock and others, on the<lb/>subject of the alarm said to be felt by<lb/>the inhabitants, in anticipation of an<lb/>armed attack upon that place.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I am directed to request that you will<lb/>furnish to these gentlemen a copy of<lb/>His Excellency's letter to you of the 20th<lb/>inst., in which the reason why His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency does not, at the present time,<lb/>feel justified in the adoption of extra<lb break="no"/>ordinary measures of precaution be<lb break="no"/>yond those already taken, are fully set<lb/>forth.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     There is one passage in your letter 
     <lb/>
     
    which His Excellency desires to notice.   
     <lb/>You say that the inhabitants of Wood<lb break="no"/>stock " feel that they are entitled to the  
     <lb/>" same consideration as some other por<lb break="no"/>tions of the Province." Every part    
     <lb/>of the Province is, no doubt, entitled to     
     <lb/>receive, and does receive, the same con-    
     <lb/>sideration at His Excellency's hands.    
     <lb/>( <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. Connell</persName> - He denied that distinctly<lb/>
           
<cb/>
       
He did not believe that.) But that the<lb/>same measures of defence should be<lb/>taken alike in all districts without re<lb break="no"/>gard to the greater or less degree of<lb/>danger to which they may be exposed;<lb/>is a proposition which will not, His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency thinks, be advance by the<lb/>gentlemen whose letters you have for<lb break="no"/>warded.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>His Excellency was glad to hear from<lb/>Mr. Connell, a few days since, an un<lb break="no"/>equivocal avowal that he did not share<lb/>this alarm, and did not anticipate seri<lb break="no"/>ous danger, and that he admitted the<lb/>cogency of the arguments adduced by<lb/>His Excellency to prove the extreme<lb/>improbability of any serious attempt in<lb/>the direction of Woodstock. His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency is confident that if Mr. Connell<lb/>gave public expression to the same sen<lb break="no"/>timents it could not but have a most<lb/>salutary influence in checking the ap<lb break="no"/>prehensions referred to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>I have the honor to be,<lb/>
          Gentlemen,<lb/>
         Your most ob't servant,</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">(Signed) D WILSON,<lb/>Private Secretary.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>Messrs. CONNELL &amp; LINDSAY, &amp;c. &amp;c.<lb/>
            </p></quote>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">


            <p rendition="simple:right">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY,<lb/>24th MARCH, 1866.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Gentlemen</hi>, 
            </p>
            <p>At the request of His Excellency the<lb/>Lieutenant Governor, we have the honor<lb/>to enclose the reply of His Excellency<lb/>to our communication enclosing the re<lb break="no"/>quest from you and 128 others, urging<lb/>the necessity of calling out a limited<lb/>portion of the Militia of Carleton<lb/>County.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Your obedient servants,</p>
<p rendition="simple:right">CHAS. CONNELL,<lb/>WM. LYNDSAY.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>To L.P. FISCHER, Mayor<lb/>J.R. HARTLEY, Warden,<lb/>J.C. WINSLOW, C.P.,<lb/>R.H. Hay, J. P.,<lb/>And 128 others, inhabitants of Wood<lb break="no"/>stock and vicinity.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>P.S. - You will please hand this with<lb/>the enclosed ot the proprietor of the<lb/><hi rendition="simple:italic">Sentinel</hi> for publication.<lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>He would now read his reply, dated<lb/>23rd March, to that communication from<lb/>His Excellency, and His Excellency's<lb/>reply of the 29th March, which he had only<lb/>received that day. (It seemed to him<lb/>as a matter of courtesy he should have<lb/>received an answer sooner.)</p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p rendition="simple:right">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY<lb/>March 23, 1866</p>

<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">May it please your Excellency</hi>:</p>

<p>I have the honor to acknowledge the<lb/>receipt of your Excellency's communica<lb break="no"/>tion of the 22d inst., addressed to Mr.<lb/>Lindsay and myself.</p>

<p>I am desirous to avoid any misappre<lb break="no"/>hension on the part of your Excellency<lb/>with regard to my opinion on the danger<lb/>to be apprehended form invasion originat<lb break="no"/>ing in the United States.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"Your Excellency states that I made<lb/>
         

            <pb n="77" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_077.jpg"/>
         
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">77</fw>

an unequivocal avowal, that I did not<lb/>share in the alarm, and did not antici<lb break="no"/>pate serious danger, and admitted the<lb/>cogency of the arguments advanced by<lb/>your Excellency to prove the extreme<lb/>improbability of any serious attempt<lb/>in the direction of Woodstock. Your<lb/>Excellency also states that you are con<lb break="no"/>fident that if Mr. Connell gives public<lb/>expression to the same sentiments, it<lb/>could not but have a most salutary<lb/>effect in checking the apprehension re<lb break="no"/>referred to."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    In reply I have to state to your Excel<lb break="no"/>lency, that whether privately to your Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency, or in my place on the floor of<lb/>the House of Assembly, I have given ex<lb break="no"/>pression to but one opinion, but that opin<lb break="no"/>ion is not correctly conveyed in the lan<lb break="no"/>guage used by your Excellency.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    I have drawn this important distinction, <lb/>that while I did not apprehend any danger<lb/>from a large body of men coming in force<lb/>and invading the Province in the direc<lb break="no"/>tion of Woodstock, I have serious fears<lb/>that predatory bands of maurauders might<lb/>cross the border, and do much injury to<lb/>property and perhaps life, and it was that<lb/>I urged the necessity of a small guard<lb/>being stationed at other points.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    That alarm does exist in the minds of<lb/>many people in the County of Carleton,<lb/>is proved by the written evidence of the<lb/>inhabitants already submitted, and in<lb/>view of these facts I was justified in mak<lb break="no"/>ing the remarks I did in the Legislature.<lb/>(Mr. Connell believed that the House<lb/>would think him justified in all he had<lb/>done.)<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>   Your Excellency should not forget that<lb/>whether the alarm is well or ill grounded,<lb/>it has, to a large extent, originated in the<lb/>personal efforts made by your Excellency<lb/>at St. Stephen, Woodstock, and other<lb/>places, to arouse the people to a sense of<lb/>the necessity of preparation.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Added to this the calling out of volun- <lb/>teers in St. John, the action had by the<lb/>Legislture at the instancy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, for land and sea defences, and the<lb/>general necessity urged by the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment for wide and general protection, are<lb/>sufficient to create in the minds of the<lb/>people of such a suspicioun that danger is<lb/>imminent, and, on all these grounds, I<lb/>feel that the Government has not dis<lb break="no"/>charged its duty to the people in the up<lb break="no"/>per district along the border.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>        I have the honor to be, <lb/>            Your Excellency's <lb/>                   Most obedient servant,</p>     <p rendition="simple:right">(Signed)           CHAS. CONNELL.</p>

<p>To His Excellency the Hon. A. H. Gor<lb break="no"/>don, C. M. G., Lieutenant Governor<lb/>    and Commander-in Chief, &amp;c., &amp;c.<lb/>
            </p></quote>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
   
            <p rendition="simple:right">
     GOVERNMENT HOUSE, 
     <lb/>March 29th, 1866.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">Sir</hi>,—<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>    I am directed by his Excellency, the<lb/>Lieutenant Governor, to acknowledge the<lb/>receipt, on the 27th inst., of your letter<lb/>of the 25th. His Excellency does not<lb/>perceive that there is any essential dif<lb break="no"/>ference between the statement, to the<lb/>correctness of which you demur, and that<lb/>which you yourself make, for you admit<lb/>that you do not fear an invasion of Carle<lb break="no"/>ton County by any large body of men,<lb/>whilst of course His Excellency was<lb/>aware that you, like himself, thought it<lb/>not impossible that in the event of a se<lb break="no"/>


            <cb/>
          

     rious attack being made elsewhere, small 
     <lb/>border raids might be attempted in the<lb/>vicinity of Woodstock.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    It being then conceded that no attack <lb/>in force need be apprehended. His Excel<lb break="no"/>lency presumes that it is needless that the<lb/>same measures of defence should be<lb/>adopted as are required a points where,<lb/>if a descent is made at all, it will probably<lb/>assume a more serious character.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    The contingency of a small predatory <lb/>raid is not now forseen for the first time,<lb/>for it was against such an attack that<lb/>His Excellency desired to provide when<lb/>recommending the formation of a Home<lb/>Guard in Carleton County. In a speech <lb/>made by you at the meeting held at<lb/>Woodstock on the 8th December, the re<lb break="no"/>port of which, His Excellency under<lb break="no"/>stands, was revised by yourself, (who<lb break="no"/>ever advised His Excellency to put that<lb/>in his letter, gave him very incorrect<lb/>advice), you discussed the possibility of<lb/>an attack by a band of some fifty men.<lb/>(Mr. Connell,—He admitted that expense<lb/>was not necessary at the time, but an<lb break="no"/>other state of things had arisen.) You<lb/>were then of opinion that it "would be <lb/>unwise," and " was needless to increase<lb/>our expenses by the step of calling out<lb/>Militia under pay, " and that " the plan<lb/>proposed, "i.e., that of enrolling a Home<lb/>Guard, to serve only in case of need,<lb/>" would be doubtless sufficient."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    His Excellency entirely concurred at<lb/>the time, and entirely concurs now, in<lb/>the sentiments then expressed by you,<lb/>and he is not aware that any circumstances<lb/>have since occurred to increase or dimin<lb break="no"/>ish the danger referred to.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    You do not, of course, imagine that <lb/>the peaceable and settled population on<lb/>the American side of the border contem<lb break="no"/>plate an assault upon their British neigh<lb break="no"/>bors, more than the inhabitants of Carle<lb break="no"/>ton meditate a descent on Houlton. The<lb/>raid, therefore, if made, will be made by<lb/>strangers. But His Excellency has not<lb/>learned that any unusual assemblages of<lb/>suspicious characters has taken place up<lb break="no"/>on the frontier ; and had any such infor<lb break="no"/>mation reached you or your colleague,<lb/>you would no doubt have hastened to put<lb/>His Excellency in possession of intelli<lb break="no"/>gence of so much importance.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    His Excellency, therefore, cannot con- <lb/>cur with you in considering that the<lb/>measures of precaution adopted in the<lb/>district in question are insufficient, and<lb/>he is well satisfied to know that his<lb/>opinion in this respect coincides with that<lb/>of the highest military authorities in<lb/>these Provinces.</p>      
<p>I have the honor to be, Sir, <lb/>              Your obedient servant, </p>     <p rendition="simple:right"> (Signed)                   F. S. KEENE <lb/>                                           Private Secretary.</p> <p>C. Connell, Esq., M.P.P., &amp;c. &amp;c.<lb/>
            </p></quote>

            <p>    It was a very small operation to in<lb break="no"/>corporate in His Excellency's reply to<lb/>his letter that allusion to his having<lb/>revised his speech. What he had said<lb/>at the meeting at Carleton he had said<lb/>publicly, and there could be no mistake<lb/>about what he did say. With reference<lb/>having manipulated his speech, he<lb/>would refer to a letter from the Editor<lb/>of the Carleton <hi rendition="simple:italic">Sentinel</hi>, to show that it<lb/>was not the case. Mr. Connell said that<lb/>he would take occasion to reply to that<lb/>last communication from His Excellency<lb/>and incorporate in it the note from the<lb/>Editor of the Carleton <hi rendition="simple:italic">Sentinel</hi>, and<lb/>would publish the whole as part of his<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
         
speech. He thought it a small, con<lb break="no"/>temptible business to make that allusion.<lb/>He did not care what position the indi<lb break="no"/>vidual held, he would not submit to be<lb/>insulted. He wished the House and the<lb/>country to know how he had been<lb/>treated. If he had the abilities of the<lb/>Hon. Leader of the Government he<lb/>would let his voice be heard with no<lb/>uncertain sound on this occasion. Had<lb/>the Hon. Attorney General been treated<lb/>in the way he had been used throughout<lb/>this transaction, would not the House<lb/>have rung with his wrongs and denun<lb break="no"/>ciations of those in high place. He<lb/>could imagine with what force and elo<lb break="no"/>quence he would have appealed to the<lb/>House and to the country. But while<lb/>saying this, he wished to be distinctly<lb/>understood that he held the Government<lb/>responsible for every one of these let<lb break="no"/>ters, that he considered that an attempt<lb/>had been made by them to place him in<lb/>a false position, and that he thought<lb/>that an injustice had been done to his<lb/>section of the country.<lb/>
            </p>


<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
            <p rendition="simple:right">HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY,<lb/>March, 1866.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">May it please your Excellency</hi>:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    I am in receipt of your Excellency's <lb/>letter of the 29th inst., and to some<lb/>points therein referred to, have to reply :<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Not agreeing with your Excellency in<lb/>the opinion that the necessary precau<lb break="no"/>tions for defence have been taken, I<lb/>still indulge the hope that the result may<lb/>snow that these precautions are sufficient<lb/>to meet the emergency.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Your Excellency admits that the con- <lb/>tingency of a small predatory raid is not<lb/>now forseen for the first time. This ad<lb break="no"/>mission on the part of your Excellency<lb/>gives force to, and fully justifies the re<lb break="no"/>presentation heretofore made by me.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>     With regard to my speech made on the<lb/>8th of December, at Woodstock, to which<lb/>your Excellency is pleased to allude, I<lb/>have to say, from the views expressed on<lb/>that occasion, I have never departed<lb/>either in private conference with your<lb/>Excellency or in my place in the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    I cannot understand why your Excel- <lb/>lency has made the reference at all, much<lb/>less what the question as to that speech<lb/>having been revised by myself previous<lb/>to publication has to do with this grave<lb/>correspondence now.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    Your Excellency's conclusions with re- <lb/>gard to my views in several particulars,<lb/>seems to be quite as far from being cor<lb break="no"/>rect, as the information your Excellency<lb/>has received about my having revised my<lb/>speech already alluded to, which is with<lb break="no"/>out foundation in fact, the evidence of<lb/>which I herewith submit is a letter from<lb/>the editor of the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Carleton Sentinel</hi>.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">FREDERICTON, March 29, 1866.</p>

<p>Charles Connell, Esq. :<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>    <hi rendition="simple:italic">Dear Sir</hi>:—In reply to your enquiry<lb/>this afternoon as to whether you revised<lb/>the report of your speech made by me<lb/>on the occasion of a meeting of Magis<lb break="no"/>trates of Carleton County, at which His<lb/>Excellency the Lieutenant Governor was<lb/>present, previous to its publication, I<lb/>have to reply that such was not the case,<lb/>nor, to my knowledge, did you see my<lb/>report until it was in print, without my<lb/>knowledge a revision could not be made.<lb/>In order to be more fully satisfied, I tele<lb break="no"/>graphed to Woodstock, and am confirmed<lb/>
     

            <pb n="78" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-29_Page_078.jpg"/>
  

     <fw type="num">78</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>
 

in my above statement, that, you did not 
     <lb/>see it.</p> 

<p>Yours &amp;e.,<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p rendition="simple:right">
     (Signed)  SAMUEL WATTS. 
     <lb/>

    <hi rendition="simple:italic"> Editor Carleton Sentinel</hi>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Your Excellency acquiesces in the pru<lb break="no"/>dence of the advice then tendered to 
     <lb/>
     Your Excellency with regard to the call<lb break="no"/>ing out the Militi, and which subsequent 
     <lb/>
     events have justified, as they have also 
     <lb/>
     the still later correspondence addressed 
     <lb/>
     by my colleague and myself to Your Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I still adhere to the opinion that if our 
     <lb/>
     advice had. been acted upon in its earlier 
     <lb/>
     stages, this correspondence need not have 
     <lb/>
     been so extended, and the general alarm 
     <lb/>
     along the border in the upper district 
     <lb/>
     might have   been allayed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     
     
     
     In the present instance, Your Excel<lb break="no"/>lency appears to have been guided by the<lb/>counsel of Your Excellency's constitu<lb break="no"/>tional advisers, a course quite consistent,<lb/>placing, as it does, the responsibility<lb/>where it should fairly rest.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I have the honor to be,         
     <lb/>Your Excellency's<lb/>Most obedient servant.</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">CHARLES CONNELL.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To His Excellency, the Honourable A. H.      
     <lb/>Gordon C.M. G., Lieutenant Gover<lb break="no"/>nor, &amp;e., &amp;c., &amp;c.<lb/>
            </p>
</quote>
    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. Connell</persName> then proceeded to speak on 
     <lb/>
     the subject of   Confederation, and   to say 
     <lb/>
     that it had been alleged throughout the 
     <lb/>
     discussion  on the subject —that the dele<lb break="no"/>gation from the Province    to the Quebec 
     <lb/>
     Conference was  totally unauthorized. He 
     <lb/>
     believed, on the contrary, that it was au 
     <lb/>
     thorized : but even if the late Govern<lb break="no"/>ment had not any authority to appoint 
     <lb/>that delegation, he considered they<lb/>would like to ask, the duty of a Govern<lb break="no"/>ment? Was it merely to draw their<lb/>salaries and transact the routine business<lb/>of the country?  Was it not rather the<lb/>duty of a Government to advance, by all<lb/>the legitimate means in their power, the<lb/>interest of the country - to introduce<lb/>measures that would benefit it and lead<lb/>it on the path of progress and prosperity.<lb/>Let what might be said to the contrary,<lb/>be considered they had a perfect right to<lb/>appoint delegates to consult with the<lb/>delegates of the other Provinces on a<lb/>measure that would advance the interests<lb/>and consolidate the power of all these<lb/>British North American Colonies. (Mr.<lb/>Needham - Was it right for the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to adopt a new Constitution for the<lb/>country, and determine to put it through<lb/>the Legislature without giving the people<lb/>an opportunity to pronounce upon it.?)<lb/>He would tell the Hose what as the <lb/>the course the late Government ought to have<lb/>taken.  He thought, in the first place,<lb/>that they should not have gone out-side<lb/>their own members to form the delega<lb break="no"/>tion. That, he considered, was wrong.<lb/>In the next place, they should have been <lb/>satisfied with reporting to the House the<lb/>result of that delegation, and with sub<lb break="no"/>mitting the resolutions passed at the<lb/>Conference in Quebec; and if they had<lb/>taken that course and given the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture an opportunity to have discussed<lb/>those resolutions freely and calmly, they<lb/>would have carried out their measure.<lb/>They did wrong in dissolving the House<lb/>and agginz to the country when they did.<lb/>But when it was said they had not authori<lb break="no"/>
     
<cb/>
     ty to appoint the delegation, he maintain<lb break="no"/>ed they had, and he would have made<lb/>it a grave charge against them if they<lb/>had not done it. (Here the hon. member<lb/>quoted from a dispatch from Mr. Card<lb break="no"/>well, of March 9, 1865, to show that the<lb/>delegation was fully authorized.)<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. Connell</persName> the, in concluding went<lb/>on to say that he hoped the result of the<lb/>vote on the question before the House<lb/>would be to make the Government place<lb/>their resignations in the hands of His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency, and give place to another set of<lb/>men who better understood the feelings<lb/>and wishes of the people. And he hoped <lb/>that these other men would take an op<lb break="no"/>portunity to allow the people to give<lb/>expression of opinion on the question that<lb/>was agitating the country.  He wished<lb/>to put an end to the unsettled state of<lb/>things in the Province.<lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     
     
     [ An irregular conversation followed, on           
     <lb/>a question of order, raised on the Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General's rising to answer Mr.<lb/>Connell on some charges in the correspon<lb break="no"/>dence that that hon. member had just<lb/>read. He appealed to the justice of the<lb/>House if he had not a right to answer<lb/>that gentleman when he brought charges<lb/>against the Government subsequent to<lb/>the bringing in of the vote of con<lb break="no"/>fidence. It was finally ruled that <lb/>member had a right to speak twice to<lb/>the question before the House.]<lb/>
            </p>
        
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BAIL1">Mr. BAILEY</persName> said the Opposition had          
     <lb/>made a number of charges against the<lb/>Government, but he could not see that <lb/>they had established a case against them<lb/>They had asked hon. members to with<lb break="no"/>draw confidence from the Government<lb/>because they had not sooner called the<lb/>House together. He did not think that<lb/>change so grave as to merit a vote of<lb/>want of confidence. The Government<lb/>had also been charged with having allow<lb break="no"/>ed the Export duty Law to expire, and<lb/>having collected revenue illegally. But<lb/>as they had pleaded guilty to that charge, <lb/>and as he did not believe that the inter<lb break="no"/>ests of the country had suffered, he<lb/>would not condemn them on that point.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     There was another charge of not filling
     <lb/>up the public offices - of not having an<lb/>Auditor General, according as the Con<lb break="no"/>stitution demanded - of not having ap<lb break="no"/>pointed a Solicitor General. He con<lb break="no"/>fessed he was not prepared to judge them<lb/>on those questions. But as to the other<lb/>charge against them about the sale of<lb/>Crown Lands, he thought that when Mr.<lb/>Gibson made his application to purchase<lb/>lands, if the Government were not pre<lb break="no"/>pared to receive his application and sell<lb/>the lands, they should not have ordered<lb/>the survey. Why, he should like to<lb/>know, make out an order of survey, and <lb/>subject Mr. Gibson to the cost of that<lb/>survey, if they had no intention that he<lb/>should have the lands? He considered<lb/>it a very great hardship that a man should<lb/>be compelled. as Mr. Gibson was, to pay<lb/>$500 for the survey of lands if no sale<lb/>was to follow upon it.  He had had per<lb break="no"/>sonal experience on this head. (Here the<lb/>hon. member gave two cases where he<lb/>made applications for lands on or near <lb/>the Salmon River, and near Newcastle,<lb/>where surveys were ordered to be made,<lb/>for which surveys he had to pay, and<lb/>pocket the loss of the amount, as no sale<lb/>followed. ) With regard to the sale of the<lb/>Crown Lands of the Province, his<lb/>opinion was that they ought to be sold<lb/>while they were available, before they<lb/>were stripped, or before all the timber<lb/>was burnt off. The sale of the public<lb/>
      
            <cb/>
    

     
     lands he showed, was far better for the     
     <lb/>revenue of the country than to lease them<lb/>for lumbering purposes. Some of the<lb/>hon. members who had spoken had<lb/>charged it against the Government that<lb/>they had not filled up the Auditor Gener<lb break="no"/>al's office, and the office of the Solicitor<lb/>General. For his own part, he thought that<lb/>the present system of Departmental<lb/>Government was a curse to the country.<lb/>Here they were in the Government, on<lb/>the floors, of the House, half-a-dozen poli<lb break="no"/>tical offices, which gave the holders great<lb/>influence and patronage, and the people<lb/>had to fight against them. No doubt the<lb/>Government had been guilty of a few<lb/>deeds of omission and, it may be, of com<lb break="no"/>mission; but no men or Government were <lb/>perfect. He was not prepared to con<lb break="no"/>demn them on the charges brought<lb/>against them.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Reference had been made to the dele<lb break="no"/>gation that had been sent home to Eng<lb break="no"/>land, and it had been said that no good<lb/>had come out of it, and that it was an<lb/>useless expenditure. His opinion was<lb/>that it had not been sent soon enough,<lb/>but late as it was sent, he held the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment could not have done otherwise,<lb/>and he hoped that he would hear of some<lb break="no"/>thing being done. He found that the<lb/>House had been in session for twenty-<lb break="yes"/>one days, and not much had been done.<lb/>The cry through the country was. when<lb/>was the House going to get through with<lb/>this debate?  He had made a calculation<lb/>of the amount of money this debate had<lb/>cost the country. and what did hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers think was the sum total? No less <lb/>then$12,000. He did not think that the<lb/>charge of wasting that amount of money<lb/>could be brought home to the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment.  (Hon.   member, - What charge <lb/>had been brought home?)  Not one.<lb/>Under all the circumstances. he could not<lb/>support the amendment and go with the<lb/>Opposition. What he had said, and the<lb/>vote he would give, he was prepared<lb/>to stand by.  He came to the House as an <lb/>independent member, and he was perfect<lb break="no"/>ly unpledged to any party or set of men.<lb/>He came here to do his duty to his con<lb break="no"/>stituents and to his country.<lb/>The HOse then was adjourned over <lb/>until Saturday at ten o'clock.</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">A.A.<lb/>
            </p>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>