<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1867-05-20"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1867-05-20">20 May 1867</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="32"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="35" to="35"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="50" to="54"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_030.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_031.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_032.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_035.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_050.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_051.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_052.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_053.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_054.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-04-10">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-04-10">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_030">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_030.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_031">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_031.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_032">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_032.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_035">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_035.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_050">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_050.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_051">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_051.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_052">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_052.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_053">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_053.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_054">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_054.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="30" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_030.jpg"/>
            

     <fw type="num">30</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> 
   

<p>
   [...]  few people living on the road, which is 
     <lb/>chiefly used by the people of King's and<lb/>Queen's Counties, who bring their pro<lb break="no"/>duce to the Saint John Market. The<lb/>Road itself is very badly situated, for at<lb/>every <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>it is overflowed, and when<lb/>the water subside, it is left a perfect<lb/>quagmire, and unless a large amount of<lb/>money is expended to put it n thorough<lb/>repair by raising it and building the ne<lb break="no"/>cessary culverts, and so forth, it can nev<lb break="no"/>er be kept in order. It is certain the peo<lb break="no"/>ple who live on the Road can do very<lb/>little indeed towards keeping it in an<lb/>efficient state. Saint John is most pe<lb break="no"/>cularly situated; the country is cut up<lb/>by creeks and lakes and streams, so that<lb/>it is a very difficult matter to keep up the<lb/>Roads and Bridges. The money they<lb/>receive is not sufficient for the Bridges<lb/>even. The work on the Marsh Road<lb/>ought to ahve been done last year, and if<lb/>it had been then looked after, much of<lb/>the damage which has been sustained by<lb/>parties going to town would have been<lb/>prevented. I have received so many<lb/>letters of complaint that really it has be<lb break="no"/>come not only embarrassing but harrass<lb break="no"/>ing.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. - There is a Railroad 
     <lb/>running parallel to the Marsh Road<lb/>which the people can use if the high way<lb/>is out of repair, so that there need not be<lb/>much cause of complaint. The hon.<lb/>member for Saint John says I don't know<lb/>much about it. Perhaps I know more<lb/>about Saint John than he does about<lb/>Carleton County. There is the road from<lb/>the city out to Indiantown through<lb/>Portland, [illegible] the whole distance, and<lb/>yet they are continually asking that it<lb/>should be kept up by the Province. If<lb/>they pursued the example set them by<lb/>Carleton they would keep it in good order<lb/>themselves. The Road from Richmond<lb/>to the boundary leading to Houlton is<lb/>outside of the Woodstock district, or<lb/>that too would be kept up by the peo<lb break="no"/>ple.<lb/> <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - Why don't they use the 
     <lb/>Railway? You got a grant for that.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. - The Railroad we 
     <lb/>have is more for the accommodation of<lb/>the popel of Houlton than it is for<lb/>Woodstock. But the hon. member for<lb/>Westmorland should not speak about<lb/>Railways. He has got Eastern Extension<lb/>over there, for which we granted them<lb/>one thousand dollars a mile, and after that<lb/>we find that they want land damages as<lb/>well. I think it comes with a bad grace<lb/>for the hon. member to speak about<lb/>grants; he should be sure that his own<lb/>hands are clean before he attempts to<lb/>cast a slur upon his neighbors. I chal<lb break="no"/>lenge the hon. member -<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName>. - Don't. (Laugh<lb break="no"/>ter.)<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. - To show a single 
     <lb/>
           

            <cb/>
        

     instance in which I was every willing to 
     <lb/>ask anything for the County of Carleton<lb/>that I was not as willing to grant to other<lb/>sections of the Province.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BEVE1">Mr. BEVERIDGE</persName>. - As it seems in 
     <lb/>order to ask questions of the Chief Com<lb break="no"/>missioner, I should like to know if any<lb/>instructions have been given to repair<lb/>the Road in the County of Victoria?<lb/>They are in a very bad state, and many<lb/>of the Bridges have been damaged by<lb/>the freshet, whilst others have been car<lb break="no"/>ried away. It is said the Artillery from<lb/>Saint John and from Canada are to pass<lb/>that way very shortly, and it is thereofore<lb/>necessary that they should be attended<lb/>to at once.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> - From per<lb break="no"/>sonal observations as well as from the<lb/>reports of the Supervisors, I am aware<lb/>that the Roads and Bridges in that sec<lb break="no"/>tion are in a very bad state, and as I have<lb/>received information from the military<lb/>authorities that the Artillery are to pass<lb/>that way, I have given instructions to<lb/>have such temporary repairs put upno<lb/>them as will suffice till more premanent<lb/>works can be carried on.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CAIE1">Mr. CAIE</persName>. - I should like the Chief 
     <lb/>Commissioner to inform me why it was<lb/>that the building of a Bridge in Kent<lb/>County was sold at auction, whilst ano<lb break="no"/>ther was put up to tender. The Bridge<lb/>over the Little North West was given<lb/>out by tender at a cost of £375, whilst<lb/>that over the Kouchibouguacis was sold<lb/>at auction for £115. It is evident that<lb/>bridges can be built cheaper when the<lb/>work is put up to auction and I should<lb/>like to know why this method is not<lb/>adopted.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName>. - I cannot 
     <lb/>give an answer with regard to these spe<lb break="no"/>cial cases without reference to my papers,<lb/>but in the case of small Bridges it has<lb/>been found advantageous to put the work<lb/>up at auction, but where large Bridges<lb/>have to be constructed it is found better<lb/>to receive tenders, because then the work<lb/>comes under supervision, and it can be<lb/>seen that the work is done thoroughly.<lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     BILLS ETC. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> moved for leave to 
     <lb/>bring a Bill to incorporate the Inter<lb break="no"/>national Telegraph Company. Leave<lb/>granted and Bill read a first time.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName> moved that this Bill 
     <lb/>
     be read a second time, and together with 
     <lb/>the Bill to incorporate the Western Tele<lb break="no"/>graph Company of New Brunswick - re<lb break="no"/>ferred to a Select Committee to report<lb/>on. Leave being granted the Bill was<lb/>read a second time and submitted to the<lb/>following Special Committee - Messrs.<lb/>Skinner, Kerr, and Smith.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     CORRESPONDENCE, ETC. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. Some time ago I under<lb break="no"/>
         
            <cb/>
          

     stood there was some trouble in the 
     <lb/>Crown Land Office with regard to some<lb/>of the subordinates, upon which a lively<lb/>correspondence passed between the Sur<lb break="no"/>veyor General and Lieutenant Governor<lb/>Gordon. I should like to know from the<lb/>Surveyor General if it is the intention of<lb/>the Government to submit that Corres<lb break="no"/>pondence to the House; and also if the<lb/>Correspondence with regard to the re<lb break="no"/>moval of Mr. Lawrence in Saint John<lb/>from the Chief Commissionership of Rail<lb break="no"/>ways, is to be submitted. I had hoped<lb/>that as no opposition had been raised to<lb/>the Address, and as it was the expressed<lb/>wish of the hon. members that the business<lb/>of the country should be pushed on as<lb/>rapidly as possible that the Government<lb/>would have been ready to bring in their<lb/>measures and submit the necessary pa<lb break="no"/>pers to this House. But they seem very<lb/>little inclined to do anything, and I should<lb/>now like the Surveyor General to give<lb/>us some idea whether this Correspond<lb break="no"/>ence will be laid before us or not. It is<lb/>said that the Correspondence between<lb/>the Surveyor General and Governor Gor<lb break="no"/>don, - who I believe is now in another<lb/>country, I don't know exactly where, for<lb/>I have not heard from him lately, - was<lb/>of a very sharp character and I should<lb/>like to know whether the Surveyor Gen<lb break="no"/>eral conquered or Governor Gordon.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Hon. Mr. CONNELL</persName>. - If the hon. 
     <lb/>member will give us a memorandum of<lb/>what he wants to know I will enquire<lb/>and give an answer on Monday. So far<lb/>as I am concerned I am quite willing to<lb/>let all that goes on inside the Government<lb/>be known by the public.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName>. - There is a 
     <lb/>constitutional method by which the hon.<lb/>member for Westmorland can get the<lb/>documents he requires before the House.<lb/>He can move an Address, if he desires to<lb/>do so, that the papers may be submitted.<lb/>With regard to the remission of the Chief<lb/>Commissioner of Railways, I think the<lb/>correspondence was pretty well made<lb/>public at the time, but if the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber is very desirous to have it submitted<lb/>he can get it by moving an Address. As<lb/>to delay in laying these matters before<lb/>the House, I think I can remember a<lb/>notable instance when the hon. member<lb/>was in the Government, in which the<lb/>business was kept back forty days before<lb/>the Address could be got through, at<lb/>which time no papers could be obtained<lb/>at all. But now the Address has passed,<lb/>business is going on, Bills are being<lb/>brought in and even passed, although we<lb/>have only been in session one week, and<lb/>really do not see how the Government<lb/>can push on the work any faster.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - I am surprised at the 
     <lb/>Chief Commissioner referring to that<lb/>notable instance of delay, for it is well<lb/>known that that hon. member, who was<lb/>then in Opposition, materially assisted to<lb/>keep back the passing of the Address.<lb/>
         

            <pb n="31" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_031.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> <fw type="num">31</fw>  
    

   
         

     Could not get papers down! No, Mr. 
     <lb/>Speaker, for it was impossible to ge a<lb/>paper submitted till the Address was<lb/>passed. We were anxious to go on with<lb/>the public business, but the Opposition<lb/>used every means to retard and keep<lb/>back the passing of the Address. How<lb/>different has been the action of the Op<lb break="no"/>position this Session. We raised no side<lb/>issues to impede the action of the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernmemt; we made no opposition to the<lb/>passage of the Address. Not but that<lb/>we could have done so, but we thought it<lb/>best to let it go and proceedd with the<lb/>business of the country, so that we could<lb/>get away our various avocations. The<lb/>Government may think they are very<lb/>strong, but I am sure there is a majority<lb/>of members on the floors of this HOuse<lb/>who condemn their acts, especially in the<lb/>appointments to the Senate. In that in<lb break="no"/>stance they have done a gross injustice<lb/>to the Catholics, but omitting to place a<lb/>member of that denomination on the list<lb/>which has been sent home. Every sec<lb break="no"/>tion of the Province and every <choice><sic>depar<lb break="no"/>ment</sic><corr>department</corr></choice> should have been regarded, - but<lb/>what do we find? The interests of the<lb/>River Counties entirely neglected and<lb/>overlooked.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. - You cant say the 
     <lb/>same for Westmorland.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - No, Mr. Speaker, I am 
     <lb/>here to say that I think Westmorland<lb/>County has been regarded to the neglect<lb/>and injury of other parts of the Province<lb/>- one member was as much as we could<lb/>expect or desire. But when I consider<lb/>that although there are two representa<lb break="no"/>tives of the River interests in the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, yet in the appointment of<lb/>Senators, these Counties have been passed<lb/>by. I cannot but be surprised tha they<lb/>are perfectly complacent, and remain in the<lb/>Government still. When I was in the<lb/>Government, these same hon. members<lb/>said that I was willing to trample upon<lb/>every right of the people of this Province<lb/>other than give up my office; when, if I<lb/>could have done so with honor to myself<lb/>and consistently with the requirements of<lb/>the people, I would have yielded glandly<lb/>up the reins of office to those who were<lb/>using every endeavor to get them into<lb/>their hands. This was the charge against<lb/>me then by the very men who were using<lb/>back stairs influence and every means of<lb/>treachery to oust the Government. At<lb/>that time they said I had not ground of<lb/>complaint against Governor Gordon. I [?]<lb/>should like to hear their opinion of him<lb/>now. I should be quite willing to take<lb/>the opinion of the Surveyor General on<lb/>that question, and abide by it. But then<lb/>he was all wrong and Governor Gordon<lb/>was all right. I have no hesitation in<lb/>saying that I suffered the worst injustice<lb/>at that time. But to return: The Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment now has not gone on with the<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
       

     business, although every opportunity has 
     <lb/>been given them, and the fullest desire<lb/>expressed to press matters on. They<lb/>Surveyor general says he is willing to<lb/>let all that transpires in the Government<lb/>be known. I wish he would; I think the<lb/>House would have no objection to hear<lb break="no"/>ing something of their movements. I<lb/>wish we could have a reporter there,<lb/>so as to know exactly what has been<lb/>taking place during the past eight or ten<lb/>days. He had better suggest the idea to<lb/>his colleagues, and see if they will be as<lb/>willing as he to let all be known; I rather<lb/>think, however, he will find them more<lb/>co[]tive than he happens to be at the<lb/>present time. I am much obliged to the<lb/>Chief Commissioner for the information<lb/>he has given that I can get the papers I<lb/>require by moving for them by Address,<lb/>and if they are not submitted I shall<lb/>avail myself of the privilege of doing so.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>. - The great dif<lb break="no"/>ference between the late Government and<lb/>the present is, that the one which was<lb/>led by my hon. friend from Westmoreland<lb/>held their power against the will of the<lb/>people, and I hope he does not wish the<lb/>House to deduce from his remars that<lb/>this, or any other Government will do<lb/>exactly as they did. Their acts were the<lb/>most extraordinary and unconstitutional<lb/>ever known in the history of Responsible<lb/>Government.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - Now, Mr. Speaker, I 
     <lb/>ask, I challenge, I dare him to show any<lb/>act of the late Government that was un<lb break="no"/>constitutional, or wherein we held power<lb/>contrary to the will of the pepole. What<lb/>was unconstitutional? what was extraor<lb break="no"/>dinary? We brought in our Address at<lb/>the opening of the Session, but the op<lb break="no"/>position raised by the present Attorney<lb/>General and others, who were anxous to<lb/>get into power, was of the most factious<lb/>and treacherous character. The Attorney<lb/>GEneral, if not himself practicing back<lb/>stairs influence, was perfectly aware, I<lb/>have no doubt, of all that was ging on.<lb/>Their acts were of the extraordinary<lb/>and unconstitutional character, not ours.<lb/>What does the Attorney General mean?<lb/>Does he think the House wil lput up with<lb/>a continuance of the present state of<lb/>affairs in the Government? I believe<lb/>there is strength enough in this House to<lb/>overturn them, and it seems as though<lb/>they knew it, and were afraid to proceed<lb/>with the business of the country.<lb/>
            </p>
 <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>. - I mwan that <lb/>
whatever was the course pursued by the <lb/>
late Government during the first ten days<lb/>
of their last Session, the Executive now<lb/>
should not be governed by anything they<lb/>
did. The hon. member speaks of trea<lb break="no"/>chery and back stairs influence being<lb/>
used. I neither practised it, nor knew<lb/>
anything about it; but immediately after<lb/>
the Address was brought in. I moved a<lb/>

            <cb/>
         

     vote of want of confidence, and it was 
     <lb/>carried, so that the Government had to<lb/>give up the power they held against the<lb/>wishes of the people, and the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment immediately afterward formed were<lb/>and have been sustained by a large<lb/>majority on the floors of this House.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - I challenge the Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General to show any differences in<lb/>the Government during the first ten days<lb/>of that Session. Never were eight men<lb/>more united than we were as to the<lb/>course to be pursued; but how different<lb/>is it now. The Government are in coun<lb break="no"/>cil day and night; they cannot spare time<lb/>even to be in their seats or to go on with<lb/>the public business, on account, it is said,<lb/>of the differences existing among them.<lb/>We were united, but the Opposition<lb/>raised all sorts of cries to excite the<lb/>people's minds against us. Popery.<lb/>Fenianism, and every other cry that could<lb/>be devised was tried to oust us. The<lb/>people were deceived and imposed upon,<lb/>and they know it now, and I would be<lb/>quite willing to go back to them upno the<lb/>questions then raised. I believe the ver<lb break="no"/>dict would be very different now, if the<lb/>people could only get the chance to de<lb break="no"/>liver it. With regard to our Speech, the<lb/>Governor declared that he spoke for<lb/>himself only, and not for the Council.<lb/>He admitted that no responsibility rested<lb/>upon us in the matter, and yet they cried<lb/>out, "There is Union in the Speech."<lb/>The Attorney General says he was not<lb/>aware that back stairs influence was<lb/>being used against us. I am surprised<lb/>to hear such a statement, for who was in<lb/>a better position than he to know of the<lb/>treachery that was being practised? He<lb/>knew, and others knew, what the answer<lb/>of the Governor to the Address of the<lb/>Legislative Council was to be before it<lb/>was delivered, and before I knew it<lb/>myself, and I would ask if treachery was<lb/>not practiced there? But now I will come<lb/>back and again ask the Surveyor Gene<lb break="no"/>ral when correspondence between him<lb/>and Governor Gordon will be handed in,<lb/>for it is said the contest was quite sharp<lb/>and Governor Gordon was the victor.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>. - I wish to make a 
     <lb/>few remarks further. Now, my hon. friend<lb/>from Westmorland speaks of Fenianism,<lb/>and the people being excited by the Op<lb break="no"/>position raising that cry. But if there<lb/>was excitement throughout the country,<lb/>who started it? Did not my hon friend<lb/>come into the House, and ask for means<lb/>to resist a threatened attack of Fenians<lb/>on the border? Did he not say that he<lb/>was not in a position to lay before the<lb/>House particulars at that time, but that<lb/>his information was thoroughly reliable?<lb/>The Opposition then said that they need<lb/>not go into particulars, but if the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment wanted means to put down the<lb/>threatened trouble, they were willing to<lb/>
           

            <pb n="32" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_032.jpg"/>
           

     <fw type="num">32</fw>  <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw>  



     help them by every means in their power. 
     <lb/>But now the hon. member says the peo<lb break="no"/>ple were deceived. If they were, who, I<lb/>ask, deceived them? It was he and the<lb/>people know it, - and they know more.<lb/>They know that during the Confederation<lb/>contest, when the hon. member for West<lb break="no"/>morland was going about from Dan to<lb/>Beersheba, trying to show that a Union<lb/>of these provinces would bring devasta<lb break="no"/>tion and ruin upon the people of this<lb/>country, and when the friends of Union<lb/>were striving to show the the benefits<lb/>which would accrue from it, he was chal<lb break="no"/>lenged by Mr. Tilley to meet him and<lb/>discuss the matter fairly and openly; but,<lb/>instead of doing it, he went off to the<lb/>cack slums of Sussex, somewhere out of<lb/>the way, and would not meet him. The<lb/>men in opposition to the Government of<lb/>that day saw the position, they realized<lb/>the danger to the best interests of the<lb/>popel by a continuance in power of the<lb/>men who were willing to sacrifice every<lb/>constitutional right for the privilege of<lb/>holding on to power, and they knew that<lb/>the people would rise n their indignation<lb/>and cooperate with the members of the<lb/>House in hurling the Government from<lb/>power and they did it. The hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber has gone into the old story of his<lb/>differences with Governor Gordon, and<lb/>now tries with high sounding words to<lb/>frighten the present Government by<lb/>challenging them to open up the<lb/>controversy again. But I tell my<lb/>hon. friend that if he want to go into<lb/>the matter, we are ready and willing to<lb/>meet him on any point, with the full con<lb break="no"/>fidence that we can vanquish him, either<lb/>here or before the people of this country.<lb/>The fact is, Mr. Speaker, taht we hve<lb/>done what my hon. freind could not do,<lb/>and it is that which makes him so sore;<lb/>he has been read out of Court, and it is<lb/>that which rankles so. We have been<lb/>able to carry measure of Union most<lb/>satisfactory to the people of this Province,<lb/>and one that is only the precursor of bet<lb break="no"/>ter times. He knows well enough that<lb/>when we go to the people they will give<lb/>us a verdict. He knows that many of<lb/>their strongest supporters, who were op<lb break="no"/>posed to the Quebec Scheme, have come<lb/>round, now that the most beneficial<lb/>changes have been effected, and are<lb/>favorable to the measure. He need not<lb/>get up here and blow off so much gas, for<lb/>it can do no good. He would be much<lb/>better employed and commend himself<lb/>to the good sense of the people, if he<lb/>were to go and help the Government to<lb/>see through the business of the country.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - the Attorney General 
     <lb/>has a happy difficulty of taking all the<lb/>glory to himself for what has been done.<lb/>But if changes have been obtained in the<lb/>Quebec Scheme who, I ask, as entitled<lb/>to praise? Is it the Attorney General,<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
         

     who for two years went about the country 
     <lb/>from "Dan to Beersheba" preaching up<lb/>the beauties of the Quebec Scheme?<lb/>No; if he had had his way the country<lb/>would at this moment have been cursed<lb/>with taht Scheme. If praise is due to<lb/>anyone, it is to those who so boldly<lb/>withstood the infliction of taht measure<lb/>upon our people, and who, when it was<lb/>found that the people were desirous for<lb/>Union, still insisted that changes should<lb/>be made. The Attorney General was<lb/>fortunate enough to be one of the Dele<lb break="no"/>gates, and now he comes back, and with<lb/>the most disinterested patriotism wants<lb/>to go to Ottawa and hold on to his office<lb/>here as well. He says that I retreated<lb/>to the back slums of Sussex Vale, but I<lb/>tell him he had better reture to the back<lb/>slums of his own political infamy. He<lb/>says it was I who started the cry of Fe<lb break="no"/>nianism, but what are the facts of the case?<lb/>Every day we received telegrams<lb/>from the Governor, of the most exciting<lb/>and threatening character, but which I<lb/>now believe were not more than two-thirds<lb/>true. I do not know where they came<lb/>from, or who was their author, - perhaps<lb/>the Attorney General can tell use; but it<lb/>is evident to my mind that they were got<lb/>up for the purpose of overthrowing the<lb/>Government. A few men did come down<lb/>to our borders, and they professed to<lb/>come to assist the Antis to prevent Con<lb break="no"/>federation. That was it; as if any one<lb/>could not see that this very statement<lb/>was sufficient to unite our people against<lb/>both Government and Fenians. They<lb/>did not come with any such purpose; but<lb/>perhaps the Attorney General can tell us<lb/>why they did come. Did he know any<lb break="no"/>thing about them? Was he in commu<lb break="no"/>nication with them? I can't tell, but<lb/>everybody knows that they were the<lb/>cause of the defeat of the Government,<lb/>and, strange to say, the moment the<lb/>Attorney General came into power it was<lb/>all over. They did turn up again on the<lb/>Canada border some time after and disas<lb/>terous consequences followed, but they did<lb/>not damage here. But I want to know what<lb/>the Attorney General means by the back<lb/>slums of Sussex? Has he been there?<lb/>Doesn't he know there are no back slums<lb/>in Sussex Vale? What does he mean?<lb/>There are back slums here, I believe; for<lb/>I have often heard it said that the Attor<lb break="no"/>ney General would go through the back<lb/>slums from his office to his home to avoid<lb/>meeting his constitutes face to face.<lb/>But I think he doesn not know what he is<lb/>talking about and had better use more<lb/>propriety in his language, for I won't<lb/>bear it. He has been in LOndon for<lb/>some months past, and probably has had<lb/>experience of such places, but that is no<lb/>reason why he should cast a stigma upon<lb/>Sussex Vale. The story he tells has been<lb/>denied over and over again, but he still<lb/>
     

            <cb/>
       

     brings it up: that I promise to meet Mr. 
     <lb/>Tilley and discuss the question of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, in the Hall connected with the<lb/>Academy at Sackville - a statement which<lb/>is as untruthful as can be. I waited on<lb/>the Secretary of that meeting, and was<lb/>told that I could go, but would not be<lb/>allowed to speak - consequently I did not<lb/>go. But I did get a challenge. It was<lb/>the close of a meeting at which I had<lb/>been speaking, when a man called out,<lb/>"I will meet you here to-morrow night<lb/>and discuss the question with you." I<lb/>had an engagement that night twenty<lb/>miles away, and the man knew it. I did<lb/>not know what I was afraid to talk on the<lb/>matter, or to let people know my opinions.<lb/>I went to Saint Johm, and Mr. Speaker,<lb/>I think you can vouch that I had a good<lb/>reception.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">Mr. SPEAKER</persName> - The people of Saint 
     <lb/>John always receive strangers who ad<lb break="no"/>dress them with every consideration.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> - I do not know that it is 
     <lb/>worth while to prolong the discussion,<lb/>but if the Attorney General is going to<lb/>use slang phrases and unparliamentary<lb/>language, I am ready for him. I think<lb/>I can talk about back slums as well as<lb/>he, if he is anxious for it. I now want to<lb/>hear from the Surveyor General in reply<lb/>to my question, and from the Attorney<lb/>General about his speech which he made<lb/>to the people in the Hall here after his<lb/>return, where he is reported to have said<lb/>that he was strongly in favor of going to<lb/>Ottawa and holding on to his seat in this<lb/>House.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. MR. FISHER</persName>. - I never said 
     <lb/>it.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - Then you were reported 
     <lb/>
     wrong. But now if the Attorney General   
     <lb/>will put on that Court Dress, of which<lb/>we have heard so much, and which it is<lb/>said has been brought to this country - <lb/> a dress that report says, cost about £60<lb/>- and come upon the floors of the House<lb/>in it, I will willingly forgive many of his<lb/>political sins, and the curiosity of the<lb/>members of this House and of the coun<lb break="no"/>try, which has been wrought up to an ex<lb break="no"/>traordinary pitch by the accounts given<lb/>in the papers, will be satisfied. (Laugh<lb break="no"/>ter.)<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>. - I am aware that 
     <lb/>the expression I made use of was un<lb break="no"/>called for and unparliamentary, but it<lb/>dropped from my mouth in the heat of<lb/>the moment, and now I am not ashamed<lb/>to retract it. I am not in the habit of<lb/>making use of language which is con<lb break="no"/>demned by the rules of this House, but<lb/>still I must tell my hon. friend that it is<lb/>no use in his coming here to glow off his<lb/>gas, but if he wants to fight the matter<lb/>out, let us have a fair field and no favor,<lb/>and I am sure that I do show that they<lb/>position he takes with regard to the<lb/>whole question at issue is wrong.<lb/>
            </p>

            <pb n="35" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_035.jpg"/>
         

<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> <fw type="num">85</fw>
         


            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - Now, whilst aplogiz<lb/>ing for the use of unparliamentary lan<lb break="no"/>guage, teh ATtorney General makdes use<lb/>of another expression equally offensive.<lb/>He must know that some words are just<lb/>as offensive as some gas, and he has been<lb/>blowing off a good deal of it of teh most<lb/>offensive character. But I am not afraid<lb/>to meet him to discuss questions at<lb/>issue between us, nor to leave the ver<lb break="no"/>dict for the decision of the people.<lb/>
            </p>
</div>
<div type="section">

            <head rendition="simple:centre">BILLS ETC.
            </head>

            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> moved for leave<lb/>to bring in a Bill relating to Great Roads.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Leave granted and Bill read a first time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> moved the House into<lb/>Committee on a Bill to amend an Act to<lb/>incorporate the Woodstock Bank.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BECK1">Mr. BECKWITH</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> explained that this Bill<lb/>was to amend the Act so as to extend the<lb/>time for the paying of the capital stock<lb/>from two to four years.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> did not intend to oppose<lb/>the passage of the Bill, but he thought<lb/>before Bills of this description passed<lb/>the ATtorney General should have ex<lb break="no"/>plained to this House how much, if any<lb/>[missing word] the IMperial Act of Union was not in<lb/>[missing word], Banking matters being one of the<lb/>powers which pas from our hands into<lb/>that of the General Government.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was agreed to.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCIN3">Mr. McINERNEY</persName> moved the House 
     <lb/>to Committee on a Bill to establish an<lb/>additional polling place in teh Parish of<lb/>Carleton, in the County of Kent.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CAIE1">MR. CAIE</persName> was surprised to hear of<lb/>such a Bill. It was a matter touching<lb/>the Parish in which he resided, and he<lb/>had never heard one word mentioned on<lb/>the subject by any one of his people. He<lb/>sought that progress should be reported,<lb/>so as to give him time to write to his<lb/>friends and see if they were desirous such<lb/>a step should be taken. No Petition<lb/> came in support of the Bill, and he had<lb/>strong doubts whether the people were<lb/>acquainted that such a Bill was to come<lb/>before the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCIN3">Mr. McINERNEY</persName> said the Bill was<lb/>introduced at the request of the people of<lb/>Point Sapan <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> that place there was<lb/>forty five voices. Teh distance to the<lb/>nearest polling place at Kouchibouguacis<lb/>was twenty miles, and the roads were<lb/>very bad. The people were all poor,<lb/>and one and all had requested him to<lb/>get a polling place established in their<lb/>vicinity. Under these circumstances he<lb/>thought the privilege should be accorded<lb/>them.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CAIE1">Mr. CAIE</persName> said it would have been very<lb/>easy for his colleague to have made him<lb/>acquainted with the wishes of the people<lb/>on the subject especially should he have<lb/>
           

            <cb/>
    
done so, as it affected matters in his own<lb/>Parish, and he did so did move that progress<lb/>be reported with power to sit again, to<lb/>enable him to obtain information on the<lb/>subject.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Progress was reported.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BEVE1">Mr. BEVERIDGE</persName> moved the HOuse| 
     <lb/>into Committee on a Bill to provide an<lb/>additional polling place in the Parish of<lb/>Grand Falls, in the County of Victoria.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BABB1">Mr. BABBIT</persName> in the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The Bill was agreed to without dis<lb break="no"/>cussion.<lb/>
            </p>

</div>

<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">REPRESENTATION OF CARLETON COUNTY.<lb/>
            </head>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> moved the House into<lb/>Committee on a Bill to increase the re<lb break="no"/>presentation of the County of Carleton.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Mr. BOTSFORD</persName> in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName>. - I should like to hear<lb/>from the hon. members from the County<lb/>of Carleton on the Bill; first from the<lb/>hon. member of the Government. It is<lb/>generally conceded that those two hon.<lb/>members are about equal to three ordin<lb break="no"/>ary members in their ability to get privi<lb break="no"/>leges for their County, and if one were<lb/>put in the Senate adn the other went to<lb/>Ottawa to represent Carleton in the<lb/>House of Commons, and the County<lb/>have three members in this House, I think<lb/>that would hardly be dealing fairly with<lb/>the Counties down below.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. - I can give my<lb/>humble opinion as to the requirements<lb/>of teh County, and whetehr I can con<lb break="no"/>vince my hon. friend from Saint John of<lb/>the encssity of this Bill is another mat<lb break="no"/>ter. I think I would be in favor of re<lb break="no"/>casting the representation of all the<lb/>Counties, and if the Government does<lb/>not introduce such a measure, I may do<lb/>so myself before the Session closes.<lb/>(Hear, hear.) At the present time, how<lb break="no"/>ever, I think I can show to hon. members<lb/>that Carleton County is deserving of an<lb/>additional representation in this House,<lb/>when compared with the representation<lb/>from other Counties. I am much obliged<lb/>to the hon. member from Saint John for<lb/>the compliment he has paid my colleague<lb/>and myself as to our abilities as repre<lb break="no"/>sentatives. The section of the County I<lb/>represent is not a seaport like Saint<lb/>John, but a district inhabited by hard<lb/>working agriculturists, and this interest I<lb/>think is worthy to be represented on the<lb/>floor of this House. If the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber from Saint John would pay us a visit<lb/>I should be pleased to take him out to<lb/>Johnville, where he will find a thrifty<lb/>and industrious people, settled in part<lb/>of the country, which a few years ago was<lb/>all wilderness; people who instead of<lb/>loafing about the corners of streets in<lb/>Saint John have gone up there, built<lb/>houses and cleared up farms for them<lb break="no"/>selves, and are now hapy and comfort<lb break="no"/>able. If we look at the representation of<lb/>
     

            <cb/>
    

Carleton as compared with other Coun<lb break="no"/>ties, we shall find that Carleton has one<lb/>representative to 8, 187 of its population,<lb/>while in Restigouche they have one to<lb/>every 2,437 adn in Saint John one to<lb/>8,155 inhabitants. I believe, however,<lb/>in making up the representation we should<lb/>not include the population of teh large<lb/>cities.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName>. - Why not?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. - Population is a good<lb/>basis, but should not embrace the large<lb/>cities, because there they have a large<lb/>floating population.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName>. - What does that<lb/>mean? Seamen?<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. - I don't know whether<lb/>my hon. friend was elected by such, but<lb/>however much he may be included to make<lb/>fun, I will let him know that</p>

<quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
<p>"Thrice is he armed, that hath his quar<lb break="no"/>rel just,"</p></quote>

<p>and therefore he had better keep quite<lb/>till I have done speaking. The represen<lb break="no"/>tation in Westmorland is on to every<lb/>7,000, which is fairer than in Carle<lb break="no"/>ton. In Gloucester they have one mem<lb break="no"/>ber for every 7,538, in Kent one for<lb/>every <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear>,927, and in King's one ofor every<lb/>7,761. These Counties should all have<lb/>a larger representation. In Charlotte<lb/>they have one for every 5,117 and in North<lb break="no"/>umberland one for every 4,700 This is.<lb/>not a fair representation surely. Carle<lb break="no"/>ton has not only large agricultural inter<lb break="no"/>ests, but it is, without doubt, destined to<lb/>become a large mining district. I am<lb/>informed that gold has been found there<lb/>by a gentleman returned from Califor<lb break="no"/>nia.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BEVE1">Mr. BEVERIDGE</persName>. - That was in Vic<lb break="no"/>toria.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. - I don't care where<lb/>it was, even if it was in the far North, for<lb/>we have booth Cooper and Iron besides. I<lb/>believe it is the duty of every man to be<lb/>faithful to the interests of the popel he<lb/>represents, and I am satisfied that when<lb/>the next census is taken the County of<lb/>Carleton will have a larger population<lb/>than some Countries that now have four<lb/>representatives. Carleton increased in<lb/>population seventy nine and half per<lb/>cent in the ten years preceding the last<lb/>census, at which time the population was<lb/>16,373, and the increase is so great that<lb/>they should have five representatives at<lb/>the present rate at the end of the next<lb/>ten years.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SKIN1">Mr. SKINNER</persName>. - The soil is better up<lb/>there than it is with us.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. - The hon. member<lb/>had better stand on his feet when he<lb/>speaks; he is not so large that he need<lb/>retain his seat. I think, Mr. Chairman,<lb/>I have said sufficient to show that in jus<lb break="no"/>tice we should have three representatives<lb/>instead of two, as now.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BABB1">Mr. BABBIT</persName>. - I was not amused as [...]</p>


            <pb n="50" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_050.jpg"/>
            <fw type="num">50</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES IN THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw>
            
   
            <p>
   [...]  States. The Senate of the United States 
     <lb/>is composed of only 72 Senators, for that<lb/>great and mighty country, containing<lb/>thirty-five million people, with all the<lb/>affairs of Empire to deal with, while this<lb/>New Dominion, which is simply a subor<lb break="no"/>dinate Province of the Empire, and hav<lb break="no"/>ing a population of only 3,000,000 is to<lb/>have 76 Senators after Newfoundland is<lb/>admitted into the Union. In the HOuse<lb/>of Commons we are to have 181 members,<lb/>while in the House of Representatives<lb/>in the United States they have about 200<lb/>or possibly 230 members to deal with the<lb/>affairs of a nation, therefore, either the<lb/>machinery of the Government of the<lb/>United States is too small, or that of the<lb/>New Dominion is too large. I think the<lb/>Parliament of the New Dominion is too<lb/>large, they having nothing to do with<lb/>the affairs of Empire, and nothing to<lb/>do with the local affairs of the Provinces.<lb/>I am satisfied that the expenses connected<lb/>with the Government will be very large<lb/>indeed, but how large I am not prepared<lb/>to say. I am prepared to predict that<lb/>the Tariff upon our people, at the very<lb/>first Session of that Confederate Parlia<lb break="no"/>ment will be at least thirty per cent<lb/>higher than it is now. I have already<lb/>said that I believed we would have a<lb/>stamp duty collected in this Province,<lb/>which will be a very odious tax upon the<lb/>people. There will also be a tax upon<lb/>newspapers, for every means will be re<lb break="no"/>sorted to, in order to increase the reve<lb break="no"/>nue to meet the expenses required to<lb/>keep up the General Government and<lb/>the expenses connected with the con<lb break="no"/>struction of their public works. While<lb/>these expenses are going on in the Gen<lb break="no"/>eral Government, I do not think there<lb/>will be any diminution in the expenses of<lb/>the Legislature here. The duties con<lb break="no"/>nected with the office of Postmaster Gen<lb break="no"/>eral will be transferred to the General<lb/>Government and the office abolished, but<lb/>there will be a new department estab<lb break="no"/>lished, that of Reeiver General. Through<lb break="no"/>out the whole canvass at the last elec<lb break="no"/>tion, it was said that the expenses of this<lb/>Legislature would be diminished, but is<lb/>there any measure before the House to<lb/>reduce the expenses? The PRovincial<lb/>Secretary will not deny that the told the<lb/>people that the expenses of the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture would be less than formerly. Where<lb/>do they intend to apply the pruning<lb/>knife? It is not in reducing the num<lb break="no"/>ber of members on the floors of the<lb/>House: it is not in reducing the number<lb/>of departmental officers, for one office is<lb/>abolished, and another is established in<lb/>its place. The Secretary can make cal0<lb/>culations and predictions on one side of<lb/>the question, but I should like to hear<lb/>him make a calculation on the other side.<lb/>He has told us of the smuggling going on<lb/>across the boundary, but he did not tell<lb/>
      

            <cb/>
         

     us it would be stopped, because it is evi<lb break="no"/>dent that it will increase and add largely<lb/>to our revenue, but I do not desire to go<lb/>into a calculation in reference to it now<lb/>because it would not be of much practical<lb/>value. I was sorry to hear, from the<lb/>Secretary, when he was making his cal<lb break="no"/>culations, that were were go get 80 cents<lb/>per head only on the population of 1861<lb/>until 1871. I would like to ask the hon.<lb/>member from St. John (Mr. Wilmot),<lb/>who took all the credit to himself for the<lb/>changes made in the Scheme, why the<lb/>Delegates did not endeavor to get 80<lb/>cents a head on our persent population,<lb/>for they could, by calculating the in<lb break="no"/>crease of population in the past ages, ap<lb break="no"/>proximate what it would be now. Per<lb break="no"/>haps they did the best they could, for<lb/>they were desirous of making all the<lb/>changes that they could in the Quebec<lb/>Scheme, but they only change that I see<lb/>which will be of any benefit is the change<lb/>allowing us 80 cents per head until the<lb/>population reaches 400,000. I objected<lb/>to giving to Canada such a preponderance<lb/>in the number of representatives ehich<lb/>she is allowed to have, and to the provi<lb break="no"/>sion of the Scheme allowing a decennial<lb/>increase of representation. I would ahve<lb/>fixed the representation where it is, and<lb/>not allowed any increase. There is a<lb/>provision in the Scheme authorising the<lb/>Parliament to increase the number of re<lb break="no"/>presentatives, provided the proportionate<lb/>representation of the Province prescribed<lb/>by the Act is not violated. If they go on<lb/>and increase the number some thity,<lb/>Upper Canada would ahve an entire ma<lb break="no"/>jority of the whole. That is one provi<lb break="no"/>sion of the Act which I object to, and<lb/>there are many objectionable features in<lb/>it, but I do not wish to take up the time<lb/>by speaking of them now. In regard to<lb/>the Secretary's figures, I do not want to<lb/>impugn them, for they may be right and<lb/>they may be wrong. When he deals in<lb/>imagination and speculation in regard to<lb/>the amount which we will be entitled to<lb/>in 1881 under the Act of Union, he does<lb/>not tell us what our wants will be for<lb/>Roads, Bridges and Schools at that time.<lb/>He gives us only one side of the ques<lb break="no"/>tion. As the population increases their<lb/>wants increase. I do not suppose that<lb/>we appropriated one-half or one-third of<lb/>the amount for Schools, Roads and<lb/>Bridges, twenty years ago, that we are to<lb/>appropriate this year, and even now we<lb/>have not as much as we ought to have,<lb/>for the late storms and freshets have done<lb/>a great deal of damage. I wil not take<lb/>up any further time, for I suppose the<lb/>Secretary will make another speech, and<lb/>if he does so I will reply to him again.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>. - I cannot allow 
     <lb/>some parts of my hon. friend's remarks<lb/>to pass without making some few obser<lb break="no"/>vations, although on the whole I was<lb/>
           

            <cb/>
           

     rather pleased with his speech, for he has 
     <lb/>not attacked the point and the position<lb/>in which the country at the present time<lb/>is most deeply interested, that is, the<lb/>amount of money we will have at the<lb/>present time for local purposes, and<lb/>whether we will have it for the future<lb/>without direct taxation. He said we<lb/>would have in the next five years, or in<lb/>the next seven years, a great deal more<lb/>than we received this year, therefore, we<lb/>would be in a great deal better position<lb/>out of the Union than in it, but he has<lb/>not attempted to disprove the statement<lb/>that we will have during the next four<lb/>years $65,508 per annum more than we<lb/>haev at present, or that after 1871 we<lb/>will have an annual surplus of $120,871.<lb/>He said he would like to have me state<lb/>what amount of Revenue we would have<lb/>in 1871. I put it down at 12 per cent<lb/>increase on the revenue of this year, pro<lb break="no"/>vided the population paid the same as<lb/>they do now. He says the increase on<lb/>last year was owing to the fact that peo<lb break="no"/>ple had begun to find out facilities for<lb/>defrauding the revenues of the United<lb/>States. The tariff is being reduced in<lb/>that country every year, so that there will<lb/>not be the same inducement to smuggle,<lb/>and there will not be the same opportu<lb break="no"/>nity for smuggling that there has been<lb/>the past year, as their force of Revenue<lb/>Officers was now more efficient than it<lb/>ever was before. ( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. Smith</persName>, - They<lb/>have not been very successful at St.<lb/>Stephen.) They have peculiar facilities<lb/>for smuggling at the Port of St. Stephen,<lb/>and it would be almost impossible to<lb/>stop them. It has been the policy of the<lb/>United States to reduce their debt, and<lb/>as that is reduced, they will reduce their<lb/>tariff, for they will find that excessive<lb/>duties do not always produce the desired<lb/>results. The speech made by my hon.<lb/>friend to-day is a strong contrast to the<lb/>arguments made in 1863, when I<lb/>endeavored to show that the construction<lb/>of the Intercolonial Railway would in<lb break="no"/>crease our population and expenditure,<lb/>and we would be better able to provide<lb/>for our local wants than we had been<lb/>His arguments were then directly op<lb break="no"/>posed to what they are now. He tells<lb/>us now that if we build this road it will<lb/>increase our population, which will in<lb break="no"/>crease our revenue. In the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Fredericton<lb/>Reporter</hi> we find a report of a speech de<lb break="no"/>livered by him in 1863, in which he,<lb/>speaking on the question concerning the<lb/>construction of the Intercolonial Railway,<lb/>says: - "The Railway Debt in Canada<lb/>would be $10 a head, while ours would<lb/>be $29 a head; in this connection he<lb/>would ask whether, in addition to all we<lb/>howe already, we were prepared to pay<lb/>$160,000 more, making in all $492,000,<lb/>we have to pay for interest, leaving our<lb break="no"/>selves only £40,000 per annum for all<lb/>
       

            <pb n="51" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_051.jpg"/>
          

     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> <fw type="num">51</fw>  
    

     local purposes; this is a grave question, 
     <lb/>and he would invoke the most serious<lb/>consideration of the House." He made<lb/>a long speech on that occasion; and took<lb/>the gloomy view that we would have but<lb/>£40,000 a year left for our local pur<lb break="no"/>poses. His line of reasoning now is just<lb/>opposite. He says now there will be a<lb/>large increase of population and a large<lb/>increase of revenue in consequence of the<lb/>construction of this Railway.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - I took the same ground 
     <lb/>then that I do now, - that our population<lb/>would increase, but our wants would in<lb break="no"/>crease with it.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>. - He took the 
     <lb/>view that our revenue would not meet<lb/>our expenditure. The hon. members<lb/>who were in the House on that occasion<lb/>must remember the plausibility of his<lb/>reasoning on this point and be struck by<lb/>the feeling he entertained on that occa<lb break="no"/>sion as contrasted with the speeches now<lb/>made, where he admits the population<lb/>will increase up to 400,000 in 1881, and<lb/>thinks the revenue will increase to<lb/>$2,000,000. My hon. friend went off on<lb/>the subject of taxation, and took occasion<lb/>to say, no doubt but we would have the<lb/>Stamp Act here, and a charge put upon<lb/>our papers. Admitting that should be<lb/>the case, if it becuase necessary to as<lb break="no"/>sess a tax upon the whole Confederacy,<lb/>and a certain amount is to be raised for<lb/>the benefit of the country, it makes no<lb/>difference how it comes out of my pocket.<lb/>If I have to pay it, I might as well pay<lb/>it in one thing as another. Men in this<lb/>Province will not have to pay one cent<lb/>more per head than they have paid. My<lb/>hon. friend says the expense of the New<lb/>Dominion will be great; the building of<lb/>the Intercolonial Railway will take £300,<lb break="no"/>000 per annum as the interest of the<lb/>Railway debt. ( <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. Smith</persName>, - How much<lb/>will it cost?) I doubt it will cost<lb/>£3,000,000. The Delegates gave the<lb/>subject some consideratin, adn there<lb/>seemed to be a disposition to give a com<lb break="no"/>pany of capitalists a subsidy to construct<lb/>the line, only stipulating that they should<lb/>run no less than a certain number of<lb/>trains a day at a certain rate for passen<lb break="no"/>gers and freight. Then I think the Road<lb/>could be constructed for less than<lb/>£3,000,000. Suppose it will cost £3,000,<lb break="no"/>000, they have to lay aside one per cent<lb/>a year, that is $150,000, as a sinking<lb/>fund, by which they whole debt will be paid<lb/>off in less than forty years. This will<lb/>not be a large sum to be paid out of the<lb/>revenue of the General Government,<lb/>when we consider that last year the sur<lb break="no"/>plus revenue of Canada alone was nearly<lb/>a million dollars. He says the General<lb/>Government will cost a large sum of<lb/>money. I will not pretend to say that it<lb/>will not, but so far as New Brunswick is<lb/>concerned, as we have paid more per<lb/>
           

            <cb/>
          

     head according to population out of the 
     <lb/>Union, we wil not have to pay any more<lb/>than in the past. I do not say the whole<lb/>of the Province will not pay it, for it is<lb/>likely they will, but the point is, suppose<lb/>we go into Union with the tariff of Cana<lb break="no"/>da, we find the tariff of Canada to-day is<lb/>as low as the tariff of New Brunswick.<lb/>All non-enumerated articles pay 15 per<lb/>cent under the tariff of Canada against<lb/>15 1/2 that ours pay, but a great many ar<lb break="no"/>ticles here pay four per cent, and some<lb/>pay fifteen per cent that do not pay any<lb/>duty at all in Canada. In Comptroller<lb/>Smith's Report I marked all the articles<lb/>that did not pay duty, and I found that<lb/>for every article we had which did not<lb/>pay duty Canada had two, therfore, we<lb/>will not have to pay any more per head<lb/>than we do now. The Tariff of Canada<lb/>will not yield any more than ours, be<lb break="no"/>cause if some of their articles pay more<lb/>than ours, others pay less. My hon.<lb/>friend says, "the Secretary told us that<lb/>thee expenses of this Legislature would be<lb/>less." I said so. I estimate the time<lb/>occupied in SEssion will be one quarter<lb/>less, the Legislative Council will be<lb/>reduced four, five or six members. He,<lb/>in his speech on Saturday, pointed out<lb/>the pitiable condition the country would<lb/>be in without money enough for Bye<lb/>Roads, Schools, &amp;c., and then asked for<lb/>£500,000 to aid in the construction of<lb/>Western extension, knowing we had the<lb/>ability to pay it. Does the House want<lb/>anything more tha that declaration to<lb/>prove that he knows that financially we<lb/>are not destroyed.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - I said I would support   
     <lb/>the Government in bringing forward a<lb/>measure to provide for Western Exten<lb break="no"/>sion. I believe it is the only opportunity<lb/>we will ever have of getting tht work<lb/>constructed. We can now get the money<lb/>at the rate of five per cent, and if we do<lb/>nt take advantage of it I think it will be<lb/>a long time before we get that Road<lb/>built. The Secretary says that I said the<lb/>country would be in a flourishing condi<lb break="no"/>tion after Confederation. I know as well<lb/>as he does what we will have after we go<lb/>into Union. In four years we will not<lb/>have one-half the money we would have<lb/>if we remained as we are. I never said<lb/>anything to lead the Secretary to infer<lb/>that I thought we had a bright future be<lb break="no"/>fore us; on the contrary, everything I<lb/>said predicted a future dark and gloomy,<lb/>although I hope it may be otherwise. I<lb/>offered to lend my assistance to support a<lb/>measure of vast importance to the people<lb/>of the country. I wished to take advan<lb break="no"/>tage of a provision in the Scheme of<lb/>Union, wherein money could be obtained<lb/>from the New Dominion at a rate of<lb/>five per cent, to build Western Extens<lb break="no"/>sion, but the Secretary, with an air of<lb/>triumph, thinks I stand guilty and con<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
          

     victed before the House of inconsistency. 
     <lb/>The Provincial Secretary has ransacked<lb/>the papers in all directions to try to<lb/>prove that I occupy a different position<lb/>from what I did in 1863. I used the<lb/>same language then that I use now. The<lb/>Secretary at that time tried to carry a<lb/>measure for the construction of 3 1/2<lb/>twelfths of the Intercolonial Railway,<lb/>and here let me ask how many people<lb/>now don't believe the responsibility was<lb/>too great for this little Province to bear?<lb/>I resisted that measure, and I gave evi<lb break="no"/>dence of my sincerity by resigning the<lb/>office of Attorney General. The Secre<lb break="no"/>tary knows that I was conscientious in<lb/>my opinion that the responsibility was<lb/>too great for this small country in view<lb/>of the debt already existing on the Euro<lb break="no"/>pean and North American Railway.<lb/>This Railway, the Secretary said, would<lb/>pay 3 per cent in five years. I said it would<lb/>not, you are entirely too sanguine. It is<lb/>now ten years since it was built, and it<lb/>does not pay more than it did five years<lb/>ago. He charged me with being against<lb/>Railways. I said that I had always in<lb break="no"/>clined to the principal fo caution, for I<lb/>was afraid of encouraging these large lia<lb break="no"/>bilities and heavy dues. I told him that<lb/>I was afraid of these large funded debts,<lb/>that we had to pay now $250,000 interest<lb/>on our debt in England. I said if the<lb/>debt was due among ourselves, the mat<lb break="no"/>ter would be comparatively insignificant<lb/>compared with having a funded debt ex<lb break="no"/>isting where we have to pay the interest<lb/>or of the country, therefore I say I<lb/>opposed the assuming of 3 1-2 twelfths of<lb/>the Intercolonial Railway as entirely too<lb/>heavy a burden for this country to take<lb/>upon itself. We know the influence that<lb/>was brought to bear at that time. The<lb/>Secretary, by his influence, was enabled<lb/>to carry that measure. I resisted it, and<lb/>felt that I was right to resist it, and I do<lb/>not believe there are five members in this<lb/>House who - if not in Confederation - <lb/>would go for the construction of 3 1-2<lb/>twelfths of the Intercolonial Railway.<lb/>The Secretary tells us now that this<lb/>Road can be built for less than £3,00,<lb break="no"/>000. If so, I have not much opinion of<lb/>the judgment of the Conference, nor of<lb/>the scientific knowledge of the man who<lb/>said to the gentleman who moved the<lb/>Bill in the HOuse of Lords that it would<lb/>take £4,000,000 to construct it, and they<lb/>wanted that much from the British Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment. Instead of expecting to get it<lb/>built for £3.000,000, the Delegates had<lb/>to give evidence that this New Dominion<lb/>could obtain an additional £1,000,000 to<lb/>build the Road, and this guarantee comes<lb/>in beyond the Imperial Guarantee. The<lb/>Secretary deals in imagination and specu<lb break="no"/>lation; he said ten years ago that the<lb/>building of our Railway would increase<lb/>the population, and would cause a large<lb/>
           

            <pb n="52" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_052.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="num">52</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw>


     emigration to the Province. I said you 
     <lb/>
     are too sanguine, and the result proves 
     <lb/>
     that I was right. As to what I have said 
     <lb/>
     to-day I am willing to appeal to any hon. 
     <lb/>
     member of the House in justification of 
     <lb/>
     myself and the language I employed. I 
     <lb/>
     did not contradict myself. I said if we 
     <lb/>
     had an increase of population the wants 
     <lb/>
     of the people would increase proportion<lb break="no"/>ally. I opposed the building of 3 1-2 
     <lb/>
     twelfths of the Intercolonial Railway, and 
     <lb/>
     I made some calculation, that after pay<lb break="no"/>ing the interest we would only have £40,<lb break="no"/>000 for local purposes. I resisted the 
     <lb/>
     passage of the Bill. I said inasmuch as 
     <lb/>
     Canada repudiates the proposition to 
     <lb/>
     build the Road, what was the necessity 
     <lb/>
     for our legislating upon the subject. The 
     <lb/>
     Secretary knows that I said I was satis<lb break="no"/>fied Canada would not accept the propo<lb break="no"/>sition. He told us that the very moment 
     <lb/>
     a change took place in the Government 
     <lb/>
     of Canada they would legislate in con<lb break="no"/>currence with us. I did not agree with 
     <lb/>
      him. Who was right, and who was 
     <lb/>
     wrong ? They never did legislate upon 
     <lb/>
     the subject. The Secretary next tells us 
     <lb/>
     that the tariff of the United States will 
     <lb/>
     be reduced, and it will lessen the induce<lb break="no"/>ment for smuggling. I do not see how 
     <lb/>
     they can reduce their tariff, their policy 
     <lb/>
     being to pay off their national debt, and 
     <lb/>
     this illicit trade will go on and increase. 
     <lb/>
     While the country was convulsed with a 
     <lb/>
     great war, trade did not settle down, but 
     <lb/>
     when the war was over, and the people 
     <lb/>
     of the country settled down to an abnor<lb break="no"/>mal condition, then smuggling went on, 
     <lb/>
     and will still continue to go go, and the 
     <lb/>
     Secretary cannot stand here with any 
     <lb/>
     propriety and tell us the United States 
     <lb/>
     Government intend to reduce their tariff. 
     <lb/>
     I do not desire to take up the time of the 
     <lb/>
     House, but I have given my opinion of 
     <lb/>the question fairly and frankly.  The<lb/>
    Secretary's object seems to have been to 
     <lb/>place me in a false position. but he has 
     <lb/>failed entirely. Suppose I was the most 
     <lb/>inconsistent man in the world, what has 
     <lb/> that to do with this great and mighty 
     <lb/>question? It is not as I say, or as the 
     <lb/>Secretary says: It is vain for us to in<lb break="no"/>dulge in these speculations at all. The 
     <lb/>Secretary intends to go to Ottawa, and 
     <lb/>he feels it his duty to present a picture of 
     <lb/>our finances in 1881, but he looks at only 
     <lb/>one side of the question. He is like an 
     <lb/>advocate; he shows us how much better 
     <lb/>off we would be in Confederation than we 
     <lb/>would be out of it. Suppose my figures 
     <lb/>are true, and we have a revenue of two 
     <lb/>million, or two million and a quarter 
     <lb/>dollars in 1881, would we not be better 
     <lb/>off? The Secretary has told as about 
     <lb/>the Intercolonial Railway, but has he 
     <lb/>stated that the Road would not pay any<lb break="no"/>thing? I think he has induced the 
     <lb/>House to believe that as a commercial 
     <lb/>speculation the Intercolonial Railway 
     <lb/>
    

            <cb/>
   

     would yield some return. Let me ask 
     <lb/>
     him if he has taken into account that the 
     <lb/>
     Intercolonial Railway will not pay any<lb break="no"/>thing at all? Has he not charged the 
     <lb/>
     entire interest on the money to construct 
     <lb/>
     the Intercolonial Railway to the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince? Has he made any reduction at 
     <lb/>
     all? I think not. I do not hesitate to 
     <lb/>
     say that I do not believe it will yield 
     <lb/>
     much, if any, return at all. That was 
     <lb/>
     my opinion in 1863, and it is my opinion 
     <lb/>
     now. His calculations are not right if he 
     <lb/>
     has taken into account that the Road will 
     <lb/>
     pay. Suppose the Intercolonial Railway 
     <lb/>
     will pay three per cent, where would his 
     <lb/>
     calculations go then ? Suppose his cal<lb break="no"/>culations were realized regarding the 
     <lb/>
     Railway which runs to St. John, does he 
     <lb/>
     give us any credit for the earnings on 
     <lb/>
     that Road ? Suppose the Intercolonial 
     <lb/>
     Railway and the Branches were built, 
     <lb/>
     would they not be feeders to the 
     <lb/>
     St. John Road and increase the traffic? 
     <lb/>
     has he given us credit for that? If he 
     <lb/>
     was right in telling us that the Interco 
     <lb/>
     lonial Railway was a good commercial 
     <lb/>
     speculation, and asking the Province to 
     <lb/>
     build 3 1-2 twelfths of it, he must be 
     <lb/>
     wrong now in not taking it into his cal<lb break="no"/>culations. If he has made any calcula<lb break="no"/>tion, then I am wrong, and shall apolo<lb break="no"/>gize to the Secretary. I am not going 
     <lb/>
     any farther unless the Secretary replies, 
     <lb/>
     as he seems to went to have the last 
     <lb/>
     word ; he had the last word the other 
     <lb/>
     day, and I suppose he wants to have it 
     <lb/>
     now, but if he speaks, I shall reply. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>.—I shall reply in 
     <lb/>
     a very few words. My hon. friend says 
     <lb/>
   he gave me the last word the other day,<lb/>but I shall not have it now. It was the
<lb/>first time in my experience that he did
<lb/>give me the last word ; I don't think
<lb/>such a thing ever occurred before. I<lb/>was struck with the circumstance as so
<lb/>remarkable that I said. Really he has
<lb/>allowed me the last word. It impressed
<lb/>itself upon my mind at the time, and I
<lb/>thought it a most wonderful victory
<lb/>over him that he allowed me to have it.
<lb/>He says he does not know why I should<lb/>come down to the House and submit an<lb/>estimate in reference to future years<lb/>

     when I am to go to Ottawa. Suppose I 
     <lb/>
     do go to Ottawa: if I feel that his 
     <lb/>
     speeches are calculated to convey to the 
     <lb/>
     country what I believe to be erroneous 
     <lb/>
     impressions, I feel it my duty to make a 
     <lb/>
     statement of facts to go to the country, 
     <lb/>
     and this statement has not been con<lb break="no"/>tradicted. We cannot allow him to 
     <lb/>
     make statements which we believe to be 
     <lb/>
     erroneous, in regard to our liabilities 
     <lb/>
     and the means we have at our disposal. 
     <lb/>
     I stated I would be prepared with 
     <lb/>
     figures to show he was wrong, and that 
     <lb/>
     there would be ample means for the 
     <lb/>
     wants of the country. It is right that 
     <lb/>
    we should view our future position in 
     <lb/>
       

            <cb/>
          

     regard to this matter. I have shown 
     <lb/>
     by taking the expenditure of the last 
     <lb/>
     seven years into account that we would 
     <lb/>
     have in the next fifteen years much 
     <lb/>
     more per year than we had in the last 
     <lb/>
     seven. Did I say there would be more 
     <lb/>
     money than was necessary ? I did not. 
     <lb/>
     Did I say population would not increase? 
     <lb/>
     I did not. Did I say the money would 
     <lb/>
     not be required and could not be ex<lb break="no"/>pended on the roads? I did not. I 
     <lb/>
     desired to show the country and the 
     <lb/>
     House that if the population was double 
     <lb/>
     it would not double the expenses of the 
     <lb/>
     Government. That was the argument 
     <lb/>
     I used in 1863, when I was advocating 
     <lb/>
     the Act to provide for the construction 
     <lb/>
     of the Intercolonial Railway, and it is 
     <lb/>
     the argument I use now. I said the 
     <lb/>
     population would be increased, and we  
     <lb/>
     would have forty per cent additional 
     <lb/>
     for our Roads, Bridges and Education 
     <lb/>
     Could I be blamed for stating these 
     <lb/>
     facts? Was it wrong for us to state 
     <lb/>
     them here and show we were right? 
     <lb/>
     I felt it my duty, and availed myself of 
     <lb/>
     the privilege of having those facts go 
     <lb/>
     to the country.   
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Then, in reference to smuggling, he 
     <lb/>says, How do I know that the United 
     <lb/>States will decrease their tariff? I can 
     <lb/>only judge from what is said as to what 
     <lb/>is likely to be the policy of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of United States. We know 
     <lb/>that during the war, and after the war 
     <lb/>was over, the Government put such  
     <lb/>duties on as were required to raise a 
     <lb/>revenue, and we judge as men judge in 
     <lb/>reference to such matters, that duties 
     <lb/>which reduce their debt two hundred 
     <lb/>million dollars a your will not long con<lb break="no"/>tinue. The longer the violation of the 
     <lb/>revenue laws continue, the more strin<lb break="no"/>gent will be the measures taken to car<lb break="no"/>ry those laws into effect. Suppose a 
     <lb/>system of smuggling was going on 
     <lb/>across our borders would our energies 
     <lb/>be more lax? Would we not take every 
     <lb/>means in our power to suppress that 
     <lb/>illicit trade? What we would do we 
     <lb/>may suppose others would do ; there<lb break="no"/>fore, we cannot expect the advantages 
     <lb/>derived front this source will continue. 
     <lb/>No one, I think, will undertake to say 
     <lb/>that such will be the case ; therefore, 
     <lb/>we will not get us much revenue from 
     <lb/>this source if we remain out of Union 
     <lb/>as in times past. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     I was rejoiced to hear my hon. friend's 
     <lb/>
     declaration, that he would give the 
     <lb/>
     Government his support to bring a 
     <lb/>
     measure giving aid and assistance to 
     <lb/>
     carry on Western Extension. I rejoice 
     <lb/>
     for two reasons: first, that he considers 
     <lb/>
     the work worthy of his assistance ; se<lb break="no"/>condly, that he recognizes our ability 
     <lb/>
     to give it. If he had not felt in his 
     <lb/>
     heart that we could give it, without 
     <lb/>
    intrenching upon the money required, 
     <lb/>
      

            <pb n="53" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_053.jpg"/>
         

     
     <fw type="running">DEBATES FOR THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw> <fw type="num">53</fw> 
  

     for Roads and Bridges, he would not 
     <lb/>have been wiling to have it. He says<lb/>it is our only chance. I admit that if<lb/>we are going to incur additional liabili<lb break="no"/>ties, there could be no better time. If<lb/>it is done before going into Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion, we can get the money at the rate<lb/>of five per cent; and we know that if<lb/>we give to assist Western Extension,<lb/>whatever we give beyond our debt of<lb/>seven million, the interest would come<lb/>out of what we receive for our local<lb/>purposes. I was rejoiced to find taht<lb/>my hon. friend recognized that the<lb/>province had money sufficient to pro<lb break="no"/>vide for local puposes and to give<lb/>this great work, also. I rejoiced to<lb/>hear that he would assist the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment, and I could not help saying<lb/>"hear, hear" to the proposition. I said<lb/>that this satisfied my mind that he took<lb/>a bright view of our future.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     My hon. friend says that when I was 
     <lb/>advocating the construction of the Inter<lb break="no"/>colonial Railway that I estimated that<lb/>we would get something out of it moer<lb/>than working expenses. I doubt if he<lb/>can find a speech of mine in which I<lb/>said it would pay more than working<lb/>expenses. I took the ground that it<lb/>would pay working expenses, and my<lb/>hon. friend from Westmorland took the<lb/>ground that it would not. I thought<lb/>that by connexion with Western<lb/>Extension it would give some revenue.<lb/>He says that I thought the European<lb/>and North American line would pay<lb/>three per cent in five years. I said if it<lb/>paid three per cent. in ten years, the<lb/>indirect advantages would equal the<lb/>the amount of money expended. My hon.<lb/>friend says I have been raking up pa<lb break="no"/>pers to prove his inconsistency. I<lb/>admit that the inconsistency of any<lb/>member of the House does not affect<lb/>the question. He says I am no true<lb/>prophet - that my prophecies had not<lb/>been realized; to prove this, he points<lb/>to the Prohibitory Law and the Rail<lb break="no"/>way; but he admits that the Prohibitory<lb/>Law had not a fair chance. With<lb/>reference to the Railway, I admit that it<lb/>cost more and the revenues from it were<lb/>not as much as I expected. In regard<lb/>to the Act which the House passed for<lb/>the construction of the Intercolonial<lb/>Railway, it was adopted by the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature - not through any influence<lb/>which I exerted in the House, but be<lb break="no"/>cause public sentiment was in favor of<lb/>it, and the most important constituen<lb break="no"/>cies voted for it two to one. We now<lb/>come in under a new arrangment, and<lb/>if my hon. friend entertained the idea<lb/>that it would not pay, and we would<lb/>only have had £40,000 for our local<lb/>purposes, he must now see the advan<lb break="no"/>tages of our position. We will hve<lb/>the Intercolonial Railway built; $1,<lb break="no"/>
            

            <cb/>
           
500,000 expended on Western Extension<lb/>and the branches; we will have more<lb/>money, making allowance for increased<lb/>expenditure; we will have $65,000 for<lb/>our Roads and Bridges in 1871 than we<lb/>had for the average of the last 7 years.<lb/>My hon. friend must agree with me that<lb/>we will be in a better position, even<lb/>allowing for an increased population,<lb/>than we would be if we remained out<lb/>of the Union.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - On this occasion I am<lb/>determined to have the last word if I<lb/>can get it. The Secretary has not an<lb break="no"/>swered my proposition at all - he has<lb/>evaded it. I asked him what our reve<lb break="no"/>nue would be in 1881, - what we would<lb/>pay into the revenues of Canada if our<lb/>tariff was no higher than now? Every<lb/>man must neal in speculation in speak<lb break="no"/>ing of the future; the Secretary has<lb/>proclaimed his opinion, and told the<lb/>advantages that would flow from Con<lb break="no"/>federation. I think his memory is<lb/>defective when he says I called him a<lb/>false prophet in his predictions concern<lb break="no"/>ing the Railway and the Prohibitory<lb/>Liquor Law. I have not even referred<lb/>to the Liquor Law, but he must admit<lb/>that he was mistaken i that; he must<lb/>have thought the public mind was pre<lb break="no"/>pared for it, as all the law is but the em<lb break="no"/>bodiment of the public mind of the<lb/>country; but he was mistaken, and he<lb/>was also mistaken in the earnings of the<lb/>Railroad. I now ask the Secretary<lb/>whether, when he made his calculations<lb/>for 1881, he was not prepared to admit<lb/>that twenty-five or thirty years hence<lb/>the Intercolonial Railway might pay. I<lb/>was surprised to hear the Secretary's<lb/>statements regarding Western Exten<lb break="no"/>sion, that, because I was willing to aid<lb/>that road, I considered this scheme of<lb/>Union would be a great advantage to<lb/>the country. I said Western Extension<lb/>was a work of great importance to the<lb/>country, and I think the people in this<lb/>country would be willing to withdraw<lb/>some of the money from the Roads and<lb/>Bridges in order to secure the construc<lb break="no"/>tion of this work. I have not changed in<lb/>the slightest degree my judnement re<lb break="no"/>garding this Confederation. The Se<lb break="no"/>cretary says, "I am surprised that he<lb/>was willing to assist the Government in<lb/>carrying out that measure." In order<lb/>to place me in a false position before the<lb/>House and country, he says I have<lb/>taken a gloomy view of the country,<lb/>but now I have changed my mind and<lb/>will now support Western Extension. If<lb/>there was anything in it, I doubt the<lb/>propriety of it; this HOuse will not be<lb/>moved by any such inference drawn by<lb/>the Secretary. I believe that Western<lb/>Extension should go on, and the money<lb/>dealt out from the Dominion of Canada<lb/>should be applied to that work. I am<lb/>
          

            <cb/>
          
not going to weary the patience of this<lb/>House any longer; therefore, I shall<lb/>apologize for the time I have taken,<lb/>because I felt that in justice to myself<lb/>I should make these observations in<lb/>reply to the Secretary.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName>. - I expect you to<lb/>have the last word, indeed I am quite<lb/>sure you will. My hon. friend says,<lb/>"the Secretary has not told us what we<lb/>will pay into the revenues of Canada in<lb/>1881." I have stated that in my humble<lb/>opinion we would not pay as much, or<lb/>not more into the revenues of Canada,<lb/>according to population, than we have<lb/>paid in the average of the last seven<lb/>years. I stated distinctly that in Con<lb break="no"/>federation, speaking for the present,<lb/>future and all time to come, the inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants of New Brunswick would not pay<lb/>more per head than the average of the<lb/>last seven years, and after they arrive at<lb/>a certain number the amount per head<lb/>will be diminished. In illustration of<lb/>this we will take the great population of<lb/>the neighboring Republic. before the<lb/>war the people of that country - whether<lb/>they paid in the shape of revenue or<lb/>imports upon the population - paid only<lb/>$1.90 a head, and they supported an army<lb/>and navy, and had ambassadors in every<lb/>port in the world. So it will be in this<lb/>case, and while our population increases<lb/>our expenditure will not increase in like<lb/>ratio.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>In regard to the Western Extension my<lb/>hon. friend says he is willing to take this<lb/>money out of the money for Roads and<lb/>Bridges. This is making a sacrifice we<lb/>did not expect him to make. It impress<lb break="no"/>ed itself upon my mind whe nhe was<lb/>making his speech, that he had come to<lb/>the conclusion that in the Union we were<lb/>not going to be so penniless after all,<lb/>and therefore he had volunteered to sup<lb break="no"/>port that work. I think him for it, as it<lb/>is a work which will be of great benefit<lb/>to the country.<lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>. - Confusion worse con<lb break="no"/>founded. I asked the Secretary for<lb/>figures as to what our revenue would<lb/>be in 1881, and he has dealt in platitudes.<lb/>In adopting the average of the tariff for<lb/>the past seven years he has not taken a<lb/>fair basis, he has given the figures on<lb/>way, but he has not doen what I asked<lb/>him to do, that is to tell us what our<lb/>revenue would be in 1881 according to<lb/>our present tariff.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Secretary ways he is obliged to me<lb/>for my offering to support the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment in aiding Western Extension. He<lb/>need not thank me, for he knows that I<lb/>advocated it last year, as I considered it<lb/>of infinitely more importance than any<lb/>other Railway in the country.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>In reference to the United States pay<lb break="no"/>ing so much per head; it depends upon<lb/>the prosperity of a country and how<lb/>much they pay as a direct tax. If you<lb/>apply the principle to the history of this<lb/>Province you will find as the population<lb/>
          

            <pb n="54" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1867-05-20_Page_054.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="num">54</fw>   <fw type="running">DEBATES IN THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1867.</fw>  
 

increase the wants of the country in<lb break="no"/>crease in proportion.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p>The House adjourned until to-morrow<lb/>at 9 o'clock.</p>

<p rendition="simple:right">T.P.D.</p>

<!-- GL, 2018-04-11, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

            <!--<p>TUESDAY, MAY 21.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>SECOND READINGS.<lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

    

    

            <p>the following Bills were read a second<lb/>time:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to repeal an Act relating to<lb/>burial grounds in the town of Saint An<lb break="no"/>drews.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to authorize the Corporation of<lb/>the City of Saint John to assess in<lb break="no"/>habitants for the purpose of an Agricul<lb break="no"/>tural Exhibition.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill relating to the Paving of the<lb/>Side-walks in the City of Saint John.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill relating to the purchase of lands<lb/>in the County of Westmoreland, for the<lb/>purpose of a Market place.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to amend the Act relating to the<lb/>levying, assessing and collecting of rates<lb/>in the City of Saint John.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill in amendment to the Act relative<lb/>to Municipalities.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill relating to the election of mem<lb break="no"/>bers to serve in the General Assembly.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>THIRD READINGS.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The following Bills were read a third<lb/>time:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to authorize the erection of a<lb/>Marine Hospital at the Port of Caraquet.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A Bill to provide for the erection of an<lb/>Alms House and Work House in the<lb/>County of Northumberland, with power<lb/>to make rules, order and regulations for<lb/>the management of the same.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>RULE OF PUBLICATION.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. SPEAKER asked Mr. Quinton if<lb/>he had brought in any Bill contrary to<lb/>the rule of the House, with respect to<lb/>the publication of notice. He saw it<lb/>stated in one of the papers that a Bill<lb/>had been brought in affecting the asses<lb break="no"/>sing of Saint John, for $20,000. He<lb/>thought there was some mistake as he<lb/>had no recollection of anything of the<lb/>kind.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. QUINTON said the statement was<lb/>incorrect. He had brought in a Bill to<lb/>assess $12,000, for the Streets of Carle<lb break="no"/>ton, and the rule was suspended in that<lb/>case as, although the Bill had been pu-<lb break="maybe"/>lished, he was not supplied with the cer<lb break="no"/>tificate; but it would be handed in if it<lb/>was not already done. The statement<lb/>in the paper was evidently a mistake, the<lb/>two affairs being mixed up by some<lb/>means.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:TILL1">Hon. Mr. TILLEY</persName> moved for leave to<lb/>bring in a Bill to Incorporate the Saint<lb/>John Trades' Co-operative Association.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Leave granted and the Bill being<lb/>brough in was read a first time.<lb/>
            </p>

    
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>GREAT ROADS.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> moved the<lb/>House into Committee on a Bill realting<lb/>to the Great Roads of the Province.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. STEVENS in the Chair.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. YOUNG said that last year he<lb/>brought in a Bill to have a very impor<lb break="no"/>tant road, in the County of Gloucester,<lb/>placed on the Great Road list; and he<lb/>wished to ask the Chief Commissioner<lb/>why that road was not included in this<lb/>Bill.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> said that every<lb/>year there were a large number of Bills<lb/>introduced to place certain roads upon<lb/>the Great Road list. Last year there<lb/>were seventeen, and it was evidently im<lb break="no"/>possible to comply with all. The object<lb/>of this Bill was not so much to increase<lb/>the number of miles as to place on the<lb/>list short roads leading to the Railways<lb/>and other very public places. It will be<lb/>found that he had not specially favored<lb/>his own County in this Bill, when, per<lb break="no"/>haps it might have been supposed he<lb/>would have done so. One road did run<lb/>into the County of Albert, but it was<lb/>more than counterbalanced by the repeal<lb/>of the road which leads from Salmon<lb/>River to Point Wolf. The County of<lb/>King's might appear to have been favor<lb break="no"/>ed, but on examination it would be<lb/>found that the number of miles taken off<lb/>was more than equivalent to those now<lb/>put on the list. The short roads leading to<lb/>the Railways had been found necessary<lb/>to be placed on, while others of les im<lb break="no"/>portance had been taken off. In West<lb break="no"/>morland County there was about half a<lb/>mile of road leading from Moncton to the<lb/>Petitcodiac Bridge, which al lwould<lb/>agree was very necessary to be placed<lb/>on the last, and another short road at the<lb/>Petitcodiac Station. There was one<lb/>road in the County of Carleton, about six<lb/>miles long, which was one of the largest<lb/>additions, and a short piece leading from<lb/>Woodstock Corner to the landing. In<lb/>SAint John County he had added the road<lb/>from the Suspension Bridge to the Port<lb break="no"/>land Road, the road from the City to In-<lb break="maybe"/>diantown, and about a mile and a half of<lb/>the road from the Marsh Bridge to the<lb/>Penitentiary. It would be conceeded on<lb/>all hands that these were quite necessary,<lb/>and he thought that partiality had not<lb/>been known to any particular section of<lb/>the country.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName> said that the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Gloucester need not complain<lb/>that one road had not been put on the<lb/>Great Road list, for he had applied a<lb/>great many times to have several placed<lb/>on, but as yet ineffectually.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> said there were several<lb/>roads in Westmorland which he would<lb/>like to have seen on the list, but he sup<lb break="no"/>posed it was not possible to put on all the<lb/>[missing] roads, and he thought the country<lb/>now was pretty well provided for, al<lb break="no"/>though of course he did not think they<lb/>had received full Justice. (Laughter)<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
    

            <p><persName ref="pers:CAIE1">Mr. CAIE</persName> thought he had great cause<lb/>of complaint, for the County of Kent was<lb/>about the only one in which additions<lb/>had not been made. He held a petition<lb/>from about five hundred of the inhabi<lb break="no"/>tants of the County, praying that the<lb/>road known as the McLaughlin Road<lb/>should be placed on the Great Road list.<lb/>The matter was a very important one,<lb/>for if this road were put in order the in<lb break="no"/>habitants of Welsford would be brought<lb/>very much nearer to the Railway than<lb/>they now are. By this road they would<lb/>be able to get their produce to the Rail<lb break="no"/>way by driving a distance of about thirty<lb/>miles, whereas now they ahve to go<lb/>eighty, and consequently thousands of<lb/>bushels of grain which would have pass<lb break="no"/>ed over the RAilway last yaer, if the road<lb/>had been passable, were disposed of in<lb/>other ways, at a loss to the people. When<lb/>the Chief Commissioner was over that<lb/>way the weather was very unpleasant,<lb/>and he was not able to go over the road,<lb/>but he (Mr. C.) hoped the next time to<lb/>have the pleasure of driving him out<lb/>there. The road was cut through a dis<lb break="no"/>tance of twenty miles; but for want of<lb/>bridges over the streams which flow into<lb/>the Richibueto and the head waters of<lb/>the Buctouche and Shediac Rivers, it<lb/>could not be used for the purposes re<lb break="no"/>quired. He hoped that at least next<lb/>Session the road would be put in good<lb/>order.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     The BIll was agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Hon. Mr. McCLELAN</persName> moved for teh<lb/>suspension fo the Rule to allow him to<lb/>bring in a Bill for the more effectual re<lb break="no"/>pairing of the Roads and BRidges of the<lb/>Parish of Hopewell, in the County of Al<lb break="no"/>bert.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The rule was suspended and leave be<lb break="no"/>ing granted the Bill was brought in and<lb/>read a first time.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:BEVE1">Mr. BEVERIDGE</persName> presented a Petition<lb/>from William Johnson, and forty others,<lb/>inhabitants of the Parish of Gordon, in<lb/>the County of Victoria, praying that a<lb/>road leading to the Tobique River might<lb/>be placed on the Great Road list.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Petition received and referred to the<lb/>Chief Commissioner of the Board of<lb/>Works.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. WILLISTON moved for<lb/>leave to bring in a Bill relating to the<lb/>election of members to serve in the House<lb/>and Legislative Assembly.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>NOTICE OF ADDRESS.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. STEVENS gave notice that he<lb/>should move the following Address:<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>"Resolved, That n humble Address be<lb/>presented to His Excellency the Lieu<lb break="no"/>tenant Governor, praying that his Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency will be pleased to cause to be<lb/>laid before this House all Contracts and<lb/>papers relating to the empllyment of the<lb/>Steamer Princess of Wales to run on the<lb/>route from Shediac to Newcastle, in the<lb/>year 1865."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. STEVENS said he had a memorial<lb/>from the Prince Edward Island Steam<lb/>
            </p>-->
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>