<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-03-08"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-03-08">8 March 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl>
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="3"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-08_Page_001.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-08_Page_002.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-03-08_Page_003.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2016-11-17">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2016-11-17">Created this document, completed metadata, </change>
         
         <change who="Yuqian Fan" when="2016-12-21">Marked-up people</change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-08_Page_001">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-08_Page_001.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-08_Page_002">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-08_Page_002.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-03-08_Page_003">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-08_Page_003.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="1" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-08_Page_001.jpg"/>
            
<div type="section">

<head> PROVINCIAL PARLIAMENT.</head>

<p>HOUSE OF
ASSEMBLY.</p>
            
<p><hi rendition="simple:italic">FREDERICTON</hi>, 8TH MARCH, 1866<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> This being the day appointed by Pro<lb break="no"/>clamation for the meeting of the Legisla<lb break="no"/>ture, at Three o'clock His Excellency the<lb/>
Lieutenant Governor came to the Council<lb/>
Chamber, and being seated on the Throne,<lb/>
commanded the attendance of the House<lb/>
of Assembly, who being come, His Ex<lb break="no"/>cellency was pleased to open the Session<lb/>
with the following<lb/>
            </p>
</div>

<div type="section">
            <head> SPEECH :<lb/>
            </head>

            <p> "<hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr.
President and Honorable Gentlemen<lb/>
of the Legislative Council,</hi></p>
            <p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the House<lb/>
of Assembly.</hi><lb/>
            </p>

            <p> " It
affords me satisfaction to meet you<lb/>
again assembled in Parliament.</p>
            <p>" In
accordance with instructions re<lb break="no"/>ceived by me since the close of the last<lb/>
Session, a Member of my Government was<lb/>
despatched to Quebec to attend a Council<lb/>
summoned by the Governor General of<lb/>
Canada from the various British North<lb/>
American Colonies, for the purpose of af<lb break="no"/>fording assistance to Her Majesty's Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment in the negociation of Commercial<lb/>
Treaties. I have directed the Report of<lb/>
that Gentleman to be laid
before you. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> “ The Government
of the United States <lb/>
having announced a resolution to
termi<lb break="no"/>nate the Treaty existing between that<lb/>
Power and Great Britain, for the recipro<lb break="no"/>cal regulation of Trade, I deemed it right<lb/>
on the invitation of the Government of<lb/>
Canada, and with the concurrence of that<lb/>
of Nova Scotia, to despatch a Delegate to<lb/>
Washington for the purpose of endeavor<lb break="no"/>ing, in concert with Her Majesty's Min<lb break="no"/>ister in that Capital, and Delegates from<lb/>
the Sister Provinces, to procure a tempo<lb break="no"/>rary prolongation of an arrangement<lb/>
which has proved mutually beneficial to<lb/>
both countries, in the hope that time<lb/>
might be thus afforded for negociations,<lb/>
with a view to a permanent renewal of the<lb/>
Treaty. I regret to inform you, that the<lb/>
efforts of the Delegates have not been at<lb break="no"/>tended with success, and that the Treaty<lb/>
will consequently very shortly expire. I<lb/>
do not, however, suppose the discussions<lb/>
on this subject to be finally closed, and I<lb/>
trust that, when revived, they may lead to<lb/>
a satisfactory issue. Meanwhile it is for<lb/>
you to consider whether any revision of<lb/>
the Revenue Laws of this Province may<lb/>
be rendered necessary by the abrogation<lb/>
of this agreement. With a view of ascer<lb break="no"/>taining whether, in this event, new chan<lb break="no"/>nels may not be opened to our commerce,<lb/>
I have, in concert with the Governors of<lb/>
          
            <cb/>
         
the other
British North American Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, despatched a Delegation to the<lb/>
West Indies and certain States of South<lb/>
America. Papers on this subject will be<lb/>
laid before you.</p>

            <p>" You will have learned with indigna<lb break="no"/>tion the existence of a conspiracy, having<lb/>
for its avowed object the dismemberment<lb/>
of the British Empire. Various circum<lb break="no"/>stances would appear to indicate that an<lb/>
attack on some portion of Her Majesty's<lb/>
North American Dominions is contem<lb break="no"/>plated by those engaged in this mad and<lb/>
wicked enterprise. It is difficult to be<lb break="no"/>lieve that an attempt, so certain to be at<lb break="no"/>tended with failure, can be seriously in<lb break="no"/>tended. I rejoice, however, in the con<lb break="no"/>viction that but one sentiment of loyalty<lb/>
animates the people of this Province, and<lb/>
that its inhabitants of every race, creed,<lb/>
and station, are alike ready to repel law<lb break="no"/>less aggression, and to punish unprovoked<lb/>
hostility. I know that I may rely on your<lb/>
hearty concurrence and support in the<lb/>
adoption of the precautionary measures<lb/>
which may be needed to avert so grave a<lb/>
calamity as the occurrence of an armed<lb/>
conflict within our borders.</p>
            <p>" You will be gratified to learn that the<lb/>
Act passed by you during the last Session,<lb/>
for the better regulation of the Militia,<lb/>
has worked in a highly satisfactory man<lb break="no"/>ner. My attention has been steadily di<lb break="no"/>rected to carrying its provisions into<lb/>
effect, and my warmest thanks are due to<lb/>
those who have afforded me zealous and<lb/>
efficient assistance in this respect. The<lb/>
attention of the Imperial Government,<lb/>
and of those of the various Colonial de<lb break="no"/>pendencies of the British Crown, have of<lb/>
late been more seriously directed to the<lb/>
organization of this important branch of<lb/>
national defence, and, with your aid, I<lb/>
trust the Militia Force of New Bruns<lb break="no"/>wick may ere long be placed in a condi<lb break="no"/>tion of efficiency.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> " The
Bill relative to the issue of Trea<lb break="no"/>sury Notes, passed by you with a sus<lb break="no"/>pending clause, has not yet received her<lb/>
Majesty's approval. The reasons which<lb/>
have induced Her Majesty to delay Her<lb/>
assent to this measure, will be forthwith<lb/>
communicated to you.</p>
            <p>" In
compliance with the request con<lb break="no"/>tained in an Address from the House of<lb/>
Assembly, two members of my Executive<lb/>
Council were directed by me to proceed<lb/>
to England to confer with Her Majesty's<lb/>
Government on various questions of im<lb break="no"/>portance, and to conduct other negocia<lb break="no"/>tions on behalf of this Province. The<lb/>
Report of these Delegates will immedi<lb break="no"/>ately be laid before you, and you will<lb/>
learn satisfaction that a Contract has<lb/>
been entered into by them which, in con<lb break="no"/>junction with measures adopted by the<lb/>
Government of Nova Scotia, will ensure<lb/>
the completion of Railway Communica<lb break="no"/>tion between St. John and Halifax at no<lb/>
distant date.<lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/>

            <p> " A Contract has also been completed<lb/>
for the construction of a Railway from<lb/>
St. John to the Frontier of the United<lb/>
States, the works on which have already<lb/>
Commenced and are now in progress.</p>

            <p>" Since I last met you in Parliament,<lb/>
the Crown has been deprived of the ser<lb break="no"/>vices of two of its most distinguished<lb/>
functionaries this Province, and I now<lb/>
desire to express to you my keen sense<lb/>
of the loss which New Brunswick has sus<lb break="no"/>tained in the retirement of Chief Justice<lb/>
Sir James Carter, and the death of Chief<lb/>
Justice Parker.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> "<hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker and Gentlemen of the House<lb/>
of Assembly,</hi><lb/>
            </p>

            <p> “ An Account of the Income and Ex<lb break="no"/>penditure of the past year will be laid<lb/>
before you. Although the Revenue was<lb/>
considerably less than that received in<lb/>
1864, it yet exceeded the Estimate, and I<lb/>
am happy to inform you that, since the<lb/>
close of the financial year, it has steadily<lb/>
improved. The Estimates, which will be<lb/>
immediately submitted to you, have been<lb/>
framed with as close an attention to<lb/>
economy as a due regard for the exigen<lb break="no"/>cies of the public service and the security<lb/>
of the Province would permit.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> "<hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. President, and Honorable Gentlemen<lb/>
of the Legislative Council,</hi></p>
            <p>"<hi rendition="simple:italic">Mr. Speaker, and Gentlemen of the<lb/>
House of Assembly,</hi><lb/>
            </p>

            <p> " I have received Her Majesty's com<lb break="no"/>mands to communicate to you a Corres<lb break="no"/>pondence on the affairs of British North<lb/>
America, which has taken place between<lb/>
Her Majesty's Principal Secretary of<lb/>
State for the Colonies and the Governor<lb/>
General of Canada ; and I am further di<lb break="no"/>rected to express to you the strong and<lb/>
deliberate opinion of Her Majesty's Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment, that it is an object much to be<lb/>
desired, that all the British North Ameri<lb break="no"/>can Colonies should agree to unite in one<lb/>
Government. These papers will imme<lb break="no"/>diately be laid before you.</p>
            <p>" I trust
that your deliberations may<lb/>
tend to advance the welfare of the Pro<lb break="no"/>vince and of its people, and a pledge that<lb/>
this will be the case may be found in their<lb/>
being undertaken, as I am sure they will<lb/>
be, under a full sense of your grave re<lb break="no"/>sponsibilities, and in a spirit at once of<lb/>
confident self reliance and of loyal attach<lb break="no"/>ment to that great Empire of which New<lb/>
Brunswick forms a part, and her connec<lb break="no"/>tion with which is at once her security<lb/>
and her pride."<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> The
Members of the Assembly having<lb/>
returned to the Lower House, His Honor<lb/>
the Speaker read the opening Speech.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. W. J.
GILBERT</persName> introduced a Bill<lb/>
to make better provisions for the secrecy of<lb/>
the ballot, and to prevent <unclear n="can't make out the last part of the sentence">?</unclear>
               <lb/>
          
            <pb n="2" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-08_Page_002.jpg"/>

<fw type="num">2</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866</fw> 

         ences at elections of members to serve in<lb/>
the General Assembly of the Province. </p>


            <p> <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Mr.
BOYD</persName> then moved the following<lb/>
Address in answer to His Excellency's<lb/>
Speech :
 <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><hi rendition="simple:italic">To His Excellency, the Honorable</hi> ARTHUR <lb/>
HAMILTON GORDON, C. M. G., <hi rendition="simple:italic">Lieut. <lb/>
Governor and Commander in Chief of <lb/>
of Province
of New Brunswick, &amp;c.,<lb/>
&amp;c., &amp;c.</hi> <lb/>
            </p>
</div>
<div type="section">
            <head> THE HUMBLE ADDRESS OF THE<lb/>
HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY<lb/>
            </head>
            <p> MAY IT PLEASE YOUR EXCELLENCY,-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>l. We, Her Majesty‘s
faithful Subjects, <lb/>
the Commons of New Brunswick, thank <lb/>
Your Excellency for the Speech
delivered <lb/>
at the opening of the present Session.
<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 2. We thank Your Excellency for the <lb/>
assurance that the Report of the
Delegate <lb/>
despatched by Your Excellency to Que<lb break="no"/>bec, to attend a Council summoned
by <lb/>
the Governor General of Canada, for the<lb/>
purpose of affording assistance to Her <lb/>
Majesty’s Government in the
negociation <lb/>
of Commercial Treaties, will be laid be<lb break="no"/>fore us.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 3. We thank Your Excellency for re<lb break="no"/>sponding to the invitation of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment of Canada in sending a Delegate to <lb/>
Washington for the purpose of endeavor<lb break="no"/>ing, in concert with Delegates from the <lb/>
Sister Provinces, and Her Majesty's Min<lb break="no"/>ister at Washington, to procure a tem<lb break="no"/>porary extension of the Reciprocity <lb/>
Treaty, with a view to afford
time for full <lb/>
negociations, having for their object the <lb/>
establishment of a permanent
commercial <lb/>
arrangement with the United States upon <lb/>
a basic mutually beneficial ; and we unite <lb/>
with Your Excellency in the expression <lb/>
of regret, that the efforts of
the Delegates <lb/>
were not successful, and we trust that dis<lb break="no"/>cussion on this subject, if
revived, may <lb/>
lead to a satisfactory issue. We
are <lb/>
pleased to learn that Your Excellency
<lb/>
has, in concert with the Governors of the <lb/>
other British North American
Provinces, <lb/>
despatched a Delegate to the West Indies <lb/>
and certain States of South America,
with <lb/>
a view of opening up new channels to our <lb/>
Commerce. We will carefully consider <lb/>
any measure having for its object any re<lb break="no"/>vision of the Revenue Laws
rendered <lb/>
necessary by the abrogation of
the Treaty. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>4.
We learn with feelings of deep in<lb break="no"/>dignation the existence of a
conspiracy, <lb/>
having for its avowed object the dismem<lb break="no"/>berment of the British Empire. We <lb/>
would hope that no attack will be made <lb/>
on any portion of Her Majesty's North
<lb/>
American Dominions ; but in that event, <lb/>
we rejoice in being able to assure Your <lb/>
Excellency that but one sentiment of loy<lb break="no"/>alty animates the whole people of this <lb/>
Province ; and its inhabitants, of every <lb/>
race, creed, and station, are alike ready to <lb/>
repel lawless aggression and to punish un<lb break="no"/>provoked hostility ; and Your Excellency<lb/>
can confidently rely upon our cordial co<lb break="no"/>operation and support in the adoption of<lb/>
any measures of a precautionary charac<lb break="no"/>ter, that may be necessary to
avert a <lb/>
calamity so serious as that of the occur<lb break="no"/>rence of an armed conflict within our <lb/>
borders. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> 5. We are gratified to learn that the <lb/>
Act passed at the last Session of the Legis<lb break="no"/>lature for the better regulation
of the <lb/>
Militia has worked satisfactorily ; and
we<lb/>
are pleased to learn that the attention of <lb/>
the Imperial Government and the Colo<lb break="no"/>nial dependencies of the British
Crown <lb/>
continues to be directed to the organiza<lb break="no"/><cb/>tion of
this important branch of
national <lb/>
defence, and we will be ready to afford <lb/>
such aid to this Institution as the financial <lb/>
resources of the country will justify. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>6 We shall be pleased to learn the rea<lb break="no"/>sons which have induced Her Majesty <lb/>
to delay her approval of a Bill passed at <lb/>
the last Session of the
Legislature author<lb break="no"/>izing the issue of Treasury
Notes, and<lb/>
when communicated to us they will be<lb/>
carefully considered.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>7. We thank Your Excellency for hav<lb break="no"/>ing complied with our request that a Dele<lb break="no"/>gation should be sent to England
to
confer <lb/>
with Her Majesty‘s Government on
im<lb break="no"/>portant subjects, and to conduct other <lb/>
negotiations on behalf of this Province, <lb/>
and we are pleased to know that the Re<lb break="no"/>port of the Delegates will be laid before <lb/>
us. <lb/>
            </p>


            <p> 8. We learn with satisfaction that con<lb break="no"/>tracts have been entered into which, when <lb/>
executed, will secure uninterrupted Rail<lb break="no"/>way Communication from Halifax to the <lb/>
United States. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 9. We join Your Excellency in the ex<lb break="no"/>pression of regret that since
the last Ses<lb break="no"/>sion the Crown has been deprived of the <lb/>
valuable services of two of its most dis<lb break="no"/>tinguished public servants in this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince, and we participate in the general <lb/>
sorrow which is felt at the death of the <lb/>
late Chief Justice the Honorable Robert <lb/>
Parker.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> 10. We thank Your Excellency for the <lb/>
assurance that the Accounts of Revenue <lb/>
and Expenditure of the past year, and the <lb/>
Estimates for the current year, will be <lb/>
laid before us ; and we are gratified to <lb/>
learn that the Revenue of the past year
<lb/>
exceeded the Estimate, and that during <lb/>
the current year it has steadily improved. <lb/>

            </p>
            <p> 11. The Correspondence which has taken <lb/>
place between Her Majesty's Principal Se<lb break="no"/>cretary of State for the Colonies and the<lb/>
Governor General of Canada, on the af<lb break="no"/>fairs of British North America, when laid <lb/>
before us will receive due attention, and <lb/>
the opinion expressed by Her Majesty's <lb/>
Government will command that respect <lb/>
and attention which is due to suggestions<lb/>
emanating from so high a source ; but in <lb/>
any scheme for a Union of the British <lb/>
North American Colonies which may be<lb/>
proposed, it is, in the opinion of this <lb/>
House, absolutely essential that
full pro<lb break="no"/>tection should be afforded to the rights<lb/>
and interests of the people of
this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince ; and no  measure which fails to <lb/>
obtain these objects should be adopted. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>12.
We sincerely trust that our deliber<lb break="no"/>ations may tend to advance the welfare of <lb/>
the Province and of its people, and we <lb/>
assure Your Excellency that they will be<lb/>
undertaken under a full sens of our re<lb break="no"/>sponsibilities, and in a spirit
of loyalty <lb/>
and attachment to our Sovereign, and we<lb/>
feel security and pride in our connection<lb/>
with that great Empire of which New<lb/>
Brunswick forms a part.<lb/>
            </p>




            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILL1">HON. MR. GILLMOR</persName> moved that-<lb/>copies of the Speech of His Excellency be<lb/>
printed for the use of the Members of<lb/>
the Honse of Assembly. Blank filled<lb/>
with 200.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">MR. BOYD</persName> moved that the House do
<lb/>
on Monday next go into
consideration of <lb/>
the proposed Address to His Excellency.<lb/>
Carried.<lb/>
            </p>

            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">MR. MCMILLAN</persName> put the question to <lb/>
          
            <cb/>
           
His Honor the Speaker if any appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of Door Keeper to the House had<lb/>
been made on the death of Mr. George<lb/>
Anderson.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SPEA1">SPEAKER</persName>.—He could not say, as he<lb/>
had not been informed.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILB1">MR. W. J. GILBERT</persName> suggested that<lb/>
some member of the Government inform<lb/>
the House.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName>.—The<lb/>
Government had appointed Mr. Benja<lb break="no"/>min Wheeler.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> contended the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment had no right to make the ap<lb break="no"/>pointment without the authority of the<lb/>
House ; and he did not see any reason<lb/>
why the House should submit to it. He<lb/>
held that if the House wished and re<lb break="no"/>quired any person for door-keeper, it ne<lb break="no"/>cessarily had the right of making the ap<lb break="no"/>pointment. The Government had no<lb/>
right to interfere with their privileges.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> said<lb/>
it was necessary to have a person at the<lb/>
opening of the Legislature to act as door<lb/>
keeper, and so the appointment was made.<lb/>
But if the House thought it had the right<lb/>
of appointment, the Government in that<lb/>
case had none. He did not wish to inter<lb break="no"/>fere with any of the privileges of the<lb/>
House.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> said he should, in or<lb break="no"/>der to test the question of right, move<lb/>
that the House do proceed to the appoint<lb break="no"/>ment of a door-keeper, in the room of<lb/>
George Anderson, deceased.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILB1">MR. W. J. GILBERT</persName> argued that the<lb/>
direct right of appointment lay in the<lb/>
hands of the Sergeant-at-Arms, and the<lb/>
House had supervision over the exercise<lb/>
of that right. The right of appointment<lb/>
of door-keeper might be a small affair,<lb/>
but if the House gave way, because it was<lb/>
small, their rights, by allowing such a<lb/>
precedent, might be invaded in matters<lb/>
of larger concern.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="UNSPECIFIED">HON. ATTORNEY GENERAL</persName> said :<lb/>
That his present opinion was that offices <lb/>
connected with the House should he ap<lb break="no"/>pointed by the House, and he would sug<lb break="no"/>gest that the matter be referred to the <lb/>
Committee of Privileges. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:FISH1">MR. FISHER</persName> had no objection to let <lb/>
the matter go to the Committee. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> said—in making the <lb/>
motion—he did it not with a wish to re<lb break="no"/>move the present door keeper, but merely
<lb/>
to ascertain and protect the privileges
of <lb/>
the House. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:KERR1">MR. KERR</persName> was of opinion that the <lb/>
House should retain the power of ap<lb break="no"/>pointing all its officials. They
appointed <lb/>
their Speaker, they appointed
their Chap<lb break="no"/>lain : why should they not appoint their <lb/>
Door Keeper? If a person received an <lb/>
appointment in the House, the House<lb/>
should have the power of making it.  It <lb/>
was the way in Nova Scotia, and, he be<lb break="no"/>lieved, all the other Provinces, that all <lb/>
officials were appointed by a direct vote<lb/>
of the House. He then referred to the <lb/>
Journals, and the appointment of the se<lb break="no"/>cond Clerk of the House by the first<lb/>
Clerk : and argued that a regular system <lb/>
should be adopted, and finally moved-<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>“ That the question to appoint the Door <lb/>
Keeper and other subordinate
officers of <lb/>
the House, be referred to a Committee of <lb/>
Privileges to report thereon.”<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Which, after further desultory conver<lb break="no"/>sation, was carried, Mr. Wetmore with<lb break="no"/>drawing his motion.</p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WILL1">MR. WILLISTON</persName> moved that a Com<lb break="no"/>mittee be appointed to take into consider<lb break="no"/>ation the Contingencies of this
House,— </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-03-08_Page_003.jpg"/>

 <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866</fw> <fw type="num">3</fw>

            <p>Committee
: Messrs. Williston, Young, <lb/>
Otty, Boyd. L. P. W. Desbrisay. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">MR.
MCCLELLAN</persName> moved that a Com<lb break="no"/>mittee be appointed to whom shall be re<lb break="no"/>ferred all matters relating to
the mining<lb/>
interests. Committee : Messrs. McCle<lb break="no"/>lan, Bailey, Thompson, Connell, Wilmot. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:GILB1">MR.
GILBERT</persName> read the report of the<lb/>
Committee appointed to provide for the <lb/>
Reporting and Printing the
Debates, and <lb/>
said the Committee had taken
great trou<lb break="no"/>ble to carry out the arrangements, and <lb/>
had done their best to
economise, and se<lb break="no"/>cure the services of competent Reporters.
<lb/>
The terms of the arrangement
were simi<lb break="no"/>lar to those that had been made last year. <lb/>
As the present Session promised to be <lb/>
one of the most important that had taken <lb/>
place in the Province, and as it
would be <lb/>
desirable that the proceedings
of the <lb/>
House should be circulated abroad, he <lb/>
proposed that 7000 copies of the Debates <lb/>
should be printed. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The report was then adopted. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:SUTT1">MR. SUTTON</persName>
moved that a Commit<lb break="no"/>tee be appointed to whom shall be refer<lb break="no"/>red all matters relating to the
agricultu<lb break="no"/>ral interests of the Province. Commit<lb break="no"/>tee : Messrs. Sutton, McClelan, Meehan,
<lb/>
Kerr, Caie, Landry, Lewis, Scovil, Per<lb break="no"/>kins, Cudlip, Hatheway, W. E.
Perley, <lb/>
Costigan, and Thompson. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName> moved that the ap<lb break="no"/>portionment of the Debates should be ac<lb break="no"/>cording to the population of 1861. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">MR. MCMILLAN</persName> contended that it was<lb/>
not in the city that the hon. mover of the <lb/>
resolution represented that the Debates <lb/>
were wanted to circulate, it was outside <lb/>
places. In St. John they had a daily sy<lb break="no"/>nopsia of the proceedings of the House <lb/>
in the newspapers, and it was found that <lb/>
the people there did not properly appre<lb break="no"/>ciate the Debates. He hoped the hon. <lb/>
mover would not object to give each mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the House an equal portion. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> After
a few observations from Messrs. <lb/>
Boyd and McClelan. Hon. G. L. Hathe<lb break="no"/>way said if the resolution was carried
out <lb/>
St. John would get the sixth of
the De<lb break="no"/>bates, as its population was a sixth of that <lb/>
of the entire Province. He agreed with<lb/>
the ex-Surveyor General that it
was out<lb break="no"/>side places—in such Counties as
Glouces<lb break="no"/>ter and Restigouche, where the people in <lb/>
the back settlements did not receive the <lb/>
newspapers—that the circulation
of the<lb/>
Debates was needed. He would much<lb/>
prefer that the arrangement for the dis<lb break="no"/>tribution of the Debates should remain as <lb/>
it was. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:LIND1">MR. LINDSAY</persName> spoke in favor of the <lb/>
resolution. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CAIE1">MR. CAIE</persName> said that the golden rule <lb/>
" to do unto others as we would be done <lb/>
by," should govern them in this
matter. <lb/>
He did not consider it fair play that Glou<lb break="no"/>cester or Restigouche should receive as <lb/>
great a portion as Kent, whose popula<lb break="no"/>tion was so much greater. He would ask <lb/>
if it was a question of supplying mate<lb break="no"/>rial wants, if it would be fair
play to give <lb/>
Restigouche as many barrels of
flour as <lb/>
Kent ? It was equally necessary to pro<lb break="no"/>vide food for the mind as the body, and <lb/>
the same rule should apply.  <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">MR.
MCMILLAN</persName> said the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber who had just spoken seemed deter<lb break="no"/>mined to stand up for Kent : yet if he <lb/>
was so determined to have fair play—as <lb/>
half of the population was French in that <lb/>
County—why did he not move that
the <lb/>
Debates be printed in French ?
He would <lb/>
move, as an amendment, that the distri<lb break="no"/>bution of the Debates be an equal num<lb break="no"/>ber to each member of the House. <lb/>
            </p>
            <cb/> 

            <p> <persName ref="pers:WETM1">MR. WETMORE</persName>
contended that if<lb/>
many of the people in St. John did get<lb/>
information of the proceedings of the<lb/>
House from the newspapers, for those<lb/>
newspapers they had the supreme felicity<lb/>
of paying. The only fair and reasonable
<lb/>
way was distribution by population. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:CORA1">MR. CORAM</persName>
said that it was only the <lb/>
people of the city that got the advantage <lb/>
of the papers published in St. John ; <lb/>
there was a large number of people
<lb/>
throughout the County in the backwoods <lb/>
who did not see a paper. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> <persName ref="pers:KERR1">MR. KERR</persName> supported the amendment, <lb/>
and argued if St. John, with its popula<lb break="no"/>tion of between thirty and forty <lb/>
thousand people, could make good <lb/>
its claim to a distribution of Debate <lb/>
on that basis, they might, if the prin<lb break="no"/>ciple was allowed, seek to apply it <lb/>
also to the distribution of bye-road
<lb/>
money, which had not been dreamt
of yet. <lb/>
In St. John, papers were issued
daily <lb/>
ly, morning and evening—there
the great <lb/>
bulk of the people received
them, and <lb/>
read the synopsis of the Debates ; but in <lb/>
the country the people could not get them, <lb/>
and in many cases, if they
could, they <lb/>
were too poor to pay for them. He
<lb/>
thought that each member should
have <lb/>
equal rights with other members, and re<lb break="no"/>ceive an equal number. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> The amendment being put to the vote, <lb/>
was carried. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion, the House was adjourned <lb/>
until to-morrow at 10 o'clock. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>A. A. <lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2016-11-16, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
 
            <!--<p> FRIDAY, March 9. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion of MR. GILBERT, a Com<lb break="no"/>mittee was appointed to whom shall be re<lb break="no"/>ferred all matters connected with the pub<lb break="no"/>lic accounts, with power to bring before <lb/>
them persons and papers. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion of MR. TROOP, a Commit<lb break="no"/>tee was appointed to whom shall
be re<lb break="no"/>ferred all matters relating to Trade and <lb/>
Commerce in this Province. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion of MR. BOYD, a Committee <lb/>
was appointed to whom shall be referred <lb/>
all matters relating to the
Lumbering in<lb break="no"/>terests of the Province. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion of MR. A. C. DESBRISAY, <lb/>
a Committee was appointed to take into <lb/>
consideration all matters
relating to the <lb/>
Fisheries of this Province. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> On motion of MR. MCMILLAN, Com<lb break="no"/>mittee was appointed, to whom shall be <lb/>
referred all matters relating to
the privi<lb break="no"/>leges of this House. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> ADDRESSING
THE DEBATES. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> MR. GILBERT said that the Commit<lb break="no"/>tee appointed at the last Session of the <lb/>
House, to make arrangements for publish<lb break="no"/>ing the Debates, had no power delegated <lb/>
to them to make arrangements for folding <lb/>
and addressing the Debates, but they had <lb/>
received an offer from Mr. Day, who <lb/>
would mail and address them for $5
for <lb/>
each member. It would be
attended with <lb/>
great delay to have them sent up here by <lb/>
the publisher, therefore he hoped the <lb/>
House would make some arrangements <lb/>
about having them addressed. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> COL.
BOYD said they had better adopt <lb/>
the same mode of having them addressed <lb/>
as they did last year ; bu: he would not <lb/>
agree to paying $5 for each member. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> MR. SUTTON said they were address<lb break="no"/>ed last year in St. John for $4 apiece. If<lb/>
they were sent to Fredericton they would<lb/>
be under their own supervision.<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p> MR. CAIE said the amount to be paid <lb/>
the publisher should be a little more
than
<lb/>
it was last year, as there are 7,000 instead <lb/>
of 6,000 copies to be addressed ; but he
<lb/>
did not think they should all be addressed <lb/>
in St. John.<lb/>
            </p>


            <p> MR. GILBERT said that last Session<lb/>
part of them were addressed here and <lb/>
part in St. John. For some Counties <lb/>
there would be a great loss of time in <lb/>
having them come to Fredericton, al<lb break="no"/>though he thought the work could be
done <lb/>
better under their own supervision, or the <lb/>
work might be done under the Post Office
<lb/>
Department, as they would know best how <lb/>
to direct them to the Way Offices. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> MR. CONNELL believed that the work <lb/>
could be done best under the Post Office
<lb/>
Department. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> COL. BOYD said, that in the good old <lb/>
times, thirty years ago, every member used <lb/>
to address his own debates, and he had <lb/>
kept to that old fashioned way
for a num<lb break="no"/>ber of years. He believed t cost £70 <lb/>
when they were addressed under the Post <lb/>
Office Department. He would like to <lb/>
have his Debates addressed in St.
John, <lb/>
as they would be delayed one or two days <lb/>
by coming up here. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> MR.
BEVERIDGE observed that the <lb/>
arrangement of last year gave satisfaction
<lb/>
in his County, his Debates being address<lb break="no"/>ed here by a person in the employ of the<lb/>
House. <lb/>
            </p>

            <p> MR. GILBERT said he could hardly <lb/>
credit that the addressing of the Debates, <lb/>
cost £70 If they had the privilege of <lb/>
having the head of the Post Office De<lb break="no"/>partment in the
House, they could get in<lb break="no"/>formation of what the labor would cost. <lb/>
Having the Debates addressed in
St. <lb/>
John is sometimes the cause of delay, for <lb/>
if you received a notice from any of your <lb/>
constituents that they do not receive the <lb/>
Debates, you have to write to the pub<lb break="no"/>lisher, and several days must elapse
be<lb break="no"/>fore it can be rectified ; but if they were <lb/>
addressed here it could be corrected at <lb/>
once. Half of the Debates have to come <lb/>
here, and the rest would be delayed but <lb/>
a day and night. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> MR. ANGLIN
said there was one ob<lb break="no"/>jection to this arrangement for
addressing <lb/>
the Debates in St. John which had been <lb/>
overlooked, that was, that they had no <lb/>
security that they should get the 7,000 <lb/>
copies for which they paid. They
had to <lb/>
depend upon the honor of the
person who <lb/>
published and addressed them. There <lb/>
should be something like a receipt of de<lb break="no"/>livery. In whatever way the arrange<lb break="no"/>ments may be made there will be
innume<lb break="no"/>rable complaints ; but in this
case there <lb/>
is no security against fraud. This House <lb/>
should, through some officer, obtain a de<lb break="no"/>livery of the whole, and then have them <lb/>
distributed ; by this means persons through <lb/>
the country would receive them
earlier <lb/>
and more regular. He did not value the <lb/>
Debates, so therefore cared little about <lb/>
it ; but the whole cost of
addressing them <lb/>
should not exceed £50 or £60. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> MR. LINDSAY said, that Hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers who made out their lists,
would cer<lb break="no"/>tainly know whether they received the De<lb break="no"/>bates or not. In his district they received <lb/>
them pretty regular. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. WILMOT
remarked,
that to ensure <lb/>
their being received, they should be ad<lb break="no"/>dressed by the Post Office Department, <lb/>
for if they were not properly
directed they <lb/>
would go to the wrong Post Office. <lb/>
            </p>
            <p> MR. CORAM
observed that on the <lb/>
Eastern side of the Harbor there was no <lb/>
way of distributing them but by carrying <lb/>
them to every man’s door ; for
the people <lb/>
            </p>-->

</div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
