<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1866-06-26"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1866-06-26">26 June 1866</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          

         
          
         
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Second Session of 1866</title>.
                    

         <date when="1866"/>. 
          

         <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="20" to="23"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_020.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_021.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_022.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_023.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-03-20">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-03-20">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_020">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_020.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_021">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_021.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_022">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_022.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_023">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_023.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="20" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_020.jpg"/>
          

<fw type="num">20</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 

       
<!-- GL, 2018-03-20, Commented out below as it precedes Debate Day --> 

            <!--<p>
     large majority of French population, 
     <lb/>
     and in Moncton there was a large ma<lb break="no"/>jority of English. In both those places 
     <lb/>
     the law operates without any class dis<lb break="no"/>tinctions at all. The people have be<lb break="no"/>come amalgamated, and you cannot 
     <lb/>
     distinguish the French from the English. 
     <lb/>
     The French have always taken care of 
     <lb/>
     their own poor, and the English have 
     <lb/>
     never been assessed for a single dollar 
     <lb/>
     for their support. As they provided 
     <lb/>
     for their own poor they thought it a 
     <lb/>
     hardship to be assessed to support the 
     <lb/>
     poor of the Parish. To avoid this a 
     <lb/>
     Bill was passed to allow them to elect 
     <lb/>
     their assessors and overseers the same 
     <lb/>
     as we do. It only drew a visionary line 
     <lb/>
     between the English and French : they 
     <lb/>
     had the same general law, only each 
     <lb/>
     party elected their own officers. This 
     <lb/>
     did not have the effect of making a dis<lb break="no"/>tinction of race, but had operated well, 
     <lb/>
     and everything had been carried on in 
     <lb/>
     harmony and good feeling. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. KERR was entirely opposed to 
     <lb/>
     the principle of this Bill, but as it had 
     <lb/>
    been introduced into Westmorland, he 
     <lb/>thought the French inhabitants of 
     <lb/>Northumberland were entitled to the 
     <lb/>same privilege.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Hon. Mr. WILMOT could not under<lb break="no"/>stand how his hon. friend could vote for 
     <lb/>
     it if it was wrong in principle. If they 
     <lb/>
     had done wrong in other Counties, he 
     <lb/>
     should endeavor to put a stop to it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Progress was then reported upon the 
     <lb/>
     Bill.  
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     HON. MR. FISHER'S RESOLUTION ON THE 
     <lb/>
     APPOINTMENT OF DELEGATES TO MAKE 
     <lb/>
     ARRANGEMENTS FOR THE UNION OF 
     <lb/>
     BRITISH NORTH AMERICA. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>.—In bringing a 
     <lb/>
     resolution before the House I have 
     <lb/>
    generally found it necessary to offer 
     <lb/>some arguments why it should pass, but 
     <lb/>I feel on this occasion that very few 
     <lb/>observations are required. I do not 
     <lb/>feel disposed, at this hurried season of 
     <lb/>the year, to occupy the time of the 
     <lb/>House to convince them of what they 
     <lb/>are already convinced of, for this is not 
     <lb/>a new proposition. When we reflect 
     <lb/>upon the history of the past, we all 
     <lb/>know that this question has been dis<lb break="no"/>cussed by the people of the country in 
     <lb/>all its bearings, and their representa<lb break="no"/>tives come here charged with their 
     <lb/>opinion upon this question. I do not 
     <lb/>intend to occupy the time of the House 
     <lb/>beyond two or three minutes. We 
     <lb/>know that the question of the Union of 
     <lb/>British North America has been in the 
     <lb/>minds of the people of this country for 
     <lb/>twenty-five or thirty years. About 
     <lb/> three years ago propositions were made 
     <lb/>for the Provinces to discuss this ques<lb break="no"/>tion, and a Scheme of Union was 
     <lb/>agreed upon. The Legislature of Ca<lb break="no"/>
          

            <cb/>
          
nada, in both its departments, have 
     <lb/>
     passed upon this question, and it has 
     <lb/>
     been discussed in this Province. The 
     <lb/>
     general election has been held in order 
     <lb/>
     to test the minds of the people of the 
     <lb/>
     country upon the Union of British 
     <lb/>
     North America. I think it is gratifying 
     <lb/>
     to all of us that the people of this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince were so unanimous upon this 
     <lb/>
     question as they really were. The pro<lb break="no"/>position which I have to make now is 
     <lb/>
     in the resolution, and I know that a 
     <lb/>
     large majority of the people are in 
     <lb/>
     favor of the measure. The Govern<lb break="no"/>ment are anxious that past differences 
     <lb/>
     should be forgotten. Much political 
     <lb/>
     strife and bitterness will arise in de<lb break="no"/>ciding a question of this kind, but we 
     <lb/>
     hope the result we have arrived at will 
     <lb/>
     advance the interest of all. The basis 
     <lb/>
     of any arrangement for the Union of 
     <lb/>
     these Provinces will be the Resolutions 
     <lb/>
     adopted at Quebec. That matter has 
     <lb/>
     been discussed throughout the Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces, and objections have been made 
     <lb/>
     to different portions of it. What we 
     <lb/>
     propose to do is, to get as many im<lb break="no"/>provements made to it as we possibly 
     <lb/>
     can. This resolution proposes that we
     <lb/>
     should ask the Governor appoint 
     <lb/>
     Delegates to unite with Delegates from 
     <lb/>
     the other Provinces in arranging with 
     <lb/>
     the Imperial Government for the Union 
     <lb/>
     of British North America upon such 
     <lb/>
     terms as will secure the just rights and 
     <lb/>
     interests of New Brunswick, accom<lb break="no"/>panied with provision for the immediate 
     <lb/>
     construction of the Inter-Colonial Rail<lb break="no"/>way—each Province to have an equal 
     <lb/>
     voice in such Delegation, Upper and 
     <lb/>
     Lower Canada to be considered as 
     <lb/>
     seperate Provinces. There are two 
     <lb/>
     principles in the resolutions adopted at 
     <lb/>
     Quebec, about which there will be very 
     <lb/>
     little discussion, that is the principle of 
     <lb/>
     Federation and the principle of repre<lb break="no"/>sentation by population. The finance 
     <lb/>
     arrangements, and the arrangements 
     <lb/>
     regarding the Legislative Council will 
     <lb/>
     be considered, and upon these points 
     <lb/>
     it will be the endeavor of the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment to secure as favorable terms as 
     <lb/>
     they possibly can. Another proposition 
     <lb/>
     in this resolution is, that not only our 
     <lb/>
     just rights and interests are to be se<lb break="no"/>cured, but there is a provision for the 
     <lb/>
     immediate construction of the Inter<lb break="no"/>Colonial Railway. This proposition is 
     <lb/>
     conveyed in as strong language as can 
     <lb/>
     be written, and it lies at the bottom and 
     <lb/>
     forms the basis of any arrangement 
     <lb/>
     that may be made. I am not going to 
     <lb/>occupy the time dilating upon the ad<lb break="no"/>vantages of Union. If we want argu<lb break="no"/>ments in favor of Union let us look at 
     <lb/>the neighboring country, and see the 
     <lb/>blood and treasure which they have<lb/>spent in preserving their Union. Here 
     <lb/>we are in a sort of transition state ; we 
     <lb/>
      

            <cb/>
           

     are now about to make arrangements to 
     <lb/>
    form a Union of the different North 
     <lb/>American Provinces under the care of 
     <lb/>the British Government. We are going 
     <lb/>to develop our national resources, con<lb break="no"/>solidate our varied interests, and 
     <lb/>secure measures for our common 
     <lb/>and mutual defence. The country 
     <lb/>have declared themselves unmistaka<lb break="no"/>bly in favor of Union, and it is our wish 
     <lb/>and determination to meet the objec<lb break="no"/>tions of the smallest minority in every 
     <lb/>way in order that when this Union is 
     <lb/>consummated it will not only provide 
     <lb/>the greatest good for the greatest num<lb break="no"/>ber, but that the smallest number will 
     <lb/>have no reason to complain.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—I suppose it is expected 
     <lb/>
     that I will make some observations. I 
     <lb/>
     believe I express the feeling of every 
     <lb/>
     hon. member on the floors of the House, 
     <lb/>
     and every man throughout the country, 
     <lb/>
     when he comes to know of the speech 
     <lb/>
     of the hon. mover of the Resolution on 
     <lb/>
     a subject so important, when I say I 
     <lb/>
     expected a more detailed explanation, 
     <lb/>
     of the policy of the Government. The 
     <lb/>
     object is to conceal what the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment intend to do. While I am prepar<lb break="no"/>ed to admit that the people of the coun<lb break="no"/>try have adopted the principle of Union, 
     <lb/>
     it has been done by agencies with which 
     <lb/>
     it is not necessary for me to deal. Fe<lb break="no"/>nianism is one of the agencies that has 
     <lb/>
     acted upon the public mind, and it has 
     <lb/>
     also been acted upon by the treacherous 
     <lb/>
     unconstitutional conduct of the Gover<lb break="no"/>nor. By these means the Government 
     <lb/>
     have obtained a majority, and I bow, as 
     <lb/>
     I have always done, to the will of the 
     <lb/>
     people. I believe that unless this 
     <lb/>
     Scheme of Confederation is accomplish<lb break="no"/>ed in a short time, the reaction upon 
     <lb/>
     this Scheme will be more powerful than 
     <lb/>
     it ever has been. Public opinion is very 
     <lb/>
     uncertain. I see many of my hon. friends 
     <lb/>
     here with whom I have sat side by side 
     <lb/>
     and contested many a political battle, 
     <lb/>
     but they have not been here continu<lb break="no"/>ously, but have been out and in accord<lb break="no"/>ing to the fluctuations of public opinion. 
     <lb/>
     I came here fourteen years ago, and I 
     <lb/>
     only see one hon. member (Mr. Kerr) 
     <lb/>
     who has been here continuously since 
     <lb/>
     that period except myself This proves 
     <lb/>
     the uncertainty of public opinion, and 
     <lb/>
     we cannot tell what another election 
     <lb/>
     may bring forth. As this question has 
     <lb/>
     now been determined by the people, we 
     <lb/>
     should endeavor, as far as practicable, 
     <lb/>
     to obtain for this country every possible 
     <lb/>
     confession promotive of its interest in 
     <lb/>
     this Confederation. I believed from the 
     <lb/>
      first that this Scheme was fraught with 
     <lb/>
     peril, and I relaxed no effort on my 
     <lb/>
     part to prevent its infliction upon the 
     <lb/>
     country. I do not regret the course I 
     <lb/>
     have taken, although my efforts have 
     <lb/>
     been unavailing. It this Union is pro<lb break="no"/>
        

            <pb n="21" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_021.jpg"/>
         
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">21</fw>


ductive of good, I will share in it. If 
     <lb/>
     on the other hand, it is productive of 
     <lb/>
     evil. I shall be free from the responsibi<lb break="no"/>lity of bringing it upon the country. I 
     <lb/>
     ask hon. members whether they are 
     <lb/>
     prepared to accept the Quebec Scheme. 
     <lb/>I believe a large majority of the people of 
     <lb/>the country are decidedly opposed to that 
     <lb/>Scheme. but i believe as firmly as I be<lb break="no"/>lieve I live that if power is given to De<lb break="no"/>legates to act in conjunction with Dele<lb break="no"/>gates from the other Provinces, no ma<lb break="no"/>terial alterations will be made in the 
     <lb/>Scheme. it is a most extraordinary 
     <lb/>thing that the Government, in moving a 
     <lb/>resolution like this. will not condescend 
     <lb/>to inform the country of the basis upon 
     <lb/>which they intend to proceed. I believe 
     <lb/>the reason' is because they know the 
     <lb/>people of the country are opposed to 
     <lb/> the Quebec scheme. This question will 
     <lb/>affect this country for all time to come, 
     <lb/>and it is important that hon. members 
     <lb/>should bring their minds to consider 
     <lb/>this question free from prejudice, and 
     <lb/> not support a resolution for the more 
     <lb/>purpose of victory. I ask erery hon. 
     <lb/>member here if it was not the duty of 
     <lb/>the Government to give some informa<lb break="no"/>tion of whatthey intend to do? Is it 
     <lb/>enough to state that the Delegates will 
     <lb/>endeavor to obtain better terms if they 
     <lb/>can? Who will be the De egates that 
     <lb/>are to be clothed with this tremen<lb break="no"/>dous power to settle and determine for 
     <lb/>the people of this country what their 
     <lb/>constitution shall be for all time to 
     <lb/>come? Where, in the history of a 
     <lb/>free country. can you find that such 
     <lb/>powers have been given to any indivi<lb break="no"/>duals to determine a Scheme of Union 
     <lb/>so important and so tremendous in its 
     <lb/>consequences as this must be to the 
     <lb/>people ot' this country. without any re<lb break="no"/>ference to the Legislature or people? 
     <lb/>Is it not right that any Scheme of Union to be 
     <lb/>carried out and consummated by an Act of<lb/>the Imperial Parliament. I may, he en<lb break="no"/>tirely in error, and my judgement may be<lb/>erroneous, but it does seem to me to be<lb/>but reasonable that the people of this<lb/>country should have some voice in the 
     <lb/>matter, because it hu net been said that 
     <lb/>the people of the muffin have affirmed 
     <lb/>the Quebec Scheme. I believe a large 
     <lb/>portion of the country are opposed to the 
     <lb/>Scheme in many ofita provisions and fea<lb break="no"/>tures. They have affirmned the principle 
     <lb/>of Union without reference to the Quebec 
     <lb/>Scheme, If then Delegates go home to 
     <lb/>England and am. in conjunction with Dele<lb break="no"/>gates from the other Provinces, is it not 
     <lb/>
  
<cb/>

     right that the people of this Province, who   
     <lb/>
     are so seriouslyto be affected by it, should 
     <lb/>
     have some voics'as to whether the Scheme 
     <lb/>
     they had agreed upon was good or bad ? 
     <lb/>
    Should they not have a right to pass 
     <lb/>judgment'upon it? Therefore the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment have failed in the way in which 
     <lb/>they have put the matter before the House. 
     <lb/>l do not think they have treated the 
     <lb/>House and people right. The Attorney 
     <lb/>General does not say whether he' in<lb break="no"/>tends to have this matter referred to 
     <lb/>the people, or whether he intends to 
     <lb/>have those Delegate go to England 
     <lb/>and there act with other Delegates in 
     <lb/> forming a Scheme of Union which is to 
     <lb/>be imported upon us by an Act of Imperial 
     <lb/>Parliament. (Hon. Mr. Fisher. That is 
     <lb/>the why it is to be done.) That then is 
     <lb/>the power which is proposed to be given 
     <lb/>to the Delegates. I am not going to dis<lb break="no"/>cuss the way in which the Government 
     <lb/>obtained power. but I believe it was by 
     <lb/>unfair means. I think the Governor did 
     <lb/>injustice to his late Council and to the 
     <lb/>country in consulting with members of 
     <lb/>he Opposition. When members of the 
     <lb/>Government went to the Government 
     <lb/>House to consult him. he left them and 
     <lb/>consulted a member of the Opposition, 
     <lb/>who was one of the most determined op<lb break="no"/>ponents oi the Government. These are 
     <lb/>the means by which the present Govern<lb break="no"/>ment obtained power, and the people 
     <lb/>have affirmed their position. They have 
     <lb/>declared against me and my late col<lb break="no"/>leagues; and we await future develop<lb break="no"/>ments to show whether we were right or 
     <lb/>wrong. That the late Government were 
     <lb/>not consuitcd'by the Governor is a fact 
     <lb/>admitted on all sides, but he has been 
     <lb/>sustained because the people were in a 
     <lb/>state of political intoxication; but when 
     <lb/>sober reason comes to exercise its away 
     <lb/>this decision will be reversed ; but in the 
     <lb/>meantime our constitution is gone. Hon. 
     <lb/>members may treat it with leiity. and 
     <lb/>think it a matter of little importance 
     <lb/>whether a man be anti-Confderate or 
     <lb/>Confederate, they ought not to think so 
     <lb/>lightly of it ; pevery. member ought to be 
     <lb/>impressed with the solemnity of this oc<lb break="no"/>casion, because it is a matter of infinite 
     <lb/>importance. If it were a matter affecting 
     <lb/>the country for but ten or twenty years, 
     <lb/>we might treat it with comparative indi<lb break="no"/>ference, but it is binding upon us for 
     <lb/>ever. It is the imperctive duty of every 
     <lb/>men who has a sense of his reponsibility 
     <lb/>to consider .this matter seriously, and not 
     <lb/>loan himself to this or that man when his <lb/>country is in danger. If any men are ani<lb break="no"/>mated by a desire for self-aggrandizement 
     <lb/>in this matter, let me apply to them the 
     <lb/>language of the poet—" Is there not some 
     <lb/>chosen curse, some hidden thunder stirs 
     <lb/>
heaven red with uncommon wrath, to<lb/>
blight the man who owes his greatness to<lb/>
his country's ruin." It has flashed across<lb/>
       

            <cb/>
         
my mind that the judgement of some of<lb/>these men may be blinded by the prospect<lb/>of a large arena where their ambition may<lb/>be gratified. I see in this resolution some<lb/>protection, there is still a hope left. In<lb/>
     
     Nova Scotia the people have never passed 
     <lb/>
     upon this question. If Confederation 
     <lb/>
     should be carried and imposed upon 
     <lb/>
     the people of that Province without their 
     <lb/>
     being appealed to, a flagrant outrage will 
     <lb/>
     have been perpetrated upon them. I have 
     <lb/>
     more confidence inths British Government 
     <lb/>
    any Act of Union can be passed without the 
     <lb/>people of Nova Scotia being appealed to. 
     <lb/>I have been told by Joseph Howe, who 
     <lb/>is admitted to be the greatest statesman 
     <lb/>in the, whole of America, that he saw 
     <lb/>the elements of discord in this Union, 
     <lb/>and he would not support it if they gave 
     <lb/>him the Governorship of India. He 
     <lb/>has fought the battles of the people and 
     <lb/>obtained for them the recognition of all 
     <lb/>their rights under the constitution un<lb break="no"/>der which they live. He has moved 
     <lb/>Nova Scotia from its centre to its cir<lb break="no"/>cumference. It has been promulgated 
     <lb/>throughout the country that Joseph 
     <lb/>Howe is imbecile or crazy. I have 
     <lb/>heard speeches about his mental imbe<lb break="no"/>cility, but I should like to hear them 
     <lb/>make one like I heard him make twelve 
     <lb/>months ago at Detroit. Then he was 
     <lb/>considered the pride of British America, 
     <lb/>but now, because he would not drop in<lb break="no"/>to those Confederation grooves, he is 
     <lb/>anathematizcd. abused, and contumely 
     <lb/>heaped upon his head. It seems the 
     <lb/>custom to abuse those who dare to raise 
     <lb/>their voice in favor of the institutions 
     <lb/>of their country. I have been most 
     <lb/>fearfully abused throughout this con<lb break="no"/>test, because I have had the hardihood 
     <lb/>to stand up to preserve inviolate the in<lb break="no"/>stitutions of the country. The Gover<lb break="no"/>nor has charged me, and he has charged 
     <lb/>his late Council, with taking a paper 
     <lb/>from the file. This was an unwarrant<lb break="no"/>able charge, for we had no access to 
     <lb/>the Council Chamber. He has put it<lb/>torward over this country'that we were 
     <lb/>guilty of felony. because he says we ab<lb break="no"/>stracted from the files of the Council a 
     <lb/>paper which he says ought to have been 
     <lb/>there. That charge was totally un<lb break="no"/>founded. lnstead of accepting our re<lb break="no"/>signation in the usual manner by ask<lb break="no"/>ing us to retain office until our succes<lb break="no"/>sors were appointed, he accepted them 
     <lb/>absolutely, and we ceased to be Execu<lb break="no"/>tive Councillors. The paper was our 
     <lb/>paper, and it never was in our Execu<lb break="no"/>tive Council Chamber. The Governor 
     <lb/>has charged me with telling untruths, 
     <lb/>and these, with other slanders, have 
     <lb/>gone forth to the country. He has ap<lb break="no"/>pealed to his high name and lineage. 
     <lb/>He says the name of Gordon was ever 
     <lb/>a guarantee for truth. When a man is 
     <lb/>
       

            <pb n="22" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_022.jpg"/>
          
<fw type="num">22</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw>

         

      driven to appeal to his name as an ar<lb break="no"/>gument to show why he is right and his 
     <lb/>adversary wrong, he must feel that his 
     <lb/>case is weak. I will show how frail 
     <lb/>his memory was. He said he addressed a 
     <lb/>letter to me, and before handing it to 
     <lb/>me, he put a date to it. The letter 
     <lb/>bears no date at all !  That shows he is 
     <lb/>liable to err. His memory has failed 
     <lb/>him often and often in many material 
     <lb/>points. I could say a great deal, but I 
     <lb/>forbear. I wish to speak respectfully 
     <lb/>of the representative of Her Majesty,<lb/>but he is a man like ourselves, and<lb/>we should have fair play and justice 
     <lb/>front him. In regard to this Delega<lb break="no"/>tion, I do not know when it is to be 
     <lb/>sent, but from indications which I see 
     <lb/>around, and from what I know of the ne<lb break="no"/>cessities of Canada, I think it will not be 
     <lb/>long before it goes. I know the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment of Canada cannot last long as 
     <lb/>it is. The Legislature was not called 
     <lb/>together. Why ? It was not called 
     <lb/>tagether because Confederation was not 
     <lb/>passed in this Province, and that Govern<lb break="no"/>ment was like a rope of sand unless Con<lb break="no"/>federation was carried. I speak, feeling 
     <lb/>that my voice will be entirely powerless ; 
     <lb/>still, I feel it my duty both to myself and 
     <lb/>country, to express my views.  I know 
     <lb/>that the Legislature of Canada was post<lb break="no"/>poned from time to time, and their Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment undertook to dictate to us when 
     <lb/>our Legislature should meet. The ne<lb break="no"/>cessity of Canada has given birth to the 
     <lb/>whole  scheme, and I can prove this by 
     <lb/>her leading statesmen, Mr. McGee and 
     <lb/>others. This measure did not emanate 
     <lb/>from the British Government, but they 
     <lb/>have approved of the Scheme, and are 
     <lb/>committed to it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     When I examined this resolution to 
     <lb/>
    appoint delegates, I found in it what, to 
     <lb/>a certain extent, relieved my mind. I<lb/>believe Prince Edward Island will not 
     <lb/>come into this scheme of Union, neither 
     <lb/>will Newfoundland. By the terms of 
     <lb/>this resolution, the delegates, unless 
     <lb/>met in London by other Delegates from 
     <lb/>all these Provinces, will have no power 
     <lb/>to make an arrangement. Unless this 
     <lb/>delegation be full they have no power 
     <lb/>to act. This is intended by the hon. 
     <lb/>mover. It is not necessary to argue 
     <lb/>that if you delegate men to act with 
     <lb/>other men representing other interests, 
     <lb/>their power ceases unless met by those 
     <lb/>they were appointed to meet. This 
     <lb/>Quebec Scheme was prepared upon the 
     <lb/>assumption that all these Lower Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces are to come in. It has been said 
     <lb/>that the interests of these Lower Pro<lb break="no"/>vinces are identical, and they would 
     <lb/>unite for the protection of the interests 
     <lb/>of the Maritime Provinces. If Prince 
     <lb/>Edward Island and Newfoundland are 
     <lb/>not embraced within this confederation, 
     <lb/>the arguments are weakened and fail, 
     <lb/>
   

            <cb/>
       

     because the influence of the Maritime 
     <lb/>Provinces is reduced to that extent.<lb/>Therefore I am glad the Government<lb/>have said they are unwilling to go into<lb/>confederation unless all the other<lb/>Maritime Provinces enter into Union at<lb/>the same time. That is the only inter<lb break="no"/>pretation that can be put upon the reso<lb break="no"/>lution. It is not necessary for me to<lb/>argue that point, for any person will<lb/>understand that if an agent is appointed<lb/>to act with other agents, that agent can<lb/>not act without the other agents acting<lb/>with him. Unless the House restrain<lb/>these delegates when they proceed to<lb/>England, we will have the Quebec<lb/>Scheme upon us. No doubt but it will<lb/>be the authors of the scheme who will<lb/>be sent, and these gentlemen have de<lb break="no"/>clared that if they get a better scheme<lb/>they will take it, if not they will take<lb/>the Quebec Scheme. As they have<lb/>made this declaration before going<lb/>there, do you suppose the Canadian<lb/>politicians will give them a better when<lb/>they know they will accept the present ?<lb/>If you want to buy a farm you will not<lb/>say to the owner, if you will not take<lb/>£450 I will give you £500. The dele<lb break="no"/>gates have been telling the people, that<lb/>under the Quebec Scheme the Lower<lb/>Provinces have a decided advantage<lb/>over the Canadas, how then can our<lb/>delegates ask for better terms than the<lb/>terms which they have said gave them<lb/>such an advantage over the Canadas.<lb/>If we are going to have confederation,<lb/>we should do everything we can to ob<lb break="no"/>tain a scheme that will be an advantage<lb/>to the Province and not a destruction<lb/>to it. If this confederation is to be ac<lb break="no"/>complished, I shall move a resolu ion<lb/>restraining the power of these delegates,<lb/>which, I think, will commend itself to<lb/>the favorable consideration of a ma<lb break="no"/>jority of the House. If the desire of<lb/>the Government is to obtain a good<lb/>scheme of Union, they will not object<lb/>to receiving instruction from this<lb/>House. If the delegates proceed to<lb/>England with these instructions given<lb/>by this House, and the Canadians find<lb/>that the delegates have no power to<lb/>consent to a Union, unless that scheme<lb/>embraces certain provisions necessary<lb/>for the country, they, rather than not<lb/>have confederation—for I know their<lb/>anxiety for it—will make those conces<lb break="no"/>sions. If our delegation goes home<lb/>without those instructions, you agree<lb/>to the scheme, believing it to be a good<lb/>scheme, and you need not seek any<lb/>amendment. Then, when this Union<lb/>is brought about, how utterly this Par<lb break="no"/>liament will fade away. It will not be<lb/>worthy of the best minds of our country<lb/>to come here, for this Assembly will<lb/>dwindle down to a mere municipality.<lb/>I trust I may be mistaken, and that the<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
      

     great interests of the country may be<lb/>advanced ; but these are my views. I<lb/>do not believe there are ten men here<lb/>who will not resign their seats at once<lb/>if confederation is carried. Whether I<lb/>shall make any effort to go to Ottawa<lb/>remains in the future. It has been no<lb/>advantage to me to be a member of this<lb/>House, but, on the contrary, it has been<lb/>a pecuniary less. I have been a mem<lb break="no"/>ber of the House for fourteen years, and<lb/>one-half of that time has been given to<lb/>the public for which I have practically<lb/>received nothing. There are others<lb/>here who have given their time to the<lb/>public without receiving an equivalent.<lb/>My hon. friend Mr. Kerr has never re<lb break="no"/>ceived a dollar ; what object can he have<lb/>in continuing a member of a Legislature<lb/>which would have no more to do than<lb/>the corporation of the City of St. John.<lb/>He would not remain here an hour.<lb/>I shall feel it necessary to express my<lb/>views upon the action of the Legislative<lb/>Council. I predicted from the beginning<lb/>that this scheme was prepared with all<lb/>the elements necessary to give it vitali<lb break="no"/>ty. Out of the Legislative Council<lb/>there are ten members to go to Ottawa.<lb/>We all have our ambitious feelings ; if<lb/>fifteen of the members of this House<lb/>were to be provided with seats<lb/>at Ottawa for life, do you not<lb/>think it would have an influence<lb/>upon the vote of this House ?<lb/>We know that personal interest blinds<lb/>the eyes and warps the judgment, and the<lb/>person under its influence is not con<lb break="no"/>scious of it. There is no doubt but that<lb/>the deliberations of the Legislative Coun<lb break="no"/>cil have been influenced by the fact that<lb/>ten of their number are to be appointed<lb/>to seats in the Legislative Council at Ot<lb break="no"/>tawa for life. That makes ten vacancies<lb/>for ten hon. members of this House, if<lb/>those seats are worthy of their ambition.<lb/>This is part of the machinery to facilitate<lb/>the passage of the Scheme through the<lb/>Legislature. It was agreed at the con<lb break="no"/>ference at Quebec that it was to be passed<lb/>through the Legislature without any ap<lb break="no"/>peal to the people. (Cries of no, no.)<lb/>Whether there was a positive agreement<lb/>I know not, but there was an understand<lb break="no"/>ing that it was to be done if practicable.<lb/>(No ; no.) Why then have they attempt<lb break="no"/>ed to do so in Nova Scotia ? Why did<lb/>not they proceed on the same principle<lb/>there as here, instead of pressing it<lb/>through the Legislature without any ap<lb break="no"/>peal to the people at all ? Did they enter<lb/>into an agreement different from the line<lb/>of action to be adopted by the Delegates 
     <lb/>in this Province ? You would suppose<lb/>they would act unitedly in the means and<lb/>agencies employed to work out their pur<lb break="no"/>pose. Therefore I consider that if they<lb/>had thought it possible to put that mea<lb break="no"/>sure through our Legislature they would<lb/>have done so. I shall take the liberty<lb/>
     

            <pb n="23" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1866-06-26_Page_023.jpg"/>
         
<fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> <fw type="num">23</fw>

         

     calling the attention of the House to <choice><sic>se<lb break="no"/>varal</sic><corr>several</corr></choice> provisions in the Quebec Scheme,<lb/>and state my objections to them ; whether<lb/>it will have any influence upon the Dele<lb break="no"/>gates I know not ; but first let us hear<lb/>what are the opinion of Canadian statesmen<lb/>on this Scheme, and how far the people of<lb/>this country may expect concessions, and<lb/>get better terms than those <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> <lb/>the Scheme. Mr. D'Arcy M'Gee in de<lb break="no"/>scribing the Scheme (Mr. Tilley, When)<lb/>When the Parliament of Canada approved<lb/>of the Scheme, and asked Her Majesty<lb/>to bring it into effect by Imperial Legisla<lb break="no"/>tion. (Mr. Smith then quoted from<lb/>speeches delivered by Messrs. D'Arcy<lb/>McGee and John McDonald, to show the<lb/>Scheme was unalterable.) We have also<lb/>the testimony of Mr. Brown, and Mr<lb/>Galt that it cannot be altered. When<lb/>Mr. Allan and I were in England Mr.<lb/>Cardwell intimated that some altera ions<lb/>might take place. We asked him could<lb/>representation by population be altered ?<lb/>No. Could the representation in the<lb/>Legislative Council be altered ? No.<lb/>Could the provision of eighty cents per<lb/>head be altered ? No. Thus we found<lb/>no material part of the Scheme could be<lb/>changed, and any delegation which goes<lb/>home will have to accept the Quebec<lb/>Scheme in its entirety, unless they re<lb break="no"/>ceive instructions from the people of the<lb/>country. If they go there clothed with<lb/>restrictive power, which says you may go<lb/>to a certain extent and no farther ; then,<lb/>when the Canadian Delegates know that<lb/>they cannot deviate from the letter of<lb/>their instructions, they may consent to<lb/>some alterations.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The debate was then adjourned until<lb/>to-morrow. Mr. Smith to resume at half-<lb break="yes"/>past nine.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House then went into Committee<lb/>on " A Bill relating to the administration<lb/>of Justice in Equity," which created<lb/>some discussion, when progress was re<lb break="no"/>ported and leave asked to sit again.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House was then adjourned until<lb/>9 a. m. to-morrow.
<lb/>
               <lb/>
            </p>
            <p rendition="simple:right">T. P. D.<lb/>
            </p>

<!-- GL, 2018-03-20, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->

           <!-- <p>WEDNESDAY, JUNE 29th.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The House met pursuant to the adjourn<lb break="no"/>ment at 9 a. m.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>A number of Bills received a second<lb/>reading.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bills passed through Committee<lb/>yesterday were read a third time, and<lb/>passed the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Leave was granted to bring in certain<lb/>Bills, and petitions were received in sup<lb break="no"/>port of the same.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. CAIE gave notice of a motion ask<lb break="no"/>ing for the Correspondence which had<lb/>taken place on the appointment of Chief<lb/>Justice Ritchie, and also for all Corres<lb break="no"/>pondence which had passed between His 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     Excellency the Lieutenant Governor, and 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Justice Wilmot on the same subject. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> asked if it was the inten<lb break="no"/>tion of the Government to submit the 
     <lb/>correspondence which had taken place 
     <lb/>between His Excellency the Lieutenant 
     <lb/>Governor, and His late Council, with re<lb break="no"/>spect to their resignation. without 
     <lb/>  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. Mr. TILLEY would give an 
     <lb/>answer to-morrow 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Mr. CAIE asked for the suspension of 
     <lb/>
     the rule, so that he might have leave to 
     <lb/>
     bring in a Bill to erect a portion of the 
     <lb/>
     Parish of Wellington in the County of 
     <lb/>
     Kent, into a separate town or Parish. He 
     <lb/>
     had fyled the certificate of publication 
     <lb/>
     with the Clerk of the House at last ses<lb break="no"/>sion, and was prepared to bring in a Bill, 
     <lb/>
     but having received an intimation that a 
     <lb/>
     petition would be forwarded against the 
     <lb/>
     Bill, he had withheld it till he was too 
     <lb/>
     late to bring it in, on account of the pro<lb break="no"/>rogation. On enquiry he found that the 
     <lb/>
     Clerk had lost or mislaid the certificate, 
     <lb/>
     and unless the rule was suspended he 
     <lb/>
     would be precluded from bringing in the 
     <lb/>
     Bill this Session. He was now pre<lb break="no"/>pared to submit the petition against the 
     <lb/>
     passage of the Bill as soon as it was read 
     <lb/>
     a first time. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Several members opposed the suspen<lb break="no"/>sion of the rule on the ground that it was 
     <lb/>a matter of no immediate importance, and 
     <lb/>as there was a petition against it, it was 
     <lb/>evident the matter was not considered by 
     <lb/>the people necessary to be hastily carried. 
     <lb/>The rule however, was suspended and 
     <lb/>leave granted, when the Bill was read a 
     <lb/>first time and the petition presented. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:JOHN1">Mr. JOHNSON</persName> moved a ryder to the 
     <lb/>Bill relating to offences against the army 
     <lb/>and navy, on its third reading, to the 
     <lb/>effect that nothing in said Act should be 
     <lb/>construed to affect any action now in pro<lb break="no"/>gress under the old Act, or to affect the 
     <lb/>penalty already adjudged to such offen<lb break="no"/>ders. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>At 10 o'clock the order of the day was 
     <lb/>taken up. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>DELEGATION ON UNION. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName> resumed—I have asked 
     <lb/>the hon. Provincial Secretary if it is the 
     <lb/>intention of the Government to submit 
     <lb/>the Correspondence on resignation of the 
     <lb/>late Gonernment, and what it means. I 
     <lb/>do not know, but I am told that he will 
     <lb/>answer to-morrow. I am aware that I 
     <lb/>can obtain the papers by motion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>HON. Mr. TILLEY—You asked if the 
     <lb/>Government would submit them without 
     <lb/>a motion, and I replied that I would give 
     <lb/>you an answer to-morrow. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—Well then, I now ask 
     <lb/>for an answer from the Attorney General 
     <lb/>to the question I put to him yesterday, 
     <lb/>whether any despatches have passed be<lb break="no"/>tween the Colonial Secretary and His 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>Excellency relating to the resignation of<lb/>the late Government, and if they are to<lb/>be submitted to the House.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:FISH1">Hon. Mr. FISHER</persName>—The Governor on<lb break="no"/>ly returned from Woodstock last<lb/>and I have not yet on the subject<lb/>will see him during the day and give<lb/>the necessary information.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Mr. SMITH</persName>—The Government do not<lb/>appear disposed to be very courteous in<lb/>their replies to questions for information<lb/>with regard to public papers, and yet they<lb/>expect respect to be shown to their wishes<lb/>in the pushing on of the public business.<lb/>I suppose I must submit to the explana<lb break="no"/>tions they give.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>When I closed my remarks yesterday,<lb/>I stated that I believed that it was most<lb/>important that the House should have<lb/>time for the consideration of so impor<lb break="no"/>tant a matter as is involved in the Resolu<lb break="no"/>tions before the House. I believe that it<lb/>is the solemn duty of hon. members to<lb/>bring their judgments to bear on this<lb/>great question, and deliberately and calm<lb break="no"/>ly arrive at conclusions that will be sat<lb break="no"/>isfactory to the people of this Province,<lb/>I stated yesterday, and again repeat it,<lb/>that as the matter now stands, and from<lb/>information which I have obtained, the<lb/>Quebec Scheme, and that alone, without<lb/>any alteration, will be decided on as the<lb/>plan of uniting these Colonies. I ask<lb/>hon. members around the boards of this<lb/>House if they are ready to adopt that<lb/>Scheme ? Many of them have been re<lb break="no"/>turned by constituencies to support a plan<lb/>of Union on a new basis : I would ask<lb/>them if they were sent to pass the Que<lb break="no"/>bec Scheme ? Were they sent to go it<lb/>blind ? to leave it entirely in the hands<lb/>of the delegates to say what the<lb/>terms of Union should be ? Or were they<lb/>sent here to exercise their judgments in<lb/>regard to the terms of any new plan that<lb/>may be submitted ? Were they sent here<lb/>to delegate their power to two or three<lb/>men who are committed to the terms of<lb/>the Quebec Scheme ? I would ask if<lb/>hon. members are ready to lay aside their<lb/>right of judging and passing upon the<lb/>plan of Union proposed to be adopted ?<lb/>This is what the Government ask us to<lb/>do ; to divest ourselves of our powers of<lb/>judgment, to delegate all our powers to<lb/>delegates—we are not told how many—<lb/>who are to meet delegates from other<lb/>Provinces in London, and there frame a<lb/>Scheme binding on this country for all<lb/>time to come, and the people are to know<lb/>nothing at all about it. I believe that the<lb/>majority of the people of this Province<lb/>are opposed to the Quebec Scheme. It<lb/>was put before them that new negotia<lb break="no"/>tions were to be opened, and they, un<lb break="no"/>der this impression, sent men here to see<lb/>to it that the terms proposed should be<lb/>such as would be for the interest of the<lb/>
            </p>-->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>