<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="lgNBLA_1865-05-20"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgNBLAssem">Legislative Assembly</name>, <date when="1865-05-20">20 May 1865</date>, New Brunswick Confederation Debates</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:lgNBLA">
          
               <title>Debates of the House of Assembly of the Province of New Brunswick; Session of 1865</title>.
                    


     <date when="1865"/>.  



          <pubPlace>St. John, New Brunswick</pubPlace>: <publisher>George W. Day</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="78" to="80"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-20_Page_0078.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-20_Page_0079.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/NB_LA_1865-05-20_Page_0080.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-02-21">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-02-21">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-20_Page_0078">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-20_Page_0078.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-20_Page_0079">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-20_Page_0079.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="NB_LA_1865-05-20_Page_0080">
         <graphic url="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-20_Page_0080.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="78" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-20_Page_0078.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="num">78</fw> <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1866.</fw> 
    

<!-- GL, 2018-02-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the preceding debate day --> 
   
           <!-- <p>
     section which refers the question back to 
     <lb/>
     the people. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>Progress reported. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. SMITH brought in a Bill re<lb break="no"/>lating to Railroads. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. CONNELL brought in a Bill relating 
     <lb/>to marriage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>House adjourned until 9 a.m., Monday. 
     <lb/>T.P. D. 
     <lb/>
            </p>-->
   


            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     SATURDAY MORNING, May 20, 1865. 
     <lb/>
            </head>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:COST1">Mr. COSTIGAN</persName> moved the House into 
     <lb/>
     Committee of the Whole on a Bill relat<lb break="no"/>ing to Attorneys and Barristers of the 
     <lb/>Supreme Court. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. Lewis in the Chair. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The Bill was agreed to. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Hon. Mr. ALLEN</persName> moved the House in<lb break="no"/>to Committee of the Whole on a BILL 
     <lb/>RELATING TO THE MILITIA.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Sections 1 to 12 were read and passed 
     <lb/>
    without discussion. On the reading of 
     <lb/>Sec.13, which provides that "the com<lb break="no"/>manding officer of every volunteer corps 
     <lb/>shall receive a sum not exceeding $2 
     <lb/>per head for every effective member of 
     <lb/>such corps, to provide for the proper 
     <lb/>care of arms and accoutrements, and to 
     <lb/>meet the expanses of the corps. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:CUDL1">Mr. CUDLIP</persName> suggested that it might be 
     <lb/>well to have some clause inserted to 
     <lb/>prevent any officer from putting into his 
     <lb/>own pocket any surplus funds that 
     <lb/>might not be expended for the purposes 
     <lb/>enumerated, but pay it back. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Hon. Mr. ALLEN</persName> explained that there 
     <lb/>would be no need of any thing of this 
     <lb/>kind, as no officer would receive any 
     <lb/>money till he had made up an estimate 
     <lb/>to show what amount the corps would 
     <lb/>need. The section passed. as did also 
     <lb/>14, 15 and 16. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>On Sections 17 and 18 there was some 
     <lb/>scattered discussion as to the volunteer 
     <lb/>corps being exempt from the payment 
     <lb/>of taxes to the extent of six dollars, 
     <lb/>after which they were struck out; 
     <lb/>but on the suggestion of Hon. Mr. 
     <lb/>WILMOT, supported by the Hon. Mr.<lb/>SMITH, and others, they were re<lb break="no"/>considered and after being amended<lb/>were passed. The alterations made<lb/>were, the striking out of Class B, as ex<lb break="no"/>empted and permitting volunteers to be 
     <lb/>clear or paying City, County and Parish 
     <lb/>rates and taxes, to the amount of six 
     <lb/>dollars.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Section 19 was passed without amend<lb break="no"/>ment, but 200 was entirely withdrawn, 
     <lb/>
     and the following substituted by the hon. 
     <lb/>
     mover of the Bill. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "20. The articles of engagement of 
     <lb/>
     all volunteer corps shall be subject to 
     <lb/>the approval of the Commander-in-Chief:<lb/>
     and such volunteer corps shall be drilled 
     <lb/>
     and exercised at such times in each year, 
     <lb/>
     (not exceeding ten days) and at such 
     <lb/>
     places as the Commander-in-Chief may 
     <lb/>
     order; and such corps shall be subject 
     <lb/>
     to inspection from time to time by such 
     <lb/>
    person or persons as shall be appointed 
     <lb/>by the Commander-in-Chief for that pur<lb break="no"/>pose."<lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
    

            <p>
     "21. The men of Class B and Class 
     <lb/>
     C, of the active militia, shall be 
     <lb/>carefully enrolled, and shall, when<lb/>not exempted, assemble for muster<lb/>upon one day in each year, at such<lb/>time and place as the command<lb break="no"/>ing officer of each battalion may direct<lb/>to each company therein, interfering as<lb/>little as possible with seed time and<lb/>harvest; but no person shall be required<lb/>to travel more than twelve miles from<lb/>his usual place of residence to attend<lb/>such must."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName> — I am opposed to the<lb/>
         

            <cb/>
         

     one day muster, as I consider that it re<lb break="no"/>sults in no benefit to the people. Ex 
     <lb/>
     perience has shown that it is a ridiculou 
     <lb/>
     farce to call out men and drill them for 
     <lb/>
     a few hours on one day in a year. The 
     <lb/>
     <hi rendition="simple:italic">Morning Freeman</hi> for September 24th. 
     <lb/>
     1864, in speaking of the last general 
     <lb/>muster says:<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     " Now that these musters are over for 
     <lb/>
     the season, would it not be well for the 
     <lb/>
     sensible men of the community to ask 
     <lb/>
     themselves " what has been effect<lb break="no"/>ed, or what can be effected by com<lb break="no"/>pelling three or four thousand men in 
     <lb/>
     the City and Portland, to leave their 
     <lb/>
     business for one day in the year to play 
     <lb/>
     fool and be the laughing stock of the 
     <lb/>
     idlers who go to see them on the Bar<lb break="no"/>rack Square or elsewhere? Is the 
     <lb/>
     strength or the efficiency of the militia 
     <lb/>
     force promoted in the slightested degree 
     <lb/>
     by such a waste of time? Would St. 
     <lb/>
     John be better able to resist attack after 
     <lb/>
     this muster and drill than it was be<lb break="no"/>fore." We believe the effect of these 
     <lb/>
     miserable displays must be to create auch 
     <lb/>
     a dislike of militia service, as must do 
     <lb/>
     material mischief should it ever be ne<lb break="no"/>cessary to set the militia to work in ear<lb break="no"/>nest. The Legislature never intended 
     <lb/>
     that those ridiculous attempts at drilling 
     <lb/>
     men in an hour or two on one day of the 
     <lb/>
     year should be made, and the law gives 
     <lb/>
     no authority to the commanding officers 
     <lb/>
     to expose the men in such a way to ridi<lb break="no"/>cule. We believe that even the muster 
     <lb/>
     is a waste of time: It is for the mer<lb break="no"/>chants and mechanics of the city le de<lb break="no"/>termine for themselves whether such 
     <lb/>
     proceedings shall be repeated." 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>This is sufficient to show the useless<lb break="no"/>ness of the one day muster All that is 
     <lb/>necessary is to enroll the names of the 
     <lb/>men, to see what is really the available 
     <lb/>strength of the country; but to give the 
     <lb/>power into the hands of the command<lb break="no"/>ing officer to call out men simply to play 
     <lb/>the fool is of no use whatever. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Hon. Mr. ALLEN</persName> — The late Bill pro<lb break="no"/>vided that men should be called out and 
     <lb/>drilled. This merely provides that they 
     <lb/>shall be mustered to answer to their 
     <lb/>names. Whether the people in St. John 
     <lb/>acted as stated in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Freeman</hi> or not, I 
     <lb/>do not know, but here, and in many 
     <lb/>other parts of the country, they acted 
     <lb/>with propriety. ln this Bill there is a 
     <lb/>dispensing clause which will give the 
     <lb/>power into the hands of the Commander- 
     <lb break="yes"/>in-Chief to call them out only if it is<lb/>needed. As to the people not being 
     <lb/>wlllin to be called out, they muster 
     <lb/>enough at races and exhibitions, and why 
     <lb/>should they not assemble when the pur<lb break="no"/>pose is a legal one? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SUTT1">Mr. SUTTON</persName>. — The men turned out 
     <lb/>
    well in Northumberland. and we had 
     <lb/>His Excellency there, who expressed 
     <lb/>himself as very much pleased with their<lb/>orderly appearance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:MCCL1">Mr. McCLELLAN</persName>. — I cannot agree<lb/>with hon. members who are anxious to<lb/> 
               <lb/>keep up with this absurdity. Every man<lb/>who turns out on the general drill day is a<lb/>dollar lost to the labour of the country,<lb/>and I am persuaded that it entails a<lb/>great amount of taxation on the people<lb/>without resulting in any benefit.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:HILL1">Mr. HILL</persName>. — I agree with the hon. mem<lb break="no"/>ber for Albert. I think it one of the great<lb break="no"/>est farce that ever came before the peo<lb break="no"/>ple. It does not answer the purpose for <lb/>which it was intended. At St. Stephen,<lb/>at the last inspection, there was a great<lb/>deal of military feeling shown; at least<lb/>there was a large amount of fighting on<lb/>men's private [...]. After 11 o'clock<lb/>those who did not belong to the temperance<lb/>
       

            <cb/>
          

     societies went in for drinking fight<lb break="no"/>ing, and before night the town presented 
     <lb/>
     in appearance very much like Doneybrook 
     <lb/>
     Fair; there were black eyes, and noses 
     <lb/>
     hat enquired the way over one or the 
     <lb/>
     other shoulder, and the whole thing par<lb break="no"/>took of the nature of a civil war. I think 
     <lb/>
    the chief tendency of a one day muster is 
     <lb/>to demoralize, and therefore I am oppos<lb break="no"/>ed to it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:LEWI1">Mr. LEWIS</persName>, <persName ref="pers:WILL1">Mr. WILLISTON</persName> and <persName ref="pers:GILL1">Hon. 
     <lb/>
     Mr. GILMOR</persName> took similar views, showing 
     <lb/>
     the loss to the country in labor, the dis<lb break="no"/>advantages of having to shut down mills 
     <lb/>
    and other places of business, and the de<lb break="no"/>moralizing effect of the proceedings of the 
     <lb/>day . They also expressed the opinion 
     <lb/>that the enrollment could as effectually be 
     <lb/>made by a Captain and Adjutant going 
     <lb/>through the respective districts and learn<lb break="no"/>ing who were fit for service. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Mr. BOYD</persName> said the day could not be 
     <lb/>
     dispensed with, as the commanding officer 
     <lb/>
     would not be able to get any accurate re<lb break="no"/>turns without it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName> said he believed the 
     <lb/>
     muster was no good; that it was demor<lb break="no"/>alizing and a burden to the country, but 
     <lb/>
     as there was a dispensing clause he should 
     <lb/>
     support it. He did not think the power 
     <lb/>
     would be need except in cases where it 
     <lb/>
    became absolutely necessary. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
<div type="section">
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     AFTERNOON SESSION — 3 P.M. 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CUDL1">Mr. CUDLIP</persName>. — I agree with hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers who think a day of general muster is 
     <lb/>
     not required; with think my constituents will 
     <lb/>
    not accord with this section of the Bill, 
     <lb/>and although I am not prepared to offer 
     <lb/>any amendments, yet I wish it set ou re<lb break="no"/>cord that I am not favorable to this one 
     <lb/>day muster, as it interferes with the busi<lb break="no"/>ness of the country. I would rather see 
     <lb/>some such an arrangement as they had in 
     <lb/>old times, when training day was com<lb break="no"/>bined with fairs and agricultural exhibi<lb break="no"/>tions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName>. — I agree with the hon. 
     <lb/>
     member ror St. John, that this one day's 
     <lb/>
     muster is of no practical use; the mills 
     <lb/>
     have to be stoped, all kinds of work sus<lb break="no"/>pended, and the day is in reality wasted. 
     <lb/>More than this, I do not believe in dele<lb break="no"/>gating the power to call them out to the 
     <lb/>Commander-in-Chief.  
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:WILM1">Hon. Mr. WILMOT</persName> . — I was one of the 
     <lb/>seven who opposed the suspension of the 
     <lb/>old militia law and I did so as I believed 
     <lb/>that every man from eighteen to sixty 
     <lb/>should be enrolled, and be willing, in case 
     <lb/>of need, to turn out to defend his home 
     <lb/>and hearth. In the United States they 
     <lb/>had little or no organization, and one day 
     <lb/>
  
     they woke up and found they had to mu<lb break="no"/>ster upon on of the most tremendous wars 
     <lb/>
     the world ever saw. I hope we shall not 
     <lb/>
     pursue the same course, and in the day 
     <lb/>
     of trouble find ourselves in the same posi<lb break="no"/>tion as they twere before the war. I do 
     <lb/>
    not look upon the turing out for one day 
     <lb/>as a burden to the country. It is simply<lb/>giving the people a holiday, just such as 
     <lb/>we had on the 4th of June, the old King's 
     <lb/>birthday.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Mr. BOYD</persName>. — If the idea of hon. mem<lb break="no"/>bers who oppose this section were carried 
     <lb/>out we might just as well sweep the 
     <lb/>whole Militia Bill from the Statue Book. 
     <lb/>If a day is not appointed for the muster<lb break="no"/>ing and enrollment of the men, no return<lb/>could be made of the available force of<lb/>the country, an no captain would be will<lb break="no"/>ing to go from house to house to obtain<lb/>his roll without being handsomely paid<lb/>for his trouble.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. — It is said the day is not<lb/>set apart for drill, but merely to get the<lb/>
men to <unclear reason="illegible">[?]</unclear> It is a ri<lb break="no"/>
       

            <pb n="79" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-20_Page_0079.jpg"/>
          
     <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> <fw type="num">79</fw> 
  

     diculous idea to make men leave their 
     <lb/>
     work and travel, as many would have to, 
     <lb/>
     twelve miles, just for this purpose. It is 
     <lb/>
    well known that the day is one of drunk 
     <lb/>enness and frolic. It seems as though the 
     <lb/>chief object was to let a few officers parade 
     <lb/>'round and show their uniforms. The 
     <lb/>whole thing puts me in mind of the lines 
     <lb/>of some poet— 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    <quote rendition="tccd:blockquote">
   
            <p>
     "Man, vain man, when clothed in brief 
     <lb/>
     authority 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Cuts such fantastic tricks before High 
     <lb/>Heaven<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>As makes an angel weep."<lb/>
            </p>
    </quote>
    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WETM1">Mr. WETMORE</persName> referred to the unfair 
     <lb/>
     manner in which the appointments had been 
     <lb/>
     made, as was evident from the fact that 
     <lb/>
     he held an ensign's commission in the 
     <lb/>
     Westmorland Militia since April 1842,— 
     <lb/>
     from the way in which his valuable ser<lb break="no"/>vices had been overlooked one would 
     <lb/>
     imagine it was dated the 1st of that 
     <lb/>
     month. He did not think that one day 
     <lb/>
     muster was a burden to the people, and 
     <lb/>
     as to their behaving unseemly at the last 
     <lb/>
     general drill in St. John, he could assure 
     <lb/>
     the House that notwithstanding the ar<lb break="no"/>ticle in the <hi rendition="simple:italic">Freeman</hi>, he had been credibly 
     <lb/>
     informed that the men behaved them<lb break="no"/>selves with h. becoming dignity, and exhi<lb break="no"/>bited an earnest desire to become profi<lb break="no"/>cient in their exercises. He did not see 
     <lb/>
     why the Commander-in-Chief should not 
     <lb/>
     have the power to call them our; if he 
     <lb/>
     had not the power, who should have it? 
            </p>

<p>
     The section then passed, as did also 22 
     <lb/>and 23.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     Section 24 : " The Commander-in- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     Chief shall by General Order designate 
     <lb/>
     the Battalions from which the companies  
     <lb/>
    so to be exercised shall be drawn, and 
     <lb/>shall appoint the time for the assembling 
     <lb/>and dismissal of such companies; but no 
     <lb/>company shall be compelled to serve for 
     <lb/>a longer period than twenty  eight days, 
     <lb/>and no Battalion shall be obliged to fur<lb break="no"/>nish more than one such company in each 
     <lb/>year. " 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName>. — I would ask if this Com<lb break="no"/>mittee is going to endorse by their action 
     <lb/>
     the principle of compulsory draft, which 
     <lb/>
     this section contemplates?  If the House 
     <lb/>
     pass it, I must before they do so, enter 
     <lb/>
     my solemn protest against it. I am sure 
     <lb/>
     the country wil not endorse it. That the 
     <lb/>
    men from the different companies shall 
     <lb/>be <hi rendition="simple:italic">compelled</hi> to have their avocations 
     <lb/>and go to some place, and there be drilled 
     <lb/>for twenty-eight days is a preposterous 
     <lb/>idea. And what benefit will it be? 
     <lb/>Will twenty-eight days suffice to 
     <lb/>make them proficient? for by this 
     <lb/>law the same men will not be taken each 
     <lb/>year, but sixty men each year til the 
     <lb/>whole have been drilled. Why, in a time 
     <lb/>of peace, are our men to be dragged from 
     <lb/>their homes and families and treated in 
     <lb/>this why? It seems that the idea pre<lb break="no"/>vails that men will volunteer. I don't 
     <lb/>believe a man will do so in Westmorland, 
     <lb/>for they are agriculturalists, and cannot 
     <lb/>afford to lose the time. they won't go, 
     <lb/>not because they are disloyal, but because 
     <lb/>they will not, except in a prospect of war,<lb/>agree to be drafted into a military camp<lb/>
               <lb/>against their will.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.—I don't think my<lb/>hon. colleague represents the whole peo<lb break="no"/>ple of Westmorland, although he seems<lb/>to imagine that he, and he alone, does re<lb break="no"/>present them. I think I have as much<lb/>of the confidence of the people there as<lb/>my hon. colleague; I have had some op<lb break="no"/>portunity of knowing what their views<lb/>are on various matters during the past few<lb/>months, and I am prepared to say that<lb/>
        
            <cb/>
         

     the people of Westmorlandare willing to 
     <lb/>
     do what is best for the good of the coun<lb break="no"/>try. I take the ground that it is neces<lb break="no"/>sary to have some power to enforce the 
     <lb/>law, and on that ground I wish the sec<lb break="no"/>tion to pass. My hon. colleague seems 
     <lb/>the only man who is really opposed to it, 
     <lb/>and he sems to be determined to oppose 
     <lb/>everything; he is the most querrulous 
     <lb/>man I ever saw in my life. He says if 
     <lb/>the law pass the people of Westmorland 
     <lb/>won't stand it. I say that they are a law 
     <lb/>abiding people and will. lt will be for 
     <lb/>the House to determine which is correct. 
     <lb/>When they look at the position of affairs, 
     <lb/>to the fact that delegates have gone to 
     <lb/>England on a military mission, that our 
     <lb/>sister colony of Nova Scotia is alive to 
     <lb/>the necessity of having the militia placed 
     <lb/>on a good footing, I am sure the people 
     <lb/>of Westmorland as well as every other 
     <lb/>section of the Province, will yield a cheer<lb break="no"/>ful obedience to the provisions of the 
     <lb/>Bill. What object could the Govern<lb break="no"/>ment or the framer of the Bill have in 
     <lb/>view în the insertion of this section if not 
     <lb/>the good of the country? 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WILM1">Hon. Mr. WILMOT</persName>. — The hon. member 
     <lb/>
     for Westmorland (Mr. Gilbert) makes a 
     <lb/>
     great time about men being taken from 
     <lb/>
    their homes, but if a man does not want 
     <lb/>to go it is easy to find a substitute. I 
     <lb/>never yet saw the time when I could not 
     <lb/>get the services of a man for £3 10s. for 
     <lb/>twenty-eight days — that is fifty cent a 
     <lb/>day and his food, and this will be provid<lb break="no"/>ed. No one need complain, for it will be 
     <lb/>easy to get substitutes at that rate. if a 
     <lb/>man's business is so that he cannot leave 
     <lb/>himself. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOYD1">Mr. BOYD</persName>.—I do not think that there 
     <lb/>
     will be any need to resort to the draft, as 
     <lb/>
     I believe there will be plenty of volun<lb break="no"/>teers to form the camp. The only diffi<lb break="no"/>culty will be that there may be too many; 
     <lb/>
     the inducements to volunteer are so great. 
     <lb/>
     for I see by section 27 that " any militia<lb break="no"/>man serving in such company, either vol<lb break="no"/>untarily or by draft, shall be exempt from 
     <lb/>
     similar services during the period of ten 
     <lb/>
     years." Such an offer as this was not made 
     <lb/>
     in old times, and I think no better plan 
     <lb/>
     could be adopted than by taking men out 
     <lb/>
     of class B to fill up the quota wanted for 
     <lb/>
     drill and exercise. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Hon. Mr. ALLEN</persName>.— The fact is, only 
     <lb/>some sixty or seventy men are wanted out 
     <lb/>of each Battalion of 1400 or 1500. and it 
     <lb/>is most probable that the full number will 
     <lb/>volunteer. If I imagined that this would 
     <lb/>be a meeting ot young men bent on dis<lb break="no"/>sipation, I would not urge its passage, 
     <lb/>but if they think it will be a spree, that 
     <lb/>they will be allowed to wander round the 
     <lb/>country and act as they please, they will 
     <lb/>be greatly mistaken. They will be under 
     <lb/>strict discipline, and I have no doubt will 
     <lb/>come out a better class of men than they 
     <lb/>go in. If I had not thought this, I would 
     <lb/>not heve brought the Bill in. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName>. — My hon. colleague has 
     <lb/>
     undertaken to catechize me for the action 
     <lb/>
     I see fit to take on this question. I be<lb break="no"/>lieve in the right of private opinion. I ac<lb break="no"/>cord to him what I require for myself, the 
     <lb/>right to think and speak freely, every man 
     <lb/>his own opinion. We have been of the 
     <lb/>same mine on this question in the past,<lb/>but since the last election he has changed<lb/>his views, not I belive becaue he has<lb/>come into power, for he has shown his dis<lb break="no"/>interestedness in this respect in the past,<lb/>but from conscientious motives. I am<lb/>opposed to making this affair compulsory,<lb/>for the loss of the labor of 2000 men to<lb/>the country is more than should be taken<lb/>out without providing an equivalent.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LAND1">Mr. LANDRY</persName>. — I believe if we cannot<lb/>
       
            <cb/>
          

     send a few men to be drilled we should 
     <lb/>
     not talk so much about our loyalty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CONN1">Mr. CONNELL</persName>. — It seems that men have 
     <lb/>
     to provide a grant of $30,000 for the Mili<lb break="no"/>tia, and then to draft the men into the 
     <lb/>
    service. I am opposed to any man being 
     <lb/>seized and taken from his farm, or shop, 
     <lb/>or desk, and forced to be drilled for<lb/>twenty-eight day, and I wish to enter<lb/>my protest against allowing the Com<lb break="no"/>mander-in-Chief to take men thus, wast<lb break="no"/>ing the public money and demoralizing 
     <lb/>the habits of the young men of the coun<lb break="no"/>try. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:CUDL1">Mr. CUDLIP</persName> —I should not have voted 
     <lb/>
     for the $30,000 grant if it had not been 
     <lb/>
     for Confederation, and I want that to go 
     <lb/>
     to the country for what it is worth. I do 
     <lb/>
     not believe in this part of the Bill any 
     <lb/>
     more than the hon. member for Carleton. 
     <lb/>
     I object to the draft, and if I had a son of 
     <lb/>eighteen who was drawn for camp, I would<lb/>
    withstand it to the utmost of my power. 
     <lb/>No nation, at any time, has any right to 
     <lb/>adopt the system of drafting men for their 
     <lb/>armies The people and papers of the 
     <lb/>United States protested against it, and 
     <lb/>showed how unfairly it bore in certain 
     <lb/>cases. In England if they want soldiers 
     <lb/>they pay for them; they never had a draft 
     <lb/>and never will ; the people would not 
     <lb/>stand it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>.- We must have some 
     <lb/>
     means to compel men to join the organi<lb break="no"/>zation. In Canada, Nova Scotia, and 
     <lb/>
     Newfoundland, they have the compulsory 
     <lb/>
     draft, and what reason is there why we 
     <lb/>
     should not? If we want to maintain a 
     <lb/>
     Military Camp, how can we get along 
     <lb/>
    without some power to force them to come 
     <lb/>forward? I agree with my hon. friend 
     <lb/>from St. John (Mr Cudlip). that if it had 
     <lb/>not been for Confederation we need not 
     <lb/>have taken the steps we are now com<lb break="no"/>pelled to. There are secret influences at 
     <lb/>work to injur this country in the eyes of 
     <lb/>Great Britain, and to force upon us what 
     <lb/>we have rejected. They are at work in 
     <lb/>secret in Canada and Nova Scotia, and 
     <lb/>we must do something to counteract them. 
     <lb/>I put it to the hon. member for Carleton 
     <lb/>whether, if this grant had not been made, 
     <lb/>and if this Bill does not pass, Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion would not he hastened? And to 
     <lb/>prevent thîs we must enter upon a com<lb break="no"/>plete Militia scheme, and to carry it out 
     <lb/>we must have some power to coerce those 
     <lb/>who are to belong to it. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMillan</persName> — I am willing to go to 
     <lb/>
     the extent of $30,000 for Militia purposes, 
     <lb/>
     not because I think it would be effective, 
     <lb/>
     for I do not think it can be so out of Con<lb break="no"/>federation, where the whole force would 
     <lb/>
     be under one head, but I strongly object 
     <lb/>
     to the section that gives the power into 
     <lb/>
     the hands of the Commander-in-Chief  to 
     <lb/>
     call them out. I do not think it should 
     <lb/>
     be done without the consent of his ad<lb break="no"/>visors. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName>. — If I thought there was 
     <lb/>
     no good in the Bill I would not vote for 
     <lb/>
    it; and if I had thought the grant would 
     <lb/>be no good, I would not have voted for 
     <lb/>that; but this is the most extraordinary 
     <lb/>way to legislate that I ever heard of, 
     <lb/>voting for things that we don't believe 
     <lb/>in. Talk about coercion. I should like to 
     <lb/>see the law that is not coercion. I don't 
     <lb/>think any injury will arise from this camp<lb/>instruction, and I don't think there will<lb/> 
               <lb/>be any need to draft; but if they won't<lb/>volunteer, they must be coerced. Hon.<lb/>members talk about this being a time of<lb/>peace; but there is a saying old but true,<lb/>"In times of peace prepare for war,"<lb/>And then I believe this camp will be of<lb/>real service to young men. It will take<lb/>them from the haunts of wickedness, that<lb/>
         
    
            <pb n="80" facs="final/images/NB_LA_1865-05-20_Page_0080.jpg"/>
         

     <fw type="num">80</fw>   <fw type="running">DEBATES OF THE HOUSE OF ASSEMBLY FOR 1865.</fw> 


     in too many cases they frequent. and keep 
     <lb/>
     them twenty-eight days under a strict 
     <lb/>
     discipline and subordination, that will re<lb break="no"/>sult in real good. If the question of the 
     <lb/>
     draft is the only difficulty in the way, hon. 
     <lb/>
     members need have no fear, for let the 
     <lb/>
     camp be stationed here at Fredericton, 
     <lb/>
     and give us the $30,000, and we'll keep it 
     <lb/>
     well supplied for years to come. 
     <lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:LIND1">Mr. LINDSAY</persName>. —I am convinced that the 
     <lb/>draft is the most obnoxious thing that 
     <lb/>was ever introduced into a nation, and it 
     <lb/>is never adopted in any form in England, 
     <lb/>except under the most pressing difficul<lb break="no"/>ties.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     
     <persName ref="pers:SMIT1">Hon. Mr. SMITH</persName>. — Under the old law 
     <lb/>
     all the men of the Province between the 
     <lb/>
     ages of 18 and 45 were called out for 
     <lb/>
     three days drill, whilst now we only ask 
     <lb/>
     for a certain number to form a camp of 
     <lb/>
     instruction, at a great saving of the time 
     <lb/>
     and producing labor of the country. 
     <lb/>
     
     
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:ALLE2">Hon. Mr. ALLEN</persName>. — The drafting of men 
     <lb/>for the Militia is not now introduced for 
     <lb/>the first time; it was established in the<lb/>Bill which passed in 1862. The 16th Sec<lb break="no"/>tion of that Bill contains the same princi<lb break="no"/>ple as this. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SUTT1">Mr. SUTTON</persName>. —If I thought the draft 
     <lb/>
     would ever be enforced, and it would be 
     <lb/>
     compulsory for' men to leave their homes 
     <lb/>
     to go to camp, I would vote against it, but 
     <lb/>
     as I believe there will be plenty of volun<lb break="no"/>teers I am willing to support this Section. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BOTS1">Hon. Mr. BOTSFORD</persName>. —Although the 
     <lb/>
    principle of drafting was established in 
     <lb/>1862 yet it was never enforced, as people 
     <lb/>came forward voluntarily. My hon. col<lb break="no"/>league, (Mr. Gilbert) although opposed to 
     <lb/>the draft here, joins the hon. members for 
     <lb/>Carleton, who were willing enough to take 
     <lb/>our men and send then off to Canada to 
     <lb/>fight her battles there under Confedera<lb break="no"/>tion. He says, things have changed; he 
     <lb/>too has changed, when he joins those who 
     <lb/>were desirous to force Confederation upon 
     <lb/>us. The hon. member for Carleton, (Mr. 
     <lb/>Connell) when asked, What shall we do?<lb/>says, Do as Canada does. Canada, who<lb/>has brought down the estimate England<lb/>held of these Colonies by refusing to es<lb break="no"/>tablish a system for defence. I think,<lb/>however, when it is known in England<lb/>what we are doing here, she will not con<lb break="no"/>sider us so disloyal nor so fond of annex<lb break="no"/>ation as they would make us out to be.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:MCMI1">Mr. McMILLAN</persName>. — The Hon. President<lb/>of the council says there are secret influ<lb break="no"/>ences at work against us in Canada and in<lb/>Nova Scotia. I would ask, Is it right for<lb/>a gentleman holding the high position he<lb/>does in this Province, to say that his fel<lb break="no"/>low colonists are animated by such un<lb break="no"/>worthy feelings, without producing some<lb/>proof. The Hon. Surveyor General seems<lb/>to be willing to shut us up entirely<lb/>to ourselves. Build a wall round<lb/>New Brunswick, like that around<lb/>China; don't break the eggshell that<lb/>separates us from the great world;<lb/>isolate us, cut us off rather from our fel<lb break="no"/>low men. and if an enemy enters Canada<lb/>at Niagara, don't go the resistance of our<lb/>fellow colonists, but leave them to do as<lb/>best they can. I believe that without<lb/>Confederation we cannot have the defen<lb break="no"/>ces of Militia in a proper conditions. They<lb/>will be of no actual service till we have<lb/>them all united under the general direc<lb break="no"/>tion of one head.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p><persName ref="pers:GILB1">Mr. GILBERT</persName> replied to some personal<lb/>remarks made by Hon. Mr. Botsford, and<lb/>then Progress was reported.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>The SPEAKER having resumed his seat<lb/>the House adjourned to meet on Monday<lb/>morning at 9 o'clock.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>J.M.<lb/>
            </p>

   <!-- GL, 2018-02-21, Commented out below, as it will appear in the following debate day -->
 

           <!-- <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     MONDAY, May 22.<lb/>
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
     
            </p>
            <p>On motion of Mr. CONNELL, the House 
     <lb/>went into Committee for the further con<lb break="no"/>sideration of "A Bill to authorize the 
     <lb/>the municipality of the County of Carleton to 
     <lb/>issue debentures for a Railway purpo<lb break="no"/>ses."<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. WILLISTON — Are the members of<lb/>the County of Carleton unanimous in their<lb/>desire that the lands of the whole County<lb/>should be taxed to support the views of<lb/>the municipality of Carleton? The Bill<lb/>which passed this House for the purpose 
     <lb/>of aiding the construction of the St. Ste 
     <lb/>phen Branch Railway authorizes the tax<lb break="no"/>ing of all property in a certain district 
     <lb/>which was to be benefitted by the road; 
     <lb/>but here the Whole County will have to 
     <lb/>be taxed, a large proportion of which will 
     <lb/>receive no benefit from the Railroad at 
     <lb/>all.<lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:NEED1">Mr. NEEDHAM</persName>. — According to the first 
     <lb/>
     secton of this Bill, the municipality frame 
     <lb/>
     a Bill, which they send down to the 
     <lb/>
     Government to sanction, and all the Gov<lb break="no"/>ernment has to do is see that it is in 
     <lb/>
     accordance with the laws of the Province, 
     <lb/>
     thus you give the municipality of Carleton 
     <lb/>
     the right to legislate for that County. 
     <lb/>
     The Corporation of St. John, with its 
     <lb/>
     executive powers and credit, have no such 
     <lb/>
     power vested in them; when they want 
     <lb/>
     to borrow money the whole thing must be 
     <lb/>
     set out in a law, and by that law they 
     <lb/>
     must borrow it ; but here you authorize 
     <lb/>
     the municipality to do the whole legis<lb break="no"/>lation, which is to affect the rights of 
     <lb/>thousands of people; and the Governor in 
     <lb/>Council must sanction their acts if they 
     <lb/>are not contrary to this law, or any other 
     <lb/>law in the Province. This Bill should 
     <lb/>cover the whole thing. It should show 
     <lb/>the form of debentures and what security  
     <lb/>should be given. It involves a large 
     <lb/>amount of money, and we are going 
     <lb/>through it with Railroad speed, none of 
     <lb/>us understanding its importance. This 
     <lb/>piecemeal legislation is the worst kind we 
     <lb/>can have. We are giving up our rights<lb/>as a legislative body and putting it in the<lb/>hands of a municipality, investing them<lb/>with a power they ought not to hvae, and<lb/>which we have not right to give them.<lb/>They should have inserted in their Bill<lb/>all that we required to render it of value<lb/>so that it would have protected the rights<lb/>of all parties, for if we do not secure those<lb/>rights to the people we depart from the<lb/>true principles of legislation.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. LINDSAY. — I would be willing to<lb/>amend it if the President of the Council<lb/>thinks it necessary, for the people of Car<lb break="no"/>leton are anxious to develope the resour<lb break="no"/>ces of the country, but are not now ask<lb break="no"/>ing for anything, but the privilege of<lb/>assessing themselves for the purpose of<lb/>carrying on a public work, and I do not<lb/>
               <lb/>think any public rights are invaded by<lb/>doing so; if we were going to tax the<lb/>whole country there might be some rea<lb break="no"/>son in the arguments of the hon. member<lb/>for York, and if he would bring in a simi<lb break="no"/>lar measure for his County, I would en<lb break="no"/>courage it, for I believe we should encour<lb break="no"/>age those who are willing to help them<lb break="no"/>selves.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Hon. Mr. SMITH. — If the hon. members<lb/>for the County of Carleton will take the<lb/>responsibility of this measure, I will sup<lb break="no"/>port the Bill; but I object to giving the<lb/>people the power to legislate on this ques<lb break="no"/>tion, because it is inconsistent with our<lb/>constitution; reference has been made to<lb/>the Seho[....] Law, but that is not a parallel<lb/>case with this; that merely gives permis<lb break="no"/>sive power to the people to accept the<lb/>provision of a law already made, I want<lb/>to record my opinion against this measure<lb/>
            </p>
            <milestone type="unknown"/>
            <p>
     which entirely ignores the principle of 
     <lb/>
     representative Government. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mr. KERR. — It appears to be the im<lb break="no"/>pression of the hon. member from Carle<lb break="no"/>ton that. this is a local matter, and no other 
     <lb/>
     part of the Province is interested in it. 
     <lb/>
     If the hon. member will raise the money 
     <lb/>
     in the County of Carleton; if the people of 
     <lb/>
     Carleton will agree to tax themselves, and 
     <lb/>
     raise the money among themselves, it 
     <lb/>
     would be well enough: but under this 
     <lb/>
    Biil there is no mention made of where 
     <lb/>thesé bonds are to be sold. They may be 
     <lb/>sold in the English market at fifty per 
     <lb/>cent discount, and by that means still 
     <lb/>further depress our Provincial securities, 
     <lb/>which are now selling at eight per cent 
     <lb/>discount; therefore, every. man in this 
     <lb/>Province is interested in this matter. I 
     <lb/>feel satisfied we are entering upon. what I 
     <lb/>consider to be a dangerous principle; that 
     <lb/>a law can be made by this Legislature 
     <lb/>and then rendered nugatory by an assem<lb break="no"/>bly of the people. It is not so in the 
     <lb/>School law to which reference has been 
     <lb/>made. That law still remains the law of 
     <lb/>the land; people do not have to pass a vote 
     <lb/>upon it to say whether it shall be the law 
     <lb/>of the land or not, but have simply to say 
     <lb/>in each locality whether they will accept 
     <lb/>its provisions or not. By adopting the 
     <lb/>principle contained in this Bill, we are 
     <lb/>entering upon a course which if followed 
     <lb/>up, will be utterly disastrous. We are in 
     <lb/>a different position in regard to building 
     <lb/>railroads from Canada; we have to import 
     <lb/>from abroad nearlyn all we require to build 
     <lb/>them, and by that means are involved in 
     <lb/>an amount of expenditure which has redu<lb break="no"/>ced our revenue very materially; whereas 
     <lb/>In Canada they have the most of the ma<lb break="no"/>terial in their own Province. It is, there<lb break="no"/>fore, absurd to say this Bill will not affect 
     <lb/>the welfare of the people of the whole 
     <lb/>Province, for every pound our debentures 
     <lb/>are sold below par is a loss to the whole 
     <lb/>country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

    

    

    
   
            <p>
     Hon. Mr. HATHEWAY. — if we had never   
     <lb/>constructed a line of Railway in this Pro<lb break="no"/>vince our revenues would have been in a<lb/>better position than they are at present;<lb/>but having commenced their construction,<lb/>they will not yield a revenue until ex-<lb break="maybe"/>tended.By grants and legislation we<lb/>have a line of Railway to within eleven<lb/>miles of the village of Woodstock, which<lb/>will be extended upwards, and if there<lb/>will be any line likely to pay it will be the<lb/>connection between Woodstock and the<lb/>St. Andrews Railway. The people of<lb/>Carleton have just as good right to put<lb/>their debentures in the market as the<lb/>people of St. Stephen; but there is a prin<lb break="no"/>ciple involved in this Bill, and I shall vote<lb/>against it without the members of the<lb/>County of Carleton take the responsibility,<lb/>for they are here as the exponents of pub<lb break="no"/>lic opinion in that County. If they will<lb/>strike out that section f the Bill which<lb/>refers it back to the people, I will vote <lb/>for it.<lb/>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. HILL — One objection taken by the<lb/>hon. member for Northumberland if, that<lb/>those debentures proposed to be issued by<lb/>the municipality of Carleton, if floated in<lb/>the English market, will depress our<lb/>Provincial debentures. I think this ap<lb break="no"/>prehension is most unfounded. If the<lb/>debentures of Carleton sell at a discount<lb/>it is not reason why the Provincial deben<lb break="no"/>tures should any more than the de<lb break="no"/>bentures of a city in Massachusetts would<lb/>affect the bonds of the State. Capitalists<lb/>in buying those bonds look at the se<lb break="no"/>curity, and if the municipality of Carleton<lb/>cannot give good security they cannot<lb/>sell those debentures, and in consequence<lb/>cannot build this road. Reference has<lb/>
            </p>-->
     </div>    </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>