<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xml:id="erasmus"
     xml:lang="en"
     type="full">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>

            <title>
               <name type="legislature" ref="lg:lgTreatyNeg">Treaty Negotiations</name>, <date from="1876" to="1878">1876 to 1878</date>, Between Canada and First Nations of Alberta and Saskatchewan.</title>
        
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Selection of input documents and completion of metadata</resp>
               <persName ref="pers:LYAL1">Gordon Lyall</persName>
            </respStmt>
        
         </titleStmt>
      
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Published by The Confederation Debates project.</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>

            <bibl corresp="bibl:Erasmus">
          

               <author>Peter Erasmus</author>.
          
         
          <title>Buffalo Days and Nights. </title>.
                    

          <date when="1976"/>.  
          

          <pubPlace>Calgary</pubPlace>: <publisher>Glenbow-Alberta Institute</publisher>.
          

          <biblScope unit="page" from="215" to="216"/>.
<biblScope unit="page" from="235" to="264"/>.
        </bibl>
        

            <list>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_215.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_216.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_235.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_236.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_237.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_238.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_239.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_240.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_241.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_242.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_243.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_244.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_245.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_246.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_247.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_248.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_249.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_250.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_251.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_252.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_253.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_254.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_255.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_256.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_257.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_258.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_259.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_260.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_261.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_262.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_263.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <ptr target="final/hocr/erasmus_page_264.hocr.html"/>
               </item>
            </list>
        </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <samplingDecl>

            <p/>
         </samplingDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="mholmes" when="2018-05-03">Transformed initial template file to incorporate corrected OCR content.</change>

         <change who="lyallg" when="2018-05-03">Created this document, completed metadata. </change>
      </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_215">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_215.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_216">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_216.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_235">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_235.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_236">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_236.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_237">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_237.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_238">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_238.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_239">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_239.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_240">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_240.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_241">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_241.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_242">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_242.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_243">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_243.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_244">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_244.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_245">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_245.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_246">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_246.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_247">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_247.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_248">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_248.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_249">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_249.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_250">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_250.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_251">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_251.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_252">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_252.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_253">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_253.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_254">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_254.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_255">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_255.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_256">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_256.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_257">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_257.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_258">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_258.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_259">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_259.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_260">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_260.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_261">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_261.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_262">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_262.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_263">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_263.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="erasmus_page_264">
         <graphic url="final/images/erasmus_page_264.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="215" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_215.jpg"/>
            <p>
     [..] unsuspecting victim for his money or furs. Many carried out 
     <lb/>
     their various schemes under the guise of being free traders. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The southern portion of the country in Blackfoot and 
     <lb/>
     Peigan territory was polluted with so-called traders whose 
     <lb/>
     unbridled use of rotgut whisky was creating havoc amongst the 
     <lb/>
     once-proud Blackfoot nation and their allies. The Americans 
     <lb/>
     from across the border of Montana had established so-called 
     <lb/>
     trading posts within our border and had accomplished what 
     <lb/>
     the thousands of Crees had failed to do in their best days, 
     <lb/>
     namely the subjugation of the southern tribes. The American 
     <lb/>
     long-range rifles and their speed with the short gun while they 
     <lb/>
     plied the natives with whisky and cheated them out of their 
     <lb/>
     belongings was a disgrace to a civilized nation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It was with horror and impotent rage that I had listened to a 
     <lb/>
     recital of the growing power that these degenerate adventurers 
     <lb/>
     who acknowledged no authority but their unmerciful use of 
     <lb/>
     guns and whisky to victimize the natives. A man named Felix 
     <lb/>
     Monroe, who had been a Blackfoot interpreter with the Palliser 
     <lb/>
     expedition in '58, spent half the night telling us of the many 
     <lb/>
     misdeeds going on in that part of the territories. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I was in those days indifferent to the need of government, 
     <lb/>
     but now was fully awake to the fact that nothing could save my 
     <lb/>
     Indian friends but some authoritative action to oust these 
     <lb/>
     American vagabonds and leeches who were sucking the very 
     <lb/>
     life blood of the southern tribes. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     My old friend Spence had kept me informed of the 
     <lb/>
     controversy raging in the settlement of the Red River and Fort 
     <lb/>
     Garry that ended with the Rebellion of 1869-70, the final 
     <lb/>
     outcome of which I had learned on this trip. During the 
     <lb/>
     transition of authority from the Hudson's Bay Company to the 
     <lb/>
     Government of Canada I had taken a neutral stand, not joining 
     <lb/>
     with any side in the disputed matters concerned with this 
     <lb/>
     change. I deemed the whole question was not of my concern, 
     <lb/>
     living in the western Territories. It would be some time before 
     <lb/>
     we were affected.
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The matter of annexation to the States was a different 
     <lb/>
     matter. Its accomplishment even to a minor degree by the 
     <lb/>
     usurping of authority by these unprincipled traders in our 
     <lb/>
     territory fairly made my blood boil as nothing had in all the 
     <lb/>
     years of agitation, petitions, and what-not that had predated 
     <lb/>
     the Riel Rebellion. I welcomed the news that a high official of 
     <lb/>
     the Government of Canada was being sent out to the West to 
     <lb/>
     investigate actual conditions and report recommendations.
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It was variously rumoured in Hudson's Bay circles that as a 
     <lb/>
     result of this investigation a police force would be made 
     <lb/>
     available to the Territories and that some form of authoritative 
     <lb/>
         

            <fw type="num">215</fw>
            <pb n="216" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_216.jpg"/>
          

     government would be established. I found myself adopting a 
     <lb/>
     completely different attitude. It had now become a personal 
     <lb/>
     matter by the loss of two winters' labour in trapping and 
     <lb/>
     trading. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The continued decrease of buffalo on the prairies was 
     <lb/>
     creating considerable resentment among the Indians whose 
     <lb/>
     livelihood depended completely on the buffalo. Though 
     <lb/>
     poison bait was unheard of among the northern tribes, a supply 
     <lb/>
     was being used and made available by these southern traders. 
     <lb/>
     Indian dogs had been killed by the baits set out for wolves and 
     <lb/>
     coyotes, and it was a common belief that horses had been 
     <lb/>
     poisoned by eating grass where an unrecovered carcass had 
     <lb/>
     decomposed. If horses could die, they argued, then buffalo 
     <lb/>
     would also be killed. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Isolated among the northern tribes, I had not given these 
     <lb/>
     matters much thought. My personal loss by one of these rogues 
     <lb/>
     filled me with a resentment almost beyond my control. At the 
     <lb/>
     moment I did not credit my brother's weakness for drink a 
     <lb/>
     factor of any importance. I had fervently expressed my hearty 
     <lb/>
     approval at Carlton and Fort Pitt and definitely stated that it 
     <lb/>
     would be easy to recruit help to route those whisky traders and 
     <lb/>
     crooks who were engaged in that nefarious business. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When we got back home, Charlotte received my bad news 
     <lb/>
     with her usual fortitude. "Well, Peter! Using your own words, 
     <lb/>
     it is tough luck. We are both healthy and we can still hunt and 
     <lb/>
     fish. We will leave our two boys with my mother and make that 
     <lb/>
     trip to Beaver Lake that you claim is swarming with mink." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Look here, woman! It will be impossible for you to go 
     <lb/>
     along. We will have to go on saddle horse and bring our stuff on 
     <lb/>
     pack horses. How can you take the girl along? Three children 
     <lb/>
     will be too much for your mother and I will not allow it." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Forget your objections," she replied, "I have made up my 
     <lb/>
     mind. If there are as many mink on that creek as you claim, you 
     <lb/>
     will have no time to trap, skin and prepare the pelts as well as 
     <lb/>
     cook your meals, and besides we both have to work to recover 
     <lb/>
     our losses this winter." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The weather was very mild for that time of year in the latter 
     <lb/>
     part of October 1870, after a sharp period that froze the small 
     <lb/>
     lakes. I made a last effort to change my wife's idea of braving the 
     <lb/>
     trip but it was useless. "We can be at that creek in four days. We 
     <lb/>
     have a good tent and the weather is mild. Look at this fur-lined 
     <lb/>
     bag that I have made for our girl. Hundreds of Indian children 
     <lb/>
     have been carried for centuries in this kind of thing. My mother 
     <lb/>
     helped me make it. Besides, she is only too eager to have our 
     <lb/>
     boys in her care while we are away." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I gave up the argument but I slammed the door good and [...]
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <fw type="num">216</fw>
            <pb n="235" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_235.jpg"/>
            <p>
   [...]  you have fingers and toes, so sit down and rest yourself while I 
     <lb/>
     get some breakfast ready." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Do not bother," I said. "I'm not hungry." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Huh," he grunted, "Stop worrying. Healthy good women 
     <lb/>
     in our tribe never have trouble with babies. When you married 
     <lb/>
     one of our girls, you did not marry trouble. Your wife has had 
     <lb/>
     four children without your presence, so why trouble yourself 
     <lb/>
     now?" 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This remark of the old gentleman had its desired effect in 
     <lb/>
     cooling my nervousness. Under his cheerful conversation 
     <lb/>
     which avoided the matter uppermost in my mind, we began 
     <lb/>
     eating. I forgot my lack of hunger and my usual good appetite 
     <lb/>
     asserted itself, much to the amusement of my optimistic friend. 
     <lb/>
     The gleam in his eye reminded me of my former protests 
     <lb/>
     against eating any breakfast. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It was now broad daylight and everybody was up and about 
     <lb/>
     their duties. I watched the old gentleman's clumsy efforts at 
     <lb/>
     washing the dishes. Then he turned to me in a grumbling voice 
     <lb/>
     and said, "You have my wife working for you and I have to do 
     <lb/>
     her work, so you had better go after my horses as I need them 
     <lb/>
     this morning." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I had a long walk after his horses. It took quite a search to 
     <lb/>
     find them but I brought them in for him at the Hunter teepee. 
     <lb/>
     Mrs. Hunter waved to me to come to my own tent. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Charlotte gave me a weary smile and said, "Peter, I am glad 
     <lb/>
     for you. It is another boy and I want him named David." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I was so relieved and glad that she was all right that I would 
     <lb/>
     have consented to the name Ebenezer had she asked. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Hunter I noticed just tied his horses up till noon, then 
     <lb/>
     turned them out again. He had merely sent me after the horses 
     <lb/>
     to keep me occupied. I was grateful for his clever management 
     <lb/>
     that had kept me busy and free from needless worry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Two days later a couple of strangers arrived and made 
     <lb/>
     inquiries as to my whereabouts. They were guided to Hunter's 
     <lb/>
     teepee by one of the camp guards. Hunter immediately offered 
     <lb/>
     them the hospitality of his teepee, placing robes for them to rest 
     <lb/>
     in a reclining position. A good meal was prepared at once as 
     <lb/>
     was the custom when strangers were guests. The guard had 
     <lb/>
     shown them to Hunter's tepee knowing how matters were in 
     <lb/>
     my tent, this with far more consideration and tact than I 
     <lb/>
     experienced among white settlers in later years. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     John sent his wife to call me from my tent without saying 
     <lb/>
     just what was wanted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "These men," said <persName ref="pers:HUNT5">Hunter</persName>, "are sons of Mista-wa-sis and 
     <lb/>
     Ah-tuk-a-kup; they have been up to Whitefish Lake and have 
     <lb/>
     followed you here." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <fw type="num">235</fw>
            <pb n="236" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_236.jpg"/>
            <p>
     I shook hands with both men saying, "My friends, you have 
     <lb/>
     come at a bad time. I'll have to talk with my wife before I can 
     <lb/>
     promise to go with you." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Discussing the matter of the arrival of these men, my wife's 
     <lb/>
     answer was typical of the way she faced all our problems. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "You have given your word to their fathers, Peter. There is 
     <lb/>
     nothing for you to do but go with them at once. I will be all 
     <lb/>
     right with Mrs. Hunter to look after me. Peter Shirt and Red 
     <lb/>
     Head can look after the carts and we will return with the others. 
     <lb/>
     Thanks to our friends, our carts are loaded and the others are 
     <lb/>
     almost ready." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I went back to the men and told them that I would be ready 
     <lb/>
     as soon as they wanted to go. "We are ready now," said one man 
     <lb/>
     as he rose to his feet from where he was resting. "My father has 
     <lb/>
     already started for Carlton and we may be late if we delay." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Packing a few things in a bag for extras, I went with the 
     <lb/>
     clothes I was dressed in, hurriedly packed food and cooking 
     <lb/>
     utensils on a pack horse and riding Whitey, my buffalo runner, 
     <lb/>
     I was ready to start. Peter had fetched the horses while I was 
     <lb/>
     packing my duffle for the trip. I bid the family goodbye and 
     <lb/>
     gave some last minute instructions to Peter in regard to the care 
     <lb/>
     of the family and equipment. These latter orders were hardly 
     <lb/>
     necessary as I had long since been dependent on the young man 
     <lb/>
     for the care of everything while I was away. Of course a man 
     <lb/>
     likes to assert his authority, especially with strangers present. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:HUNT5">Hunter</persName> decided to come along with us as he wanted to listen 
     <lb/>
     to the treaty negotiations. I was just a bit worried that the fast 
     <lb/>
     trip would be too much for him but he was well mounted as we 
     <lb/>
     all were and if he grew too tired I could leave the pack outfit and 
     <lb/>
     he could follow up at an easier gait. I need not have given the 
     <lb/>
     matter any thought for he stood up to the trip as well as any of us 
     <lb/>
    and his saddler turned out to be the best riding horse of the lot. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>We arrived at Carlton the evening of the fifth day of hard 
     <lb/>riding and long hours, but our horses were all in excellent 
     <lb/>condition to start with and stood up well to the trip. A large 
     <lb/>encampment appeared, and separated by a lane were the 
     <lb/>various tents and canvas shelters that housed the traders. 
     <lb/>Apparently they had anticipated an agreement on treaty terms 
     <lb/>and had come prepared to do business with the Indians.3 Later I 
     <lb/>learned that my youngest sister was there also. She had married 
     <lb/>a trader, a big strapping Swede by the name of Pederson. 
     <lb/>Though I was kept pretty busy, we managed to get together for 
     <lb/>a visit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     A comfortable teepee had been set up for our use with 
     <lb/>
     buffalo robes, new blankets, cooking utensils, and even 
     <lb/>
     prepared food. Mr. Hunter was particularly impressed with the 
     <lb/>
          

            <fw type="num">236</fw>
            <pb n="237" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_237.jpg"/>
         

     care lavished on us for our stay. Certainly it was the best 
     <lb/>
     hospitality that could be provided. The camp crier rode among 
     <lb/>
     the teepees and announced our arrival. He was riding on a gaily 
     <lb/>
     decorated pinto pony. He was telling the people that their 
     <lb/>
     interpreter had arrived and that the chiefs and councillors 
     <lb/>
     should get ready for the meeting the next day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I decided to take a walk around camp and saw Governor 
     <lb/>
     Morris walking in front of the Hudson's Bay post. There were 
     <lb/>
     over 250 teepees on the Indian section of the grounds. It was an 
     <lb/>
     impressive sight. I had never seen so many teepees in one 
     <lb/>
     locality before. There were hundreds of horses feeding on the 
     <lb/>
     flats, some picketed close by their owner's teepee with the usual 
     <lb/>
     assortment of dogs which appeared to have barked themselves 
     <lb/>
     to exhaustion as they lay before each teepee. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:BALL4">Peter Ballenden</persName> and his brother Sam came to the chiefs and 
     <lb/>
     informed them that the Governor desired them to meet him at 
     <lb/>
     the fort that evening. I had just returned from my walk when 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:MIST1">Mista-wa-sis</persName> came to my tent and asked me to accompany them. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "I have been told," said <persName ref="pers:MIST1">the chief</persName>, "that the Governor has 
     <lb/>
     hired two other interpreters. However, we have decided to pay 
     <lb/>
     you ourselves, even if the Governor does not." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The chiefs were dressed in all their finery, feathers, plumes, 
     <lb/>
     and ermine-decorated coats. I felt a little out of place among the 
     <lb/>
     tribal costumes; and when we came before the assembled 
     <lb/>
     officials, they also had quite as great an array of finery as our 
     <lb/>
     Indian chiefs. My work clothes, though neat and clean, when 
     <lb/>
     compared against all the other finery were indeed inadequate. I 
     <lb/>
     wished that I had come better prepared for this situation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When I saw Peter Ballenden and the Rev. John McKay 
     <lb/>
     seated among the official group, I presumed they were the 
     <lb/>
     interpreters the chief had mentioned. I was not too greatly 
     <lb/>
     concerned, as I knew both men; their ability as interpreters to a 
     <lb/>
     large gathering such as we would be faced with on the morrow 
     <lb/>
     would be tested to the limit. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Governor Morris, Hon. James McKay, Clarke, William 
     <lb/>
     Christie, now retired from the Hudson's Bay service, and a Dr. 
     <lb/>
     Jackes were all seated at the table when we entered" Clarke 
     <lb/>
     jumped up and came forward to introduce our party. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I was standing beside Mista-wa-sis, but Clarke paid no 
     <lb/>
     attention to my presence while he was conducting the 
     <lb/>
     introductions. Although Clarke, Ballenden, Christie, and the 
     <lb/>
     Rev. McKay all knew me by name, they did not offer any sign of 
     <lb/>
     recognition. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Governor advanced and shook hands with the chiefs, 
     <lb/>
     saying, "I have come to meet you Cree chiefs to make a treaty 
     <lb/>
     with you for the surrender of your rights of the land to the 
     <lb/>
          

            <fw type="num">237</fw>
            <pb n="238" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_238.jpg"/>
         

     government, and further I have two of the most efficient 
     <lb/>
     interpreters that could be obtained. There stand Peter 
     <lb/>
     Ballenden and the Rev. John McKay." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     His words were interpreted by <persName ref="pers:BALL4">Peter Ballenden</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MIST1">Big Child</persName> answered, "We have our own interpreter, Peter 
     <lb/>
     Erasmus, and there he is. Mr. Clarke (he pointed directly at 
     <lb/>
     Clarke) advised me that Peter Erasmus was a good man to 
     <lb/>
     interpret the Cree language. Further than that, he recommend<lb break="no"/>ed the man as the best interpreter in the whole Saskatchewan 
     <lb/>
     valley and plains. Why he did so, only he knows. On Clarke's 
     <lb/>
     advice, though I have no acquaintance with the man, I went to 
     <lb/>
     a great deal of trouble to fetch him here and though I know 
     <lb/>
     nothing of his efficiency, I am prepared to use his services. All 
     <lb/>
     our chiefs have agreed." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Is that correct?" asked <persName ref="pers:MORR4">Governor Morris</persName> of Clarke. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Peter Erasmus lives several hundred miles from here and I 
     <lb/>
     did not know that the chiefs had sent for him; therefore I hired 
     <lb/>
     these two other interpreters." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "It was quite unnecessary to send for the man," said <persName ref="pers:MORR4">the 
     <lb/>
     Governor</persName>. "We have two interpreters hired by the government 
     <lb/>
     and it is up to the government to provide the means of 
     <lb/>
     communication." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I had quietly interpreted these side conversations to the 
     <lb/>
     chief and he was prepared for an answer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Very good," said <persName ref="pers:MIST1">Mista-wa-sis</persName>, "you keep your interpreters 
     <lb/>
     and we will keep ours. We will pay our own man and I already 
     <lb/>
     see that it will be well for us to do so." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This latter statement by the chief, I interpreted to Morris 
     <lb/>
     directly, not waiting for Ballenden to misinterpret the chief's 
     <lb/>
     meaning. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "There is no need for you to assume this extra expense for 
     <lb/>
     an interpreter when the government is willing to pay for the 
     <lb/>
     interpretations," reiterated <persName ref="pers:MORR4">the Commissioner</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MIST1">The chief</persName> replied rather heatedly, "Our man will interpret 
     <lb/>
     as well as yours. I can speak Blackfoot and I know what it takes 
     <lb/>
     to interpret. If you do not want the arrangement, there will be 
     <lb/>
     no talks. We did not send for you, you sent for us." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I was quick to translate the conversations before waiting for 
     <lb/>
     Ballenden's hesitant and slow interpretations. The Governor's 
     <lb/>
     party were huddled at the table in low conversation, none of 
     <lb/>
     which I could hear. In the meantime the chiefs gathered 
     <lb/>
     together and were about to leave the room when the Governor 
     <lb/>
     looked up and saw they were going to leave. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "All right," he said. "You can have your interpreter. My 
     <lb/>
     tent will be pitched on the prairie where we will meet. There 
     <lb/>
     will be a band playing to notify you of our presence." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <fw type="num">238</fw>
            <pb n="239" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_239.jpg"/>
      
<div type="chapter">
<head rendition="simple:centre">CHAPTER FOURTEEN</head>
            <head rendition="simple:centre">
     Treaty No. Six 
     <lb/>
            </head>
   
            <p>
     THE GOVERNOR'S TENT was pitched on a slight rise some 
     <lb/>
     distance from the fort. Most of the other officials were already 
     <lb/>
     waiting for him in the tent. Then the Governor's carriage 
     <lb/>
     appeared, accompanied by the Mounted Police and led by the 
     <lb/>
     promised band. The Police, dressed in their smart scarlet 
     <lb/>
     uniforms and riding well trained horses, made a big impression 
     <lb/>
     with the Indians. In fact the great prestige of the Governor was 
     <lb/>
     somewhat overshadowed by the smart appearance of his escort. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Many Indians of that camp were seeing the Mounted Police 
     <lb/>
     for the first time. Though small in number, the Police were to 
     <lb/>
     be an important factor in establishing in the minds of the tribes 
     <lb/>
     the fairness and justice of government for all the people 
     <lb/>
     regardless of colour or creed — something they had no concept 
     <lb/>
     of in its broader sense. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Indian's own rules were handed down from the dim 
     <lb/>
     past, their oldest traditions accepted without question. The 
     <lb/>
     chiefs and councillors were chosen for outstanding qualities of 
     <lb/>
     character. Bravery and ability were the sole measures by which 
     <lb/>
     their leaders were qualified to take positions of trust. A son of a 
     <lb/>
     chief assumed office following the death of the chief only if he 
     <lb/>
     had proved himself qualified under these standards of office. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Indians recognized and respected the personal qualities 
     <lb/>
        

            <fw type="num">239</fw>
            <pb n="240" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_240.jpg"/>
          

     of the individuals comprising the Force as being the qualities 
     <lb/>
     they demanded in their own leaders. The administration of 
     <lb/>
     impartial justice without regard to colour or creed, and the 
     <lb/>
     tenacity of its members in carrying out their duties, soon 
     <lb/>
     became a topic of Indian campfire conversation. The small 
     <lb/>
     number of this Police Force would have been utterly incapable 
     <lb/>
     of handling the thousands of Indians if they had attempted to 
     <lb/>
     employ force to compel obedience. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The chief and his councillors administered the laws for 
     <lb/>
     their band and the tribe recognized the necessity for rules 
     <lb/>
     governing individuals who at times broke the rules set by their 
     <lb/>
     leaders for the benefit of the majority. That, in my opinion, is 
     <lb/>
     what made possible the successful role that this small Force 
     <lb/>
     played in the progress of settlement of one country. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Our approach to the Governor's tent was delayed by certain 
     <lb/>
     ceremonial proceedings that have been far better described than 
     <lb/>
     I feel capable of doing. However, let me say that these 
     <lb/>
     ceremonial practices had a deep significance to the tribes and 
     <lb/>
     can only be explained as a solemn approach to a vital and 
     <lb/>
     serious issue for discussion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Few people realize that those so-called savages were far 
     <lb/>
     more deeply affected and influenced by their religious beliefs 
     <lb/>
     and convictions than any comparable group of white people, 
     <lb/>
     whose lip service to their religion goes no deeper than that. The 
     <lb/>
     forms of ceremonial behaviour with which the Indians 
     <lb/>
     approached the Governor's tent were based on practices whose 
     <lb/>
     actual meaning has long since been lost. The ceremony in the 
     <lb/>
     crowning of the kings and queens of England would have little 
     <lb/>
     meaning were it not for the benefit of a written language. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We were finally seated on the grass in a large semicircle in 
     <lb/>
     front of the Governor's tent crossed-legged, a position that 
     <lb/>
     seems to be the most restful and relaxed manner of listening to a 
     <lb/>
     speech. I have seen quite old men rise to their feet to speak from 
     <lb/>
     this position without the use of their hands or arms to assist 
     <lb/>
     them, all with apparently effortless ease. My own attempts in 
     <lb/>
     this regard were never graceful or even easy. I always had to use 
     <lb/>
     my hands and arms to assist me. It was a physical feat that I 
     <lb/>
     never successfully conquered. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We were patiently awaiting the Commissioner's conven<lb break="no"/>ience when the <persName ref="pers:MCKA4">Hon. James McKay</persName> came to the front and called 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:ERAS1">Peter Erasmus</persName> to come forward to interpret the Governor's 
     <lb/>
     speech. I rose to my feet and said, "I object, Sir. It is my 
     <lb/>
     impression that I am not employed by the government but am 
     <lb/>
     acting only on behalf of the chiefs assembled here. Therefore, I 
     <lb/>
     refuse to interpret the Governor's speech; that I consider is the 
     <lb/>
         

            <fw type="num">240</fw>
            <pb n="241" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_241.jpg"/>
       

     duty of its paid servants." I then faced the Indians and repeated 
     <lb/>
     my words in Cree. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MCKA4">McKay</persName> again insisted but I just as promptly refused. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MIST1">Mista-wa-sis</persName> turned to me and in an undertone asked me if I 
     <lb/>
     thought that I was capable of interpreting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Certainly I can, or else I would not be here. Let their own 
     <lb/>
     men talk first and then you will understand why I refuse to do 
     <lb/>
     their bidding." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MIST1">Big Child</persName> and <persName ref="pers:AHTU1">Star Blanket</persName> on each side of me nodded their 
     <lb/>
     agreement. The former rose to his feet. There was considerable 
     <lb/>
     stir among the Indians at the delay. Voices were noticeable 
     <lb/>
               from those seated furthest away from the stand. As soon as <persName ref="pers:MIST1">Big 
     <lb/>
     Child</persName> stood up there was immediate silence. He was a 
     <lb/>
     commanding figure of a man, not tall, but he stood straight and 
     <lb/>
     his wide shoulders spoke of strength. He didn't say a word until 
     <lb/>
     there was complete silence. Showing his closed fist with index 
     <lb/>
     finger protruding, he spoke, "This is number one," indicating 
     <lb/>
     "one" with the raising of his hand for all to see. "Already you 
     <lb/>
     have broken your word on what you have agreed." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I stood beside him and interpreted word for word as he 
     <lb/>
     spoke. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     All the Indians rose to their feet and crowded forward 
     <lb/>
     behind their chiefs. The Police were kept busy keeping them 
     <lb/>
     away from the table. They were like a forest as a gathering 
     <lb/>
     storm of words rolled forward. I was thoroughly angered at the 
     <lb/>
     manner in which the Governor had been inveigled into this 
     <lb/>
     situation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I had expected neither the strong reaction from the Indians 
     <lb/>
     nor McKay's determination to have his own way. I knew that 
     <lb/>
     Peter Ballenden had not the education or practice to interpret, 
     <lb/>
     and his voice had no carrying quality to make himself heard 
     <lb/>
     before all this large assembly. The Rev. McKay had learned his 
     <lb/>
     Cree among the Swampy and Saulteaux. While there was a 
     <lb/>
     similarity in some words, and I had learned both languages, the 
     <lb/>
     Prairie Crees would not understand his Cree. Further, the 
     <lb/>
     Prairie Crees looked down on the Swampy and Saulteaux as an 
     <lb/>
     inferior race. They would be intolerant at being addressed in 
     <lb/>
     Swampy or Saulteaux words. I knew that McKay was not 
     <lb/>
     sufficiently versed in the Prairie Cree to confine his interpreta<lb break="no"/>tions to their own language. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Rev. Mr. McDougall was busy trying to calm Bear 
     <lb/>
     Skin, the most irate and the loudest of any of the crowd. Both 
     <lb/>
     leading chiefs stood without saying a word while all the fuss 
     <lb/>
     went on. Finally Big Child was satisfied that the Government 
     <lb/>
     party had been sufficiently chastised. He waved to those 
     <lb/>
        

            <fw type="num">241</fw>
            <pb n="242" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_242.jpg"/>
    

     immediately surrounding him to be seated, and as before, with 
     <lb/>
     a few words, restored order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Governor was quick to take advantage of the lull after 
     <lb/>
     Mista-wa-sis had waved his people to silence. You could almost 
     <lb/>
     feel the strong tension that still remained. <persName ref="pers:MORR4">Governor Morris</persName> 
     <lb/>
               started his address with the <persName ref="pers:MCKA12">Rev. McKay</persName> interpreting. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "You nations of the Crees," he began, "I am here on a most 
     <lb/>
     important mission as representing Her Majesty the Queen 
     <lb/>
     Mother to form a treaty with you in her name, that you 
     <lb/>
     surrender your rights in these northern territories to the 
     <lb/>
     government." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     He went on to explain that treaties already had been signed 
     <lb/>
     by other tribes, naming those that had been treated with. He 
     <lb/>
     mentioned the Touchwood Hills Crees and some of the others, 
     <lb/>
     saying that he had been chosen because he was familiar with 
     <lb/>
     Indian conditions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:MCKA12">McKay's</persName> interpretations were mixed with Swampy and 
     <lb/>
     Saulteaux words. I mentioned this in English to the table, and 
     <lb/>
     the <persName ref="pers:MCKA4">Honourable James</persName> angrily shouted, "Stop that, or you will 
     <lb/>
     rattle him!" 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MIST1">Mista-wa-sis</persName>, after listening for a time, jumped to his feet 
     <lb/>
     and said, "We are not Swampy Crees or Saulteaux Indians. We 
     <lb/>
     are Plains Crees and demand to be spoken to in our own 
     <lb/>
     language." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     McKay understood, was confused, and sat down. The 
     <lb/>
     Governor turned to me and asked what the chief had said. I 
     <lb/>
     explained the chief's words. The Rev. McKay again tried to 
     <lb/>
     continue, got mixed up with Saulteaux words and took his seat. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Ballenden was now called up. I was delighted, for I knew 
     <lb/>
     the man quite well. He was a good man to interpret personal 
     <lb/>
     talks but I knew he would be completely out of his element as 
     <lb/>
     an interpreter for such a large meeting, where a man's voice had 
     <lb/>
     to carry to reach the men furthest from the stand. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     His attitude of the previous evening in not showing me any 
     <lb/>
     recognition; and Clarke's conspicuous neglect of a formal 
     <lb/>
     introduction, even though he was personally acquainted with 
     <lb/>
     me, had fairly made my blood boil. I had no pity for the men 
     <lb/>
     who had contributed their share to having me discredited with 
     <lb/>
     the Commissioner. Ballenden did exactly as I thought. He 
     <lb/>
     made an excellent interpretation of the Governor's words but 
     <lb/>
     in a voice so low that it could not be heard beyond the first ten 
     <lb/>
     rows of men seated on the ground. The men in the back rows 
     <lb/>
     got to their feet and demanded that he speak in a louder voice; 
     <lb/>
     again there was some confusion and the two chiefs beside me 
     <lb/>
     got to their feet and ordered the men to be quiet. Ballenden tried 
     <lb/>
     to raise his voice, choked, and then sat down. My revenge at that 
     <lb/>
         

            <fw type="num">242</fw>
            <pb n="243" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_243.jpg"/>
          

     moment was sweet but I could read consternation on the faces 
     <lb/>
     of my impolite friends at the table. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MORR4">The Governor</persName>, who I could see was growing exasperated at 
     <lb/>
     these frequent interruptions to his talk, said, "All right, 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:ERAS1">Erasmus</persName>. Let this be your chance to justify your chiefs' 
     <lb/>
     confidence in your work." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I immediately rose to my feet, stepped beside the Governor's 
     <lb/>
     table, faced the Crees, and spoke in Cree, reviewing the text of 
     <lb/>
     the Governor's speech to them. Then I motioned to the 
     <lb/>
     Commissioner to continue his address. I knew my voice had 
     <lb/>
     suffered nothing from my heated veins or the exultation that I 
     <lb/>
     felt at the complete disposal of the slight so desperately 
     <lb/>
     manoeuvered by these men sitting around the table. The 
     <lb/>
     Governor spoke for an hour or so explaining the purpose of the 
     <lb/>
     treaty and its objectives, and describing in some detail the 
     <lb/>
     terms. He especially emphasized the money each person would 
     <lb/>
     get. There were no further interruptions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Once during a pause in the Governor's speech, the 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:MCKA4">Honourable James</persName> differed with me over an interpretation of 
     <lb/>
     one word. However, his brother supported my interpretation in 
     <lb/>
     the matter and no further objections were expressed during the 
     <lb/>
     whole of the remaining treaty negotiations. Though that first 
     <lb/>
     day I felt high strung and angry over the treatment I had 
     <lb/>
     received, I was determined that nothing would prevent me from 
     <lb/>
     doing my work with credit to my employers and justice to the 
     <lb/>
     Governor's talks. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Indians had retired to their teepees or were sitting in 
     <lb/>
     groups discussing the treaty terms. Hunter was around 
     <lb/>
     somewhere with the other Indians. I was reclining in our tent 
     <lb/>
     trying to calm my ruffled feelings and assess the value of my 
     <lb/>
     contribution to the talks when the Governor's cook stuck his 
     <lb/>
     head in the tent flaps and said that the Governor wanted to see 
     <lb/>
     me. I was about to give the men a curt refusal, thinking that 
     <lb/>
     sending the lowest man on their staff to summon me to the 
     <lb/>
     great man's presence was another effort to emphasize my status. 
     <lb/>
     Then I heard the Hon. James McKay, Christie, and Dr. Jackes 
     <lb/>
     questioning the cook, asking if he had found my tent. He 
     <lb/>
     answered in the affirmative; then they all came to the tent and 
     <lb/>
     said they were there to escort me back to the Governor's 
     <lb/>
     quarters. Entering, I stood without making any comment, 
     <lb/>
     awaiting the gentleman's pleasure. "Well, Mr. Erasmus. I 
     <lb/>
     suppose you are slightly exhausted over your labours this 
     <lb/>
     forenoon?" I thought I detected a slight hint of sarcasm in his 
     <lb/>
     tone and immediately answered, "No, Mr. Morris. Not by the 
     <lb/>
     work but by the preliminaries that led up to the work." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     He smiled and I heard laughs in the background. Then he 
     <lb/>
          

            <fw type="num">243</fw>
            <pb n="244" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_244.jpg"/>
         

     came forward to where I was standing and handed me a glass of 
     <lb/>
     brandy, which I accepted, for to have refused would have 
     <lb/>
     indicated that I was still nursing a grievance in the face of his 
     <lb/>
     apparent effort at appeasement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Mr. Erasmus, I called you here to congratulate you on your 
     <lb/>
     work. You are the first man I ever heard who interpreted to such 
     <lb/>
     a large audience without making a mistake. I see you have 
     <lb/>
     friends around here, although our first impressions may have 
     <lb/>
     discouraged this view." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     It was pretty much of an after-dinner speech. Some of the 
     <lb/>
     Governor's guests applauded but I noticed that Clarke and 
     <lb/>
     Ballenden were not among them. Mr. Morris advised me that, 
     <lb/>
     beginning that day, I would be in his pay for the balance of the 
     <lb/>
     talks. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Thank you, Sir. I hope that I may have better co-operation 
     <lb/>
     in the next few days. I promise to give you the best I have, and 
     <lb/>
     assure you that today's unpleasantness will not be repeated 
     <lb/>
     from our side." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I begged to be excused and took my departure without 
     <lb/>
     further words. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The next day the Police band preceded the Governor as 
     <lb/>
     before, but there was not so much pomp and display from the 
     <lb/>
     Government party. Even the Governor walked unescorted from 
     <lb/>
     his carriage the short distance to the stand. The Indians were 
     <lb/>
     already in place in their usual postures of comfortable listening 
     <lb/>
     as on the previous day. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Commissioner formally opened the meeting by stating 
     <lb/>
     that today he wanted to hear what they had to say, adding, "I 
     <lb/>
     cannot go any further in regard to the terms I explained 
     <lb/>
     yesterday." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POUN1">Poundmaker</persName>, who was not a chief at that time but just a 
     <lb/>
     brave, spoke up and said, "The governor mentions how much 
     <lb/>
     land is to be given to us. He says 640 acres, one mile square for 
     <lb/>
     each family, he will give us." And in a loud voice he shouted, 
     <lb/>
     "This is our land! It isn't a piece of pemmican to be cut off and 
     <lb/>
     given in little pieces back to us. It is ours and we will take what 
     <lb/>
     we want." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     A strong wave of approval came back from the seated 
     <lb/>
     Indians at his statement. <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Some braves</persName> in the last row rose to 
     <lb/>
     their feet, waved their hands and arms, shouting, "Yes! Yes! " in 
     <lb/>
     Cree. Apparently these were Poundmaker's followers. It was 
     <lb/>
     some time before the main chiefs could restore order. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Commissioner was visibly shaken by this demonstra<lb break="no"/>tion that erupted at the beginning. His assumption had been 
     <lb/>
     that the Indians had completely adopted his treaty terms, 
     <lb/>
     which by his own words he was not authorized to change in any 
     <lb/>
     

            <fw type="num">244</fw>
            <pb n="245" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_245.jpg"/>
    

     form. I thought to myself, "A boxer sent into the ring with his 
     <lb/>
     hands tied." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Governor went on to explain that unless certain lands 
     <lb/>
     were set aside for the sole use of the Indians, the country would 
     <lb/>
     be flooded with white settlers who would not give the Indians 
     <lb/>
     any consideration whatever. He made references to other areas 
     <lb/>
     where settlement was growing very fast. Morris's speech and 
     <lb/>
     explanation were couched in simple terms for the understand<lb break="no"/>ing of the Indian people. His manner held a sincerity that was 
     <lb/>
     most effective in impressing his audience. Knowing the 
     <lb/>
     Indians as I did, I could see that they were receiving the message 
     <lb/>
     with a growing understanding of its purpose. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Standing at the Governor's table I was able to observe the 
     <lb/>
     reactions of some of the listeners. I felt that Big Child and Star 
     <lb/>
     Blanket were both convinced of the fairness and justice of the 
     <lb/>
     terms explained to them by the speaker. I had an increased 
     <lb/>
     confidence in my interpretations, my sympathies transferred to 
     <lb/>
     the Governor's side, and my early animosity to the party was 
     <lb/>
     completely gone. The translations came to my tongue without 
     <lb/>
     effort and I seemed inspired to a tension that made my voice 
     <lb/>
     heard in the back rows where I had placed Hunter to give me a 
     <lb/>
     sign if my voice was not being heard distinctly. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MIST1">Mista-wa-sis</persName> rose to his feet at the conclusion of Morris's 
     <lb/>
     detailed explanations of the treaty terms and answers to 
     <lb/>
     questions that arose during the proceedings, saying, "We heard 
     <lb/>
     all you have told us and I want to tell the Governor how it is 
     <lb/>
     with us as well. When a thing is thought out quietly, that is the 
     <lb/>
     best way. I ask this of him today, that we go and think over his 
     <lb/>
     words." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MORR4">Governor Morris</persName> agreed with the chief and the meeting was 
     <lb/>
     adjourned till Monday. It was now Saturday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Indians did not hold a council on Sunday. The main 
     <lb/>
     chiefs said it was better to let the people have time to talk things 
     <lb/>
     over among themselves before calling a meeting. So word was 
     <lb/>
     sent to the Governor that they wanted to postpone the meeting 
     <lb/>
     till Tuesday. Permission was granted and a council called for 
     <lb/>
     Monday. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I was asked to attend the council with them and was 
     <lb/>
     personally escorted to the meeting by Mista-wa-sis and his ally 
     <lb/>
     Star Blanket. They said that I might be called upon to explain 
     <lb/>
     the talks, in case of any misunderstanding of my interpreta<lb break="no"/>tions of the treaty terms. "There are many among us who are 
     <lb/>
     trying to confuse and mislead the people; that is why I thought 
     <lb/>
     it best to give them lots of time for their bad work. Today they 
     <lb/>
     will have to come out in the open and will be forced to show 
     <lb/>
     their intentions," said <persName ref="pers:MIST1">Big Child</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <fw type="num">245</fw>
            <pb n="246" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_246.jpg"/>
            <p>
     <lb/>
     about an understanding among their own. people before 
     <lb/>
     meeting with the Commissioner. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Whether the treaty was actually misunderstood or deliber<lb break="no"/>ately misconstrued I know not, but the meeting was hardly 
     <lb/>
     underway when Big Child motioned me to disprove any wrong 
     <lb/>
     statement by those opposed to the agreement. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There were immediate objections to my taking part in the 
     <lb/>
     council but <persName ref="pers:AHTU1">Star Blanket</persName> got up and spoke most emphatically. 
     <lb/>
     "Mista-wa-sis and I fetched this man here at a great deal of 
     <lb/>
     trouble to ourselves because we were told that Peter Erasmus 
     <lb/>
     was learned in the language the Governor speaks. You all heard 
     <lb/>
     and saw the other men fail to interpret what he tried to say. He, 
     <lb/>
     Peter Erasmus, is the people's hired man. He is here to open our 
     <lb/>
     eyes and ears to the words that you and I cannot understand. 
     <lb/>
     Mista-wa-sis and I have asked him here to keep us right on what 
     <lb/>
     was offered in the treaty terms." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:AHTU1">Ah-tuk-a-kup</persName>'s words had the immediate effect of silencing 
     <lb/>
     any further attempts to confuse treaty terms. There was then no 
     <lb/>
     further need to dispute any statement intended to be misleading 
     <lb/>
     by those opposed or trying for better promises under the 
     <lb/>
     agreements. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The talks went on all day, only adjourned for a short noon- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     hour meal. Indian eloquence had full play that day. Many of 
     <lb/>
     the council men spoke in addition to the chiefs. There was a 
     <lb/>
     Chipewyan Indian present who argued considerable time 
     <lb/>
     away and was supported by Poundmaker and The Badger until 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">a council man</persName> rose and objected to his interference. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "This man is not a chief and has no authority to speak for 
     <lb/>
     his band. Why should he be allowed to interrupt the council 
     <lb/>
     and waste so much of our time?" 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There was loud assent from many voices and that silenced 
     <lb/>
     the voluble Chipewyan, whom I judged to be the main 
     <lb/>
     troublemaker. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:POUN1">Poundmaker</persName> and <persName ref="pers:BADG3">The Badger</persName> led the faction who were 
     <lb/>
     strong in their objections and refused to grant the possibility of 
     <lb/>
     existing by agricultural pursuits. These men had most of their 
     <lb/>
     support from those with less than thirty lodges to their count. 
     <lb/>
     Late that afternoon, I thought there was little hope of reaching 
     <lb/>
     an agreement. I was getting tired and about to ask permission 
     <lb/>
     to retire when I saw Ah-tuk-a-kup nod to Big Child. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MIST1">Mista-wa-sis</persName> rose to his feet. All afternoon he had sat 
     <lb/>
     without taking part in the speeches. All those who were taking 
     <lb/>
     part in the previous arguments sat down. There was silence as 
     <lb/>
     the man stood and waited for every person to be seated. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "I have heard my brothers speak, complaining of the 
     <lb/>
          

            <fw type="num">246</fw>
            <pb n="247" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_247.jpg"/>
         

     hardships endured by our people. Some have bewailed the 
     <lb/>
     poverty and suffering that has come to Indians because of the 
     <lb/>
     destruction of the buffalo as the chief source of our living, the 
     <lb/>
     loss of the ancient glory of our forefathers; and with all that I 
     <lb/>
     agree, in the silence of my teepee and on the broad prairies 
     <lb/>
     where once our fathers could not pass for the great number of 
     <lb/>
     those animals that blocked their way; and even in our day, we 
     <lb/>
     have had to choose carefully our campground for fear of being 
     <lb/>
     trampled in our teepees. With all these things, I think and feel 
     <lb/>
     intensely the sorrow my brothers express. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "I speak directly to Poundmaker and The Badger and those 
     <lb/>
     others who object to signing this treaty. Have you anything 
     <lb/>
     better to offer our people? I ask, again, can you suggest 
     <lb/>
     anything that will bring these things back for tomorrow and all 
     <lb/>
     the tomorrows that face our people? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "I for one think that the Great White Queen Mother has 
     <lb/>
     offered us a way of life when the buffalo are no more. Gone they 
     <lb/>
     will be before many snows have come to cover our heads or 
     <lb/>
     graves if such should be." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There were loud groans and exclamations of despair at the 
     <lb/>
     latter statement from many places among the group. Mista-wa- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     sis continued after waiting for the murmur to die down. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "I speak the tongue of the Blackfoot. I have been in their 
     <lb/>
     lodges. I have seen with my eyes and listened with my ears to the 
     <lb/>
     sorrows of that once-proud nation; people whom we have 
     <lb/>
     known as our enemies, the Peigan and the Bloods who are their 
     <lb/>
     brothers. Pay attention, listen hard to what I am about to say. 
     <lb/>
     The Big Knives of the south came into Blackfoot territory as 
     <lb/>
     traders; though few in number they have conquered these 
     <lb/>
     nations, and that, all the Crees in the days of our fathers and 
     <lb/>
     their fathers before them failed to do. How did they do it? Listen 
     <lb/>
     closely, my brothers, and you will understand. What was done 
     <lb/>
     to them can be done to us if we throw away the hand that is 
     <lb/>
     extended to us by this treaty. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "These traders, who were not of our land, with smooth talk 
     <lb/>
     and cheap goods persuaded the southern tribes it would be a 
     <lb/>
     good thing to have a place to trade products of the hunt, the 
     <lb/>
     hides and tanned goods. The traders came and built strong 
     <lb/>
     forts, and with their long rifles that can kill at twice the distance 
     <lb/>
     of our own and the short guns that can spout death six times 
     <lb/>
     quicker than you can tell about it, they had the people at their 
     <lb/>
     mercy. The Blackfoot soon found out the traders had nothing 
     <lb/>
     but whisky to exchange for their skins. Oh, yes! They were 
     <lb/>
     generous at first with their rotten whisky, but not for long. The 
     <lb/>
     traders demanded pay and got Blackfoot horses, buffalo robes, 
     <lb/>
     and all other things they had to offer. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <fw type="num">247</fw>
            <pb n="248" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_248.jpg"/>
            <p>
     "Those traders laughed at them for fools, and so they were, 
     <lb/>
     to sell their heritage for ruin and debauchery. Some of the 
     <lb/>
     bravest of the Blackfoot tried to get revenge for the losses but 
     <lb/>
     they were shot down like dogs and dragged to the open plains 
     <lb/>
     on horses to rot or be eaten by wolves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "The Great Queen Mother, hearing of the sorrows of her 
     <lb/>
     children, sent out the Red Coats. Though these were only of a 
     <lb/>
     number you could count on your fingers and toes, yet the 
     <lb/>
     cutthroats and criminals who recognized no authority but their 
     <lb/>
     guns, who killed each other on the slightest pretence and 
     <lb/>
     murdered Indians without fear of reprisal, immediately 
     <lb/>
     abandoned their forts, strong as they were, and fled back to their 
     <lb/>
     own side of the line. I ask you why those few men could put to 
     <lb/>
     flight those bad men who for years have defied the whole of the 
     <lb/>
     southern Indian nations? 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Surely these Red Coats are men of flesh and blood as 
     <lb/>
     ourselves and a bullet is just as effective on them as on any 
     <lb/>
     Blackfoot. Why of course, they are of flesh and blood. They 
     <lb/>
     could be killed as easily as any Blackfoot, but ask yourselves 
     <lb/>
     why the traders fled in fear from so few men. The southern 
     <lb/>
     tribes outnumbered this small Police Force one hundred to one, 
     <lb/>
     but they were helpless in spite of their numbers. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Let me tell you why these things were so. It was the power 
     <lb/>
     that stands behind those few Red Coats that those men feared 
     <lb/>
     and wasted no time in getting out when they could; the power 
     <lb/>
     that is represented in all the Queen's people, and we the 
     <lb/>
     children are counted as important as even the Governor who is 
     <lb/>
     her personal speaker. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "The Police are the Queen Mother's agents and have the 
     <lb/>
     same laws for whites as they have for the Indians. I have seen 
     <lb/>
     these things done and now the Blackfoot welcome these 
     <lb/>
     servants of the Queen Mother and invite her Governor for a 
     <lb/>
    treaty with them next year. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     "I, for one, look to the Queen's law and her Red Coat 
     <lb/>
     servants to protect our people against the evils of white man's 
     <lb/>
     firewater and to stop the senseless wars among our people, 
     <lb/>
     against the Blackfoot, Peigans, and Bloods. We have been in 
     <lb/>
     darkness; the Blackfoot and the others are people as we are. 
     <lb/>
     They will starve as we will starve when the buffalo are gone. We 
     <lb/>
     will be brothers in misery when we could have been brothers in 
     <lb/>
     plenty in times when there was no need for any man, woman, or 
     <lb/>
     child to be hungry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "We speak of glory and our memories are all that is left to 
     <lb/>
     feed the widows and orphans of those who have died in its 
     <lb/>
     attainment. We are few in numbers compared to former times, 
     <lb/>
     by wars and the terrible ravages of smallpox. Our people have 
     <lb/>
           

            <fw type="num">248</fw>
            <pb n="249" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_249.jpg"/>
        

     vanished too. Even if it were possible to gather all the tribes 
     <lb/>
     together, to throw away the hand that is offered to help us, we 
     <lb/>
     would be too weak to make our demands heard. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Look to the great Indian nations in the Long Knives' 
     <lb/>
     country who have been fighting since the memory of their 
     <lb/>
     oldest men. They are being vanquished and swept into the most 
     <lb/>
     useless parts of their country. Their days are numbered like 
     <lb/>
     those of the buffalo. There is no law or justice for the Indians in 
     <lb/>
     Long Knives' country. The Police followed two murderers to 
     <lb/>
     Montana and caught them but when they were brought to the 
     <lb/>
     Montana court they were turned free because it was not murder 
     <lb/>
     to kill an Indian. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "The prairies have not been darkened by the blood of our 
     <lb/>
     white brothers in our time. Let this always be so. I for one will 
     <lb/>
     take the hand that is offered. For my band I have spoken." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There was a deep silence after Mista-wa-sis had taken his 
     <lb/>
     seat. No one appeared to have anything to say. Then, finally, 
     <lb/>
     <persName ref="pers:AHTU1">Star Blanket</persName> rose to his feet and for along minute stood with his 
     <lb/>
     head bowed as if in deep thought or as if he had been 
     <lb/>
     profoundly impressed with the former speaker's words. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Yes," he said finally, "I have carried the dripping scalps of 
     <lb/>
     the Blackfoot on my belt and thought it was a great deed of 
     <lb/>
     bravery. I thought it was part of the glory of war but I now agree 
     <lb/>
     with Mista-wa-sis." Then he raised his voice so that it rang 
     <lb/>
     with the power of great conviction, "It is no longer a good 
     <lb/>
     thing. If we had been friends we might now be a host of people 
     <lb/>
     of all nations and together have power to demand the things 
     <lb/>
     some of you foolishly think you can get and insist on now 
     <lb/>
     demanding. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "No, that is not the road we took, but killed each other in 
     <lb/>
     continuous wars and in horse stealing, all for the glory we all 
     <lb/>
     speak of so freely. The great sickness took half our lodges and 
     <lb/>
     the dreaded disease fell as heavily on our enemies. We are weak 
     <lb/>
     and my brother Mista-wa-sis I think is right that the buffalo 
     <lb/>
     will be gone forever before many snows. What then will be left 
     <lb/>
     us with which to bargain? With the buffalo gone we will have 
     <lb/>
     only the vacant prairie which none of us have learned to use. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Can we stop the power of the white man from spreading 
     <lb/>
     over the land like the grasshoppers that cloud the sky and then 
     <lb/>
     fall to consume every blade of grass and every leaf on the trees in 
     <lb/>
     their path? I think not. Before this happens let us ponder 
     <lb/>
     carefully our choice of roads. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "There are men among you who are trying to blind our 
     <lb/>
     eyes, and refuse to see the things that have brought us to this 
     <lb/>
     pass. Let us not think of ourselves but of our children's 
     <lb/>
     children. We hold our place among the tribes as chiefs and 
     <lb/>
         

            <fw type="num">249</fw>
            <pb n="250" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_250.jpg"/>
          

     councillors because our people think we have wisdom above 
     <lb/>
     others amongst us. Then let us show our wisdom. Let us show 
     <lb/>
     our wisdom by choosing the right path now while we yet have a 
     <lb/>
     choice. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "We have always lived and received our needs in clothing, 
     <lb/>
     shelter, and food from the countless multitudes of buffalo that 
     <lb/>
     have been with us since the earliest memory of our people. No- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     one with open eyes and open minds can doubt that the buffalo 
     <lb/>
     will soon be a thing of the past. Will our people live as before 
     <lb/>
     when this comes to pass? No! They will die and become just a 
     <lb/>
     memory unless we find another way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "For my part, I think that the Queen Mother has offered us a 
     <lb/>
     new way and I have faith in the things my brother Mista-wa-sis 
     <lb/>
     has told you. The mother earth has always given us plenty with 
     <lb/>
     the grass that fed the buffalo. Surely we Indians can learn the 
     <lb/>
     ways of living that made the white man strong and able to 
     <lb/>
     vanquish all the great tribes of the southern nations. The white 
     <lb/>
     men never had the buffalo but I am told they have cattle in the 
     <lb/>
     thousands that are covering the prairie for miles and will 
     <lb/>
     replace the buffalo in the Long Knives' country and may even 
     <lb/>
     spread over our lands. The white men number their lodges by 
     <lb/>
     the thousands, not like us who can only count our teepees by 
     <lb/>
     tens. I will accept the Queen's hand for my people. I have 
     <lb/>
     spoken." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     With the last of his words, the councillors of both main 
     <lb/>
     speakers rose to their feet, together held up their hands as a 
     <lb/>
     gesture of acceptance, and again took their places. Other chiefs 
     <lb/>
     among the assembly spoke a few words in agreement. The 
     <lb/>
     greater majority with a few exceptions had accepted the views 
     <lb/>
     of the two main chiefs. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MIST1">Mista-wa-sis</persName> adjourned the meeting by saying, "It is good 
     <lb/>
     that my brothers go back to their teepees and study these 
     <lb/>
     matters with care. We will not be hasty. You will have a chance 
     <lb/>
     to ask questions on things you want cleared up. We will have 
     <lb/>
     our interpreter mark down the things we think we should 
     <lb/>
     have." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To this the Indians agreed. Dismissed, many of the chiefs 
     <lb/>
     came up and shook hands with Mista-wa-sis and Ah-tuk-a- 
     <lb break="yes"/>
     kup, thus expressing their unanimous approval of the speeches 
     <lb/>
     of the two men that had swung the meeting in favour of treaty 
     <lb/>
     terms. I noticed that Poundmaker and The Badger were not 
     <lb/>
     among those who came forward to shake hands. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     After I had retired to our tent, I lay awake thinking of the 
     <lb/>
     things spoken by the two chiefs, and marvelled at the 
     <lb/>
     confidence they both felt in the fairness of the justice carried out 
     <lb/>
     by this slender arm of the Queen Mother. The statement that 
     <lb/>
        

            <fw type="num">250</fw>
            <pb n="251" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_251.jpg"/>
        

     the Police had the same laws for white men and the Indians was 
     <lb/>
     true of our country, whereas only the previous year some 
     <lb/>
     Americans had committed murder on our side of the line. They 
     <lb/>
     had been followed to Montana and arrested but when they were 
     <lb/>
     brought before the Montana court, in spite of all the clear 
     <lb/>
     evidence of their guilt, the case was dismissed. The men had 
     <lb/>
     only killed Indians and that was not considered a crime on that 
     <lb/>
     side of the line.
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On Tuesday the Indians were slow in gathering at the 
     <lb/>
     Governor's tent. Poundmaker and The Badger were trying to 
     <lb/>
     gather support for their demands in the matter of treaty terms. 
     <lb/>
     Majority opinion had forced them to a grudging consent at the 
     <lb/>
     meeting. The Chipewyan was again active wherever he could 
     <lb/>
     find an audience, and backed by the other two men had 
     <lb/>
     regained his former boldness. But I noticed he was having 
     <lb/>
     difficulty in getting anyone to listen. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The Governor did not waste any time on preliminary talk 
     <lb/>
     but said he was ready to listen to the people and was prepared to 
     <lb/>
     clear up any question about which there was any doubt. 
     <lb/>
     Poundmaker immediately spoke, asking help when the 
     <lb/>
     Indians started to settle on the reserves. <persName ref="pers:BADG3">The Badger</persName> took up the 
     <lb/>
     theme with more elaboration. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "We think of our children. We do not want to be greedy but 
     <lb/>
     when we commence to settle on the reserves we select, it is then 
     <lb/>
     we want aid and when we can't help ourselves in case of 
     <lb/>
     trouble."
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
               <persName ref="pers:SAKA2">Sakamoos</persName> and <persName ref="pers:ANON1">others</persName> spoke, referring to portions of the 
     <lb/>
     treaty in regard to settlement on reserves, the need for medical 
     <lb/>
     help, and guidance in regard to the new project of agriculture. 
     <lb/>
     A summary of their remarks meant that they wanted assistance 
     <lb/>
     to get established in their new occupation of agriculture, not 
     <lb/>
     only financially but also in instruction and management. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Then the <persName ref="pers:MCKA4">Hon. James McKay</persName>, in a somewhat arrogant tone, 
     <lb/>
     admonished them in Cree for their demands. "In my experience 
     <lb/>
     you always want more than you were promised in the first place 
     <lb/>
     and you are never satisfied with what is given you." He made 
     <lb/>
     other biting remarks detrimental to the character of the 
     <lb/>
     Indian.
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     In view of my knowledge of what had transpired at their 
     <lb/>
     council I thought his speech most unfortunate and very 
     <lb/>
     harmful. His very attitude insulted the intelligence of his 
     <lb/>
     listeners. There was distinct murmur of disapproval all over 
     <lb/>
     the crowd. McKay had hardly taken his seat when <persName ref="pers:BADG3">The Badger</persName> 
     <lb/>
     leapt to his feet.  
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "I did not say that I wanted to be fed every day. You, I know, 
     <lb/>
     understand our language and yet you twist my words to suit 
     <lb/>
           

            <fw type="num">251</fw>
            <pb n="252" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_252.jpg"/>
    

     your own meaning. What I did say was that when we settle on 
     <lb/>
     the ground to work the land, that is when we will need help and 
     <lb/>
     that is the only way a poor Indian can get along." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The speech that McKay had made was not interpreted into 
     <lb/>
     English but Morris could see that it had made a bad impression 
     <lb/>
     on the people by the angry stir that prevailed. <persName ref="pers:ERAS1">I</persName> interpreted all 
     <lb/>
     Indian replies and said, "Let McKay, the Honourable James, 
     <lb/>
     explain his own speech." However, I noticed the Governor did 
     <lb/>
     not take the trouble to inquire into the contents of McKay's 
     <lb/>
     speech that had so roused the Indians.
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "You will remember the promise that I have already made," 
     <lb/>
     he said instead. "You will get the seed and you need not concern 
     <lb/>
     yourselves about what your children will eat. They will be 
     <lb/>
     taught and be able to look after themselves." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MIST1">Big Child</persName> spoke, "It is well known that if we have plenty in 
     <lb/>
     our gardens and crops we would not insist on getting more 
     <lb/>
     provisions, but it is only in the case of extremity and from the 
     <lb/>
     ignorance of Indians in commencing to work the land that we 
     <lb/>
     speak. We are in the dark. This is no trivial matter with us."
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "The things we have talked over in our Council, we think 
     <lb/>
     are for our good," said <persName ref="pers:AHTU1">Star Blanket</persName>. "I believe that the good 
     <lb/>
     councillors of the Queen Mother and her commissioners know 
     <lb/>
     what is best for them. I was told that the Governor was a good 
     <lb/>
     man and now that I have seen him and listened to him talk, I 
     <lb/>
     know I heard right. He has removed some of the obstacles to our 
     <lb/>
     understanding and I hope he will remove them all."
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Star Blanket paused in his discourse as Big Child rose to his 
     <lb/>
     feet and demanded silence from the back where the Chipewyan 
     <lb/>
     was again causing a disturbance. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Star Blanket continued, "We want food in the spring, when 
     <lb/>
     we begin to farm; according as the Indian settles on the land 
     <lb/>
     and as he advances, his needs will increase. I would now ask the 
     <lb/>
     Governor to give us time to consider all the things that he has 
     <lb/>
     told us today." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This was granted, with a warning from the Commissioner 
     <lb/>
     that he could not spend too much time with them as he had 
     <lb/>
     other tribes to treat with that would be waiting for him. He 
     <lb/>
     further stated that he had heard that the buffalo were near and 
     <lb/>
     they would want to be on their way to get their winter 
     <lb/>
     provisions. "Food, my friends, is getting scarce in camp." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MORR4">The Governor</persName> now turned to the Chipewyan who had been 
     <lb/>
     making a disturbance in the crowd. "You are only one of those 
     <lb/>
     people you claim to represent. You are no wiser than your tribe 
     <lb/>
     who have already accepted treaty terms with the Government. 
     <lb/>
     If you have anything to say, I will speak to your people after I 
     <lb/>
     have finished with the Crees." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <fw type="num">252</fw>
            <pb n="253" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_253.jpg"/>
            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:TEET1">Teequaysay</persName> on the following day got up at the outset of the 
     <lb/>
     meeting to say, "Listen, my friends, all of you sitting around 
     <lb/>
     here, be patient and listen to what our interpreter has been 
     <lb/>
     instructed to tell you. What he will tell you are the things our 
     <lb/>
     main chiefs and councillors have decided to ask for and have 
     <lb/>
     agreed are for our best interests. There will be no more talk or 
     <lb/>
     questions asked of the Governor."
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I first explained to the Commissioner that the document I 
     <lb/>
     was about to read had been prepared by the main chiefs and 
     <lb/>
     their councillors and actually contained little more than what 
     <lb/>
     already had been promised, but I had been asked to read the 
     <lb/>
     petition to all the people for their agreement. Thus I 
     <lb/>
     interpreted the contents to the Indians before handing it to the 
     <lb/>
     Governor. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MORR4">The Governor</persName> then spoke at some length as he dealt with 
     <lb/>
     each section of the petition and gave reasons for the few of the 
     <lb/>
     things that could not be granted. However, he consented to a 
     <lb/>
     grant of one thousand dollars to assist those actually engaged 
     <lb/>
     in farming land on the reserves, but this would operate for three 
     <lb/>
     years only. This would apply to each band. They would receive 
     <lb/>
     a plough and harrow for three families under the same 
     <lb/>
     conditions. They would be at liberty to hunt and trap on 
     <lb/>
     government lands the same as before. The things they would be 
     <lb/>
     getting would be a present on top of what they had before nor 
     <lb/>
     would they be compelled to go to war except on their own free 
     <lb/>
     will. A medicine chest would be placed in the house of every 
     <lb/>
     agent for the free use of the band. Each band would get four 
     <lb/>
     oxen, one bull and six cows, one boar and two pigs. After a 
     <lb/>
     band had settled on its reserve and started to raise grain, they 
     <lb/>
     would get one hand mill. Each chief would get one horse, 
     <lb/>
    harness and wagon. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Most of the chiefs expressed agreement, but Poundmaker 
     <lb/>
     was still not satisfied. <persName ref="pers:TOMA1">Joseph Toma</persName> asked for guns and said he 
     <lb/>
     was speaking for <persName ref="pers:REDP1">Red Pheasant</persName>. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MORR4">Morris</persName> replied, "When the list of things the interpreter read 
     <lb/>
     was handed to me, Red Pheasant sat in silence and I presumed 
     <lb/>
     he was satisfied as the others were. Then the principal chiefs 
     <lb/>
     expressed approval. I cannot grant your request." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:REDP1">Red Pheasant</persName> got up and repudiated the statement of 
     <lb/>
     Joseph Toma's as his own and not by his permission. That 
     <lb/>
     terminated the discussion in the formation of the treaty terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MORR4">The Governor</persName> thanked the Indians for their attention and 
     <lb/>
     co-operation in all the proceedings and stated that the 
     <lb/>
     additional requests would be written in the treaty in all things 
     <lb/>
     he had agreed to. These special provisions were added into the 
     <lb/>
     draft of the treaty before the signing began. There were fifty 
     <lb/>
           

            <fw type="num">253</fw>
            <pb n="254" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_254.jpg"/>
          

     signatures to that historic document and other adhesions 
     <lb/>
     followed the same wording as that signed at Carlton. The 
     <lb/>
     reading of the treaty took a great deal of time and required the 
     <lb/>
     services of all the interpreters but this time there were no 
     <lb/>
     fireworks in the matter of words used, nor the objection to 
     <lb/>
     Ballenden's voice. Half the Indians were not concerned. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Mista-wa-sis had called me aside and told me to keep a close 
     <lb/>
     watch on the wording to see that it included everything that 
     <lb/>
     had been promised. However, the other chiefs appeared 
     <lb/>
     satisfied that the Governor would carry out his promises to the 
     <lb/>
     letter. I was able to assure Mista-wa-sis that everything 
     <lb/>
     promised had been included in the writing. He was satisfied 
     <lb/>
     and his name was the first in the signing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The following day the Governor was at his tent at ten 
     <lb/>
     o'clock while the chiefs' uniforms were issued, complete with 
     <lb/>
     medals and a flag. The councilmen were to receive theirs at the 
     <lb/>
     Hudson's Bay store. The Governor gave them a short discourse 
     <lb/>
     on the meaning of the uniforms, which in substance meant that 
     <lb/>
     they were now representatives of the Queen Mother and to see 
     <lb/>
     that their people should receive justice, and on their part to 
     <lb/>
     fulfill the obligations contained in their positions. There 
     <lb/>
     would be an issue of uniforms to the men that they chose from 
     <lb/>
     time to time to represent them as chiefs and councillors. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There was a great deal of hand-shaking and some fine 
     <lb/>
     compliments exchanged on both sides before the Governor 
     <lb/>
     took his departure. Mista-wa-sis and Star Blanket, I knew, 
     <lb/>
     meant every word they said, as did the Governor. Poundmaker 
     <lb/>
     was equally well versed in complimentary words but I felt 
     <lb/>
     certain that he didn't mean a word he said; in this I was right, 
     <lb/>
     for eight years later he served in jail for his activities in the Riel 
     <lb/>
     Rebellion. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Treaty payments were started immediately after the 
     <lb/>
     signing. Christie was in charge and retained me for the balance 
     <lb/>
     of that day to assist in the interpretations. "Peter, the Governor 
     <lb/>
     wishes to see you at the fort this evening for a private talk and I 
     <lb/>
     believe Clarke has something to say as well," he advised me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Later in the evening I made the call. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "I'm proud of you, Erasmus," said Clarke, "the way you 
     <lb/>
     handled the first day of the talks. I was in a bad spot after hiring 
     <lb/>
     those two men. I could not go back on my word." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Well, as it turned out there was no harm done, but I hope 
     <lb/>
     you realize that your actions almost created a riot and could 
     <lb/>
     have wrecked the whole business. Trying to pretend you did 
     <lb/>
     not know me that first evening I considered a rank insult, and 
     <lb/>
     that, my high-minded friend, I do not take without repayment. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <fw type="num">254</fw>
            <pb n="255" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_255.jpg"/>
            <p>
     Further, you should know that you cannot treat men like 
     <lb/>
     Mista-wa-sis and Ah-tuk-a-kup as children, and the manner in 
     <lb/>
     which the Honourable James spoke during the meeting was 
     <lb/>
     equally as stupid." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Well, Peter, I hope you hold no grudge. You can 
     <lb/>
     understand the position I was in at the time. I hope you will 
     <lb/>
     forget the whole miserable business." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Certainly, Clarke. The victor is never the man to bear a 
     <lb/>
     grudge; it is always the loser, and I hope you bear that in 
     <lb/>
     mind." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Later in the day I had an interview with the Governor which 
     <lb/>
     was more than satisfactory, as he shook hands with me and told 
     <lb/>
     me to take a seat. Christie was present and appeared to be busy 
     <lb/>
     with treaty business. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Your salary will be five dollars a day, as you have 
     <lb/>
     interpreted for the Indians as well as the government." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "He has done two men's work," said Christie, "so he is 
     <lb/>
     entitled to that money as well. And the man has travelled 
     <lb/>
     several hundred miles to be here — he should be given 
     <lb/>
     something for that." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "You are right, Mr. Christie," replied the Governor. "Put 
     <lb/>
     him down for fifteen dollars for four days' pay. He will be paid 
     <lb/>
     at five dollars a day during treaty negotiations and a travel 
     <lb/>
     allowance until I am through at Fort Pitt." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This was indeed good news and the unexpected support 
     <lb/>
     from Mr. Christie was, you can believe me, more than ample 
     <lb/>
     compensation for  my real or imagined slight of the first 
     <lb/>
     evening of the talks. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "You may go with me to Fort Pitt by way of Battleford or 
     <lb/>
     you can go direct to Fort Pitt and meet me there. You will be 
     <lb/>
     paid at the rate of five dollars per day for travelling and the 
     <lb/>
     same for interpreting when I arrive." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "I would prefer to go direct to Fort Pitt as I have a friend 
     <lb/>
     with me who will take care of some supplies that I intend to 
     <lb/>
     take back to my people." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
            <p>
     So it was arranged to meet at Fort Pitt. 
     <lb/>
     
            </p>
            <p>Hunter, during all our stay at Carlton, had taken care of our 
     <lb/>horses, and also made himself useful in keeping me informed of 
     <lb/>all the latest developments in camp in relation to the activities 
     <lb/>and opinions in regard to treaty talks. I was thus free to devote 
     <lb/>all my time to a study of the treaty terms in the conduct of my 
     <lb/>duties. He had cultivated a friendship with Mista-wa-sis and 
     <lb/>Ah-tuk-a-kup, and I suspect kept them fully informed on all 
     <lb/>angles of their opposition. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     On the morning of the twenty-fifth, we were making 
     <lb/>
        

            <fw type="num">255</fw>
            <pb n="256" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_256.jpg"/>
        

     preparations to go to Fort Pitt when the two main chiefs called 
     <lb/>
     at our teepee to inform us that they had not collected all the 
     <lb/>
     money from their Indians for our pay. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "We were waiting for the Indians to receive all their treaty 
     <lb/>
     money before we started collecting your money." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I replied: "We will have to start today or this evening as it 
     <lb/>
     will just give us time to meet our appointment with the 
     <lb/>
    Governor." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     "All right," said Star Blanket. "We will start at once and see 
     <lb/>
     what we can do. You must wait until we see you later in the 
     <lb/>
     day." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     They handed me two hundred and thirty dollars that 
     <lb/>
     afternoon, and with the sixty I had received from the paymaster 
     <lb/>
     Mr. Christie, I felt well paid for my trip. I thanked them for the 
     <lb/>
     money and told them I was well satisfied with the amount they 
     <lb/>
     gave me. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     An Indian stopped me while I was making the rounds of the 
     <lb/>
     traders' stores and offered to buy Whitey, my buffalo runner 
     <lb/>
     horse. "I want a hundred dollars for him without the saddle or 
     <lb/>
     bridle," I said. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     He accepted at once and handed me a roll of bills for me to 
     <lb/>
     count out the money. I called Hunter to witness the counting, 
     <lb/>
     as he had been instructed in the use of money. The animal was 
     <lb/>
     good value for the price but I mention this incident to show 
     <lb/>
     how easily at that time the Indians could have been cheated out 
     <lb/>
     of their money. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I bought a good stout cart horse harnessed to a cart for fifty 
     <lb/>
     dollars to carry our duffle and the goods we bought. The traders 
     <lb/>
     were getting ready to move to the next trading spot at Fort Pitt 
     <lb/>
     and were offering some good deals to lighten their loads. I 
     <lb/>
     bought a shotgun practically new for about half the asking 
     <lb/>
     price from my new brother-in-law, then loaded our carts with 
     <lb/>
     staple articles of food and a stove. This would be the first 
     <lb/>
     cooking stove we would have since our marriage. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     At our evening stop I took the gun and presented it to John 
     <lb/>
     Hunter; his pleasure was something to see, as he alternately 
     <lb/>
     polished the blued steel of the barrel and took aim as if to get 
     <lb/>
     used to the feel of the gun. Then I showed him a handsome 
     <lb/>
     piece of good print for dresses for his wife and some household 
     <lb/>
     utensils as well, but when I showed him all those things his 
     <lb/>
     former pleasure evaporated and he looked very grim. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Peter," he said, "I cannot accept this gun with all the other 
     <lb/>
     things that you have bought for us. I never could match such a 
     <lb/>
     gift with a return. It is too much. My wife shall have all the 
     <lb/>
     things you bought for her but I am sorry you must take the gun 
     <lb/>
     back." 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <fw type="num">256</fw>
            <pb n="257" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_257.jpg"/>
            <p>
     "That gun, my friend, is not a gift. It is in payment for all 
     <lb/>
     the work looking after the horses and your trouble mixing with 
     <lb/>
     the Indians to bring back a report of what was going on in 
     <lb/>
     camp. You have earned the price of that gun five times over. 
     <lb/>
     Without your help, I could not have prepared my interpreta<lb break="no"/>tions or made myself familiar with all the things the Governor 
     <lb/>
     had to tell the people in that paper the chiefs and councillors 
     <lb/>
     signed." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Yes," said Hunter, "but I was doing those things for my 
     <lb/>
     own pleasure and didn't know that it was any help to you. I 
     <lb/>
     would have looked after the horses in any case." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "You must not think," I said, "that I would be so ungrateful 
     <lb/>
     and selfish as to take all that pay and not give you something 
     <lb/>
     for all your wife has done for us and all the kind friendly acts 
     <lb/>
     you have done for me personally." Assuming an angry tone, I 
     <lb/>
     said, "Throw the gun away if you wish. It is yours to do what 
     <lb/>
     you like with it. I do not need another gun as I have one at home 
     <lb/>
     just as good." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     He was profuse in his apologies. Luckily I had hit on the 
     <lb/>
     only theme that could dissolve his ethical beliefs that a gift 
     <lb/>
     must always have compensation. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "You must give those things to my wife as a gift. Do not give 
     <lb/>
     her those things as payment for care of your wife, or she will be 
     <lb/>
     hurt and refuse them even as a gift." I had not thought of it his 
     <lb/>
     way. Such delicate management hadn't occurred to me. To pay 
     <lb/>
     his wife for what they considered a friendly service would be 
     <lb/>
     putting a price on friendship that would take away the pleasure 
     <lb/>
     of doing things for your real friends. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We were both happy on the first leg of our journey towards 
     <lb/>
     home. We were well satisfied with our trip. John Hunter was a 
     <lb/>
     chief in his own tribe. His name interpreted in English was 
     <lb/>
     Little Hunter. He was not a small man as his name would 
     <lb/>
     indicate but I found that the name may have been received as a 
     <lb/>
     child. He was not a big man but he certainly wasn't little either 
     <lb/>
     in physical stature or in character. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Poundmaker," he said while discussing the meeting, "is 
     <lb/>
     not satisfied, nor will he ever be satisfied. He does not think but 
     <lb/>
     just talks and keeps on talking. He and some of the others will 
     <lb/>
     make trouble. Times will be hard for the prairie Indians once 
     <lb/>
     the buffalo are gone. They will have nothing and will not settle 
     <lb/>
     on the land until they are nearing starvation. Steinhauer has 
     <lb/>
     often told us that we must learn to farm and raise animals to 
     <lb/>
     support ourselves for the day when the buffalo will be no more. 
     <lb/>
     Now I have to believe him. We are lucky that we already know 
     <lb/>
     something about raising grain and vegetables, and besides we 
     <lb/>
     still have bush game and fish. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <fw type="num">257</fw>
            <pb n="258" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_258.jpg"/>
            <p>
     We arrived at Fort Pitt ahead of the government party. A 
     <lb/>
     detachment of Police was already camped on the north side of 
     <lb/>
     the river and I counted a hundred Indian teepees camped on the 
     <lb/>
     flat near the fort. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We crossed the river with a boat that some traders were 
     <lb/>
     using to carry their goods across. Although the river was 
     <lb/>
     unusually low that fall, crossing goods over safely always gave 
     <lb/>
     some concern. By assisting the traders, we got the use of their 
     <lb/>
     boat that made the crossing a simple matter. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On the morning of September the fifth, the Governor and 
     <lb/>
     his party arrived with a Police escort that had gone out to meet 
     <lb/>
     him. All the tribes that were to meet there had not yet arrived 
     <lb/>
     but they had sent riders ahead to tell the others of their coming. 
     <lb/>
     Finally on the sixth, the last of the tribes pitched their teepees 
     <lb/>
     with the others. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I was resting under my cart when William Bull of the James 
     <lb/>
     Seenum band came to where I was resting. "The chiefs have 
     <lb/>
     called a meeting and have sent me to bring you to speak to 
     <lb/>
     them." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I thought it necessary for one of us to stay with our cart as 
     <lb/>
     there was a host of prowling dogs around. Train dogs are 
     <lb/>
     cunning beasts and I always said that I thought they would 
     <lb/>
     sooner steal than be fed in a proper way. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Go ahead," said Hunter. "I can keep your shady couch 
     <lb/>
     warm till you return. Then we will move in with the chief 
     <lb/>
     Seenum and William who have invited us to share their teepee. 
     <lb/>
     We can get a canvas and bind our load for safety." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I was questioned at some length about the attitude of the 
     <lb/>
     tribes who signed the treaty at Carlton, about details in 
     <lb/>
     reference to treaty concessions, and the terms agreed upon, 
     <lb/>
     which by that time I had memorized by heart. I gave them a 
     <lb/>
     review of the discussions of the council meeting of the chiefs at 
     <lb/>
     Carlton, reporting the objections raised by those who opposed 
     <lb/>
     the signing, and spoke of the petition that had been drawn up 
     <lb/>
     for the Commissioner, with the points agreed to and those 
     <lb/>
     refused. I mentioned Poundmaker's and The Badger's efforts at 
     <lb/>
     trying to block or misinterpret the terms of the treaty, at which 
     <lb/>
     there were some expressions of disgust about their attitude." 
     <lb/>
    Then I wound up my talk by a report of the two speeches made 
     <lb/>by Mista-wa-sis and Ah-tuk-a-kup that had swung the whole 
     <lb/>opinion of the assembly in favour of the signing. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     I could see that the content of these two speeches had a 
     <lb/>
     tremendous effect on my audience, as I had reserved the latter 
     <lb/>
     for the last before sitting down. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WEEK1">Sweet Grass</persName>, who was the most important chief among 
     <lb/>
         

            <fw type="num">258</fw>
            <pb n="259" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_259.jpg"/>
         

     those gathered in council, rose to his feet to speak to their 
     <lb/>
     people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Mista-wa-sis and Ah-tuk-a-kup, I consider, are far wiser 
     <lb/>
     than I am; therefore if they have accepted this treaty for their 
     <lb/>
     people after many days of talk and careful thought, then I am 
     <lb/>
     prepared to accept for my people." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SEEN1">Chief Seenum</persName> then took his place and spoke. "You have all 
     <lb/>
     questioned Peter Erasmus on the things that have taken place 
     <lb/>
     at Carlton. He is a stranger to many of you but I am well 
     <lb/>
     acquainted with him. I have respect for his words and have 
     <lb/>
     confidence in his truthfulness. Mista-wa-sis and Ah-tuk-a-kup 
     <lb/>
     both sent their sons all the way from Carlton to where he lives, 
     <lb/>
     and he is married to one of our favourite daughters. He was not 
     <lb/>
     at home but they followed him to the prairie where he was 
     <lb/>
     hunting buffalo with our people. Little Hunter is a chief and 
     <lb/>
     brings back a good report of his work during treaty talks. He 
     <lb/>
     would not tell us something that was not for our good. 
     <lb/>
     Therefore, as those other chiefs who are in greater number than 
     <lb/>
     we are have found this treaty good, I and my head man will sign 
     <lb/>
     for our people. I have spoken." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:ANON1">Each of the other chiefs</persName> with their councillors expressed 
     <lb/>
     agreement, each man expressing in his own words ideas that 
     <lb/>
     conformed to the general acceptance of treaty terms. They were 
     <lb/>
     all willing to sign the treaty and there was not a single 
     <lb/>
     dissenting voice. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     There was some delay on the morning of the seventh, which 
     <lb/>
     was the day set for the meeting with the Governor, as it was 
     <lb/>
     found that there were insufficient young men for the 
     <lb/>
     manoeuvres that always preceded a gathering of this kind as at 
     <lb/>
     the meeting at Carlton. Finally two young men volunteered 
     <lb/>
     their help. They were in training but as yet were not considered 
     <lb/>
     fully qualified. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The riders were performing in front of the people who were 
     <lb/>
     advancing to the Commissioner's tent when suddenly the two 
     <lb/>
     young men got confused in their movements and crashed their 
     <lb/>
     horses into each other. Both men were thrown to the ground, 
     <lb/>
     receiving injuries, and the horses were hurt. Fortunately there 
     <lb/>
     was a Police doctor on hand who took charge of the injured 
     <lb/>
     men. One had a dislocated hip while the other had only minor 
     <lb/>
     injuries; as they were taken care of the proceedings went ahead. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     To an inexperienced person, viewing it for the first time, the 
     <lb/>
     show would appear to be a disorganized, undisciplined, crazy 
     <lb/>
     display of horsemanship, but this was not true. I had watched 
     <lb/>
     them training from a slow walking speed; all movements had 
     <lb/>
     an exact timing that was finally speeded up to manoeuvres that 
     <lb/>
   

            <fw type="num">259</fw>
            <pb n="260" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_260.jpg"/>
 

     were carried out with a speed and intricacy of movement that 
     <lb/>
     was most confusing to those watching for the first time. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     When the people were finally seated in their usual posture, 
     <lb/>
     sitting cross-legged, the Governor opened his address. There 
     <lb/>
     were no interruptions, but quiet attentive listening. At the 
     <lb/>
     conclusion of his talks, he asked the people for their opinions, 
     <lb/>
     but no one responded. There was a considerable pause as he 
     <lb/>
     waited for their reaction to his words. Morris looked puzzled, or 
     <lb/>
     rather "disappointed" might be the better description of his 
     <lb/>
     attitude. At other places he had received many objections and a 
     <lb/>
     lot of questions. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Finally <persName ref="pers:KIHE1">Chief Eagle</persName> got to his feet, faced the people, and told 
     <lb/>
     them not to be afraid to speak their minds. If there was 
     <lb/>
     anything they did not understand or wished to know, this was 
     <lb/>
     the place and the time to express their thoughts. However, there 
     <lb/>
     was no response; apparently they had made up their minds the 
     <lb/>
     day previously. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:WEEK1">Sweet Grass</persName> made a speech of some length, expressing his 
     <lb/>
     willingness on behalf of his people to accept the treaty terms 
     <lb/>
     and summed up his address by saying, "I am no wiser than my 
     <lb/>
     brothers at Fort Carlton who have accepted the Queen Mother's 
     <lb/>
     hand. I will sign for my people." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SEEN1">James Seenum</persName> spoke with some feeling, referring to the 
     <lb/>
     plough he had received as a gift from Mr. Christie some years 
     <lb/>
     previously. He stated that they had pulled the plough by 
     <lb/>
     manpower when their ponies had refused to work, had used the 
     <lb/>
     roots of trees for hoes, and had now learned the value of 
     <lb/>
     growing grain and vegetables. He was greatly pleased to know 
     <lb/>
     that now they would be furnished with better tools and the 
     <lb/>
     means to work the land. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:SEEN1">Chief Seenum</persName> asked for a large tract of land. "For my part, I 
     <lb/>
     wish to say that I want a large area to settle all the Cree — the 
     <lb/>
     Woods Crees and Plain Crees — who may not now be taken in 
     <lb/>
     by the treaties at this time."
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Apparently he wanted a general reserve that would 
     <lb/>
     accommodate all Indians who might not at this time be willing 
     <lb/>
     to choose land and which would be set apart for this purpose. 
     <lb/>
     The chief went on to say, "I want an area from the Whitemud 
     <lb/>
     River to Dog Rump Creek, extending back as far as the Beaver 
     <lb/>
     River and its southern border to be the Saskatchewan River." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     <persName ref="pers:MORR4">The Governor</persName> replied that he could not promise such a 
     <lb/>
     large tract of land without consultation with his superiors. The 
     <lb/>
     area selected was beyond his instructions. "It is not in my 
     <lb/>
     power to add clauses to this treaty, no more than you have 
     <lb/>
     already been promised, but I will bring your request before the 
     <lb/>
     House at Ottawa. However, I know it will not be accepted. As 
     <lb/>
      

            <fw type="num">260</fw>
            <pb n="261" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_261.jpg"/>
    

     you said so, being a chief, I will bring the matter to the 
     <lb/>
     attention of my superiors." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Eight years afterward, in June of 1884, James Seenum 
     <lb/>
     engaged me to accompany him and interpret in regard to his 
     <lb/>
     request for a large area as requested in this treaty at Fort Pitt. 
     <lb/>
     We went to Regina where he was successful in getting the 
     <lb/>
     Saddle Lake Reserve lines extended to take in a block of land to 
     <lb/>
     the east. He had amended his claims considerably but won his 
     <lb/>
     demands for better farm land, because the Whitefish and 
     <lb/>
     Goodfish Reserves were not large enough to accommodate the 
     <lb/>
     young people according to the average per-person allowance 
     <lb/>
     by treaty terms. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     On September 9th, the treaty terms were read and explained 
     <lb/>
     to the people. The chiefs agreed to sign, and so the treaty was 
     <lb/>
     quickly completed with none of the dissension that had 
     <lb/>
     occurred at Carlton. The paying of treaty money and issuing of 
     <lb/>
     uniforms took the greater part of two more days. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     Governor Morris advised me that I would now be in the 
     <lb/>
     government service and that he would recommend me at a 
     <lb/>
     salary of fifty dollars per month. I would act for the government 
     <lb/>
     in the distribution of rations and goods in fulfillment of the 
     <lb/>
     government's part of the treaty terms. I would also be called 
     <lb/>
     upon from time to time to interpret the treaties to those chiefs 
     <lb/>
     who had not yet signed. I was to remain at my present abode at 
     <lb/>
     Whitefish Lake for the purpose of handling matters concerned 
     <lb/>
     with Indians of that area and its precincts. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     This information was most agreeable and an entirely 
     <lb/>
     different prospect than that I was faced with on my first 
     <lb/>
     appearance at Carlton. Governor Morris further advised me 
     <lb/>
     that I would be on call for any assignment for which my 
     <lb/>
     services might be required. To all this I agreed, suitably 
     <lb/>
     expressing my appreciation of his confidence and assuring him 
     <lb/>
     of my fidelity in the accomplishment of my duties. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The departure of Governor Morris and his entourage was 
     <lb/>
     attended by all the chiefs and their head men, with considerable 
     <lb/>
     show of appreciation and good wishes from the Indians at Fort 
     <lb/>
     Pitt. For myself, I felt that all the chiefs there would carry out 
     <lb/>
     their obligations with sincerity and would make every effort to 
     <lb/>
     assist their people to become established on the reserves that 
     <lb/>
     they would choose the following summer. This was verified in 
     <lb/>
     later years when I had an opportunity of visiting some of their 
     <lb/>
     reserves. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The camp now broke up. William Bull came to me and said 
     <lb/>
     he wanted to travel home with me. I was glad and arranged 
     <lb/>
     with him to drive one of the carts. I bought another cart and 
     <lb/>
     horse from a trader at a very low price as he had sold out his 
     <lb/>
      

            <fw type="num">261</fw>
            <pb n="262" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_262.jpg"/>
         

     goods and did not need the outfit on his return to Fort Garry. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I also bought five sacks of flour from the government stores 
     <lb/>
     from stock they had on hand to meet requirements of the 
     <lb/>
     Indians in the treaty negotiations, a half keg of tea, and a half 
     <lb/>
     keg of sugar from a ten gallon barrel. I took all the tobacco I 
     <lb/>
     could get, as there had been a heavy run on this luxury item. 
     <lb/>
     Taking advantage of the lower prices of the traders anxious to 
     <lb/>
     clear their stocks for the return journey, I was able to practically 
     <lb/>
     name my own price for the things I wanted. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     The cart that I had purchased from Alexander Kennedy was 
     <lb/>
     iron bound, the first to make an appearance in the trade, so I 
     <lb/>
     was not afraid to load heavy. I was very well pleased with myself 
     <lb/>
     as I made the rounds of the traders preparing to leave, picking 
     <lb/>
     up bargains wherever I could. Money, my friend, had a great 
     <lb/>
     deal more value in those days and I still had money in my 
     <lb/>
     pocket when my carts were loaded. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     William Bull was usually the best of companions but for the 
     <lb/>
     first few days I thought he was very quiet and somewhat 
     <lb/>
     despondent. Actually he seemed to be occupied in some deep 
     <lb/>
     thought, so I finally asked him what was troubling him. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "The chief has asked for a great stretch of land about which 
     <lb/>
     he now speaks as if it had already been promised to him. I 
     <lb/>
     listened carefully to your interpretations of the Governor's 
     <lb/>
     answer to his request. The Governor stated that he had no 
     <lb/>
     authority to grant any such request and merely stated that as 
     <lb/>
     James Seenum was a chief and had asked, he would pass the 
     <lb/>
     request on to his superiors. Is that right, Peter?" 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Yes, it certainly is. To have an unrestricted amount of land 
     <lb/>
     for one chief would have broken the terms of the treaty to all 
     <lb/>
     those others who had already signed. Surely Chief Seenum does 
     <lb/>
     not think that he has been promised the land from the Dog 
     <lb/>
     Rump Creek as far west as the Whitemud River, with the 
     <lb/>
     Beaver River at the north and the Saskatchewan River as its 
     <lb/>
     southern boundary?" 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Yes! That is exactly what he told me only the last night 
     <lb/>
     before the camp broke up. I tried to explain to him that this was 
     <lb/>
     not true but he would have none of my explanation, and we had 
     <lb/>
     some words between us. That is why I asked to go along with 
     <lb/>
     you. It would be a good thing if you would speak to him about 
     <lb/>
     the real truth as spoken by the Governor." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Well of course I will talk to him, but if he does not listen to 
     <lb/>
     the words of his own councillor, how will he listen to me? If he 
     <lb/>
     is not satisfied with the terms of the treaty why did he sign? It 
     <lb/>
     seemed to me that he understood everything that I spoke about 
     <lb/>
     the night of the first council of the chiefs." I explained to them 
     <lb/>
         

            <fw type="num">262</fw>
            <pb n="263" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_263.jpg"/>
          

     that each man, woman and child then living would be 
     <lb/>
     apportioned eighty acres each, according to the number of 
     <lb/>
     Indians then belonging to his tribe. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "I and the others all understood exactly as you now explain. 
     <lb/>
     Further than that, the Governor also mentioned the amount of 
     <lb/>
     land each Indian would be entitled to when they picked their 
     <lb/>
     reserves next year. For myself, I can only occupy a small portion 
     <lb/>
     of the land my family would be entitled to, but I understand 
     <lb/>
     that all the land, regardless of the amount each family uses, will 
     <lb/>
     belong to the band and can be used by our children's children." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "You are quite right, William. I know the chief is a 
     <lb/>
     stubborn man but surely he is a man of his word. He has 
     <lb/>
     promised to abide by the agreement that all the other chiefs 
     <lb/>
     signed. He signed for his band and so did you." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "This thing will someday make trouble for us, mark my 
     <lb/>
     word," said William Bull, "for the man is not easily turned 
     <lb/>
     from his way, once he makes up his mind. I am afraid he will 
     <lb/>
     persist in claiming that the land was promised by the 
     <lb/>
     Governor, and many of our people will follow his lead. You 
     <lb/>
     and I both know differently but will the people believe us? 
     <lb/>
     Suppose they did, can we go against our chief?" 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     "Well, William, we will cross the bridge when we come to 
     <lb/>
     it. In the meantime, I do not think we should bother our heads 
     <lb/>
     about it. All the Governor promised, as I said before, was that 
     <lb/>
     he would bring his request to his superiors, and he also said 
     <lb/>
     that he was certain that they would refuse." 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     We were heavily loaded but by travelling early and late, we 
     <lb/>
     made good time. The weather remained clear and our stock 
     <lb/>
     stood up to the work. Our equipment did not give us any 
     <lb/>
     trouble or cause of delay. My iron bound cart proved an 
     <lb/>
     excellent improvement over the other all-wood carts. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     My family was not yet home by the time we arrived at 
     <lb/>
     Whitefish, so we unloaded our carts and arranged to have my 
     <lb/>
     new horses taken care of. I caught up a fresh saddle horse and 
     <lb/>
     started out to meet the buffalo hunters. 
     <lb/>
            </p>

            <p>
     I shot a black bear near where the village of Spedden is now 
     <lb/>
     situated. He was standing on his hind legs eating saskatoons on 
     <lb/>
     a side hill. He was bending the branches with his paws much as 
     <lb/>
     man would do. I shot him just behind the front legs in the body. 
     <lb/>
     He dropped and rolled almost to my horse's feet from about 
     <lb/>
     twenty-five steps away. The thick growth of grass had deadened 
     <lb/>
     the sound of my approach. It was a tempting shot but a foolish 
     <lb/>
     one. If our party were not on this side of the Saskatchewan, the 
     <lb/>
     meat would spoil before it could be used. I felt guilty of a crime 
     <lb/>
     against all the laws of prairie life — unwritten laws, but 
     <lb/>
          

            <fw type="num">263</fw>
            <pb n="264" facs="final/images/erasmus_page_264.jpg"/>
         

     nevertheless lived up to by all the tribes of my acquaintance. 
     <lb/>
    Wasting animal life without cause was looked upon as the act 
     <lb/>of a stupid and unthinking person. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
   
    

            <p>
     Fortunately for my conscience, our people were close at 
     <lb/>
     hand and I met them within an hour's ride. My family was well. 
     <lb/>
     My newest son showed his objections to being stopped on the 
     <lb/>
     trail by a lusty show of lung power that wouldn't stop till the 
     <lb/>
     cart moved on. There was one son who would follow his 
     <lb/>
     father's footstep — he loved travelling before he could even 
     <lb/>
     crawl. The party camped early that evening and some men 
     <lb/>
     went out to bring the bear back to camp for distribution among 
     <lb/>
     the people. 
     <lb/>
            </p>
            <fw type="num">264</fw>
       </div>  </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>